<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">For the last time William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> acted as my chauffeur by driving me to Darlington for the early train</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> As we turned into the station the speedometer registered the completion of 13,000 miles. On my way to London I read through a little book of lectures on "Christianity and the Religions of the World" by Albert Schweitzer. It is, of course, a very rapid sketch of a very large subject, but it is full of priceless <hi rend="underline">obiter dicta</hi>. On arriving in London, I deposited my bags at 21 Park Lane, and went to the hair&#8211;dresser, where my Nazirite locks were shorn, &amp; my head cleansed. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I went to the House of Lords to investigate tomorrow's prospects. Lord</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Malmesbury</hi><persName xml:id="5393"></persName><hi rend="bold underline">introduced himself to me, &amp; said that the opposition were counting on me to make the principal speech.</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Danescourt</hi><persName xml:id="2092"></persName> (Butcher), &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><persName xml:id="4032"></persName> both said that they w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> vote with me. So did <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charnwood</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName>, with whom I walked as far as his house, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sumner</hi><persName xml:id="5393"></persName>, whom I met in the Club. <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3465"></persName> expressed his intention of voting against the Bill: and there will be several bishops against it. Still I doubt whether we shall be able to defeat the Bill. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lords Selbourne</hi><persName xml:id="311"></persName> and others have issued a whip on their side, &amp; they count for a good deal.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I dined in the Club. There were 11 members dining viz:</p>
         <p>1. George Trevelyan<persName xml:id="5121"></persName></p>
         <p>2. Sir Charles Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName></p>
         <p>3. Sir Frederick Kenyon<persName xml:id="2534"></persName></p>
         <p>4. Herbert Fisher<persName xml:id="2107"></persName></p>
         <p>5. Sir Henry Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName></p>
         <p>6. Hon: Edward Wood<persName xml:id="586"></persName></p>
         <p>7. Rudyard Kipling</p>
         <p>8. Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName></p>
         <p>9. Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName></p>
         <p>10. Lord Crawford<persName xml:id="5377"></persName></p>
         <p>11. Bishop of Durham University</p>
         <p>The talk was vivacious and well&#8211;sustained. It ranged over many subjects, but dwelt longest on India and Egypt. I sate between Oman and Trevelyan. Kipling was talkative &amp; interesting: but I remembered nothing worthy of record!</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">This afternoon, L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Darling asked me whether I was dining at Grillions:&#8211; &amp; when I said that I was not a member: he said that my name had been put up for membership</hi><hi rend="italic">. Am I to conclude that my name had been rejected at the ballot? That would be humiliating.</hi> I should like to belong to Grillions, but I am so rarely in town that I should very rarely be able to dine, if I were elected: and the subscription could not be negligible. Besides, I grow old, and youth is an indispensable condition of enjoyment in these societies! </p></body></text></TEI>