<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The papers report another insulting pronouncement of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Bircham<persName xml:id="5380"></persName> on his Bishop.</hi> This time, of course, it is his Lordship's deplorable language about "Temperance" which moves him to explode in his parish magazine. I wonder how the Dean likes his comrade! If any proof were needed of the need of some protest against the extravagance of these fanatics, such language as Bircham's might provide it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> motored into Northumberland to visit the Burges. I worked on the Charge: and, after lunch, played bowls with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. While so engaged, a Canadian clergyman, the Venerable Archdeacon J.P.D. Llwyd, arrived. He had but 20 minutes before hustling off to catch a train back to Durham, but he ran round the house, begged a book from me, &amp; drank tea!! Elizabeth Smith<persName xml:id="3077"></persName> also arrived.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The 'Times' prints a letter from Arthur Smith calling attention to the alleged discovery of the lost books of Livy by a certain D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Mario di Martino&#8211;Fusco, director the review Mouseion and editor of the associated Biblioteca. The announcement is quoted from the Rivista Indo&#8211;Greco Italica, which M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Smith guarantees to be "a serious publication".</hi></p>
         <p>The more I write of this Charge, the less it seems worth writing. There is no likelihood, not even the smallest, that anybody will be persuaded to accept what I suggest as probable improvements of the system created by the Enabling Act. Why then do I make the suggestions? I am too far out of sympathy with the methods and ideals of the clergy to be able to influence them, and, indeed, I begin to doubt whether there is not a degree of remoteness which is actually incapacitating. One must have <hi rend="underline">some</hi> followers, if one is to effect anything at all: and the fact is dawning on me that I have literally none!</p></body></text></TEI>