<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Prayers were read at 8.45 a.m. in the detached chapel in the classic style, built at the same time as the Palace. I wrote letters to the Archbishop of York about Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> consecration: to Hudson Barker<persName xml:id="3575"></persName> undertaking to officiate on September 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> at his marriage (the belated old idiot!); and to the Secretary of the Clergy Assistance Society commending Rust's application for a grant.</p>
         <p>The Archbishop took me for a walk in the grounds, &amp; from a rising place showed me a most beautiful view of the cathedral. <hi rend="bold underline">It is placed on the wooded hill given to S. Patrick in A. D. 440</hi>. Behind it is the new Roman Catholic Cathedral, a pretentious building with two spires, which has a curiously exotick appearance. It the foreground rises the spire of the Presbyterian "cathedral". <hi rend="bold underline">Thus the via media of Anglican Christianity is effectively symbolised!</hi> By descending a little we found a point at which a convenient tree blotted out the modern rivals, &amp; showed S. Patrick's church in unchallenged possession of Armagh. This little town, with about 7000 inhabitants is sufficiently equipped with "places of worship". <hi rend="bold underline">Besides the three "cathedrals", there is an Anglican Church, a Roman Church, a Methodist Chapel, &amp; a meeting house of the Plymouth Brethren</hi>.</p>
         <p>I preached to a large congregation in the Cathedral at 3 p.m. The service was choral sung by the members of choirs in the diocese mostly, so far as I could see, consisting of girls!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>However, they were creditably attentive, although the sermon must have been painfully dull. The Archbishop &amp; some others expressed themselves flatterously, <hi rend="bold underline">but I incline to think that my preaching days are over</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to the Mayor of Sunderland, who had the impudence to write to me about J. S. Brown, no doubt in view of the vacancy at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring.</p>
         <p>We had a good deal of talk about serious subjects after dinner. The Archbishop agreed with my view that the apologia for Christianity lay in its character as the true d&#x00E9;nouement of Theism, that Christ indicated the proper order of the argument when he said to the disciples: "<hi rend="bold underline">Ye believe in God: believe also in me</hi>". We discussed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes's</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> efforts to modernize theology, which <hi rend="doubleunderline">D'Arcy</hi><persName xml:id="1361"></persName> was more inclined to think needed &amp; useful than the rest of us. He holds that the religious beliefs of the people have been seriously shaken by the sudden and rapid dissemination of scientific knowledge &amp; speculations, which have indeed been long known to the educated minority, but are startlingly novel to the religious public as a whole. Therefore, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> is fulfilling a much needed ministry, when he expounds as if they were perilous novelties, interpretations of the Bible which have for more than a generation been the assumptions of the schools and universities. A very large public is grateful to him for what to them appears his audacious courage. </p></body></text></TEI>