<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>A rainy dark morning. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went out with me to Darlington, where I took the early train to London. After leaving my bags at the Admiralty, I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended a meeting of the Ecclesiastical Courts Commission. Then I had tea in the Club, and went to the Admiralty in time for dinner at 7.30 p.m. The Chelmsfords<persName xml:id="65"></persName> went to Court, and I to bed!</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cruikshank</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to me: "He (Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>) referred to K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, and said the appointment would not be popular in the diocese. He said that you were not popular with the clergy, because to use his own words, you who are 'the kindest and most generous of men' sometimes 'show your rough side to them'. So you see we come round to '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Rehoboam</hi><hi rend="italic">' after all! I mention this because, while popularity is a contemptible thing to seek after, it oils the whole from a practical point of view". This is interesting and may very well be true. The change from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Moule's</hi><persName xml:id="276"></persName><hi rend="italic"> oleaginous phraseology to my brutal frankness must be very trying to the clergy. My refusal to accept so many men for Ordination, whom he would have welcomed must give mortal offence to some. The Anglo&#8211;Catholicks and Socialists can hardly love me, &amp; I must be very hard to understand even for those who w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> like to love me if they could!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>