<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast the Provost took us to the Library, and there introduced <hi rend="bold underline">us to the Sub&#8211;Librarian, who showed us the Book of Kells, a truly marvellous production of the Irish, probably written about the year 800</hi>. He also showed us other objects of less interest. Then we strolled in the streets for an hour, returning to the Provost's House for lunch.</p>
         <p>After luncheon we were taken for a motor drive to a little sea&#8211;side resort called Greystones, where M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bernard hoped to find lodgings for her grandchildren. The road lay through fair and varied scenery. The Sugar&#8211;loaves are fine hills. We returned by way of the sea&#8211;shore, after having tea in a pretentious hotel. I noticed that a Masonic temple was in ruins. <hi rend="bold underline">The chauffeur interested me, a lanky young rascal, with saucy good humour in his speech, &amp; a spice of dare devilry in his eye. He said that he came from Tipperary; where no mansions had been left standing, and the Protestant population had fled the country. I suspect that he was a Republican, as his references to the Free State were not respectful</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard</hi> told me that the Archbishop of Dublin and he had been of pains to discover the precise amount of truth that there was in the dreadful statements as to the raping of Protestant women by the Irish, and that they had satisfied themselves that <hi rend="bold underline">there were three cases and no more</hi>.</p>
         <p>I read most part of a new book which had just come into the library:&#8211; "Among wild tribes of the Amazons an Account of Exploration &amp; Adventure on the Mighty Amazon &amp; its confluents with descriptions of the savage Head&#8211;hunting &amp; anthropophagus tribes inhabiting their banks' by Charles W. Domville&#8211;Fife (Seeley, Service &amp; Co.)</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>There came to dinner two interesting men, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Guinness</hi>, Head of the Bank of Ireland, who is a Member of the Senate, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alton</hi>, one of the fellows, a good Latinist, who is a member of the Dail. Both talked freely about the political situation, &amp; on the whole hopefully. They said that Jews were increasing in Ireland very rapidly, a fact in their judgement very regrettable. Both seemed hostile to the Ulster contention as to the Boundary question, but thought that some arrangement would be reached. I inquired whether there was any prospect of a formidable "Labour" movement developing in the Free State, and I was assured that there was none. In an almost purely agricultural community like the Irish the farmers are the dominant factor, and they will not vote "Labour". <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Alton</hi><hi rend="bold underline">assured me that the assaults on women were limited to the followers of Rory O' Connor, who were largely "Bolshevist"</hi>. The influence of the Roman Catholic Church was declining, &amp; would continue to decline. It was a common thing now for the people to walk out of church when the priest embarked on political matters, e.g. if he denounced robbery, arson, &amp; murder. The Sub&#8211;Librarian told me that in his district there had been much robbery, &amp; the parish priest spoke strongly on the matter at Mass. He was waited for outside the Church by a party of young men, who addressed him thus: "<hi rend="underline">Look you, Father: we will not have such words from you. Your business is inside the church: what we do outside is ours</hi>". This crude declaration is said to express a general &amp; growing attitude of mind.</p></body></text></TEI>