<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The nations asked, Can we prevail against Israel? The answer was given, Not if you hear the voices of the children babbling over their books in the Synagogues. See how deeply loved of God the children are. The Sanhedrin was exiled, but the Shechinah (Divine Presence) did not accompany its members into exile; the Priests were exiled, but still the Shechinah remained behind. But when the children were exiled, forth went the Shechinah with them.</p>
         <p>Quoted in "Studies in Pharisaism &amp; the Gospels by J. Abrahams. First Series. P. 119</p>
         </div>
         <p>I prepared notes for the "sermons" in the Chapel to the Sunday School Teachers' Association this afternoon, and to the Freemasons tomorrow. Frank Berry walked with me in the Park. We talked about the differences between culture and civilisation.</p>
         <p>At 6 p.m. the service in the Chapel was held. About 100 teachers were present. Parry Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName> read the prayers: and I preached.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ravensworth</hi><persName xml:id="3719"></persName> arrived for the week&#8211;end. I took him for a walk in the Park before dinner. He is a frank, simple soul of the sort which is nourished by the Public School and High Church party. His grandfather was that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robert Liddell</hi> who was once Vicar of Barking, &amp; who, he tells me, was offered the Vicarage of Hartlepool by Bishop Van Mildert. But Baring came in and quashed the appointment which had not been completed!</p></body></text></TEI>