<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went off to London in order to attend the Court, where the elder lady is to present the younger. I motored to Durham, and had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hil</hi>l in the Castle, I told him that he could not be ordained at Trinity. He acquiesced with his enigmatic placidity! </p>
         <p>I motored to <hi rend="bold underline">Trimdon Grange</hi>, and there confirmed 118 persons in the little mean church which was crowded to excess. The atmosphere was stifling, but, on the whole, I was pleased. The sexes were about equally divided. The sight of these big pit&#8211;lads bending their heads for the laying on of hands, with a look of resolute purpose on their faces is a spiritual tonic. After service I had tea with the parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rust</hi>, a poor pallid mimick of a man, but evidently capable of good work. <hi rend="bold underline">He spoke in favourable terms of Hodgson<persName xml:id="5274"></persName>, the Vicar of Escombe, and, as this in that man's case is quite unparalleled, I record it</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> Then I motored to Ferry Hill, and confirmed 138 persons in a woeful low&#8211;pitched building, once a skating&#8211;rink. The place was densely crowded, the heat was tropical, &amp; the atmosphere almost intolerable. However, the attention was close: the demeanour of the candidates reverent: &amp;, I hope, the service was edifying. This parish was the scene of a hostile demonstration against me during the coal strike three years ago: but tonight there was nothing but friendly greetings as I motored through the parish on my way back to the Castle.</p></body></text></TEI>