<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>My "holiday" has begun, and my appointed task cries out for a start to be made, and I can do no more than fumble about my study, tearing up paper, re&#8211;collecting scattered books, and accumulating a degree of personal uncleanness through dust &amp; dirt that makes me repulsive to myself. Every element in my nature which is hostile to work gathers force, and threatens to defeat my good purpose. "<hi rend="underline">There is a law in my members</hi>", as S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul might say, which goes far to defeat the "<hi rend="underline">law of my mind</hi>". With the Apostle I can but cry out '<hi rend="underline">O wretched man that I am</hi>!' Beyond writing a quite superfluous letter to an editor, and thanking Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> for her condolence I had achieved nothing before the car arrived to take me to Durham for Brown's institution to the canonry.</p>
         <p>After instituting Brown, we went to the Club, and were entertained at lunch by Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> with his usual generosity. Apperley, Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, Brown, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; myself were his guests. We picked up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at the College gate, &amp; so returned to the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The undertaker's bill exceeds &#x00A3;60., which with the fees paid at Birchington will make at least &#x00A3;75. for the funeral. A letter from Kate acknowledged receipt of &#x00A3;36. viz: &#x00A3;10 from Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>: &#x00A3;10. from Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>: &#x00A3;10. from me: &#x00A3;6. i.e. 2 months wages from Ella. I sent both the bill and the letter to Arthur.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The weather continues to be uncertain, by turns warm and chilly. Wet and dry – a comfortless &amp; disconcerting state of affairs.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to Loney offering him the living of Westgate, vacated by Greenway's acceptance of Eldon. Also, I wrote to Rainbow, offering him the living of Shotton, vacated by Fenton's resignation. Also, I wrote to Knowlden<persName xml:id="5439"></persName>, asking him to give the addresses to the candidates, &amp; to preach at the Ordination in October.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Murray</hi> of Murraythwaite arrived in her car to stay over the week&#8211;end.</p>
         <p>Some new books arrived from the bookseller:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. <hi rend="underline">The Waning of the Middle Ages</hi>, A study of the forms of Life, Thought, and Art in France &amp; the Netherlands in the XIV<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and XV<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries, by J. Huizinga.</p>
         <p>2. <hi rend="underline">Freemasonry</hi>: its aims and ideals, by J.S.M. Ward.</p>
         <p>3. <hi rend="underline">Savage Life in Central Australia</hi> by G. Horne and G. Aiston.</p>
         <p>4. <hi rend="underline">Studies in Pharisaism and the Gospels</hi> by J. Abrahams, 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Series.</p>
         <p>5. <hi rend="underline">The Idea of the Holy</hi>, an inquiry into the non&#8211;rational factor in the idea of the Divine and its relation to the rational, by Rudolph Otto, translated by J. W. Harvey.</p>
         <p>6. <hi rend="underline">Ethics and some Modern World Problems</hi> by William McDougall, F.R.S.</p>
         <p>7. <hi rend="underline">The Decalogue</hi>, being the Warburton Lectures by R. H. Charles D.D.</p></body></text></TEI>