<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> after breakfast, and there continued writing letters until lunch time. I lunched in the Club, and then walked to Westminster, where I continued in the House of Lords until about 7 p.m. Lord Danesfort<persName xml:id="2092"></persName> moved the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Reading of his Bill for suppressing Blasphemous &amp; Seditious Teaching, which after considerable debate, was carried by 102 votes to 20. I voted with the Majority.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Several peers spoke in praise of yesterday's speech, of which there is but a meagre report in the papers: but I fear my success may be fatal to my purpose, for the advocates of the Bill have been so frightened that they are said to be whipping up all their big guns. In any event, whether the measure be fully passed or not, considerable publicity will be given to the situation created by the Enabling Act, and many things will have been said which will hardly be forgotten.</hi></p>
         <p>In the Athenaeum that amazing old creature, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Browne</hi>, told me that when he was bishop of Bristol, he found the see too small to provide him an adequate sphere of work. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Wakefield</hi> speaks to the same effect about his see. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ullswater</hi> said that there was no case of a see once divided desiring to revert to its former state: I replied that division always had the effect of creating a number of vested interests. It was <hi rend="underline">these</hi> that hindered any return to the past, not a conviction of the advantages of division.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Parsons,</p>
         <p>I do not understand why you sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be "wounded very deeply" by the fact that I am unable to agree with you on the manner in which Temperance is best advanced in the community: nor do I see why your Methodist friends sh<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> have "aching hearts" because I disapprove of Prohibition.</p>
         <p>I think the principle of 'Local Option' – which seems to me indistinguishable from the principle of Prohibition – unsound, &amp;, therefore I shall oppose its embodiment in legislation.</p>
         <p>It neither angers nor surprises me to learn that many excellent Christians differs from me in opinion on many important questions: &amp; I have ever held that it is a part of Christian duty to tolerate such differences of opinion, &amp; not to allow them to interfere with friendly relations.</p>
         <p>Certainly I make no claim to infallibility: but I do my best to ascertain the facts &amp; to form a sound judgement: &amp; I think my position requires that I should offer that judgement for what it is worth to my fellow citizens. Do you think the Bp. of Durham ought to keep silence on all questions respecting which differences of opinion exist in order to avoid giving offence?</p>
         <p>Ever sincerely yours. H. D.</p>
         <p>The Rev. George Parsons.</p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>