<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O almighty God, who alone canst order the unruly wills and affectations of sinful men; Grant unto thy people, that they may love the thing which thou commandest, and desire that which thou dost promise; that so, among the sundry and manifold changes of the world, our hearts may surely there be fixed, where true joys are to be found; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I went into the Chapel for prayer, &amp; the Epistle seemed to give me the counsel I needed for handling this difficult matter of Briggs. "<hi rend="underline">Let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath: for the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God</hi>". And the Gospel, with its assurance of the guidance of the Spirit of Truth, had a message of encouragement.</p>
         <p>I motored to Winlaton, and preached to a church crowded with Oddfellows, Territorials, Boy Scouts, Girl Guides etc. The old Vicar, Canon Jones, is now without curates, &amp; at his wits' end. After service I lunched with the Verekers, &amp; then returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> about the appointment of Quirk's<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> successor. Also I wrote to the ex&#8211;papist Albert de Burton about his application to be accepted for Holy Orders. These Ordination problems will drive me crazy. I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.</p></body></text></TEI>