<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[170] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi><persName xml:id="3462"></persName> a sad affectionate letter in response to me letter of condolence on the death of his nephew's young wife. He writes:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>"I had a faint hope that he and his wife would live here after me, but now that is shattered and I feel that I shall be the last Lambton of Lambton<placeName xml:id="75"></placeName>. It is not vanity or pride, and I know that you can understand my sentiments".</p>
         </div>
         <p>So the last but one of the great houses will be deserted when L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> dies, for Wynyard<placeName xml:id="53"></placeName> and Lumley<placeName xml:id="62"></placeName> are practically unoccupied. <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnard</hi> lives at Raby, but Ravensworth Castle is let to a girls' school. It is all very melancholy.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="5197"></persName><hi rend="bold underline">I worked at the Charge, &amp; succeeded in finishing it after a fashion. But I am profoundly discontented with it.</hi> I suppose I ought to print in an appendix, the Visitation Inquiries, and some summary of the answers of the clergy. Also, I shall add the sermon on "Divine Guidance" which I preached at Cambridge.</p>
         <p>After lunch I played bowls with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, &amp; won two games out of three.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> Swiss friend, Fran Kőrsteiner arrived for a visit.</hi> She tells me that greater crowds of visitors come now to Switzerland for the winter season, than during summer. The ruin of our family life fills alien purses!</p></body></text></TEI>