<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Winchester Measure was carried by 71 to 60 votes after a heavily one–sided debate, in which the speeches were more concerned with the demerits of the Bishop of Durham than with the contents of the measure. The adjournment was refused with great unfairness. The "Times" has a leader expressed with much hostility to me, and, (most significant of all) my letter is refused</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and, in the Castle Chapel, instituted Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> to the archdeaconry and annexed Canonry. Then we lunched in the Common Room with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, who had got together a company to meet the new archdeacon. After lunch I presided at a meeting of the Board of Finance, and then went to the Castle, where I had an interview with Bailey<persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, to whom I unfolded the woeful case of the man John.<persName xml:id="5355"></persName>  After this, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> rejoined me, &amp; picking up Wilson in the Bailey, I motored to Hartlepool, where I instituted Salter to the Rectory. There was a fair congregation including, I was pleased to observe, a contingent of the Boys' Brigade. Macdonald, as Rural Dean, inducted the new Rector. I was glad to notice that the neighbouring clergy were mostly present. After service we returned to Auckland, dropping Wilson at his door on our way through Durham. We got home about 10 p.m. The weather became cool, and almost chilly as night drew on, but the sunsetting was brilliant.</p></body></text></TEI>