<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The Prime Minister sends me a civil reply to my letter about Lilley, though he promises nothing.</p>
         <p>"I do wish your church would one day have the commonsense [sic] not to trouble Prime Ministers with unnecessary political rows and ecclesiastical disputes! This of course is a general remark and does not apply to your letter. I shall always welcome any communication from you".</p>
         <p>I wrote many letters, and read through the "Copec" report on Education. Slovach with his wife and infant came to lunch, and afterwards played bowls with me and Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. After tea they returned to Durham.</p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me some papers about Auckland Castle, which had been found among old Miss Fancit's papers in Durham, and presented to me for preservation among the archives here by her heir. They are rather interesting than valuable.</p>
         <p>The working of the Enabling Act for its first 4 years must be reviewed: and the gravity of its failure to win the acceptance of the parishioners in sufficient measure must be pointed out. Some suggestion of an amending measure might, perhaps, be made. Such a measure sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> provide for (&#x3B1;) a directer method of election to the National Assembly, (&#x3B2;) a referendum on measures affecting directly the dioceses, (&#x3B3;) providing for a lay Chairman. The question of diocesan assessments might also be discussed in connexion with the representative character of the Assembly.</p></body></text></TEI>