<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>It was from the ruri&#8211;decanal chapter of Christianity that I received a strong protest against my consecration as a bishop. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><persName xml:id="249"></persName> tells me that this Rural Dean is in medieval documents often called the Dean of Exeter – a fact which has led to much confusion. I wonder whether the gentleman was present last night, and whether he repents of his activity. Perhaps, if he is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick, he is more than ever persuaded of its rightness: &amp;, from that point of view, who shall say that he is wrong?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Quirk's</hi><persName xml:id="2785"></persName> death has come too soon for my intentions about K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> to mature conveniently. Why should not the suffragan bishoprick be linked to the richly&#8211;endowed benefice of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring? This would raise the question of remuneration. It would hardly be wise to let the suffragan bishop's services be altogether voluntary.</p>
         <p>We motored to the Priory, Woodchester, by way of Taunton, Glastonbury, and Bath, a distance of 114 miles, leaving at 10.25 a.m. and arriving at 4.45 p.m. We spent an hour over luncheon etc. at Glastonbury. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Soltau Simmons</hi> welcomed us, and, after tea, I wrote to Watts of Shildon, Major E. Atkin, and George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.</p>
         <p>This is a 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house with some good panelling, and the quiet stateliness of its age and type.</p></body></text></TEI>