<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3466"></persName> took us to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welbeck</hi>. I had not expected to find there so great an accumulation of pictures, books, and treasures of all kinds.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The chalice from which Charles I received the Holy Communion, and the earing which the King wore, are here preserved</hi>. The former appears to have come from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Luxor</hi> through Sir Henry H whose arms are engraved on it. The latter was given by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary ii</hi> to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bentinck's</hi> wife. A jewelled dagger which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry viii</hi> was wont to carry is also notable. Among a noble collection of Vandykes a picture of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strafford</hi> arrested my notice. In the Library are many interesting letters from sovereigns, prime ministers, &amp; other important people. A letter from Garrick to the Duchess of Portland about a young man whom her Grace had recommended for employment is very amusingly expressed. There are, as might be expected, many pictures of horses, for the heiress of Charles I's Newcastle bought that noble horseman's collection to Welbeck. Racing men would be interested in two pictures of 'the bloody&#8211;shouldered Arabian'. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duchess</hi> herself showed us over most of the house, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Goulding</hi>, the Librarian expounded the books &amp; pictures. We had tea with their Graces before returning to Sandbeck. It was all most interesting.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p>I had some conversation with the Duchess, who is still a beautiful woman, full of vivacity and charm. Her picture by Sargent displayed a very lovely creature, when she was young. She showed me the book in which she kept a careful register of the sick and injured miners whom she personally visited, and assisted. It disclosed a care &amp; accuracy of description which would have done credit to a professional nurse. During the War, Welbeck was used as a Hospital, – sixty seven beds being provided with all the requisites, even an operating theatre. She said that the Duke held on to Welbeck with difficulty owing to the heavy taxation: that the number of gardeners &amp; servants had been greatly reduced since the War: &amp; generally that the future of the vast house was doubtful. In the Ball room – 60 feet by 60 – there is a marble bust of the late Duke, whose eccentric shyness caused the excavation of the underground rooms &amp; roads. It is a handsome countenance, thoughtful and refined in no common degree. The Librarian scouted the common theory that the duke was insane. He had been crossed in love, and hated women in consequence – that was all. In the Ball Room is Sir Joshua Reynold's wonderful picture of the angel gazing on the cross, the design of <hi rend="bold">[15]</hi> the window of New College. I was surprised to see two pictures of Shakespeare's friend, Wriothesley, Earl of Southampton. But the series of heiresses of great houses who carried their lands &amp; treasures into Welbeck can account for anything. <hi rend="underline">A contemporary picture of the Battle of the Boyne by a Dutch artist interested me.</hi></p>
         <p>There are some remains of the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, portions of the Premonstratensian house out of which the vast pile of modern Welbeck has developed.</p>
         <p>I had some conversation with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Fitz&#8211;Alan</hi><persName xml:id="4221"></persName>. He spoke of his nephew, the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duke of Norfolk</hi>, who is a minor. It will be very difficult for him to live at Arundel.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>As auxiliary to the main argument, we may fairly add the indications of character which Byron provided throughout his life. In every department of sexual morality he was deplorable, and the only plea that can be made for his behaviour is one that infringes on his vanity: but apart from this there is much to suggest a character of genuine humanity. His kindness to his servants, his love of dogs, his friendly concern for the poor, his popularity with the Newstead tenants – all these traits are thoroughly congruous with the view that his warfare for liberty had its roots deep in his character.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p></body></text></TEI>