<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent most part of the day at Lambeth. We began by discussing that tiresome old chestnut, Education. The subject was brought forward by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi>, whose diocese (Salisbury) is full of church schools, on which the local inspector has just reported <hi rend="underline">that they are a school in bad hygiene to all the children who attend them.</hi> The laity will not subscribe for their maintenance. A similar declaration was made by two other bishops – Ely and Winchester – who also have many bad rural schools. The Abp. undertook to convene yet another conference to frame a "central policy" for the Church, which might be imposed even on the National Society. His Grace nominated me to be one of the members, but I had to decline as I must be in Ireland when the Conference meets on June 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. The Bishop of Liverpool raised the painful question of removing names from the Caution List. There was a valuable but most hateful discussion. Then we got on to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson's</hi><persName xml:id="5413"></persName> faith–healing missions, which the Bishop of Bradford inclines to sanction in his diocese. <hi rend="bold underline">I made a strong speech denouncing the fatuous statement issued by the Australian episcopate</hi>, and published in the <hi rend="underline">Record </hi>for this week. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> spoke at great length, and very cryptically. The bishops want to be deceived!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Hereford brought forward the subject of marriage with the deceased wife's sister. He thought the bishop ought to issue a dispensation after the Roman fashion. I said that the statute was itself a general dispensation.</hi></p>
         <p>After this, as the rest of the Agenda looked uninteresting, I came away, and went to the Club, where I had tea. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Newbolt</hi><persName xml:id="3946"></persName> was there: <hi rend="underline">he spoke flatterously of my 'Rede' Lecture</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Chelmsford</hi> carried us off after dinner to witness a performance by the Anchorites, a society of Amateurs. The piece, 'Dorothy' was rendered with remarkable vigour, and was much appreciated by an audience which seemed to be mainly drawn from the Admiralty staff, &amp; its friends. Captain Frazer, who had been an aide–de–camp to Lord Chelmsford<persName xml:id="65"></persName> in India, and is a brother of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Haggie, accompanied us. He impressed me as an intelligent and agreeable man. In the course of <hi rend="italic">a conversation on the present situation of India, he quoted the observation of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M. Clemenceau</hi><hi rend="italic">, when he was shown the mighty structures of the new Delhi. "It will make as good a ruin as the others".</hi> There's a vast amount of humiliating truth summed up in that brief sardonic comment.</p></body></text></TEI>