<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is one of the finest problems in legislation, and what has often engaged my thoughts whilst I followed that profession, &#8211; What the state ought to take upon itself to direct by the public wisdom, and what it ought to leave, with as little interference as possible, to individual discretion. Nothing, certainly, can be laid down on the subject that will not admit of exceptions, &#8211; many permanent, some occasional. But the clearest line of distinction which I could draw, whilst I had my chalk to draw any line, was this: that the state ought to confine itself to what regards the state or the creatures of the state ….</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burke</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">Thoughts &amp; details of Society</hi>. (v. 167) </p>
         <p>In A.D. 1795</p>
         </div>
         <p>While I was playing bowls with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> after lunch, Bailey<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> appeared with John, whom he had brought hither in a taxi, as the doctor "could do nothing more until his interview with me was over". It was of the briefest. I simply stated my ultimatum. He must return his license at once: then I would address a letter to the Vicar granting permission for one year, under necessary conditions, &amp; undertaking to review his case at the end of that period. After tea I motored to Durham, &amp; brought out the Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burge who were visiting the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>.</p></body></text></TEI>