<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Lord Ravensworth<persName xml:id="3719"></persName> went away after breakfast. I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, and had an interview with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. I told him of the difficulty which had arisen through the Dean's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> strange behaviour, and asked him frankly whether in spite of this, he would be prepared, if I asked him to do so, to take on as Quirk's<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> successor. He was evidently much astonished at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon's</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName> strange behaviour, but <hi rend="underline">none the less he said that if I offered him the position, he would accept it</hi>. I said that I would consider the whole subject, and, when my mind had settled to a decision, I would let him know. I returned to the Castle in time for lunch. Graham White, the Vicar of Dawdon, lunched, and divers others. He came to sing the praises of his curate, Key. Later, I motored to Haswell, where I confirmed 19 persons, and afterwards had tea with the Vicar, Skene. Then I motored to Wheatly Hill, and confirmed 79 persons. On both occasions the preponderance of females over males was exorbitant. I returned to Auckland after the service, &amp; found that Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had already returned. <hi rend="underline">I incline to think that it might be a more edifying practice, if there were separate confirmations for boys &amp; girls</hi>. The spectacle of a handfull of boys forlornly placed against three times the number of girls in a congregation almost wholly composed of females cannot but give the impression that Confirmation is mainly a woman's affair, not naturally appertaining to the concern of normal males – an impression now but too common.</p></body></text></TEI>