<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Low Sunday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Rain fell heavily until about 2 p.m. In spite of this there was a great congregation of soldiers &amp; people in the nave at a special service held in honour of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I received the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 7.45 a.m. The Dean celebrated. It was a quiet &amp; reverent service, &amp; followed the Prayer Book lawfully.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Sunday paper reported the death of Bishop Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>.</hi> This was an unexpected blow, as the latest reports had been favourable. A canonry at Durham, the Archdeaconry of Durham, &amp; the suffragan bishoprick are all vacated.</p>
         <p>The Dean and I took a short 'constitutional' in the rain. At 6.30 p.m. I preached in the Nave. The large congregation was very attentive, and, I think, interested. The Bishop of Exeter &amp; Lady Florence came to see me during the afternoon, &amp; stayed for the service.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I made Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName> read through my Byron lecture. He expressed warm approval, &amp;, as I allow myself to assume his sincerity, I was pleased &amp; reassured. For on a literary subject his opinion is not without weight.</hi></p>
         <p>Radcliffe's death at Oxford was reported last week. So the usual trinity of fatalities is completed – M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Headlam, Radcliffe, &amp; Bishop Quirk.</p></body></text></TEI>