<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A wet day, very depressing. I preached to the University at 10 a.m. in Trinity College Chapel. The congregation was mainly composed of undergraduates, the seats of the mighty being mostly vacant. The sermon was not, I fear, a success, and I was grievously handicapped by the persistent coughing of the brazen students</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Provost told me that he knew </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Armitage Robinson</hi><persName xml:id="44"></persName><hi rend="italic"> well, and accounted him to be the best critic of the New Testament in Europe. He admitted that he was "mulishly obstinate" in his opinions, but held that his critical judgement was remarkably sound. It was a pity, he thought that he (A. R.) had transferred his interest to antiquarianism. His ascetic aspect was no true indication of his normal habit of life.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 3.15 p.m. I preached in S. Patrick's Cathedral</hi>. The detestable weather did no doubt affect the size of the congregation, which, however, was considerable. The music was elaborate and fairly good, but, perhaps, too noisy. The sermon was listened to with attention, but was not, I fear, effective. We returned to the Provost's House after service, &amp; had tea. Then I walked in the college grounds for an hour with the Provost. I took advantage of the opportunity to consult him about the woeful &amp; perplexing case of John; &amp; he counselled the withdrawing of his license. That would, of course, mean his total ruin: yet it is hard to see what else can be done. There seems little of that deplorable vice among the Irish Protestant clergy.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard</hi> thinks that a disruption of the Church of England is probable, and perhaps desirable. He spoke of the poor quality of the English bishops, and contrasted them with their predecessors a generation ago. He thought the influence of the Bishop of London on the Bench had been disastrous. <hi rend="bold underline">In the London diocese children of five were confirmed, and in some churches the Latin tongue was used in the public services</hi>. We spoke of <hi rend="underline">Malines,</hi> which he regarded rather as an amiable weakness, than as an indefensible proceeding. But herein he was evidently swayed by his friendship for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Armitage Robinson</hi>, and his regard for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cantuar</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">He heartily agreed with my dislike of the assumption of something like Divine inspiration made by the Lambeth Conference, and emphasized by some of the Bishops, but he thought the fiasco of the Appeal for Reunion could hardly fail to check it</hi>. Of "Copec" he spoke with contempt, mixed with alarm. It was a most mischievous movement. His estimate of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName> was not high, perhaps not high enough. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi> was in his opinion one of the ablest of the Bishops, and with this I agreed. He said that since as Provost he had comparatively large leisure, he was devoting himself <hi rend="bold underline">to the completion of the commentary on S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> John's Gospel which he had undertaken some years ago, &amp; now hoped to publish next year. He had regretfully come to the conclusion that there had been a displacement of the text in one place. Chapter VI ought clearly to follow Chapter IV. Chapters V and VII were properly continuous</hi>.</p></body></text></TEI>