<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">June, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and there took train for Leeds. On my arrival I was met at the station, and carried to lunch at a Restaurant. I sate beside the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vicar of Leeds</hi><hi rend="underline">, and had some talk with him, but not to much effect as he is a cryptick cautious fellow who is so mortally afraid of giving himself away that he says nothing worth remembering</hi>. Then I attended the meeting in the Church Institute, in the interest of the 'Waifs &amp; Strays' Society. The Archbishop of York presided, and speeches were made by me, and Sir Gervase Beckett. Then I had tea with the Archbishop in the Club, and came away. I was met at Darlington by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and got back to the Castle in time for dinner. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Lasbrey</hi>, who is to address the Diocesan Conference on Foreign Missions, arrived &amp; stayed the night.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" gives more than a column on its front page to my speech on <hi rend="underline">Prohibition</hi>; &amp; brief reports of it appear in several of the papers. I shall become more than ever odious to the Fanaticks, and unintelligible to the Saints! It is obvious enough that the prominence given to a very insignificant little meeting reflects the anxiety of "the Trade" to make the most of such episcopal support as they can get! Had I spoken like an angel on a subject which did not affect that interest, my words w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> never have been reported at all.</p></body></text></TEI>