<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sends me "Notes &amp; Queries" vol. 147, No.7, which contains a note on my predecessor, Richard Barnes, signed J. C. Whitebrook. It offers some corrections of the Article on Barnes in D.N.B., and quotes a scurrilous account of his death</hi> from Lee's "The Church under Q. Elizabeth", adding this note:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"It is, however, curious that the diversity of Bishop and Dean at Durham over the question of the consumption of beer sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have commenced in Elizabethan days".</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There is no such diversity indicated in the passage quoted, but only that the Dean, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Toby Matthew</hi><hi rend="italic">, asked the dying bishop 'in sign of his faith to hold up his hands', &amp; that, in response to this appeal, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic">'always held his fingers to his mouth', an action which 'his base son' explained to mean a desire for drink. This precious scandal is quoted by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lee</hi><hi rend="italic"> from "An ancient Editor's Note Book", a contemporaneous account preserved in MS. at </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Stonyhurst</hi>.</p>
         <p>Making an act of faith in the weather, we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Baddeley, Peel Dennistoun<persName xml:id="4889"></persName>, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and I) left the Castle at 10.45 a.m., and motored to Borcovicus, where we arrived at 1.15 p.m., and found M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray with the two girls already on the ground. After a picnic lunch in the Roman Camp, we walked down the wall for some distance, and then returned to Chollerford, where we had tea, &amp; parted with Baddeley. We motored back to Auckland by way of Blanchland and Stanhope, nearly coming to grief on the high ground out of Blanchland.</p>
         <p>Peel Dennistoun left by the night train.</p></body></text></TEI>


