<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Thirty seven years ago, I put my presumptuous hand to the plough of Christ, and now I hardly know how to keep it thereon. The world has changed strangely, almost terribly. "There are first which were last; &amp; last which were first". Old names no longer carry old meanings. I find myself already an exile from the life of my time.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham for the service at 10 a.m. Macdonald preached, &amp; roared like a Bashan&#8211;bull, so that I, who was within a few feet of him, was nearly deafened, while the echoes of the cathedral were so effectually raised that probably few could distinguish anything intelligible through the clamour! There were less than 20 communicants, though I consecrated enough bread &amp; wine to have communicated 200. Accordingly, there was a long interval during which the Elements were distributed among the newly ordained, &amp; such of the clergy as possessed consciences free to permit the reception of these hallowed Gifts when non fasting. The notion of a social act has so perished from Anglican minds that Communion is thought of, &amp; treated, as a matter of private devotion. This is a real injury to corporate life.</p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the cathedral, &amp; then, after tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, motored to Whickham, &amp; there consecrated an extension of the churchyard. There was a special service in church, at which I preached, &amp; then consecrated a banner for the Girl Guides. I returned to Auckland, arriving about 10 p.m. </p></body></text></TEI>