<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>A fine still morning, which, if its promise be fulfilled, will be ideal for motoring, and I must abandon the car for the train, the country for the town, and the familiar comradeship of <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> for the grimacing humbug of a public luncheon. Oh dear! And what is Byron to me, or I to Byron, that I should do this, and waste five pounds on railway fares in the bargain?</p>
         <p>We left the Priory after breakfast. I caught the 10.5 a.m. train to Stroud, and travelled to London: Ella continued her journey homeward in the car. <hi rend="bold underline">The Byron Centenary Luncheon was held in the Victoria Hall, Charing Cross</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Baldwin</hi><persName xml:id="4118"></persName> presided over a numerous company. I made a speech which was not particularly successful. <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Ernle</hi><persName xml:id="1394"></persName> spoke well, but was rather too declamatory. I had my hair cut, and, then, after tea in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, caught the 5.30 p.m. express to Bishop Auckland, where I arrived shortly after 11 p.m.</p>
         <p>I beguiled the journey by reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry Ford's</hi> remarkable book, "<hi rend="underline">My life and work</hi>". He means well, but his head has been turned by the immense success of his motor&#8211;industry, which he seems to misunderstand, &amp; he bases on his misunderstanding opinions about the organization of industry, which cannot be sound. Life in his vast factories, though the workmen are paid profusely, must be horrible.</p></body></text></TEI>