<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a sermon on "The sweet uses of Advertisement" for Westminster Abbey, when I preach there on July 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> to the International Advertising Convention. At lunch were several ladies of the Women's Institute Committee, including Lady Bell, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pease, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Stobart. They had a F&#x00EA;te in the Park. After lunch I motored to Durham, &amp; presided at the meeting of the Diocesan Conference. My address, which was very short, was coldly received. My references to Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> appointment were not applauded, &amp;, indeed, I had every reason to think that I was as odious as I deserve to be. The discussion on Foreign Missions was mortally dull. After the conference I went to the Castle, and had interviews with (&#x3B1;) Williams, one of the masters of Durham School, who desires to be ordained, (&#x3B2;) Kay, one of the ex&#8211;choristers, now at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Chad's, who seeks a grant from the Diocesan Fund to assist his preparation for Holy Orders, (&#x3B3;) Major Slorach, whom I desired to see with reference to that hateful business of John, (&#x3B4;) the Barrington Trustees, who allotted four scholarships, of which one (&#x00A3;40) went to Peter Hughes. Then I returned to Auckland in time for dinner.</p>
         <p>I had two abusive communications about my speech on Prohibition, &amp; one flatterous letter from a parson who wound up by begging for a living! Is there such a thing as an honest clergyman left on earth?</p></body></text></TEI>