<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to Durham for the meeting of the Council of the Rescue &amp; Preventive Association. As the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk had been rather specially concerned with this work, I thought it proper to make some observations about his death. A suitable resolution of condolence was adopted, which on my return to Auckland I sent to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk.</p>
         <p>We lunched with Colonel<persName xml:id="3825"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ritson<persName xml:id="3826"></persName> in order to meet their prospective son&#8211;in&#8211;law, Mr Strakes. Then we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">I sent away a number of copies of the Byron lecture to various people. Probably the only effect is to suggest that I am an idle fellow, who neglects his diocese in order to indulge his hobby! And it is true that much of the time, which could have been much better employed, was wasted on that precious lecture: and that my own conscience is so far exercised by the fact, that I have made a mental resolve that nothing shall induce me to accept any new proposal which will turn me aside from the straight&#8211;forward pathway of diocesan obligation.</hi><hi rend="italic">"I cannot imagine how you find time to do work of this kind and articles for Reviews in the midst of your other work. I admire &amp; envy" – so writes the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archbishop of York</hi><hi rend="italic"> sub&#8211;acidly. Probably his Grace expresses his admiration somewhat less flatteringly when he speaks of the Bishop of Durham to others.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But the key to my performance is that I have no party claims, decline all invitations to address meetings, and avoid the Church Societies</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>