<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>At last a fine day, and, of course, our last! I strolled for an hour after breakfast with mine host, and talked. Then had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ednam</hi>. He is intelligent, and rather positive. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I sate awhile in the little sheltered house by the shore, &amp; watched the terns. Occasionally a heron flopped by majestically. Then I read an article in the "<hi rend="underline">Contemporary</hi>" on "The new Reformation" by the American faith&#8211;healing parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Samuel M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Comb</hi>. It appears that the Church of the Future is to include Spiritualism, Socialism, &amp; Faith&#8211;healing in its Gospel, and every conceivable variety of spiritual exercise in its worship, while its creed is to be the sum of all kinds of opinion. The prospect is not attractive.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">We left Mount Stewart at 5.30 p.m., and motored to Belfast, where we caught the train to Larne</hi>. The sea was like a mill&#8211;pond. We crossed in two hours, the steamer being escorted by a school of porpoises as it neared Stranraer. We had reserved a cabin on board, and seats in the train. These arrangements wasted 8/&#8211;. At Carlisle Ella got out in order to spend the night in a Hotel with a view to going on to Glasgow in the morning. I continued in the train until, at 2.40 a.m., I reached Newcastle. A bed&#8211;room had been reserved for me in the Railway Hotel and, within a few minutes of 3 a.m., I had gone to bed for a brief rest.</p></body></text></TEI>