<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[164]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast a Committee of the Barnard Castle School Governors with the headmaster arrived, and we duly elected a young parson from Newcastle, who had been trained in S. Chad's, to be an assistant master, and to act as chaplain. He thought it his duty to explain that his conscience wouldn't allow him to administer the Holy Communion to unconfirmed boys! I expounded the salutary and indeed indispensable doctrine of the limits of responsibility, and he acquiesced: but there will probably be a return of the mischief. Fanaticism is a restless spirit, &amp; it never continues in one stay!</p>
         <p>Then I returned to my 'Charge', &amp; worked at it with little result until lunch. In the afternoon I played bowls with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. After tea, finding myself too stupid – for the atmosphere was sulphurously close – to work, I fell to reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. A. Froude's</hi><persName xml:id="1409"></persName> account of the Oxford Movement, which is included in his "Short Studies". His dislike of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Keble</hi> is apparent, and probably well&#8211;grounded. I have myself formed the opinion that he was a narrow spirit, whose fame will hardly survive the reign of the fanaticism he did so much to re&#8211;bind on Anglicans. Of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Newman</hi> he writes with sympathy and understanding. Indeed, I hardly know where to find a more illuminating account of that alluring figure. His references to his brother are charming. There can hardly be any doubt that, if he had lived, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Richard Hurrell Froude</hi>, would have led the secession to Rome.</p></body></text></TEI>