<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I could not sleep last night, and the only book I had to relieve the tedium of my involuntary vigil was a translation (very crude, however faithful) of Schweitzer's "Dale Memorial Lectures 1922" entitled "Civilization and Ethics". Part 1. "The Decay &amp; the Restoration of Civilization: The Philosophy of Civilization" is readable enough, &amp; the work of a Translator named Campion: but Part II is horrible. M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> John Nash, the Translator, may have known German, but he can't write English! And I am divided in mind, as I read, being unable to determine whether the eminent author is elaborating a platitude, or enunciating a mare's nest! However, as in all <hi rend="doubleunderline">Schweitzer's</hi> writing his pages glitter with <hi rend="underline">obiter dicta</hi> which are worth having. The general effect of the book is depressing. If the only hope for civilization lies in the general attainment of a satisfying "world&#8211;view", which shall be strong enough to make the individual able to hold his own against the depersonalizing influences of the world as it is now, the prospect of escape seems sufficiently slight. He dismisses brusquely the notion that the breaking up of the present civilization might be the prelude to a new civilization, possibly higher, by <hi rend="underline">observing that there are no undeveloped races competent – like the Teutons – to construct a new order. We know the potentialities of humanity by this time</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left Park Lane after breakfast, and went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I wrote telegrams to the rector of Birchington and Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, arranging that the funeral should be at 2 p.m. on Wednesday. Then I went to the hair&#8211;dressers, and had my hair cut<hi rend="italic">.</hi> This done, I went to the Passport Office to enquire about William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> pass&#8211;port. It had already been sent to him. Next, I called at the Deanery, but, to no purpose, as the Dean was presiding at the Election. Then I went to Rees &amp; bought "S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Joan" to read on the train. It was now noon, so I went to King's Cross, &amp; secured my place. My compangnon de voyage was a pleasant maiden named Joan Ivy Heaton, who, like me, was travelling to Darlington. She was visiting a school&#8211;fellow there. We lightened the journey with talk. At Darlington Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> and Leng met me with the car.</p>
         <p>At 9.30 p.m. there was a short service in the Chapel conducted by Bishop Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. The doctor &amp; a few neighbours with the servants and ourselves composed the congregation. We sang two hymns, "Jesu, Lover of my soul" and "Abide with me". Alexander expressed to me the sympathy of the servants. Indeed, they have all been very kind. I think Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> sweetness of aspect and temper had appealed to them. </p></body></text></TEI>
