<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> June, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Our hosts motored us to Duncannon Park, where we lunched with Lord and Lady Ranfurly. On the way through Armagh we stopped to visit the public library which was built &amp; endowed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Primate Robinson</hi>, who built the palace. <hi rend="underline">It has inscribed over the entrance the significantly suitable word </hi>^[Greek word]^<hi rend="underline">, a hospital for the mind</hi>. It is said to be the Greek equivalent of an Egyptian term for a library. <hi rend="bold underline">After lunch we took train to Belfast, where we were met by a car, &amp; motored to Mount Stewart</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Here at last I got hold of the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>": and found my letter in the first page of yesterday's issue. It nearly fills a column, and seems to hang together. Lord Daryngton's<persName xml:id="5400"></persName> delay in answering my request for the postponement of the debate on the Winchester Diocese (Division) Measure has had the effect of my writing a superfluous letter, which may, however, do good in awakening interest in the matter. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Carson</hi> &amp; his wife are staying here: and tomorrow <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> is coming.</p>
         <p>After tea I strolled with L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Carson, &amp; had much interesting talk with him. He said that he was once offered the Presidency of the Divorce Court, which, with much hesitation, he had declined. I made him read my letter. He said my point about the Ecclesiastical Committee was a good one.</p></body></text></TEI>