<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>[written in Greek, with English translation following] It is the hatefullest of all human sorrows to have much knowledge and no power.</p>
         <p>Herodotus. Bk.ix. 16.</p>
         </div>
         <p>These words of the prophetic Persian exactly express my mind as I review the situation into which the Church of England has been brought by the fatuous levity of its leaders. They express my mind as I contemplate my diocese, and set my actual knowledge of the clergy and their work against my power to reform the one and improve the other. They express my mind when I examine myself and contrast what I know of my own faults and limitations with my ability to find &amp; remove the last. "<hi rend="underline">O God there is no mercy with Thee: therefore shalt thou be afeared</hi>". It is inscrutable long–sufferance of the All–Holy that most terrifies me. </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>We sin, and sin again,</p>
         <p>While the sky which noticed all makes no disclosures,</p>
         <p>And the Earth maintains its terrible composure.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The fearful verdict of the prophet on God's ancient people, 'that they caused the Lord's People to transgress,' will, I fear greatly, be the verdict ultimately passed on us, who claim to speak to the English People, in the "honourable name" of Christ.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote two letters, the one to Gooch accepting the invitation of the Historical Association that I should deliver an "inaugural address" at the annual meeting in Newcastle next January: the other to John<persName xml:id="5397"></persName>, asking for his opinion as to Briggs's fitness for Holy Orders.</p>
         <p>Then I visited the hair–dresser: &amp; afterwards walked to Westminster with the intention of calling on Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, but I found the Abbey Church environed on every side with motors, and was told that a great function of the Knights of the Bath was in progress. So I called on Carόe, only to find him about. Then I returned to the Admiralty, and lunched with mine host. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me being apparently well satisfied with the Court last night, at which she had presented <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne Booker</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName>. After lunch I drove to Lambeth for the meeting of Bishops, &amp; stayed there until nearly six o'clock, when I returned to the Admiralty.</p>
         <p>I called at Downing Street in the course of the day. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Duff, the Patronage Secretary, told me that he was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Duff's</hi> son. The Solicitor–General, Sir Henry Slessor<persName xml:id="5399"></persName>, &amp; his wife – manifest Jews – came to dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Chelmsford</hi><persName xml:id="65"></persName> took us to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard Shaw's</hi> historical play, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Joan. It is certainly a fine piece of work, but the epilogue is a failure. Two reflections visited my mind as I witnessed the performance. First, how terrestrially impossible is "sainthood", and how helpless are "persecutors" to save "saints" from "martyrdom" to which they send them. Next, how completely the Christian tradition has lost its hold on modern minds and consciences. "Hell" was made a joke of, and provoked laughter.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At the Bishops' meeting nothing of any interest or importance was done. The Archbishop said something about the dates at which the measures recently passed by the National Assembly would come before the House of Lords. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I said that it was my desire to oppose the measure for dividing the diocese of Winchester, &amp; that I should resent the choice of a date on which it was not reasonably possible for me to be present</hi><hi rend="italic">. His Grace made some observations on the "Pilgrimage" which the Anglo–Catholics have been making to the Holy Land under the leadership of</hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">that episcopal jack–ass</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> the Bishop of Nassau<persName xml:id="5386"></persName>. I asked whether he had informed the Eastern ecclesiastics as to the wholly unauthorised character of the whole proceedings, and especially of the statements of doctrine which the pilgrims offer as properly Anglican. I was assured that the afore–mentioned </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Jack–ass</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic">, was discretion incarnate!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>