<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me an application for the position of Hangman which had come to him as Deputy Sheriff. It is certainly a curious document, worth inserting in this curious journal!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A correspondent from Winnipeg wrote to me an interesting account of the working of Prohibition in Canada</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> He held that its advantages were far outweighed by its evils. I wrote civilly to him, and sent him a copy of my speech. There is some reason for desiring that a correct version of it sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be accessible on that side of the Atlantic. After lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I played bowls.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Thurlows</hi><persName xml:id="5272"></persName>, passing through Auckland on their way to Scotland, called to see us. The 3 boys are very promising and attractive. </p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Sir Vincent Baddeley</hi> arrived in time for dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">It is, perhaps, an unfortunate circumstance that the attempt to establish a congregational autonomy in the Church of England has coincided with the remarkable increase in the mobility of the population. One reason why so little interest has been evoked for the new parochial church councils is the fact that even the church people are no longer attending the services of their parish church with any regularity. They naturally leave all that concerns the parish to those who form the regular congregations, and these form a diminishing number of the humbler folk.</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi></p></body></text></TEI>