<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> still lingers, though mostly unconscious or semi&#8211;conscious. I went to see her about noon, &amp; she knew me, and said "Goodbye", but this flicker of intelligence was but momentary. I wrote to my Brothers, Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> &amp; Frank<persName xml:id="3368"></persName>. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I finished the sermon for Gray's Inn, &amp; then set myself to the Herculean task of putting my table to rights.</hi></p>
         <p>That grotesque parson, Hudson Barker<persName xml:id="3575"></persName>, came to see me about the details of his marriage ceremony. As he was ordained as long ago as 1893, he cannot be less than 54 years old and is probably some years older. He is resolved that his marriage shall be exemplary. It is to be at 9 a.m. and followed by a celebration of the Holy Communion. He is in a fatuous condition of self&#8211;absorbed vanity! One could but humour the poor wretch.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I walked round the park with the dogs.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Alexandra Fisher</hi> came to see me about the confirmation of a doctor's wife who has been trained as a Scottish Presbyterian.</p>
         <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived from Sedburgh for the night. He seemed well and in the highest spirits.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Several letters came to me from people who were shocked &amp; disgusted by Welldon's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> insolent attack on his diocesan. It was, of course, a monstrous proceeding, but, so far as I am concerned, there is nothing to be said</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>