<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I went in to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Lay Readers' Committee. There was a kind of revolt brewing, some of the lay&#8211;readers affecting to be mightily indignant at some utterances of mine at the last meeting of Convocation! I let them "blow off steam", and then gave them 'the soft answer', which, I trust, 'turned away wrath'. Then I went to my rooms in the Castle, &amp; had an interview with Wynne&#8211;Willson's<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> curate, Lister, who has been offered a living by Bishop Frodsham. After tea, I motored to Gateshead, and confirmed 210 persons in S. George's Church. It was in impressive, indeed an inspiring service. The confirmation was all over in 1 hour and 20 minutes, which, considering that I confirm in pairs, was fairly expeditious. We returned to Auckland after the service, carrying the old Rector of Gateshead Fell as far as the foot of the hill leading to his parish. We reached the Castle about 10 p.m. I may fairly say that my working day has extended to 14 hours. At 8 a.m. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I started with the correspondence, &amp; I have been working without intermission save briefly for meals, until 10 p.m. And this is not an unrepresentative day.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is not an idle life: but the work is not the real burden on an English Bishop. That may bring to him as much comfort as fatigue. But when, perforce, he sits in judgment on others – Ordination candidate &amp; clergy – and closes abruptly this one's career, &amp; darkens this one's prospects, he is miserable indeed. 'Who are thou that judgest another?</hi>'</p></body></text></TEI>