<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>With joy I heard Ambrose in his sermons to the people, oftentimes most diligently recommended this text for a rule. "The letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life": whilst he drew aside the mystic veil, laying open spiritually what according to the letter, seemed to teach something unsound.</p>
         <p>L. Augustine Confessions Bk. VI.c.iv.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the morning in revising the charge</hi>: &amp; then I wrote to Hodder &amp; Stroughton inquiring they would undertake its publication. It makes up about 25000 words as I reckon.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dobson</hi> came to lunch, and afterwards played bowls with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and me. He has decided to accept the curacy of Whickham. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Little</hi> is an experienced parish priest who ought to be able to teach him the parson's business. I had some talk with him, urging him particularly to be modest and teachable. The special difficulty with young men of the humbler social type, who are above the average level of intelligence, and have gained some distinction in the university, is the tendency to over&#8211;estimate both their powers and their achievements. <hi rend="bold underline">Nor do they realize how desperately disadvantaged they are by the lack of that broad inbred culture, which forms the foundation of all formal training in the case of well&#8211;born, well&#8211;brought up Englishmen. The discovery of this fact presently may be very painful</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>