<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfasting with Lord S., I went to the Club, and found some letters. Then I walked to Eccleston Sq., and saw Geordie<persName xml:id="571"></persName> and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. I lunched at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName>, and then walked to Westminster, where I tried vainly to see Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> &amp; Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. <hi rend="underline">There was a good muster of peers for the debate on the Winchester Bill, </hi>but so much time was wasted, first in discussing a tiresome Scotch Bill, and then, by Lord Northbrook<persName xml:id="5403"></persName> in his speech, that the debate stood adjourned. After Northbrook had spoken, the Bishop of Winchester spoke, &amp; was followed by the Bishop of Norwich. Then came Lord Selbourne<persName xml:id="311"></persName>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">then for about 20 minutes I spoke.</hi><hi rend="underline">My speech was delivered in a great hurry, with my eye on the clock. It was well&#8211;received, &amp; I think, if the division had been taken when I sat down, the measure would have been thrown out.</hi> Several peers congratulated me on my speech. <hi rend="underline">I hurried off to Park Lane, dressed in haste, and drove to the Mansion House</hi>. Ella was already in her place. I proposed <hi rend="underline">"The Church Overseas"</hi> in a dull speech. Then we came away, and I was back in my "Prophet's Chamber" by 10.45 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
         <p>It is difficult to secure any real authority in a deliberative Assembly in which one is but an occasional visitor. If one's attendance were frequent, one could not fail to get into personal touch with the Peers who are regular in the House, and this would generate friendship and confidence. As things stand, my appearance and speeches are so infrequent, that they have something portentous about them, and certainly my modes of reasoning and of expression are so unfamiliar to my hearers that they are apt to be misunderstood and disliked. But is it worth while for a Bishop to acquire influence in the House of Lords, when the power of that House has almost passed away, and when its ecclesiastical activity has shrunk to the narrowest proportions? The only certain consequence of taking even successful action in the House of Lords is to widen the gulf between one's self and "the Church", and so to lessen one's influence in one's own sphere of activity. Why then, should I trouble myself about the House of Lords at all? It must not be supposed that public opinion is materially affected by speeches in that House. Commonly they are reported in the briefest outline by the secular press, and only garbled "snippets" in the press ecclesiastical. Beyond providing "copy" for the "Church Times", there is no result. Why, then, it must again be asked, should the Bishop of Durham waste time &amp; money in attending the debates of the House of Lords?</p></body></text></TEI>