<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>In spite of the falling rain and hopeless sky, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Rostrevor, and lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John</hi><persName xml:id="5388"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Ross</hi> with whom was their niece <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lawrie</hi>. I was interested in the old man's conversation, for, although he is a papist, he talked very freely about Irish politics. He did not appear to be very hopeful about the future. After lunch he shewed us round his garden which was filled with rare &amp; beautiful plants. The rain having ceased, &amp; the sun at length shining, we were able to enjoy a spectacle of great beauty and variety. <hi rend="bold underline">We returned to Mount Stewart in time for a late tea</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">The Ulster Protestant Voters' Defence Association</hi>" sent me a resolution signed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir R. Kennedy K.C.M.G.</hi>, the President, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">James Crossey</hi>, the Secretary. It is expressed in a style of stilted fanaticism, with which I am but too familiar in England. The <hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi> will certainly get hold of it, and seize so excellent an opportunity for making me look ridiculous! I wrote a brief acknowledgement.</p>
         <p>I has come talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> on ecclesiastical affairs. He is dogmatic, omniscient, and plausible, but quite hopelessly remote from the actual situation. The bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> has a letter in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" on the Winchester Division Measure, which went through the House of Commons after a farcical debate.</p></body></text></TEI>