<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>June 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1924.</p>
         <p>Dear Lord Northbrook<persName xml:id="5403"></persName>,</p>
         <p>Your letter was sent on to me from Auckland Castle. I am very willing to add my name to "the Whip" which you propose to issue. It does seem to me important that a measure for cutting up the ancient diocese of Winchester should be treated as something more than a local matter, and that the implied policy of multiplying bishops should come under the direct cognizance and consideration of Parliament, before it is acted upon.</p>
         <p>And I must needs think that, in the present state of politics, a special responsibility attaches to the House of Lords.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>my Lord,</p>
         <p>Yours v, faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The R<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hon<hi rend="superscript underline">ble</hi></p>
         <p>The Earl of Northbrook</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>June 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1924.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rashdall,</p>
         <p>I can quite understand, &amp; sympathize with, the resentment you must needs feel at many things that are said about the Dean<persName xml:id="117"></persName>. But I do not think they are worth noticing. After all, the importance of compliments &amp; censures turns on the quality of their authors: &amp; the hurtful misunderstandings &amp; even perversions of fact which distress you come from persons who have no title to speak about the Dean's beliefs, &amp; no kind of weight, intellectual or moral. <hi rend="bold underline">Your husband's reputation is quite secure: it has its attestations in his books which are accessible, &amp; will be read long after the controversies which gathered about his name have been forgotten. Of my contemporaries I know</hi><hi rend="underline">none</hi><hi rend="bold underline">respecting whom there has been so remarkable a consensus of approbation as he has evoked</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>I think it is certainly unnecessary to <hi rend="underline">defend</hi> his memory: I think it might be unwise. Because his critics are mostly fanatics, &amp; cannot see what fools they make of themselves when they enter a sphere in which knowledge &amp; candour are indispensable conditions of reaching truth. Therefore they would seek to justify themselves by still more offensive writing.<hi rend="bold underline"> You know that I loved &amp; valued him, &amp;, therefore, that if I thought his fame was likely to be injured in the least by his</hi><hi rend="bold">[70] </hi>[symbol] <hi rend="bold underline">post&#8211;mortem detractors, I would urge championship. But I see no reason whatever for thinking that his memory will be even temporarily injured by that kind of detraction</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>With ever kind regards,</p>
         <p>I am, ever yrs,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Anonymous writing carries always its own disproof</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the whole morning writing letters in Lady Londonderry's room, which she abandoned to me with her usual kindness. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked a little, &amp; sate by the Lough. We noticed three herons fishing. There is a heronry on this property. At dinner I sate between Lady Ednam &amp; Lady Dufferin, both pretty and pleasant young women, but their present manner of dressing is not beautiful! After dinner Carson and I talked together until we dispersed to our bed&#8211;rooms. He has known so many people, &amp; has such an amusing manner of retailing his knowledge, that his talk is both informing and entertaining. But he evidently belongs to a world which is dead, and on the way to be forgotten: and he is not unconscious of the fact. He is in his 71<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> year, &amp; speaks as a 'laudator temporis acti'.<note xml:id="545" n="1"></note></p></body></text></TEI>