<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I left the Admiralty House after breakfast, and drove to King's Cross, dropping <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> on the way at the British Museum. I left at 10 a.m. and reached Darlington at 2.50 p.m., where William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car. He told me that the fatal letter had come from Johannesburg, and that he was invited to go thither. So I must make up my mind to part with him.</p>
         <p>Chancellor P. V. Smith<persName xml:id="765"></persName> arrived about 5 p.m. His natural dullness is so powerfully re&#8211;inforced by his deafness that it is almost impossible to carry on conversation with him. The obvious requirements of a decent hospitality compelled me, none the less, to essay the well&#8211;nigh hopeless task, and by the time I showed the old gentleman to his bedroom, I was physically exhausted! It was as if I had been practising for open&#8211;air addresses for two hours on end!</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The time is long past for supporting any form of Christianity on a foundation of historical disguise" – Coulton<persName xml:id="4746"></persName>. 'Five centuries of Religion', p. 321.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is certainly true, and yet I do not think I am mistaken when I say of the most energetic religious movements in the country that the [sic] are supported, almost confessedly, 'on a foundation of historical disguise'. The 'Anglo&#8211;Catholics' almost exult in outraging History.</p></body></text></TEI>