<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I came away by the early train, leaving Glasgow at 8.40 a.m. and reaching Newcastle at 12.39 noon. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car, &amp; carried me to the Castle, where I arrived about 2 p.m. I wrote letters, <hi rend="underline">including one to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi> came to see me. He has received a tentative proposal for the sale of his Vicarage, and he thinks that, if anything above &#x00A3;8000 can be obtained for it, the sale should be made in the interest of the living. Half the money w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be needed for the provision of a new vicarage, &amp; half w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> go to improving the meagre income. I don't like the tendency which subordinates history, and spiritual interest, and pastoral convenience to the simple consideration of finance. The sale of the vicarages situate in the "business&#8211;neighbourhoods", in order to garner for the benefice the fantastic values which attach to the sites, does not attract me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi> assures me that another site, not less convenient to priest and people is obtainable, and that the poorness of the endowment is now a grave obstacle to finding a good man for the living. I admitted the force of these pleas, and authorized him to "explore" the possibilities of sale. At the end of the year at latest we shall have to find a successor to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi>, &amp;, if changes are to be made, they had better be made before a new appointment.</p></body></text></TEI>