<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[125]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to Darlington, and took train for York where we arrived a full hour before the time appointed <hi rend="bold underline">for the consecration of the Bishop of Jarrow.</hi> We used the time by strolling in York, &amp; visiting three of the parishes, of which one was unused &amp; most interesting. The service in the cathedral was admirably arranged, &amp; carried through. Paget of Chester and I presented the bishop&#8211;designate<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">The dean of Christ Church (White) preached the sermon which included a warm eulogy on </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Knight</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, which in the circumstances was as timely as, I doubt not, it was sincere and merited.</hi> We lunched with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knights</hi> in the Station Hotel, and then I caught the 2.3 p.m. express. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leng</hi> met me at Darlington, &amp; drove me to Barnard Castle, where I presided at a meeting of the School governors. After this, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The afternoon post brought me a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Home Gordon</hi> (i.e. Williams &amp; Norgate) assuming that I would [do] them "the honour of writing the Reformation for the Home University Library".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"With regard to the date. That we must leave to you. The present writer is quite aware how rapidly you are able to write on a subject which appeals to you, as this evidently does".</p>
         </div>
         <p>The good man in this case knows a good deal more about me than I know about myself. So far from being a "ready writer" I am both mentally and physically a very slow one!</p></body></text></TEI>