<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for Newcastle, being much handicapped by the absence of the letter t from my typewriter. I had never realized the importance of that letter. However I <hi rend="underline">did</hi> finish the beastly thing, and "for this relief much thanks"!</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Middleton, &amp; there confirmed 58 persons. Middleton is just 20 miles from Auckland, &amp; the road lies over open moorland most of the way. I returned to the Castle for tea, and then set out again for Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street. There I confirmed, as the Rector assured me, no less than 215 persons, very equally divided between the sexes. I made as much speed as I could, &amp; we were out of the church by a few minutes after 8 p.m. After service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The waste of time over the Byron lecture led me to resolve that I would accept no more invitations to undertake tasks which lay outside my proper work. Now arrives a request from G. P. Gooch, the President of the Historical Association asking me to deliver the "inaugural address" when the Association holds its annual meeting at Newcastle in January, 1925. I hardly like to decline; yet I hardly venture to accept. Probably I shall have to do it, and waste yet more time. I can take any historical subject I like</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>