<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cosgrave</hi><persName xml:id="5313"></persName> came to see me about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hill</hi>, and practically recalled his letter, on which I had acted. It did not appear to me advisable to go back altogether on my decision, so I consented to postpone his ordination for yet another six months.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Apperley</hi> came to lunch, and afterwards looked over the Castle, which Apperley, though he has lived all his long life in the diocese, had never before seen.</p>
         <p>At 4 p.m. I instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Birney</hi><persName xml:id="5383"></persName> to the Vicarage of Witton Park. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Boddy</hi>, the incumbents of Ferryhill and Pittington, who have known him from boyhood, came to the service, &amp; several other clergy. The congregation consisted largely of the people from Ferryhill, whose presence was no mean certificate to the worth of his character.</p>
         <p>At 6 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frederick Briggs</hi> of 4, Cochrane Terrace, Ferryhill, came to see me with reference to an application, which he had addressed to me, to be accepted as a candidate for Holy Orders. He is 241/2 years old, with no degree, the son of a miner, and out of work. He has been converted to Papistry, and returned from that field after a year! He has a pleasant manner, &amp; smile, but a weak look, which is not prepossessing: &amp; his account of himself was not altogether satisfactory. However I was sufficiently interested to write letters of inquiry to five persons, whom he named as having had dealings with him.</p></body></text></TEI>