<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>He ever warr'd with freedom and the free;</p>
         <p>Nations as men, home subjects, foreign foes,</p>
         <p>So that they utter'd the word 'Liberty!'</p>
         <p>Found George the Third their first opponent. Whose</p>
         <p>History was ever stain'd as his will be</p>
         <p>With national and individual woes?</p>
         <p>'The Vision of Judgement s. xlv.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The weather was unkindly, for, though the temperature was mild, the sky was clouded, and during the afternoon the rain fell with quiet pertinacity. After lunch, Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName> motored us to <hi rend="underline">Wentworth</hi>, the seat of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Fitz William</hi>. It is an immense house, built by Vanbrough. I was particularly interested in the pictures, among which are several of the great <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Strafford</hi>. One which depicts him dictating to a century is specially noteworthy.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Milner</hi>, Papists but pleasant people, arrived. The papers announce the death of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marie Corelli</hi>, a popular but foolish writer.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3465"></persName> is a student of Napoleonic literature, but he had never read Byron's lines on Napoleon in "The Age of Bronze". I read them to him, &amp; also the description of Newstead in 'Don Juan'.</p>
         <p>The Christ Church scientifick don is named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lindamann</hi><persName xml:id="5404"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Ah! thine was not the temper or the taste</p>
         <p>For thrones: the table sees thee better placed:</p>
         <p>A mild Epicurean, form'd, at best,</p>
         <p>To be a kind host and as good a guest,</p>
         <p>To talk of letters, and to know by heart</p>
         <p>One <hi rend="underline">half</hi> the poet's, <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the gourmand's art:</p>
         <p>A scholar always now and then a wit,</p>
         <p>And gentle when digestion may permit:&#8211;</p>
         <p>But not to govern lands enslaved or free;</p>
         <p>The gout was martyrdom enough for thee.</p>
         <p>The Age of Bronze. S. xiii.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This picture of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Louis xviii</hi> is inimitable: the companion picture of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Czar Alexander</hi> is not inferior.</p>
         <p>His contemporaries knew Byron, not merely as the brilliant poet and the scandalous profligate, but also as the champion of oppressed people in Ireland, Italy and Greece. His influence on the side of national liberty was felt on both sides of the great controversy. His memory was that of a Martyr to the Cause, &amp; his death ensured its victory in Greece, &amp; hastened its advent in Italy. The verdict of history is decisively honourable on this aspect of his chequered &amp; shadowed career. Tried by every test we must adjudge Byron to be the servant of humanity.</p></body></text></TEI>