<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Peter’s Day, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Almighty God, who by thy Son Jesus Christ didst give to thy Apostle Saint Peter many excellent gifts, and commandedst him earnestly to feed thy flock: make, we beseech thee, all Bishops and Pastors diligently to preach thy holy Word, and the people diligently to follow the same, that they may receive the crown of everlasting glory; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>'Preaching' is here plainly assumed to be the principal function of the Bishop. 'Bishops and Pastors' probably are intended to refer only to the Bishop.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 11 communicants including </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It will be the last time that I shall give the Blessed Sacrament to him before he goes to South Africa next month, for I shall not be here on another Sunday until he has disappeared. May God's Blessing rest on him all the way he goes! His departure will leave a great void in my life, for during these five years of close &amp; continuous comradeship, he has become very dear to me, more like a son than a servant. But parting is the law of the world, and I am drawing to the end of my career while he is but starting his. It is folly &amp; worse to give one's heart to anything or anybody in this passing show of life.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p>A blustering day, with splutterings of rain and intervals of sunshine. I motored to Monkwearmouth, diverging on the way out in order to pick up Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> at Sherburn Hill. We ran into the Mayor's procession on its way to the parish church. There was, of course, a crowded congregation. The service had been carefully thought out, and was carried through without a hitch. The Mayor read the lessons, and I preached the sermon. The Bishop of Wakefield (Eden) walked in the procession. In the vestry afterwards I spake shortly to the Choir, and announced that I had nominated the Vicar to be an hon: canon. Then we returned to Auckland in time for lunch.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 3 p.m. there was the annual confirmation for adults in the chapel</hi>; 62 were presented, of whom a third were males. Parry&#8211;Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName> presented the candidates: the choir of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, Bishop Auckland, assisted, &amp; their organist played. After the service I had a few words with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Noel Gwilliam</hi>, who had motored some candidates from his father's parish, and I gave him a copy of the Byron lecture. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Berry</hi> was present: he had never before seen a confirmation.</p>
         <p>I wrote a number of letters, which ought long ago to have been written; but in these days of hustlement there is no help for it, &amp; if one only leaves letters unanswered long enough, they answer themselves! Also, I acknowledged another little volume of verse from M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dolphin of Edmundbyers. She has facility, but is not a great poet! </p></body></text></TEI>