<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I drove to Gray's Inn, and preached to a little congregation of lawyers, American and English, which filled to overflowing the Chapel. The service was curiously accordant with the melancholy sentiments which filled my mind. David's exquisite lament for Jonathan came in the first lesson. The phrase "passing the love of women" never before seemed so full of meaning. The anthem was alas strangely relevant – "<hi rend="underline">Comes at times a stillness as of even, Steeping the soul in memories of love</hi>". Then followed lunch, &amp; I tried to interest myself in the conversation. The Benchers and the Americans were insistent on printing the sermon, and, of course, I promised to let them have the Ms.; but they will have forgotten their wish by the time they get it! Then I went to the Athanaeum, and read a novel. After tea I walked to Westminster, and called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. Then I went back to Park Lane, and dined quietly with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3466"></persName> &amp; her sister. Thus ended the fourth year of my tenure of the Bishoprick of Durham. Tomorrow I enter on "the fifth year of Our Translation". In some important respects the conditions of my life have changed, and a new chapter in it is opening.</p></body></text></TEI>