<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 10.20 a.m., and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington, where I booked to Cambridge. There were three changes on the way – at Peterborough, at March, and at Ely – and I arrived at Cambridge at 5.21 p.m. Hardly had I reached <hi rend="bold underline">the Master's Lodgings at Corpus</hi> before a thunderstorm broke. <hi rend="bold underline">The Master took me to dine with "the Family" at Trinity.</hi> This club is of ancient origin, &amp; has a Jacobite tradition. The host on this occasion was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lawrence</hi>, one of the editors of L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Acton's writings. Opposite to me was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Durnford</hi>, the V. Provost of King's, and on my other side, was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Benson</hi>. So I was well placed: &amp; had a pleasant evening.</p>
         <p>I beguiled the journey from Darlington to Cambridge, by reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">Foakes Jackson's</hi><persName xml:id="3566"></persName> new book, "<hi rend="underline">Anglican Church Principles</hi>". It is brightly written, informing, suggestive, and stimulating: but what Anglican church principles are, or whether there <hi rend="underline">are</hi> any Anglican church principles, is left wholly undisclosed. We are told how the parties which distract &amp; divide the Church of England came to be, and what they represent, but how their several teachings can be combined in a single witness is not shown. The fact that the term 'Anglican' covers contradictory teachings, practices, &amp; ideals is admitted, and the inference is drawn, or suggested, that Anglicanism is a large, tolerant, inclusively&#8211;veracious version of Christianity: but how this can be is not made out.</p></body></text></TEI>