<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>At 6 a.m. the motor&#8211;hearses arrived. All the household gathered in the Chapel, &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> read a few prayers. Then, accompanied by Kate, the melancholy carriage moved off.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Rector of Birchington</hi> wrote very movingly about Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The gentleness of God makes men great, &amp; those who, like your mother, have learned from the Spirit's gentleness have written their names ineffaceably on human hearts. Her gentle spirit &amp; her kindly deeds will never be forgotten".</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> sent me a very kind letter about her. She "combined in a singularly beautiful way such strength &amp; loveableness of character as to win the warmest affection of all who knew her".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Many a time have I been encouraged by her confidence &amp; sympathy. You will feel the breaking up as of the foundations of life, but it will be your constant solace <hi rend="underline">to have, as you must have the knowledge that to the end you brought to her the greatest happiness, &amp; were able to surround her with every proof of devoted affection</hi>".</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the day in reading and writing letters. I had the foolish audacity to sign the agreement with "Williams &amp; Norgate" for the little volume on "The Reformation".</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Old Canon Wilson<persName xml:id="433"></persName> of Worcester sent me a pamphlet "<hi rend="underline">The Theological Outlook</hi>", being No. 1 of "the 'D' Society Pamphlets". He explains in a covering letter that "the 'D' Society is a private gathering of men of all ages under the presidency of the Lady Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Professors". The pamphlet is a courageous and stimulating pronouncement, very impressive as coming from a man approaching 90. He is still wonderfully optimistic. The Victorian dream – or delusion – of human progress still holds his mind, &amp; determines his thought.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century is an age worth living in, as ours has been. The motive force is just the same still: I cannot doubt that it is the Holy Spirit of God: the Eternal Word which has developed man up to his present stage".</p>
         </div>
         <p>But what if this cheerful assumption be itself challenged? Can it be taken for granted that the higher type of manhood is being evolved? Is it not evident that modern life is increasingly hostile to individuality? Are not men generally becoming items or echoes, and ceasing to be fully persons? Is not this apparent in politics, in economics, in society, in religion? And if all this must be conceded, what basis for optimism remains? We have no longer men of the mental &amp; moral stature of this ancient thinker, who at an age which is only reached by most who reach it at the price of senility, speaks with the courage of a youth, &amp; the deliberate wisdom of a veteran.</p></body></text></TEI>