<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, who shewest to them that be in error the light of thy truth, to the intent that they may return into the way of righteousness; Grant unto all them that are admitted into the fellowship of Christ's Religion, that they may eschew those things that are contrary to their profession, and follow all such things as are agreeable to the same; through our Lord Jesus Christ. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>"The fellowship of Christ's Religion" is an excellent definition of the Catholic Church.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 10 communicants, including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and Frank Berry.</p>
         <p>After breakfast I walked and talked with Lord R. until church&#8211;time, when he went to S. Anne's for mattins with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and I went to my study. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 3 p.m. the Freemasons gathered in good number to the service in the Chapel. Lord R. read the lesson</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Ecclesiasticus vi. 5&#8211;17 – which I chose to illustrate the subject of my address – Friendship. It was an impressive, and (possibly) an edifying function.</p>
         <p>At 6.30 p.m. I confirmed 35 persons at Evensong in Shadforth Church, which was crowded. The number allowed me to take every candidate separately, a procedure which is far more edifying than coupling the candidates, which must be done when the number exceeds fifty. I returned to the Castle after the service.</p></body></text></TEI>