<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[168] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The greatest man who has yet given himself to the recording of human affairs is, beyond question, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cornelius Tacitus</hi>. Alone in Tacitus a serene calmness of insight was compatible with intensity of feeling.</p>
         <p>J. A. Froude<persName xml:id="1409"></persName> 'Short Stories' I.30</p>
         </div>
         <p>Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Drake &amp; Gorham write to report that 'the cost of extending the service mains from the point where they terminate at the present time to the Basement of the Castle Lodge will be &#x00A3;82: that 'before they take any steps to lay this cable they require payment': that 'this is a matter of great urgency as we are informed by the Power Company that they will want at least 4 weeks to provide &amp; lay this cable'. Now did you ever? I gnashed my teeth, &amp; wrote a cheque encased in an angry letter.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Charge which, as it grows longer, becomes ever more repulsive.</p>
         <p>After lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I motored to South Hylton, where I dedicated a Memorial window to the memory of old Doxford &amp; his wife. We got back to the Castle a little before 7 p.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had opened a Sale of Work at Merrington. The weather was fine throughout the day, &amp; the farmers were busily engaged in harvesting their damaged crops.</p></body></text></TEI>