<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> a letter headed "<hi rend="underline">Parliament and the National Assembly</hi>", in which I quoted the remarkable figures of the Deanery of Hartlepool. The Church Papers are silent about the debate in the H. of L. last Tuesday, save for a brief hostile reference in the '<hi rend="underline">Record</hi>'. Anything that might be thought to advance the credit of the Bishop of Durham needs no other title to complete neglect! On the other hand, both <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Adam Smith</hi><persName xml:id="244"></persName> came to me in the Club &amp; expressed their warm approval of my speech. I attended the meeting of both the Convocations in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>. We agreed upon a form for Ordaining deaconesses, &amp; decided to insist upon a 3 years course of theological training in the case of non&#8211;graduate candidates for Ordination.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who was staying in Dean's Yard, dined with me at 81 Albert Gate Mansions. Beside our host <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><persName xml:id="4032"></persName> and his two daughters, there were <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord &amp; Lady Raglan</hi>, and Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dewar</hi><persName xml:id="5396"></persName>. The latter is an Irish landlord, whose house was burned down. <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Raglan</hi> has for some years been employed in the Sudan. He did not speak very favourably of the missionaries in that region. His wife interested me. She and Miss Darling sang after dinner very pleasantly. We came away shortly before 11 p.m., and parted at 21 Park Lane.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p>Lord Dewar spoke rather despondently of Ireland. He thought Cosgrave was honestly trying to "play the game", but was probably unable to restrain the Republicans. He might "keep things going after a fashion" until the next election, but then the Republicans would "sweep the board", and a situation of acute difficulty w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be created. England might, and probably would, desire to leave well alone, but she c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not ignore the fact that her Atlantic frontier was the Irish coast, nor c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> she stand aside &amp; let the six counties of Ulster be overrun by the Republican troops. He expressed great admiration for Bernard, whom he described as "really a great man".</p>
         <p>Lady Raglan sate beside me at dinner, &amp; our conversation drifted to religion. She expressed dislike of 'Anglo&#8211;Catholicism", and a very mean opinion of the clergy. She said that she could no longer endure the services in church, &amp; had abandoned church&#8211;going. I expressed a genuine regret, &amp; a less genuine confidence that matters w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> improve. She said, and I fear that she spake truly, that young men &amp; women had generally abandoned the profession of Christianity. I could but maunder some platitudes about the disturbing effects of the War. My mind went back to the Convocational discussions of this afternoon, and I realized the unbridged and perhaps unbridgeable chasm which parts Society from the Church. In which camp does one feel most at home?</p></body></text></TEI>
