<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There are at this moment 9 cures vacant in my diocese, and of these 6 are in my own patronage. Of these 2 have been vacated by death, and 3 by resignation. The incumbent's health vacates one, &amp; the health of the incumbent's wife another. Two are vacated by 'preferment', and of these one may, perhaps, be described as a desertion of the diocese. Thus, with the doubtful exception of the last, the whole number may fairly be said to represent normal 'wastage'. The list of vacancies is:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. Easington – the new district.</p>
         <p>2. Shotton, 7000 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;445 net value. miners.</p>
         <p>3. Heatheryclough. 1096 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;468 n.v. agricultural.</p>
         <p>4. Eighton Banks. 4450 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;335 n.v. miners</p>
         <p>5. Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. 10,000 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;1274 n.v. miners.</p>
         <p>6. Christ Church, W. Hartlepool. 7274 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;396 n.v. ship&#8211;builders.</p>
         <p>7. Jarrow. 11,000 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> &#x00A3;356 n.v. miners &amp; ship&#8211;builders.</p>
         <p>8. Norton. 4000 pop. &#x00A3;1123 n.v. agricultural &amp; residential</p>
         <p>9. Eldon. 6300 pop. &#x00A3;343 n.v. miners.</p>
         <p>There are also <hi rend="underline">probably</hi> vacant two more livings viz:</p>
         <p>10. Thornley 1114 pop. &#x00A3;410 n.v.</p>
         <p>11. S. John, Monkheseldon. 1500 pop. Poundsign296 n.v. miners.</p>
         <p>Of these the first is in the patronage of the Bishop of Chester, the last is in my own patronage. Now where am I to find men to fill all these places?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast I walked and talked with mine host. He thinks that the Roman Catholics will absorb the six counties, and that Belfast will stand alone. This is an ill prospect. After lunch we motored into Belfast, and there I gave an address to the clergy in the Bishop's chapel. They attended in considerable number, and after the performance in the chapel, gathered in the dining&#8211;room, &amp; thanked me formally. Then I motored on to have tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridget Tallents</hi>, and her family. Her husband's parents were there, &amp; her four charming children. <hi rend="bold underline">We returned to Mountstewart [sic] in time to listen to the singing of a male quartet from Newtownards</hi>, which sang very sweetly in the library. After dinner we had a considerable discussion on female ministry, and spiritualism. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> is at his best in discussions of this kind. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carson</hi> took little part, &amp; was, I think, really bored. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi> belonged to the "constitutional" section of the Feminist movement, which lays it down as an axiom that sex may be, and ought to be, simply ignored in social &amp; political life, but refrains from violent methods of agitation while dwelling with suspicious insistence on the success which attends them. She herself however is a very charming woman, an affectionate wife &amp; mother, possessed of her full heritage of female attraction.</p></body></text></TEI>