<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53] [sic]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We were somewhat delayed by fog, which compelled a frequent blowing of the foghorn not favourable to repose. However we disembarked at the North Wall about 8 a.m., and <hi rend="bold underline">had our first reminder of the new status of Ireland by being compelled to pass the customs. The official was not unkindly, and we got away in time to reach the Provost's House about 8.15 a.m</hi>. I was glad to get a bath and shave before breakfast. <hi rend="bold underline">After breakfast I wrote a letter to the Times on the Winchester Bishoprick (Division) Measure, explaining that I cannot be in the House of Lords on Thursday, when L. Daryngton<persName xml:id="5400"></persName> moves the usual address to the Crown, and setting forth the reasons why I should oppose the motion. I showed the letter to the Provost, and he expressed a general approval. After lunch we visited the Zoo, a most attractive place. The lions are particularly good: they breed in Dublin better than elsewhere. Most of the lions in the cages have been bred in the Zoo. The keeper, a most intelligent man, told us they were generally bred from one wild parent: that they tended to be greater in size partly because he included special bone&#8211;building elements in their diet; and that their manes were finer. Lady Constance Butler<persName xml:id="5398"></persName> was with us. The signs of recent violence are very noticeable in the City. The Courts of Justice and the Custom House, two of the finest buildings in Dublin, are miserable ruins</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Provost told me that the income of his office was just under &#x00A3;6000 yearly besides the House maintained by the College</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>There came to dinner the Archbishop of Dublin (D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gregg<persName xml:id="5387"></persName>), and several of the Professors of Trinity. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Luce &amp; his wife I did identify as the latter sate beside me &amp; it was agreeable.</p>
         <p>I inquired how the recent political changes had affected the Church of Ireland, and was told that in certain districts the parishes had had to be extinguished altogether as the Protestants had been driven from them. The full measure of the disaster had been experienced, and the outlook was brighter than they had at one time dared to hope. I asked if Trinity College was finding any difficulty in keeping up the number of its students, &amp; was told that so far the numbers had been well&#8211;maintained. <hi rend="bold underline">We discussed the appointment of Tim Healey to be Governor&#8211;General, which the Provost condemned, &amp; the Archbishop approved.</hi> Both agreed that the Government treat His Excellency with scant respect, and allow him the least possible authority. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Fitz&#8211;Alan</hi> was held to be responsible for the appointment. The Roman Catholic Church had treated L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Fitz&#8211;Alan</hi> himself with the utmost discourtesy, only allowing him a chaplain with reluctance, &amp; straitly limiting the said chaplain to the work of saying Mass. The Provost himself had been asked to say Grace at the Castle through lack of a Papist chaplain! I was impressed by the resentment against England expressed by these eminent Protestants, and by their dislike of Ulster. The Provost thinks that the Free State will 'make good'. Disorderly as the country undoubtedly is, it is not so disorderly as it had been under the British Government, for juries could now be got to condemn criminals, but then never.</p></body></text></TEI>