<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast I went round to Eccleston Square. &amp; saw <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>: then, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; wrote my letters. Then I returned to Park Lane, &amp; lunched with mine hosts. Then I picked up Ella, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; a lady&#8211;friend of Geordie<persName xml:id="571"></persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; went to Buckingham Palace for the Royal Garden Party.</hi> There was a monstrous crowd: I lost touch with my females, &amp;, after hanging about to the last moment looking for them, came away in a rage by myself. After picking up my bag in Park Lane, I went for the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> time to Eccleston Square, joined Ella, &amp; went to Victoria S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> where <hi rend="underline">we caught the train for Chichester</hi>, which left at 7.20 p.m. and arrived at its destination about 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ullswater</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Dibdin</hi><persName xml:id="909"></persName>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Ed. Clarke</hi><persName xml:id="4002"></persName>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward Fielden</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Kitty Inge</hi><persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, &amp; some others: but mainly the crowd was unknown to me. <hi rend="italic">Lord S. asked me about the vacant bishoprick of Birmingham: I said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was the man: to which he demurred, &amp; indicated </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Guy Rogers</hi><hi rend="italic"> – who passed at the moment with his exceedingly plain wife – as more suitable. I did not object, but said that, perhaps, he would be more suitable for another see.</hi></p>
         <p>On my journey I read a queer book – "<hi rend="underline">Beasts, Men, &amp; Gods</hi>" by a Polish Professor, whose honesty &amp; competence are vouched for by some unknown American. It is certainly an astonishing book, and discloses a mad world, in which the most archaic superstitions are oddly jumbled together with the shameless secularities of the most recent phases of European "civilization".</p></body></text></TEI>