<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I worked on a sermon for the Liverpool sectaries, but to little effect. Then, after an early lunch, we all motored to Durham to attend the marriage in the Cathedral at 2 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">I united Alister Straker to Jean Adam Ritson in marriage, &amp; afterwards went to the bride's home, &amp; proposed her health</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Then I walked to the Castle, where I was hailed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bob Bineham</hi><persName xml:id="630"></persName>, one of the old choirboys of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's, Westminster. He has come safely thorough the war, and has returned to his bank clerkship. His description of the German Army as "<hi rend="underline">Just a crowd of harmless bank&#8211;clerks like our own</hi>" interested me. Like most of the soldiers I meet he was severe on the French, &amp; disposed to be magnanimously merciful to the Germans. I had an interview with a young miner, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joseph Maughan</hi>, who aspires to be ordained, though he has no more education than the elementary school had given him when he left it at 14, and is now 22 years &amp; 6 months old. I was not very encouraging, though I liked the lad. After this I went to East Rainton, and consecrated an addition to the churchyard. In my address to the people, I emphasised the importance of keeping the burial ground in good order, &amp; excluding glass globes! After the function, I returned to Auckland where I arrived in good time for dinner.</p></body></text></TEI>
