<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Before leaving the castle I visited Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. She was sleeping, and had a profoundly peaceful aspect. Kate said that she had been unconscious for some time. Indeed, she did not recognise me last night.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I motored to Darlington, and took train for </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Liverpool </hi><hi rend="italic">at 8.33 a.m., changing at York, and Manchester (where I lost my connexion), and finally arriving at 2.20 p.m. After leaving my bag at Lime Street, I went to the Cathedral, where </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I had undertaken to preach at a special service arranged for "Free Churchmen".</hi><hi rend="italic"> There was a great congregation. A Primitive Methodist minister read the first lesson which was a mosaic of verses from Zechariah: the second lesson, S. John XVII, 15–end, was read by a Presbyterian Minister: and a Congregationalist read the Prayers. The Bishop read a form of Welcome, and pronounced a Benediction. The Bishop of Sheffield (who was to preach to Friendly Societies at 5 p.m.) sate on one side for the Bishop in his throne, and I on the other. The said throne is very magnifical, and emulates the prelatic altitude of my own Durham. "Loud Speakers" made the sermon audible to the whole congregation, though inflicting on the preacher an uncomfortable sense of artificiality. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r </hi><hi rend="italic">Dann, the Secretary of the Liverpool Free church Federation, who had led the Thanksgiving, carried off my MS.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After service one of the clergy motored me to Lime Street, where I took train for Euston, leaving at 5.20 p.m., and arriving punctually at the scheduled time, 9.15 p.m. At Crewe the old Bishop of Bangor got into the carriage, &amp; we dined together en route. I drove at once to Park Lane, where I found two telegrams.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">1. "</hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Mother has just passed away peacefully</hi><hi rend="italic">". <persName xml:id="112">Ella Henson</persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">2. "No passport received for William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>". Berry.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The end has come as we could not but desire, without pain of body or distress of mind. –</hi><hi rend="i bold">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">So He giveth His beloved sleep</hi><hi rend="i bold">".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Thus ends the long partnership which began 51½ years ago, when she came into my life. I was then a poor little desolate boy of 9¼ years. It was owing to her that I did not go into commerce as my brothers, wherein I should assuredly have come to grief. She insisted, &amp; finally against the greatest difficulties succeeded in securing, that I should be sent to Oxford. From that circumstance all the course of my life has been determined. But she did more for me. Her type of religion, which was strongly ethical &amp; "mystical", led me to hold lightly to ecclesiastical forms, &amp; to apply moral tests to religious theories. Her devotion to me was wonderful. She exulted in every success that lightened my cheerless &amp; clouded career: &amp; she sympathized with every failure. My Father died in my house on Nov: 8</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1896 when I was preaching at Oxford: now Carissima has died in my house when I was preaching at Liverpool.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p></body></text></TEI>