<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> went off in the course of the morning. I read through the 'Copec' Report on 'Politics &amp; Citizenship'. It is distinctly saner than the other reports.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> turned up for lunch: &amp; played bowls with me afterwards. At 4 p.m. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Francis, the Vicar of Middleton S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George, brought a young man, named Harold Bainbridge Goundry, to be confirmed in the Chapel. He was accompanied by his mother, brother &amp; sweet&#8211;heart. He is going to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Michael's College, Tenbury, as an assistant master. After tea I gave them all tea, &amp; then settled to writing letters until post&#8211;time. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived before dinner fresh from a walking tour of the English Lakes, and looking very fit and bronzed.</p>
         <p>The four years which I must review in my Charge have been marked in exceptional measure by economic disturbance &amp; international unrest. It is natural that the minds of religious men should have been exercised by the apparent helplessness of the Churches to arrest attention &amp; influence the course of affairs. There is a widely&#8211;extended disposition to ascribe the comparative failure of organized religion to its remoteness from the interests which dominate the minds of the people. The demand is made, &amp; pressed ever more insistently that the direction &amp; emphasis of Christian teaching should be transferred from the personal to the social implications of Christ's Religion; that the redemption of society should be dwelt upon rather than the salvation of the individual: that the 'Kingdom of God' should be set up visibly &amp; by direct action in the economic &amp; political spheres.</p></body></text></TEI>