<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for Armagh, and then, after lunch, motored to Barnard Castle where M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hughes was holding the first conference of his Rural Deanery. I brought with me Miss Headlam, who represents her parish. Then I had some conversation with Brereton about the appointment of a chaplain to the school since the new Headmaster is a layman. After carrying Miss Headlam to Whorlton, I returned to the Castle, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">there had a painful interview with that unhappy youth, Briggs, whom I definitely refused to accept for Ordination. He wept woefully, and I felt deeply grieved for him, but, in view of the facts which he himself disclosed, there was really no other course open to me. I made him write a letter to John<persName xml:id="5355"></persName> telling him that he had fully disclosed the story of their relations to one another. After making a copy of this letter, I sent it to its destination with a sternly–expressed covering letter from me. Now I must consider what course of action to take with the scoundrel</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>The Chancellor came to dine &amp; sleep. He brought to me a hypocritical presentation from S. Francis, South Shields. The Churchwardens 'present' the Vicar for removing the Tabernacle without a faculty, for stopping the Daily Services and neglecting the Parochial Social Organisations!</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Norwich sent me the Report of the Ecclesiastical Committee of the Privy Council on the Winchester Diocese (Division) Measure.</p></body></text></TEI>