<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> John the Baptist, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I ordained <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lake</hi> to the Priesthood in the Chapel. A number of the students from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Chad's, to which he had himself belonged, attended, &amp; formed an efficient choir. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName> sang the Litany. There was no sermon, and the service hardly occupied an hour and a half. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> presented the candidate.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert</hi>, offering him charge of the new Easington district: to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prideaux</hi><persName xml:id="3181"></persName>, offering him S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's, West Hartlepool: &amp; to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pestle</hi><persName xml:id="5238"></persName> offering him Tanfield, of which the Vicar, old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Archdale</hi>, died yesterday.</p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me the following lines, which, he says, were posted up in the mess&#8211;tents in France: they carry a counsel which is very relevant to the requirements of episcopal office:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>A wise old owl sat on an oak;</p>
         <p>The more he saw, the less he spoke;</p>
         <p>The less he spoke, the more he heard;</p>
         <p>Can't we be like that wise old bird?</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Annefield Plain, &amp; confirmed 87 persons in a tin church which was stifling. The very unpleasant parson, Talbot, would handicap any function, &amp; there <hi rend="underline">was</hi> a dreadful disparity in the sexes; nevertheless, I was not wholly displeased.</p>
         <p>We returned to Auckland after the service, getting noble views of the Cathedral on the way.</p></body></text></TEI>