<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I walked with <hi rend="underline">Baddeley</hi> to Escomb, and, happily finding the Vicar absent, was able to show him the little old priceless church without distraction. We got back to the Castle a little late for lunch.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I played bowls with <hi rend="underline">Hill</hi>, the Vicar of Coundon, and <hi rend="underline">Baddeley</hi>, and beat them both easily.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After tea, I set myself to go through the Visitation returns of the clergy. It was painfully evident that partisan interest rather than a regard for the facts determines their answer to my question, whether in their experience they had found reservation of the Sacrament requisite for the communion of the sick.</hi><hi rend="italic underline">All</hi><hi rend="italic"> the High Churchmen say that reservation </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> requisite: and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> the Evangelicals say that it </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">isn't</hi><hi rend="italic">! On the whole, though the overwhelming majority reply in the negative, there are many more affirmative answers than I thought would have been the case. But the "anglo&#8211;Catholic" propaganda is telling.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="underline"> Gideon Murray</hi> arrived to stay the night. Years ago I married her to her husband now the Master of Elibank in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.</p>
         <p>After prayers <hi rend="underline">Baddeley</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and I walked in the garden to enjoy the spectacle of the Castle in the brilliant moonlight. It certainly is most beautiful. The proportions of the building are seen to perfection thus. </p></body></text></TEI>