<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; collated Little to his hon. canonry in the Castle Chapel. Also I instituted &amp; licensed divers clergy. Then I lunched at the Club with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. After lunch I had an interview with the rheumatical Welshman who has been taking duty at Pelton during the Vicar's absence. He has a son at Keble who wants a grant to assist him in his academic course: &amp; he himself wants a living! The daughters of the horse&#8211;leech have many descendants. Then I motored to Wolsingham, &amp; there confirmed 77 candidates. After tea with the Rector, I went on to Crook, &amp; confirmed a sick girl in bed, before going to the parish church for the general confirmation – whereat 74 candidates were presented. There is life in this church, but everything is very rough. Between the heat of the atmosphere, (for the church was very crowded, &amp; the windows fast closed,) &amp; the raucousness of the singing, I was near to fainting. However they meant well, &amp; the candidates were attentive &amp; earnest. After the service, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">My mind steadily hardens to the resolution that I will, in spite of the waywardness of the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> and the timidity of the Canons, carry out my purpose of making K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> the successor</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Q. in all his three offices. For, not only would it be </hi><hi rend="italic underline">pessimi exempli</hi><hi rend="italic">[of a worst example] to give way to an opposition so plainly unreasonable, but also I cannot see any other appointment which would be so good. Besides, I think equity requires that I should stick to K.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>