<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington to catch the early train to York under a dropping sky. I arrived at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> William's College in good time for <hi rend="bold underline">the Convocation.</hi> Here I continued until 4 p.m., when I got away to catch the fast train home. At Darlington William met me with the car. I wrote letters until dinner, and afterwards. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">In Convocation I moved the resolution, of which I had given notice, declaring the expediency of giving the Bishops power to ordain men at 21, when they thought it necessary, requiring a three year diaconate.</hi> The discussion was on the whole sympathetic, &amp; perhaps useful. I was impressed by the unanimity with which the bishops accepted my gloomy picture of the present situation. It is evident that Durham is not alone in its dolorous condition. But this circumstance, while it may contribute a debased kind of consolation, does not bring any real assistance. Indeed it discloses the hopelessness of any relief from outside the diocese. There are no men to be attracted here in order to make up for the diocesan shortage.</p>
         <p>I prefaced the proceedings by a brief reference to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, who was not a member of the Upper House, but whom the President allowed me none the less to commemorate. The question of finding a successor now confronts me, &amp; grows harder to answer the more it is considered. If only Quirk could have survived another three years.</p></body></text></TEI>