<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant to us, Lord, we beseech thee, the spirit to think and do always such things as be rightful; that we, who cannot do anything that is good without thee, may by thee be enabled to live according to thy will; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel: there were 10 communicants including my three guests.</p>
         <p>I motored to Lumley, dropping <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Baddeley, &amp; Peel Dennistoun<persName xml:id="4889"></persName> at the Cathedral on the way. The old ailing parson, Stewart, received me with a kind of superannuated effusion which was almost pathetic. I had particularly suggested that no notice of my coming should be given in the parish so I was not surprised to find a very small congregation. The parish contains 3406 souls, &amp; of these about 60 were in church. No doubt both the industries in which the people are engaged, namely agriculture and mining, are prolific of Sunday&#8211;work. Still, on any showing, the attendance at Divine Service was certainly wretched.</p>
         <p>Rain started to fall about noon, &amp; continued for the rest of the day. I read through the proof of Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> Primary Charge. It will attract much notice, &amp; is a considerable pronouncement, though open to serious criticism both as covering too much ground, and making many bold, but insufficiently based assumptions.</p></body></text></TEI>