<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent the day unpleasantly in the Assembly. At 4.30 p.m. I went across to the House of Lords, but the business was dull, &amp; I soon came away. I dined in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with Meade&#8211;Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, and had much talk with him. He is the most elusive of men, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">au fond</hi><hi rend="italic">, I verily think, a mere pagan.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The sense of reaction after the excitements of yesterday lay heavily on my spirits.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My speech is made much of by the papers, &amp; described as the outstanding feature of the debate. And, as reporting goes, it is not ill reported. Lord Novar<persName xml:id="5395"></persName> came up &amp; congratulated me in the House: &amp; I was congratulated by several laymen in the Assembly, and by several men in the Club.</hi><hi rend="italic">On the other hand, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Barlow</hi><hi rend="italic"> – whom I account both a good &amp; a considering man – expressed to me his regret that I had felt it needful to oppose the Bill, and I received an ill&#8211;written letter from Ryton informing me that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">somebody at Wallsend had declared that I was not fit to be Bishop of Durham,</hi><hi rend="italic"> and asking that the matter might be threshed out!! I sent this precious epistle to the Vicar of Ryton</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> asking whether he could tell me anything about the writer. So I dropped far from the fatuous exaltation of yesterday, &amp; went to bed heavily enough.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>