<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I made Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> read through so much of the Charge as I have written. He said that he thought that no one could fairly say that it was not both useful, and (blessed word!) constructive</hi>. Then Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> took our guests to see Escomb, while I made a start on the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> part of the Charge, viz, the criticism of "Copec". After lunch we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, the Bishop of Oxford and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Burge) motored to Aycliffe, where the Vicar and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Eade received us with kindness, &amp; showed us the interesting medieval church with its fragments of Anglo&#8211;Saxon crosses, its Jacobean benches and pulpit, and its fine tower. Then we had tea, and returned to the Castle. Burge and I walked and talked for an hour in the Park before dinner. Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> from Stanhope arrived to spend the night. We had some interesting conversation about "Copec". Burge tells me that Shebbeare has been appointed to a Lectureship at Oxford. In view of the fact that, on the ground of poverty, he has dismissed his assistant curate, and is "working" a scattered parish of 2500 people with no more than occasional help, I am not at all sure that he is morally free to undertake additional duties. The net value of his benefice is set down at &#x00A3;1165 per annum. He is an extremely bad man of business, and, though I doubt not that he visits the parishioners, &amp; is personally liked by them, I feel sure that they take account of the reduction of staff, and make comments which are not flattering to the Church.</p></body></text></TEI>