<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended the choral celebration at 8.30 a.m. in the College Chapel, when the Master celebrated. There was a goodly attendance of surpliced youths, a fact the more noteworthy since attendance is quite voluntary. The commandments were illegally shortened, &amp; there were many hymns. For the rest the service followed the Order of the Prayer&#8211;Book.</p>
         <p>It was an impressive and edifying function.</p>
         <p>The son of the house came to breakfast, a pleasant, loquacious, self&#8211;confident lad who at present intends to be ordained. He spoke with much contempt of pre&#8211;war Religion, of which, however, he could have no personal knowledge, &amp; about which he seems to have been told many strange things. 'Victorian' is evidently a "bad word" in his milieu.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Woods</hi> came to fetch me for the service at Holy Trinity. This is <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simeon's</hi> church, a fact that is recalled by many pictures &amp; relics in the vestry. There was a very large congregation which included a considerable number of undergraduates. My sermon, which was addressed largely to undergraduates, was closely listened to, and seemed to give satisfaction to the Vicar.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 2.30 p.m. I preached in Great S. Mary's to the University</hi>. The floor of the church was well filled, &amp; there were about 50 undergraduates in the gallery. I think the sermon interested the congregation and probably offended many members of it. The Editor of the 'Cambridge Review' requested leave to print it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p>The Vice&#8211;Chancellor and I walked together for an hour after the sermon. On our way we fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Professor Sorley </hi>and his son, &amp; had some converse with them. Then we called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cunningham</hi> at Westcott House, and looked in on Sydney Sussex chapel, a new building ordered carefully on Anglo&#8211;Catholic lines. This college is said to be the headquarters of the sect.</p>
         <p>At tea some of the undergraduates came in. I retired to rest myself, my labours in preaching two sermons uniting with a thunderous state of the weather to make me feel much fatigued. But scarcely had I lain down before two "<hi rend="underline">Old Dunelmians</hi>" called to invite me to meet the O.Ds tomorrow. One of the two was Canon Oakley's son, an undergraduate at King's. I was pleased with the loyalty of the youths, but perforce declined their proposal.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I dined in Hall, and met divers persons, among them the Anglo&#8211;Catholic </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Spens</hi><hi rend="italic">, with whom I had some conversation. He told me that he had been pressed to accept office as Secretary of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> at the time when </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arnold Pinchard</hi><persName xml:id="5422"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was elected, &amp; that he was now disposed to doubt the wisdom of his refusal. He expressed himself with much reasonable moderation, &amp; was properly resentful of "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Copec</hi><hi rend="italic">", but I cannot lightly believe in the candour of an Anglo&#8211;Catholic!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey Butler</hi>, a lame man, who is one of the burgesses of the University, sate by me in Hall, &amp; was agreeable enough.</p>
         <p>We came away about 9.15 p.m., and so brought to an end a pleasant &amp; not inactive Sunday.</p></body></text></TEI>