<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carissima</hi><persName xml:id="76"></persName> grew worse in the course of the day, and about 2 p.m. seemed trying to ask for something. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kate</hi> was sure that she desired the Sacrament, so I celebrated at 2.30 p.m. using the shortened form appointed for the Sick. She was able to receive the Elements, and, perhaps, she followed the service. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> thinks so, but I'm not sure. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Berry</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kate</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and I communicated with her. The doctor was sent for. He thought she could not live many hours longer. It is difficult to realize.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I walked round the park after lunch. <hi rend="bold underline">In view of Carissima's condition I decided to cancel the meeting of Archdeacons and Rural deans which had been arranged for this afternoon, and tomorrow morning.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent much time in typing again with some amendments an old sermon on Justice which was originally composed for use on an Assize Sunday. It will have to serve for these American lawyers with some addition of a 'topical' nature. I suppose something might fitly be said about the common heritage of English law, as enabling the two great English speaking nations to contribute to the world's recovery that sane and resourceful justice which at this time is the world's supreme need. The other common tradition is Protestantism in a distinctive type, evangelical, socially active politically free. This makes the two nations intelligible to one another, and predisposes then to union in philanthropic adventure.</p></body></text></TEI>