<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote letters, among them one lengthy epistle to a Presbyterian minister in Canada who had offered himself as a candidate for Ordination. His letter interested me as a revelation of spiritual penury of non&#8211;liturgical Protestantism, and it had a ring of sincerity which saved it from the w.p.b., but the applicant's age – 44 – was itself disqualifying.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I walked in the Park with young Westcott<persName xml:id="5385"></persName>, and tried to discover the direction of his interests, &amp; the type of his mind. But I didn't make much headway. His special subject is "psychology",</hi><hi rend="italic"> which doesn't sound promising. He is only 27; has been ordained about 2 years: is already married &amp; has two small children. He is shy &amp; silent. His wife is a little chattering Italian, whom can only treat as a child.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
         <p>Very suddenly and unexpectedly a heavy blow has fallen on the Diocese of Durham. Bishop Quirk's<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> death at Lugano removes a familiar and much loved figure from our sight. His was one of those gracious personalities which radiate kindness and goodwill, whose presence makes easy the movement of business, &amp; acts ever as an influence of coherence &amp; harmony. Who can forget him with his cheery voice, ready but always kindly humour, and the unfailing comradeship of an adoring dog? His efficiency in practical affairs went along with an undeviating loyalty to his colleagues. A wise counsellor, an indefatigable worker, a true friend, he drew to himself in unusual measure the affection, respect, &amp; confidence with those with whom he was associated. Inseparably linked with him was ever his wife. In work as in life they stood together. The generous hospitality of their beautiful house in the College was enjoyed &amp; appreciated by many, clergy &amp; laity, whom business or pleasure carried to Durham. The loss to the College and to the Diocese which his death inflicts is very great. By the Bishop, with whom necessarily he was constantly &amp; intimately associated, the Bishop of Jarrow's death is felt not only as a grave public calamity but as a personal bereavement.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
         <p>I asked the Cambridge Press to send presentation copies to the following:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. Balfour</p>
         <p>2. Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName>.</p>
         <p>3. Ernle<persName xml:id="1394"></persName>.</p>
         <p>4. Baldwin<persName xml:id="4118"></persName>.</p>
         <p>5. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Byron.</p>
         <p>6. Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3465"></persName>.</p>
         <p>7. Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>.</p>
         <p>8. Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>.</p>
         <p>9. Duchess of Portland.</p>
         <p>10. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fraser.</p>
         <p>11. Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName>.</p>
         <p>12. Abp. of Canterbury.</p>
         <p>13. " " York.</p>
         <p>14. Sir H. Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName>.</p>
         <p>15. Miss Ishbell Macdonald<persName xml:id="5384"></persName>.</p>
         <p>16. John Murray.</p>
         <p>Also I ordered 100 copies for myself.</p></body></text></TEI>