<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I called on <persName xml:id="906">Lady Dawkins</persName>. She is a tall, handsome woman with a dignified carriage, &amp; that deference which one often observes in those who have been reared as Papists.</p>
         <p>I drafted the following letter to <persName xml:id="327">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowling</persName>, and submitted it to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowling,</p>
         <p>I have received a report from <persName xml:id="121">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss&#8211;Custard</persName> which justifies me in requesting the Churchwardens to continue <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> in his present position, &amp; may perhaps justify you in thinking that he had better continue to work at his music with a definite purpose of making music the career of his life.  As you know, Harold has been much under my observation during the year, &amp; has been much in this house.  Both my wife &amp; I are attached to him, &amp; w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> desire to help forward his purpose in life.  He must certainly work hard, &amp; devote himself to his work if he is to succeed, &amp; he has no time to lose.  If you think well to accede to this proposal, I should like <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> to reside here regularly for the next three months, so as to avoid so much getting about, which wastes time, &amp; is not particularly good for him during the damp &amp; cold weather.  We have seen enough of his behaviour to make us confident that he will not <hi rend="bold">[10] </hi>discredit our household, &amp; I hope it may be possible for him to make some serious effort to improve his education, which is not equal to what his age requires.</p>
         <p>You will, I think, understand that in making this proposition we are giving the best evidence we can of our goodwill to Harold and desire for his welfare.</p>
         <p>Believe me, most sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson.	</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
