<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m. There were but 16 communicants, all women save the clergy and <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName></hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="31">Cecil</persName> </hi><hi rend="italic">arrived on a hired motor at breakfast–time.  He preached a lengthy &amp; characteristic sermon, in which he covered an immense area, &amp; traversed the entire cycle of homiletic moods and modes!  </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName></hi> preached in S. Margaret's.  In the afternoon, I preached in the Abbey, with considerable difficulty, my throat being in a bad state, &amp; by consequence my voice harsh, &amp; my delivery painful.  Moreover, the sermon was too abstract &amp; literary to arrest the multitude.  Thus, it was the case – as I judge – that my preaching displeased both preacher &amp; congregation.  The text was Hosea. XII.13: &amp; the subject <ref xml:id="540">"Hebrew Prophecy"</ref>.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="underline">Carissima.</hi>  At evensong in S. Margaret's there was a good congregation.  I preached with discomfort to myself on "The Ministry of the Prophets".  After service a Mother brought her daughter to the Vestry as a Confirmation Candidate.  <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="121">Custard</persName></hi> came in to supper, and afterwards my <persName xml:id="584">father–in–law</persName> brought in <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="907" display="no">Col: Dunlop</persName></hi>, just returned from India, the commander of the regiment in which <persName xml:id="556"><hi rend="underline">Jim Dennistoun</hi></persName> is captain.  He seemed a frank and amiable person.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
