<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> presented me with an excellent Edition of <persName xml:id="915">George Herbert's</persName> <ref xml:id="98">'Life &amp; Works'</ref>. At Mattins, the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> being absent, &amp; the <orgName xml:id="32">School</orgName> present, I read the Prayer of Thanksgiving for Benefactors. I presided at a meeting of the Standing Committee, which authorized the <persName xml:id="456">Headmaster</persName> to proceed with the repair of the Dormitory Roof, pronounced by the <persName xml:id="917" display="no">District Surveyor</persName> to be dangerous.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">About 7 p.m. the Dean called on me, &amp; stayed talking for an hour. He began by expressing his entire concurrence with every word of my letter.</hi><hi rend="italic">  He said that if <persName xml:id="508">Balfour</persName> had still been in office he would have consulted him, and gave me the impression of actually having meditated resignation!!  I spoke rather strongly about the unfairness of handling the discussion in this personal way: &amp; he appeared to admit the justice of my words.  Then I tried to get him to yield the point of "the Ordinary", </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but he is evidently resolved to yield nothing</hi><hi rend="italic">. We parted amicably but no nearer an understanding than before. As a psychological problem the Dean of Westminster is a curiously interesting problem, but as a negotiator he is the most exasperating creature in the world.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
