<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At 10 a.m. the Canons assembled in my study, &amp; discussed the situation.  We agreed to act together, &amp; that the <persName xml:id="296">Sub&#8211;Dean</persName> should speak for us all.  So we went into the Chapter at 11 a.m.  After other business &#8211; <hi rend="bold underline">including <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh's</persName> appointment as High Bailiff</hi> &#8211; had been transacted, we came to the pi&#x00E8;ce de resistance.  The <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> read the statement he had already circulated, &amp; as he read, he answered questions.  Having come to the end of his statement, the Sub&#8211;Dean took up his parable, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">formally asked the Dean to join in an Appeal to the <persName xml:id="908" display="no">Visitor</persName></hi>.  The Dean displayed great emotion, hinted that he would rather resign than accept an abatement of his powers, &amp; seemed on the verge of tears.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> thereupon broke away, &amp; ranged himself on the side of the Dean</hi>, &amp; his defection visibly affected the <persName xml:id="109">Arch&#8211;deacon</persName>. Finally we reached an impotent conclusion. Welldon should draft a "Consuetudinary" against the next Chapter on Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>: &amp; if we c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> agree thereon, we could ask the Visitor to validate it.  <hi rend="italic">The Dean evidently was much relieved, &amp; expressed his gratitude to Welldon with injudicious freedom, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">revealing rather to the latter's embarrassment that he had assisted in the composition of his (the Dean's) statement</hi><hi rend="italic">.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We came away much incensed against Welldon, &amp; much annoyed with the Dean</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I was so much perturbed by the proceedings in Chapter that I forgot that I was "in Residence", and bound to attend the Abbey&#8211;service. <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> and I walked the length of the Embankment and back.</p>
         <p>In the evening I attended the performance of the Adelphi of Terence, which was well acted by the boys.  <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> of Ch. Ch. sate next me, &amp; we had some conversation.  <persName xml:id="909">Sir Louis Dibdin</persName> was behind me, and in the intervals was communicative on the subject of the Ecclesiastical Disorders Commission Report.<note xml:id="43" n="1"></note>  <hi rend="bold underline">He said that he had himself drawn the said Report</hi>, that the evidence would fill three stout Blue Books, that much of the "expert evidence" was worthless, (e.g. that of <persName xml:id="910">Canon Maccoll</persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">who actually supposed that Saragossa was a person!</hi>), that the Report would be published about Easter.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
