<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attend<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Mattins in the Abbey: and then prepared the final <listEvent><event xml:id="26">"Golden Lecture"</event></listEvent> of this course. I was interrupted by the entrance of the <persName xml:id="14">High Bailiff</persName>, who was cruising about Westminster on the business of his office.</p>
         <p>Then <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and I drove to S. Margaret's, Lothbury, and I gave the final lecture of this Course to the smallest congregation! Afterwards the <persName xml:id="384">Rector</persName> shewed us his church with legitimate pride: &amp; we lunched with him. Then we drove to S. Bartholomew's, Smithfield, &amp; looked at the Church, after seeing which we returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>. After a short walk with <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, I came home for tea: whereto appeared <persName xml:id="460">Rutherford</persName> and <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName>, with whom I talked until it was time to dress &amp; dine with the <persName xml:id="912">Mayor of Westminster</persName>, who was entertaining the employe's [sic] of the Council.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I managed to type rather a severe letter to the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName>, protesting against his treatment of the Chapter, &amp; reserving my liberty of action. This letter I shewed to <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, &amp; at his suggestion made some alterations.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
