<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I did not go to Church before breakfast, not having recovered myself from what I suppose was a slight chill contracted last Thursday (presumably) when returning from Prothero.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="642">Sir Peile</persName> and <persName xml:id="925">Lady Thompson</persName> went off duly to the Abbey. I introduced the former to the <persName xml:id="296">Archdeacon</persName> before service. He (the said Archdeacon) was simply bubbling over with political optimism, having dined overnight with <persName xml:id="509">C. B.</persName>!! As I came away from the Abbey I ran into <persName xml:id="539">Alfred Lyttelton</persName> &amp; his family. They explained their absenteeism from <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> by the plea that now they had no more title to a seat there. This I decisively disallowed.</p>
         <p>There was a fair congregation in S. Margaret's.  <hi rend="bold underline">In the absence of <persName xml:id="121">Custard</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> was at the organ</hi>, and played the hymns very well. The Psalms we sang without accompaniment. I preached rather wearily from Gal. I. 15&#8211;17, on "The Conversion of S.Paul".</p>
         <p>At Evensong there was again a fair congregation. I preached an old sermon. <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
