<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906, Broadmeadows, Selkirk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fine day from start to finish. <persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> went to the Episcopalian church, but I preferred to accompany <persName xml:id="1060">mine hostess</persName> to the parish church, where I heard a rather thin &amp; sentimental sermon on the great subject of Prayer. The minister, <persName xml:id="1061" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lawson</persName>, is said to be an excellent and popular parochus.  As usual when attending the Presbyterian service <hi rend="bold underline">I found the extemporaneous prayers disagreeable and unedifying.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the afternoon <persName xml:id="1062" display="no">Miss Lang</persName> headed a walk on to the adjacent hills, from the top of which the most beautiful views of the valley of the Yarrow were gained.</p>
         <p>In the smoking room after dinner I exerted myself to extract his reminiscences of the South African War from <persName xml:id="1063" display="no">Captain Maxwell</persName> of the Scots Greys, who went through Paardeberg &amp; Bloemfontein, was badly wounded, and invalided home.  He repudiated <persName xml:id="1064">Burdett&#8211;Coutts'</persName> account of the hospitals with energy. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[104]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"It is too much to say, perhaps, that <persName xml:id="1065" display="no">Napoleon</persName> received the honours of apotheosis, but short of that point it is difficult to exaggerate.  He received, at any rate, the most singular &amp; sublime honour that has even been awarded to humanity.  For he was known in France not as General, or Consul, or Emperor, or even by his name, but </hi>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">simply as "The Man" (l'homme</hi>
<hi rend="i bold">).  </hi>
<hi rend="italic">His son was "the Son of the Man", he himself was always "The Man". He was, in fact, the Man of the popular imagination, and it was thus that Liberals swore by him. His intense individuality, even more than his horror of anarchy, had made him an absolute ruler. But, as the product of the Revolution, as the humbler of kings, a glamour of liberty grew round his name".</hi>
         </p>
         <p><ref xml:id="116">"Napoleon, the last phase</ref>"</p>
         <p>By <persName xml:id="292">Lord Rosebury</persName>, p 215</p>
         <p>(Arthur L. Humphreys 1900)</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
