<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A close sultry morning with no air to breathe!</p>
         <p>At the early celebration there were 23 communicants. I preached wearily at Mattins to a sadly dwindled congregation. Indeed it were questionable whether the Apostle Paul himself would be able to retain the faithful when the holiday season has really set in.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> was in church and came in afterwards to lunch.  I had some speech with him about these disturbing Cornish rumours: and he went round to the Athenaeum to collect rumours.  </hi>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">There he fell in with <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName> who gave it as his opinion that the P.M. would appoint on party grounds, and said that he understood the appointment to have been already made. This I trust may assure me that I shall not have to face episcopacy &amp; exile just yet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="42">Steel&#8211;Maitland</persName> called at tea&#8211;time.</p>
         <p>There was but a moderate congregation at Evensong, and I preached wearily. Raleigh was again in Church, &amp; came to supper, as did also <persName xml:id="489">Sherwood</persName> and <persName xml:id="121">Custard</persName>. Afterwards I walked with him as far as Charing Cross.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday, July 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1906 the work of cleaning the organ began in good earnest.</p>
         <p>In the evening I entertained the '<orgName xml:id="66">Brethren</orgName>' at dinner. The following attended. viz:&#8211;</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="1052">Shelford</persName></cell>
			   
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="1053">Le Bas</persName></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="1054">Hadden</persName></cell>
			 
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="398">Morrison</persName></cell>
			   
               <cell rend="Normal"><persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>It was decided that I should invite <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> and <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> to join the society.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, July 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1906, <persName xml:id="759">Lord Lytton</persName> came to consult me with respect to his speech on the education bill.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Aug. 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1906, I attended the debate in the House of Lords, and heard <persName xml:id="1056">Lord Crewe</persName> introduce the Education Bill, and the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> make an effective speech against it. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Thursday, Aug 2</hi>
<hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi>
<hi rend="bold underline"> 1906, I attended the installation of <persName xml:id="752">Barnett</persName> as Canon:</hi> afterwards we went on our holiday, going first to Frant, then to Canterbury, then to Robertsbridge, &amp; finally to Scotland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the Chancel of S. Mildred's Church, Tenterden, on the north wall inside the communion rails was an inscription which interested me so much that I copied it. It ran thus: &#8211;</p>
         <p>To the Memory of the <persName xml:id="1057" display="no">Rev. Matthew Wallace</persName>, son of the <persName xml:id="1058" display="no">Rev. D. Wallace of Edinburgh</persName>, Vicar of Tenterden, Doctor of Laws, who was born on the 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of October 1728 at Moffat in Scotland, &amp; died at his Vicarage on the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th </hi>of November 1771, aged 43 years and 6 days.</p>
         <p>Agreeable manners, great benevolence, and excellent parts, united to extensive learning, pastoral fidelity, and discourses uncommonly elegant as well as instructive, rendered him universally beloved, respected, and esteemed in an English parish, even in times during which the National Prejudices that had formerly subsisted were again attempted to be highly inflamed between the Northern and Southern divisions of Great Britain.</p>
         <p>								(Aug 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1906).</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
