<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The newspapers report a shocking outrage from Madrid. A <persName xml:id="944" display="no">miscreant</persName> threw a bomb at the newly&#8211;married <persName xml:id="942">King</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="943">Queen of Spain</persName>. The Sovereigns were uninjured, but many persons in their immediate entourage were killed.<note xml:id="49" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wasted the forenoon in writing to the <persName xml:id="945" display="no">Rural Dean</persName> <hi rend="bold underline">refusing to take part in the mass meeting to protest against the Education Bill</hi> on June 28.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName> came in to tell me that the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> had offered him the living of S. Mark's, Notting Hill, and that he had decided to accept it.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Whitsunday, June 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1906, I preached a long sermon on <ref xml:id="583">"Christian Unity"</ref>, or rather in connection with that subject, which had been specially commended by the Bp. of London.  I took for my text the words of our Lord, "Thou, hypocrite, cast out first &amp;c".: and I stated with much frankness my conviction that so long as the exclusive validity of the Episcopal ministry was maintained by Anglicans, they were disqualified for preaching unity.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I travelled to Oxford in order to attend the <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">college</orgName> Gaudy.<note xml:id="50" n="2"></note></p>
         <p>On Whit. Monday, <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray</persName> took me in his motor to Stratford on Avon, where for the first time I visited the grave of Shakespeare. The church is worth a visit for its own sake.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> June, I returned to town by the early express: drove immediately to Mesr<hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi> Russell in Baker St: &amp; was photographed.</p>
         <p>On Thursday the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> June I had the choir boys here to tea, &amp; shewed them over the Abbey: &amp; on Saturday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I shewed a numerous party from S. Columba's over the abbey &amp; <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
