<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th </hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The day broke calm &amp; bright, with some menace of heat. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had acquired the requisite implements, and succeeded in achieving the manufacture of "early tea". The forenoon was spent lazily on the terrace; after lunch we went on board the steamer, &amp; made the Tour de Lac. The colour of the water on the further side of the Lake was wonderful, and the beauty of the wooded mountain sides exceeded the expectations created by a distant view. We changed steamers at Bouveret, and got out at Evian les Bains. Here everything was shut up: preparations for the season being in slow progress. We saw the process of bottling the mineral water, of which some 37,000 bottles are said to be exported daily. The care with which the cleaning of the bottles was carried out was astonishing. Five separate cleansings were effected in the most rapid &amp; withal thorough fashion: the man who handled the corks was compelled to wear indian rubber gloves. We had tea in a cake&#8211;shop, and then returned to Vevey. We crossed the lake to Ouchy&#8211;Lausanne, &amp; there changed steamers. The journey was assisted with the most amazingly beautiful views of the mountains. As the sun sank in the sky, the more lofty heights caught his latest beams.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
