<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Another bright day. The country under sun light is ravishingly beautiful.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The post brought me the proofs of my </hi><ref xml:id="113"><hi rend="italic bold underline">2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Contemporary Article.</hi></ref>  These I corrected and returned to the printers. Then we started for a short walk before lunch, but misjudging distances arrived ¾ hour late for that meal. We saw both the waterfalls &#8211; Barwick and Turret. The former is an immensely long, deep&#8211;cut gulley along which, with divers romantical turns, and deep intervening pools, a considerable stream frothed &amp; foamed fiercely. The latter is the more considerable Fall. Both were in prime condition.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the afternoon we drove through Crieff to <placeName xml:id="25">Drummond Castle</placeName>, where the <persName xml:id="843">Countess of Ancaster</persName> has just been entertaining the <persName xml:id="942">King of Spain</persName>. The situation is splendid, and the Italian gardens amazingly fine. In the old keep, which we ascended for the view, were shown various curiosities, amongst others the cast of <persName xml:id="1065" display="no">Napoleon's</persName> face taken after death.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
