<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull and menacing sky, from which the rain began to fall, promising vacancy &amp; depression. At 8 a.m. I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> and celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 37 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. It was good to look again on the East Window.</p>
         <p>The rain fell at intervals all day long: and the congregation at Mattins was not as large as I had hoped. However the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> was in his pew: and the Parliamentary Seats were filled, presumably by Members &amp; their wives. I recognized <persName xml:id="853">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lough</persName>, <persName xml:id="419">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Craig</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1010">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dixon&#8211;Hartland</persName>: but <hi rend="bold underline">the familiar faces had all disappeared</hi>. I preached a <ref xml:id="573">'political Sermon'</ref> from Zeph. I. 12 &amp; Heb. XI. 27.<note xml:id="85" n="1"></note></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="401">Sir Ed.</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="991" display="no">Lady Russell</persName> came to lunch.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon there was a Memorial Service for the late <persName xml:id="1011">King of Denmark</persName> instead of the usual sermon. In S. Margaret's we contented ourselves with playing <persName xml:id="1012" display="no">Chopin's</persName> Marche Funebre after Mattins, &amp; the Dead March in Saul after Evensong.</p>
         <p>At Evensong, the Moderator of the Church of Scotland, <persName xml:id="1014">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Milne</persName>, was present.  He came in to supper afterwards.  <persName xml:id="571">Geordie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="167" display="no">Ethel</persName> were also here.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Convocation met on Tuesday, Feb. 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1906.  I attended, &amp; moved the adjournment of the debate on the Educational issue, thus leaving myself in possession of the House<hi rend="bold">.</hi>  On Wednesday, Feb. 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, <hi rend="bold underline">I made a speech, 40 minutes long</hi>, which was well received by the House.  There was even a sprinkling of people in the galleries, including <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> and <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. </p>
         <p>In the evening I attended a reception at the Deanery to meet the Members of the British Academy. I had some talk with <persName xml:id="988">Hodgkin</persName>, <persName xml:id="987">Maund Thompson</persName>, <persName xml:id="986">Vinogradoff</persName>, <persName xml:id="1016">Fairbairn</persName>, <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Friday afternoon I went to Oxford for the Bursar's Dinner.<note xml:id="24" n="1"></note>  <persName xml:id="586">Wood</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="306">Gwyer</persName> travelled down with me.  It was a pleasant enough party. <hi rend="italic bold underline">On Saturday, I returned to town travelling alone with <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName>. We had an intimate &amp; profoundly interesting conversation, in the course of which I strongly urged him to go into the House of Lords</hi><hi rend="italic">.  It is clear to me that he feels deeply the ill&#8211;treatment he has received from his political friends: &amp; hungers to be again on the floor of the House of Commons to have it out with them.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
