<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most glorious bright day. The window glowed and gleamed like a cohort of seraphim commissioned to guard the Cross. I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, and read the Ante&#8211;Communion service.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><ref xml:id="92">Since bloud is fittest, Lord, to write</ref></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Thy sorrows in and bloudie fight;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My heart hath store, write there, where in</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">One box doth lie both ink and sinne.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">That when sinne spies so many foes,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Thy whips, thy nails, thy wounds, thy woes,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">All come to lodge there, sinne may say,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">No room for me, and flie away.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Sinne being gone, oh fill the place</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">And keep possession with thy grace!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lest sinne take courage and return,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">And all the writings blot or burn.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was a comparatively small congregation at Mattins, and the Offertory (&#x00A3;11.2.0.) was the smallest on record. I added the Ante&#8211;Communion Service to Mattins &amp; Litany, with the result that the whole function was not over until a few minutes before 1 p.m.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went round to <persName xml:id="1547">Uncle Charles</persName> for tea, and had some conversation with him.</p>
         <p>At Evensong, <persName xml:id="851">Walters</persName> preached an excellent simple discourse.  He will make a good parochial preacher if he doesn't fall into the <hi rend="underline">ex tempore</hi> heresy.  His voice is a pledge of success, a deep sympathetic bass, which it is joy to listen to.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
