<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="296">Sub&#8211;dean</persName> nobly came to the rescue of my distressed throat, &amp; volunteered to take the Celebration at 10 a.m. and to preach in the evening.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1115" display="no">Kenneth</persName> preached from the Gospel "And he was a Samaritan"; it was a good sermon and well&#8211;delivered. He told us that 'Samaritan' = Dissenter, and drew the moral frankly enough.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The rain began to come down smartly about 2 p.m., and so continued sharply for about 2 hours. Thus the congregation in the Abbey was extremely small, which I did not regret, as my throat was in a bad case, &amp; I could not have made myself heard over the full church.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>All this week my throat continued in a bad way: improvement being retarded by the necessity of continual speech. <persName xml:id="148">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sinclair</persName> prescribed a nauseous mixture, of which the fumes were to be inhaled, but to no effect, so that on Saturday he took me off to a throat doctor &#8211; <persName xml:id="1117">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dundas Grant</persName>. This good man made me very uncomfortable by excursions into my gullet.  He said that there was nothing seriously wrong, but the throat was in a bad state, &amp; I was run down &amp;c.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> preached in the Abbey on S. Matthew's day, and stayed the night.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Thursday I had a very lively dinner party consisting of <persName xml:id="548">Hardinge</persName>, <persName xml:id="206">Baddeley</persName>, </hi><persName xml:id="1118"><hi rend="italic">Col. M</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="italic">Cabe</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, a Virginian of his acquaintance &amp; an old soldier of <persName xml:id="1119" display="no">Lee's</persName>, <persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1120" display="no">Browne</persName>.</hi>         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
