<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was a violent &amp; bitter North&#8211;Westerly Gale, which made church&#8211;going a trial, &amp; affected badly attendance in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. I celebrated at 8 a.m.: there were 30 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. At Mattins I preached with some discomfort through an attack of lumbago. <persName xml:id="784">The Speaker</persName> was in his seat. The sermon was that which I had preached at Aberdeen last October, but with some omissions. The congregation was not large, but it was virile, &amp; it was attentive. In the afternoon, accompanied by <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; my Godson, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, I went to Bethnal Green, and <listEvent><event xml:id="27">lectured</event></listEvent> for 50 minutes on "Democracy &amp; Religion" to about 300 men in the <placeName xml:id="8">Excelsior Hall</placeName>. They were very appreciative. Then I returned to Westminster &amp; preached again in S. Margaret's to a moderate congregation. <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>, <persName xml:id="167" display="no">Ethel</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="467">Chart</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Feb. 1906, we travelled to Scotland by the M.R.  At Rothwell we were met by the carriage &amp; so were driven to <placeName xml:id="19">Murraythwaite</placeName>.  On Wednesday, mine <persName xml:id="227">host</persName> motored me into Dumfries, but it was bitterly cold, &amp; the next day I suffered much from lumbago.  On Saturday <hi rend="bold underline">we went to Glasgow where we stayed with <persName xml:id="895">Principal Story</persName></hi>.  At dinner to meet us there dined <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="244">George Adam Smith</persName></hi> on Saturday; and on Monday, <persName xml:id="581">Donald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="978" display="no">Prof. Campbell</persName>. On Sunday, I preached three times. In the Cathedral, in the <placeName xml:id="20" display="no">Bute Hall</placeName>, &amp; in Hillhead Church. The congregations were large in every case, but that in the Bute Hall, when I preached to the University, was the largest<ref xml:id="426"></ref>. It included the <persName xml:id="976">Lord Provost</persName> &amp; the Baillies in their robes. On Monday, I visited the Municipal Building &amp; Art Galleries, &amp; lunched with <persName xml:id="712">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Adam Muir</persName>. <hi rend="italic">At dinner I received a telegram (91 words) from <persName xml:id="981">Earl Howe</persName>, requesting a Memorial Service for his <persName xml:id="982" display="no">wife</persName>. </hi>On Tuesday, the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Feb., we returned to Westminster.  <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> was awaiting us.    </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, February 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1906, we went to the Premier's Reception in 10 Downing Street.  There was a frightful crush, and the atmosphere was indescribable.  Among the throng we recognized a few familiar faces.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
