<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Last week has been a shadowed and anxious time.  <hi rend="bold underline">A letter from <persName xml:id="1095">Gilbert</persName> told me that my eldest brother, <persName xml:id="1096">Walter</persName>, had died after an operation for appendicitis. I had not seen him for 30 years, for it is so long since he went out to Canada: and through all that time no letter has passed between us. I heard indirectly that he had married, &amp; now Gilbert tells me that he leaves a son, <persName xml:id="1097">Harold</persName>, who is 15 years old. The thought of the boy's desolation affected me, and I wrote to him a kind letter, sending also my photograph as a kind of introduction</hi>
<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This news of Walter's death arrived on the very day on which a Memorial Service was held in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> for <persName xml:id="1098">Lady Campbell Bannerman</persName>. The <persName xml:id="109">Archdeacon</persName> came up from the Isle of Wight &amp; read the Lesson.</p>
         <p>The discomfort of the house, added to my natural indolence, has caused this week to be a blank in the matter of work. However, with the aid of <persName xml:id="826">Bennett</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1100" display="no">Abbott</persName>, two of the senior choir&#8211;boys, I did get my books into their shelves at last: &amp;, now, feel that next week ought to show a better result in the output of work.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1101">Canon Talbot</persName> of Bristol, a tall man with a clear and pleasant voice &amp; a curiously springing gait, preached in the Abbey, and, rather to my alarm, preached extempore. His text was the famous prophecy, "They shall become one flock, one shepherd", and his sermon was a plea for 'Fundamental Christianity'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At 3 p.m. there was a very large congregation. I preached an 'old' sermon on "Temptation", but with much difficulty with a sore throat. Scarcely had I returned to my study before </hi> <persName xml:id="1102" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">r</hi>
<hi rend="italic"> Fred W. Downer</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> of Lethbridge, Canada, with <persName xml:id="1103" display="no">his wife</persName> called in order to give me some information about my deceased brother.  They spoke of him in terms of affectionate respect, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">described the boy as unusually bright and intelligent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At 7 p.m. the Abbey was again crowded.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1104">Ware</persName></hi> preached on the Parable of the 'Good Samaritan'.  He has an immense voice, which he cannot quite control; and he has too many 'leading thoughts' set forth in by no means the clearest and happiest language; but he is a good man, &amp; means well.  He came in to supper, and talked about the old Rural Deanery which I first ruled, and then he.<note xml:id="70" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, September 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1906, a Postman, giving his name as <persName xml:id="1105" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> A. Cooper</persName> of 15 Dawson Road, Walworth, S.E, called on me, and told a tale of trouble.  He had become security for somebody else, &amp; that somebody else had brought him into debt.  Hence the Money&#8211;lender, <persName xml:id="1106" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Eckstein</persName>, and divers consequential 'executions'.  Meanwhile his wife was confined, &amp; domestically he himself in extremis.  Finally, the irate &amp; insistant [sic] Eckstein had written to the G.P.O; and he must either pay up or lose his position.  <hi rend="bold underline">The amount was only &#x00A3;4.5.6: and I let him have the money</hi> on the understanding that he would repay me at the rate of 5/&#8211; weekly, from Nov. 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>. This man was but 25 years old, &amp; yet the father of 4 children, of whom the eldest was no less than 6 years old. His wife was younger than himself. He had been 9 years in the G.P.O, and had earned a good conduct stripe.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1107">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Carr&#8211;Gomm</persName> was married to <persName xml:id="1108">Miss Rome</persName> in S. Margaret's.  I gave a short address.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[119]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Sept. 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1906.</p>
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="327">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowling</persName>,</p>
         <p>I had intended to write to you before this with respect to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, but I delayed until I had had the opportunity of consulting <persName xml:id="121">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss&#8211;Custard</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="885" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Smart</persName>.</p>
         <p>They appear to be quite decisively of the opinion that Harold's powers as a musician do not justify our encouraging him to make Music his profession, while quite sufficient to justify the expectation that they will provide him with a serviceable adjunct to some regular employment.</p>
         <p>Harold will himself, perhaps, have told you that I was prepared to pay his college expenses for two years, in order that he might make a fair start in the musical profession; but, of course, I could not rightly do this in the teeth of the advice I have received.</p>
         <p>It appears, then, to be the best thing for Harold's interest that we should endeavour to find for him some suitable situation, where he could earn his living, &amp;, at the same time, keep up his music.</p>
         <p>I shall exert myself to do this for him, though, of course, my influence in this direction is limited, &amp; there are reasons which <hi rend="bold">[120] </hi>make it not altogether easy to place him suitably. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss&#8211;Custard assures me that his time has not been wasted, &amp; that he will make a fair average musician, if he continues to study music.</p>
         <p>You will not need that I should say that my interest in Harold's welfare &amp; happiness is a deep one, &amp; that I shall at all times be ready to do anything in my power to help him.</p>
         <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday, September 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905, I celebrated the marriage of <persName xml:id="1109" display="no">Captain Stockwell</persName> and <persName xml:id="1110" display="no">Miss Vale</persName>.</p>
         <p>Also, later on the same day, I celebrated the marriage of young <persName xml:id="1111" display="no">Westray</persName> and <persName xml:id="1112" display="no">Miss Guthrie</persName>.</p>
         <p>Both weddings were seemly and apparently sincere proceedings.</p>
         <p>In the course of the day, Harold came to see me, and talked over his position and prospects. Later in the day I resumed the subject with Custard, who dined with me. As a result of these consultations I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowling a letter, which is copied into this Journal.</p>
         <p>On Friday, September 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1906, I celebrated the marriage of <persName xml:id="1113" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Angus Hamilton</persName> to <persName xml:id="1114" display="no">Miss Helen Reilly</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the <persName xml:id="296">Sub&#8211;Dean</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName> dined here to meet <persName xml:id="1115" display="no">Kenneth</persName>. Suitably enough <persName xml:id="677">Sir Elliott Lees</persName> sent me some partridges.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
