<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> and celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There were 15 communicants including <persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> and <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>. But <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> was not there, being confined to her room with neuralgia and cold &#8211; an ill promise for the year. <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> came to see me with respect to the constitutional crisis.</p>
         <p>After writing a few letters I walked to the City along the Embankment in the teeth of a biting wind, and changed a cheque.  On my return, Harold brought me a ludicrous <hi rend="italic">specimen of local penny&#8211;a&#8211;lining, which </hi><hi rend="italic underline">he</hi><hi rend="italic"> thought splendid!  The Rector of S. Margaret's was described as a miraculous blend of the Archangel&#8211;Boanerges&#8211;Adonis!!  The last especially comic.  It served to amuse my wife.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="491">Lady Frances Balfour</persName> wrote to me from Whittinghame in a strain of intimacy &amp; friendship, which &#8211; as I like her &#8211; pleased me: she wanted information on a historical reference, which I was able to give her. It was an allusion to the Salter's Hall Controversy in 1719. <persName xml:id="571">Geordie</persName> &amp; a relative of hers came to entertain the choir boys, who had failed to appear. They stayed to dinner. Later appeared <persName xml:id="18">Gerald</persName>, with a huge box of toys: he stayed the night. My <persName xml:id="584">Father&#8211;in&#8211;law</persName> also dined. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> in the course of the day.</p>
         <p>Thus started the New Year. "Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee."</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>