<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Instead of going to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m, I remained at home, and typed six pages of M.S. for the <listEvent><event xml:id="25">final "Golden" Lecture</event></listEvent>, due next Tuesday.</p>
         <p>The service at 10 a.m. in the Abbey was lengthened by the slowness with which the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> read not only the long Gospel, but also the long Exhortation to Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="398">Morrison</persName> preached the Sermon: good as a fragment, but lop&#8211;sided as a whole. After service we walked in the Abbey Garden, where also came the <persName xml:id="208"><persName xml:id="804">Beechings</persName></persName>, and we talked together of educational prospects.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="795">Nixon</persName> came in to lunch.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation in the Abbey: but the air seemed to be exhausted; &amp; I preached wearily.  <hi rend="bold underline">The <ref xml:id="577">sermon</ref> took nearly 40 minutes in delivery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At Evensong in S. Margaret's there was a large congregation: among others, </hi><persName xml:id="215"><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Asquith</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> was there.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="888" display="no">Anthony Browne</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>A constable came to say that a light was left burning in the belfry. I went round and put it out.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Monday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April, 1906, I went across to the House in order to hear <persName xml:id="889">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Birrell</persName> introduce the Education Bill.  He spoke for an hour and 40 minutes: and spoke well. The speeches from the Opposition Benches were frankly hostile.  <persName xml:id="890">Masterman</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="891">Ramsay Macdonald</persName> urged secularism pure &amp; simple.  <persName xml:id="892">Macnamara</persName> blessed the Bill.  On the whole the reception struck me as chilling.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Sitting next to me in the Gallery was the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of Canterbury</persName>,</hi> with whom I had some conversation.  <hi rend="italic">He clearly doesn't want to fight the Bill, but fears he must. <persName xml:id="759">Lord Lytton</persName> was there, &amp; I promised to discuss the Bill with him in the evening, but when the time appointed had come had so bad a headache that I could not keep tryst.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
