<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[67]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The day was bright, but not altogether promising when we went aboard the steamer at 9. 7 a.m., and started for Geneva, at the farthest end of the Lake. We lunched on board, and arrived at our destination at 1 a.m. [sic] Our course was straight as far as Lausanne, then we crossed to Evians, and kept down the French side of the Lake as far as Thonon when we crossed back to Nyon, and kept to the Swiss side until we came to Geneva. The city has a stately approach. The Rhone flows out of the lake clear and limpid, and is immediately made to serve the citizens with 'power' for all civic users. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> left us at the railway station in order to go to Monge, and visit a friend: she rejoined the steamer there later. We had two hours in Geneva, &amp; spent the time in driving round the town. The Cathedral is a fine building, with the most wonderful 11<hi rend="superscript underline">tẖ</hi> century capitals.  We duly noticed <persName xml:id="930">Calvin's house</persName>: &amp; were told to mark the dwelling of the King of Servia.  At 3 p.m. we started on our return journey, keeping entirely to the Swiss coast.  We got in to Vevey at 7.20 p.m in the midst of a fine storm.  The colour of the water became bright pea&#8211;green against the lurid purple of the mountains, &amp; the minatory murky sky.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
