<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Eternal and All&#8211;Pitying Saviour, Who knowest the secrets of all hearts, and the shadows of all lives, have compassion on me, the worst and weakest of Thy Servants, whom yet in Thy mysterious Wisdom Thou hast called to the Ministry of Thy Gospel. Cleanse my conscience from dead works; purge the vision of my spirit; order my steps in the way of Thy commandments. Remember not, O dread Master, my old sins, and visit me not with Thine indignation. Look with mercy upon Thy flock, who seek at my hands the food of Thy Message. Suffer them not to perish through my sin, or go astray through my evil example. Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="851">Thomas Collins Walters</persName> entered on his duties as Curate, &amp; read his declaration of assent at Mattins.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 44 communicants. At Mattins I was pleased to see in his place the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> and his family. <persName xml:id="853">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lough</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="633">Sir Henry Graham</persName> were also present, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; a number of strange men in the Members' seats whom I must assume to be Members</hi>. At Evensong there was a large congregation. I preached an old sermon on the famous Petrine text, "Tu es Petrus", but my treatment of it was not "controversial". There remained to the devotional service a considerable number of the people, &amp; many appeared to come into the church specifically for that service.</p>
         <p>At supper were <persName xml:id="1708">Alec Beeching</persName>, <persName xml:id="467">Chart</persName> &#8211; who came to say "Goodbye" on going into Cornwall, <persName xml:id="571">Geordie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="102">Ethel</persName>, <persName xml:id="489">Sherwood</persName>, <persName xml:id="851">Walters</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>.  </p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> the last letter that I shall address to her at Horley.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After the <listEvent><event xml:id="23">"Golden" Lecture</event></listEvent> on Tuesday, March 20</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, I was taken off to lunch by the Haberdashers. We drank champagne out of tumblers in the middle of the day!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> <listEvent><event xml:id="24">Address on "Fundamental X<hi rend="superscript underline">ity</hi>"</event></listEvent> was duly delivered in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> on Saturday afternoon (March 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>).  In spite of the weather which was very wet &amp; bitterly cold, a considerable company assembled. I spoke on "Un&#8211;dogmatic Christianity". After the address, I was thanked by one of my hearers, who said he was a <persName xml:id="856" display="no">nephew</persName> of that most genial of bigots &#8211; <persName xml:id="855">Dean Burgon</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday evening I attended the annual meeting of the <orgName xml:id="65">Wesleyan London Mission</orgName> in <placeName xml:id="19">Wesley's Chapel</placeName>, City Road.  It was a pouring wet night; but notwithstanding rain &amp; mud, the Hall was completely filled.  The extempore prayer was <hi rend="underline">most</hi> trying; and there was much partisan politics in the chairman's speech.  As usual the people seemed greatly preferable to their ministers.  <persName xml:id="857">W. Crooks</persName> M.P. made a speech.  He is a born comedian.  I was received with great enthusiasm.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
