<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I attain the age of 43 years today. The rain fell in streams when I sallied forth to the early Celebration in the Abbey, posting <ref xml:id="154">my letter to the Times</ref> on the way. The <persName xml:id="296">Sub–Dean</persName> celebrated, and the <persName xml:id="1167">Bishop of Lincoln</persName> was one of the communicants. Ten years ago on this day my <persName xml:id="83">Father</persName> died. After breakfast I walked round to <persName xml:id="208">Beeching's</persName> house, and left a small present for <persName xml:id="807">Helen</persName>, who also was born today.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="401">Sir Edward</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="991" display="no">Lady Russell</persName> sent a telegram of Birthday congratulation, &amp; I received letters &amp; gifts from divers relatives &amp; friends.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="759">Lord Lytton</persName> called to ask advice anent the Education Bill.</hi>  We had a Canons' meeting at the Sub–dean's house to discuss the procedure at the next Chapter.</p>
         <p>I went round to the Schoolhouse to distribute a Birthday cake to the <orgName xml:id="32">Abbey boys</orgName>, in slices charged with sixpences. <persName xml:id="75">Tommie Hall</persName> called to give me Birthday wishes, and ask me to fulfil an old promise by marrying him on the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> December.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><ref xml:id="154">My letter</ref> appeared duly in the Times of Saturday Nov: 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. On that day I travelled to Oxford by the morning train, lunched with <persName xml:id="898">Peile</persName> in University College, attended the meeting of the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName> Council, had tea with <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>, and dined with the <persName xml:id="93">Rector of Exeter</persName> (where I met <persName xml:id="1168">Lady Acheson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1169">Sir Charles Lyall</persName>). On Sunday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Nov., I attended service in the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion.  It pleased me much to observe the Puritan fashion of administering the Elements in the seats.  <hi rend="bold underline">After breakfast I deserted mine host – <persName xml:id="1124">Bigg</persName> of Ch. Ch.</hi> – and went to <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">All Souls</orgName>.  First, <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> went with me the round of the Parks, and then <persName xml:id="652">Compton</persName>.  Then, after some talk with <persName xml:id="650">Lionel Smith</persName>, I lunched at the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName>, where came also <persName xml:id="1171">Raper</persName> and 'Dolly' <persName xml:id="132">Liddell</persName>.  After lunch the Warden proposed a motor–drive in order to see the autumnal tints.  To this I gladly assented &amp; spent the afternoon merrily enough in motoring to Pusey &amp; back.  Then I had tea with <persName xml:id="1172">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Temple</persName> at 8 Keble Road, after which I called on <persName xml:id="346">Alan</persName>, &amp; had some talk with him.  I dined in the Hall at Christ Church, but did not go into Common–room, as I was pledged to preach in <orgName xml:id="61">S. Mary's</orgName> to the Undergraduates.  These turned up in considerable numbers; the Church being fairly filled: <ref xml:id="423">my sermon</ref> from the words, 'Brethren, be not children in mind &amp;c' was me judice a failure.  <hi rend="bold underline">Afterwards I spent some while in <persName xml:id="1173">Willie Temple's</persName> rooms in Queens.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
