<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Convocation met at 11 a.m. Immediately after the prayers had been read by the <term xml:id="5">Prolocutor</term>, and the members '<term xml:id="22">preconized'</term> by the official, the <persName xml:id="128">President</persName> accompanied by his <persName xml:id="667">suffragans</persName> entered the Hall, &amp; taking the Prolocutor's chair, proceeded to read an address. This ended, the Prelates retired and left us to our work. After two notices of <term xml:id="7">Gravamina</term> from the <persName xml:id="377">Archdeacon of Lincoln</persName>, the <persName xml:id="44">Dean of Westminster</persName> moved for a Committee to consider procedure as to the Letters of Business, &amp; the <persName xml:id="1219">Archdeacon of Leicester</persName> seconded. The <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> moved an amendment, and had <persName xml:id="1220">Canon Bartram</persName> as seconder. I made a short speech explaining that I had acquiesced in the Committee because free liberty of action was reserved. So the Committee was voted without opposition, Wace's amendment being withdrawn. After lunch we discussed a motion for the Reform of Convocation, and I moved an amendment which was defeated.</p>
         <p>My <persName xml:id="584">father in law</persName> departed and my <persName xml:id="2672">sister in law</persName> arrived.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1177">Allan Edwards</persName>, who is regarded as a leader of the more religious Evangelicals, passed a note to me on which he wrote of the members of Convocation, who number 175:. 'About 24 members at the outside who might be willing to be described as Evangelicals: but only 5 such at the most among the Representative Procters'.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
