<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet morning, with a fallacious episode of brightness at the start, speedily followed by continuous rain. I celebrated at 8 a.m. (39 commt<hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi>) and preached twice. At Mattins there was a better congregation than (under the dark &amp; dropping sky) seemed probable. <persName xml:id="784">The Speaker</persName>, <persName xml:id="193">'Black Michael'</persName>, <persName xml:id="679">Ainsworth</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="990">Runciman</persName> were in the Parliamentary Seats, among others. I preached on 'The Weakness &amp; the Strength of the Saints'. There were 78 commt<hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi> at the midday Celebration.  In the evening the congregation was a small one.  I preached an old sermon on 'The State of the Departed'.  After the service, a young man asked me to give an interview to himself and a friend as they were in doubt on religious questions.  His name and address were:</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1159" display="no">W. H. Marston</persName>, 5 Oakley Crescent, Chelsea.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1160" display="no">Miss Cockerell</persName> and <persName xml:id="888" display="no">Anthony Browne</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>It never rains but it pours. So today (Monday the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Nov.) I receive a letter from the <persName xml:id="1161">Rev. Irton Smith</persName>, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's Vicarage, Ilkley asking me to make the acquaintance of a youth named <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1162">George Mackarness</persName></hi>, (33, Handforth Road, Brixton), who is said to attend <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. If all the young scape&#8211;graces in London are to make me their Father Confessor, my time will be occupied! However, I remembered his <persName xml:id="1163">uncle</persName>, who ordained me, nearly 20 years ago, &amp; was kind to me, and wrote civilly to the youth.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1164">Dawson</persName> from Loughton came to see me during the afternoon. I dined with the Brotherhood, taking with me <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, who has just joined us. Returning I went on with the Churchwardens accounts until midnight.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
