<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright deceiving day break introducing a wet Sunday. There were 32 communicants at the early Celebration. <persName xml:id="885" display="no">Smart</persName> having forgotten to bring the key of the organ key&#8211;board we had to break the protecting glass. This untoward incident began a service which was strangely wearisome. The atmosphere of the Church seemed to be asphyxiating, and I felt myself half asleep as I preached! My text was the Gospel for the day &#8211; the episode of Christ's decision as to paying tribute to Caesar. In the afternoon I left cards (since the ladies were out) on the young lady who wrote to me asking to make my acquaintance.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glasgow Bell</persName> came in to tea after the Abbey service.  There was a large congregation at Evensong, when I preached on S. John VI.15 'The Temptation of Prosperity'.  After service, <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1162">George Mackarness</persName></hi> came in to supper.  He is lodging at 36 S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's Square, Notting Hill Gate W: and is a nephew of the <persName xml:id="1163">Bishop of Oxford</persName>, by whom I was ordained.  He is scarcely 22 years old, and has racketted about more than most men.  He is now on the stage.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
