<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It was raining heavily when I went to church for the early celebration, but there was a rise in temperature. At this service were 21 communicants.</p>
         <p>The congregation at 11 a.m. was wretched. It included, however, both the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> and <persName xml:id="193">Lord S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aldwyn</persName>.  I preached an old begging sermon for the <orgName xml:id="120">Q.V. Clergy Fund</orgName>: and a collection was made at the doors amounting to &#x00A3;16.0.8., which exceeded my expectations.</p>
         <p>The Rain fell throughout the day, and spoiled the congregation at Evensong. I preached on "Staying the mind on God". <persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> brought in a <term xml:id="45">Rhodes scholar</term> to supper named <persName xml:id="1327" display="no">Sterry</persName>, to whom I gave a copy of <ref xml:id="12">"Cross&#8211;Bench Views"</ref>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>This has been a disastrous week, publicly and privately.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Education Bill has been wrecked to the dismay of all sensible men, and to general astonishment, for when it became known that the Majority in the Lords was prepared to negociate, everybody assumed that a reasonable settlement was assured.  </hi>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">But everybody had left out of account the singular personality of </hi><persName xml:id="508"><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Arthur Balfour</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline">.  That subtle and violent Politician had resolved to 'keep open' the Education Question in the interest of the Unionist Party; and his influence sufficed to carry the wiser members of his following into silent acquiescence, if not active support</hi>
<hi rend="italic">. Significantly enough, the <persName xml:id="1328">Duke of Devonshire</persName> voted with the Government in the final division.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A violent cold seized me in the course of the week, and reduced me to great discomfort and helplessness.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
