<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1906.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The bitter weather continues. There were but 8 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> including the clergy.  Accompanied by <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> I went to S. Peter's, Vere Street, and there I preached in the place of <persName xml:id="1332">Canon Page Roberts</persName>, who is laid by with influenza.  It was the third time of preaching the same sermon, on the Method &amp; Range of the Incarnation.  <hi rend="italic">I was told in the vestry that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> was in the congregation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the evening I preached on 'Judgement': the evil weather spoiled the congregation: &amp; there was a hurricane of coughs. We sang four carols after the service, &amp; then stood for the 'Dead March' in honour of the old <persName xml:id="585">Baroness Burdett Coutts</persName>who died this morning.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
		 <div type="letter">
         <p>To <persName xml:id="601">Sir Kenneth Muir&#8211;Mackenzie</persName></p>
         <p>Dec: 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1906</p>
         <p>My Dear Sir Kenneth,</p>
         <p>First, let me thank you very warmly for your kindness to <persName xml:id="113">Knowling</persName>, &amp; then let me make a few observations with respect to him.</p>
         <p>His defects are fairly obvious, &amp; not inconsiderable: he has been ill educated, &amp; has very poor intellectual powers. He has a bad memory, &amp; no great power of application.</p>
         <p>His musical ability, which three years ago seemed considerable, &amp; his voice, which was always exceptionally fine, brought him far too early for his permanent advantage into importance, and (in my judgement) gave him a special &amp; a specific claim to something more than consideration from those who might be said to have encouraged the sacrifice of his schooling to the cultivation of his singing. The most obvious thing was to do for him what is constantly done for choir&#8211;boys at the Abbey &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's, who show genuine musical ability viz: facilitate their entrance into the only career their boyhood prepares them for.  This, after consulting my <persName xml:id="121">Organist</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="560"><persName xml:id="156">churchwardens</persName></persName>, I have attempted: &amp; in order to give the boy what he could not get at home, and <hi rend="bold">[163]</hi> also to avoid risks to his health, which two years ago seemed to be serious, <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; I took him to live in this house, where he was of some service to me in my work, &amp; where also I had the advantage of overlooking pretty closely his work at the Vestry.  He behaved excellently: &amp; my wife &amp; I have never had the slightest reason for thinking that he was unworthy of being here: &amp; we both mean to let him stay till Easter, when the winter may be said to be over. He impresses favourably our visitors, &amp; has improved quickly in tone &amp; manners.  But it has happened with him, as I learn from the books happens not rarely with musical boys, that his ability does not survive the emergence out of boyhood.  Goss&#8211;Custard was as much disappointed as I was at his lack of power, when the serious work of learning began.  This is now past history, except for the right it gives me to be dogmatic as to his powers.  He ought <hi rend="underline">me judice</hi> to be encouraged to go on cultivating his music, which he will be able to make a civilizing force in his personal life, &amp; a serviceable adjunct to his earnings.</p>
         <p>He is competent to become a clerk in a public office: &amp; in point of character to be a trusted &amp; responsible clerk, but it would be for his advantage in all respects that he should be given <hi rend="bold">[164]</hi> clearly to understand that he can only gain admission into such a career by some specific &amp; serious preparation.  He is apt to be far too easy with himself: &amp; it would be kindness to be severe on indolence or lack of memory.  He responds wonderfully to the kindness of his friends: &amp; would "play up" with a word from them, as never by any general considerations of interest or duty.</p>
         <p>If you could see your way to putting before him as an object of attainment a permanent place in a public Office, &amp; could indicate to him clearly the course of work necessary to make possible that future, you will have done him a great kindness. He has conceived an immense admiration &amp; affection more suo for you, &amp; with these levers he may be raised perhaps higher than we think.</p>
         <p>Meanwhile it is excellent that he should be in your own office: &amp; if he be compelled to associate his entrance there with a continuous &amp; steady work of self&#8211;improvement, he will be lastingly the better for it.</p>
         <p>I have written so freely &amp; so fully because in truth you deserve nothing less.  Nor do I apologise: for the longer I live the <hi rend="bold">[165] </hi>more sure I am that the thing best worth doing for any of us, is to secure a chance for the beginners.</p>
         <p>With much gratitude for your kindness, &amp; all good wishes for the new year,</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>most sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson	</p>
		 </div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
