<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1907</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                                                          </p>
         <p>The first meeting of the <persName xml:id="128">Convocation Committee</persName> met at the <placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName> in the room commonly used by the Upper House.  We voted <persName xml:id="1219">Archdeacon Stock</persName> of Leicester into the Chair, &amp; discussed our procedure.  <persName xml:id="384">Preb: Ingram</persName> was elected Secretary.  <hi rend="bold underline">"One fanatick bottled up” was the comment I wrote on a sheet of paper &amp; passed to my cronies.</hi>  I moved that 'no communication be made to the press or to the public with respect to the proceedings of the committee except through the Chairman.'  <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> seconded this, and after some discussion it was carried.  Then the <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> moved that no decisions involving an alteration of the Prayer Book should be definitely adopted until they had been confirmed by the meeting next to that in which they had been passed: &amp; this, after much talk, was also adopted.  Then the question of what sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be the range of our labours was raised.  <persName xml:id="44">The Dean of Westminster</persName> was for limiting them strictly to the fewest possible points.  <hi rend="bold underline">I urged that we should make a complete job of the matter</hi>
<hi rend="underline">.</hi>  Finally we agreed to postpone the meeting until the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March, in order that the Chairman might determine a course of action.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
