<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I was up betimes, and having recalled my sleep&#8211;disordered wits by a cup of tea, proceeded to write (in pencil) a letter to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>: after which I read <persName xml:id="1491">Taylor Innes's</persName> <ref xml:id="283">'Law of Creeds in Scotland'</ref>. Then breakfast comfortably with <persName xml:id="1492" display="no">mine host</persName>. After this our functions began. I was carried off by a brace of chaplains to <placeName xml:id="27">Holyrood</placeName> for the lev&#x00E9;e. In the long ante&#8211;room adorned with the portraits of the Scottish Kings I was introduced to a charming little old white gentleman, named <persName xml:id="1493">Mair</persName>, whose name I had read overnight in <persName xml:id="1491">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Taylor Innes</persName>' volume in connection with efforts to reunite the Presbyterian Churches.  We had some conversation while we waited.  The ceremony itself was a bijou edition of a Lev&#x00E9;e at S. James'.  <persName xml:id="345">Lord Kinnaird</persName> is not a very impressive figure, but he had clothed his little person with as much magnificence as possible, &amp; managed well enough.  Then we drove back to the Hotel, where the <persName xml:id="1135">Moderator</persName> &#8211; profanely called 'the invisible Bride' &#8211; awaited his summons to the assembly.  There were considerable crowds in the streets expecting the procession from Holyrood.  The scene was animated &amp; interesting; the way being kept by troopers of the Scots Greys.  I mentally compared the blank indifference with which the populace of London regard the meetings of Convocation.  The Procession itself was long &amp; imposing, but the rain compelled the closing <hi rend="bold">[206] </hi>[symbol] of most of the carriages. The Commissioner himself, however, rode in an open carriage, &amp; was rewarded with a welcoming cheer. Among his company I noticed the bulky form and supercilious features of the <persName xml:id="1494">Archdeacon of London</persName>.</p>
         <p>The opening of the Assembly was a fine spectacle. A crowded <placeName xml:id="42">Hall</placeName> &#8211; six or seven hundred clergy &amp; elders, mostly middle&#8211;aged &amp; some aged men &#8211; galleries filled with ladies &amp; onlookers &#8211; the touch of pomp at the end of the Hall where was the 'throne'. There was a significant order in the proceedings &#8211; the election of the Moderator &amp; the constituting of the Assembly preceding the reading of the King's Commission &amp; Letter.<note xml:id="97" n="1"></note> His Grace was brief, strident, &amp; jerky: &amp; the new Moderator's reply was dignified &amp; simple. Indeed all his speeches &#8211; complimentary for the most part were very well done. <persName xml:id="1495">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott</persName>, the Leader of the House, made courteous references to <persName xml:id="268">Rainy</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1496">"Ian Maclaren"</persName>.  Then there was the election of a <hi rend="underline">clerk depute</hi>, which aroused much interest. <persName xml:id="1498">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gillespie</persName> was chosen; by a majority of three to one.  In order to vote the members filed out through doors, right &amp; left of the Moderator's chair.  The newly&#8211;elected officials took the oath of office <hi rend="underline">more Scottico</hi> with uplifted hand, &amp; then returned thanks for the election. <hi rend="bold">[207] </hi>[symbol] The proceedings began with the Clerk's exclaiming &#8211; Lock the Door! The formal mode of Address adopted by the Commissioner &amp; the Moderator is 'Right Hon<hi rend="superscript underline">ble</hi> &amp; Right Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi>'. I spoke with several members of the House e.g. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott, <persName xml:id="1499">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregor</persName>, a queer little broken man said to have been a great preacher, <persName xml:id="1500">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Murtrie</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1501">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Niven</persName> (ex&#8211;moderator), <persName xml:id="1183">Lord Balfour of Burleigh</persName>, <persName xml:id="235">Sir Mark Stewart</persName>, <persName xml:id="236">Sir Charles Dalrymple</persName>, <persName xml:id="581">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Donald M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName>, <persName xml:id="1137">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cameron Lees</persName>, <persName xml:id="1138">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fisher</persName>.</p>
         <p>The moderator receives an official stipend of &#x00A3;400: but this by no means suffices for the expenditure of his year of office.  In the case of most Moderators there is a contribution made by their congregations in addition to the official payment.  </p>
         <p>The Commissioner receives officially &#x00A3;2000, but this is understood to be quite unequal to the charge.  </p>
         <p>The Senior Clerk receives &#x00A3;300 yearly: &amp; the Clerk depute &#x00A3;100. These offices appear to be greatly regarded.</p>
         <p>The actual number of the General Assembly is about 730, and of these the major part are clergy. The total number of clergy in the Church of Scotland is about 1400.</p>
         <p>We dined at Holyrood.  It was a pleasant and picturesque function.  The company was mainly clerical &amp; municipal.  There were very few ladies: &amp; these were allocated to the principal guests.  I was very fortunate <hi rend="bold">[208] </hi>[symbol] in my partner. The hon. <persName xml:id="1221">Miss Jean Bruce</persName> was bright, intelligent, &amp; most kind. We had to be everything to one another for the adjacent company was dull &amp; decorous to the last degree. Immediately opposite were the Archdeacon of London &amp; <persName xml:id="1060">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Marshall Lang</persName>, who seemed to bore one another cruelly.  After the ladies had withdrawn I sate by Lord Kinnaird, &amp; had some conversation with him.  <persName xml:id="1502">Sir Andrew Agnew</persName> introduced himself to me, &amp; <persName xml:id="1503" display="no">Sir ___ Campbell</persName>, who claimed to be a cousin of <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>From the Palace we drove to a quaint gathering &#8211; the reception of the <persName xml:id="1504">Moderator of the Wee Frees</persName>.  It was like a rather squalid parochial tea.  There clearly is nobody supporting the handfull of fanaticks who are responsible for the latest Scottish schism.  I put my foot into it with the Pontiff himself: for by way of saying something pleasant, I violated his feelings abominably.  "I am always looking forward to visiting Inverness: because &#8211; to put the lowest reason first &#8211; <hi rend="underline">I want to buy some claret</hi>!' His Reverence's countenance was a study of mingled wonder &amp; resentment!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
