<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A doubtful morning: to and from church under umbrellas. <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated at 8 am. when there were 35 cts. <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName> fainted during the service.</p>
         <p>There were poor congregations both at Mattins and at Evensong.  In the one case the fact may be explained by the circumstance that the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> was preaching in the neighbourhood, in the other by the fineness of the weather, which rendered the Parks irresistible.  I preached the old sermon on 'Friendship' which was published in the volume <ref xml:id="13">'Preaching to the Times'</ref>.  At Evensong I preached on "Absalom's Monument." The Offertories throughout the day amounted to &#x00A3;65.: and were devoted to the Restoration Fund.<note xml:id="73" n="1"></note> </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1185">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Tait</persName>, <persName xml:id="1186">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Tait</persName>, <persName xml:id="204">Tom</persName>, <persName xml:id="1173">Willie Temple</persName>, <persName xml:id="1206" display="no">Miss Barber</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1182" display="no">Miss Lister</persName> came to lunch.  <persName xml:id="520">Oxford</persName> brought an American Unitarian, named <persName xml:id="1187" display="no">Blake</persName>, to see me.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[231]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday. (July 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1907) we lunched with <persName xml:id="1183">Lord Balfour of Burleigh</persName>:</p>
         <p>I conducted a funeral service in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> for <persName xml:id="1184">Sir Spencer Walpole</persName>.  </p>
         <p>We attended <persName xml:id="1188">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi>  Herbert Gladstone's</persName> reception in Downing street.  <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="398">Morrison</persName></hi> was there bursting with the latest gossip about church appointments. </p>
         <p>We raised about &#x00A3;77 from the offertories on Sunday, <hi rend="underline">plus</hi> some small amounts sent in privately.  We can now complete the payments for the Restoration.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
