<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[234]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Warm but close and overcast: a day to depress &amp; disenchant. I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m.: and celebrated. There were 38 cts, of whom no less than 31 were feminine: &amp; of the remaining seven, 3 were clergymen, one an official of the church, and 2 were boys. The effective laymen were embodied in the single person of <persName xml:id="1194" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Geddes</persName>. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The sense of general emptiness in Westminster is overpowering. If the present tendencies hold, these great churches will be an <term xml:id="20">Baalbec</term>, or <term xml:id="21">Ravenna</term>, the silent memorials of a vanished life.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I preached wearily at Mattins to a small congregation which listened wearily. A batch of the older choir&#8211;boys came to tea; also <persName xml:id="1352" display="no">Waterfield</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1353" display="no">Marshall</persName>, King's Scholars. At Evensong there was a better congregation. I preached on 'Singlemindedness': twisting the history of Solomon to my purpose.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="121">Goss&#8211;Custard</persName> and <persName xml:id="1204">Miss Scott</persName> came in to supper.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[235]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, July 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1907, we went to Southampton to visit the <persName xml:id="1123">Bishop Suffragan</persName>, who lives in a very pleasant house about 4 miles out of the town.  On Wednesday, we motored in the new Forest.  On Thursday, I came up to town, and conducted the annual service in the Alms&#8211;houses.  <hi rend="bold underline">Then I assisted at the wedding of <persName xml:id="305">Raymond Asquith</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1193">Miss Horner</persName> in S. Margaret's</hi>. <persName xml:id="1191">Scott&#8211;Holland</persName> tied the knot, and gave a characteristic address. The same evening I returned to Southampton. The <persName xml:id="1197">Archdeacon of Winchester</persName>, &amp; a local parson reputed a preacher, <persName xml:id="1192">Trevaski</persName> were at dinner. On Friday, we motored to Romsey, &amp; viewed the noble Abbey Church, under the enthusiastic &amp; efficient guidance of the <persName xml:id="1354">Vicar</persName>. In the afternoon we motored into Southampton, and inspected the Huguenot church, the Tudor House, boldly described as Henry Vlll<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="superscript">'s </hi>palace, the Walls, &amp; the new parish church of S. Mary, built as a memorial of <persName xml:id="507">Bishop S. Wilberforce</persName>. On Saturday we concluded our visit, &amp; returned to Westminster. In the evening we went to Richmond, and I <listEvent><event xml:id="38">addressed</event></listEvent> a gathering in the grounds of the <orgName xml:id="80">Wesleyan Training College</orgName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, with his arm in splints from a bicycling accident, came to stay for a while.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
