<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather continues bitterly cold. <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m., and I served. There were but 18 communicants, the smallest number on the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> Sunday in the month I can recall.  There was but a modest congregation at 11 a.m. when I preached on "Christian Fraternity", and made appeal for the <orgName xml:id="125" display="no">Jamaica Church Fund</orgName>. I celebrated the Communion; <hi rend="bold underline">there were 73 communicants, including <persName xml:id="491">Lady Frances Balfour</persName> and <persName xml:id="1255">Signorina Castelvecchio</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the Evening the congregation was by no means large; and the coughing was distinctly aggressive: but the collection was better than I ventured to expect. The total amount raked together during the day exceeded <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;48.0.0.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of February 1907 <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and I went to Canterbury on a short visit to <persName xml:id="383">Archdeacon Spooner</persName>. I preached in the Cathedral on Quinquagesima at Evensong. There was a large congregation. On Monday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, we returned to town: &amp; I attended the Chapter Meeting.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> very civilly asked us to tea, and we had a pleasant half&#8211;hour in his company. He showed us the fine series of Decanal portraits.</p>
         <p>I made a rough pencil sketch of the <persName xml:id="1355">Orlando Gibbons</persName> monument for the Chapter Meeting tomorrow.</p>
         <p>On the platform I was addressed by a stout gentleman, who announced himself as <persName xml:id="1356">Atlay</persName>, who once was known to me at Oxford &#8211; 23 years ago. Even with this announcement I recognized him with difficulty.</p>
         <p>The Chapter Meeting on Monday, Feb. 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, was mainly concerned with the fabric; and we had another interesting evidence of the impracticableness of our architect, <persName xml:id="1202">Prof. Lethaby</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, Feb. 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, the young man, <persName xml:id="1357" display="no">Nairne</persName>, came to say that <persName xml:id="1358" display="no">his wife</persName> was dead. I promised to read the service in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 10 a.m.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="928" display="no">The King</persName> opened Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> in State: but the rain spoiled the show.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
