<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[219]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet thunderous day, dark to live under, difficult to live through. <persName xml:id="456">Blackmore</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m., and I assisted. There were 32 cts, among whom old <persName xml:id="232">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Talbot</persName>, <persName xml:id="1194" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Geddes</persName>, two strange clergymen &amp; five other males.</p>
         <p>At Mattins there was by no means a large congregation.  I preached from the Gospel for the day &#8211; Dives &amp; Lazarus &#8211; but wearily.  Also I celebrated the Holy Communion: there were 69 cts. </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="666">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="836" display="no">Buff</persName> came to lunch. Also M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Griffith&#8211;Jones.  </p>
         <p>At Evensong I preached a second time on Dives &amp; Lazarus. There was a large, but not a crowded congregation.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="227">Murray</persName> and <persName xml:id="1255">Signorina</persName> came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[220]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The following letter to <persName xml:id="752">Barnett</persName> will serve to throw light on the proceedings of a somewhat stormy chapter:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
		 <p>June 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1907</p>
         <p>My dear Barnett,</p>
         <p>I think I owe you an explanation. When I said that you were not 'straight', I did not mean to convey any imputation on your personal rectitude, but that you did not 'play the game' as a member of our body politic. It would be the merest affectation for me to pretend that on this point I have changed my opinion, but I should be sincerely sorry if you thought that I designed any reflection on your honour. That was not, and is not, in my thought: but I feel that the language I used might give you another impression, and, therefore, I beg to withdraw what I said, and to ask your pardon for saying it.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>v. faithfully yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p>
		 </div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
