<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[241]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] [symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="336">Galton</persName> preached in the Abbey at 10 a.m. He made the festival of S. Bartholomew the peg on which to hang a long &amp; rather bitter disquisition on ecclesiastical bigotry, which is indeed a large &amp; lamentable theme, which never grows old.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1196" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> John Homer Deis</persName> of S. Mark's, Washington, lunched here, and attended service in the Abbey. There was a great congregation, largely (as I judge) of visitors from America. I <ref xml:id="589">preached</ref> from the Gospel for the day, "Who is my neighbour?"</p>
         <p>After tea, Galton, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, and I walked the length of the Embankment &amp; back.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The preacher in the Evening was a Cowley Father named <persName xml:id="1197">Conran</persName>. He ranted and roared wonderfully, and a large congregation listened without sign of resentment, perhaps with approval. He has the aspect of a good &amp; sincere man, though religiously a mere dervish. At supper the conversation drifted on to the Athanasian Creed, and there quickly developed itself a sharp discrepancy of attitude between Galton &amp; Conran!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[242]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>All merciful Saviour, have compassion on my misery and sin.  Speak the word of enlightening power and give me spiritual vision: break from off me the yoke of wrong&#8211;doing and the desire of it: and bind on me the holy burden of Thy Service.  </p>
         <p>Most loving Master, make possible to me the bearing of Thy Yoke, and shew me the path wherein Thou willest me to walk. Give me a measure of Thy pure and righteous Spirit, that I may be able to overcome sin within and without me. Kindle in my heart the fires of Thy own mighty and suffering love, and make me strong to persevere in Thy Service. Purge from my mind the stains of past transgression, and banish the darkening clouds of resentment &amp; prejudice. Make possible to me, O good Shepherd, the help &amp; service of Thy children, and own me as Thy servant in the end. Shew Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
