<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> took to her bed last Monday, and developed a <term xml:id="48">quinsy</term>, with which she has spent a miserable week, &amp; still is in great discomfort. <persName xml:id="898">Peile</persName> called last night to inquire: he cried off staying the night here on the score of <persName xml:id="1346" display="no">his mother's</persName> illness: which happened conveniently for us. The doctor tells me that Influenza is raging in Westminster.</p>
         <p>A dull, cold, misty morning not favourable to large congregations. I preached on 'The naturalness of Christianity' at the morning service, and begged for the <orgName xml:id="124">Church Missionary Society</orgName>: but the congregation was both scanty and poor: and the collection did not reach &#x00A3;24.!</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1054">Haddan</persName> preached at the afternoon service in the Abbey from the words of Job; 'Canst thou by searching find out God?' It was an eloquent and well&#8211;delivered sermon, of a somewhat archaic type. There seemed, so far as I could judge from my stall, to be a large congregation.</p>
         <p>I preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> to a rather disappointing congregation. My text was Isaiah LVII.20,21. <persName xml:id="888" display="no">Anthony Brown</persName> came in to supper: &amp; afterwards I read <persName xml:id="1348" display="no">Browning's</persName> <ref xml:id="277">"Saul"</ref> aloud to him &amp; <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
