<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="1135">Moderator's</persName> breakfast is a formidable function. About 160 members of the <orgName xml:id="134">Assembly</orgName> &amp; their wives &amp; daughters were entertained this morning. We began with a little service. The <persName xml:id="1505" display="no">Chaplain</persName> read a chapter &amp; some prayers: &amp; then the Moderator gave the blessing. Breakfast followed to which we went in order as our names were called. I took in <persName xml:id="1506" display="no">Miss Dalrymple</persName>, a pleasant young lady enough but not to be named with my <persName xml:id="1221">Princess of Holyrood</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">At 10.30 a.m. we assembled in S. Giles' for the Holy Communion. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">For the first time in my life I received the Sacrament according to the Presbyterian Rite.</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> It was a deeply impressive &amp; edifying service.  A form was used by the Moderator which appeared to include most part of the Anglican Liturgy.  Lessons from both Testaments were read; and Psalms, Paraphrases, &amp; Hymns sung.<note xml:id="192" n="1"></note>  The most original feature from an Anglican point of view was the administration of the Elements.  This was done by the Elders: the communicants remaining in their seats</hi><hi rend="italic">.<note xml:id="193" n="2"></note>  A square piece of bread was passed round, &amp; everybody broke off a small piece.  Then followed the Cup.  Nothing could be more congregational.  Most of the communicants, after receiving, knelt down, or at least assumed an attitude of devotion.  </hi>I have rarely, if ever, been at a more <hi rend="bold">[210]</hi> [symbol] genuinely Christian service.  The priest is entirely subordinate: the <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="50">Corpus Fidelium</term></hi> is paramount.  </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I must not omit that before the service began a stout, bearded small old man read a protest against the use of the Form of Service. His name is <persName xml:id="1507">Jacob Trimmer</persName> [sic], &amp; he plays in the Church of Scotland a rôle hardly dissimilar from that of <persName xml:id="1508">Kensit</persName> in the Church of England. From S. Giles's we passed to the <placeName xml:id="42">Assembly Hall</placeName>, where the transactions were mostly of a formal &amp; honorific character.</hi>  Deputations from the Presbyterian Churches of America, Wales &amp; Canada, were heard, &amp; courteously welcomed.  <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1510" display="no">M. Merle d'Aubigny</persName></hi>, a son of the <persName xml:id="1509">ecclesiastical historian</persName>, made a very lucid &amp; excellent oration in English on the religious situation in France: &amp; the Waldensian Churches in Italy were represented by an English Minister. Reports on the Church in India brought some rather humbling allusions to the narrow &amp; unworthy conduct of the Anglican Bishops in the matter of the garrison Churches.<note xml:id="98" n="3"></note> I observed clear indications of an anti–liturgical spirit in the discussion on the Report of the Committee on Aids to Devotion.<note xml:id="99" n="4"></note> I joined <persName xml:id="491">Lady Frances</persName> in the Royal box for the last part of the proceedings. She introduced me to a fine old parson named <persName xml:id="1511" display="no">Pagan</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I dined at <placeName xml:id="27">Holyrood</placeName> again, but was not favoured by fortune in the young lady whom I took down to dinner – <persName xml:id="1512" display="no">Miss Grainger Stewart</persName>.  She told me that she belonged to the <orgName xml:id="118">United Free Church</orgName>; &amp; her manners were marked by the freedom which one associates with Dissenters.  I had some conversation with <persName xml:id="1221">Miss Bruce</persName> after dinner, but <hi rend="underline">that</hi> was speedily cut short by those truly formidable ladies, <persName xml:id="1492" display="no">mine host's</persName> <persName xml:id="1513" display="no">sisters</persName>, who engaged me in a discussion on psychical research.  After dinner the Moderator carried me off to a reception given by <persName xml:id="904">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Paul</persName>, where we stayed but a short time.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
