<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[247]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A calm, bright morning for the last day of my canonical residence. I walked round to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, and was there joined by <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, who had been to Communion. We walked round the bridges feasting our eyes with the fairest visions in the world of river &amp; bridge, palaces &amp; temples.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="62">Kirschbaum</persName> preached at 10 a.m. It was a good sermon, but he spoke over&#8211;loudly for pleasant hearing. There were 101 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. After service we walked round the bridges talking of d.w.s.</p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation at 3 p.m. My voice was disappointingly weak &amp; husky. I doubt whether everybody could hear the sermon. It was an old one on the difficult &amp; now urgent matter of <ref xml:id="420">'the claims of Ceasar &amp; of God'</ref>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1242">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fleet</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1243">her daughter</persName>, relatives of <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, were in the Abbey, and afterwards came in to tea.</p>
         <p>An immense congregation in the Abbey at 7 p.m. I preached another old sermon, '<hi rend="underline">Staying the mind on God'</hi>. My voice served me well, &amp; everybody seemed able to hear.</p>
         <p>Then after supper, Harold &amp; <persName xml:id="165">Wilson</persName> sang to us: &amp; when they had gone away, I made my farewells to <persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, &amp; went off to S. Pancras to catch the night express to Scotland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[248]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday, the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept: 1907, the motor met me at Annan about 7 a.m. and carried me quickly to <placeName xml:id="19">Murraythwaite</placeName>, where I had time to bath &amp; change before breakfast.  My wife arrived later in the day.  We spent the week very happily in making motor excursions about the county.  On Tuesday we <hi rend="underline">picniced</hi> [sic] at the 'Devil's Beef Tub': on Wednesday at Sanquhar Castle: on Thursday, at the hermitage.  On Friday we motored to Sweet&#8211;heart Abbey: on Saturday we lunched with the <persName xml:id="995"><persName xml:id="996">Johnson&#8211;Fergussons</persName></persName>: on Sunday we rested according to the commandment: on Monday we visited Lethudy(?) Abbey &amp; the Ruthwell Stone: and on Tuesday" took up our own carriages", and departed to visit <persName xml:id="1060">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lang</persName> at Broadmeadows, Selkirk.</p>
         <p>Here we received an affectionate welcome, &amp; continued in great contentment until Monday, the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept.  <persName xml:id="1244" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hamilton</persName> was there with her motor&#8211;car, by means of which we were able to see much of the country, &amp; to revisit the Abbeys of Jedburgh, Dryburgh, &amp; Melrose.</p>
         <p>On Sept 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1907 we left Broadmeadows, &amp; journeyed to Sauchieburn, near Stirling, where we found a party assembled for the Stirling Ball.  <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with the rest, &amp; danced till nearly 6 a.m., with result that she was discomposed on Thursday, &amp; held us back from going on as we had arranged.  On that day I was taken in the motor to Kennet, Alloa, the house of <persName xml:id="1183">Lord Balfour</persName> <hi rend="bold">[249] </hi>of Burleigh, <hi rend="bold underline">where the charming &amp; admirable young lady, <persName xml:id="1221">Miss Jean Bruce</persName>, showed me the relics of <persName xml:id="1222" display="no">Mary, Q. of Scots</persName>, which are the pride of the family</hi>. These consist of</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>A ciborium of enamelled copper: a lovely example of Limoges work of the XII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century.</item>
            <item>A cup, said to have been <persName xml:id="1223">Malcolm Canmore's</persName>.</item>
            <item>A necklace, with a beautifully carved stone.</item>
            <item>Some small tea&#8211;spoons.</item>
            <item>A small brass bell.</item>
         </list>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">Friday, the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Oct, was a lovely autumn day: we loafed about the policies until lunch time.  Ella was now well again, &amp; joined in a visit to the fishery after lunch.  The spectacle of the trout &#8211; 2000 in each of the larger, and 500 in the smaller &#8211; was truly astonishing.  They leapt in crowds for the chopped cray&#8211;fish &amp; whelks which were thrown in to them.  At 6p.m. everybody save ourselves &amp; <persName xml:id="1225" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Meicklejohn</persName> went off in the motor to Edinburgh for another ball.  We dined peacefully, intending to depart on the morrow.  We <hi rend="underline">did</hi> depart, but thro' some blunder the cab failed to come in time for the train, so that we lost our connections and had to spend Sunday in Aberdeen.  On the road I read with much interest <persName xml:id="1224">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ward's</persName> novel, <ref xml:id="163">'The Marriage of William Ashe'</ref>.  In the course of the day we sent off no less than five telegrams in various directions.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
