<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; to <persName xml:id="1162">George Mackarness</persName> before getting up. <persName xml:id="1135">The Moderator's</persName> breakfast introduced me to <persName xml:id="1510" display="no">M. d'Aubign&#x00E9;</persName> and <persName xml:id="1514" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wallace</persName>.  I took in one <persName xml:id="1515" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Alison</persName>, who professed herself a friend of Ella's.  The post brought me the announcement that <persName xml:id="1516">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gough</persName> of the Colonial Office is dead.  I wrote to <persName xml:id="1517" display="no">his daughter</persName>; also to <persName xml:id="1518" display="no">Whitton</persName>, the <persName xml:id="214">Dean of Ripon</persName>, &amp; divers others.  Then Mr. Wallace met me by arrangement concluded at breakfast at S. Giles' &amp; showed me over the Church: &amp; <placeName xml:id="43">Advocates' Library</placeName>.  We saw the courts at their business; &amp; then went on to the <orgName xml:id="134">Assembly</orgName>, where the discussion on the new Formula of Subscription began.<note xml:id="100" n="1"></note>  <persName xml:id="1495">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott</persName> and <persName xml:id="1183">Lord Balfour of Burleigh</persName> spoke well: &amp; there was a minister from the Shetlands, named I think <persName xml:id="1519" display="no">Ker</persName>, who moved the hilarity of the House by a ready &amp; humourous speech.  In the end the motion to proceed to the drafting of a new Formulary was adopted by a large majority.  <persName xml:id="1520">Forsyth</persName> whom I had met overnight asked me to join him in some lunch; &amp; we went together to a restaurant in Prince's Street, &amp; lunched.  He is an interesting man, who distinctly impressed me favourably.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>He speaks with much energy of the 'New Theology', which outrages his theological self&#8211;respect &amp; alarms his Christian conscience. '"If they believe not Moses &amp; the Prophets, neither will they believe though one rose from the dead" &#8211; that disposes of the evidential worth of Christ's Resurrection' &#8211; this observation impressed me: but he says many striking things. I took him to the Hotel, &amp; gave him tea after lunch: &amp; we had some conversation. Then I returned to the General Assembly, but there was in progress nothing beyond a dreary discussion of schemes for clerical pensions.</p>
         <p>One incident in the Assembly's proceedings this morning impressed me. An assistant&#8211;Secretary had appointed for the <orgName xml:id="117" display="no">Home Mission Committee</orgName>, &amp; the vote which effected this requested the Moderator to commend him in prayer to the guidance of the Almighty. This request was immediately complied: &amp;, in the most natural way in the world, the Assembly fell to prayer: after which business was resumed. Nothing of this kind could happen in the formal &amp; frivolous atmosphere of an English Convocation without giving a painful impression of unreality. Moreover, the use &amp; custom of extemporaneous prayer would seem to be indispensable for such a purpose.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
