<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[250]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">We breakfasted comfortably at the Hotel, and afterwards attended service &amp; received the Holy Communion at S. James's Church. The building was rather above the average of Scottish churches: the congregation was meagre, and mainly in petticoats. The service was audibly &amp; reverently read: and the singing, led by a poor organ &amp; a small choir, not worse than might have been expected. The minister, whose name seems to be <persName xml:id="1227" display="no">Farquhar</persName>, had a depressed &amp; resentful aspect, as of one whose fortune appeared to himself worse than his merits. The sermon was read from a MS., but gained nothing from the fact save that relative coherence which always sets prepared above extemporaneous discourses. After lunch we wrote letters, &amp; then went to the old University, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="719">Principal</persName> and <persName xml:id="1060">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Marshall Lang</persName>, who gave us tea very hospitably.  The Principal also showed us the medieval cathedral, dedicated to S. Machar.  We walked back through falling rain to the Hotel, &amp; re&#8211;packed our luggage with a view to sending off the dispensable portion thereof by luggage train, &amp; so facilitating motoring if the weather permits, next week.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[251] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">On Monday, the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Oct, we travelled to Dinnet, and there hired a carriage for the drive to Tillypronie, a house situated 1120 feet above the sea&#8211;level &amp;, indeed, one of the highest, if not actually the highest, gentlemen's residence in Scotland.  We arrived at our journey's end in good time, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">were hospitably welcomed by <persName xml:id="1205">Sir John Clark</persName>. Our host is a remarkable old man, born as long ago as 1821. He was present at the Coronation of <persName xml:id="1228" display="no">Q. Victoria</persName>, and as a member of the British Embassy at Paris in 1847&#8211;9, he was eye&#8211;witness of the Revolution which upset the throne of <persName xml:id="1238">Louis Philippe</persName></hi>.  In the evening he read to us a written statement of his reminiscences of that time, prepared originally as a lecture to the local Institute.  It was extraordinarily interesting.  On Tuesday, I walked with <persName xml:id="1241" display="no">Coltman</persName>; <hi rend="bold underline">we put up two capercailzie [sic] on the road</hi>. In the afternoon we went for a carriage drive to a ruined house, built (as an inscription still records) by <persName xml:id="1240" display="no">John Gordon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1239" display="no">Isabel Carnegie</persName> in 1590. The local minister dined in the evening. He seemed rather a good specimen of Presbyterian Parish priest. The following morning (Wednesday, Oct 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) we drove to Ballater, about 12 miles distant, and there joined <persName xml:id="584">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dennistoun</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="861" display="no">Dennis Webster</persName>, who had arrived by motor overnight.  We motored as far as Perth, being somewhat incommoded by rain, and at Blangowrie delayed by some mishap to the internal economy of the motor.  The scenery was wild &amp; romantic, &amp; had the weather been more kindly, we could not have avoided a rare enjoyment.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[252]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">On Thursday, the 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of October, we motored from Perth to Row, stopping to lunch at Killearn (?) [sic] a hostel of the cousinhood.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">On Friday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Oct:, I returned to Westminster.  My train ran into Euston at 11.30 p.m. just 3/4 hour after time.
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
