<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">The weather continues bitterly cold, and up&#8211;rising even for the holiest purposes is penitential.  However I <hi rend="underline">did</hi> get up, and go to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> where I celebrated the Holy Communion for the last time this year.  There were only 11 communicants including the clergy, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; <persName xml:id="77">my sister</persName></hi>. Save for <persName xml:id="1033">Ramsay</persName>, who was present officially, all the rest were of the gentler sex.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">At Mattins, the congregation was small &amp; strange. I preached an old sermon on 'the use &amp; abuse of the memory'. The Offertory was but &#x00A3;9.16.6.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">In the afternoon I remained within doors, &amp; completed the sermon for the Abbey.  <hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="560">Admiral Rolfe</persName> came in at tea&#8211;time, and spoke with much vivacity, and in a very interesting way of his early memories of <persName xml:id="1410" display="no">Froude</persName>, <persName xml:id="1409">James Anthony's</persName> scientific brother, who, though a martyr to <term xml:id="24">mal de mer</term> pursued with enthusiasm his study of the problem of rolling ships</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">The Abbey appeared to be quite full at 7 p.m. I <ref xml:id="592">preached</ref> for 3/4 of an hour on Hebrews xiii.8: and then went over to S. Margaret's for the carol&#8211;singing. <persName xml:id="1255">Signorina</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[271]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">On the last day of the year everything was commonplace.  I misused rather than used my time by running thro' <persName xml:id="1413" display="no">Hearne's</persName> <ref xml:id="170" display="no">Diary</ref>, noting the stories of preachers &amp; preaching which it contains.  In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> walked with me into the City in order to see the horse setup on the Wellington statue.  <hi rend="bold underline">We called on <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>, who was about to go to Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph"><persName xml:id="1162">George Mackarness</persName> came to see me. He &amp; his <persName xml:id="1213">young lady</persName> had been in the Abbey on Sunday night.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">It has been a year full of anxiety and but little lightened by success.</p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph"><hi rend="bold underline">The only publication was the little book on <ref xml:id="171">'Christian Marriage'</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
