<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[361] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.  Auchenlea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I preached in the Episcopalian Church, and assisted at the Holy Communion. The weather, which overnight had seemed promising, now went back to rain: &amp; one's spirits became as low as the hopes of farmers.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Yesterday's "Times" contains my <ref xml:id="242">letter</ref> in reply to <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName>. I hardly see how it was possible for me to leave his <ref xml:id="243">letter</ref> without answer: but I would greatly have preferred to do so.</hi><hi rend="italic">  And it is the case that I resent the method of his writing.  He comes in to the Rescue of the Fanaticks whenever they are really up a tree: &amp; his great reputation for learning &amp; balance of judgement make his assistance of immense value.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Sept, we motored to Pitnacree in Perthshire &amp; stayed the night at that house with <persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford–Bell</persName>.  The weather was unkindly, &amp; save for a short distance round the northern end of Loch Lomond (whereof the spectacle was entrancingly beautiful), we travelled with the hood on the motor–car.  At Pitnacree were staying <persName xml:id="1624" display="no">Miss S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George</persName>, who sang very prettily: &amp; <persName xml:id="1625" display="no">Capt<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> Graeme</persName>, who had, or professed, a genuine interest in bull–fights, of which he had attended more than fifty.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Sept., it rained most part of the day: we motored in the afternoon to Balharry, Meigle, where we stayed two nights with the <persName xml:id="1622"><persName xml:id="1623">Dunroach Smiths</persName></persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[362]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept, we motored to make a call on <persName xml:id="1311" display="no">Admiral Drummond</persName>, an ancient comrade of my <persName xml:id="584">father–in–law</persName>, who had settled down to play at farming in his old age.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon we motored to Dundee, a distance of about 15 miles from Balharry. In the evening <persName xml:id="1626" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Halker</persName>, the stipendiary magistrate of Hull, dined.  He shewed me a letter addressed to <hi rend="italic">him by <persName xml:id="1310">Hayes Fisher</persName>, speaking in terms of the warmest respect &amp; affection of <persName xml:id="1710">Whitmore</persName>, whose very unexpected death was reported a week since.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept, we motored from Balharry to Row via Perth, Dunblane and Donne.  We stopped at the cathedral at Dunblane.  It is a beautiful building, and seemingly well restored.  The eastern window by <persName xml:id="104">Kempe</persName> is a fine specimen of modern glass.  On the chancel floor are the tombs of the three Drummond <persName xml:id="1304"><persName xml:id="1305" display="no"><persName xml:id="1306" display="no">sisters</persName></persName></persName> said to have been poisoned by the Scottish nobles who desired to wed <persName xml:id="1302">James IV</persName> to <persName xml:id="1303">Margaret Tudor</persName>.  </p>
         <p>In the evening we dined at Artarman.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>The 'Times' of Thursday, 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept, contained a leader entitled <ref xml:id="244">'Episcopacy &amp; Reunion'</ref>, in which it summed up the correspondence, in which I have contributed two letters.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[363] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>From Monday, the 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept, to Saturday the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Oct., the Convocation Committee on the <orgName xml:id="85">Letters of Business</orgName> sate at the <placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName>, daily from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m, and from 2 p.m. to 5 p.m.  <persName xml:id="1219">Archdeacon Stocks</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1312">Canon Hammond</persName> stayed here: and daily the Committee lunched at the Deanery &amp; here, one side of the table going to the one place, &amp; the other side to the other.</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">N.B.</cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">On <hi rend="bold">Saturday, the 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> October,</hi> a second copy of the Petition to the King as Visitor was sent to <persName xml:id="1313">Lord Knollys</persName>.  The first copy, which <persName xml:id="296">Duckworth</persName> left by hand at Buckingham Palace, went astray, and thus, through the carelessness of some menial, we have lost two months of important time.<note xml:id="77" n="1"></note></cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
