<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[347]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. There were but 10 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> including the <persName xml:id="1608">Bp. of North Dakota</persName>, <persName xml:id="1019">Addis</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> who returned from his holiday last week.  The collect fitted well my mood of perplexity &amp; vacillation.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>O God, Whose never&#8211;failing providence ordereth all things both in heaven &amp; earth, We humbly beseech Thee to put away from us all hurtful things, and to give us those things which be profitable for us; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</item>
         </list>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> celebrated in the Abbey at 10 a.m., and the Bishop of Duluth (<persName xml:id="398">Morrison</persName>) preached. He was extemporaneous, verbose, and declamatory. There were 120 comts.</p>
         <p>At 3 p.m. there was a very large congregation, including the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName>. I preached on 'Single&#8211;mindedness', repeating the discourse preached in S. Margaret's on July 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1907.</p>
         <p>At 7 p.m. the Abbey was again crowded. The Bishop of North Dakota preached well.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[348] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Pros</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>A change of work, probably beneficial both to mind and body.</item>
            <item>A public <hi rend="underline">imprimatur</hi> to the views I have maintained as to the Church of England.</item>
            <item>An opportunity of 'sweetening Jordan at its source' by getting into touch with the clergy&#8211;in&#8211;the&#8211;making.</item>
            <item>Connection with a famous, numerous, &amp; powerful society.</item>
            <item>A chance of writing a serious work.</item>
            <item>Relief from this ceaseless round of preaching.</item>
            <item>The advice of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Wednesday, Aug. 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1908, I received a letter from the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> offering me the vacant Professorship at Oxford</hi>. I replied at once asking for a fortnight's grace before giving my final decision: then I wrote to <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName>, and to the Archbishop. On Saturday I lunched at Lambeth, and talked the matter over with his Grace. He undertook to reflect, and then write before going abroad on Monday. I saw Raleigh, who on the whole favoured my going.</p>
         <p>The matter was strangely complicated by the fact that <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> had told me that the <persName xml:id="1554">Bp. of Salisbury</persName> was pressing him on the Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> for the post, &amp; I had eagerly </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[349]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Con</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>The loss of nearly &#x00A3;300 per annum.</item>
            <item>The deadly resentment of the disappointed pundits.</item>
            <item>The labour of embarking on a new method of life, and the risk of failure therein.</item>
            <item>The separation from S. Margaret's &amp; the Abbey.</item>
            <item>Leaving the constitutional conflict <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="34">in medias res</term></hi>.</item>
            <item>The forfeiture of the special independence which the position at Westminster possesses.</item>
            <item>The clear advice of <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, and Watson.</item>
            <item>Lending myself to a handling of the Chair which my deliberate judgment disapproves.</item>
         </list>
         <p>approved, not suspecting that I should myself come into debate. <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName> also had come to see me, and indicated that he was an aspirant. I had written to <persName xml:id="1054">Hadden</persName> pressing him to use his influence, and had set forth the candidates in what appeared to me the order of their merit &#8211; 1. Watson 2. Rashdall. 3. <persName xml:id="1820">Charles</persName> 4. <persName xml:id="1781">Cruttwell</persName>. Hadden had called to see me, and I renewed my insistence on Watson's claims.</p>
         <p>On Monday, 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> August, a long letter came from the Archbishop, the gist of which was (as I read it) that I ought to go.  I wrote to the Warden, &amp; he strongly counselled acceptance; also to Gow and <hi rend="bold">[350] </hi>[symbol] Beeching, who gave conflicting counsel, the first being against, the last for acceptance.</p>
         <p>I went carefully into the financial aspect of the matter, and concluded that I should not be able to maintain the position adequately on the official income. To this effect I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>, indicating that unless she had some very strong reasons to urge against that course, I should decline the P.M.'s offer. Later in the day &#8211; Thursday, the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Aug: &#8211; on which I wrote thus decisively the Warden came in, and persuaded me to adventure the risks of poverty and failure, which indeed he declined to consider serious.  He said that the Canons of Ch. Ch. did not entertain to any great extent.  So thus I was sent back into the perplexities from which I had seemed to escape.  Hearing that the <persName xml:id="1447">Archdeacon</persName> was in residence, I wrote to him privately asking for information on certain points viz.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>What is the statutory residence of the Canons?</item>
            <item>Who does the dilapidations?</item>
            <item>When does the income accrue, whether from the death of the old, or the installation of the new Canon?</item>
            <item>Who pays the rates &amp; taxes on the house?</item>
         </list>
         <p>On Saturday, the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> August, <persName xml:id="1300" display="no">Merton</persName> carried me to Oxford in his motor, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> being with us.  On Sunday <hi rend="bold">[351] </hi>[symbol] <hi rend="bold underline">I went before breakfast into the Chapel at All Souls, and spread the P.M.'s letter before the Lord</hi>. The collect for the day (9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> after Trinity) matched well my situation: I prayed it several times over:&#8211; 'Grant to us, Lord, we beseech thee, the spirit to think &amp; do always such things as be rightful: that we, who cannot do anything that is good without thee, may by thee be enabled to live according to thy will, through Jesus Christ our Lord'.  After breakfast, I went to service in Christ Church.  The Dean, <persName xml:id="1782">Ottley</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName> were present.  Ottley preached the sermon.  <hi rend="bold underline">When service was ended, I went in to the Deanery, and talked over the whole matter of the Professorship with Strong. He was most kind, but I went away in a state of great indecision</hi>.  <hi rend="underline">My wife had written definitely advising me to go to Oxford</hi>, and thus all the factors requisite for making the final choice were in my hands.  <hi rend="italic underline">When I awoke on Monday, the 17</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> Aug., my mind was made up, and before leaving Oxford to motor back to Westminster I sent notes to Strong and Watson stating my resolve to decline the Professorship.  We reached home about lunch&#8211;time, and as soon as that meal was over, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote the fatal letter to Asquith</hi><hi rend="italic underline">.<note xml:id="83" n="1"></note> Thus after 12 days of mental debate I reached the conclusion to which my first impressions had pointed. I hope I have done right: assuredly I have not acted rashly or irreligiously.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[352] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> August 1908, I travelled to Scotland via Euston, and joined <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> at Auchenlea.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">My reception indicated no slight measure of disappointment</hi><hi rend="italic">: the dear lady had brought herself into a desire for change, and was quite grieved to know that Oxford was definitely 'off'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday I received a telegram from Harold announcing that he had passed his exam<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>. May this be the beginning of a steady and settled progress!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On Thursday, a friendly letter from the P.M. acknowledged my letter declining Ch. Ch. I seized the opportunity, and wrote to him, stating my view of the Professorship, and strongly urging him to appoint Watson.<note xml:id="84" n="2"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, we enjoyed the delicious excitement of a tea party at <persName xml:id="286">Aunt Sabina's</persName>!</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the motor having returned from the repairer, we planned a long ride in Argyllshire: but we had to turn back when we were but half way on our journey.  However we saw Loch Long &amp; Loch Lomond to great advantage.  Harold sent me his photograph.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1785">Gordon Craik's</persName> death is announced in the <ref xml:id="265">Scotsman</ref>. I wrote to condole with his parents.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[353]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Books read during my holiday:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1783" display="no">Black</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="232">'Kilmeny'</ref></item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1784" display="no">John Oliver Hobbes</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="233">'The School for Saints'</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1153">Jowett's</persName></hi> <ref xml:id="234">Translation of the Four Socratic Dialogues of Plato</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1443">Abbott's</persName></hi> <ref xml:id="235">Philochristus</ref></item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1496">Maclaren</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="236">Graham of Claverhouse</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<persName xml:id="1789" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Justin M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="underline">Carthy</hi></persName>. <ref xml:id="237">Dear Lady Disdain</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1788" display="no">Oswald Dykes</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="220">'The Christian Minister &amp; his Duties'</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1786" display="no"><persName xml:id="1787" display="no">Williamson</persName></persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="238">'My friend the Chauffeur'</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline">Williamson</hi>. <ref xml:id="239">'The Lightening Conductor'</ref>.</item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1790" display="no">O'Donnell</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="240">Paraguay on Shannon</ref>.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
