<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[315] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 24 communicants.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation at Mattins, but it was more than commonly <hi rend="underline">feminine</hi>. <persName xml:id="122">Hine–Haycock</persName> intoned the service, and assisted at the celebration. I preached and celebrated.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1300" display="no">Merton</persName> and <persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName> came to lunch.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="1601">Bishop of Pretoria</persName>, whom I knew well 21 years since as Carter of the Eton Mission, came to see me this afternoon.</p>
         <p>At Evensong there was a fair congregation. I preached on the 'Love of Money'. Aiken–Sneath intoned the service.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="560">Admiral</persName>, <persName xml:id="121">Custard</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1462">Denham</persName> came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[316]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Lectures at Yale are fixed for the following dates:–</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Wednesday, April 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Friday, April 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Monday, April 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Wednesday, April 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Friday, April 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Monday, May 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Wednesday, May 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
            </item>
            <item>Friday, May 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>Preaching pledges as follows:–</p>
         <p>April 25. Preach at Yale.</p>
         <p>? May 2. Preach at Harvard.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[317]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>On Tuesday and Wednesday (May 19 &amp; 20) I sat daily from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. in the <placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName> working at the revision of the Prayer–book. We did not make very much progress.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday night I travelled by the express from King's Cross to Edinburgh, arriving to the minute. I drove along Prince's Street to 39 Palmerston Place, admiring the beauty of the scene.</p>
         <p>After breakfast mine host &amp; I walked to the <placeName xml:id="32">Assembly Hall</placeName>, and attended the opening of the proceedings.  <hi rend="bold underline">The new Moderator, </hi><persName xml:id="1606"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Theodore Marshall</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, is a fine figure of a man</hi>, &amp; fulfils his duties with dignity.  I slipped away, under <persName xml:id="1765" display="no">Reid's</persName> guidance, to pay visits of courtesy to the rival Assemblies.  The <orgName xml:id="118">U.Fs</orgName> have a fine Hall, &amp; conduct their business with gravity.  The members have the aspect of earnest &amp; even enthusiastic men: but <hi rend="bold underline">the <orgName xml:id="86">'Wee Frees'</orgName> are a horde of squalid savages</hi>.  The discussions on the claims of individuals seeking admission to the Ministry of the Scottish Church were keen, &amp; interesting: but they left me wondering what might be their value to the Church, &amp; what risk they implied of grave wrong to individuals.  As a court for judging heresy I cannot think a numerous Assembly to be satisfactory.  In this respect our Erastian tribunals are better constituted.  <persName xml:id="1027" display="no">Fleming</persName> took me off to lunch at his club.  <persName xml:id="1604">Sir Ralph Anstruther</persName> <hi rend="bold">[318]</hi> [symbol] was of the party.  I prepared his two daughters for Confirmation, but had never met him.  The U.Fs spent the afternoon in debating their disestablishment policy.  Many unwise &amp; uncharitable things were said, but the division showed that the party of strife is waning.  For no more than 380 voted for the resolution, &amp; no less than 167 voted against it.  The bulk of the assembly abstained from voting.</p>
         <p>The next day (Friday, May 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>) we went to the U.F. Moderator's breakfast in the Music Hall. The proceedings began with prayers &amp;c, &amp; after breakfast, there were some short speeches. I had to speak briefly. The main part of the day in the General Assembly of the Est<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Church was filled with the Reunion debate, to which the proceedings overnight in the rival assembly added zest.  An excellent speech was made by <persName xml:id="1524">Norman M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Leod</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1140">Prof. Patterson</persName> spoke on the same side. A venomous–looking man named <persName xml:id="1610" display="no">Wane</persName> did all the mischief he could on the other side, &amp; was seconded by a strange–looking fanatic called <persName xml:id="1605" display="no">Sutherland</persName>, but <persName xml:id="1183">Lord Balfour</persName> spoke effectively, &amp; in the end they were shown to be but a fraction of the Assembly. Later in the day there was an Appeal &amp; Petition from a lady &amp; her son on the subject of unfermented wine in the Holy Com<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>, they being strong tee–totallers, &amp; conscientiously unable to communicate like ordinary Christians!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[310]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="491">Lady Frances Balfour</persName>, <persName xml:id="1751" display="no">Col. Burn</persName>, <persName xml:id="1495">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1758">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Scott</persName>, and a parson from the Shetland Islands dined.  I found Col. Burn's conversation most interesting. He was a friend of <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName>, who asked him to go to India as his military secretary.  He had raised &amp; commanded a regiment in the Boer War.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">Lady F.B. tells me that <persName xml:id="1525">Cooper</persName> murmurs against my admission to the Assembly, &amp; that the </hi><persName xml:id="345"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord High Com</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> inquires anxiously whether I am 'sound'!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> May, I got up betimes, and went for a walk along Prince's street before breakfast.  The loveliness of Edinburgh filled my eyes &amp; stamped itself on my mind.  The green turf, through which the dark rock pushes in naked wedges which cast fantastic shadows, is wonderful.  The gardens brilliant with flower–beds form a splendid foreground: &amp; the line of buildings along the crest of the hill, though hardly including a single notable fabric, are yet by some happy instinct of grouping combined into an effect, at once dignified &amp; romantic.  In truth I am altogether in love with <term xml:id="43">'Auld Reekie'</term>.  There was not much of importance stirring in the Assembly.  Delegates from the Churches in England attended,<hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; some kindly references were made to me</hi>.  I observed with some interest that they confessed resentment at the exclusive attitude of the Church of England and some consciousness of pressure from the Dissenters to take sides against that church.  In the afternoon I listened to the 'Scottish <persName xml:id="1508">Kensit</persName>', the <persName xml:id="1752">Rev. Jacob Primmer</persName>, <hi rend="bold">[320] </hi>[symbol] who attended at the bar of the house to prosecute an appeal, or rather two appeals, against the action of the Presbytery of Edinboro.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">The man is a short, stout, bearded creature, with a loud voice &amp; a ribald wit, not dissimilar to our Kensit, with whom he is naturally compared.</hi><hi rend="italic">  He was listened to with much gravity, and his appeal dismissed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then I attended the reception of the Moderator's lady, which rather bored me.  After this, mine host took me to the Grass market, and then to the Grey Friars Churchyard <hi rend="bold underline">where is the Memorial to the Covenanting Martyrs who – to the number of 18000 as the inscription affirms, though I suspect that most of these fell in battle as rebels – were martyred during the reign of the restored Stuarts, 1661–1688</hi>.  In this churchyard are gathered many sepulchral monuments of Scottish families – monstrous erections at once sinfully proud &amp; woefully ugly.  <persName xml:id="1753">Alexander Henderson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1754">William Carstares</persName> were side by side.  Here also I came upon the tombs of <persName xml:id="112">my wife's</persName> ancestors – the Dennistouns of Dennistoun.  <hi rend="italic">This churchyard seemed a revelation of Scottish character, in which individualism is so marked a feature, that it shapes the very fashion of their sepulchres.  Moreover it threw light on the sectarian divisions of Scotland.  As they will not lie side by side in a cemetery but must needs build </hi><hi rend="italic underline">walls</hi><hi rend="italic"> round their several graves, so will they not worship together, but must needs have as many churches as worshippers!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[321] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>In the evening we dined at <placeName xml:id="27">Holyrood</placeName>.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="234">Lloyd–George</persName>, who is here for a Licensing–Bill demonstration, was one of the guests. I got a few words with him on the Education question: he seemed the reverse of optimistic</hi>. My friend, <persName xml:id="1221">Miss Jean Bruce</persName>, had arranged that I should take her in to dinner, so that I was quite happy in that matter. Indeed she was so gracious as to get her Grace's permission to carry me off to the private apartments, &amp; show me the quaint pictures of the child Mary, &amp; the child her son. The latter represents the boy kneeling at prayer with a company of nobles.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Sunday, the 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> May, I <listEvent><event xml:id="78">preached</event></listEvent> in S. George's</hi>. There was a large &amp; very attentive congregation. Afterwards I lunched with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott, &amp; met <persName xml:id="1759">Prof. Kay</persName> (Prof. of Hebrew at S. Andrew's).  Then I returned to mine host.  At tea–time there came in <persName xml:id="1760" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Caie</persName>, the minister of S. Matthew's, Morningside, where I had arranged to preach.  This arrangement was duly carried into effect.  The Church, which is handsome and commodious, was crowded to excess; &amp; the attention was excellent.  The elders came in to the vestry afterwards, &amp; thanked me.  <hi rend="bold underline">At supper, Prof. Paterson &amp; Prof. Kay came in, and we had much &amp; pleasant conversation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  Assuredly there is good stuff in this <orgName xml:id="100" display="no">Church of Scotland</orgName>, &amp; we of the English Church are great fools not to get on terms with it, &amp; to have its support in the ill times which are coming upon us.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[322]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>On Monday, the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of May, I attended the Moderator's breakfast at the North British Hotel.  The Moderator himself took Miss Jean Bruce, &amp; left me to solace myself with <persName xml:id="1777" display="no">Miss Dalrymple</persName>, who proved a cheerful &amp; amiable companion.</p>
         <p>The proceedings at the Assembly, were neither uninteresting nor unimportant. In the forenoon, an hour was spent discussing the 'form of process'. The presbyteries are responsible for maintaining good discipline within their bounds: but this involves an indefensible combination in the same hands of the functions of prosecutor &amp; judge. A motion was made limiting their duty to the preliminary inquiries, &amp; providing for the reference of a case certified by them to be judicable to some central court for judgement. This however, was rejected in favour of a milder proposal.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I was hospitably given lunch by <persName xml:id="1138">Fisher</persName> in his club, &amp; with us came also the redoubtable <persName xml:id="1525">Prof. Cooper</persName>. He spoke incessantly of the extreme value of daily services, &amp; public catechisnig [sic], so that there was no need for me to say anything, whereby doubtless friction was averted.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On returning to the Assembly, I found that the Formula debate had just begun. By an overwhelming majority the Presbyteries had rejected the new formula proposed to them at the last General Assembly. Five new formulas were proposed, &amp; all were rejected. Finally, on the motion of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott, supported by Prof. Paterson, the whole<hi rend="bold"> [323]</hi> [symbol] subject was referred to a Committee, with instructions to bring it forward again next year.  <persName xml:id="1761">Warr</persName>, the minister of Rosneath, moved the abandonment of the whole matter for the time being; &amp; he led into the lobby 103 members of Assembly, but he spake without conviction &amp; without impressiveness, &amp; his following was mainly made up of the opponents of all change.</p>
         <p>One old man – <persName xml:id="1762" display="no">Gillan</persName> – made quite a moving speech against any alteration of the existing formula: his speech, though plainly counter to the sentiments of the House, was greatly applauded.  The Committee received 237 votes.  It is evident that no more than half the members were in attendance.  </p>
         <p>Then I attended a meeting in the 'Edinburgh Café' to promote a monument commemorating <persName xml:id="930">Calvin</persName>, whose 'quarter–centenary' occurs next year. Patterson spoke admirably. I moved a vote of thanks to <persName xml:id="1387">Lord K.</persName> for presiding. Finally we attended the reception at Holyrood. There was a fearful crush, and I was rather bored especially as I failed to discover Miss J. Bruce until just when we were going off. She introduced me to her <persName xml:id="1763">brother</persName>, a soldier quartered at Stirling. We got our carriage after some delay, &amp; reached home about 20 minutes before midnight.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[324]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, May 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1908, I attended the session of the Assembly in the forenoon, &amp; was rewarded by hearing an admirable speech from <persName xml:id="1139">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wallace Williamson</persName>, the junior minister of S. Cuthbert's.  He was seconding the Report of the <orgName xml:id="117" display="no">Home Missions Committee</orgName>, which had been moved in a rather declamatory speech by <persName xml:id="1766">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Martin</persName>, the minister of the Barony Church, Glasgow.  Of both these speeches it must be said that they belonged rather to the type which we associate with a public meeting than with that which we should think proper to a deliberative body.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1765" display="no">Cameron Reid</persName> took me to see the portraits (engravings and photographs) of the Moderators from <persName xml:id="1768">George Buchanan</persName> until this present time. From the reverential way in which these portraits had been spoken of by several Members of the Assembly, I expected a series of oil paintings, such as that of the Deans of Canterbury preserved in the Deanery there: &amp; I was inwardly amused at the spectacle of a set of prints &amp; photographs such as many an English incumbent collects of his predecessors in his course. It was one more evidence of the patriotic megalomania thro' which the Scotch see everything Scottish! After lunch Reid &amp; I went to the Scottish National Exhibition, where we looked at the pictures. There are many excellent portraits by <persName xml:id="1770">Raeburn</persName>.  In the industrial section who sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> we run into but Miss J. Bruce with a gay party from Holyrood?  Returning to Edinburgh I made early purchases, &amp; then went to dine with <persName xml:id="936">W. Forrest</persName>, <hi rend="bold">[325] </hi>a learned pundit of the U. F. Church, who is just back from Palestine. Then I 'took up my carriages', &amp; made tracks for the Waverly Station, where I caught the night express for King's Cross.</p>
         <p>On Ascension Day May 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1908, I preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 11 a.m: and then went off to Lowestoft, and <listEvent><event xml:id="79">preached</event></listEvent> there.  I stayed the night with <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1771">Tupper Carey</persName>, the Rector</hi>; and on Friday morning made the round of the docks, &amp; watched the fishermen discharging their catch on the quays, where it was rapidly sold by auction. In the afternoon, I returned to Westminster.</p>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
