<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[286]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1907 [sic].</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A calm, cold, bright morning after the rain. I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> more than commonly depressed by the sense of the failure of my ministry to individuals. The Epistle &amp; Gospel accorded well with the mood of melancholy, and deepened it. "Lest when I have preached to others I myself should be a castaway'. 'Many be called but few chosen'. There were but 17 communicants in all.</p>
         <p>The congregation at 11 a.m. was not large: but it included the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName>, <persName xml:id="539">Alfred Lyttelton</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="344">Sir H. Craik</persName>. I <ref xml:id="434">preached</ref> from a favourite Pauline text &#8211; "Take thought for things honourable in the sight of all men". In the course of my sermon I referred to the <orgName xml:id="56">Salvation Army's</orgName> neglect of <persName xml:id="1272" display="no">Manson's</persName> <ref xml:id="177">book</ref> as an illustration of a breach of the Apostle's rule.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> &amp; I went in a taximeter cab to the <orgName xml:id="65">Leysian Mission</orgName>, where I <listEvent><event xml:id="48">lectured</event></listEvent> for 3/4 hour on "Other&#8211;worldism" to a large &amp; (on the whole) appreciative set of men.</p>
         <p>I preached again at Evensong.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[287]</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Feb. 17, 1908.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear <persName xml:id="601">Sir Kenneth</persName>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> &amp; I will be very pleased that <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> stay here while he prepares for his exam</hi><hi rend="i sup u">n</hi><hi rend="italic">, always provided that the time is well mapped out &amp; sufficiently filled to prevent the danger of his being at a loose end. I am personally too much pressed with work to be able to undertake any burden of supervision in that regard, &amp; of course I know nothing about the work itself. We do both of us really want to see him started fairly: &amp; will gladly co&#8211;operate to that end as far as we can.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Yours ever,</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">H. H. H.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
