<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[326]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. and asked for prayers on behalf of <persName xml:id="456">Blackmore</persName> who is reported gravely ill.</p>
         <p>At Matins there was a large congregation but no <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName>.  I preached on the Gospel for the day, <hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; made some allusion to the unhappy incident in India where the <persName xml:id="1692">Bishop of Lahore</persName> refused the consecrated garrison church to the Presbyterian soldiers for Holy Communion</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <persName xml:id="1139"><hi rend="italic"> D</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Wallace Williamson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> was in church; he came in to the vestry afterwards.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the afternoon I went to the <orgName xml:id="116">Stockwell Training College</orgName> for women teachers, &amp; <listEvent><event xml:id="73">addressed</event></listEvent> the students, who are leaving. They asked the Principal (<persName xml:id="1694" display="no">Miss Manly</persName>) to ask me. The college is undenominational, but seemed very Christian.</p>
         <p>The congregation at Evensong was not over large. I noticed <persName xml:id="42">Steel&#8211;Maitland</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="701">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>The collections at all services were given to the Pan&#8211;Anglican Thankoffering.<note xml:id="79" display="no" n="1"></note> They reached the modest sum of rather more than &#x00A3;36.!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[327] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Monday, the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> of June, 1908, <persName xml:id="1269">Lord Montgomerie</persName> was married to <persName xml:id="1270">Lady Susan Dalrymple</persName>. I gave an address. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wallace Williamson came to lunch.  <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> came also.  I dined with the <orgName xml:id="66">Brotherhood</orgName> at <persName xml:id="249">Gamble's</persName> House.  About 10.30 p.m. there was a thunderstorm.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> of June, 1908, <persName xml:id="372">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Reginald M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Kenna</persName> the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> Lord of the Admiralty, was married to <persName xml:id="852">Pamella Jekyll</persName>.  He was 44: she was 19.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Thursday, the 4</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="italic">of June, 1908 the annual <term xml:id="37">Vestry</term> was held. Everybody was re&#8211;elected: all things going with the fatuous tranquillity of utter &amp; self&#8211;conscious unreality! Later in the day, Blackmore died at Hindhead. He sank under the effects of a severe operation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went to Birchington.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
