<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[330]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Twenty one years since my Ordination at Cuddesdon on June 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1887.  It is a melancholy retrospect of fault and failure, &amp; what do I take from it today but <persName xml:id="1460">Matt. Arnold's</persName> <ref xml:id="207">bitter summary</ref> of disillusionment – <quote>'the sick fatigue, the languid doubt, Which much to have tried, in much baffled brings'</quote>?  Spiritually what is the aspect of these years of ministry?  To me at least it is a very Baruch roll unfolded before my memory.  <quote>''Thou knowest, Lord, the secrets of our hearts; shut not thine Ears to our prayer''</quote>.</p>
         <p>I celebrated in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi></orgName> at 8 a.m.: there were 25 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, including my <persName xml:id="1608">guest</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Signorina</persName>.</p>
         <p>At Matins there was a very large congregation, obviously composed in no slight measure of <orgName xml:id="94">Pan–Anglican</orgName> delegates.  I preached on Isaiah's Vision, but with much difficulty from hoarseness.  <hi rend="bold underline">The speech yesterday was a mistake.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="227">Willie Murray</persName> was in church, and came in to lunch. At Evensong the Nave of the Abbey was crowded, the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName>, <persName xml:id="296">Sub–Dean</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> were present. I preached for 50 minutes on <ref xml:id="332">'Anglicanism &amp; Reunion'</ref>, and 'liberated my soul' on the subject of 'the Historic Episcopate'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[331] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Pan–Anglican Congress began its sessions with an Intercession Service in the Abbey. There was an ill–attended 'over–flow' service in S. Margaret's at the same time.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday morning I read a short &amp; mild paper on <listEvent><event xml:id="75">''Essentials &amp; Non–essentials''</event></listEvent>.</p>
         <p>We entertained the lay delegate of the diocese of Fredericton, New Brunswick, <persName xml:id="1609" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Hannington</persName>.  Also the <persName xml:id="1608">Bishop of North Dakota</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1607" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mann</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Thursday's ''Times'' contained a long letter from Turner, signed ''C. H. T.'', &amp; headed <ref xml:id="208">''Canon Henson &amp; Episcopacy''</ref>, which impugned my statements as to the verdicts of historical students as to the origin of the Episcopate. I replied in a short <ref xml:id="209">letter</ref>, which appeared on Friday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Very unfortunately I contracted a chill on Wednesday which placed me <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="36">hors de combat</term></hi> for all effective purposes.</p>
         <p> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
