<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[358]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet &amp; chilly morning. I wrote to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>. We went to the parish church, &amp; heard a characteristic discourse from <persName xml:id="1637" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Donaldson</persName>, the parish minister.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1644" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1645" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Douglas</persName> came to lunch: afterwards mine host, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Douglas, &amp; I walked over the estate; they discussing divers questions of local arboriculture; &amp; I listening to their talk not without disinterested interest.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Monday, the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> Sept.</hi> was a persistently wet day.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Tuesday, the 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> Sept.</hi> Wet from start to finish: yet our hosts motored us to Craigenputtock, the house <hi rend="bold">[359] </hi>to which <persName xml:id="495">Carlyle</persName> brought his <persName xml:id="1639">wife</persName>, after their marriage. It is an unpretending stone–built two–storied farm–house, far away in the moors, most solitary. <persName xml:id="1640" display="no">Miss Carlyle</persName>, a niece of the philosopher, lives in the house, which she shows to visitors without charge. The sitting–room was adorned with sundry prints illustrating the history of <persName xml:id="1641" display="no">Frederick the Great</persName>, and annotated by the sage. The small apartment adjoining was that in which <ref xml:id="253">'Sartor Resartus'</ref> was written.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Wednesday, the 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> Sept. 1908</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet night led in a wet morning<hi rend="bold">.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the time in writing a <ref xml:id="254">letter</ref> to the 'Times' commenting on two subtly written letters on the <ref xml:id="244">'Episcopate &amp; Home Reunion'</ref> signed 'Principal of a Theological College'.</hi>  I think I detect the hand of <persName xml:id="1451">Johnston</persName> of Cuddesdon.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon we had a run in the motor.</p>
         <p>There dined <persName xml:id="1638" display="no">Miss Clark</persName>, a local proprietor, &amp; the Episcopalian minister from Annan.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Thursday, the 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> Sept. 1908</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Another wet day, wet until about 4 p.m. We travelled to Selkirk via Carlisle &amp; Galashiels, arriving in Broadmeadows at tea time. On the way I bought the 'Times', &amp; read the report of the death of <persName xml:id="749">Prebendary Montagu Villiers</persName>. There are now two important West End churches vacant, both I think in the gift of the <persName xml:id="1167">Bishop of Lincoln</persName>.</p>
         <p></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
