<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[304]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The <persName xml:id="509">Prime Minister</persName> has resigned, and the King has sent for <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>. I met <persName xml:id="645">Ilbert</persName>; and he said that the House was to be adjourned pending a re&#8211;ordering of the Ministry.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I am in the prophetic vein; and I foretell that Asquith's accession to power will mean further calamity to whatsoever relics of liberty linger in the Church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">He is known to be an advocate of Disestablishment, he is believed to be friendly to the High Church faction: he is committed to a Licencing Bill &amp; Old Age Pensions, projects in which the sacerdotalist fanaticks will support him. I believe he will favour them in his eccl</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">l</hi><hi rend="italic"> appointments; encouraging the futile cry for "autonomy"; treating the Church as an episcopalian sect: and moving towards Disestablishment with the aid of the High Church Party.  I look to see the Education Bill dropped, &amp; replaced with something on <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> lines.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Personally this gives the coup&#8211;de&#8211;gr&#x00E2;ce to my attempt to galvanize our Establishment into a working system</hi><hi rend="i bold">.  </hi><hi rend="italic">"Denominationalism" i.e. the spirit of sect reigns.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[305]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There were two 'Memorial Services' in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> this week. On Thursday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April, for the <persName xml:id="1600">Hon. R. Greville</persName>, and on Saturday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, for <persName xml:id="1598">Sir Howard Vincent</persName>. To the latter a large number of the <orgName xml:id="70">Queen's Westminsters</orgName> came in uniform.</p>
         <p>At 3 p.m. on Saturday I baptized <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1599">Peter Limond Derville Teichmann</persName></hi>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
