<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[277]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A cold fog came down upon us as the hour for Church service drew on, and, taking the local defilements in its descent, had grown into a dark &amp; smoky mantle of vapour by the time the service had started. Accordingly there was but a scanty congregation in the Abbey, with an unusual amount of coughing. I <ref xml:id="419">preached</ref> on Isaiah LV. 4, 8, making my text a peg to hang some observations on Foreign Missions upon. This Sunday had been set apart for sermons throughout the Rural Deanery of Westminster on that subject, to pave the way for the <orgName xml:id="94">Pan&#8211;Anglican Congress</orgName>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName> preached in the Abbey at 3 p.m.  As we were going in to the service we <hi rend="bold underline">encountered <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1316" display="no">Miss Tennant</persName>. He told me that the <persName xml:id="1190">Attorney General</persName>, whose death was announced yesterday, was only ill 36 hours</hi>. Gamble is a good preacher, but more 'popular' than I had supposed.</p>
         <p>There was a fair congregation in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at Evensong, when I <listEvent><event xml:id="45">preached</event></listEvent> again in the Missionary Congress.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1255">Signorina</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[278]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On S. Paul's Day <persName xml:id="1218">Ridgeway</persName> was consecrated in the Abbey as Bishop of Chichester.  I attended the service, and made a point of shaking hands with him, &amp; wishing him well.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> preached a sermon marked by great plainness of speech. He swept away with proper decision the apostolic succession fiction: &amp; spoke wholesome words as to the impropriety of the prattling habit of our present bishops, &amp; the duty of episcopal silence</hi>.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I taught <persName xml:id="1317" display="no">Miss Dorothy May</persName> for an hour with a view to her Confirmation: &amp; later I went in to <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> to inquire as to <persName xml:id="816">Cuthbert's</persName> breaking his leg at football.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
