<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[380]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                             </p>
         <p>I returned to Westminster by the 10.41 a.m. express, and got in to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> in good time for lunch.  At 3 p.m. I attended Evensong in the Abbey; &amp; after service picked up <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1826">Durward Moffatt</persName></hi>, aged 17, a lad whose devoutness had arrested my notice. He says that I picked up his <persName xml:id="1827">brother</persName> some while since, and showed him all over the Church.</p>
         <p>I dined with <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName> at the <orgName xml:id="109">Old University Club</orgName> in Suffolk Street.  <persName xml:id="1008">Simon</persName>, <persName xml:id="1828">Robinson</persName>, <persName xml:id="324">Amery</persName>, <persName xml:id="1427">Baker&#8211;Wilbraham</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="132">Liddell</persName> completed the party.  We had a great discussion over (&#x3B1;) Chinese labour: (&#x3B2;) the Licensing Bill.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Robinson</hi> says that the general depression of trade in South Africa has put out of employment a great number of natives: that these have been flocking to the mines; and that therefore the places of the Chinese have for the time being been filled: but that this will not continue to be possible when the return of normal prosperity sets in, of which there are already signs:  &amp; that that then the need of labour at the mines will again become acute.  He also said that the notion that the Chinese would degrade morally the natives of South Africa was absurd; the said natives being already addicted to the "Chinese" vices.  He says that <persName xml:id="311">Lord Selborne's</persName> ready piety takes on greatly with the Boers: but that they hoodwink him to their hearts' content.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[381] </hi>[symbol] </p>
         <p>On Saturday, <hi rend="underline">the 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="underline"> of Oct. 1908</hi>, I went out for a short walk after Evensong, and when half way over Westminster Bridge, <hi rend="bold underline">fell in with the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>, who asked me to walk across to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> with him. He started at once on the Education question, &amp; said that he was in good hope of reaching a settlement</hi>.  He had agreed on terms with <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="990">Runciman</persName> which would infuriate the sections of opinion represented by the <persName xml:id="49">Bps. of Birmingham</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="242">Manchester</persName>, by <persName xml:id="1748">Lord Halifax</persName> &amp; the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName>, &amp; by <persName xml:id="314">Lord Hugh Cecil</persName>.  He thought that the support of the <persName xml:id="166">Bps. of London</persName>, <persName xml:id="105">Southwark</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="130">Stepney</persName> might be secured: &amp; he was very anxious that when the new proposals were made public <hi rend="bold underline">the first opinions in favour of them sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> come from the orthodox camp.  His meaning was, of course, obvious</hi>, that he hoped <hi rend="doubleunderline">I</hi>, being <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="29">persona ingratissima</term></hi> to the clergy should not appear on his side!  I told him that my single aim was to secure a reasonable settlement, that I should always be particularly glad to find myself conscientiously able to support him, that he need never fear my being offended by any hint of his personal wishes: but I confess my scepticism as to the possibility of proposing a <hi rend="underline">reasonable</hi> scheme, which shall secure the support of the Bishops of London, Southwark, &amp; Stepney.  This is a singular side&#8211;light on the solitude in which I stand in the Church of England.</p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[382] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Saturday is our day of calamity. So once again. <persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> had convened some neighbour's girls for a Hallow E'en Party, &amp; the fun was about to begin when a telegram arrived from <persName xml:id="1844" display="no">Miss Smith</persName> ("Cousin Helen") in these terms:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>'Your <persName xml:id="584">father</persName> taken stroke at Kempsey four miles from Worcester taken to doctor's house I am with him and got a nurse.'</item>
         </list>
         <p>A telegram inquiring whether immediate presence was desired drew an answer summoning Ella to go forthwith. So arrangements were hurried on for her departure by the 7.30 p.m. from Paddington. The maidens were dismissed as early as possible, &amp; then we went to the station, where we parted. <persName xml:id="556">Jim Dennistoun</persName> is due to arrive from India next Thursday. It had been arranged that he with his father &amp; sister should motor to Rome, but that arrangement must be cancelled in view of this untoward event.</p>
         <p>My wife's <persName xml:id="828">Mother</persName> died on July 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905.  It would be rather sad if Jim returned to England to find himself bereft of <hi rend="underline">both</hi> his parents.</p>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
