<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[403]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The 'Times' announces the death of the <persName xml:id="32">Bishop of Colchester</persName></hi>. It is just 20 years since I made his acquaintance when I became Vicar of Barking. He was then Archdeacon of Essex. <persName xml:id="181">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Johnson</persName> died a few days before her husband.  My last sight of them both was on October 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> when I attended the <orgName xml:id="126">Diocesan Conference</orgName> at Chelmsford, &amp; went round to the Rectory during the Luncheon Hour.  <hi rend="bold underline">He was extremely kind to me, but our intimacy never really survived my open association with the <orgName xml:id="84">Broad Church Party</orgName>: nor did I easily pardon his action in bringing <persName xml:id="1792">Eisdell</persName> to Barking, an appointment which I resented as a job</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="301">Winfred Burrows</persName></hi> has declined the Abpk. of Capetown.  I understand that the post has now been offered to the <persName xml:id="625">Bp. of Ipswich</persName>; &amp; that he will decline it.  There is only an increase of £1000: and a necessary expenditure of at least twice that amount.</p>
        
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[404] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>This week has been mainly wasted in attending the meetings of the <orgName xml:id="85">'Letters of Business' Committee</orgName> on Wednesday, Thursday, &amp; Friday. We had before us the record of the <orgName xml:id="90" display="no">Lower House C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi></orgName> for York: this is on the whole more sacerdotalist than we.  Especially on the subject of the Athanasian Creed, the Yorkists recommend that the Rubric be left unaltered.  The <persName xml:id="44">Dean of Westminster</persName> moved to acquiesce in this, merely adding a resolution affirming the desirableness of giving power to the Ordinary to dispense the priest from saying the Creed.  <hi rend="bold underline">I resisted this motion strenuously, &amp; it was finally rejected by 8 votes to 6.  There is clearly a reaction in favour of 'orthodoxy' proceeding everywhere.  </hi>
         </p><p>
         <hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="1083">Loisy's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"><ref xml:id="261">"Quelques Lettres sur des Questions actuelles et sur des événements recents"</ref> arrived, &amp; I fell at once to reading it. The extreme interest of Loisy's letters cannot conceal the intrinsic indefensibleness of his positions.</hi></p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="325">Bishop of Winchester</persName> called on Saturday to ask me about <persName xml:id="297">Bainbridge</persName>, to whom he meditates offering the post of Suffragan Bishopric, vacated by <persName xml:id="1793">Boutflower's</persName> departure to Japan.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="3560">George Dennistoun</persName> came to stay from Saturday to Monday.</p>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
