<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[413]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I had caught cold in the Cloisters talking to the <persName xml:id="296">Sub&#8211;Dean</persName> after the Carol Service on Boxing Day. Accordingly I was not equal to getting out for the early service, &amp; sent a message to <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> saying so.</p>
         <p>The weather was very cold &amp; there was a sprinkling of snow.  At Mattins a very small congregation, but unusually <hi rend="underline">masculine</hi>. I <ref xml:id="601">preached</ref> with difficulty. Offertory under &#x00A3;8.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="556">Jim Dennistoun</persName></hi> went off in his motor after service.</p>
         <p>At Evensong the congregation was very small, and the Offertory duly expressed the fact, being only about half the normal amount.  I preached the sermon which last year was delivered in the Abbey.  After service the choir sang four carols.  <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="468">George Rudge</persName></hi> came into the vestry:  he is becoming very fat, so much so that at first I failed to recognize him.  Evidently the feeding at ''Commercial Hotel'' is something more than sufficient.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="922">Waggett</persName></hi>, whom I met on my way home, stopped to express his approval of my sermon on ''Judgement'' &#8211; presumably that which I preached on December 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[414]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The cold which I contracted in the cloisters after the Carol singing on Boxing Day developed quickly into quite a considerable discomfort, which destroyed all possibility of work for the week. It was aggravated by the vagaries of the weather. A great snow&#8211;storm on Monday was followed by bitter cold for two days, and then by a rapid thaw which had removed all traces of snow before the end of the week.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Monday was the date of the greatest earthquake on record. Messina &amp; Regis &#8211; two populous cities &#8211; were completely destroyed;</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the death&#8211;roll is estimated to exceed 200,000.  An estimate in the 'Westminster Gazette' sets the material damage at &#x00A3;140,000,000.<note xml:id="91" display="no" n="1"></note>  The whole civilized world is offering help: &amp; the efforts at rescue have been splendid.  Thus a gilding of heroism is visible on the disastrous cloud.  ''What is man, that Thou art mindful of him?''</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On New Year's Day, 1909, the Abbey Choirboys came for their annual party. The new Master &#8211; <persName xml:id="1570" display="no">Davis</persName> &#8211; came with them. He is evidently a capable &amp; cheery little man &#8211; <persName xml:id="18">Gerald</persName>, looking more spectral than ever, came with his treasury of toys.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
