<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[389]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull, raw morning. There were 31 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> at 8 a.m.  The congregation at Mattins was small, restless, &amp; noisy: the offertory only about &#x00A3;12.  I read the letter about 'Personal Service among the Poor' from the pulpit, &amp; recommended it: but, in that atmosphere of inattention, it could not possibly have any good effect.  Oh!</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I went with <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName> to the Hoxton Wesleyan men's meeting, where I <listEvent><event xml:id="71">descanted</event></listEvent> for 35 minutes to about 100 men in the Chapel on the subject of 'Forgiveness'. It was a chilling performance: &amp; I think the men were as tired of it as I was.</p>
         <p>The congregation at Evensong was fairly good, but still disposed to cough. I continued my sermon on 'Forgiveness', dealing rather with the practical applications of the Christian doctrine.  On the whole this has been a <hi rend="underline">bad day</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[390]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
         <div type="letter">
<hi rend="italic">November 16</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1908</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I must send you the assurance of my very sincere good wishes for your success in the best sense of the term in this great place.  I am, of course, surprised that you go </hi><hi rend="italic underline">straight</hi><hi rend="italic"> to an archbishoprick: I expected that you would have gone via a bishoprick.  But you are too meteoric for precedent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I am sorry, of course, very sorry that you are so stiff a High Churchman</hi><hi rend="italic">: but on that score, your way in the Church will be the easier. You will have many large questions to answer. May God give you grace to answer them in a large way!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours aff.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. Hensley Henson.</hi>
         </div>
         </p>
         <p>The above was written to Lang on reading the announcement of his promotion to the Archbishopric of York.</p>
         <p>How far does this sensational appointment confirm my prophecy (v. p.304)? The new Primate of England will be received with enthusiasm by the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName>, and the 'Church Times'.	   </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
