<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[393]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> and I walked in the Park during the forenoon.  <hi rend="bold underline">He wrote to the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> protesting against the appointment of <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName> to lecture in the Abbey on 'The Church &amp; the Ministry' during Advent, since everybody knows that he is 'the Principal of a Theological College', with whom I had some controversy last September in the columns of the 'Times'. (v. 359).<note xml:id="88" n="1"></note></hi>  His appearance in the Abbey pulpit could not but be understood as an insult to me of the most hurtful kind imaginable.  <hi rend="bold underline">Last night I received from the Dean an 'explanation', which indeed did not greatly improve matters</hi>.  He had decided not to give the lectures <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="28">in propr&icirc;a person&#x00E2;</term></hi> to avoid the appearance of attacking me; but had asked Headlam to do so in his place, because he supposed that his anonymity in the Times had been preserved, &amp; because he shared Headlam's views.  I briefly acknowledged the letter, &amp; begged him to make no further reference to the subject.  So my suspicions were well&#8211;founded: <hi rend="bold underline">the Dean's far&#8211;published liberalism in Eccles</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">l</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> questions was an affair of well&#8211;turned phrases, not of principle.  After more than 40 years of liberalism the Abbey, so far as its Dean can secure, becomes one more citadel of the reigning sacerdotalism!  How the fanaticks will exult!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
