<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[373]</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. There were 28 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> including <persName xml:id="1922">Geake</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1923">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> was in his place at Mattins; but the attendance of members was lamentably small. However the congregation was fairly good, &amp; the offertory exceeded &#x00A3;20. <persName xml:id="633">Sir Henry Graham</persName> was in Church. I preached about social duty from the words in the Gospel for S. Luke's Day <ref xml:id="597">'The Labourer is worthy of his hire'</ref>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> <persName xml:id="1862">Bonney</persName></hi> preached in the Abbey, and after service came in to lunch &#8211; a pleasant, &amp; well informed man ready to talk of what he knows, and able to talk well.</p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation in the Abbey at 3 p.m. when I preached on 'The one thing needful'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="898">Peile</persName></hi> preached at 7 p.m. to another great congregation.  He has an excellent voice &amp; manages it excellently.  His sermon was well composed &amp; well&#8211;delivered: but too lop&#8211;sided in its emphasis.  The situation of Christianity at the present time was described too darkly for a general congregation, &amp; the consolatory tail&#8211;piece of the discourse was too brief to correct the melancholy impression created by the bulk of it.  The time&#8211;limits of modern preaching are so narrow that lop&#8211;sidedness is one of the most difficult of faults for the preacher to avoid.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[374]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This week (Oct: 19&#8211;24) has slipped by very resultlessly. Monday was wasted in preparing the constitutional case with <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>. Tuesday, Wednesday, &amp; Thursday were filled with the attempt to collect materials for a sermon on 'Reserve', which I meditate delivering at Cambridge. On Saturday morning there was a memorial service for <persName xml:id="1924">Sir John Puleston</persName> in S. Margaret's. I managed to revise &amp; partially rewrite two sermons for next Sunday.</p>
         <p>The <orgName xml:id="103">S. Margaret's Guild</orgName> made its new start on Wednesday, the 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st </hi> Oct.  About 40 members turned up, &amp; the new secretaries, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> and <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, entered on office.  I took for the subject of an address, the Worship of Christ in the Eucharist.  This seemed likely to be serviceable in view of the general disturbance of religious notions induced by the Papists in connection with the Eucharistic Congress.</p>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
