<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[391]	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1908.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather changed last night: &amp; this morning we find ourselves back again in the high temperature.  By consequence I am languid &amp; listless &#8211; the negation of devoutness.  Why should one's spirit respond with such fatal alacrity to the impressions of one's physical conditions?  But this was the least of the circumstances which spoiled my worship at the Eucharist.  <hi rend="bold underline">My thoughts play round the appointment to York, &amp; always arrive at a more depressing conclusion with respect to it.</hi>  The <hi rend="underline">right</hi> side in that Province will be presented to the public view in the hopeless &amp; tactless <persName xml:id="1132">Straton</persName> of Newcastle: the <hi rend="underline">wrong</hi> side in the charming young Daniel come&#8211;to&#8211;judgement unmarried Primate! In the southern Province we can hardly be said to have <hi rend="underline">any</hi> representation left of the right side.  Episcopalianism (i.e. the spirit of sacerdotalist sectarianism) reigns: for the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> has no courage: &amp; the <persName xml:id="325">Bishop of Winchester</persName> no health.  Yesterday's papers announced that the <persName xml:id="111">Bp. of Southwell</persName> has accepted the Abpk. of Cape town.  The new bishop will probably be another Christian Socialist.  Filled with such regrets &amp; apprehensions, I went to church &amp; Celebrated at 8 a.m., but with little comfort to myself.  There were but 16 communicants, &amp; of these 3 were officials.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[392] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I <listEvent><event xml:id="69">preached</event></listEvent> at the <orgName xml:id="108">Foundling Hospital</orgName> in the forenoon. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> came with me in the car. There was a considerable congregation in addition to the foundlings, who rose to the ceiling on either side of the organ in the gallery behind the preacher. The aspect of the church was curiously old&#8211;fashioned; with square pews, galleries &amp; exalted reading desk &amp; pulpit. The coughing of the children was rather trying during the sermon. After service we went into the dining room &amp; heard the children sing grace.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; I went to Stratford, where I <listEvent><event xml:id="70">addressed</event></listEvent> a meeting of about 1000 men in the <placeName xml:id="36">Memorial Hall</placeName>. The meeting is an "undenominational" venture of a local draper, named <persName xml:id="1949" display="no">Boardman</persName>; who seems to be very keen about it. I spoke on the 'Originality of Christ's Religion', trying to make myself intelligible to the audience, which was mostly if not exclusively working&#8211;class.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="475">Bishop of Hereford</persName>, who had been preaching in the Abbey, called with <persName xml:id="1950">his wife</persName>.  <hi rend="bold underline">He is evidently very sore at the appointment to York.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 7 p.m. There was a fairly large congregation, &amp; on the whole very attentive. In the course of the sermon I invited candidates for confirmation to send in their names.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
