<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[417]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m., and celebrated. There were but 14 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, and these, save <persName xml:id="919">Cecil Chapman</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1033">Fred Ramsay</persName>, were all women.</p>
         <p>At Mattins there was a moderate congregation, among whom I recognized <persName xml:id="193">Lord S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aldwyn</persName>, <persName xml:id="344">Sir Henry Craik</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1547">Uncle Charles</persName>. I preached an old sermon on 'The home–life of Jesus'. The offertory amounted to a little more than £11.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I read </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1083">Loisy's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> chapter on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">La carrière de Jésus</hi><hi rend="italic">' in <ref xml:id="270">'Les Évangiles Synoptiques'</ref>. It is extraordinarily well–written, but entirely unconvincing. The historical basis he would offer to the Christian is quite inadequate to carry the fabric of personal faith, even if it be allowed to suffice for the explanation of the historical Religion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1875">Miss Heather Nepean</persName> came in to tea.</p>
         <p>There was a fair congregation at Evensong. I peached again on the '<hi rend="underline">Boyhood of Jesus</hi>'. The Offertory exceeded £5.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="122">Hine–Haycock</persName></hi> brought in a friend to supper.  <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="888" display="no">Anthony Browne</persName></hi> also brought in his brother <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1321" display="no">Philip</persName></hi>.  After supper I took <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> into the study, &amp; had some talk with him.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[418] </hi>[symbol]   </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> wrote to say that <persName xml:id="1054">Father Tyrrel</persName> was at Ivy House</hi><hi rend="italic">, Old Town, Clapham, &amp; would welcome the opportunity of making my acquaintance. So I walked to the address, &amp;, as he was absent, left my card. The next day (Saturday, Jan</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">y</hi><hi rend="italic"> 16</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1909) he called on me, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">spent about two hours in my study. He is a weak–looking man, with receding chin &amp; unsettled countenance: intellectually active &amp; hungry; but unbalanced &amp; doubtful of first principles: with a sense of humour, to keep him back from obvious blunders</hi><hi rend="italic">. He admitted that Loisy was now wholly destructive. He says that <persName xml:id="1876">Houtin</persName> has returned from America reporting ill of the Churches. A non–dogmatic Theism is spreading quickly: the dogmatic system of traditional X</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">ity</hi><hi rend="italic"> is quickly losing its hold.  He spoke with severity of the seminary system, to which he ascribes many of the mischiefs of the Roman Church.  </hi><hi rend="i bold">(</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Morally it works badly. An old &amp; experienced French priest had told him that in his belief about 25 per cent of the priest–hood kept their vow of celibacy; about as many went wholly to the bad: &amp; the remaining 50 per cent lived in decorous incontinency.)</hi><hi rend="italic">  The system of delation is now in full swing: &amp; is assiduously served by a fanatical society, <orgName xml:id="102">"The League of Catholic Women"</orgName>.  <persName xml:id="1081">Pius X</persName> is described as in a half–dazed condition, quite overborne by an office altogether greater than his modest powers can sustain.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
