<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[449]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fresh bright morning. Before breakfast I revised my morning sermon. My discourses are concerned with the same subject. At 10 a.m. I preach on "The core of the Gospel", taking the passage 1.Cor.XV.3–5, from the epistle for the day: and at 3 p.m. my theme is "The fixed factors of Christianity", &amp; my text the famous phrase in Jude 3, "The faith which was once for all delivered to the Saints".</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName> came to breakfast, &amp; spent the day here. He was joined by <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> after morning service. Thus the clans gather.</p>
         <p>The Abbey seemed to be quite full at 10 a.m. Many stood through the sermon. There were 85 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> among whom I recognized <persName xml:id="2713">Sir Francis Channing</persName>, and the tall young clergyman who was our <hi rend="underline">compangnon de voyage</hi> on the "Empress of Ireland".  In the stalls I espied <persName xml:id="1794" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Grosvenor</persName>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1179">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bowlby</persName> came in to lunch.  She told me what I had not heard viz: that <persName xml:id="775">Bowlby</persName> is leaving Eton to become Head–master at Lancing.</p>
         <p>The Abbey was again very full at 3 p.m.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1177">Allen Edwards</persName> preached at 7 p.m. to a very crowded church. He came in to supper afterwards. <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName>, <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1180" display="no">his wife</persName>, Gilbert, &amp; Ernest made up the party.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[450]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="b subscript">^</hi><hi rend="bold">v 441</hi><hi rend="b subscript">^</hi> 
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday morning (August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1909) I received a letter from <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> stating that he did not intend to prosecute me in the <term xml:id="19">Arches</term>.  I walked round to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh's</persName> rooms, and asked his advice.  He was strong for my accepting this decision without further negotiation.  He said it was kinder to Gore.  In the afternoon I walked to Lambeth and asked the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> advice.  He spoke much in the same sense as Raleigh.  Persuaded thus by these two Scotchmen I wrote amicably to Gore, asking him to communicate his decision to the Press</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, Aug. 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1909, <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> went to Cheltenham to pay a visit to <persName xml:id="1405" display="no">General Smith</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
