<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[438]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A lovely spring morning, bright, soft air, singing birds. I celebrated at 8 a.m: there were 37 comt<hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="692">Carlile</persName> preached at Mattins, a characteristic sermon. The collection at the doors for the <orgName xml:id="50">Church Army</orgName> amounted to &#x00A3;41. The ordinary collection was just over &#x00A3;12.</p>
         <p>Our luncheon party consisted of <persName xml:id="1884">Lord</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1885">Lady Inverclyde</persName>, <persName xml:id="560">Admiral Rolfe</persName>, <persName xml:id="290">Charlie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="950">Dorothy</persName>, <persName xml:id="1261">Miss Markham</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1878">John Hole</persName>, Carlile, <persName xml:id="851">Walters</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, &amp; ourselves &#8211; the ill&#8211;omened total of 13. </p>
         <p>I baptized 3 young women in S. Margarets &#8211; <persName xml:id="1879" display="no">Minnie Bent</persName>, <persName xml:id="1880" display="no">Helen Goddard</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1881" display="no">Elizabeth</persName> &#8211;.</p>
         <p>The weather changed during the afternoon, &amp; by Evensong was wet: so the congregation was reduced.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1882">Brierley</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[439] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Throughout the week beginning on Monday, the 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> March, much correspondence passed between the <persName xml:id="49">Bishop of Birmingham</persName> and me with reference to my preaching for <persName xml:id="1725">Jowett</persName> next Wednesday</hi>.<note xml:id="154" n="1"></note>  On Saturday morning a formal <hi rend="underline"><term xml:id="27">inhibition</term></hi> reached me, and I at once wrote to assure the Bishop that I should ignore it.  Later in the day I received from him a telegram &amp; a letter acquiescing in the suggestion (made by me in a former letter) to postpone the fight until my return from America.  But it was then too late.  <hi rend="underline">Jowett</hi> had asked me to keep my promise for next Wednesday, &amp; I had assured him that I would do so<hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi rend="bold underline">  <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> looked up for me in the Law Reports the cases cited by the Birmingham Chancellor, but they have no bearing on the action which I contemplate.</hi>  <persName xml:id="1883" display="no">Fillingham</persName> "ordained" and "celebrated the Lord's Supper" in a dissenting chapel.  In another case a squire quarrelling with his parson fetched a clergyman to read service for him in the schoolroom.  In another the dispute arose between a newly appointed incumbent &amp; a curate whom his predecessor had allowed to officiate in an unconsecrated building, &amp; who would not cease to do so when <hi rend="underline">he</hi> cancelled the permission.  <hi rend="bold underline">I cannot suppose that even ecclesiastical lawyers would deny that these cases differ essentially from anything involved in my preaching to Jowett's Institute on the occasion of its first anniversary.</hi>  Yet <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> Chancellor had the temerity or ignorance to quote them.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
