<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[434]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The thaw is in full progress &#8211; a small lake has formed about the goal posts. <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m: there were but 17 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>There was a larger congregation than I expected, but the coughing was continuous! I preached on the Gospel for the day, which contained the episode of Christ &amp; the Syro&#8211;phoenician woman. There was a touch of the 'New Criticism' at the beginning of my discourse, wh. will probably destroy old <persName xml:id="232">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Talbot's</persName> church&#8211;going intentions for the next few years. I celebrated the Holy Com<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>: there were 71 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="630">Bob</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> accompanied me to Bethnal Green, where I addressed a considerable body of working men in the <placeName xml:id="8">"Excelsior Hall"</placeName>. In the course of my address I read to them <persName xml:id="660">Faber's</persName> poem, <ref xml:id="61">'The Old Labourer'</ref>. We returned to Westminster in a deluge of rain mingled with hail.</p>
         <p>The congregation at Evensong was small, but not so small as I expected. I preached an old sermon on "Christian Marriage".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[435] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1650">Bridget Hole</persName> wrote me an unusually intelligent &amp; interesting letter. She is older than the average confirmation candidate &#8211; she was 18 on Sunday the 8</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> March 1909 &#8211; and is, of course, much better educated.  Evidently she had been brought up in an atmosphere of ecclesiastical &amp; theological interests, her grandfather was <persName xml:id="1866">Dean Hole</persName>, more famous as a grower of roses than as a guide of souls.  I lent her <persName xml:id="1443">Abbott's</persName> '</hi><hi rend="italic underline"><ref xml:id="190">Silvanus the Christian</ref></hi><hi rend="italic">', as likely to match her present mood.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to pay a week&#8211;ending visit to <persName xml:id="1867" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Oldfield</persName> at Milston nr Salisbury.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName> came to lunch: &amp; afterwards Inge came with <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; me for a run to Richmond Park in <persName xml:id="1300" display="no">Merton's</persName> car. The excellent Merton came to dinner afterwards &amp; brought his fiddle. So the young men made music for me.</p>
         <p>The 'Times' publishes a little <ref xml:id="245">letter</ref> from me calling <hi rend="italic">attention to the report in the <ref xml:id="246" display="no">'British Weekly'</ref> that the <persName xml:id="276">Bp. of Durham</persName> has </hi><hi rend="italic underline">worne</hi> [sic]<hi rend="italic"> the Eucharistic Vestments</hi>.</p>
         <p>The death of <persName xml:id="1868">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Arnold&#8211;Foster</persName> took place on Friday.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
