<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[458]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull, damp day. <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> preached well in the Abbey at the morning service. His delivery hardly does justice to his matter. Perhaps attendance at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's has damaged him by the bad examples of <persName xml:id="1191">Scott&#8211;Holland</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="385">Newbolt</persName>.  It was a blessed &amp; comforting spectacle to see the Westminster boys coming to the Communion together for the beginning of term.  How could any tolerable substitute be found for <hi rend="underline">this</hi>?</p>
         <p>In spite of the rain a very large congregation assembled at 3 p.m. I took occasion from the circumstances that the 'Black Letter Saint' for Sept. 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> is S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cyprian to preach a careful <ref xml:id="417">sermon</ref> on Apostolical Succession.  I made a reference to the negociation now proceeding in Upsala between the Churches of England &amp; Sweden, &amp; quoted the <persName xml:id="325">Bp. of Winchester's</persName> sermon, as it was shortly reported in the <ref xml:id="204">'Times'</ref>.</p>
         <p>After the Abbey service <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; I hastened away to Chigwell, where I preached in the parish church to a very large congregation, of which a great part had to stand. It was their Harvest Festival, &amp; I adapted the sermon which I preached on S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Matthew's day in Brixton.  We had supper in the Vicarage, where came also <persName xml:id="91">Swallow</persName> from the Grammar School, and got back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> about 11.15 p.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
