<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[425]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bitterly cold morning with a gathering fog. Knox celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 27 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>The fog looked formidable until about 11.30 a.m., by which time it had effected its sacrilegious work in spoiling the congregation. The Church was thinly attended, a fact which was the more annoying as I had taken special pains with the sermon on <ref xml:id="603">[']The Secularizing of Christianity'</ref>. The Lord Advocate was present, but nobody else of the parliament men whom I recognized.</p>
         <p>I celebrated at midday, when there were 77 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  Later may wife and I went to Barking, &amp; there I preached in the parish church to a great throng of people.  The coughing was incessant: congregational manners have degenerated since my departure: I <hi rend="underline">had</hi> to supplicate for some restraining of the clamour.  The parish has evidently changed much, &amp; is really now no more than a strip of this monstrous London.  The population is said to exceed 30,000: &amp; yet the religious equipment of the district remains precisely what it was 15 years ago.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[426] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, Feb. 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1909, I went to Sevenoaks, &amp; read a paper on "Reserve &amp; the Casuistic Problem implied in the modern Preacher's use of Scripture".  It was my 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> American lecture.  My audience consisted of about a score of the clergy of the Rural Deanery.  It was the first Chapter meeting of the newly constituted R. Deanery.  The 'discussion' was not very illuminating, but one or two of the younger men spoke well.  I made half an hour's speech in summing up the discussion.  On my return to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, I took my Confirmation Class at 6.15 p.m.  <hi rend="bold underline">Raleigh dined here, &amp; I consulted him about a letter I had received from <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>. Though expressed in affectionate terms, &amp; marked 'private', this letter seemed to threaten some interference on the Bishop's part when I go to Birmingham on March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, to speak in the Institute attached to the Carr's Lane Chapel</hi>.</p>
         <p>On Friday, the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Feb. <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; I lunched with Miss Markham at 8 Gower St.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Alf Lyttelton, George Prothero &amp; his wife, &amp; two others were there.  A pleasant party.  Afterwards we looked in on Ker, whom we found browsing among his endless books.  <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to make some calls: I sate on for a couple of hours with the Sage.</p>
         <p>The 'Spectator' printed a note with which I had accompanied a subscription to the fund for the murdered Irish policeman's widow.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
