<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[432]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A wintry day, with a considerable snow&#8211;fall. There were but 10 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> at 8 a.m: and a small congregation at 11 a.m. among which <hi rend="bold underline">I was interested to observe old </hi><persName xml:id="232"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Talbot</hi></persName>. Presumably he elects to undergo his penance in this form. I preached on 'Fasting' taking the passage from Isaiah 58 as a text.</p>
         <p>I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="1307">Sir Robert W. Perks</persName>, begging him to extend the time&#8211;limit within which the present tenents [sic] of Parker Street must clear out of their houses. He has issued notices on the 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Feb: requiring no less than 400 people men, women, &amp; children to be gone bag &amp; baggage by March 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Hence great indignation &amp; much vehement protesting.</p>
         <p>The weather grew worse as the day drew to its close: it was snowing hard by 5 p.m: &amp; at Church time a considerable amount of snow had fallen. The congregation in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> was less than half its usual size. I preached from Rom. X on the essentials of Christianity.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="1611">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hider</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1613">Leslie</persName> came in to supper, also <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[433]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday, the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> March, the <orgName xml:id="66">Brotherhood</orgName> dined here.  The weather continued very bad: a considerable snow&#8211;fall took place on Wednesday.  <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> lunched here.  <persName xml:id="296">Duckworth</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> also came: &amp; we discussed sundry aspects of the 'Constitutional question': concerning which that strange <persName xml:id="601">Sir K. M.</persName> has been speaking oddly to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>. I went to S. Margaret's at 8 p.m. with the intention of cancelling my "instruction" on the Bible. But some 70 people or more had come through the snow, so that I spoke extemporaneously.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> caught some kind of a chill on Thursday, &amp; was laid up for the rest of the week.</p>
         <p>The 'Church Times' has a <ref xml:id="250" display="no">second leader</ref> attacking the Convocational Report, which &#8211; in its many bad features &#8211; expresses the influence of <hi rend="bold underline"><quote>'the energetic &amp; forcible personality of a certain Canon of Westminster'!</quote></hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the 'Nation' (Saturday, March 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) appeared a signed article from me on <ref xml:id="247" display="no">"The Revision of the Prayer&#8211;Book"</ref>, I rather sniff at the Report on the score of its slightness.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="1322">Bishop of Crediton</persName> has cried off my 'gravamen', and written to that effect to the <ref xml:id="248" display="no">'Guardian'</ref> &amp; the <ref xml:id="249" display="no">'Church Times'</ref>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> came to see me on Thursday, &amp; stayed to dinner. He looks well &amp; happy as if Oxford suited him.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
