<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[423]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. in H.C. Only a dozen com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> including clergy.  The weather was quite bitterly cold.</p>
         <p>At Mattins the congregation was by no means large: but it was unusually attentive.  I preached an old sermon on the "name, 'Christian'".  It was probably new to most part of my hearers, as it was originally delivered at Evensong in 1906.  <persName xml:id="1314" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Gabrielson</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the inquiring Swede, attended service, &amp; then came to lunch.  He has been hearing many conflicting accounts of the C. of England.  <persName xml:id="1452">Father Stanton</persName> had been enlightening him yesterday</hi>. <persName xml:id="888" display="no">Anthony</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1321" display="no">Philip Browne</persName> came to lunch also.</p>
         <p>At Evensong the congregation was disappointing. I preached another old sermon (which was quite over the heads of the people) on S. Paul's Conversion. The organ broke down, so the whole service was either accompanied by the harmonium, or unaccompanied. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, <persName xml:id="630">Bob</persName>, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1300" display="no">Merton</persName> were at supper. Merton brought his camera, and explained to me its working. I propose to arm myself with the machine before embarking for America. Before the party broke up, I read <persName xml:id="660">Faber's</persName> <ref xml:id="61">'Old Labourer'</ref> &amp; some other of his less mawkish poems.</p>
         <p>The Offertories throughout the day slightly exceeded the modest sum of &#x00A3;16. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
