<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[459]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The day began with a smart down–pour of rain, and a warmth which was fatiguing. <persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated the Holy Com<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> at 8 a.m., &amp; I assisted.  There were 40 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, including <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="7">Alfred Spelling</persName>. In all, with the clergy, there were 13 males, &amp; 27 females.</p>
         <p>The bad weather reduced the congregation at Mattins. I preached on <ref xml:id="442">"The Unity of the Church"</ref>, and afterwards celebrated the Holy Comm<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>. There were 77 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon, I <listEvent><event xml:id="57">lectured</event></listEvent> to the Grafton Square Men's Meeting in the Clapham Congregational Church. My subject was "The American Religious Census". Alfred, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie</persName> – the three boys whom I have baptized – went with me.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="1800">Rev. Z. Barney Thorne Phillips</persName> from Chicago was in <orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Marg<hi rend="superscript">t's</hi></orgName> &amp; came to lunch.  He gives an evil report of the morals of the Roman Catholic Clergy in America.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> called in the afternoon. I found him in the drawing room on my return from lecturing.</p>
         <p>There was a crowded church at Evensong. I preached on <ref xml:id="443">"The Unity of the Spirit"</ref>. Afterwards there came to supper <persName xml:id="1261?">Miss Markham</persName>, <persName xml:id="571">Geordie</persName>, <persName xml:id="1178" display="no">Clarence Stock</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, Reggie, &amp; Gilbert.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[460]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Wednesday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, 1909, I went to Brighton and <listEvent><event xml:id="58">addressed</event></listEvent> a great meeting in the Dome</hi>, assembled in connection with the <orgName xml:id="87">Sunday School Alliance</orgName>. <persName xml:id="1798">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> F. B. Meyer</persName> followed me in speaking; and we travelled back together to town afterwards.  On the way we had much conversation.  I was astonished at his attitude towards the <persName xml:id="392">Campbell</persName> movement.<note xml:id="88" n="1"></note>  He said 'it had come to stay', that it was gaining ground: that 'in ten years' time it would probably have carried the day in the Congregational Church.  I objected that his (Campbell's) language about Christ, throwing doubt on His historical reality, and implying sinfulness, was properly inconsistent with discipleship: he admitted this, yet seemed less resentful of the language than his admission might seem to require.  We talked of possibilities of reunion.  He has just returned from China, where he declares that much kindly feeling between churches exists: but that "new criticism" threatened a formidable schism.  I rejoined that as much might be said of our situation in this country, &amp; he admitted the statement to be true.  He expressed great admiration for the <persName xml:id="105">Bp. of Southwark</persName>, who, from what he says, had spared no pains to cajole into acquiescence that simple soul.  He said that Congregationalists were being driven by circumstances to abandon their old local independence, &amp; seek some more effective organisation in order to enable themselves better to co–ordinate their resources.  There was no reason why such organisation sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be essentially episcopal.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[461]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday, October 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1909, I took the chair at a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="101">Shop Assistants' Early–Closing Association</orgName> in Hammersmith. <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> went with me. It was a wet night, and the attendance was but small.</p>
         <p>On my return I wrote a letter to a lady advising her to have no dealings with <persName xml:id="1799">Stead's</persName> Bureau for establishing communications with the departed.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, October 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1909, I dined with <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>. <persName xml:id="1262">Danks</persName>, Canon of Canterbury, and <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> were there. We had much &amp; fierce talk on Church questions.</p>
         <p>I bought at a book stall four volumes:–</p>
         <p>	<ref xml:id="193">Culture &amp; Anarchy</ref> – <persName xml:id="1460">M. Arnold</persName></p>
         <p>	<ref xml:id="194">Pastoral Care</ref> – <persName xml:id="1435" display="no">Burnet</persName> <term xml:id="26">'ex dono authoris'</term></p>
         <p>	<ref xml:id="195">The Bishops in the Tower</ref> – <persName xml:id="1801" display="no">Luckock</persName></p>
         <p>	<ref xml:id="196" display="no">Tracts</ref> (XVIII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century)</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
