<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The first object my eyes rested upon, when I looked out of my dressing&#8211;room window was a splendid rain&#8211;bow rising sublimely over the little Cumbroe. After breakfast we ascertained by telephone that the car would be ready after noon. Then I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>,<note xml:id="480" n="1"></note> being doubtful when next I should find leisure for writing, &amp; being anxious that the sequence of my letters should not fail the boy in his long exile.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burroughs</hi><hi rend="italic"> inviting him to introduce the subject of Women's ministrations in the Diocesan Conference. He has another column&#8211;long letter in yesterday's "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" on "Christianity the anti&#8211;dote of Bolshevism". His notion seems to be sufficiently crude. He would have the State organise the Christian resources of the nation for a great crusade against Bolshevism. The existing churches, being largely sunk in sterilising error, and everywhere incapable of combined action, must be replaced by the State, to which all would defer. This seems absurd enough, but he promises to elaborate his proposals in another epistle, &amp; then we shall know what they amount to.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch I went in to Glasgow to fetch the car, sending <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> on before. We motored back to Fairlie, &amp; arrived in good time for dinner. The weather was plainly worsening, and became much colder, promising an ill day for tomorrow's journey.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>