<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I am interested in mine host, whom his wife describes as "only just a business man". He is, in fact, one of the great British ship owners, &amp;, I should judge a wealthy man. </hi><hi rend="italic">But he has hobbies which have small, if any, relation to business. Last night he showed me his books, of which the bindings and illustrations expressed his own taste &amp; labour. He takes some well&#8211;known book, for instance, Sabatier's<persName xml:id="1320"></persName> Francis of Assisi<ref xml:id="1071"></ref>, or Macmillan's Italy and sets to work collecting photographs &amp; engravings to illustrate it. These carry him to the scenes of the narrative, and compel him to acquire a personal knowledge of them. He has them bound into a copy of the illustrated work at the right places, &amp; himself designs the tooling of the binding.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The result is a series of unique copies, full of personal interest. </hi><hi rend="italic">Rawnsley's<persName xml:id="243"></persName> Lake District<ref xml:id="1072"></ref> was thus garnished with portraits of the individuals – poets &amp; others – mentioned in the book. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His exercise is walking, his passion old churches. He is a total abstainer on grounds of expediency, for even moderate drinking is a disadvantage in the mercantile navy, where "you want to be sure, that a man is fit" at all times, &amp; of health, for more than 30 years experience had convinced him that "total abstinence suited him." But he had no fanatical feelings, &amp; gave his guest good wine, &amp; plenty of it. He was himself a Presbyterian, &amp; had been an elder in Ian Maclaren's</hi><persName xml:id="1496"></persName><hi rend="i bold">[114] </hi><hi rend="italic">congregation in Liverpool: but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">his wife was Episcopalian,</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; he now attended the episcopal church, &amp; held office therein as a sidesman. His garden, which is lovely, was his own creation, &amp; expressed both taste &amp; effort. A pianola in his study enabled him to "get a bowing acquaintance with the best composers." He is devoted to his wife and his hobbies, &amp; evidently regarded with respect in his profession. He perceives the difficulties which now attach to a sincere profession of the Christian Creed, but prefers a reverent agnosticism to any definite repudiation of belief. He is regular in his attendance at divine service, benevolent to the poor, &amp; indifferent to ecclesiastical controversy. He has a low estimate of politics &amp; politicians. He is now 63 years old &amp; can out&#8211;walk all his contemporaries. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His dislike of Americans is, perhaps, the only exception to his general kindliness: &amp; this is based on a fairly close acquaintance with their methods &amp; manners. </hi><hi rend="italic">He inclines to a fairly optimistic view of economics, but is opposed to Governmental interference. "If the Yorkshire miners want to stay out for 6 months, why shouldn't they? In the long run, it is far better to leave them alone." M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henderson impresses me as a strong, just man, essentially religious, &amp; with no mean artistic capability.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After lunch M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henderson carried us off in his motor to Tarbet where we called on M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> McCunn<persName xml:id="4991"></persName>, the wife of the ex&#8211;professor<persName xml:id="4979"></persName>. The ex&#8211;professor himself and his friend Bradley had gone off for the day, so that we were "shut up" to the lady's company. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> M. is herself an accomplished historian, and has written a life of John Knox<persName xml:id="2239"></persName><ref xml:id="1073"></ref> which I am assured is the best existing account of that distinguished but unpleasing person. The views of Loch Lomond which illustrated our drive were exceedingly beautiful, all the more, perhaps for the curtains of mist on the hill&#8211; tops. On our way home we left cards on Sir Ian Coloughon (!). </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then we took our departure from Ardencaple. </hi><hi rend="italic">I dropped <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at Seaside, and went on to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barochan,</hi><hi rend="italic"> where I arrived shortly after 6 p.m. &amp; found </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Renshaw</hi><persName xml:id="2311"></persName><hi rend="italic"> sen., with her married daughter &amp; Madge. Also the 4 grandchildren. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barochan</hi><hi rend="italic"> is full of memories, all kindly. We were staying here on that eventful Sunday in August 1914, when the Rubicon of human destiny was crossed, &amp; the world took its great plunge into the bloodbath of war. How well I remember the sentiments of foreboding with which </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Charles Renshaw</hi><persName xml:id="230"></persName><hi rend="italic"> and I discussed the future. We were not hopeful, though quite clear as to the necessity of drawing sword, but neither of us could have imagined then what a long course of horrors lay in front of us.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>