<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The doctor's report on my condition was so far discouraging that he advised me to abandon the Oxford sermon next Sunday. I wrote forthwith to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marriott</hi><persName xml:id="4624"></persName> explaining the reason of my failure to fulfil my undertaking.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came to see me about the Diocesan Conference. He thinks that I had better invite a special speaker to introduce the subject of Women's Functions in the Church. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName> spent the afternoon in my bedroom, <hi rend="italic">&amp; gave me much interesting information about America, acquired in the course of his recent visit. Feeling appears to run high against </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">President Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2814"></persName><hi rend="italic">, and in Washington, a hothouse of slander, not even his personal character is spared. It would seem to be the case that he has grave faults, &amp; is not the God&#8211;given Prophet our pacifists declared him to be. The Roman church in U.S.A. has "exploited" the war with much energy. No doubt the circumstance that the Prussians are Protestants made it easy; and the Italians, Poles, Tchecks [sic], and many others of the combatants against Germany are Papists. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In Canada, Ireland, Australia, Malta, &amp; generally outside the Empire the Roman Church has been our unsleeping and cunning adversary. None the less the War will bring to the Papal See an accession of importance, &amp; possibly an increase of power &amp; prestige</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Garbett</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, Vicar of Portsea, has been appointed Bishop of Southwark in succession to </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Burge</hi>. This has been generally expected. He is said to be a sensible type of High Churchman, well&#8211;disposed towards the Enabling Bill. Lloyd&#8211;George's<persName xml:id="234"></persName> appointments are multiplying.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Hereford. Percival<persName xml:id="475"></persName> replaced by Henson</item>
            <item>Worcester. Yeatman Bigg<persName xml:id="2047"></persName> " " Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName></item>
            <item>Truro. Burrows<persName xml:id="301"></persName> " " Guy Warman<persName xml:id="5047"></persName></item>
            <item>Chester. Jayne<persName xml:id="1727"></persName> " " Luke Paget<persName xml:id="2409"></persName></item>
            <item>Southwark. Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> " " Garbett<persName xml:id="4762"></persName>.</item>
         </list>
         <p>There yet remain St. Alban's and Lincoln to be filled. It is hard to say whether liberal Anglicanism has gained or lost by these changes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter, or rather signed article, on "England free or England sober"<ref xml:id="1093"></ref> appeared in the "Sunday Pictorial", illustrated with a very bad picture of me. It is not altogether a satisfactory or congruous organ for giving expression to a bishop's opinions on any subject, but in these ill days one cannot be too punctilious. The circulation of the paper is the main thing; and that, in the case of the S.P. is said to be very considerable. And the subject would be really interesting to its readers</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>