<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>What can I say wisely at the meeting this afternoon in aid of the French &amp; Belgian Protestant churches? The appeal for assistance can hardly avoid some reference to their religious character, &amp; to its bearing on our duty. There is abundant historical material, but then there are 2 circumstances which cannot be ignored. <hi rend="bold underline">These churches have failed to justify their claims as national systems: and they have generally lapsed into Socinianism</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A parallel between the XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and the XX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century suggests itself. Then as now the brunt of the struggle for liberty fell on France and Belgium: &amp; then as now the British Fleet played a decisive part. Jutland is the modern equivalent of Calais Downs. The scuttling of the German Navy corresponds with the desperate flight of the Spanish Armada, &amp; its ruin in the stormy waters of the North.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I met Dibden</hi><persName xml:id="909"></persName><hi rend="italic"> in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. He had read the letter of the Bishops of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> and Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, which appears in today's "Times": and was evidently pleased with it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He thinks the Enabling Bill will be referred to a Joint Committee of the two Houses with a view to recasting the Bill in [order] to make it a practical measure of administrative Reform. He disclaims all share in the constitution drawn up by the Selborne Committee</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked to 146 New Bond Street, and was photographed for the Freemasons. On the way I was addressed by a young man, who announced himself as Lionel Box<persName xml:id="1664"></persName>. His brother, Norman<persName xml:id="1665"></persName> is, he says, with the Army of Occupation in Cologne, and the elder brother, Gilbert<persName xml:id="1208"></persName> is being married in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> tomorrow. It is both pleasant and painful to be reminded thus of the old time in Westminster.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I lunched in the club, &amp; then walked to Sion College, &amp; made a speech at the Foreign Churches Aid Society</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>My subject was, "The renewal of fraternal relations between the French Protestants &amp; the British Church". There were about 30 persons present! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> came in at the end of the meeting, &amp; carried me off to pay calls &#8211; a tiresome procedure of which I soon tired.</p>
         <p>Ernest Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName> dined with me at the Club. He says that Truro has been offered to Guy Warman<persName xml:id="5047"></persName> of Bradford, &amp; that Southwark will probably go to Garbett<persName xml:id="4762"></persName>. Lincoln may go to Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>; if this comes about, Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> might be appointed to the Regius Professorship. I heard with some surprise that Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> was being pressed for the Preachership of the Temple. We walked in the Park before going to bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>