<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Of all forms of public utterance, perhaps the most unsatisfactory is the address at a wedding</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Not only is everybody impatient to be done with the marriage ceremony, but everybody is in the highest degree expectant of the personal references which the preacher, more often than not, is not in a position to make. He knows that too often there is a rather squalid background of business behind the tender sentiment, and that sometimes one or both of the principal parties would desire nothing so much as to regain the freedom they are publicly surrendering. He knows also that there is very often an uncomfortably inadequate married life about to follow from the union which he exalts and officially effects. The sublime borders closely on the ridiculous, &amp; certainly in marriage the sentimental passes swiftly into the most prosaic &amp; unvarnished selfishness. The preacher, therefore, is in no mood to "let himself go" in deference to the mood of the moment. Yet with all its embarrassments, I must manage to undertake the task today. Of the bridegroom I know nothing: he looks heavy, &amp; is said to be shy. Of the bride I know enough to think that she has the makings of a good wife, and also some qualities which ought to make for a successful married life. And she is old enough to avoid the mistakes of youth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henderson explained at breakfast the method of training adopted in the shipping trade. It was, and is, considered essential that the young man should learn his business in America, where work is harder, &amp; no account taken of any properly irrelevant consideration. But, though thus personally familiar with America, few Englishmen cared to live there.</p>
         <p>I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>:<note xml:id="475" n="1"></note> and also wrote some necessary letters: &amp; then made a few notes for the marriage address.</p>
         <p>The wedding took place in S. Michael's at 2.30 p.m. There was a large congregation: indeed the church was crowded. I "tied the knot" and gave the address. Then we went to Carbeth where the reception was in progress. Here I proposed the health of the bride &amp; bridegroom: &amp; then went with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Henderson to see old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Story<persName xml:id="2188"></persName>, the widow of the late Principal<persName xml:id="895"></persName>. This amazing lady is now 92 years old, but retains her memory &amp; appears to be keenly interested in events.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henderson gave me an example of government extravagance from his own experience. One of the ships of his firm which had been taken over by the government was released 6 months ago, &amp; has since been employed in trade: but the Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> subsidy still continues to be paid, in spite of repeated letters of protest!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>