<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After breakfast I resumed with the Bishop<persName xml:id="276"></persName> the discussion which we had held overnight. He is evidently reluctant to join in any action which would present him to the public as an ally of the old&#8211;fashioned Protestants represented by the Bishops of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> &amp; Liverpool<persName xml:id="477"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He pressed on me the importance of my not endangering my future leadership by giving the impression of agreement with mere Protestants</hi><hi rend="italic">. He said that he believed himself to be essentially in agreement with me. I gathered that he would not easily be induced to affix his signature to any public declaration.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We lunched at Ravensworth Castle<placeName xml:id="63"></placeName> with the Liddells, and then motored to Durham, where we were hospitably received by the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, who had drawn together a considerable company of old friends to meet us. Among these was Colonel Hills, the local member, with whom I had much interesting conversation. <hi rend="bold underline">He is one of the members who have pledged themselves to support the Enabling Bill, but he did not seem to know much about it, &amp; appeared to be impressed by my criticisms</hi>. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> and Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName> came to dinner. I learn from the latter that the School now includes more than 200 boys, which beats all records. Cruickshank &amp; I talked much before going to bed about the College, etc.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>