<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Warm, thunderous weather, but still no rain, though it is urgently needed. <hi rend="doubleunderline">James</hi><persName xml:id="4292"></persName>, armed with wig, gown, and documents, came with me in the car to Lyonshall, where I instituted and inducted the new vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullwick</hi><persName xml:id="4951"></persName>, who has come from a squalid &amp; crowded suburb of Birmingham. His churchwardens &amp; some others came in to lunch at the Vicarage, and we had some interesting conversation. We motored next to Kingsland, where I consecrated an addition to the churchyard. A fair number of the local clergy, &amp; a considerable gathering of the parishioners came to the service. Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Jobling</hi><persName xml:id="4789"></persName>, the Rector, lost his wife a week ago. She had already been buried in the new ground, anticipating its consecration. The church&#8211;wardens &amp; farmers came in to the Rectory for tea. They seemed good typical English folk, &amp; thanked me for my sermon with a downrightness, which was rather embarrassing! Among the clergy present was <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Whitcombe</hi><persName xml:id="5053"></persName>, the Vicar of Monkland, respecting whom so many strange rumours have reached me. He had an uncertain &amp; enigmatic eye, but otherwise his aspect was rather unusually devout! But it is rarely safe to go by appearances. There was thunder &amp; some drops of rain as we motored back to Hereford. I was back in the Palace about 6 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
