<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The paper announces two ecclesiastical appointment of considerable interest – <hi rend="bold underline">Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> is translated from Southwark to Oxford: and Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> becomes Canon of Westminster. I wrote to congratulate both</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> writes: "There are plain signs of fright on the part of the promoters of the Enabling Bill. I had a long talk with Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName> yesterday afternoon, &amp; he told me at length the purpose of his interview with Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, which is to take place tomorrow. Dibdin seemed anxious that I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> indicate what is in the minds of those who want to get the Bill, but with clear limitations to the power of the Assembly."</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; [sic] from Leominister, who poured out a woeful list of accusations against the Vicar</hi><hi rend="italic">. I said that it was impossible for me to pay attention to charges made in secresy,</hi> [sic]<hi rend="italic"> &amp; without evidence, but that if the churchwardens appealed to me with specific allegations which they c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> substantiate, I would take such action as the law permits. The whole situation in that unhappy parish is most distressing. Yet I judge the Vicar to be rather weak than wicked, &amp; I suspect he is hard&#8211;driven by debt. The want of money, as well as the love of it, is a root of all kinds of evil.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We left Hereford at 12.42 p.m. and travelled easily to Paddington. The papers think it good "copy" to print some absurd declamations of old Webb&#8211;Peploe<persName xml:id="561"></persName>. He announces that he is convinced that the end of the world will come in 1920, basing his conviction on Biblical and Scientific reasonings of the most elaborate kind! There will doubtless be sufficient noodles in England to keep </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that</hi><hi rend="italic"> ball rolling! </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">We were entertained at the Deanery, Westminster</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">There came to dinner Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName>, Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>, Lady Burgclere</hi><persName xml:id="3273"></persName> [sic],<hi rend="italic"> George Macmillan<persName xml:id="1330"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="4992"></persName>, and Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. It was a pleasant &amp; congruous party save that, on the inevitable subject of the Enabling Bill, we were skating on thin ice, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">for both the Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName> and M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Ryle<persName xml:id="326"></persName> are deeply committed to that unhappy measure</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">However, we succeeded in steering clear of it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I consulted the Dean about the case of Treherne<persName xml:id="4426"></persName>. He thought that probably I had done what was right. Lady Burghclere<persName xml:id="3273"></persName> is an interesting &amp; intelligent person. It is not without a certain suggestiveness that all the men of the party saving the host were opposed to the Enabling Bill. And all the four were different, &amp; represented distinct sections of public opinion. Muir Mackenzie, &amp; George Macmillan, Ralph &amp; I cover between us a good extent of ground.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>