<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName> <hi rend="bold underline">writes about the Enabling Bill. He is clearly getting interested</hi>. He names a friend of his, Sir Ryland Adkins<persName xml:id="4918"></persName> M.P., as a sincere &amp; ardent Nonconformist who, while seeking to defeat the Bill, would be willing to facilitate ecclesiastical legislation for effecting practical reforms. He suggests that I should write directly to him on the subject. The "Times" contains a rather ineffective letter from D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Forsyth, and a feeble one from Bishop Browne<persName xml:id="172"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came with me to Lindridge where I confirmed 22 candidates, including a lad named Wood who had been accidentally omitted at the confirmation in the Cathedral. It was a pleasing service, and, I hope, edifying. This was the first, and will be the last visit which a Bishop of Hereford will make officially to Lindridge, which is to be immediately transferred to the diocese of Worcester.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive Smith</hi><persName xml:id="1696"></persName> and her mother<persName xml:id="2659"></persName> arrived on a visit. She is to be married at the beginning of August, and I have rashly promised to perform the ceremony. In these days, when the world seems to be rushing into chaos, it must require no common measure of courage to disregard the counsel of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul, coloured no doubt by a touch of asceticism, but really based on practical wisdom, in I. Cor: VII.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
