<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nield<persName xml:id="5000"></persName> from Leominster called to see me about the Jarvis school, and I seized the opportunity to make some inquiry about ecclesiastical matters in Leominster. <hi rend="bold underline">His testimony coincides with that of the churchwarden, and leaves me embarrassed, &amp; so far as action penal or remedial goes, paralyzed</hi>. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent most of the day in preparing sermons for tomorrow, and after lunch I walked with Herbert<persName xml:id="2285"></persName>. He is probably representative of a great number of young men. At 18 he joins the army with enthusiasm, that is, he, a Territorial, volunteers for Foreign service. He has been through the whole War, from August 1914 to November 1918, and has neither been wounded nor invalided. Now he is demobilised at the age of 23, and has to decide what civilian work he will attempt. The Army has enlarged his knowledge of the world, and widened his ambitions. He finds Barking intolerably squalid &amp; limited, his own home comfortless &amp; crowded. But he has no trade or profession. What shall he do? In his case, there are relations in various occupations, who might fairly be expected to help him in his quest for suitable employment, but here emerges that familiar but inexplicable fact, that relations are the most difficult to approach with a request for help, &amp; the least willing to render it.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>