<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>About 6 a.m. rain began to fall, and continued falling for about 4 hours. The country was refreshed, but not really relieved. On all sides doleful records of the shrinkage &amp; failure of the crops under drought are coming in. I muddled away my morning by writing a sermon for Eton, and a sheaf of letters.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Phelps, the Vicar of Withington, came to lunch. He wants to resign his benefice though he is but 65. Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> walked with me for an hour. Then more letters: and an interview with Albert Henry Bromfield<persName xml:id="4930"></persName>, a Post Office clerk aged 36, who seeks to be ordained. He impressed me favourably, &amp; I wrote a recommendation for a grant to send him to Cambridge. He knows nothing.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to congratulate Ellershaw<persName xml:id="3459"></persName> on his appointment to the Mastership of University College, Durham</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> He is a worthy man enough, but hardly equal to that position. Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName> departed in the course of the afternoon to join her parents in Bath.</p>
         <p>The Festival of Corpus Christi is reported in the local paper to have been observed with much pomp in All Saints Church. This is, of course, grossly illegal, but I hardly see how I can make any protest, or take any effective step. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>