<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked again to Adeney, &amp; tried on the new clothes. Then to the club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where <hi rend="bold underline">I found Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, about to start for Brookwood Cemetery to officiate at poor Knowling's<persName xml:id="473"></persName> funeral</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> We walked together to West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi>; on the way we fell in with the Speaker<persName xml:id="784"></persName>. He asked me when the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> appear, &amp; said that he had been asked to write the Life of Lord S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aldwyn<persName xml:id="193"></persName>. He said that he thought the attempt to bring the Kaiser to trial was a grave blunder, &amp; that the best thing that c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> happen w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be for Holland to refuse to surrender him, &amp; to offer him a permanent residence in Java. I spent the day very fruitlessly in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>. At 5.30 p.m. I attended a meeting of the Harley Trustees<orgName xml:id="308"></orgName> in Bloomsbury Square. Accompanied by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pember<persName xml:id="4356"></persName> I attended the dinner at the Mansion House given to the Archbishop &amp; Bishops. We were fairly placed at the high table opposite the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName>, &amp; the Abp. of Armagh<persName xml:id="1361"></persName>. The speeches were far too long, but the evening was not unpleasing on the whole. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop of C.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> said to me afterwards that he thought his views and mine generally coincided; but we expressed them differently</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> We got back to the Hotel about 11 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>