<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Maples</hi><persName xml:id="4993"></persName> came to see me with reference to the Jarvis Trust<orgName xml:id="313"></orgName> school at Staunton&#8211;on&#8211;Wye. He made out a good case for rejecting M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nield's<persName xml:id="5000"></persName> scheme for a college of boarders. The cost of the requisite building would be prohibitive, &amp; there could be no reasonable probability of securing students.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" publishes my letter<ref xml:id="1092"></ref> on the Prohibition Crusade, which has been announced as a consequence of the success of the Prohibitionists in America</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi rend="italic"> came to report himself. He enters on his duties as my chauffeur tomorrow. It is rather an experiment, but I like the youth, and, if he turns out a success, he will have made a good start in a useful way of life.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The new book<ref xml:id="1068"></ref> on the 39 Articles by <hi rend="underline">Bicknell</hi><persName xml:id="4924"></persName>, the V.P. of Cuddeson, came to me. It is a creditable piece of work, though, of course, <hi rend="bold underline">written from the neo&#8211;Tractarian point of view</hi>. He refers to the very interesting letter of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hort to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> H. Brinton written in 1886 on the subject of subscription. It is printed in the 'Life'<ref xml:id="1069"></ref> vol. ii, p. 324ff. "<hi rend="underline">Thus one may say that for at least 2 1/2 centuries these Articles have been accepted by at least the greatest part of the English clergy rather for their general purport than for all their details of language</hi>." <hi rend="bold underline">It is odd to notice that the articles which were most questioned in 1886 were still the old Calvinistical ones w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">h</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> nobody bothers about now</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>