<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I find it in my mind to regret that I was never grounded in philosophy, so as to move easily in the hag&#8211;ridden territory of philosophical discussion. For theology, (which is the philosophy of the uneducated,) now fails to serve its proper purpose: and even the uneducated have no more use for it. They too would be philosophers, and have a notion of the sub&#8211;structures on which the theologians have reared their systems. They know enough to doubt what alone they are taught in the churches, not enough reasonably to believe or disbelieve it. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rashdall's</hi><persName xml:id="117"></persName> <hi rend="italic"> criticisms of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pringle Pattison</hi><persName xml:id="1619"></persName><hi rend="italic"> leave me uncertain as to my own understanding of either. When I read them separately, I think I agree with both, but when I set one beside the other I fall into doubt. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There is no independent philosophic knowledge of my own which shall make me able to weigh and decide their respective contentions</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The apparent and admitted futility of philosophical speculations may, perhaps, go far to reconcile me to an ignorance, which is practically embarrassing and personally humiliating. To confess one's self as </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Agnostic</hi><hi rend="italic"> may be as modest as it is properly unavoidable, but </hi><hi rend="italic underline">it has a disconcerting effect when one bears the character &amp; makes the claim of a religious teacher</hi><hi rend="italic">. There is no longer any church of believers in which the assumptions of faith can be securely taken for granted by the ministry.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather today has been perfect. After lunch I walked on the hill with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Griffith&#8211;Jones</hi>. The old Barochan Cross is a finer specimen of its kind than I had imagined. It has been reproduced as a monument at the grave of the late baronet. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephen</hi> &amp; his wife with two friends appeared at lunch. One of the latter, a soldier named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Green</hi>, who had served in France &amp; Mesopotamia, was <hi rend="bold underline">very positive that there was no real foundations for the allegations of outrage against the German troops</hi>: and he was supported in this attitude by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephen Renshaw</hi><persName xml:id="2314"></persName>, who said the Belgian population greatly preferred the German to the English officers. So complete a reversal of the general judgement des not command my belief, but I doubt not that the ill&#8211;conduct of the Germans has been greatly exaggerated. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">David Murray</hi><persName xml:id="4998"></persName>, Lady Renshaw's<persName xml:id="2311"></persName> brother, came to dinner. He is a well&#8211;known antiquary, and talked very interestingly on many subjects. Among these, was the water&#8211;supply of Australia. He said that the artesian wells produced water of a high temperature, and heavily charged with chemicals. It was thought also that the supply was limited. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>