<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wasted the morning in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName> at Westminster. <persName xml:id="1097">Harold Henson</persName> turned up at the Hotel in good time to take my luggage to Paddington. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and we walked to the Palace for the King's Garden Party. The day was brilliantly fine, &amp; the well&#8211;dressed crowd made a brave show in the garden. I conversed with a good many people, among the rest with Lords Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, Crewe<persName xml:id="1056"></persName>, and <hi rend="italic">Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, and Lady Frances Balfour<persName xml:id="491"></persName>. They agree in thinking that something substantial was effected in amending the Enabling Bill, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but they also agree in thinking that their episcopal allies cut a poor show</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Haldane, indeed, spoke highly of the Bishop of Manchester's<persName xml:id="242"></persName> speech.</hi> Leaving Ella in the care of the Bishop&#8211;designate of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName>, I went to Paddington, &amp; took the express to Bristol. A young soldier relieved the tedium of the journey by his conversation. He gave me his name and address &#8211; Percival H. Hall, Avondale, Pearl St., Bristol. I motored to the Deanery at Bristol, where I found both <hi rend="bold underline">the Dean<persName xml:id="4449"></persName> &amp; the Bishop<persName xml:id="2533"></persName></hi> expecting me. We had much talk on affairs ecclesiastical before going to bed. I cannot make up my mind about either of these good men. Would they stand in at a difficult fight?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>