<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked at the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> came to lunch, and afterwards I motored him back to Bridstow. We had much conversation about the state of affairs in the Church. He says that Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> has been writing letters to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> conceived in a very fanatical tone, &amp; he has passed one of these for publication. On the whole we stand to gain by the dispersion as widely as possible of his fulminations. I was pleased to see that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi> and his wife<persName xml:id="450"></persName> are evidently pleased with their new home, and settling down there happily. He continues to write a good deal for the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>"; and finds that, by means of a telephone in his house, he can communicate easily and speedily with London.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Bombay<persName xml:id="2498"></persName> communicates a long letter to the "Pulpit Exchange" discussion. He disapproves of course, but has some fantastic scheme of his own which seems to come to much the same thing. The strange fondness for splitting hairs which marks the Pharisees, new &amp; old, is one of the least alluring features of their sect. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But I prefer the old persecuting bigot to the modern type of sinuous &amp; soft&#8211;spoken fanatick, who conceals his bigotry from himself by a plenitude of fraternal language</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Old </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Wilson's</hi><persName xml:id="433"></persName><hi rend="italic"> letter yesterday was unfortunate rather than hostile, untimely rather than mischievous. He grows old.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>