<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to John Murray<persName xml:id="348"></persName> urging him to write to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the character of the Anglican layman only anxious for practical reforms. Then I had a long talk with Nickson<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, to whom I gave similar advice, viz. that he, as one who had supported the Enabling Bill on practical grounds, dissociated himself from the "idealists", and hoped that, if the E.B. were defeated or withdrawn, a more modest measure of a practical character might replace it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Captain &amp; Madame <hi rend="doubleunderline">Crapin</hi> took their departure before lunch. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">William Badham</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi rend="italic"> arrived to see me about becoming my chauffeur. I covenanted to give him 35/&#8211; a week, &amp; to find him in his motoring clothes. He [sic] to live at home with his mother. If he does well, he is to receive &#x00A3;2 per week after the end of the year. He is to enter on his duties on Saturday, the 19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> of July.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">H. E. Grindley</hi><persName xml:id="4966"></persName>, Vicar of Bosbury, lunched here. He wanted to expound to me his notion about uniting Coddington with one of the adjacent parishes. He thinks that Wellington Heath would be the best&#8211;suited for union. I took Nickson for a walk after tea, &amp; shewed him All Saints &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's Churches. Then I wrote a number of letters, including one to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ward<persName xml:id="5045"></persName>, conveying an offer of the diocesan Missioner's office at a stipend of &#x00A3;400 plus official expenses.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The "Times" has another leader on the Enabling Bill. It states that many peers are intending to speak in the resumed debate.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>