<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">We left <placeName xml:id="102">Rode Hall</placeName>, after two false starts</hi>, at 9.45 a.m. &amp; motored to Carlisle, a distance of about 130 miles. Our route lay through Brereton &amp; Knutsford to Warrington, where we left Cheshire &amp; entered Lancashire, crossing the Manchester Ship Canal by a swing bridge. From Warrington to Wigan our way lay through an industrial district – dirty, crowded, disaffected. We spent &#x00A3;2.3.0 on petrol at Warrington, &amp; then went on to Preston, where we lunched comfortably (save that there was no bread on account of the Bakers' strike) at the Park Hotel (10/&#8211; for ourselves, chauffeur, &amp; a 6d tip.). From Preston we motored, via Lancaster to Carnforth to <hi rend="bold underline">Kendal, where we had tea with D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Jackson at Singleton Hall</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> With him we found the Vice&#8211;Chancellor, Blakiston<persName xml:id="4136"></persName>. Then we went on to Carlisle over Shap. The car behaved beautifully, &amp; carried us over the formidable hill with ease. From Shap there was an easy run to Carlisle, which we reached at 8.30 p.m., our journey being illustrated throughout with glorious scenery displayed in an evening sun. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rashdalls</hi><persName xml:id="117"></persName><persName xml:id="5019"></persName> received us with much kindness &amp; even improvised a lodging for the chauffeur, whom, rather oddly, they had not expected to need provision!!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>