<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Williams<persName xml:id="5056"></persName>,</p>
         <p>Your letter of the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> inst. has been forwarded to me. I gather from what you say that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lucas is a "guilty divorc&#x00E9;", that is, he was divorced by his wife for "adultery &amp; cruelty", as the law permits.</p>
         <p>In that case, you are legally entitled to refuse to officiate at his re&#8211;marriage, though, if he can find another clergyman willing to officiate, you must allow him the use of your church, and in any case cannot refuse to publish the Banns.</p>
         <p>I think a clergyman should certainly exercise his legal option, &amp; refuse to marry a guilty divorced person: and that, as respects publication of banns, &amp; use of the church, he should obey the law.</p>
         <p>In the case of an "innocent party", I cannot think he should refuse to marry, for not only would his doing so imply a breach of the law, but also would obliterate the distinction between guilt and innocence, which would be offensive to equity.</p>
         <p>And, since he cannot himself investigate the question of guilt or innocence, he is bound on that issue to accept the verdict of the Court.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi> [symbol] </p>
         <p>I am, my dear Sir, Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         <p>The Rev. G. M. Williams</p>
         <p>Chelmarsh Vicarage, Bridgnorth</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Newcastle</hi><persName xml:id="1980"></persName> writes to ask me to be one of two speakers on the Enabling Bill at "a large public meeting on the evening of Nov 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>". I declined the invitation because "I did not think it advisable for Bishops to contend with presbyters on public platforms. The position was unnatural at best, &amp; might easily become also unseemly". After discussing the situation with respect to the Enabling Bill, &amp; stating the amendments which in my view should be aimed at in the House of Commons, I proceeded: &#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The effect of these amendments w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be to preserve the general plan of the Establishment, substituting for the purely clerical Convocations, a mixed assembly of clergy &amp; laity, &amp; for the old system of letters of business substituting a large grant of powers, reserving only certain cardinal points. If there were substantial agreement among Church folk, &amp; a spirit of goodwill, the new Constitution might work. As, however, neither condition can be counted upon, I hold it fairly certain that our present difficulties will continue, &amp; that the pace of our progress towards disruption will be accelerated".</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then I went on to sound him on the declaration which the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> &amp; I are devising:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"I want you to be ready to cooperate in a positive policy with respect to the constantly debated subject of our relations with Non&#8211;episcopalians. If the Bishops who mainly agree on this matter, would put forward a declaration stating for the information of their own clergy </hi><hi rend="italic underline">what they are prepared to sanction within their dioceses</hi><hi rend="italic">, it w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have a very wholesome effect: &amp; w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> command the eager welcome of all that body of younger men – chaplains, students' union members etc. – who have been led by their experiences during the War to desire closer relations with Non&#8211;episcopalians. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">And such action on the part of the Bishops w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> help to bring to secession point our Romanizers, who must go if the Church of England is to hold together"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I declined Lady Renshaw's<persName xml:id="2311"></persName> invitation to go to Garvochs, and remained all the morning in the house writing letters. The local episcopalian ministers came to lunch, &amp; afterwards I walked for 1 1/2 hours with the spaniel. After tea I wrote to the President of Magdalen<persName xml:id="2521"></persName> about the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and also to my brother Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, urging him to visit us while we yet occupy the Palace.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>