<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">We left Hereford in the motor at 10.45 a.m. and reached our destination about 6 p.m.</hi> We delayed a full hour through taking the wrong road at Newcastle&#8211;under&#8211;Lyme. Our route lay through Leominster, Ludlow, Church Stretton, Shrewsbury, Market Drayton, &amp; Newcastle. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> went with us, and then after tea went off to stay with his sister in Crewe. We walked in the Park, and talked until dinner. <hi rend="bold underline"><placeName xml:id="102">Rode Hall</placeName> is a pleasant house</hi>, the older part of which dates from the middle of the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. It is set in the midst of a wide park well&#8211;varied with wood, and graced by a large lake. During the war it was used for a military hospital, for which it would appear to be excellently suited, being commodious and retired. I had some pleasant conversation with mine host, and was much pleased with his sterling good sense, and evident determination to play his part like a man.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We read the 'Times' in the car: it is not pleasant reading. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The rioting at Liverpool continues, and the epidemic of causeless strikes shows no abatement</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Neither does the fever of pleasure hunting and festivity. The pageant on the Thames fills many pages.<note xml:id="473" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>