<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I sent for the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName>, and discussed the rather impertinent article in the "Hereford Times", clamouring for a fund to be raised forthwith for the relief of the poor clergy of the diocese. We agreed that it was probably written with no friendly intention, and that it would be as well for me to write a letter pointing out that the Diocesan Finance Board already existed for the specific purpose of raising clerical incomes, &amp; inviting more support for the same.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came to see me; and, after lunch, <hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> G. E. Wright</hi><persName xml:id="4456"></persName> came to talk over diocesan finance. He approved of my letter to the 'Hereford Times'. <hi rend="bold underline">I asked him about Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName>, and he did but confirm the ill reports that have reached me about him</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>We talked of the public situation, and he declared himself frankly pessimistic. His own gross income remained what it has been, but his net income was little more than one third of what it was five years ago. <hi rend="bold underline">He declared himself, rather to my disappointment, in favour of the 'Enabling Bill'; but he evidently had little or no understanding of it</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> assisted in drafting the letter to the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> respecting the Nonconformists, or rather, in drafting some proposals about preaching which were appended to it. Thus with visits from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName> and the doctor, together with the more normal dissipations of the newspapers, I passed through another wasted day.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>July 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1919</p>
         <p>My dear Bishop</p>
         <p>I think we must preface whatever specific permissions are indicated by some general statement, for the main purpose of our declaration is, less the guidance of our own clergy, than the guidance of the public mind. Also, I do not think we can well ignore the question of what has been called rather misleadingly "exchange of pulpits". The recent discussions in the Canterbury Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName> have had more reference to the pulpit than to the altar; &amp; though, in point of principle, the last is the more decisive, the first takes the more prominence in the common view. I attach also some importance to emphasizing the union of incumbent &amp; churchwardens in any co&#8211;operative essays with Nonconformists. Local feeling cannot be ignored, &amp; ought not to be, because, if it be hostile, the total result of what is attempted is not a step in the direction of unity, but a superfluous exasperation of feeling.</p>
         <p>We must avoid any appearance of <hi rend="underline">dictating </hi>to the clergy, especially as we are really issuing a public declaration <hi rend="underline">urbi et orbi</hi> [to the city (Rome) and the world].</p>
         <p>I have drafted a few sentences on the fly&#8211;leaf.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>They might introduce your excellent points about communion, &amp; also something on (&#x3B1;) common services in church on national occasions, (&#x3B2;) invitations to non&#8211;episcopalians to give special addresses or lectures in churches, (&#x3B3;) exchange of pulpits (this is not so urgent).</p>
         <p>I write in bed with all the incidental disadvantages.</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         <p>P.S. There is a further reason why we sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> put as much as possible into our statement. We shall escape the destructive description of it as another 'ridiculus mus'! and the public always rallies best to large projects and bold policies.</p>
         <p>In view of the general &amp; growing desire for some closer association between the C. of E. &amp; the non&#8211;episcopal churches, not merely in social service, but also in spiritual work &amp; witness, we have thought that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be without public advantage if we indicated some directions in w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> religious fellowship may even in existing circumstances find frank expression. Recent discussion in Convocation have moreover made it important that the clergy sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> know the mind of their own Bps on the subject, &amp; the degree of official approbation w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> they can count upon. There is, however, a preliminary caution. We <hi rend="bold">[80]</hi> [symbol] cannot think it superfluous to point out the necessity of guarding against the risk of local friction &amp; discord, &amp;, therefore, we w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> counsel the clergy to take no action without making reasonably sure that they count upon the hearty goodwill of their congregations. With this end in view we suggest that the incumbent sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> always be associated with the churchwardens in all formal approaches to non&#8211;episcopalians.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item> On exceptional occasions on which the community as a whole is concerned united services may with evident fitness be arranged in the churches. On such occasions non&#8211;episcopal Ministers may be invited with the Bishop's permission to take part in the preaching &amp; prayers.</item>
            <item>With the approval of the Bishop the Incumbent and Churchwardens may invite members of non&#8211;episcopal churches to deliver special lectures or addresses on occasions other than those of the statutory services.</item>
            <item>On special occasions the Bishop will be prepared if adequate reason be shown, to sanction the issuing of an invitation by the Incumbent &amp; Churchwarden to a non&#8211;episcopal minister to preach at a statutory service of the Church.</item>
         </list>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>