<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ceitho Davies wrote some weeks ago to seek Ordination. Four years service as a Nonconformist Chaplain have "completely changed" his views. He had read the sermon I preached in the Congregational Church at Hereford, &amp; was led to address himself to me. He is "a fully&#8211;ordained Minister with the Welsh Calvinistic Methodist connexion", of which the "Confession of faith is identical with C. of E. creed": &amp; he has been "Moderator of the Pembrokeshire &amp; Monmouthshire Presbyteries of the Connexion". He came to lunch, &amp; his aspect was rather daunting. A squat Welshman of 50 years old, rather dingy to look at, &amp; not very pleasant to smell. He had never been further than Ireland during the War: had never been to any University: and had no private means. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I advised him to address himself to an urban bishop</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> In the afternoon, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, &amp; I motored into the county, &amp; paid calls. We began with Lady Essex at Bodenham Hall, but failed to see her: then we went on to Puddlestone, &amp; had tea with the Wrights<persName xml:id="4456"></persName>. Then we went on to Hatfield, where the miserable story of the parson's<persName xml:id="4923"></persName> inexplicable misconduct was poured into me by Major Chambers<persName xml:id="4939"></persName>. This is another of the Lord Chancellor's<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> appointments. There are but 205 people in the parish, &amp; its value is under &#x00A3;200. Nobody is ever prepared for Confirmation, &amp; the parish church is almost totally deserted.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>