<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.<note xml:id="490" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">After breakfast I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Macfadyen repeating my refusal of the invitation to go to America for the "Interchange Commission"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After stating the specific engagements which prohibited my acceptance, I continued: &#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The situation in this country is so uncertain &amp; unstable that, even if I were not in bondage to duties which are themselves, as I have shown, almost prohibitory, I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> find it difficult to decide on a protracted absence. In some ways I reach my refusal with real regret, for not only do I retain a very pleasant recollection of my previous visits to the U.S.A., but also, as you know, I am more than willing to exert myself in any direction which may tend to unify English&#8211;speaking Christianity.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">The situation within the C. of E. has become very strained &amp; threatening. There is a conflict of first principles, &amp; the question is again emerging, as in the middle of the 17</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> century, &amp; at its end, &amp; again in the middle of the 19</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, whether the C. of E. shall stand with, or against, the principles of the Reformation. I may not be absent from my post here at this juncture"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>That ought to be accepted as a final refusal to go.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Ganarew, and dedicated a Shrine to the memory of soldiers fallen in the war. There were but 6 names on it, but the whole population of the parish is less than 150. The situation was romantically beautiful, &amp; the parson, who combines with his parochial duty the work of assistant master of Monmouth Grammar School, had brought over the school choir. The singing was remarkably good. I myself was the only failure, for my address was stilted &amp; out of touch! As I was speaking two <hi rend="underline">chars &#x00E0; banks</hi> full of miners passed. They went very slow, &amp; all bared their heads.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At 6 p.m. the Archdeacons<persName xml:id="4450"><persName xml:id="3618"></persName></persName> came to see me. It is evident that a measure of soreness exists between them &amp; the Rural Deans. The latter claim to be the Bishop's officers, &amp; refuse to "devil for" the former. But there is a certain inconvenience involved in the Bishop's receiving from the Rural Deans communications about Archdeacon's business. I must say something when they meet here on Wednesday. It appears to be the case that the new Vicar of All SS. has "reserved" the Sacrament, &amp; hangs out a notice of the fact. What ought I to do? I do not feel called upon to initiate proceedings, but if my attention is formally called to the fact, I could hardly avoid action without failing in my duty.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>