<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The wind during the night was very boisterous; &amp; the lawn was freshly littered with leaves &amp; branches, the d&#x00E9;bris of a tempest: but the sun shone brightly as the day progressed. "Heaviness may endure for a night but joy cometh in the morning". As I dressed I learned the Sonnet</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Upon Westminster Bridge.</p>
         <p>Earth has not anything to show more fair:</p>
         <p>Dull would he be of soul who could pass by</p>
         <p>A sight so touching in its majesty:</p>
         <p>This City now <hi rend="underline">doth like a garment wear</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The beauty of the morning</hi>: silent, bare,</p>
         <p>Ships, towers, domes, theatres, and temples lie</p>
         <p>Open unto the fields, and to the sky;</p>
         <p>All bright and glittering in the smokeless air.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Never did sun more beautifully steep</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">In his first splendour valley, rock, or hill</hi>,</p>
         <p>Ne'er saw I, never felt, a calm so deep!</p>
         <p>The river glideth at his own sweet will:</p>
         <p>Dear God! the very houses seem asleep;</p>
         <p>And all that mighty heart is lying still!<note xml:id="479" n="1"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>The scene on which my eyes rested when I looked from my window in the intervals of dressing, illustrated the poet's words. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After consultation with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, I decided that it might be prudent to send the car in to the Argyll Works (Hozier Street, Bridgeton, Glasgow. Telephones. Bridgeton 624 &amp; 177). The seamy side of a motor tour begins to disclose itself. After lunch Edmund Parker<persName xml:id="5002"></persName> accompanied me into Glasgow in the motor. We went by way of West Kilbride, Dalry, Beith, and Paisley. The Argyll Works lie in a woeful slum infested by dirty Irish children, who rush across the road in the face of the motor, and escape destruction by miracles of fleetness &amp; sinuosity. We left the motor for inspection, and returned to Fairlie for dinner. We had lunch with the dowager Lady Glasgow<persName xml:id="4928"></persName>, who lives hard&#8211;by, a well set&#8211;up old lady of ready speech &amp; decisive demeanour. I was interested to hear from another lady staying at the house, who had lived in Algeria, some account of the "North Africa Mission", which had a familiar sound to me as being the "work" carried on by an oleaginous Plymouth brother, Edward Glenney, resident in Barking a quarter of a century ago when I was Vicar there, &amp; perhaps a keener critic of sectaries than I have since become. Beyond a reputation for ample means, &amp; a rigorous use of the advantages thereof, I could learn nothing about him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>