<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At breakfast I found M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pember<persName xml:id="937"></persName> &amp; Katherine<persName xml:id="4356"></persName>, who had come to town for the Oxford &amp; Cambridge match. I proposed that M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pember should accompany me to the Mansion House tomorrow. She readily consented, &amp; offered the use of her car. After breakfast I walked to Adeney's, &amp; tried on my new clothes. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I went to Westminster for the meeting of Convocation</hi><orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>. There was very little business, as the serious matters – position of women &amp; relations with Nonconformists – had been postponed until the Lower House had said their say on them. I lunched at the Arundel Hotel with Bevan<persName xml:id="1029"></persName> &amp; the Dean of Chichester<persName xml:id="3967"></persName>. I dined in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with the Bishop of Southampton<persName xml:id="1123"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The evening papers report that M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Edward Lyttelton<persName xml:id="4990"></persName> had committed suicide. The poor lady had suffered much pain for many years. It is a sad stroke.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> told me that he, and many others who shared his dislike of the Enabling Bill, voted for the 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> reading, so that the number of the majority gave no trustworthy indication of the feeling of the House. The Bishop of Southwark<persName xml:id="602"></persName> did not turn up for the debate. Burge is an excellent good fellow, but he never "comes up to the scratch" when there's any serious fighting to be done</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>