<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName> about the vacant Deanery, and begged him to consider certain names. I also urged on him the fitness of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Walker</hi><persName xml:id="5045"></persName> of Queen's for the Mastership of the Temple. I wrote to [sic] also to a young ex&#8211;Service man who desires to be ordained but knows neither Latin nor Greek, and imagines that both can be dispensed with in the case of men in his position. His testimonials were so good, and he himself seemed so obviously well&#8211;suited for the Ministry, that I wrote to him more kindly than I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> naturally have done, bidding him indicate what parts of the syllabus he c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not attempt, &amp; promising to consider whether I c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> admit him as an ordination candidate. The residue of my time was expended on the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. After lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked for two hours, &amp; talked much. <hi rend="bold underline">If only he had more depth of character, and could outgrow the childish egoism, which makes him for ever talk and think about himself, he might be a serviceable minister. I should have more hope if he were younger, but at 32 most men have made a fairly complete disclosure of themselves. There can be few untapped resources of character then</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> came to dine in order to meet Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>. He is the very model of the demure, courteous, omniscient county solicitor, who has the key to every skeleton&#8211;holding cupboard in the country&#8211;side!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>