<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote something about the Peace to serve in lieu of a sermon at Eton tomorrow. Then I paid my reckoning at the Hotel, and picked up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in Little <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and went off to Paddington. We arrived at the Headmaster's House about 4 p.m., and went to look at the Eton &amp; Winchester Match. The visitors triumphed, but it was a good match. On the field I saw Lord Powis<persName xml:id="4265"></persName>, John Murray<persName xml:id="348"></persName>, Babington Smith<persName xml:id="2654"></persName>, &amp; others. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Buff Murray</hi><persName xml:id="836" display="no"></persName><hi rend="italic">, looking robuster than of old, was there. She has had great experiences as a transport driver in France. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Neville Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="2023"></persName><hi rend="italic">, a young giant who has done excellently as a chaplain in France, is staying here. We had some talk before going to bed. He displays his father's<persName xml:id="105"></persName> characteristics of candour in feeling and purpose with mental confusion &amp; rigidity of religious attitude. That is the fault also of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Oliver Chase Quick</hi><persName xml:id="5016"></persName><hi rend="italic">, whose book "The testing of Church Principles"<ref xml:id="1067"></ref> is much applauded by the Talbots &amp; their following. I finished reading it this morning, &amp; was much struck by the author's evident desire to be thoroughly open&#8211;minded, and his evident inability to escape from the narrow convictions in which he has been reared. He also, like the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Talbots</hi><hi rend="italic">, father &amp; son, possesses that fecundity of phrase&#8211;making which tends to conceal from them both their dearth of ideas, and their immobility of attitude.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>