<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>						
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We spent the morning in Carlisle. I got my hair cut <hi rend="bold underline">and bought a "sweater" for William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, whose clothing equipment is of the scantiest</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I walked with the Dean<persName xml:id="117"></persName>, who very kindly showed the Cathedral to William. After lunch we resumed our motor tour, &amp; travelled through a pleasant country to Garvald, a country house some miles beyond Biggar, where we were courteously received by <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dennistoun Mitchell</hi>, a connection of <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. Colonel Donald Stewart did the honours of the house. I had some conversation with him, &amp; found him neither ill&#8211;informed nor unintelligent. <hi rend="bold underline">He said that the drunkenness &amp; immorality of the new army were far graver than had been the case with the old professional army, while the "honour" of the last was almost unknown in the first</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I suggested to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rashdall</hi><hi rend="italic"> that he should be ready to assist me as a counsellor during the sessions of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. I have in mind the formation of a little cabinet of experts whom I could draw upon for special information with respect to the subjects which will come up for debate. Marriage and Episcopacy will certainly be included among these.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>