<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A confused day, frittered away in letter–writing and interviews. After lunch </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lilley</hi><persName xml:id="3618"></persName><hi rend="italic"> walked with me for 1 1/2 hours. He gave me an account of a visit which he had paid to the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Percy Dearmers</hi><persName xml:id="2633"></persName><hi rend="italic">, in the course of which he had witnessed the process of automatic writing by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Dearmer</hi><persName xml:id="4955"></persName><hi rend="italic">. She brought herself into the requisite condition by reading a book – a novel of Maurice Hewlett's: then her fingers began to move quickly, at first making erratic &amp; meaningless marks, &amp; by degrees writing intelligent English with great rapidity. She was quite ignorant of what she had written which was in fact a discussion of hope &amp; prayer, coherent and good stuff of the kind which any educated &amp; liberal theologian might compose. This she attributed to her first husband, who had given her to understand that he wished to communicate with her daily for half an hour 'when her mind was fresh.'</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lilley</hi><hi rend="italic"> watched the process with more interest since the supposition of fraud was wholly inadmissible. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He concluded that there was some unknown natural process (self–suggestion) at work, but nothing that could justify the notion of communication with the dead</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Beattie<persName xml:id="4506"></persName> came in to arrange about the service next Sunday. Wynne–Wilson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came over for the letters, &amp; stayed the night.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>