<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit Tuesday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName></p>
         <p>I send herewith the Report of the debate in the Representative Church Council<orgName xml:id="57"></orgName>, &amp; I have taken leave to add a review of the "Report" which I wrote for the 'Edinburgh', and an article in the 'Modern Churchman' which will serve to show you what are the Reforms which seem to me really urgent.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I do not think the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Reading will be refused</hi>, but I shall be greatly astonished if the Bill does not receive amendment &amp; I suspect that any serious amendment will render it unacceptable to its more ardent supporters.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">What I sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> like w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be to drive a wedge between those who are seriously seeking practical reforms, &amp; those who are pursuing an ideal properly incompatible with the Establishment as we have received it</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>And a clear indication that you w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be willing to assist some modest measure simplifying the process of ecclesiastical legislation would have considerable effect.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">It seems to me that the inefficiency of the Establishment can be no interest of the Christian or of the patriot</hi>; &amp; English Churchmen, while they may, &amp; ought to, be held to the essential conditions of Establishment, ought not to be driven to the dilemma of accepting removable defects in its working.</p>
         <p>You in Scotland are a religiously united people in spite of Disruptions &amp; Secessions; but we in England are <hi rend="bold">[20]</hi> divided by the sacerdotal movement w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> tends to identify itself with the division between clergy &amp; laity. Social &amp; political factors enter &amp; widen the breach, but the original &amp; determining fracture is religious.</p>
         <p>Yours ever sincerely,</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         </div>
         <p>Scarcely had I started work on a diocesan letter before <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilley</hi><persName xml:id="3618"></persName> appeared, and wasted more than an hour of my best working time. Then an impecunious parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry</hi>, from Knowbury, came to lunch, &amp; afterwards poured out the statement of his needs. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilley </hi>walked with me for two hours, and then I wrote letters. After dinner, the night being warm, I walked with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive</hi><persName xml:id="1696"></persName> in the garden &amp; we conversed much upon her approaching marriage. Then she came indoors, &amp; sang. Thus ended a very ill&#8211;spent day.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi> sending him the Report of the debate in the Representative Church Council, my Review in the Edinburgh Review, &amp; my article in the Modern Churchman. How far his Lordship is seeking his own political ends, and how far he is genuinely concerned for larger interests, I am quite unable to determine: but at least I would have him fully informed of the position which I myself adopt with respect to the Establishment.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>