<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> &amp; Ethel<persName xml:id="2751"></persName> went off before breakfast. Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers<persName xml:id="2708"></persName> <hi rend="italic">immediately afterwards. Miss Barlow<persName xml:id="2697"></persName> &amp; Miss Spooner<persName xml:id="5030"></persName> left a little later. So the party dispersed rapidly. I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.<note xml:id="483" n="1"></note> After breakfast I wrote a number of letters. The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" contains a long &amp; highly characteristic letter from the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName>, evidently designed to mitigate the asperity of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore's</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="italic"> diatribe, while endorsing its substance. He had evidently written before Carnegie Simpson's<persName xml:id="4591"></persName> letter had appeared, and his letter suffers greatly from comparison with it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I almost incline to think that events are moving to a secession. The inner dissidence of the Church of England has reached a point at which common action is becoming difficult</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore's</hi><hi rend="italic"> resignation of his Bishoprick has released an eager, passionate fanatick of great ability &amp; reckless courage, who is now "spoiling for a fight". </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burrows</hi><persName xml:id="301"></persName><hi rend="italic">, now Bishop of Chichester, sends me a pamphlet containing an account of his relations with the rebellious parson, Wason<persName xml:id="5048"></persName>, whom he prosecuted for various outrageous proceedings. It is a curious side&#8211;light on the Church of England. There are many clergymen who are expressing sympathy with this absurd parson, apparently on the general ground that</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> every</hi><hi rend="italic"> step towards "Catholick" ideals is to be supported, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">every</hi><hi rend="italic"> effort to enforce discipline is to be resisted. I hardly see how some kind of disruption can be, or even ought to be, averted.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[170] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Olga Montague</hi><persName xml:id="711"></persName><hi rend="italic"> came to lunch. I had much talk with her on the question of women's ordination, to which she expressed the utmost repugnance. She is evidently a devout "Anglo&#8211;Catholic", &amp; worships regularly in S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Matthew's, Westminster: but she is a very intelligent woman, &amp; more fair&#8211;minded than most religious women are apt to be. It is sufficiently evident that she has not the slightest knowledge of modern Biblical criticism, for she expressed considerable alarm when I assumed that the Fourth Gospel was not written by S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> John. Her attitude towards Protestantism is plainly determined rather by her temperament than by her reason. She declaimed against the irreverence &amp; worldliness of Low Churchmen, &amp; exalted the devoutness of Roman &amp; English Catholics. I pointed out that the reverence of the latter was very evidently connected with their doctrine of the Real Presence, which the former disallowed as superstitious. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">She expressed strong dislike of clerical marriage, &amp; said she could never make her confession to any but a celibate. Her notion of a priest was exactly the Roman, but she admitted that women might possibly be well qualified to hear the confessions of "sisters" and nuns</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">She had with her a rather poor&#8211;looking musician, who, she says, is a musical genius of the first quality, but I forgot his name!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>