<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Bishop<persName xml:id="1816"></persName></p>
         <p>You know that I have always maintained that the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> is <hi rend="underline">au fond</hi> a thorough&#8211;going sacerdotalist, though a kind heart &amp; muddled understanding combined with considerable power of dignified &amp; moving speech have obscured the fact both to himself &amp; (largely) to the general public. Watch his vote, &amp; weigh his influence, &amp; you cannot remain in doubt as to the side on which he must be counted. Add that his family influence ramifies in all directions, &amp; you have a sufficient explanation of the deference which he commands. As to the motion in the Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>, I am not averse from it, though we shall almost certainly be met by a dilatory motion to refer it to the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. The debate ought to do good, &amp; it will be very important that, <hi rend="underline">if</hi> the matter is referred the L.C. we sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> state quite clearly &amp; strongly that this is a question of urgent domestic concern, that the situation in England has no parallel elsewhere, that we cannot possibly make our action in matters of episcopal administration turn on the votes of the L.C., and that the matter of<hi rend="underline"> principle</hi> cannot any longer be treated as doubtful in the C. of E. It is from my point of view that last point w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> is of paramount importance. <hi rend="bold underline">Is the C. of E.to be counted as a Reformed Church, standing for the spiritual franchises w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">h</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> the Reformation claimed &amp; won? Or is it to repudiate its history &amp; its principles, &amp; become a soi&#8211;disant "Catholic" body&#8211;hanging on the skirts of Rome</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This is the really urgent question, &amp; it presses for answer. The Christianity of the English people <hi rend="underline">cannot</hi> be made other than Protestant in type &amp; tendency, but it can be divorced from the C. of E., &amp; <hi rend="underline">that</hi> is the real danger. I wish the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> was more able to work with others: he always "breaks away" on a "stunt" of his own at junctures when united action is of the first importance. But timidity is our main opponent – an unconfessed but dominating fear of the <hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi> &amp; its following, which are as nettles innocuous if firmly grasped! <hi rend="bold underline">The threat of a schism must be treated with resolute contempt</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It cannot mature into anything really harmful.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Yours ever.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Norwich.</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the whole morning on the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and produced two sheets! It is woefully slow work. Cave&#8211;Moyle<persName xml:id="4162"></persName>, the Vicar of Abbey Dore lunched here. After lunch I took Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName> into the cathedral, and went round with her. I noticed with concern that the behaviour of the young Welsh miners, who were sight&#8211;seeing, was very bad. This is a matter which the new Dean must reform. </p>
         <p>Winnington&#8211;Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came to see me.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>