<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After breakfast I motored to Stirling with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; bought 8 gallons more petrol at 3/&#8211; per gallon. If things go properly with the car, that ought to enable 120 miles. We mounted the Castle Hill, and I made W. go into the Castle, &amp; see what he could. After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Steele&#8211;Maitland</hi><persName xml:id="701"></persName> [Steel&#8211;Maitland] and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> motored to Alloa to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jean Balfour</hi>. I walked on the high ground above the wood, and enjoyed the noblest views. When I returned to the house I was laid hold of by the children, &amp; taken to see the pony &amp; the goats. The ladies brought back <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Steele&#8211;Maitland</hi><persName xml:id="42"></persName> [Steel&#8211;Maitland], and an Eton master, named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Blakiston</hi><persName xml:id="4925"></persName>. We had much talk after dinner. Mine host expresses himself very strongly against the opportunism of Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> and Bonar Law<persName xml:id="2278"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">He thinks Milner<persName xml:id="839"></persName> the ablest of modern politicians, but for my part I have never understood the Milner&#8211;cult of the young Tories</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I finished the extracts in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> from Ludendorf's<persName xml:id="4989"></persName> History of the War<ref xml:id="1074"></ref>. On the whole, I get the impression that he is writing honestly. It is odd to note that the Germans appear to have felt towards the Entente precisely what we felt towards them. They were contending heroically against an overwhelming superiority of armaments &amp; numbers! And the balance of atrocities lay always with the Entente!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>