<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Neither letters nor papers, for the Railwaymen had gone on strike at midnight</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> <hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" arrived about 5 p.m. by motor transport. The Government make very brave protestations, but whether they will hold to them remains to be seen. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Wardle</hi><persName xml:id="5046"></persName><hi rend="italic"> said that a railway strike could not last a fortnight, but he may be as wrong in this opinion as he was in his view that no strike would take place. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is more than ever apparent that there is a resolute body of men behind all the Labour unrest, determined to bring about a social upheaval</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Meanwhile, I proceed with the poor little cycle of unreal duties &#8211; Harvest Festivals, Dedications of War Memorials &amp;c – as if anybody really felt the smallest interest in any of them. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who has now made up her mind to stay on in Italy for another year, to take a degree at the Roman University, and to publish her thesis on "Ossian in Italian Literature". She is a most courageous person, as well as very brilliant; &amp;, if her health does not give way, she will yet astonish the world. Her description of Italian feeling with respect to D'Annunzio's<persName xml:id="4953"></persName> raid on Fiume is illuminating – "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The universal feeling here shows that we are in a mood to accept even the military dictatorship of a theatrical maniac rather than submit to Wilson's dictatorship</hi><hi rend="italic">". </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wilson</hi> <hi rend="italic">himself is reported to be suffering from nervous prostration as the result of his rhetorical campaign. I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.<note xml:id="485" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>