<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I travelled to Oxford by the early train, and arrived about 10.30 a.m. I had time to get my hair cut before going to the Cathedral <hi rend="bold underline">for the Freemasons' Service of Thanksgiving and Commemoration</hi>. It was an impressive service. I preached for exactly half an hour. There was a considerable gathering of brethren, who sang very heartily. Then we were all photographed in Tom Quad. I sate beside <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Valentia</hi><persName xml:id="5040"></persName> in my robes. Then followed luncheon in the Town Hall. I came away while the meal was proceeding, &amp; caught the 3 p.m. train for Hereford. I was back at the Palace by 6.20 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Bethune Baker</hi><persName xml:id="4131"></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> has a letter in the 'Times' supporting the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>, pressing for inter&#8211;communion &amp; belittling exchange of pulpits. He does not appear, however, fully to understand the Bishop of Norwich's<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> proposal, nor does he sufficiently appreciate the importance of the fact that the Nonconformist leaders have accepted it. The really important matter now is neither inter&#8211;communion, nor exchange of pulpits, but the saving of the Church of England to the cause of the Reformation</hi><hi rend="italic">. If </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="105"></persName><hi rend="italic"> are allowed to succeed in vetoing every approach to the Non&#8211;episcopal churches, and in compelling the Anglican to contemplate reunion only with reference to Rome &amp; the East, the "game is up" so far as evangelical religion and liberal churchmanship are concerned. Hence the importance of defeating them.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>