<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I revised my 'Peace' sermon before breakfast, and preached it to the boys at Mattins. The text, or what served as such, was added at the last moment:&#8211; "<hi rend="underline">Shew Thy servants Thy work; &amp; their children Thy glory</hi>". <hi rend="italic bold underline">Both the Provost and the Vice&#8211;Provost were very warm in their expressions of approval afterwards</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; the boys seemed to be attentive. So I assume that it was not altogether unsuitable or unsuccessful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Alington<persName xml:id="541"></persName> took me to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Warre</hi><persName xml:id="203"></persName>, who yet lingers, a truly melancholy spectacle. Then I attended a meeting of the older boys, who were addressed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Neville Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="2023"></persName> in an extemporaneous address delivered with much vehemence and appearance of conviction. I thought much of what he said must be "above the heads" of his audience, but Alington thought otherwise. On the whole I was more favourably impressed than I had expected to be.</p>
         <p>I lunched in Hall, &amp; had some talk with James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> and Rawlings. Then, after speaking with young Lord Castlereagh<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> and Roger S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aubin<persName xml:id="5031"></persName>, who had been convened to meet me, I walked with Alington until tea&#8211;time; and then attended chapel. The boys sang with remarkable vigour &amp; heartiness.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Moore</hi><persName xml:id="4331"></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Peter's, seems to have gone out of his way at the Evangelical Conference at Cheltenham to make what </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who was present, describes as "a bitter attack on his diocesan". The "Hereford Times" prints his words, or some of them, with warm commendations on his 'courage' etc. But it omits all reference to the speech in which Wynne&#8211;Willson corrected Moore's account of what happened at the Church Defence Meeting. It also publishes what purports to be a verbatim report of my sermon in the Abbey, but which </hi><hi rend="italic underline">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> a gravely inaccurate version of my words.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It would be curious to know what precisely has led Moore to this indecent behaviour. Partly, I incline to think, it is a jealousy of Wynne Willson, and partly chagrin at not counting for more in Hereford. He finds compliments &amp; a measure of prominence can be secured by making attacks on me, &amp; he probably knows that he has nothing to fear from me, as I have long settled it with myself to take no notice of personal attacks. Nevertheless, an attack from that quarter is a little surprising, &amp; may be not a little disconcerting if it secures acceptance &amp; approval. My ill&#8211;impression of the little man has been justified more quickly than I expected.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>