<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[186]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright but frosty morning. Winter comes on apace, &amp; with its coming, every social problem becomes more difficult of solution. This railway strike will either cease quickly as soon as the resentment of the public is realized by the strikers, or it will be the beginning of a life&#8211;&amp;&#8211;death struggle for social order.</p>
         <p>I went to the Cathedral, &amp; celebrated at 8 a.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName> alone was there, &amp; he arrived on the scene after the hour had struck. The belated post of yesterday arrived at breakfast time. It was official &amp; precious, bringing my quarter's income, &amp; my re&#8211;payment of income tax. The latter amounted to &#x00A3;235.13.4, which was more than I expected.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Abbey Dore, where I preached twice. In the morning I dedicated some memorials of fallen soldiers – three beautiful stained glass windows, and a lych gate. The glorious church looked its best. The villagers filled the Laudian seats, &amp; everything was ideal. I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Partridge</hi><persName xml:id="5009"></persName>, whose husband<persName xml:id="5008"></persName> &amp; son<persName xml:id="5007"></persName> two of the 3 windows commemorated. Colonel Protheroe<persName xml:id="5015"></persName>, &amp; Captain Partridge<persName xml:id="5006"></persName> with their wives<persName xml:id="5010"></persName> were there. <hi rend="italic">After lunch I walked to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bacton</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; saw that charming little church. </hi>The Vicar, Rev. C. T. Brothers<persName xml:id="4931"></persName>, seemed to be well&#8211;informed about it, &amp; pointed out its notable features with sympathy and intelligence. He <hi rend="bold">[187]</hi> [symbol] took me into his house, &amp; showed me from the garden one of the most magnificent views I have ever seen. Also, I saw the great treasure of this church – <hi rend="bold underline">a very perfect &amp; beautiful pre&#8211;Reformation chalice</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> There is but one other in the diocese – at Leominster. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Brothers was at much pains to impress on me the unwisdom of uniting small parishes, and the extent of the rural clergyman's labours. He himself has but 117 parishioners, and no school, but he has never worked so hard in the whole course of his life as during the 15 years of his vicariate of Bacton. He does the duties of sexton;<note xml:id="486" n="1"></note> he is his own gardener; he must himself do all his clerical duties, &amp; do them always. The value of his living is about &#x00A3;120 and a house – hardly "a living wage". We returned to Abbey Dore for tea, &amp; then I preached at the Harvest Festival. There was a large congregation, &amp; a very heaty &amp; reverent service. <hi rend="bold underline">The Rector, Rev. G. E. P. Cave&#8211;Moyle<persName xml:id="4162"></persName> has purchased the advowson from M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Partridge who is selling the family property</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> He is a youngish man, with a remarkably good voice, and a sense of humour. He gave me the impression of being genuinely interested in his work. I noticed that he has an evening communion on Easter day, &amp; on every 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sunday in the month. He says it is the only possible time for many of his rustics. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>