<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. After breakfast I stayed in my study, &amp; strove to order my thoughts for the address at the "Drum head Service" this afternoon. How great an advantage on such an occasion is a simple mind which can hypnotise itself with the appropriate convention, and speak without embarrassment &amp; in uncompromising terms!</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There was an immense crowd in the piazza of High Town. An adjoining shop was used as a vestry, and there we formed a little procession. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Beattie</hi><persName xml:id="4506"></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cope</hi><persName xml:id="4946"></persName><hi rend="italic">, the two chaplains who were to read the prayers, went first. Then came Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> with his staff, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Stanley</hi><hi rend="italic">, another chaplain, who carried the pastoral staff. Then I came in full episcopal attire, &amp; the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> followed as my chaplain. The Dean<persName xml:id="3471"></persName> had been established on the platform in advance, as he was in a bad state of decrepitude. The hymns were well sung: &amp; the prayers well read. I preached for 20 minutes, and was listened to with much attention. Several people assured me afterwards that my voice carried well. On the edge of the crowd I noticed two small red flags on poles. I hope this does not indicate the presence of a Bolshevist in Hereford. On the whole I think it was a dignified and impressive service. After tea </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName><hi rend="italic"> went with me to Ballingham where I preached in the parish church, a well&#8211;kept medieval building of no conspicuous merit. Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> read the service very well.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>