<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Treasure,</p>
         <p>I am now in a position to tell you definitely that I will not accept you as a candidate for Ordination to the Priesthood: because I am satisfied that the Bishop of Liverpool<persName xml:id="477"></persName> is the only Bishop who can rightly be responsible for ordaining you. His Lordship does not appear to be willing to request me to act in his behalf. I shall be willing to sanction you officiating in Leominster for the present.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully,</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to the Jarvis School at Staunton&#8211;on&#8211;Wye, and attended a meeting of the Managers. Sir Geoffrey Cornwall<persName xml:id="4947"></persName> [Cornewall] presided, and D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maples<persName xml:id="4993"></persName>, the new organizer of education for the county, attended. Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and his sister came to lunch. They are cheerful and evidently enjoying their new life. But the financial cloud darkens his horizon as it darkens mine. The dilapidations of a great house like Hartlebury involve a great expenditure. I wrote a number of letters, and ordered a supply of wine. <hi rend="italic">How long my "reduced circumstances" will permit me to exercise my Christian liberty becomes a matter of some uncertainty!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>