<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I walked to Westminster, reflecting on the course I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> take anent the "<hi rend="underline">Relations with Nonconformists Report</hi>".<note xml:id="469" n="1"></note> I decided that, so far as I had opportunity, I w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> oppose the appointment of any more Committees or Conferences, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> advise the abandonment of any attempt to secure the adoption of a general policy, &amp; the decision to leave the matter to the discretion of individual bishops</hi>. The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> was clearly perplexed as to his course, &amp; made an embarrassed statement. Probably he will nominate another Committee. After the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> had spoken, <hi rend="bold underline">I took up my parable, &amp; spoke with brutal frankness</hi>.<note xml:id="470" n="1"></note> Probably I was more sincere than prudent. <hi rend="bold underline">After the session had ended, I went to the House of Lords, &amp; sat on the steps of the throne for an hour, watching the proceedings in Committee on the Enabling Bill. It was evident that the Archbishop had got a phalanx of about 100 peers, who were ready to see the thing through, &amp; that the mass of their Lordships were taking no interest in the business. The Bill may go through the Upper House: will it go through the Lower?</hi> I dined with the <persName xml:id="66">Pembers</persName><persName xml:id="937"></persName> at the Carlton Hotel. It was pleasant enough, but amazingly <hi rend="underline">unreal!</hi> I turned in shortly after 10 p.m. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>