<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received a long &amp; affectionate letter from <hi rend="underline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, and I answered it forthwith. Most part of the morning was spent at the Jarvis School, where I presided over a meeting of the Trustees. In the afternoon I read the paper, and "fooled away" the time until <hi rend="underline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came for the letters. There was nothing of real importance.</p>
         <p>Somebody sends me the parish magazine of "<hi rend="underline">S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Silas&#8211;the&#8211;Martyr" Kentish Town</hi>. It is an illuminating document, &amp; merits the study of anyone who w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> understand he Church of England. The most part consists of a letter from the Vicar, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Napier Whittingham<persName xml:id="5055"></persName>, who writes from Cadenabbia, where he is acting as chaplain. One passage interested me particularly: &#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Never before has the necessity for electing our own Bishops been so clear: <hi rend="underline">few of the present occupants of Sees w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="underline"> be in them if the Church had her own way</hi>. Blind leaders of the blind, "semper pavidi", as D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Newman<persName xml:id="337"></persName> said years ago, they dare take no action that will magnify the Church, but instead court popularity by proposing the interchange of pulpits with Nonconformists, &amp; the admission of women as preachers, &amp; possibly some day as priests. Small wonder, that D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, Bp of Oxford, has resigned his see, &amp; will have none of them."!!!!</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Edmund Gosse<persName xml:id="2083"></persName> has a very sensible letter on the Crusade for Prohibition which the Americans are about to start in this country. I was moved to write to the Times in the same interest.</hi><hi rend="italic"> One disadvantage of living in the country is that there must needs be so long delay before anything can appear. It is unlikely that my letter will be published before Friday at the earliest.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In the form of recantation provided for certain Anabaptists in the year 1575 the religious identity of the Church of England and the Dutch Church in London is distinctly affirmed. The abjurant has to say:</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"further I confess, that the whole doctrine &amp; religion established in this realm of England, as also that which is received &amp; practised in the Dutch church here in this city, is sound, true &amp; according to the word of God, etc."</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is rather startling to find Elizabeth issuing a special commission to Sir Nicholas Bacon<persName xml:id="4920"></persName> to burn hereticks</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">But the Reformed Churches could not quickly or easily purge their minds of the old persecuting assumptions, &amp; they felt themselves under a special necessity of demonstrating their orthodoxy by such acts of religious zeal.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>