<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked to Westminster &amp; visited <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. The East Window had been replaced, &amp; looked more beautiful than ever. Then I went in to the Abbey, and picked up there a young American soldier (Henry Bucknor<persName xml:id="4934"></persName>, Nashville, Tennessee). He had been four times in the Abbey, &amp; had never ventured past the gates. <hi rend="bold underline">So I took him in to Henry VII</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">'s Chapel,</hi> &amp; showed him the Coronation Chair etc. He was most grateful. Then I visited the dentist. From him I went to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName>, &amp; had lunch &amp; talk. <hi rend="italic">He told me that he had come into conflict with Lord N., who had received a communication adverse to him, alleging that he had been brought into the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> office by my influence, that he was a German, etc etc. K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> stood to his guns like a man, &amp; demanded both the name of the letter&#8211;writer, &amp; an apology. The first was that of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><persName xml:id="311"></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; the last was amply given. This shows the depths of baseness to which these zealous gentlemen can sink. For K. might have been wholly dependent on his pen, &amp; he might have been completely ruined by this low intrigue. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">K. thinks the Enabling Bill is really done for</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> came to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and took me to his house that I might see the children</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Peggie<persName xml:id="2764"></persName> is six: and Rex<persName xml:id="2799"></persName>, my godson, is three. Very promising children both. Then we called on Sir Henry Graham<persName xml:id="633"></persName>, &amp; Lady Margaret<persName xml:id="634"></persName>. He is quite blind, but has set himself pluckily to learn the Braille type. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Marjorie<persName xml:id="369"></persName> has been divorced from her husband, and has married the co&#8211;respondent. </hi><hi rend="italic">Thus the marriage which satisfied Lady M.'s requirements has ended in lamentable failure: while that which she lamented &amp; toiled to hinder, has turned out well. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">She told me herself that Harold's children were the joy of her life</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">One of the evening papers is good enough to say that I am going to be transferred from Hereford to Southwark, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">because I am passionately devoted to London</hi><hi rend="i bold">!!! </hi><hi rend="italic">I suppose it would have been possible for me to have had Southwark before, when Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> was offered Hereford. My feelings about living in London are far other than those which the journalist imagines. The unceasing noise &amp; movement weary &amp; alarm me: the distractions bewilder my mind. I can hardly imagine deliberately re&#8211;inserting myself into this scene of folly &amp; bustle. Happily there is but little likelihood of my being compelled to face the contingency. </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>