<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>The Trosachs</p>
         <p>There's not a nook within this solemn pass</p>
         <p>But were an apt confessional for one</p>
         <p>Taught by his summers spent, his autumn gone,</p>
         <p>That Life is but a tale of morning grass</p>
         <p>Wither'd at eve. From scenes of art which chase</p>
         <p>That thought away, turn, and with watchful eyes</p>
         <p>Feed it 'mid Nature's old felicities,</p>
         <p>Rocks, rivers, and smooth lakes more clear than glass</p>
         <p>Untouch'd, unbreathed upon. Thrice happy quest,</p>
         <p>If from a golden perch of aspen spray</p>
         <p>(October's workmanship to rival May)</p>
         <p>The pensive warbler of the ruddy breast</p>
         <p>That moral sweeten by a heaven&#8211;taught lay,</p>
         <p>Lulling the year, with all its cares, to rest!<note xml:id="478" n="1"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>The paper reports the death of the Bishop of Lincoln<persName xml:id="1643"></persName>. His resignation was to have taken place on September 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hicks</hi> was a man of considerable ability, a scholar of distinction, and an energetic social worker. His advocacy of total abstinence and feminism was ardent and indiscriminating. There was certainly an element of fanaticism in his character. As a <hi rend="bold">[125]</hi> Churchman he would be classed as a Tractarian with a strong infusion of "Christian Socialism". I shall always think of him with kindness, for he acted honourably when the clamour was raised against my consecration, and at once informed the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> that he would desire to be one of the consecrating bishops. He wrote to me in very kind terms, and expressed great disgust at the tactics of my orthodox opponents. <hi rend="underline">One of his last actions was to sanction the preaching of a woman in a parish church at a statutory service. He was, I think, plainly inclining towards an acceptance of the feminist claim to ordination on the same terms as men. Logically it is difficult to distinguish between the ministry of the word and the ministry of the Sacraments. There is a very general disposition to concede the first, and an almost universal reluctance to concede the last</hi>. Yet it is arguable that the female temperament is better adapted for priestly work than for that of the preacher: and since half of the human race belongs to the female sex, and sacraments are held to be "necessary" for salvation, there is much to be said for entrusting sacramental ministries to woman. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch we "took up our carriages", <hi rend="bold underline">and went on to Fairlie to visit Charlie<persName xml:id="290"></persName> &amp; Dorothy Parker<persName xml:id="950"></persName></hi>. On the hill above Largs we were enveloped in mist, but Fairlie was bathed in sunshine. The views of the islands were magnificent. I found some letters awaiting my arrival. Among them was one from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. He says that he will be absent from England for 18 months. As usual, he clamours for letters. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Treherne writes from Tintagel to say that her husband<persName xml:id="4426"></persName> has cancer in the stomach in an advanced stage. Bowen<persName xml:id="4492"></persName>, the Congregationalist minister, writes to say that he has decided to decline the "call" to Manchester, &amp; to remain in Hereford. There is rather a resentful note in his letter as if he felt himself aggrieved by the clergy!</p>
         <p>At Fairlie besides Charles &amp; Dorothy we found Edmund Parker<persName xml:id="5002"></persName> from California, and his brother<persName xml:id="5003"></persName>, who was stationed at Newcastle while we were in Durham. I was glad to find somebody who could give me some first&#8211;hand information about Prohibition in America. He gave a very ill account of the "saloon", and of the American modes of drinking. The California wine&#8211;growers were grubbing up their vines as if they believed that Prohibition had come to stay. Nevertheless Edmund Parker himself thought that the experiment could not permanently succeed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>