<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is "Hospital Sunday", but I shall not preach on the subject of Hospitals. The circumstances in which we stand must excuse, for they almost compel, a "topical" sermon. In the phrase of the XVII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, I must "preach to the times". <hi rend="bold underline">It is, perhaps, a little embarrassing for mine host, who is in the opposite camp to my own: but I shall avoid any direct mention of the Enabling Bill, &amp; move on a plane where we do not openly conflict.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went into the Abbey Church at 8 a.m., &amp; there received the Holy Communion. The glorious building in the light of a fine summer morning was looking is best. My heart was filled with a great sense of regret at having ever gone away from it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After breakfast I picked up the Life of Canon Barnett by his wife. There are two references to myself which struck me. In 1910 he wrote to a friend:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">'Have you been reading Henson? He seems to me to speak words of wisdom, &amp; if only he was inspired with greater feeling might do much for the cause.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">How far is this a just criticism? Again he quotes me as saying that "it will take fifty years for people to learn the distinction between the Incarnation and the Virgin Birth." This seems to me to be a true observation, &amp; I endorse it now. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We attended Mattins in the Abbey Church. There was a very large congregation, for not only was Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> the preacher, but also the Lord Mayor attended in State in honour of the Hospitals. </p>
         <p>It was a very fine sermon, &amp; very characteristic. His subject was, How can the Divine Justice be vindicated in such a world as this? He illustrated it by quotations from Well's latest book, and <hi rend="bold underline">worked in some severe reflections on the shallow optimism which assumes a law of indefinite progress</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Outside the Church we fell in with Colonel Phipps. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We lunched at the Authors' Club, Whitehall Court, with Professor Edward Moore<persName xml:id="1266"></persName> and his son John, who have returned from Constantinople, and sail for America this week. The conversation was both interesting &amp; melancholy. Moore is a strong Republican, &amp; vehemently opposed to President Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName>, who has in his belief entirely lost his position in America. He said that the "Bone dry" condition of the Republic would certainly not last, &amp; gave some interesting facts to show the hollowness of the Prohibitionism, which now carries all before it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">One grave consequence was the impossibility of inducing a good type of man to enter the police force. No honest man could take the oath to enforce the laws knowing the while that he would have to wink at the breaches of the anti&#8211;Liquor laws. This is a new point, &amp; good one</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the evening I preached<ref xml:id="1091"></ref> in the nave of Westminster Abbey. There was an immense congregation, many of which were standing. My sermon took 34 minutes in delivery. The text was Isaiah 65.8. "<hi rend="underline">Destroy it not for a blessing is in it</hi>".</p>
         <p>The bulk of my Whitsuntide sermon was repeated. At the end the Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName> reminded the people that 8 years before the King had been crowned in the Abbey on this day, &amp; that I and he were the sole survivors of those who bore the Regalia. It is but too true – Duckworth<persName xml:id="296"></persName>, Wilberforce<persName xml:id="109"></persName>, Beeching<persName xml:id="208"></persName> and Barnett<persName xml:id="752"></persName> have all died in the interval. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The newspapers report an amazing occurrence. Nearly all the surrendered German ships have been sunk by the 'skeleton' crews which were on board. It is an action of disgusting perfidy, but it solves the problem how to dispose of the ships. </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishoprick of Chester is filled by the appointment of the Bishop of Stepney (Luke Paget<persName xml:id="2409"></persName>). </hi>
         </p>
         <p>He is more than 65 years old, and an advanced High Churchman. Thus a change for the worse in the balance of parties is effected in the Northern Province. Bishop Jayne<persName xml:id="1727"></persName> had grown into a Liberal. Bishop Paget will be an active + earnest obscurantist of the modern type. There remain 4 bpks to be filled – Truro, Southwark, Lincoln, St. Alban's. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>