<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37] </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We had tea with Lady Chelmsford<persName xml:id="1857"></persName> yesterday in order to say, Goodbye, as she sails for India next Friday. She looked rather tired, but spoke cheerfully. The Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName> had some talk with me about the appointment to the Hereford Deanery, which must be vacant shortly. He thought Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName> would hardly stand the climate even if he were induced to accept the responsibility. Algy Lawley<persName xml:id="973"></persName>, Lord Wenlock, seemed to be a very suitable man. If </hi><hi rend="italic underline">his</hi><hi rend="italic"> health would stand the mild debilitating air of Hereford, he would probably be acceptable: and, as a Shropshire man, his nomination to the Hereford Deanery would tend to reconcile that rather restive portion of the Diocese. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">R. J. Campbell<persName xml:id="392"></persName> seems to be dangerously eager in seeking preferment. The Mastership of the Temple is now the object of his ambition. But his health does not admit of residence in London. He practically lives in Brighton and come up to Westminster to preach in Christ Church. This must make any effective &amp; continuous parish work impossible</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The essential deficit of the Nonconformist conception of ministry comes out in their indifference to, and incapacity for, pastoral work. For purposes of platform agitation – what they are pleased to describe as a "prophetic" ministry – they are no doubt far better equipped than the ordinary English clergyman: but they have an eye to the newspapers, &amp; they weary quickly of unreported labours! </hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After getting my hair cut &amp;c. I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and prepared a speech for this afternoon, &amp; wrote some letters. Then I returned to the Deanery, &amp; lunched. <hi rend="bold underline">Garbett<persName xml:id="4762"></persName>, the Vicar of Portsea</hi>, was there. He is <hi rend="underline">probably</hi> destined to follow Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> at Southwark. After lunch <hi rend="bold underline">I called on Gow<persName xml:id="216"></persName> who is terribly blind in spite of the operation:</hi> &amp; on Charles. Then I presided at a meeting of the Curates Augmentation Society. A dreadful man from New Zealand, Lord Steynham, foamed and ranted for 45 minutes. Joynson&#8211;Hicks<persName xml:id="4295"></persName>, who was to have seconded him had to leave: &amp; after having driven me to brink of desperation he insisted on introducing to me the whole bevy of female relations!! Then I recovered my baggage from the Deanery &amp; went to Garland's Hotel. I read through Wells' book, which Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> recommended in his Abbey Sermon. Then I dined in the Club, &amp; I had some talk with Bernard Holland<persName xml:id="4975"></persName>, who is a papist. After dinner I wrote some more letters. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The "Times" has a short extract from my sermon: none of the other papers had any reference to it. If the press be any indication of the public mind then there is not the smallest interest in the Enabling Bill among the people.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>