<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>,<note xml:id="471" display="no" n="1"></note> and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colin Kennedy</hi><persName xml:id="2432"></persName>. Also to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Downing</hi>, expressing again my desire to retain Tenbury with St. Michael's College, in the diocese; &amp; to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Stafford</hi>, thanking her for the copy of Thomas &#x00E0; Kempis from her late father's books. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Antonia</hi><persName xml:id="5018"></persName> took their departure. Also, to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold</hi>, who had inquired the reason of the distinction between "by Divine permission' in the case of bishops, and "by Divine Providence" in the case of Archbishops.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName><hi rend="italic"> took down in shorthand a letter on the Enabling Bill which I propose to send to the Committee of Nonconformist members, which has been formed to consider the Bill. Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> was with me for 1 1/2 hours dealing with the correspondence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There is a certain risk in holding intercourse with the Nonconformists about the Enabling Bill for </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the vice of the Bill, (viz: the underlying assumption that Nonconformists have neither part nor lot in the National Church</hi><hi rend="italic">) makes appeal to all the mingled aversion – religious, social, political, personal – which parts the Anglican from the Dissenter. There is risk that one will be denounced as conspiring with the enemy, when it is not the enemy, but a good section of National Churchmen with whom one is really having dealings. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The conception of a National Church is wholly dead in the popular mind</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>