<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather seems to have broken at last. Today, there is a falling glass, a high wind, &amp; occasional essays at rain. Olive<persName xml:id="1696"></persName> &amp; her mother<persName xml:id="2659"></persName> left us in the forenoon. I employed myself on the letter for the diocesan Messenger<hi rend="italic">. To lunch came </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Ward&#8211;Jackson</hi><persName xml:id="4873"></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his wife. He is evidently being harried by the clergy for having drawn back on the Enabling Bill. He had never seen the Bill, and was rather startled when he did see it. I comforted him by pointing out that, after all, not one tenth of the clergy in his constituency had written to him!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I visited the Horse &amp; Cattle Show. There were some amazingly fine animals exhibited, but the spectacle mainly bored me, for there was a violent wind which raised the dust, &amp; the dust of a cattle show is the nastiest in the world. We dined with Frank James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> and met there his brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Lawrence</hi><persName xml:id="4986"></persName>, an interesting &amp; intelligent man, who had recently returned from Palestine. <hi rend="bold underline">He says that the Zionist adventure is foredoomed to failure. The country cannot sustain a large population, and it is already occupied by non&#8211;Jewish people, who will not welcome the new arrivals from Europe. The outlook is certainly unpromising</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>