<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Bishop,</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I have been hors de combat for the past fortnight with a recurrence of that painful &amp; disgusting ailment w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">h</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> prostrated me last year. The heats of Hereford are plainly too much for me</hi> as yet. By this time next year, the increase of the income&#8211;tax will probably have made it quite impossible for us to live in this house: &amp; we shall in that event seek a cottage on the healthier slopes of the Clee Hills in Shropshire! Now for my object in writing. The Bp. of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> has the idea (w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> certainly accords with my own view of what is desirable) that we, the liberal &amp; Evangelical Bps, ought to meet the situation created by recent developments in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName> &amp; Parliament by putting forward a statement indicating to our own clergy what we, as Bishops, are prepared to approve &amp; allow within our own dioceses in the matter of co&#8211;operation with non&#8211;episcopalians. He suggested certain situations in w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> communion might be conceded: I add that we must certainly include also the matters roughly indicated by the rather foolish formula "exchange of pulpits". I have urged also that we sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> introduce our specific permissions with a few sentences of explanation. <hi rend="bold underline">In form the document w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be addressed to our own clergy: in fact it w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="bold underline">be a public pronouncement of the first importance</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> answer effectively Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> &amp; his faction: w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> provide a significant &amp; timely commentary <hi rend="bold">[100] </hi>[symbol] on the negative clause of the elector's declaration: and might even (I hardly dare hope as much) edge out the fanaticks into the <hi rend="underline">Scarlet Woman's</hi> arms!</p>
         <p>If we c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> succeed in combining even half&#8211;a&#8211;dozen bps in a practical policy, it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi>provide something to w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> the right&#8211;minded might rally. <hi rend="underline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName> is just back from Swanwick, where the returned chaplains &amp; demobilised soldiers were much in evidence. <hi rend="bold underline">He assures me that such a lead as I have suggested is precisely what they are longing for, &amp; he thinks (and here I incline to agree) that such a pronouncement as I have described w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="bold underline">be received with large agreement &amp; even enthusiasm</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Surely we can count on these:&#8211; Manchester, Hereford, Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, Birmingham<persName xml:id="421"></persName>, Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, Carlisle<persName xml:id="720"></persName>, Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, Truro<persName xml:id="5047"></persName>, and possibly Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName>, Ripon<persName xml:id="2074"></persName>, &amp; Liverpool<persName xml:id="477"></persName>.</p>
         <p>There is a further consideration very weighty in my eyes. If we are to <hi rend="underline">acquiesce</hi> in reservation etc. by the "Catholicks", we must take some positive action w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> makes clear our own position, &amp; restores the balance of things. You will take my meaning, though the phrasing is a trifle cryptic. <hi rend="bold underline">Do brace yourself for a bold course: think, &amp; when the time comes be ready to act. If we c</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> agree generally, we might manage a meeting of Bps</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Yours aff<hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi>,</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote the above to the Bishop of Bristol. He is rather timorous, though at bottom sound</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The main rocks in the way are two: (1) the notion that as the Abp.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> is arranging yet another conference, we ought to abide its issue before taking action for ourselves; (2) the dread of friction within our own dioceses. Still I think there is a chance that a sufficient number will bring themselves to the point of making a venture.</p>
         <p>I got up for lunch, &amp; afterwards did some indispensable clearance in my study. The atmosphere became exceedingly sultry &amp; enervating, with the usual consequence to my head &amp; temper. <hi rend="bold underline">There can be no doubt that these "Hereford heats" are very depressing to body &amp; soul.</hi> If the income tax is raised next year – a contingency which must be allowed to be extremely probable – I shall be unable to continue residence in this house. <hi rend="bold underline">In that event we must make an effort to discover some suitable small house which we can occupy in a vigourous air. The Palace under the combined charge of Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> at the Lodge, &amp; Jones in the garden, would serve as an episcopal office</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I think nobody will be surprised if we have to leave in view of the rapid and continuing increase of taxes, rates, &amp; prices. In any event, "necessity is relentless".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>