<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Another brilliant day, and very warm. The post brought me an affectionate letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi><persName xml:id="554"></persName>, in which he gives me the important news that he expects to add paternal responsibility to his other cares at an early date. This is excellent, for no marriage can be truly called successful where there are no children. The heat of the weather made activity irksome; so I stayed within doors and read "<hi rend="underline">Tom Jones</hi>". It is a very great book in spite of its grossness: and I doubt if its reading would do harm to any healthy&#8211;minded person, and the unhealthy&#8211;minded would get harm from anything. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to Ross for some meeting. <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir John</hi><persName xml:id="2244"></persName><hi rend="italic"> and Lady </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Struthers</hi><persName xml:id="2708"></persName><hi rend="italic"> came for a short visit. After dinner we all strolled in the garden in the moonlight, and talked until the bell rang for prayers. Sir John thinks that female teachers will be far more largely used in the Scottish schools than heretofore. He gives an ill account of the temper of the male teachers, who are cynically insistent on their own claims, &amp; quite destitute of the true teacher's spirit. In all this his testimony does but accord with the witness of others. Largely drawn from artisan homes, the teachers imbibe in their childhood the Trade&#8211;union spirit, &amp; grow up in the Trade&#8211;union atmosphere. What wonder, therefore, that they act according to Trade&#8211;union principles?</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>