<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The wet weather continues, and begins to threaten the harvest. I walked round to the "<hi rend="underline">Hereford Times</hi>" Office, and had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bex</hi><persName xml:id="4922"></persName>, the editor, about the function on Saturday. <hi rend="bold underline">He said that he had often seen me on the Thames Embankment when I was living in Westminster. </hi>After an early lunch I attended a meeting of the Diocesan Board of Finance, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi><persName xml:id="4456"></persName> resigned the Secretaryship on the urgent plea of his doctor's imperative orders. I made a short speech expressing the obligations of the diocese to his zeal &amp; ability. Later in the afternoon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="553"></persName> arrived. They brought their Aberdeen, 'Pepper' with them. After tea I took <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi> for a walk, but it rained all the time, &amp; I was quite comfortless.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Money&#8211;Kyrle</hi><persName xml:id="4330"></persName> had an interview with me about the person whom he wished to engage as curate, and whom I declined to license. I satisfied him that the reasons for my refusal were adequate, &amp; he went away pacified &amp; perplexed. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Beattie</hi><persName xml:id="4506"></persName> came to see me about the Memorial Service on Sunday. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came to settle a number of points relating to the Diocesan Conference, and the Examination of Ordination candidates. <hi rend="bold underline">Thus was frittered away yet another day in the futilities of diocesan administration</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It is difficult to persuade one's self that any purpose of real value is being served by this manner of life.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>