<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Felton, &amp; viewed the piece of glebe which the vicar &amp; churchwarden desire to use for a parish room, to be erected as a war memorial. The population of the two parishes – Felton &amp; Preston Wynne – is little more than 200, yet the killed number no less than 10. <hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Evelegh<persName xml:id="4957"></persName>, the parson is helplessly deaf, a circumstance the more regrettable as his countenance and manner suggest an intelligent &amp; courteous man</hi>. The churchwardens were there to meet, prosperous men &amp; not without brains.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Creswell, the widow of the late Vicar of Yarkhill, came to see me. She has no money to meet the demand for dilapidations (c. &#x00A3;140). Her husband was vicar for barely 2 years. I gave her an application form for the Harley Trust<orgName xml:id="308"></orgName>.</p>
         <p>This day was again wasted. The extreme fineness &amp; warmth of the weather almost compelled an indolence which, however, those circumstances could not excuse. I began a letter on the vexed question of Holy Communion v. Mattins as 'the principal service on the Lord's Day', but made little progress. Major has a letter in the Times suggesting as a possible compromise the amendment of the Enabling Bill by 'reserving' the main points of the Establishment. I am not sure that it is not somewhat premature to speak of compromise until the fate of the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Reading has been decided.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>