<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The rain seems to have fallen throughout the night, and it was still falling when I set out for the Confirmation at <hi rend="underline">Kinlet</hi>. This will have damped the popular enthusiasm, &amp; possibly extinguished the festal bonfires: <hi rend="bold underline">but it will accord with the melancholy which reigns in every considering citizen's mind</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I started in the motor at 9 a.m., &amp; proceeded by way of Leominster, Brimfield, &amp; Cleobury Mortimer to Kinlet, which I reached about 10 minutes after 11 a.m. The Vicar, Prebendary <hi rend="doubleunderline">Payton</hi>, was at the porch waiting with some anxiety for my appearance. I confirmed 21 candidates. There should have been 22, but one – a girl described as the best loved person in the parish – had died suddenly yesterday to the grief of everybody. I lunched very pleasantly with Colonel<persName xml:id="4958"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Childe</hi>. The latter is a Swede. The parish church of S. John is most interesting. It has four remarkable monuments of the Cornewall &amp; Blount families. Also a chantry of S. Catherine wonderfully preserved. After lunch I motored to <hi rend="underline">Tenbury</hi>, arriving five minutes late. The rain ceased about 3 p.m. I consecrated an addition to the churchyard after preaching in the church. <hi rend="bold underline">Preb. Ragg &amp; his son declared themselves Socialists, rather to my surprise. The world changes</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> We had a pleasant run home, arriving about 7.10 p.m. The evening lights were beautiful.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>