<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Thirty two years have passed on such a glorious day in June as this I was ordained in Cuddesdon Parish Church. I had little vision of what the course of my life was to be: <hi rend="bold underline">but it was certainly the case that I was not consciously ambitious of advancement in the Church. My mind then was powerfully attracted by the ascetic ideal, &amp;, though Biblical criticism had moved many questions, I should probably have called myself a "Catholic". I was drawn towards the poor, and almost immediately accepted the Headship of the Oxford House<orgName xml:id="15"></orgName> in Bethnal Green. But I was very ignorant of the world, and very ignorant of myself. And now I look ^back^ upon a ministry which has been stormy throughout. Laborious and painfully conscientious always, though marked by strange personal failures. May the All Merciful Saviour, whose Yoke I have borne, forgive the faults &amp; failures of my course</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>When I told the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> in the Vestry after the Celebration at 8 a.m. that it was the completion of 32 years since my Ordination, he said "I congratulate you". The formula is suggestive, &amp; from some points of view, surprising. I recall M. Arnold's<persName xml:id="1460"></persName> "The Lord's Messengers", a very pathetic little poem. </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Some in the tumult are lost. </p>
         <p>Baffled, bewilder'd, they stray. </p>
         <p>Some as prisoners, draw breath. </p>
         <p>Some, unconquer'd are crossed </p>
         <p>(Not yet half through the day)</p>
         <p>By a pitiless arrow of death.</p>
         <p>Hardly, hardly shall one </p>
         <p>Come, with countenance bright,</p>
         <p>At the close of day, from the plain;</p>
         <p>His Master's errand well done,</p>
         <p>Safe through the smoke of the fight,</p>
         <p>Back to his Master again. </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> went with me to Weobley, where I instituted the new Vicar, Edwards<persName xml:id="4552"></persName>, &amp; preached a sermon. A contingent of his former parishioners had chartered a brake, &amp; come over from Kimbolton to attend the service. Afterwards we were entertained at lunch by old Sir Joseph Verdin<persName xml:id="5043"></persName>, who showed us his beautiful gardens with much pride. Later I motored to Bullinghope, accompanied by Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName>. The Vicar, Riddell<persName xml:id="4840"></persName>, had been stung by a bee in the foot, and could not stand. So I read the service as well as preached the sermon. There was a good congregation which filled the little church. I am perforce reverting to the practice of preaching from notes. There is no time to write sermons, &amp; the simplicity of these country congregations makes elaborate compositions unedifying. The peacock from the veterinary surgeon who lives next to the Palace has apparently taken up its residence in the garden.	</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I received a letter from Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> stating that Sir Lewis Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName> had written to suggest a conference on the Enabling Bill. This would indicate that the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> is attempting a compromise</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">But it is hard to see how any compromise is really possible on the main question raised by the Bill.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>