<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The view from my dressing room window was magnificent. On the left the great hill rose out of a girdle of blue mist into a blue sky, &amp; showed clear&#8211;cut &amp; radiant under the morning sun. The meadows in the fore&#8211;ground gleamed with a million dew&#8211;drops like glittering diamonds. A procession of 8 pea&#8211;hens with one proprietary peacock moved with dignity along the grass. There was a perfect stillness, so that not a leaf stirred, but a faint humming of insects filled the air. Heaven preserve me from the fate of those undone spirits, of whom it is true that "<hi rend="underline">no grandeur now in nature or in book, Delights them</hi>." Still my mind delights in, and finds refreshment from "<hi rend="underline">Nature's old felicities</hi>". The generous prodigality which marks the Creator's gift of natural beauty is a revelation of Himself, for which I thank Him. If we can see our way to believe in a personal Creator, then the beauty of the World is as truly a disclosure of His character as the moral law, which our consciences attest. Cruelty &amp; ugliness cannot be allowed a revealing function because these conflict with the evidence of our moral and aesthetic faculties. Their presence in Nature is a separate problem, very dark &amp; difficult, which forms a large part of the ultimate question, whether indeed we <hi rend="underline">can</hi> see our way to believe in a personal Creator.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[139]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Blakiston</hi><persName xml:id="4925"></persName> and I walked to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Ninian's, &amp; attended service in the parish church. The rest followed in the motor. The parish church is the meanest conceivable "place of worship". It is a comparatively modern building. There is nothing left of the former church but the tower, which now serves as a <hi rend="underline">campanile</hi>. The cheese&#8211;paring economy of the "heritors" was certainly more evident than the "beauty of holiness". A congregation of about 300 persons, which about half&#8211;filled the building, assembled. <hi rend="bold underline">I was struck by the absence of boys &amp; youths. The choir consisted of young females</hi>, &amp; there was a considerable contingent of "girl&#8211;guides", but the boys were conspicuous by their absence. The parish&#8211;minister, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Jones</hi>, conducted the service, and preached the sermon. He is said to have volunteered for service in the ranks, &amp; to have gone through the war as a private in the Artillery. He had an unpleasing habit of swaying to and fro as he preached, which made it difficult to look at him comfortably. I was not displeased by the sermon, &amp; concluded that the congregation, which was very attentive, was probably edified. After luncheon I sate with mine host<persName xml:id="42"></persName> &amp; Blakiston on the front steps of the mansion, &amp; talked politics hard – an interesting but unfruitful performance. The pleasantness of the air made life out of doors extremely attractive.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi> [symbol] </p>
         <p>We had tea on an island in the lake. It would be impossible to find a more beautiful spot. The Sauchie Rocks in three vast natural bastions formed an impressive feature on the one hand, a wide stretch of bracken interspersed with heather extended on the other. In the foreground was the still surface of the lake, &amp; far in the distance rose the noble &amp; varied mountains. The walk home through the Woods in the evening sunlight was a thing to be remembered. Nothing could exceed the beauty of the shadows on the Ochill Hills. <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Steele&#8211;Maitland</hi><persName xml:id="42"></persName> <hi rend="italic">[Steel&#8211;Maitland] talked much of his plans. He is undoubtedly a man of considerable ability, and of ambition perhaps even </hi><hi rend="italic underline">more</hi><hi rend="italic"> considerable than his ability justifies. He is only 43, and has already made a figure in politics. His marriage has given him social consideration, and a fair income. He is industrious, handsome, and a good speaker. I do not think he is likely to embarrass his political career by an inconvenient loyalty to his principles, not because he is an insincere man, but because he really has no convictions firm enough to be described as principles. He is in this respect a thoroughly representative politician. He likes popularity and prominence. With favourable conditions he may play an important and considerable r&#x00F4;le in the politics of the next 20 years.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>