<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the forenoon I had two interviews (1) with the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">W. A. Norman</hi><persName xml:id="5001"></persName>, Rector of Mamble with Bayton, (2) with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Norman Stanley Kidson</hi><persName xml:id="4983"></persName> of Ridley Hall, Cambridge, who desires to be ordained to a curacy next Advent in Kington. Then a note came from the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> announcing his indisposition. So I had to go to Ashperton, &amp; discuss the question of the school alone. The two parsons – Randle &amp; Hunt – turned up. After the meeting, at which it was decided to continue the school, I went to tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Hopton</hi>. After tea <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; Captain &amp; Madame Crapon, came to pick me up, &amp; were walked round the gardens. Then we went home under a threatening sky, from which rain fell. We hoped that the long desired rain had at last arrived, but nothing considerable came. The Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Webb<persName xml:id="5051"></persName> his chaplain arrived. <hi rend="bold underline">Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="5059"></persName> came to dinner. He brought the news that his brother<persName xml:id="4449"></persName>, the Dean of Bristol, was engaged to be married! How are the mighty fallen</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> The electric light failed in the course of dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> writes that the Bishop of Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName> has offered him the Canonry &amp; Professorship which Knowling<persName xml:id="473"></persName> has resigned, &amp; asks my advice. I had not the smallest hesitation in counselling him to cleave to his Deanery. He would find the Durham work very unpalatable now.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>