<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote at some length to the Bishop </hi>^<hi rend="italic">of Manchester</hi>^<persName xml:id="242"></persName><hi rend="italic"> with reference to his suggestion that, in view of the progress of the Enabling Bill, we should go in for a policy of intercommunion with Nonconformists. I must needs doubt the wisdom of such a course. It would place weapon in the hand of our enemies, &amp; immerse us in many practical embarrassments. I think, however, that it might be well for such of the Bishops as can act together to put forward a manifesto announcing their intention to authorize exchange of pulpits &amp; specifying the conditions. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">If we could take some action which would visibly disprove the claim of the "spikes" that the English Church is not Protestant, the consequences might be considerable. Even a secession might be induced</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I am reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">Crabbe's</hi><persName xml:id="4948"></persName> poetry to the ladies after dinner. Certainly the picture he draws of rural England is extremely unattractive, and squalid. Would a similarly honest, and well&#8211;informed, description given today by a country parson as able &amp; discerning, be equally so? Certainly, the witness of the clergy and "purity" workers is sufficiently disconcerting. Yet a revolution in the conditions of the agricultural labourer's life has been effected during the last half century, &amp; surely it has been mainly for his good.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>