<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I prepared a sermon for the Oxford Freemasons</hi> by combining a Thanksgiving Sermon preached last year in Hereford cathedral and an address to the Durham Freemasons delivered in that Cathedral. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rushton</hi><persName xml:id="4842"></persName> of All Saints came to see me about Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>: Prebendary <hi rend="doubleunderline">Seaton</hi><persName xml:id="4672"></persName> came to lunch. I instituted several clergy, including <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tallents</hi><persName xml:id="4860"></persName> to Kimbolton. After lunch I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName> on my letter<ref xml:id="1094"></ref> which appeared in today's <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, alongside of letters from the Bishops of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> and Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>. Miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mundella</hi><persName xml:id="2712"></persName> arrived on a visit, &amp; was soon followed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne Booker</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It will be interesting to see how the ecclesiastical situation develops. In any case, the near approach of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> gives a special importance to these disclosures of the episcopal mind. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">So far the Bishops of Oxford<persName xml:id="49"></persName> and Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> – the "great twin brothers" as I have dubbed them in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName> – alone have spoken against the Norwich plan. The Bishops of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, Carlisle<persName xml:id="720"></persName>, Manchester and Hereford have taken the other line. Will any more of their Lordships take a hand in the game? If the Liberal &amp; Evangelical Bishops had any insight and any courage, they would rally at once to the Norwich platform, and destroy the possibility of Gore &amp; Talbot's pretence to speak for the English Church being ever allowed to pass. But mostly they are as blind as bats, and as fearful as hares</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>