<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> went off in his motor after breakfast. I received a letter from Archbishop S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> accepting my undertaking to lecture in Upsala in Sept&#8211;Oct: 1920. I finished making a summary of my Abbey sermon, and sent it off to K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> for the '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>'.</p>
         <p>I presided at a meeting of the Poor Benefices Augmentation Fund, &amp; agreed to invest &#x00A3;6500 <hi rend="underline">in the new War Loan</hi>. I instituted 4 clergymen, including Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> to Ballingham, and Pelly<persName xml:id="4654"></persName> to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Devereux.</p>
         <p>I presided at a meeting of the Kemble Theatre, at which the work of the Church Army huts was exhibited on a film – a performance more dizzy than edifying.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then I wrote a series of letters, including one to the Moderator of the C. of Scotland (Prof. W.P. Paterson) thanking him for his address to the Gen: Assembly, and sending him a copy of "The Church of England". I observe with melancholy interest that the bigotry of the High Church faction is telling on the attitude of the Presbyterians of the Established Church. They are inclining under the pressure of a natural resentment towards the Nonconformists, with whom there are obvious ties of friendship. There is also a re&#8211;action against the Anglicising tendencies of the late Moderator.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>