<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At noon the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> and I motored to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Stoke Lacey</hi><hi rend="italic">, and lunched with Prebendary Morgan, the patron and vicar, an excellent man of the squarson type, very useful in the local government of the district, &amp; generally respected. After lunch he motored us to the adjacent parishes of Avonbury [sic] and Stanford Bishop, where we were received by the vicars, Archer&#8211;Shepherd<persName xml:id="4919"></persName>, and Naylor<persName xml:id="4999"></persName>, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">and discussed with them the question how Avonbury could best be extinguished as a separate parish, &amp; either divided up between the other parishes, or wholly annexed to one of them</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The church at Avonbury is situated in a hollow, far from the parishioners. It is not without architectural interest, &amp; has some fine 15</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century benches. Stanford Bishop is notable for a mighty yew tree in the churchyard, of immense antiquity, far the largest I have ever seen. The parson, Naylor, gave us tea, &amp; introduced his daughter, and a son who was about to start his course at Wells Theological College with a view to taking Holy Orders. The church at Stanford Bishop is set out by itself on a rising ground with a very noble prospect, but quite remote from the parishioners. What suitableness have buildings thus placed for those new uses, non&#8211;religious &amp; semi&#8211;religious, to which the Bishops would put them? They are difficult of access, inconvenient in their arrangements, unwarmed, &amp; ill lighted – who would frequent them for comfort or amusement? </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>