<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote letters in the club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; then went to the Academy &amp; looked at a very poor show of pictures. Then, falling in with Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>, I walked in the Park until lunch. Then I returned to the Club, &amp; lunched. After this I walked into the City, &amp; attended a meeting of the Royal Society of Health in the Mansion House. I proposed the vote of thanks to the Lord Mayor. Then I went to Bloomsbury Square, &amp; attended a meeting of the Council of the Royal Society of Literature<orgName xml:id="107"></orgName>. Lord Crewe<persName xml:id="1056"></persName> presided, &amp; Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName> was the chief speaker. Gosse<persName xml:id="2083"></persName> was there, &amp; Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>. I dined with Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Sir Ryland Adkins<persName xml:id="4918"></persName> was there, &amp; I had much talk with him about the Enabling Bill. He is a Nonconformist, but not ill&#8211;disposed to the Church. He did not speak very warmly of the Bishop of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName>, who seems nowise a strong man, for good or for ill</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>I was distressed to see how thin and white Antonia<persName xml:id="5018"></persName> has become. No doubt the death of her little brother<persName xml:id="4721"></persName> is a grievous experience for so young a girl. She carried herself admirably throughout, but she has evidently been fretting. I got back to the Hotel about 11.30 p.m. Taxis are practically unobtainable, but the underground served my turn well enough.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>