<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The spirit of dissipation inseparable from a Bank Holiday being in the air, I abandoned the effort to do any work, &amp; went off with Olive<persName xml:id="1696"></persName> and the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="383"></persName> to see churches, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Spooner<persName xml:id="2162"></persName> having left by a morning train. We motored first to Abbey Dore, then to Kilpeck, finally to Madley, getting home in good time for lunch. It would be difficult even in England to find a trinity of parish churches superior in beauty and interest. A slight rain during the night had laid the dust, so that motoring was relieved of its worst drawback. In the afternoon I remained in my study, &amp; wrote letters. Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came to dine, and we had some interesting conversation. Then Olive sang divinely, &amp; we made an end of another day.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ralph Guy<persName xml:id="4970"></persName>, the Vicar of Claverley, tells me that his Easter Vestry agreed unanimously to condemn the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">The 'Times' contains another protest against the Bill from a Nonconformist. This time it is Guttery<persName xml:id="4969"></persName>, the Methodist, who takes up his parable. The disgusting self&#8211;complacency of these sectaries makes one regret the more that they should have so strong a case. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Disestablishment is the true d&#x00E9;nouement of the "Life &amp; Liberty" agitation</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>