<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I took <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wardle</hi><persName xml:id="5046"></persName> to see All Saints. He showed some interest in the chains of the chained library, and in the timber&#8211;work of the roofs. Then I showed him round the Cathedral, where he brightened up at the sight of the "<hi rend="underline">Mappa Mundi</hi>", &amp; was curious over the old episcopal chair. He confided to me his opinion that Lichfield was the finest of all the English Cathedrals! <hi rend="italic bold underline">I asked him if the artisans cared for these glorious buildings; &amp; he answered that he thought they lay so far outside their lives that they had no use for them</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> He went back to London by the 12.50 p.m. train. </p>
         <p>Two clergymen came to lunch on business about their parishes &#8211; Rev. E. K. Venner<persName xml:id="5042"></persName>, Rector of Monnington&#8211;on&#8211;Wye, and Rev. W. F. Serjeantson<persName xml:id="5026"></persName>, Curate of Acton Burnell. The one wants an exchange; the other is in doubt about accepting the living of Frodesley. After they had gone, I wrote to the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> asking for his consent to my licensing Serjeantson to live out of Frodesley. Then Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I motored to Bromyard, &amp; I preached to a rather small congregation at a Harvest Festival. The Vicar, Rev. J. F. S. Pritchitt<persName xml:id="5014"></persName>, is a High Churchman of a conventional type, and has rather an obstinate face. He has set up a war&#8211;memorial in the side&#8211;chapel which causes (I suspect) some resentment in his parish. The congregation did not exceed 300 out of a population of 1600 at a Harvest Thanksgiving! William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> burned his face by the explosion of an acetylene lamp just before we started for our return journey. We were back at the Palace by 10 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" contains a remarkable letter from the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> in which he threatens to exercise episcopal functions in every English diocese whose Bishop has adopted the Bishop of Norwich's<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> modest scheme for exchanging pulpits. The letter is almost comical in its extravagance, and its reception by the "Catholicks" will be an interesting &amp; serviceable disclosure of their attitude. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="105"></persName><hi rend="italic"> must needs be considerably embarrassed by their ardent friend &amp; disciple. It is not to be supposed that Zanzibar has acted without much deliberation with his friends, and it is certain that his attitude in the Kikuyu episode endeared him to a large body of ardent folk. These will be slow to abandon so acceptable a leader. Moreover I suspect that there is a considerable volume of fanaticism, which has with difficulty been suppressed for some years past, &amp; which is only waiting for a good opportunity in order to flare out quite irrepressibly. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Darwell Stone's<persName xml:id="4414"></persName> "League of Catholic Priests" is said to number as many as 700 English clergymen: that would probably include all the "Zanzibarbarians" and a good many others who would think twice before passing from "tall talking" to schismatical action</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">This is only 1 in 30 of the established clergy at most, &amp; probably not more than half of them would be ready to face the sacrifices involved in secession. The Church could stand that.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>