<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Our plans have been disconcerted by a letter from Cloan saying that the Haldanes [Steel&#8211;Maitlands]<persName xml:id="42"></persName><persName xml:id="701"></persName> cannot conveniently receive us on the 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> inst. This fell in with the message from the Argyll Company that they could not have the car ready before that day. So we arranged with Dorothy<persName xml:id="950"></persName> to stay here until the 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, &amp; then to motor to Sauchieburn.</p>
         <p>I read through the Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="234"></persName> speech in the House last night. It is uncomfortable reading. The situation of the country is threatening in the last degree.</p>
         <p>We (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I, with our hosts) lunched with Lord Glasgow<persName xml:id="4927"></persName> and his wife. Kelburn contains a tower &amp; some rooms of 1581: but most part of the house dates from 1700, and one part is as recent as 1896. Lord G has recently returned from naval service in the far East. He describes the Bolsheviks as monstrous, murderous folk, whose criminal misgovernment cannot last much longer: but he seemed to have made no real effort to understand their political creed, &amp; owned that "he had never seen a Bolshevik".</p>
         <p>Charles Parker<persName xml:id="290"></persName> went off to his business in London, and I had the more conversation with his two brothers, Edmund<persName xml:id="5002"></persName> and Ernest<persName xml:id="5003"></persName>, the first has lived long in California, the last is an officer in the Navy. We prolonged our discussion until close on midnight. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>