<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">National Thanksgiving, 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A dull morning but without rain. I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion, using the Form set forth by the Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName>. There were about 60 communicants. The special service of Thanksgiving was attended by the Mayor and Corporation. The cathedral was well&#8211;filled, &amp; the service was stately and moving. The Dean<persName xml:id="3741"></persName> read the special exhortation &amp; act of Thanksgiving very impressively, and I preached the sermon. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After lunch I motored to Bridstow, &amp; there instituted Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> to the vicarage of that parish</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> in wig &amp; gown went with me. Also <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Herbert<persName xml:id="2285"></persName>. The little church was quite full. I preached from the words "<hi rend="underline">Feed My Sheep</hi>": &amp; I spoke strongly in commendation of Knight. I hope it was a good start for his ministry there. Then I went to Ross, &amp; had tea with Money Kyrle<persName xml:id="4330"></persName>. He had got the High Sheriff (Trafford<persName xml:id="5037"></persName>) and his wife to meet me. They seemed to be pleasant &amp; friendly people. I preached in the parish church to a large congregation from the words: <hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Jesus said unto them. Would ye also go away? Simon Peter answered &amp; said unto him. Lord, to whom shall we go: Thou hast the words of eternal life</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi> The collection was for the C.M.S.<orgName xml:id="124"></orgName>, and I worked in an appeal for that society by dwelling on the increase of imperial responsibilities imposed on Great Britain by the Peace Treaty. We did not stay for supper, but motored back to Hereford immediately after the service, arriving about 8.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>