<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A glorious summer's morning. I didn't go to church at 8 a.m., as I had to prepare notes for my sermon at Pembridge. At 10 a.m., I started in the car for Pembridge, and arrived at the church in good time for service at 11 a.m. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Green&#8211;Pryce<persName xml:id="4237"></persName>, the Rector, was at the gate to receive me, &amp; the bells rang merrily from the quaint belfry. The service was Mattins &amp; Ante&#8211;Communion with sermon. Sir Elliott Wood<persName xml:id="4493"></persName> read the lessons very well, and I preached from Acts XVII.29. "<hi rend="underline">Being then the offspring of God, we ought not to think that the Godhead is like unto gold, or silver, or stone, graven by art &amp; device of man</hi>". There was a fair congregation from the village. I counted 40 grown men. But the population, which is, however, scattered, is said to amount to as many as 995. I lunched at the Rectory, where were also M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Beeby from Old Radnor. After lunch I returned to Hereford. After a short interval I motored to Ledbury, and there preached at Evensong in the parish church. The congregation was not so large as the Vicar's assurances had led me to expect. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> went with me at his own request. The sermon was an old one on Jacob's dream. I motored back to Hereford immediately after service, and arrived in the Palace about 9 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>