<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[217]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> arrived. It is dated from Singapore on Sept. 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. He says that he arrived there on the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and found a budget of letters including mine of July 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> and July 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. He asks me to address letters to S.S. Eurypalus, c/o Booth &amp; Co. 17 Battery Place, New York, where he expects to arrive 'about the first week in November'. I got Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> to read through the final chapter of the 'Memoir'<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and also the chapter on the Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName> 'as Churchman'. He said that he thought both very excellent. Accordingly, thus encouraged, I despatched the MS registered to the Clarendon Press. My letter to Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName> undertaking to attempt this work is dated October 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1916. It is a very gross example of the 'ridiculus mus'! I completed a letter to the diocese for publication in the Diocesan Messenger, &amp; sent the MS. in to the Editor. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Stooke&#8211;Vaughan<persName xml:id="5032"></persName>, the Vicar of Wellington Heath, came to see me about leasing Coddington Rectory: &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Craft, the diocesan secretary of <orgName xml:id="4538">S.P.G.<orgName xml:id="23"></orgName></orgName> came to organize his annual meeting. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Selbie Lennie<persName xml:id="4987"></persName> came to talk over Ordination. All stayed to lunch. Godfrey &amp; Dorothea<persName xml:id="2768"></persName> took their departure after lunch. In the evening I presided in the Town Hall over a meeting in aid of S.P.G. It was not very well attended, and the speeches were neither illuminating nor effective. I undertook to preach in All Souls on All Souls Day.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>