<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[224]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I attended the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. and received the Holy Communion. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ruth</hi><persName xml:id="2161"></persName> took me in to hear the Archdeacon's<persName xml:id="383"></persName> sermon. After service I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Venn</hi>, &amp; had some talk with her.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Dover<persName xml:id="3920"></persName> came to lunch, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">talked ardently of the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="italic">. His boisterous confidence fills me with depression &amp; dismay. You cannot discuss the policy with a man who never dreams of doubting that whatever policy his superiors approve needs no other commendation. You cannot debate the principles implied in the policy with a man who has never analysed conduct, or looked beneath the surface of life. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Bilbrough</hi><hi rend="italic"> is totally conventional, an excellent specimen of the type of the successful parish priest. I hear without surprise that he is extremely popular with the clergy, whose ideals &amp; prejudices he shares, &amp; whose interests he advocates.</hi></p>
         <p>We visited the ruins of S. Augustine's monastery. They are extensive &amp; full of interest. I had tea with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dean<persName xml:id="212"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wace<persName xml:id="3786"></persName></hi>, &amp; then revised my sermon.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation in the Cathedral when I preached at the second Evensong, but the military element so conspicuous in recent years had nearly disappeared. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>