<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[223]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Talbot</hi> after breakfast, &amp; then revised the sermon for tomorrow.</p>
         <p>The "Times" reports the decision on the Bredwardine case. <hi rend="bold underline">A very strong Bench decides that churchwardens must reside in the parish</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Thus <hi rend="doubleunderline">Compston</hi><persName xml:id="2010"></persName> is condemned &amp; he will be both humiliated and impoverished. It is not improbable that he will lose heart, &amp; throw up his living. I begin to think that in sending him to that parish I made a mistake.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wandered into the City, &amp; walked round the Dame John where a busy sale of horses, cattle &amp; sheep was proceeding. Then (having the Archdeacon's<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> keys) I went into the cathedral, and walked about it, observing &amp; reflecting. What will the future of these immense &amp; inscrutable monuments be? All over them is the limitless pride of nobles &amp; prelates. They enshrine a challenge to "democracy" in every corner, and are almost insolently contemptuous of everything that is utilitarian. What use has "Labour" for these glorious 'sepulchres'?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We had a great talk after tea about ecclesiastical and religious questions. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot</hi> bore himself with admirable temper, though, of course, all I say must needs be odious to him. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard Holland</hi><persName xml:id="4975"></persName> came to dinner, looking more cadaverous &amp; spectral than ever!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>