<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Grant, O Lord, that my preaching this day may help, and not hinder the cause of justice and peace. Pour out upon us the spirit of reasonableness and goodwill, and restrain the evil forces of the enemy, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Cathedral. At 11 am. the nave seemed quite full. I had to suppress the coughing of the choirboys &amp; school at the beginning of the sermon, but had no reason afterwards to complain of my audience, which listened closely throughout. I must have preached for fully 45 minutes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="i bold">(</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Varro, B.C. 116&#8211;28, was the author of the familiar saying, "God made the country, but man made the town".)</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I motored to Leysters, and there I preached in the little parish church, which was crowded for their Harvest Thanksgiving. Everything was well enough, except for the Vicar's appeal for the congregation there &amp; then to hold up their hands as a token of their resolve to raise &#x00A3;100 for restoring the church. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This was a vulgar touch which surprised me until I heard that Fortescue<persName xml:id="4760"></persName> had been an auctioneer's clerk before taking Orders. But the "free &amp; easy" manners now fashionable among the junior clergy, who are said to model themselves on a mission preacher called Walter Carey<persName xml:id="4937"></persName>, are disconcerting</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[203]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Major Prescott<persName xml:id="5013"></persName>, the patron of Leysters, &amp; the next parish Bockleton, came to supper together with the Vicar of Bockleton, Rev. E. S. Hewitt<persName xml:id="4971"></persName>, who, I think, is his brother&#8211;in&#8211;law. These parishes ought to be united. The combined populations do not reach a total of 450 and the whole endowment of both would barely reach &#x00A3;400. We motored home through a thick mist, rising from the ground, which made the chauffeur's task very difficult. <hi rend="bold underline">On arriving at the palace about 11 p.m. I was met by the news that the Strike had been settled, and that the men were returning to work at once</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It looks rather like a surrender to the rebels, but we must wait for particulars. I doubt whether my exertions this morning were not superfluous. But this is only one more example of the inconvenience which arises from the increasing tendency to centralize everything. <hi rend="bold underline">The railwaymen are plainly helpless in the hands of their central authorities, which manage all the negotiations, &amp; commit the men to courses of action which they have certainly never considered, &amp; would probably never have approved. But the rest of the public is hardly less helpless</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><persName xml:id="234"></persName> issues a bold statement, on which we all rise up &amp; exert ourselves. Then he 'climbs down', &amp; we are left rather absurdly committed to a patriotic conflict! One had need be a chameleon in order to match the changing requirements of such a world as ours is now becoming.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>