<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent the whole day at Lambeth. There was much to interest and inform. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> made a statement about the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">He said it was "an open secret that it had been supposed that a promise had been obtained that the E.B. w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be introduced in the first days of the Session." Now he had received "an intimation that this was not possible, &amp; this may mean that the Bill will not be introduced before Christmas. Thus the prospects are not bright at this moment. The whole thing is very uncertain &amp; confused at present." His Grace added that this set–back had happened </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">in spite of the fact that 284 members had made known their desire that the Bill sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be introduced</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Later the Archbishop reported, with emphatic exhortation to the strictest secresy </hi>[sic]<hi rend="italic">, the result of a conference on Religious Education bet: Anglicans &amp; Nonconformists under Fisher's presidency. The members included on the Anglican side, the Abp<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, the Bp. of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>, Boyd<persName xml:id="2525"></persName>, A. Riley<persName xml:id="213"></persName>, &amp; Holland<persName xml:id="4976"></persName>: and on the Nonconformist side, Scott Lidgett<persName xml:id="1009"></persName>, Clifford<persName xml:id="57"></persName>, Selbie<persName xml:id="2558"></persName>, and Guttery<persName xml:id="4969"></persName>. The Abp. postulated 3 principles viz. (1) that Religious education is essential: (2) that such education w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be useless unless given by religious &amp; adequately trained men: (3) that religious teaching must be definite. Scott Lidgett accepted these: D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Clifford rejected them &amp; w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">have the Bible</hi> <hi rend="bold">[229]</hi> <hi rend="italic">taught 'lexically': Guttery at once repudiated this, and Selbie agreed with him. The Abp. proceeded to say that, if these principles were conceded, he preferred a national to a denominational system. The Bp. of Manchester stuck out for the dual system. The Roman Catholics and the Teachers are the 2 main obstacles to a settlement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> gave a discouraging account of his dealings with the Revenue officials. I asked about the legal position as to letting Palaces, &amp; was told that a Bishop might not add anything to his statutory income. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I inquired what had been done about London House, &amp; the Bp. of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> explained how he had circumvented the law, &amp; added £1000 to his income. I counselled him to put that money apart, &amp; not keep it for himself: for if attention were drawn to an essentially fraudulent proceeding the discredit w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be great both to himself &amp; to the church</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We had a considerable discussion about Benediction etc. from which it appeared that none of us was really prepared to prosecute. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I explained my policy of anarchy all round as the only practicable course, &amp; I was interested to note that it commanded general assent. It is ludicrous</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I dined with Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers<persName xml:id="2708"></persName>. Sir George Younger<persName xml:id="4464"></persName> was there, &amp; Captain &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Crapon.</hi> 
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>