<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I have spent all my time today on the Strike sermon for tomorrow. <hi rend="bold underline">My difficulty is that the case of the men seems so thoroughly bad that there is nothing to mitigate the condemnation which one must needs express. This gives an aspect of severity to the discourse so unpalatable that it is hardly possible that the men should receive it without resentment. But what can I do but speak what I think</hi><hi rend="bold">? </hi>The Bishop of Peterboro<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> has a letter in the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Times"</hi> hinting that the men have something to say for themselves, and that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Geddes</hi><persName xml:id="4961"></persName> is the stone of stumbling. <hi rend="bold underline">I cannot but think that this prelate is mainly what Bishop Latimer<persName xml:id="4985"></persName> would have called a 'claw&#8211;back'. It is so pleasant to be complimented &amp; belauded as "a Daniel come to judgement" by flattering "Labour"! The wheel has gone full circle: and the clerical toadies of this age do not flatter princes but mobs</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The news today is certainly more serious. Rather surprisingly the attempt to resume negotiations has failed and this morning's papers are full of bellicose language. The Government call for Citizen Guards. I told <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> to give in his name. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> has also done so. The difficulty of keeping order will be considerable in the railway centres &amp; if there are great numbers of other workmen thrown out of employment &amp; the weather becomes wintry, the situation may be serious.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>