<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The strike continues on the whole satisfactorily. There are a few acts of sabotage reported, but mostly good order has been kept. The general unsettlement infects one's mind and makes the performance of duty enormously difficult. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName><hi rend="italic"> motored with me to Kimbolton, where I inducted the new vicar, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Tallents</hi><persName xml:id="4860"></persName><hi rend="italic"> to the parish. In spite of damp &amp; depressing weather a good congregation had come together. The Rural Dean, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Davies</hi><persName xml:id="4189"></persName><hi rend="italic">, Rector of Stoke Prior attended &amp; several of the neighbouring incumbents. The service was reverent, &amp; not unimpressive: but</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I was annoyed by the parson's insistent &amp; clamorous protest against the dilapidation assessment for his late parish</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The amount, &#x00A3;120, did not seem to me excessive in view of the increased price of materials &amp; the rise in wages. It would certainly be the equivalent of no more than &#x00A3;50 five years ago. In this parish there is a lay&#8211;reader bearing the unattractive name </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Urry</hi><persName xml:id="5039"></persName><hi rend="italic"> whose license is the cause of unending friction. The man is rather an unpleasant fellow to look at, and has a bullying manner. He is rougher &amp; more uncultivated in speech &amp; aspect then most men who are given a lay&#8211;reader's commission, &amp; generally causes offence in the parish. The churchwarden told me that he ought not to be entrusted with such work &amp; in short that the parishioners positively refuse to accept him!</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">A note from the Vicar of All Saints informs me of his desire to introduce incense into his church at the next Festival of All Saints, and sending to me a form of Vespers for the dead for my approval</hi><hi rend="i bold">!!</hi><hi rend="italic"> He says that the members of his Church Council have asked him to do this. Now in dealing with this letter I must remember that there can be no question of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">prosecution</hi><hi rend="italic"> for anything that will not carry the clear condemnation of the general conscience. This means that I cannot "bite his head off" as I w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> dearly like to. Nor can I any longer stand frankly on the Law </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">because I am already committed to the policy of 'Anarchy all round' as the only tolerable alternative to the self&#8211;respecting but impracticable course of enforcing the Law</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I have just announced my willingness to sanction the preaching of non&#8211;Anglicans under the conditions of the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, which is certainly illegal under any conditions. It follows that I cannot stand merely on the Law. Nor, though in my heart of hearts I may know that this is the certain condition to which I must finally be brought, can I acquiesce in mere individualism. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Some pretence of episcopal control must be made: some parade of administrative principles must be attempted</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I, as Bishop, will 'acquiesce in' not sanction, any innovations which are (&#x3B1;) congruous with the mind of the Church of England as expressed in her standards and history, and (&#x3B2;) are not repugnant to the wishes of the mass of religiously&#8211;reminded parishioners.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>