<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[222]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The post brought me a volume which may bring trouble. "<hi rend="underline">The Christ &amp; his Critics. An Open Pastoral Letter to the European Missionaries of his diocese by the Rt. Rev. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Weston<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> D.D.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Zanzibar</hi>". It seems to be mainly an elaborate onslaught on the Bishop of Hereford! <hi rend="bold underline">In the train on the way to London</hi> I ran through it, and found it very crude and extravagant. He involves in a comprehensive anathema practically the whole English hierarchy, for the presence of the Bishop of Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName> at my consecration involved the Province of York in the crime! By parity of reasoning the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> will be spiritually contaminated if it admits me to a share in its deliberations! <hi rend="bold underline">I wish the book were less grotesquely violent, for then I could the more properly have made it the text of an Apologia, which on many grounds I desire to write, and which might be of real service not only to my reputation, which matters little, but also to the cause of religious sincerity which matters much</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> got on the train at Ross, &amp; accompanied us to Paddington. I showed him the Zanzibarian fulmination &amp; he also inclined to regard it as too vehement to merit reply, or to have much effect.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>