<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Churchmen believe the Church to be a religious society as much so as a congregational body, as much so as the Roman Catholic body. It has also become in England an Established Church; but it has not therefore ceased to be a religious society, with principles and laws of its own. We have inherited an anomalous state of things, in which the logical inconsistencies show the traces of our keen &amp; repeated struggles; but like other Englishmen, we put up with many anomalies which have come down to us.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dean Church to G.W. Russell Esq. M.P. April 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1881</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">N.B. I quoted this passage in the H. of L. when speaking on the Revised Prayer Book, Dec. 14</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1927. H.D.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 8 communicants, including Lady Eden and Penelope.</hi></p>
<p><hi>After breakfast I revised a sermon on Religion and Education for use at Spennymoor, and wrote a brief &amp; brutal letter to the Editor of the Durham County Advertiser anathematising the pretentious scheme for transforming Durham into a commercial centre. The very suggestion is abhorrent.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[98] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I walked in the Park before lunch. Two miners showed me two coins which they had picked up, as they said, in the Park. I bought them for eighteen pence. One was a George III penny, of no particular interest; the other was a 25 sous piece with the inscription 'Louis XVI Roi des François, 1791. On the side has the date 'L'an 3 de la Liberté'. It may have belonged to one of the French prisoners who worked on the road at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ella and Lady Eden accompanied me to Spennymoor, where I preached at Evensong. My sermon was designed for School Teachers, of whom (as I was assured) about 100 were in the congregation. They had been having what they call a 'Refresher Week', and the attendance in Church was a polite attention to Religion, which they thus 'bowed out' of their work! The Church was well filled, &amp;, of course, the atmosphere was asphyxiating. But the attention was close, &amp; my M.S. was asked for by the Reporters! We returned to Auckland in pouring rain. Lionel was preaching at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Anne's, and Ernest at Stillington. This is, I suppose, Ernest's last Sunday in the diocese. The experiment of a "diocesan Chaplain" will not lightly be repeated.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
