<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. Brockham End.</hi></p>
<p rend="Header">
<hi>The morning was fine after yesterday's deluge, and the rain&#8211;washed landscape seen in the sun&#8211;light was very beautiful. We all attended the morning service in the little parish church of North Stoke. Save for 3 hymns, the service was read, and I thought the effect excellent. The elderly Australian rector preached an excellent little simple edifying sermon from the concluding verses of the 137</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Psalm: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Yes, blessed shall he be that takethy thy children, and throweth them against the stones</hi><hi>". On the whole I have not attended a service which pleased me better for many a long year. The whole congregation including parsons &amp; choir numbered about 20 persons.</hi></p>
<p rend="Header">
<hi>In the afternoon Ella went in to Bath to visit Miss Percival, and Aleck took me out to inspect his plantations. But we were soon driven indoors by a violent thunderstorm, which was accompanied by deluges of rain. After 2 hours it cleared, &amp; the sun shone brightly. Leng drove me into Bath to meet Ella, and we had another but lesser storm!</hi></p>
<p rend="Header">
<hi>On returning to the house, I wrote to William. It pleased me that the gardener here inquired after him in a very friendly way. He seems to have made a good impression, which pleased me the more since it added a confirmation to my own judgement of him.</hi></p>
<p rend="Header">
</body></text></TEI>
