<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>In harvest this year </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>1747</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi><hi> I was presented by John Hay Esq. of Spot, to the church of Cockbarnspath. As my father,&amp; grandfather were always against resisting Providence, I was obliged to accept it. </hi><hi rend="underline">It was an obscure distant place, without amenity, comfort, or society, where if I had been settled, I would have most probably fallen into idleness and dissipation than a course of study</hi><hi>: for preferment is so difficult to be obtained in our Church, and so trifling when you have obtained it, that </hi><hi rend="underline">it requires great energy of mind not to fall asleep when you are fixed in a country charge</hi><hi>. From this I was relieved by great goodluck.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Alex. Carlyle</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="underline">Autobiography</hi><hi>. p. 211</hi></p>
<p><hi>The same thing is said by candid observers in 1927, but it is no longer acquiesced in as inevitable. We assume &#8211; in spite of reiterated disallowance in life &#8211; that the deadening influences of "an obscure distant place, without amenity, comfort, or society "can be effectively counterbalanced by "quiet days", the intermittent exhortations of the bishop and a platform of printed counsels! There is something in the very constitution of human nature which conforms a man to his </hi><hi rend="underline">milieu</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I received a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Leslie Scott, M.P</hi><hi>. asking for my "views about the proposed new prayer book". He adds:</hi></p>
<p><hi>"I always find myself in agreement with what you say about important questions, &amp; if I worry you, please forgive me for attaching importance to your advice.!"</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wrote at once &amp; at some length, enclosing the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>. Also, I sent the letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halsbury</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I read through cursorily, a very careful and illuminating study. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">English Monastic Finances in the Late Middle Ages by R.N. Snape. M.A. Cambridge 1925</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is one of the valuable "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Cambridge Studies in Medieval Life and Thought</hi><hi rend="italic">" which </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">G.G. Coulton</hi><hi rend="italic"> is editing. On the whole the conclusion to which the argument leads is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">decisively unfavourable to the monasteries as they had come to be at the end of the Middle Ages.</hi><hi rend="italic"> There is comparatively little in these later years to be seen beyond a life of easy sauntering comfort. Though extravagant luxury might be absent, ease &amp; plenty were not …. The monk lived comfortably, as comfort went then: he was provided with pocket money for luxuries, apart from those which the ordinary fare of the monasteries gave him." It is a restrained and kindly verdict. Materials exist in abundance for a much harsher judgment. After all, the ease with which the Monasteries were dissolved, tells its own tale.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
