<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A brilliant warm day from morning to nightfall. I made a start on the Edinburgh Article.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Morris Young<persName xml:id="5580"></persName> came to talk about Shildon. He stayed to lunch. Captain Armstrong, and his wife, whom I knew as Eleanor Murray, arrived on a visit: and were soon followed by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Murray, &amp; an American friend named Coolidge. There was lawn–tennis in the afternoon. Lionel returned from his holiday. </hi></p>
<p><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">The awful worries of the Coal Trade position make everything more difficult</hi><hi>" – so writes </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Priestman</hi><hi>, himself a coal–owner, to me this morning. What reception is he likely to give to an appeal for £120,000 for the saving of Durham Castle? Normally, he is a public–spirited and generous man, who might be reasonably counted upon for assistance, but now? </hi><hi rend="underline">If from the coal–owners I turn to the ship–builders, I find no more promising outlook</hi><hi>. That industry is just struggling back into activity after a prolonged period of almost complete paralysis. </hi><hi rend="underline">The Ecclesiastical Commissioners are large land owners and royalty owners. In this character they certainly ought to contribute largely, but when I raised the question with Sir Lewis Dibdin, he swept it aside as if obviously answerable in the negative! Nevertheless, I think it must be raised again. If I write directly to the Archbishop, the letter could hardly be ignored. The Commissioners ought to do for Durham Castle what they did for S. Paul's, viz: make a grant of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">£10,000</hi><hi rend="underline">: but they won't</hi><hi>!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
