<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I received a letter from the Vice&#8211;Chancellor (Prof. Heawood) telling me that the report of the Architect &amp; Engineers who had been directed to examine Durham Castle had been received. It is sufficiently serious:&#8211;</hi></p>
<p><hi>"They agree with the authorities that matters are serious both on the West front and in the wall which supports the Norman Gallery, but speak in terms of high praise of the work that has been done so far and heartily commend M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jones &amp; the contractor. They roughly estimate the sum required to deal with everything at from &#x00A3;100,000 to &#x00A3;150,000 &#8211; something like the figure we have talked about or rather more?"</hi></p>
<p><hi>The raising of so great a sum of money would be a formidable undertaking in any circumstance, but in the present state of our Northumbrian industries appear to be almost hopeless. But it must be attempted. I observe with some alarm the tendency to look to the Bishop, rather than to the University to take the lead in such matters. For my burdens present and prospective are already over&#8211;heavy for my resources: and the whole outlook is so uncertain that one shrinks from incurring responsibilities.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
<p><hi>There came to lunch an interesting clergyman, Canon Ford, who said that he had last met me in Glasgow, when I preached in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Andrew's Hall to the World Sunday School Convention. He was extremely racy &amp; amusing in spite of his age and lumbago &#8211; At his suggestion we made an expedition to Monasterboyce, where we were amazed by the round tower, 3 Celtic Crosses of great beauty, &amp; the ruins of a primitive church. I have never seen any ecclesiastical remains which impressed me more. The rain fell pitilessly, but we went on to the ruins of Mellifont Abbey, which was disappointing. We got back to the house about 8.15 p.m.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I had read through a novel by Canon Sheehan, who is said to be a trustworthy painter of Irish life. &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">Glenemaar, a story of Irish Life</hi><hi>: It was published in 1905, and must be related to the situation then existing in Ireland. The horror and hatred with which the "informer" were regarded, &amp; which went to the length of creating a doctrine of blood&#8211;taint, as ruthless and far less natural than that which severs negroes &amp; Anglo&#8211;Saxons in America, are portrayed with power &amp; pathos. The blending of sentiment &amp; savagery in the Celtic Irish is effectively described.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
