<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. Lytchett Heath, Poole.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Maurice de Bunsen</hi><hi rend="italic"> left after breakfast. Mine host, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Howard Carter</hi><hi rend="italic">, and I went for a long walk, and talked hard all the way. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Carter was very severe in his condemnation of Spritualism. In America he employed the photographer who had been employed previously by Conan Doyle, &amp; for the same purpose viz. managing the slides at public lectures. This man told him that Conan Doyle's spirit–photographs were gross &amp; manifest frauds!</hi><hi rend="italic"> The stories of visitors to the tomb of Tutankhamen who had shortly after their visit died, were entirely baseless, since none of them were allowed to visit the tomb at all. The common belief that the Egyptian tombs were guarded by curses was without foundation. The Egyptians did not curse, but made appeals. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We had some talk about the valuelessness of human testimony, suggested by an observation which Sir Maurice had made at breakfast about the false statements of alleged eye–witnesses of the Bomb–throwing at the King of Spain's wedding which he had himself witnessed.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The death of Zaghlul Pasha</hi><hi> [sic]</hi><hi rend="italic">, which was announced in the papers, pleased Carter greatly. After lunch, Carter also departed, leaving on me a very pleasant impression, all the more pleasant since it was unexpected, for I had heard say that he was a difficult morose man.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Cecil motored Ella and me to Christ Church, where we visited the glorious Priory Church. The roads were very full of motors, and the church was crowded with visitors. I had forgotten that the great Norman nave was builded by my predecessor, Ranulph Flambard. The carved Miserere Stalls are hardly equalled elsewhere. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Our guide directed particular attention to the carved representation of a sermon.</hi><hi> The Fox preaches from the pulpit and draws to himself a congregation of geese! There was no lack of scepticism and ribaldry in the so–called ages of Faith.</hi></p>
<p><hi>At a second–hand bookseller's shop in Christ Church I bought for a shilling apiece, two books of the late M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Gladstone viz: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The state in its Relations with the Church</hi><hi>. London. 1838"; and, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church Principles considered in their Results</hi><hi>. London. 1840". Both are, indeed, obsolete enough now, but they retain a certain historic interest, which makes it worth my while to possess them.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wrote to the Dean of Westminster commending the application for the organist's position which Culley tells me that he has sent in. I do not suppose that there is much likelihood that he will be chosen. His Orders and his age will be against him.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
<p><hi>"She (i.e. Elizabeth Barrett, afterwards M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Browning) was surrounded by that most poisonous &amp; degrading of all atmospheres – a medical atmosphere. The existence of this atmosphere has nothing to do with the actual nature or prolongation of disease. A man may pass three hours of every five in a state of bad health, and yet regard, </hi><hi rend="underline">as Stevenson regarded</hi><hi>, the three hours as exceptional and the two as normal. But the curse that lay on the Barrett household was the curse of considering ill health the natural condition of a human being."</hi></p>
<p><hi>(v. Robert Browning by G.K. Chesterton, "English Men of Letters". London. Macmillan &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o. </hi><hi>p. 60.)</hi></p>
<p><hi>The reference to Stevenson seemed to me so just and happy that, for the sake of it, I got out of bed, and copied it here. At least it will serve to illustrate a passage in my speech in Edinburgh. That speech begins to hang heavy on my spirit. It must take the form of a serious appreciation of R.L.S. as a writer of fiction, and as a man. I am too unfamiliar with fiction to achieve the one, and too unsympathetic with this type of genius to achieve the other! </hi></p>


</p>
<p>
</body></text></TEI>
