<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A brilliant morning. A pair of thrushes and a pair of blackbirds breakfasted busily on the grass before my dressing room window as I dressed, and there was a mingled undertone of cawing rooks and cooing pigeons in the air, with intermittent cock&#8211;crowings to suggest domesticity. A robin sang boldly at intervals. Who would live in Babylon who could escape it? I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. We numbered 10 communicants in all.</hi></p>
<p><hi>After breakfast I wrote a letter to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> in answer to that which appeared yesterday from the Sectary.</hi></p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon we motored to Durham, where I had some talk with my Suffragan, preached to the boys in the Chapel of Durham School, had tea with the Headmaster &amp; the monitors, and returned to Auckland. Ella &amp; Miss Binnington attended Service in the Cathedral.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="underline">The usages</hi><hi> in the Non&#8211;Jurors' Controversy were: 1. a definitely expressed Oblation of the Elements in the Eucharist to God the Father. 2. A direct Invocation of the Holy Spirit upon the Elements they might be made by the Body and Blood of Christ. 3. Such alterations in title &amp; expression in the prayer for the Church on the Great Intercession as wold include the departed as well as the living. 4. The use of the mixed chalice.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
<p><hi>The brilliant weather continued all day. We returned from Durham about 6 p.m. in Sunshine.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
