<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">He was perhaps the most significant preacher of his generation: the only one who suggested to his hearers the presence of a prophetic gift. His sermons before the universities or at S. Paul's were almost always upon moral &amp; social questions.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Beeching on Dean Church in D.N.B.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Certainly, Church's sermons impressed me more than any that I had heard, and there are some which I like better to read. "In a letter (21 Sept. 1857) to a correspondent who consulted him on the cultivation of style, he says </hi><hi rend="underline">the only training in style he had recognised in himself, was watching against the temptation of "unreal" and "fine" words: and he adds that he owed it to Newman, if he could write at all simply &amp; with a wish to be real</hi><hi>."</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I motored to Newbottle, where, in pouring rain I consecrated an addition to the churchyard, &amp; afterwards preached the sermon at Evensong, it being the Patronal Festival of the parish. We returned to Auckland after the service.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Several fanatical letters arrived from Protestants moved to exasperation by my letter to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">. I suppose it is extraordinarily difficult for them to understand how a man </hi><hi rend="italic underline">both</hi><hi rend="italic"> dislike Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, and loathes Protestantism! But I abhor all "enthusiasm"!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
