<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Brockham End.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The post brought a picture&#8211;postcard from James. It was apparently posted at Cristobal on July 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. With the simplicity of youth he adds the words "With love", to his brief statement about the voyage. The Auckland postman may well "open his eyes" when the 'Buttons', thus addresses the 'Bishop', and yet I like it well enough, for it is certainly both natural and sincere. I wrote a number of letters, including a "Collins" to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Pyke Fortesque and a letter of advice to Jimmie.</hi></p>
<p><hi>There came to lunch Lady Horner and her daughters, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Raymond Asquith, who is now a papist. There was also with them a man, whose name I failed to catch, but whose face seemed familiar. He told me that he used to dine at All Souls, and meet me there. He spoke affectionately of W. P. Ker, and Rashdall.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The excavator of Ur, and his wife (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Wooley) came to tea. He told me that </hi><hi rend="underline">Lawrence of Arabia</hi><hi> was his assistant, and a queer creature. I suggested that he had "a screw loose" and he assented. He dissented from the severe judgement on the French in Syria which I suggested, but allowed that Sarrail was an unspeakable ruffian, whom it will take long to "live down". Balfour's mission was, he thought, a grave blunder, which placed the French in a difficult situation. Half the objects discovered have to go to Bagdad, and one quarter come to England.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ella and I went for a 'constitutional' before dinner. The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" devotes its first leader to the Reunion Conference at Lausanne. Advertisement &amp; journalism are the "Jakin and Boaz" of this tabernacle!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
