<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">We left Mount Stewart about 9 a.m.</hi><hi>, parting from our kind host &amp; hostess with real regret. Indeed they must be the perfectest [sic] hypocrites on earth if they are not as kind &amp; hospitable as they seem! We motored to Belfast, &amp; there took tickets for </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Bundoran</hi><hi>. We had a through carriage, &amp; travelled with comfort. The customs on entering the Free State were the merest form. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The officer grinned as he asked me whether I had any deadly weapons</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Gore Booth</hi><hi> met us at the station. We put up at the Great Northern Hotel, which was crowded with golfers. Bundoran is evidently a popular health resort. The general appearance of the visitors suggested that they belonged mainly to the lower&#8211;middle class. Ramsgate &amp; Margate came to my mind at every turn. We walked to Sea View, West, &amp; had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Gore Booth</hi><hi> &amp; her family. We returned to the Hotel for dinner, &amp; afterwards walked along the cliffs for an hour. The view of bay &amp; mountain seen in the glory of a brilliant sun setting was superb. Among the numerous visitors, who were taking the air, were a good many priests, and some soldiers of the Free State Army.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
