<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I was interrupted about 11 a.m. by the Archbishop of Sydney &amp; his son, who were on their way to lunch with the Bishop of Gloucester. He stayed for an hour, &amp; talked much. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He had been at Lausanne, where he said that Headlam made an impression: but he is a man whose judgement is worth little</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi>After lunch I walked round the Park with Fred. Holmes, a lad of 16, whom (he told me) I confirmed at Kelloe. He is the son of a schoolmaster at Willington. Then Kenneth Hodgson called, &amp;, when he had gone his way, I betook myself to the Article, but to no purpose. I read Voltaire's account of the Quakers in the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Dictionnaire Philosophique</hi><hi>". Probably the witty Frenchman's approbation explains much of the popularity which the Quakers have enjoyed among men of the world. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Rufus M. Jones</hi><hi> sets on his first page some words of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph's</hi><hi>, which are curiously wide of the truth as I see it</hi></p>
<p><hi>"The Quakers, of all Christian bodies, have remained nearest to the teaching and example of Christ".</hi></p>
<p><hi>He refers to their munificent charity to the war&#8211;shattered population of Central Europe: and this is, of course, quite admirable, but does it justify the statement that they have "remained nearest" to Christ's Teaching &amp; Example? This munificence in charity is a comparatively recent trait of Quakerism, &amp; it is as much a demonstration of their secular prosperity as it is the disclosure of their spiritual quality. Through the greater part of their history, they did not impress their contemporaries as conspicuously generous.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
