<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. The Priory, Woodchester.</hi></p>
<p><hi>We left Lytchett Heath at 10.30 a.m., and motored to the Priory, Woodchester; a distance of about 110 miles. We stopped at </hi><hi rend="underline">Salisbury</hi><hi> to visit the Cathedral, and lunched very comfortably at </hi><hi rend="underline">Malborough</hi><hi>. At </hi><hi rend="underline">Cirencester</hi><hi> we visited the fine church, of which K. C. Bayley's brother&#8211;in&#8211;law is the Rector. Here I was recognized by the Verger, whose acuteness was rewarded by a tip of two shillings! We arrived at our destination about tea&#8211;time. There was present Sir Ware, who is in charge of the Military Graves. He said that he has heard about me from his friend M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Anstruther.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">Our visit to Evelyn Cecil was certainly very pleasant to us, and I think also to our host &amp; his wife. She is an able &amp; attractive woman, the daughter of Lord Amherst of Hackney</hi><hi>. The two daughters, Margaret and Maud, are pleasant &amp; spritely young ladies, less shamelessly modernized than most of their contemporaries. Maud is to be married in the autumn to some connexion of Steel&#8211;Maitland.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[40] </hi></p>
<p><hi>Mine host has become treasurer of the Conservative Association in his district, and has acquainted himself, or thinks he has, with the political conditions thereof. He thinks that there is a real revival of Liberalism, but that it will not carry many seats. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But the tide is running strongly in the direction of Labour, and the probabilities point to a Conservative </hi><hi rend="underline">débacle</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> at the next election. </hi><hi rend="italic">He told me that the peers &amp; M.P.s were being heavily canvassed by the opponents of the Revised Prayer Book. He doubted, however, whether the effect of this canvassing would be considerable</hi><hi>. The Roman villa has again been covered up, &amp; will not be opened again to the public view for some years. The total gains from its exhibition had been &#x00A3;680: of which &#x00A3;500 had been invested for the due up&#8211;keep of the church&#8211;yard. Thus the ancient pagans are forced to pay tribute to their Christian conquerors!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
