<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">M. Siegfried leads his readers to a startling conclusion which would even appear to be an evident paradox viz: </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that in the Anglo–Saxon world the Roman Catholic Church is the very palladium of individuality</hi><hi rend="italic">. I suppose he reaches it by the identification of Christianity with the Roman version of it, which is natural in a Frenchman, and is practically true for a great part of Christendom. Under the heavy incubus of its elaborated sacerdotalism, &amp; in spite of its gross &amp; pervading superstition, the Roman Church delivers the Christian message, &amp; that must include personal responsibility, the primacy of the spiritual over the material, and the faith in immortality. And these are all flagrantly repudiated by the hungry materialism of Anglo–Saxondom, especially that part of it which exploits the wealth of America. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But everywhere Roman Christendom seems to be reverting to paganism. It is swinishly sensual, selfish, and irreligious</hi><hi rend="italic">, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">having no hope, &amp; without God in the world</hi><hi rend="italic">". Has it any other superiority over America than that which its immemorial culture ensures? And is not the crude materialism of U. S. A. reproducing itself in Europe as fast as the circumstances of European life permit? May not envy, even more than justice, determine our condemnation of the Americans?</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Still, with all discounts made, these American phenomena of 'standardization', 'mass–production', and 'advertisement' are truly horrifying, all the more so since they so plainly fascinate the older world of Europe. On all sides, one hears praise of American business methods: it is becoming a common practice to send young men to New York or some other American city to learn 'modern business': the public is too familiar with admonitions to study &amp; imitate America. And this goes on along with a deepening dislike, &amp; a noisy assertion of it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">For myself, I think that the influence of America on Europe, and especially on Great Britain, where for obvious reasons that influence is specially potent, almost entirely bad</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> What Macedonia was to Greece that U. S. A. is to the northern lands of Europe. It does not understand the culture which it borrows, &amp; its enormous material superiority gives to its crude &amp; impudent procedures an authority to which the heirs of that culture yield with reluctance &amp; self–contempt. Even in the sphere of religion there is no exception to the general rule. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The conference now meeting in Lausanne is only one more illustration of American bombast. It is interesting to note that the English members are mainly concerned with showing that the Conference can do nothing effectual. But the report of the proceedings make excellent "copy" for the papers: &amp; swell the volume of American vanity wonderfully</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I went through the dolorous ritual of packing before descending to breakfast. After breakfast we took a last walk along the cliffs. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We left Bundoran at 11.10 a.m., and travelled to Dandalk</hi><hi>, where we arrived about 4.50 p.m. The train was crowded with holiday folk, and the first class carriages were only preserved for the use of first–class passengers by being locked until they were occupied by the latter. Twice over we were encountered by the ceremonial of a Customs' barrier. At Dundalk we were met by the motor, and carried safely to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephenstown</hi><hi>, where we were received with kindness by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fortescue</hi><hi>. After tea we walked in the demesne. Mine host, who is an Australian, &amp; served as a chaplain with the Australian forces, showed me the trees, many of which are very fine, especially the ash &amp; fir. Dundalk appears to have suffered by the new régime, for not only has the departure of the English withdrawn the considerable sums which they expended in the town, but also the creation of a customs barrier has destroyed the trade with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Newry</hi><hi> &amp; the adjacent districts, which once was considerable. The paper announces the decision of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">De Valera</hi><hi> &amp; his followers to take the oath, and their seats. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">They carefully explain that they intend nothing by the oath beyond the indispensable preliminary of taking their seats, &amp; working for a Republic</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Mine host related to me his history, which was certainly unusual. He was born a Jew in Sidney, and brought up in the orthodox Jewish fashion. To him the human race was represented as falling into two categories, Jews &amp; Christians, and the latter he was taught to regard with loathing as the persistent persecutors of his race. At 13 he was admitted to full membership, &amp; yet he retained the shawl &amp;c which he wore at his admission. I asked what had led him to become a Christian. He said that when a lad he had chanced to hear a street preacher of Christianity, and had been arrested by his declarations about Christ. In due course, he became a Baptist preacher, but was disgusted by the proselytising from other Christian denominations &amp; the emphasis on the Second Advent which was expected of him. When the War broke out, he volunteered to go to Europe as a chaplain with the Australian contingent. He had been wounded, and, when in hospital, had met his wife. He had desired ordination in the Anglican Communion, but his lack of all academic training &amp; association with the Baptist ministry had been insuperable obstacles. However, nothing would induce him to continue in the Baptist ministry. He now lives at home, managing his wife's property. Such was his story, and I doubt not that it is substantially true. I was particularly interested to hear that he found the lack of reverence which marks the general habit of Christians very perplexing, &amp; contrasted it with the awe which Jews were wont to associate with Religion. </hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
