<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>We left Chester in pouring rain at 10.15 a.m. and (changing at Bristol) arrived at Bath at 3.23 p.m. The train was uncomfortably crowded, and the lunch in the dining car immeasurably bad! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Lady Lawrence &amp; John met us at the station, and motored us to Brockham End</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We were taken to tea at a neighbouring house, being nearly overturned by our reckless john, the aforesaid John, on the way. General Bonham Carter, and his very pleasant wife, whose mother, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Fisher, was also there, received us with kindness, and showed us the interesting house which they had purchased. It was connected with Bath Abbey, and has evident tokens of its ecclesiastical origin. In the garden there is a "Wishing Well", at which, observing the prescribed ceremonial, we duly formulated our wishes. For my part I "wished" that I might have wits &amp; will to handle the situation in Durham rightly! I received a letter from Ernest, in which he enclosed a cutting from a local paper. It reported a speech by the local Labour member, Batey, abusive enough of course, but less violent than I had expected. I should be more concerned by such denunciations if I were not well assured that the Labour members are not greatly regarded by their own followers.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
