<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I worked rather helplessly at the Article. Ella led most of the party to Mount Grace to see the pageant, and I walked round the Park. Ralph &amp; Kitty arrived about tea&#8211;time: &amp; the Dean of Westminster &amp; his wife shortly afterwards. Lord Darling and Di arrived by car. So we are rather a large party, with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Murray &amp; her American, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Armstrong &amp; her husband.</hi></p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice Roche writes:&#8211;</hi></p>
<p><hi>"I was talking to young Halsbury some weeks back, &amp; found him like so many of us laymen suspicious about the Prayer Book &amp; inclined to oppose. Finding, as was not unnatural, that he respected your opinion, I told him to talk to you, &amp; he promised to do so, &amp; be guided thereby. I fancy he is not without influence amongst the younger peers &amp; lay politicians generally and therefore such a talk may be worth while."</hi></p>
<p><hi>I have never met </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halsbury</hi><hi>, so that I hardly see how to get at him. It might, perhaps, be worth while to send him the copy of the Bishoprick which contains the E.R. article.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Our dinner party numbered 16, viz: the house&#8211;party, with the General from Catterick and ourselves. </hi><hi rend="underline">I have just enough conscience to spoil my enjoyment of social pleasures, not enough to induce me to abandon them!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
