<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The papers give great prominence to a sermon preached yesterday in Westminster Abbey by the Bishop of Birmingham on "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Religion &amp; Science: the present phase</hi><hi rend="italic">". After his usual fashion he emphasizes the conflict between the scientific theory of human origins and the formal doctrine of the church; &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">employs himself in "flogging a dead horse" with enormous vigour, but his conclusions are demurely orthodox, or, at least, well within the compass of what is now regarded as orthodox.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Thus, while we are told that "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Darwin's triumph has destroyed the whole theological scheme</hi><hi rend="italic">", we are also assured that "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">on the whole the modern scientific view of the origin of man's body &amp; mind agrees well with Christ's teaching</hi><hi rend="italic">". It would seem more reasonable in itself, more befitting a Christian Bishop, and more charitable to "weaker brethren" to have thrown the emphasis rather on the essential harmony than on the apparent conflict between Faith and Science. I fear that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> is suffering from the eulogies which he receives in such abundance from the semi&#8211;Christian and non&#8211;Catholic public. The effect of his pronouncements is not good so far as the Church of England is concerned, for they inflame the orthodox, and give strength and credit to the fanatical. Whether they commend Christianity to the acceptance of men of Science is very doubtful. His own treatment of the New Testament brings the teaching of Christ into considerable uncertainty, &amp; his contempt for the ecclesiastical tradition even in its apostolic form shuts us up to a critical handling of the Synopticks!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">A creed, a theory of the origin and order of the world is not necessarily religion, but whatever the case with other men, no religious man ever doubted that he had a direct and immediate relation to God, that he was God's choice and handiwork and care. Religion, in its earliest and in its most perfect form, rests on this faith, as the first axiom and foundation for all that it feels and hopes and speak and does and endures.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Church. 'A Particular Providence' a sermon preached in Lincoln's Inn Chapel. 1884</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">(v. Pascal &amp; Other Sermons. p. 312)</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">A Press&#8211;cutting agency sends me a cutting from the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Leeds Mercury</hi><hi rend="italic"> which used to take rank as reputable journal, repeating the imbecile gossip about the succession to Randall Cantuar. It would appear that the Bishop of D. 'is becoming recognized in the Southern Ecclesiastical Province as a strong champion of the Church's rights &amp; as such is discussed freely as the probable successor to the See of C. after the present occupant retires'. This preposterous babblement is not merely offensive. It does, I am persuaded, real harm in more than one direction.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi> came to lunch, and afterwards walked with me in the Park. He carried away with him a parcel of my books on 'Spiritual Healing'. The great Pastor Jeffries is coming into his neighbourhood, &amp; he meditates showing fight.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">James made his appearance. He looks thinner, &amp; has evidently suffered much during the voyage, so much that he will hardly be induced to face another. I cannot blame him for his experience must have been terrible.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
