<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. Mountstewart.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The fine weather continues. I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Gainford</hi><hi> a package of Bolshevist publications against Christianity. They are indeed as contemptible from the artist's point of view as they are abhorrent from the Christian's. The rage of these miscreants against religion makes no distinction. It is reported that the British Communist Ass</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> has solemnly censured the notorious </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Saklavarna</hi><hi>, for having his children admitted to the Parsee persuasion to which he himself belongs.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A pleasant letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">James</hi><hi>, enclosing a snapshot of himself, assures me that his initial disgust has passed, &amp; that he has settled down to his life happily enough.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wrote a long letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi>An interesting book, which throws light on the life &amp; manners of the XViii</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century, was commended to me, &amp; I read much of it in the course of the afternoon, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Memoirs of an Eighteenth Century Footman, John Macdonald. Travels, (1745&#8211;1779). With an Introduction by John Beresford, Editor of "The Diary of a Country Parson" George Routledge &amp; Sons, Ltd. 1927</hi><hi>. The relation between the gentleman and his servant was very remarkable. Intimacy and freedom of speech went along with the acceptance of a complete division of status &#8211; a very Caste system.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
