<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">S. Michael &amp; All Angels. Thursday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A stormy wet morning. Ernest went off early in his precious [sic] leaving me a highly characteristic letter, and a bill for 32/– for Postages and Travelling! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">So ends the experiment of a ''Diocesan Chaplain''. Could it have succeeded if the Chaplain himself had been a more reasonable &amp; responsible being?</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Ordination was held in the Chapel at 10.30 a.m. A number of the clergy formed a choir, and de Bunton sang the Litany. I ordained 3 deacons viz:–</hi></p>
<p><hi>1.</hi><hi rend="underline"> Robert David Baxter</hi><hi>. B.A. (Camb). 25</hi></p>
<p><hi>2. </hi><hi rend="underline">James Edward Talbot</hi><hi>. B.A. (Durham). 24</hi></p>
<p><hi>3. </hi><hi rend="underline">Michael Wilkinson</hi><hi>. B.A. (Oxon), 29</hi></p>
<p><hi>Among the clergy was Jimmie Dobbie and I took occasion to have a 'heart–to–heart' talk with him after the service. Our luncheon party numbered over 30.</hi></p>
<p><hi>After lunch Lionel and I walked round the Park, &amp; were joined by old D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> McCullagh, to whom I lent Fulop–Miller's book on </hi><hi rend="underline">'The Mind &amp; Face of Bolshevism'</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carnegie–Simpson</hi><hi> sent me a type–written copy of his Address to the Free Church Federal Council on the </hi><hi rend="underline">''Free Churches and the New Prayer Book''</hi><hi>. It is perfectly fair and, largely for that reason, extraordinarily embarrassing to the Bishops! I wrote a civil letter in acknowledgement. The chances of the Measure in Parliament would certainly be increased by some declaration from the Episcopate.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
