<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[214]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>The newspapers report the death of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Pease</hi><hi>. It is an untoward event for his was a just&#8211;minded and statesmanlike man, much trusted in the county, and respected for his personal character. I considered him to be the most trust&#8211;deserving mine&#8211;owner in the diocese, &amp; I gained much from talking with him. He was only 61 &#8211; three years younger than myself. I wrote a very sincere letter of condolence to Lady Pease. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Then I finished the sermon for S. Hilda's, S.Shields. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><hi rend="italic"> telegraphed for six copies of the "Open Letter" and these were sent to him forthwith. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I motored to Sunderland, where </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sinnamon</hi><hi> took me to confirm a poor young woman, far gone in consumption who lived in a back street. Then we had tea at the Rectory. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi><hi> has had his teeth out, &amp; has just learned that he is really suffering from arthritis. So he was doubly depressed. However, he went with me to a conference about the schools in S. John's Parish. where we came to some necessary conclusions, and then, Lionel and I went on the South Shields, where I preached in S. Hilda's to a disappointingly small congregation, which, however, included the Mayor and Corporation. After the service I exchanged civil speeches with them in the vestry. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Gill</hi><hi> brought an upstanding youth named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harvey</hi><hi> to see me. He aspires to become a clergyman, &amp; seeks to achieve his end by the path of Kelham. We then returned to Auckland, where we arrived at 9.35p.m. </hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
