<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lionel accompanied me in the car to Darlington, where I took train to London. At York the Archbishop got into my compartment, and, as we had it to ourselves, we had much &amp; intimate talk about the affairs of the Church. He seems really anxious as to the prospect of the Revised Book in the House of Lords On arriving at King's Cross, I went to the hair–dresser, &amp; got my hair cut tc. Then I walked to Sackville Street, &amp; was measured for a dress–suit by the servile &amp; swindling Adeney. I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; found it in the hands of the builders. I had tea in the United Service Club, which is receiving the members of the Athenaeum during their exile from their own building. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then I walked to the Home Office, and attended the first meeting of the Street Offences Committee</hi><hi>. When this was finished I walked to Lambeth. I found the Bishops of Newcastle and Salisbury already arrived. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Archbishop talked much with me, and was most friendly. He is evidently pleased at the good reception which his letter has had. He asked me whether I thought Pearce ought to be present when we discussed the course to be taken about the Revised Book when Parliament meets, since he is an opponent. I replied that I thought he should go to his own place</hi><hi>.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
