<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[192]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">This is dear Marion's birthday. She was one of the saintliest souls that ever abode on earth, and her life was shadowed all through its course until it ended in tragedy. I would have given much to have been able to lighten it, but my power was small, and the end came too suddenly for my hopes.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lionel accompanied me to Darlington, where I took the early train to King's Cross. Leaving my bags in Park Lane, I went to the hair&#8211;dresser, and then walked to Dean's Yard,where I </hi><hi rend="bold underline">attended the session of the Church Assembly.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I dined in Park Lane. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Haldane</hi><hi> &amp; his sister, and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pears</hi><hi> of the Office of Works dined also: we had much interesting but discursive conversation. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Haldane</hi><hi> thinks that the Revised Prayer Book Resolution will pass through both Houses without difficulty. He hopes to lead the Labour Lords into the lobby to vote for the Resolution. he spoke of the case of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Oscar Ashe</hi><hi>, who has just been released after 17 years imprisonment. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Loreburn</hi><hi> and he had gone through the evidence carefully, &amp; came to the conclusion that the man was guilty: and no new evidence had come to light. It was an unwise thing in these circumstances to have released him.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pears</hi><hi> was very sympathetic about Durham Castle.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
