<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wasted the morning in writing letters and also a short article on "</hi><hi rend="underline">Democracy and Education</hi><hi>" for the new magazine which the Bede College students are fools enough to start. Its early demise may be expected! After lunch I motored into Durham, and addressed a number of Headmasters &amp; Headmistresses in the S. Margaret's Institute. I had nothing to say, and said it badly for 35 minutes! Then I returned to Auckland. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to ask me to read a paper on "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Church as the Spiritual Organ of the Nation" </hi><hi rend="italic">at the Church Congress. What the words mean, it is hard to say. The Enabling Act destroyed whatever meaning they may have had. Yet I hardly see how I can wisely refuse. He has worked out a rather ambitious program with reference to "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Anglican Communion</hi><hi rend="italic">" as the general theme. He seems to be "making a corner in" Anglicanism. Possibly the revision of the Prayer Book provides a suitable opportunity for an examination of that subject, but, if everybody else is as weary of all the things Anglican as I am, the programme of the Cheltenham Church Congress will hardly be found attractive. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> has a friendly leader on the Report of the Ecclesiastical Committee.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
