<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[218]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I expended most of the morning in writing a letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Knox</hi><hi> in answer to one from him, which clearly indicates some purpose of making my 'Open letter' the text for some fresh effort.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Principal of Cuddesdon</hi><hi> says that he has read the 'Open letter' 'with great interest and profit' and is himself 'in hearty agreement with it[']. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi><hi> writes that he has read it 'with much admiration'. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Harry Verney</hi><hi> finds it 'most helpful': and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Field</hi><hi> bestows on it a discriminating approval. "You may be amused by a story, which amused the Archbishop. A friend of mine woke up dreaming that he (the Abp.) had written to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Barnes</hi><hi> 'No, my dear Bishop, the address of Lambeth is S.E.1, not Ten S.E." In these dull times we accept gracefully the smallest gift! Canon </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hannay</hi><hi> 'particularly enjoyed part of the Open letter, which dealt with the inevitableness of doctrinal change.'</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Dean of Salisbury, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Burn, </hi><hi>a learned man of a somewhat old–fashioned type, died in a nursing home as the result of an operation for appendicitis. he was 63, the same age as mine when I went through that experience.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I walked round the Park during the afternoon. the 'wishing Temple' has been repaired, and if only the aborigines will refrain from stealing the lead from the roof, it ought to "last my time"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Times gives prominence to the announcement that an American friend has left </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dick Shepherd</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">a legacy of 100,000 dollars.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
