<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Prideaux</hi><hi> came to lunch, and to say Goodbye before going to his new work in Damaraland. I am sorry to lose him from the diocese, for he is one of the very few clergymen who are also gentlemen.</hi></p>
<p> 
<hi rend="bold underline">I worked on the Edinburgh lecture, &amp; wrote 14 pages.</hi><hi> It is a monstrous waste of time precisely when I want every minute for my proper tasks.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Old </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Halifax</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times'</hi><hi rend="italic"> to urge the clergy to disobey the Revised Prayer Book. Having fomented clerical law–breaking all his long life through, he will "die game". But it is an odd position for a zealous "Catholick" thus to preach revolt.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Church Family Newspaper stands strongly for Barnes, doubtless under the influence of Ralph, who is the mainstay of that journal.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic"> is much gentler to him than might have been expected. Of course the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> is violently hostile, but its hostility rather assists his cause than injures it. Linetta writes to me from Birmingham an immense and vehement letter on his behalf. There seems a determination to give the episode the aspect of a "heresy hunt"; to ignore altogether the public aspect of Barnes's conduct, which is wholly indefensible, &amp; to concentrate attention on the particular issue raised by his sermons which is properly irrelevant.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
