<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[220]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lionel came with me to Darlington, where I took passage to London by the early train. I travelled in a carriage which I had to myself. The papers contained various items of intelligence about the approaching debate on the Revised Prayer Book </hi><hi rend="bold underline">which seem to show that the Opposition still cherish the hope of victory in the House of Lords.</hi><hi> About 40 peers responded to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi>'s invitation to discuss the question with him. Lord S. was among them, and he gave me a more comfortable account of what happened than the statement in the papers had suggested. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">A foolish indulgence in ceremonial extravagances by the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Alban's is made much of by the Protestant Association, and provides a valuable weapon to the enemy.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I went to the House of Lords, &amp; sate through a fairly interesting discussion of a proposal to petition the Crown for two new judges. Lords Buckmaster, Hewart, Darling, &amp; Hanworth spoke variously, but no division was challenged.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I had some talk with the Archbishop about Durham Castle. He is sympathetic but non&#8211;committal. Also, I spoke to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Salisbury</hi><hi> on the same subject.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I dined pleasantly at </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Grillions</hi><hi>, where I was in the Chair: the company was the following:&#8211;</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Archbishop of Canterbury.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lord Buckmaster</hi></p>
<p><hi>Sir Edmund Gosse.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Editor of the Times.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Editor of Punch.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lord Fitz Alan</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lord Hugh Cecil</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lord Middleton</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Bishop of Durham.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Hugh Macmillan</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Buckmaster</hi><hi> spoke very strongly against </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi>. He said that his fund amounted to nearly &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="underline">3,000,000</hi><hi>, of which no less than &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="underline">1,750,000</hi><hi> was paid into L.G.'s personal account.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
