<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[179]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I fritted away the morning in writing letters </hi><hi rend="bold underline">and working at the Edinburgh lecture</hi><hi>. I wrote to the Duke of Atholl, and I sent him a copy of "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Bishoprick</hi><hi>".</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic underline">Watson </hi><hi rend="italic">from Houghton le Spring came to show me his statement of income, from which I gather that out of the gross income of &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">2500</hi><hi rend="italic">, he actually has to his own use about &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">1400</hi><hi rend="italic">. He told me that by his mother's death he had come into an income of about &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">1000</hi><hi rend="italic"> per annum. So he can hardly be reckoned among the poor clergy.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I motored to Darlington, and took train for Leeds. There I was met by the motor car of mine host, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Baillie</hi><hi>, and carried to his house (Bardon Hill, Westwood, Leeds). There came to dinner, Prof: &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamilton Thompson</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maldon</hi> 
<hi>&amp; his wife (or daughter) and another lady, whose name I have forgotten. We talked freely &amp; on many subjects. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi> &amp; the controversy he has aroused came under discussion: and finally we settled down to a considerable argument about Anglo&#8211;Catholicism. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamilton Thompson</hi><hi> professes to be a moderate Anglo&#8211;Catholick, and repudiates the extremists: but I doubt whether any essential distinction can be established between moderates &amp; extremists. The whole position seems to me unsound, and a travesty of historical fact.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
