<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[219]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I finished reading through Coulton's 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> volume of "Five Centuries of Religion", and ran over the copious Appendices. He certainly makes out his case, and leaves the fashionable fictions about Monasticism in a very tattered condition. He is extremely severe on the dishonest handling of documents by the Roman Catholick writers, of whom </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Gasquet</hi><hi> is his especial aversion. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Claude Jenkins</hi><hi> comes in for some smart strokes: and he 'deals faithfully' with some characteristically sweeping criticisms of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Headlam</hi><hi>. I suppose there is some ground for the prevailing impression that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi> is an unfair as well as a discourteous controversialist. Certainly </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Coulton</hi><hi> is precisely the man whom it is perilous to treat unfairly, for he is relentless, resentful, and (worst of all) as nearly omniscient as a mortal may be.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Lyttelton</hi><hi> sent me her Anthology, 'A Girl's Book of Verse'. I thanked her straight away.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The death of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Vaux</hi><hi> is reported in the Evening Paper. He was 65 years old.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I walked round the Park by myself. Everything was at is best in the stillness and sunshine. But I fear that this means Fog in London, and so the newspapers foretell.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Then I read through a wonderful little sixpenny pamphlet by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi rend="italic"> on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Protestantism</hi><hi rend="italic">', most brilliant, suggestive, sophistical, and irreligious!!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
