<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[186]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The cold weather continues. My morning post contained several letters which required immediate answering, and took long to answer. Thus my whole morning was occupied with letter&#8211;writing.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlins</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Rainton, came to lunch. He is only 62, but he asks permission to retire on the score of incapacitating infirmity. He has a weak heart, is asthmatical, and has recently had some kind of a stroke. He speaks with visible embarrassment, &amp; is said to be difficult to understand. He gave me a harrowing account of his experiences during the long strike. The Church life of Rainton seems to have been almost destroyed by this eruption of "envy, hatred, malice, &amp; all uncharitableness". It is easy to see why the clergy in the mining parishes tend to join the Labour Party, &amp; to dabble with Communism. There seems no other way of securing a tolerable existence.</hi></p>
<p><hi>After Rawlins had departed, I walked round the Park. A decent old man addressed me, &amp; said that he had known five of my predecessors. Bishop </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maltby</hi><hi> had patted him on the head, &amp; given him half&#8211;a&#8211;crown, for answering well when his Lordship visited the School. His grandfather had made the gates for the Castle, &amp; his father had described to him the pomp of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Shute Barrington</hi><hi>, who emerged in a carriage drawn by six horses! His name was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tillburn</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[187] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury sent for 12 copies of the Bishoprick: &amp; </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Earl Gray</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> asked for a supply in order to send to some of the Peers</hi><hi rend="italic underline">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Canon </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Peter Green</hi><hi rend="italic">, acknowledging a copy, writes appreciatively:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"May I say that the Open Letter to a peer strikes me as far and away the best &amp; most convincing thing that I have yet read on the subject".</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This is handsome. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes:&#8211;</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"Your 'Open Letter' is quite admirable, &amp; the "Sunday golf &amp; motoring" sentence will surely enable the higher critic of 4000 A.D. to identify the Author though the signature be missing from the letter."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">', '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic">', &amp; '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Family Newspaper</hi><hi rend="italic">' ignore it altogether: &amp; the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Record</hi><hi rend="italic">' quotes it with hostile intention!! I do really think that the "Church" papers are an excellent standard of quality. What they emphasize &amp; magnify is surely bad: what they ignore or abuse is probably good!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The local paper reproduces the nonsense which the 'Observer' wrote about me on October 23</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> There must be much gossip in circulation, for </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic"> tells me that I am credited with 'ambition' to become Cantuar, &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes darkly of my "further advancement". Even M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="italic">Storr, who ought to know better, babbles of my being at Lambeth!! It is the most annoying folly in the world!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
