<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The frost continues with slight snow fallings at intervals. I wrote letters, &amp; sent off copies of "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Bishoprick</hi><hi>".</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Simpkinson</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Stella, came to lunch. Then J.G. Wilson came, &amp; motored with me to Barnard Castle, where I presided at a meeting of the trustees of the Bedelink benefaction. There was really no business, and the meeting was convened to please the old "benefactor", Richardson, who nears ninety, &amp; is as suspicious as a leading flea! We had tea. Young Watson showed me photographs he had taken this year of a raven's nest in Teesdale. he says that there are ravens still in that district.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wrote to those who had sent me Birthday congratulations.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Clement Webb</hi><hi rend="italic"> has an excellent letter in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> explaining why he, as a member of the Churchmen's Union, dissents from the letter addressed by the Council of the Union to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic">. He expresses a suspicion that the Bishop "does not know what the doctrine of Transubstantiation is"</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"The Bishop is, I know, a very distinguished Mathematician: but there is no evidence that he is versed in the history of philosophical theology".</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
