<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[211]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A very wet day, gloomy and gusty. I spent the morning in writing letters. There came to lunch </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> John Troupe,</hi><hi> a secondary school master, who brought his brother to see me with a view of ordination. He is an ardent member of the Labour Party.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I motored to Durham taking </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><hi> with me. He came to the door just as I was starting. I had some talk with the Bishop of Jarrow on divers matters of diocesan business. Thanks, partly, to my absence in London, &amp;, partly to my proper incompetence, the actual administration of the diocese is passing rapidly into the hands of my suffregan! Happily he loves power and importance, and I don't! On returning to the Castle, I addressed &amp; despatched 30 copies of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>. </hi></p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> contains the following:&#8211;</hi></p>
<p><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">Wildboars, considered to be the sign of a severe winter are particularly numerous this year in Switzerland</hi><hi>. Several herds numbering from five to nine animals have been seen in the Jura mountains, &amp;, for the first time in 100 years, wildboars have made their appearance in the Rhone Valley. </hi><hi rend="underline">The presence of windboars in Switzerland is a consequence of the War.</hi><hi> In 1914 troops of wildboars disturbed by the fighting in the Vosges emigrated into Switzerland, &amp;, it looks as if, since then, some families have taken the habit of spending their "winter holidays" in the Swiss mountains, where they are very welcome guests."</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
