<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[213]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I received a latter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi>. He has been somewhat staggered by the baser side of undergraduate life as disclosed in a "rag" on November 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, &amp; at a Bump supper: but he writes in a simple manly way which pleases me. He is not yet 18, and Oxford is a bigger world than he has yet known. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><hi> writes to [sic] about </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halsbury</hi><hi>, who is doubtful about the revised prayer book:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi>To cut a long story short, he said that he was torn with doubt, that his inclination was to vote against it, but </hi><hi rend="italic">there was one man above all others with whom he would like to discuss it, and that was you. I asked him if I might tell you so, &amp; he readily agreed."</hi></p>
<p><hi>So, on the strength of this, I wrote to Lord </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Halsbury</hi><hi> telling him when I should next be in London. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Guy Wrightson</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Maude</hi><hi> came to lunch, and afterwards talked with me about S. Agnes's home in Darlington which languishes for lack of local interest. </hi></p>
<p><hi>I motored to Hart, through pouring rain, picking up Lionel on the way in Durham. I instituted the new Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><hi>, and gave him a high character. There was but a scant congregation which, considering the weather, was nowise surprising. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas</hi><hi>, his predecessor, read the prayers, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derry</hi><hi>, whose blindness is increasing, inducted the new Vicar. Then we returned to Auckland, giving </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas</hi><hi> &amp; his wife a lift home. The rain poured down all the while. </hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
