<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[226]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Bishop's life does not provide an edifying version of Christian ministry, for the distinctively episcopal work is essentially secular. An English diocesan spends his time very largely in the transaction of business, generally financial business. He attends meetings &amp; Committees increasingly. All the "great Societies" which affect to carry on the redemptive policy of the Church require his presence in the Chair &amp; on the Platform. There are many claims on him which arise in the borderland between religious and secular interests: for </hi><hi rend="bold underline">an English Bishop is still for most English folk a normal part of the State system, &amp; no civic or public function can fitly dispense with his presence. In the parishes he is mainly valued as a magnet of money. When he preaches the congregation will be increased, &amp; correspondingly the collection</hi><hi>. At every turn he finds himself associated with the excitements, anxieties, humiliations, &amp; squalours of money&#8211;raising. Society gives him a place, &amp; brings its own irrelevant interests, every one of which takes off something from the spiritual significance of his office. And through all this maze of distraction, the wretched Bishop has to vindicate for himself a Pastorate and a Discipleship! Those medieval satirists who were wont to give the Bishop a prominent place among the Damned had excellent justification for their satire. '</hi><hi rend="underline">Be not many teachers, my Brethren; for we shall receive heavier judgement</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[227]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I breakfasted with Lord Scarbrough, &amp; then went away. Leaving my bags at the Club, I walked into the City, and made an unsuccessful effort to see M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Hird</hi><hi>. The clerk told me that "M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hird never came down on Saturdays". I turned into S. Paul's and was immediately recognized by the Verger, who insisted on showing me the dome. It presents a curious spectacle, all the piers being swathed in scaffolding. Then I went to the Deanery, &amp; talked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> for half an hour. He told me that he was going to review </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi>'s new volume for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Church Family newspaper</hi><hi>, and that he found the book in some respects more unsatisfying than he had expected. He thought the Review in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> was unduly favourable. Of course </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> discussed the succession to Cantuar. He thought </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi>'s appointment by no means as secure as I have assumed it to be, and said (which surprised me) that it would be unpleasing to Cantuar himself. I returned to the Club, picked up my bags, and drove to King's Cross, where I caught the 1.15 p.m. express to Darlington. I beguiled the journey by reading a novel by A. E. W. Mason, '</hi><hi rend="underline">No other Tiger</hi><hi>'. At Darlington </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> met me with the car. I at once proceeded to deal with the correspondence which had accumulated during my absence. It was more considerable than important.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
