<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I left Little Cloisters soon after breakfast, and after calling at the bookseller's, proceeded to King's Cross, where I caught the 11.20 a.m. Pullman express, which took me viâ Harrogate to Darlington, arriving there at 3.59 p.m. I came on to Bishop Auckland, after an hour's wait, by a train which brought me in at 5.44 p.m. There I was met by Lionel and a taxi.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> Had a considerable extract from my sermon. I found my MS returned with a polite note, on which was written with Dawson's own hand:&#8211; </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"P.S. the Editor wishes to add that he heard the said sermon (standing!) &amp; found himself in profound &amp; respectful admiration and agreement. G.D."</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Daily Telegraph also had a fair report. The Northern Papers, having had no access to the MS, report it very inaccurately.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">I sent to Ralph the letter which I wrote at the Club telling himfrankly that his article on " the latest Heresy Hunt " was ill&#8211;named, unfair, &amp; misleading. </hi><hi>He is far too opinionate &amp; exalted to accept the rebuke even of so old a friend as I may claim to be: but none the less, I held it the duty of friendship to let him know how I felt about Barnes, and about his own attitude.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
