<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi><hi> writes very kindly about the 'Open Letter':–</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"It is far the best statement of the case that I have yet read: indeed, I do not see that there is any room for an answer. Let me say also what a pleasure it is to read English prose on the great lines. You and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic"> are two people to whom I look for this and you never disappoint me."</hi></p>
<p><hi>He proceeds to urge me to publish the Letter as a sixpenny pamphlet: and I am half–disposed to do so, though it will certainly cost me some money.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning in writing some necessary letters, and in clearing up my room. After lunch Lionel &amp; I motored to Newcastle where I took the 3.39 </hi><hi rend="bold underline">p.m. train for Edinburgh. </hi><hi>I arrived about 6.30 p.m., and found a very comfortable room in the Hotel reserved for my use. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Robert Louis Stevenson Club mustered to the annual dinner in considerable numbers. The Chairman was Lord Elphinstone. I took occasion to ask him whether he would vote for the Revised Prayer Book, &amp; he replied that such was his intention. My speech took 35 minutes to deliver, &amp; seemed to give much satisfaction. I was interested to meet Miss Rosaline Masson, &amp; Miss Christie Orr, two novelists.</hi> 
</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[189] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Sands</hi><hi> spoke to me in a very friendly fashion. A M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Guthrie, the son of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Guthrie, </hi><hi>introduced himself to me, &amp; presented his son, a modest youth. Also a M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Balfour</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">who is a connexion of R.L.S.</hi><hi> I asked what had happened to </hi><hi rend="underline">Vailima,</hi><hi> &amp; he said that the house was still kept up. </hi></p>
<p><hi>The vote of thanks to me was proposed by a man, whose </hi><hi rend="italic">name was the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Rev</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> T. Ratcliffe Barnett. Ph.D. He said that his first acquaintance with me was in London when as a student he attended S. Margaret's, and was attracted to me as a man of an adventurous mind, who shrank from no facts etc.</hi><hi rend="italic"> It was a curious experience to hear oneself so described by a middle–aged man who had all the appearance of sincerity.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Christie Orr</hi><hi> is a striking figure, tall, dark, with regular features, &amp; hauntingly beautiful. She reminded me of the elder of the two sisters in "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Pirate</hi><hi>" I allowed myself to speak to her as we were dispersing, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">she expressed a touching gratitude for my observations about fiction &amp; its influence in modern democracies.</hi><hi> Her father, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sheriff Orr</hi><hi>, was also dining – a large, dignified man, on the lines of municipal greatness. The other novelist </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Rosalie [sic] Masson,</hi><hi> also pleased me. She has a sense of humour, &amp; professes herself an Episcopalian.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I asked </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Masson</hi><hi> to tell me what manner of man</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Stevenson's</hi><hi> step–son, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd Osbourne</hi><hi> actually was: and she replied by a gesture of aversion. "I would not deal with him personally. He got </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">£500</hi><hi> out of me when I published my book, &amp; that doesn't predispose me in his favour. But he is an insufferable person.' It is the fact that, for some unintelligible reason, I had formed a very hostile judgement on the gentleman from reading his papers on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stevenson</hi><hi>, and the notices of him in </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Balfour's</hi><hi> life; &amp;, therefore, I did not resent this confirmation of my opinion.</hi></p>
<p><hi>There is certainly an unusual intensity of municipal patriotism in the citizens of Edinburgh. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Douglas</hi><hi> was almost rhapsodical in his language, when he proposed the toast of "</hi><hi rend="underline">The City of Edinburgh</hi><hi>:' and the Lord provost, a clownish little vulgar gesticulating man, who however seemed to be very popular with the company, exceeded in expressions of civic pride. I contrasted the lethargic cosmopolitanism of London, and reflected on the disadvantages which attach to enormous size and imperial character. Who co</hi><hi rend="underline">u</hi><hi>ld be proud of being a Londoner?</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
