<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Another brilliant day. Lord Ullswater spent an hour in showing us the gardens which we had hastily glanced at in the failing light of yesterday evening. They are wonderfully beautiful. It was pleasant to hear that they were freely open to the public, and that, though as many as a thousand people would be in then in the course of a single day, no damage was ever done. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Lancelot Sanderson K.C.</hi><hi rend="italic">, who arrived overnight, expressed much approval of my Congress Sermon, and strong disapprobation of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes's</hi><hi rend="italic"> recent pronouncement about Evolution. It was the time, manner, tone, &amp; suggestion of it that disgusted him, not its acceptance of evolution, which he thought was almost commonplace.</hi></p>
<p><hi>We were motored to Ipswich, whence we took train to Darlington. The cathedrals of Ely and Lincoln looked magnificent, especially the latter. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Welldon</hi><hi> shared our carriage, &amp; was very amiable. We reached Darlington at 5.30 p.m., and were met by the car.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi> gives great prominence to my congress sermon which was, it says, "the outstanding feature of the opening of the Congress". There is something unintelligible and portentous, like the prophesyings of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cassandra</hi><hi>, about a sermon on such an occasion which does not paint everything 'Coleur de rose'!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
