<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I celebrated he Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 12 communicants including William, Edward &amp; Florrie Brydon, and John. It is a goodly spectacle when young folk present themselves at the altar. I left the Castle, and motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Tynemouth</hi><hi>, where I preached in the Parish Church to a large congregation which included the Mayor and Corporation, &amp; the local member. The latter told me after the service that he meant to vote for the Revised Prayer Book, &amp; that he thought it would go through without difficulty. After lunching at the Vicarage with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Holmes</hi><hi> (who is growing thin &amp; deaf), I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishopwearmouth</hi><hi> Rectory where I had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Wilson</hi><hi> &amp; his wife. He told me that he had interviewed Pastor </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jeffries</hi><hi> in company with several other clerics &amp; Sectarian ministers: that he thought the said Pastor was an ignorant but sincere fanatick: that he had come with some local controversy by his observations on his methods. I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">S.Thomas's, Westoe</hi><hi> in South Shields, &amp; preached at Evensong. The Jubilee of the Consecration of the Church was being observed. There was a large, but not a crowded congregation. After the service I returned to Auckland arriving about 9.30 p.m.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Who can claim that the Church (which has nothing to do with real religious belief or hope, for they require no one's interference) stands any longer on the same plane as science, since the latter is always striving to show its will &amp; ability to help men &amp; women to live happier, healthier lives?</hi></p>
<p><hi>Tropical Life. October 1927</hi></p>
<p><hi>This strange paragraph is worth examining. The writer's notion of "</hi><hi rend="underline">the Church</hi><hi>" is odd enough. The Church "</hi><hi rend="underline">has nothing to do with real religious belief or hope</hi><hi>". If we inquire what it is with which the Church is concerned, we are left in the dark. The Church "interferes" and does so superfluously. This futile interference apparently exhausts it function. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Science</hi><hi>" is personified into a benevolent person, "</hi><hi rend="underline">always striving to show its will and ability to help men &amp; women to live happier, healthier lives</hi><hi>". Presumably by manufacturing poison gases, tanks, submarines &amp; big Berthas! This crude nonsense passes muster easily enough with the half&#8211;educated multitude, which dislikes "</hi><hi rend="underline">the Church</hi><hi>", &amp; admires "</hi><hi rend="underline">Science</hi><hi>", knowing nothing of either!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
