<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>O Almighty and most merciful God, of thy bountiful goodness keep us, we beseech thee, from all things that may hurt us: that we, being ready both in body and soul, may cheerfully accomplish those things that thou wouldest have done: through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">There was a very large congregation in the Abbey when I preached at the morning service. My sermon occupied 37 minutes in delivery and was listened to with close attention. many people were standing in the transepts, and they did not go out, as they are accustomed to do, if they are bored or unable to hear. I stayed to assist at the Holy Communion, and noticed </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><hi rend="italic"> among the communicants.</hi><hi> After the service, representatives of the "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi><hi>" and the '</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Daily Telegraph</hi><hi>' asked for the loan of my MS. I gave it to the former, and asked him to let the latter see it. The Swedish Bishop was in the congregation. I am not sure whether my sermon was altogether pleasing to mine host, or to the Dean. It sounded too critical of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi> for the one, </hi><hi rend="bold">[173] </hi><hi>[symbol] and too sympathetic with hi to please the other!</hi> 
</p>
<p><hi>I attended evensong in the Abbey, and heard, without understanding, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles's</hi><hi> sermon. His voice doesn't carry, though it sounds very loud. After the service I walked to the United Services Club, read the papers, and had tea. Then I attended the service in the Abbey at 6.30 p.m., and heard a very vapid discourse [from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Hoste</hi><hi>.] I said Goodbye to the Dean, </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">who took the opportunity of thanking me, even warmly, for my sermon</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>Then I returned to No. 4, and listened to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles's</hi><hi> talk until bed&#8211;time.</hi> 
</p>
<p><hi>While crossing S. James's Park, I fell in with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Holmes</hi><hi> the Archdeacon of London, who talked with me for half an hour. He spoke strongly in criticism of his Dean, whose influence suffers from his journalism, and the indiscreet conversation of his wife! He spoke even more strongly against his Bishop who has lost all authority in the diocese, but is more than ever persuaded of his own indispensableness! He says that old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Newbolt</hi><hi>, who was at first incensed against </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bullock&#8211;Webster</hi><hi>, has now " come over" to his support: that strong pressure is being brought to bear on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingram</hi><hi> in order to get him to inhibit </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi> from preahing in his diocese: and that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingram</hi><hi> is immersed in most dubious negotiations with the extremer Anglo&#8211;Catholicks.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
