<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lord ^[two names struck though]^ was very free&#8211;spoken about Lloyd&#8211;George's famous fund, which according to his Lordship exceeds </hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;2,000,000</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Reading</hi><hi> receives &#x00A3;50,000 per annum for managing L.G.'s newspapers: and L.G. himself is credited with having secured out of the general loot a considerable sum for his own private possession. I asked whether the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post'</hi><hi> Articles, which seem to attribute actual dishonesty to L.G., would not inevitably force him to bring a libel&#8211;action: and he replied that '</hi><hi rend="underline">Cross&#8211;examination</hi><hi>' was an unpleasant experience: and he thought the L.G. would hardly face it! British politics are becoming rapidly Americanised.</hi></p>
<p><hi>We discussed the prospects of the next general election: and Lord H. said that it as generally thought that L.G. would be returned with about 100 followers: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ramsay Macdonald </hi><hi>with perhaps twice that number: leaving </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi><hi> at the head of a small majority. He said that this was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Younger's</hi><hi> calculation.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pears</hi><hi> exhibited a small plaque of gold stamped with a representation of the Annunciation, and evidently intended to be fastened to a coat. It had been found in Roche Abbey by the workmen of the Office of Works. He said that they had also found a silver spoon with an inscription on it. It probably dated from the 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century. These belong properly to Lord S. as the owner of Roche.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[194]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I breakfasted pleasantly with mine host, and afterwards he walked with me to the scene of what once was Grosvenor House. The famous mansion was in process of being pulled down in order that it may be replaced by mountainous flats. The garden has already been built on. It is more than the destruction of a house: it is the passing of an epoch. I walked to the Club, and in Pall Mall fell in with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Birmingham</hi><hi rend="italic">. We had quite a considerable talk. He is in a highly pugnacious mood, speaks of the more than 2000 letters which he has received from those who approve his utterances, and announces his intention of repeating all that he has said. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I did my best to induce him to take a more reasonable view of the situation, and of his duty: but I fear my efforts were of none effect</hi><hi rend="italic">. He is evidently a very obstinate man, and he is gathering a clientèle about him which will not let him go back, even if he wished to do so. When I got to the Club I was called to the telephone, and arranged to </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">breakfast with the Prime Minister tomorrow at 9 a.m.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Then I went on to the Assembly, where proceedings were mortally dull.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[195] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">At noon I had an interview at The Church House with an Ordination Candidate, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">William Burdon Frazer</hi><hi rend="italic">. He is, of course, and Anglo&#8211;Catholick. In the course of the morning I had some talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Guy Rogers</hi><hi rend="italic">, the Rector of Birmingham. He said that the Bishop was supported by the University and by the mass of the Nonconformists: but </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">that many clergy and religious laity were much distressed</hi><hi rend="italic">. he said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes </hi><hi rend="italic">was greatly disappointed by the attitude of the Bishops and amongst them preeminently of mine: but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he allowed that it was impossible to approve of the Bishop's language about the Holy Communion.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Evidently the local situation is very strained.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I lunched pleasantly at the Deanery, in the company of the Archbishops, and several bishops. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I had some talk with his Grace of Canterbury as to the chances of the Revised Book in Parliament, &amp; fond him moderately hopeful.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Both the Law&#8211;officers are opposed to the Book, but</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> the prospect in the Lower House is thought to be brighter than that in the Upper.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I was speedily bored with the Assembly, and soon transferred myself to the Library of the House of Lords.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[196] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>I went into the House, but such business as there was on the Order of the day was quickly finished. However I got speech with some of the Peers, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">did some propaganda work for the Revised Prayer Book. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I walked away with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp;, as we crossed the road to S. Margaret's, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I stupidly kicked against an impediment, &amp; fell 'spread&#8211;eagle'. However I sustained no injury beyond the humiliation.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I dined at 'The Club'. There was a numerous attendance:&#8211;</hi></p>
<table>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Lord Haldane</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Hugh Macmillan</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Lord Grey</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Sir Henry Newbolt</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Lord Balfour </hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Bishop Gore</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Lord Stamfordham </hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Archbishop of York</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Sir Fred: Kenyon </hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Sir John Simon</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>George Tuchea</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Bishop of Durham University</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>R. Bailey </hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Prof. Eddington</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>
<hi>Lord Hugh Cecil </hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Rudyard Kipling</hi>
</cell>
</row>
</table>
<p><hi>I had much interesting conversation with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi><hi>, first about birds: then, about politics. He said that he was now restricted to Braile for his reading: that he liked listening to his wife when she read to him, but she was soon tired. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Unhappily I came away without my umbrella</hi><hi>. It was spitting with rain as I drove back to Park Lane in a taxi. </hi></p>
<p><hi>On the whole it was an unusually pleasant evening.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
