<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ralph wrote to me an affectionate letter, recalling our long friendship, but still insisting on his accusation that I have 'changed'. What can I say? To carry the responsibilities of episcopal office, to acquire the knowledge which ten years of episcopal administration brings, to have been brought into situations almost incredibly novel &#8211; these are circumstances which could not but necessitate change of many kinds. The society of criticising talkers, and clever men of the world, with whom </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> constantly associates, &amp; which creates about him a perilous atmosphere of adulation, is relatively unchanging. It takes no account of forces &amp; tendencies, and being wholly free from responsibility can express its own preferences and prejudices without restraint. It still uses the language of severe legalism which seemed reasonable enough half a century ago. It is not affected by the impossibility of recruiting the clergy, or manning the parishes apart from this Anglo&#8211;Catholick party which has now almost a monopoly of enthusiasm. To discuss ecclesiastical politics with these "Modernist" doctrinaires is almost impossible.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[181] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>The congregation which faced me when I went into the pulpit to preach to the University of Leeds was in khaki, and the service was obviously arranged as a memorial service! But my sermon on the subject of </hi><hi rend="underline">Tolerance</hi><hi> had no connection whatever with the Great War! It was a comfortless and embarrassing situation. There was nothing for it but to go resolutely forward as if nothing untoward was happening. This I did, and the congregation was more attentive &amp; interested than might have been expected in the circumstances. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Baillie</hi><hi> expressed warm approval of the sermon, which, he said, was just what a sermon to students ought to be. So far, so good. A '</hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post'</hi><hi> reporter carried off my MS. after the service. Before lunch I walked for an hour with mine house discussing the state of the new universities in general, &amp; Leeds in particular. After lunch I returned to Auckland, being met at Darlington by the car.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The '</hi><hi rend="underline">Observer</hi><hi>' completes its review of the Bishops by a flatterous description of Woods, Headlam, and Temple. I do not remember a more impudent piece of journalism. And all this indecent discussion of possible appointments is altogether 'previous', for His Grace of Cantuar lives &amp; may live for a long while yet.</hi> 

<p>
</body></text></TEI>
