<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A wet gloomy day from morning to nightfall: that inveterate editor of joint–potboilers, Sir James Marchant, is moved by my letters in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> to propose that I should co–operate in a series of Books on moral Theology, or, at least, in a volume. But I have no belief in these blendings of piety &amp; business, and no particular fondness for Sir J.M. as bear–leader, so I declined.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi> writes to me at some length in reply to my inquiry about Wynyard: </hi></p>
<p><hi>"The disastrous coal strike &amp; coal position has crippled my plans for the future, &amp; I am bound to take cognizance of it, more for Robin's sake &amp; the sake of the business than my own, because I can manage but of course, on a different scale without my coal interest at all."</hi></p>
<p><hi>So he will imitate the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Duke of Northumberland's</hi><hi> treatment of Alnwick, &amp; vacate it for 3 years. I am very sorry, and disappointed for in Ireland I took the impression that Lord L. meant to live more regularly at Wynyard.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><hi> came to see me during the afternoon, &amp; had tea. Ella took Miss Haldane to see Raby Castle.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The following dined here:–</hi></p>
<p><hi>Miss Haldane &amp; D. McCullagh. </hi></p>
<p><hi>Capt. Morley &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Morley.</hi></p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hedley &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Hedley.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Sir Timothy Eden &amp; Lady Eden.</hi></p>
<p><hi>With ourselves the party numbered 12 persons. I wrote to Peter Richardson.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
