<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>That preposterous Mohammedan, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Headley</hi><hi> sends me some papers of his own explaining why he abandoned the Cross for the Crescent; and accompanies them with a letter in which he writes, </hi></p>
<p><hi>"It does seem terrible to think that Christians and Muslims cannot continue to defeat the forces of anarchy, atheism and idolatry we see all around us in the present day!</hi></p>
<p><hi>Why cannot we be satisfied with what Christ enjoyed – keep the Commandments &amp; Duty to God &amp; neighbour? The Muslim British subjects of his majesty outnumber the Christians – there are over 100,000,000 of us in the Empire – and yet we have not a suitable place of worship in London! </hi></p>
<p><hi>What with Hindus on one side &amp; the misleading and inaccurate statements of certain fanatics on the other, we are – to use a lowly expression which I hope you will pardon – 'between the devil and the deep sea'."</hi></p>
<p><hi>Has there ever been a period in the history of the Church before this in which an Apostate from Christianity to the religion of the 'accursed Mahound' could thus address a Bishop of Durham? My predecessor the crusading Bishop Hugh de Pudsey would have known how to answer him. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ella and I motored in to Durham, she to attend a meeting, I to license clergy. Before the licensing I had some conversation with the Bishop of Jarrow. We returned to Auckland for lunch, and then with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Eden</hi><hi> motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Middlesbrough</hi><hi> where I opened the 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> season of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Bell's</hi><hi> "Winter Garden" and made a drivelling speech. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Hugh Bell</hi><hi> presided, and was very amiable. The mayor recalled first hearing me when, some 25 years ago, I lectured on the Fire of London in his congregational Chapel. The gentleman who seconded the vote of thanks said that he had travelled in my company to London, &amp; that I had discussed the industrial situation all the way! </hi><hi rend="italic">Finally the Town Clark who said his name was </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kitchen</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; that I had called him </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'Lord Kitchener'</hi><hi rend="italic"> had known me in Barking and Ilford, that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Albert Mason</hi><hi rend="italic">, now Town Clark at Barnsley, had been in his office, &amp; that he himself still possessed books that I had given him. Now I had totally forgotten all these reminiscences, was ungrateful to say the least!</hi><hi> On the way home we stopped in</hi><hi rend="underline"> Stockton</hi><hi> to visit </hi><hi rend="underline">'Stanley House' </hi><hi>where </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Eden</hi><hi> runs a training house for domestic servants. Eleven rather squalid looking maids we marshalled in front of me, &amp; I said a few rather imbecile words of exhortation!! We got to Auckland about 6.45p.m. </hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
