<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The brilliant weather continues. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ullswater</hi><hi> went to London after breakfast, and all the rest of us motored to Ipswich – 17 miles – for the Congress. We went in procession to </hi><hi rend="underline">S. Mary–le–Tower, where I read an inflated form of the Bidding Prayer, and then preached to a great congregation, largely composed of clergy</hi><hi>. We then returned to the Town Hall, where luncheon was provided for a numerous company by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bunnell Burton</hi><hi>. There were speeches. the Bishop of Liverpool proposed the toast of the Congress to which I (!!!) responded in a very flippant speech, which seemed to please the audience. Then we proceeded to the Hall for the President's speech. After the usual delusive incident in which a deputation of Sectaries "welcomed" the Congress with their wonted unction, the Bishop of S. Edmundsbury &amp; Ipswich delivered his Presidential Address. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It occupied about 50 minutes, &amp; was to my thinking very dull and commonplace</hi><hi>. The concluding sentences insisted on fraternity with the Sectaries, &amp; did not, I thought, please the audience, which, however, applauded loudly at the end. Then we returned to Campsea Ashe, and were shown the very beautiful garden in the failing light.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lord Ullswater said that when he vacated the Office of Speaker, it appeared that some of the official plate was missing. He set the police to work, but they were unable to trace it, and finally concluded that the missing pieces had been stolen by Americans! When the American Lawyers were entertained at the Inns of Court, the prudent Benchers were careful to secrete their own plate, &amp; used only ?lind? plate of no value. Such is the reputation for thieving of those vainglorious Puritans!</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lady Ullswater is justly proud of the gardens, on which she bestows both thought and money. The cedars are famous. One, a giant, is said to be the largest in England, &amp; about 300 years old. The yew hedges are marvellous, &amp; require an immense amount of labour. The house is mainly modern, but there are two fine ceilings, and some Elizabethan chimneys from the older building. She urges us to re–visit Campsea Ashe, and make it our headquarters for a visit to the Suffolk churches. This might be possible next year.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
