<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I received from Ralph the answer to my letter which I expected though, perhaps expressed rather more brutally than was befitting. He probably is less sure of his own rightness than the strength of his language might suggest.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">The morning was devoted to R.L.S., on whom I actually wrote 13 pages out of the requisite 100.</hi><hi> Then the Annfield Committee came to lunch. The 3 laymen &#8211; Cooper, Greener, &amp; Wilson &#8211; were intelligent and well&#8211;spoken men. Cooper is evidently a man of many interests; including the poetry of Herbert &amp; Keble, and he is a recognised authority in the mining world. The broad determining fact which they made clear to me was that the mines in Stanley &amp; Annfield Plain are drawing to an end, that the longest lived of them would be finished in 70 years, &amp; most would not continue for half that time. In these circumstances it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi><hi>be indefensible to expend great sums in building churches of brick &amp; stone. The obvious policy is to put up temporary buildings substantial enough to last out the requisite period.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Then I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lillingston</hi><hi> relieving him of his responsibility for the Women's Work in the diocese, which is obviously too great for him.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ella, Lady Eden, &amp; Fearne motored to Gateshead on some fool&#8211;errnd of so&#8211;called good works!</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
