<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[168]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Have I really changed since 1918, when I was the object of much vituperation as a heretick? Do I indeed lie open to the charge of tergiversation? Can it be justly said of me that episcopal office has had the effect of transforming the "liberal" into the conservative? </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In plain words, ought I to be standing with the opposition to the Prayer Book, and championing Barnes?</hi><hi rend="italic"> Undoubtedly, there are many who would return to all these questions a prompt &amp; emphatic affirmative. How am I disposed to answer them myself? It is, I think, certainly often the case that I convey unintentionally, &amp; for the most part unwittingly, a false or at least an inadequate impression of myself. Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, Protestants, Modernists &#8211; all have claimed me as belonging to them on no better ground than my championship of them, or alliance with them, in certain situations. The defence of the Establishment in the eighties &amp; nineties brought me into alliance (not membership which I decisively rejected) with the E.C.U., and into collision with the Dissenters. This was the occasion of "the emissaries of Satan" </hi><hi rend="bold">[169] </hi><hi rend="italic">speech in 1892, which suggested that I was a vehement bigot of the "Catholick" type. It was grotesquely false: &amp; when in 1895 I reduced the ceremonial in the Hospital Chapel in Ilford, and, in 1898, addressed to Lord </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Halifax</hi><hi rend="italic"> the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Open Letter</hi><hi rend="italic">' published as a pamphlet under the title "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Cui bono?</hi><hi rend="italic">', I was loudly denounced as a deserter. My steady opposition to the "Ritualists" endeared me to the Protestants, who ignored my "Modernism", because I assisted their conflict against their rivals: and when the outcry was raised against me on doctrinal grounds, the Evangelicals, with the formidable exception of Dean Wace, stood aloof. But I had nothing in common with </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">those pinched &amp; unlettered bigots</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic">, and the discovery of the fact led them to denounce me as a deserter. My ministry at S. Margaret's, &amp; especially my defence of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Thompson</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Beeby</hi><hi rend="italic">, gave the impression that I was an "advanced liberal", whereas in both cases I was defending the rights of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">individuals</hi><hi rend="italic"> against what I conceived to be </hi><hi rend="italic underline">oppressive</hi><hi rend="italic"> treatment, not their specific opinions, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">from which in fact I differed.</hi><hi rend="italic"> When I became a Bishop I set before myself the ideal of large&#8211;minded justice, and I accepted the obligation to "hold the Church together". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Hence my determination to assist the passing of the Revised Prayer Book, [ &amp; my strong disapproval of </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">'s pugnacious partisanship.] I do not plead guilty</hi><hi rend="bold"> [170] </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">to any unworthy tergiversation,</hi><hi rend="italic"> and I confess to no more changes of mind &amp; policy than the changing circumstances of my life have compelled: but I admit that the accusations against me have a measure of plausibility, and are urged by men who are really ignorant of the facts, or really unable to understand them. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My deliberate judgment on myself, as I review my life, is not that I have changed too much, but that I have been too rigid, mentally &amp; morally.</hi><hi rend="italic"> More than once the phrase originally spoken of the younger Pitt, '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">that he was cast &amp; didn't grow</hi><hi rend="italic">', has been applied to me by unfriendly criticks, and my conscience admits an element of justice in the application. My terseness of speech, &amp; vehemence of manner mislead men into supposing that I am more convinced or whole&#8211;hearted in any course that I take than in fact I am: &amp; this fact also explains many disappointments. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">For, in truth, I am with respect to most of the issues which excite religious people, a born Gallio: and only when large issues of truth &amp; justice have been raised, do I become keenly interested. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[171] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
<p><hi>After breakfast I walked to 10 Downing Street in order to see the Prime Minister's secretary about Redmarshall, which (if Bates goes to Spennymoor) he will have to fill up. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">As I entered the house I ran into the Prime Minister himself. He welcomed me with something like affection, &amp; said that he desired to see me about Prayer Book Revision. I must be sure &amp; breakfast with him when next in town, which I promised to do. </hi><hi>We spoke of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi>, who, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi><hi> agreed, had acted badly. I particularly insisted that here was no question of a heresy hunt. After he had gone off to Chequers, I went to Duff's room, &amp; had some talk with him. I suggested that Salkeld, from S. Aidan's, Gateshead, should be sent to Redmarshall. Then I went to the hairdresser, &amp; was shampooed, after which I walked to the Club, &amp; remained there until after lunch. During the afternoon I walked to the Tate Gallery to see the 'finest nude' in existence. It is a picture of a young naked lady reading in a low chair with her legs stretched out. Comparatively a decent picture, but </hi><hi rend="bold underline">it was odd to see a company of lads and lassies still in their teens studying it.</hi><hi> Then I called on </hi><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Gow</hi><hi>, &amp; had tea with her: after which I returned to Westminster. We dined with the Dean and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Norris. The Swedish Bishop was there: also, a Canon &amp; his wife from the Salisbury diocese. All very pleasant. </hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
