<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A bright morning and a white frost. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 15 altogether, only old Canon Croudace being absent. </hi></p>
<p><hi>At 10.15 a.m. our conference was resumed, &amp; went on for two hours. After lunch, to my great surprise, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the company presented us with a salver, and old Croudace made a graceful speech</hi><hi>. I am so unused to receiving either presents of compliments from the clergy that I could hardly respond decently!</hi></p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon I walked around the Park, &amp; then wrote letters. Among them I wrote one to Kenneth at Wadham, enclosing a note authorising Blackwell to supply him with books.</hi></p>
<p><hi>My letter appeared on the front page of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> under the heading "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Religion in Modern Life". Back to the Cardinal needs. An end to petty dispute</hi><hi>". It reads less savagely than I feared. The Bishop of Jarrow approved it, and I think it can hardly do harm to anybody except possibly to myself.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">Miss Haldane arrived about 6 p.m</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We had a good deal of talk. She had read my letter in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, and expressed approval. Her interests are mainly philosophical and sociological. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi>'s crude essays in metaphysics would neither interest nor impress her. Besides, she is, like most Scotch women of her generation, reverently religious, &amp; disposed to treat the Kirk with respect. Neither the tone nor the attitude of the Bishop of Birmingham accords with her sense of the fitting. She spoke of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Einstein</hi><hi>, whom she liked: and of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ludwig</hi><hi>, whom she 'could not abide', both foreign Jews, but immensely prominent in the intellectual life of this time.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
