<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop's letter to the Bishop of Birmingham dominates the morning papers. It is an effective document, not too long, or too discursive. in effect it amounts to a very severe rebuke to the Bishop.</hi> 
<hi>The Archbishop dismisses the Evolution Controversy as properly obsolete." "</hi><hi rend="underline">Believe me, this teaching, however admirable, is to the most of us not novel, and I do not think that those who hear you on the subject with interest &amp; advantage would recognize themselves as 'wistful agnostics'</hi><hi>. As far as I can judge, it is not on what you have said with regard to that branch of science or theology that the attention of thoughtful men has been centred. It is too familiar. You may, I am certain, dismiss, my dear Bishop, the fear that anyone in England desires to lead or drive you either to Rome or to Tennessee. This is almost contemptuous, but it is thoroughly merited, and must be most damaging. Then his Grace passes to the matter of Sacramental doctrine, which is the real cause of the general indignation, and he indicates courteously but clearly that Barnes has deeply offended against the duties of his office. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He examines the Birmingham Sermon, &amp; finds it quite indefensible.</hi><hi> The Archbishop is explicit:</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi></p>
<p><hi>"In your natural and legitimate desire to denounce the few in the Church of England who hold or teach the doctrine of Transubstantiation you were led to speak of the Sacrament of Holy Communion in a way which &#8211; quite reasonably as I think &#8211; gives real offence to the great body of devout Churchman and Churchwomen, &amp; not least to those who are able to give scholarly as well as reverent consideration to the Sacramental doctrines which our Church upholds".</hi></p>
<p><hi>This is very severe, but not too severe. The Archbishop ends with a reference to "our Prayer&#8211;book discussions".</hi></p>
<p><hi>"To the larger tasks which lie beyond these discussions we Bishops must lead the way. But we shall lead only if we walk" with all lowliness &amp; meekness, with long&#8211;suffering…giving diligence to keep the unity of the Spirit the bond of peace".</hi></p>
<p><hi>Now, what is </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi> to do? If we would accept the rebuke, and avoid any repetition of the offence, he might in time recover his position: but, unless I misjudge him, he is not 'built that way'. He is far more likely to break away, &amp; become a kind of ecclesiastical 'rogue&#8211;elephant'.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Haldane</hi><hi> went away after breakfast. Ella went with her in the car to Darlington. We were all sorry to see her depart.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I revised the Westminster sermon. After lunch I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Church Building Board. I returned to Auckland, and had an interview with one of my clergy who had been accused ( think unjustly) of ill&#8211;conduct. Then I wrote a letter for the Mission which has been projected in Roker, Monkwearmouth.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitterick</hi><hi>, &amp; sent him a &#x00A3;1 to get a present with together with the Grey Lecture. Why should I concern myself with a lad, whom I have spoken to but once in my life, when his father brought him to me at his Confirmation, and whom I am little likely to see again? </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Partly, I suppose it is a desire to help his unfortunate father by simulating so mc concern for the lad as may make it seem natural that I should pay his school&#8211;fees: and, partly a sentimental or imaginative sympathy with the lad himself, whose life must needs be shadowed by the woeful tuberculous inheritance from his father, and by the poverty of his family</hi><hi>.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
