<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[215]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>This day was just frittered away in doing disconnected things, which had no real importance, and yet could not be neglected. In the afternoon Lionel and I motored to Burnopfield, a parish of nearly 6000 souls, high placed in the hills beyond Annfield Plain. There I consecrated an addition to the Churchyard. The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Madill</hi><hi>, was ordained as long ago as 1886, and has no degree. For 37 years he has lived in Burnopfield, first as a curate for 16 years, &amp; then for 21 years as Vicar. He is aging &amp; cantankerous. What influence can he gain over the rough population of miners, which forms his charge? We returned to Auckland immediately after the service, being lightened and cheered by the glorious sunset on the way.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Nine volumes of the Loeb Classical Library came in. viz:</hi></p>
<p><hi>Lyra Groeca. vol. iii.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Athenoeus, the Deipnosophisto. vol. i</hi></p>
<p><hi>Dio's Roman History vol. ix.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Plato. vol. viii</hi></p>
<p><hi>Josephus. vol. ii</hi></p>
<p><hi>Isoeus</hi></p>
<p><hi>Ciscero. Letter. vol. i</hi></p>
<p><hi>The Attic Nights of Aulus Gelluis vol. i.</hi></p>
<p><hi>""""" vol. ii.</hi></p>
<p><hi>The number of volumes increases quickly. They now fill 2 1/2 shelves of my book case. To whom shalt I bequeath them?</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
