<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[147]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Twenty five years have run out their course since Ella and I exchanged our vows before the High Altar in Westminster Abbey in the presence of a great congregation. One &#8211; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Duckworth</hi><hi> &#8211; of the officiating clergy has passed away. The others &#8211; the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of London</hi><hi>, who "tied the knot", and the Dean of Westminster (</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Armitage Robinson</hi><hi>) &#8211; still remain. My step&#8211;mother &amp; sister are gone, and so are Ella's parents. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">W. P. Ker</hi><hi>, my "best man", is dead, and many of my friends who were present at the ceremony. I was then the youngest Canon of Westminster, and no expectation was in my mind that I should ever leave that Church. But God willed otherwise, and, after 25 years, I am Bishop of Durham, and am looked upon after nearly 10 years of episcopal ministry, as one of the senior bishops. We have had our dark hours, the darkest for me was that in which I was told that the child was dead. Our childlessness has been the greatest shadow on our married life. That, and the growing infirmities of age, have at least this element of mitigation, that we are not responsible for them. We have been given good health for the most part, and opportunities for manifold service. There is much, very much, to be thankfull [sic] for in these 25 years. At 8 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel, which looked glorious in the sunlight. The servants came, so that we numbered no less than fifteen communicants.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[148]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Barnes</hi><hi> is evidently determined to force the crisis which I could have forced in January 1918, and deliberately (not without loss, though undeserved, of personal credit) avoided. His '</hi><hi rend="underline">Open Letter</hi><hi>' to the Archbishop is expressed in the sharpest &amp; most inflaming terms, &amp; seems designed to destroy in advance all chance of pacification. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><hi> has a well&#8211;written letter, which the Editor sets out on the front page, calling attention to the real gravamen viz. the partisan attitude &amp; temper disclosed by one whose office demands impartiality &amp; sympathy. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi> does not help matters by writing to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bullock&#8211;Webster</hi><hi> in staccato terms of censure: and, plainly, all the discontented elements in the Church, which have been hardly kept in check during the progress of Prayer Book Revision are eagerly seizing their opportunity. Personally, this new crisis must be extremely unfortunate for me. I cannot support </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi>, for I think he has behaved with unpardonable recklessness and uncharity; but if I stand against him, I shall certainly draw upon myself the full stream of odium which so conspicuous a refusal of one "heretick" to support another cannot but occasion. It is all as lamentable as unnecessary.</hi> 
</p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Hannay</hi><hi> (George Birmingham) with his wife and daughter lunched here, and were shown the Castle. Then I walked in the Park for an hour, &amp; watched the cutting down of a considerable beech tree. The Archdeacons and Rural Deans arrived for their annual Conference. All were here except</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Lillingston</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas</hi><hi> who were reported to be ill. After tea we held conference for 2 hours, &amp; then had dinner.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">The Servants presented us with a silver bowl, which seemed to me an extraordinary kind action</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Lionel, Fearne, &amp; Lady Eden also gave us gifts: and the post brought offerings from several friends.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I had some talk with the Bishop of Jarrow who told me that he was the author of the review in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Time</hi><hi>s of Dick Sheppard's book. ^(^ It appears that the said book was first offered to the Editor of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, &amp;, when it had been declined by him, it was transferred to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi><hi> and the </hi><hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi>.^)^. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He agrees with me that the book is the poorest trash conceivable, so poor that it throws an unfortunate light on the author's competence to play any considerable part in public life</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
