<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[116] </hi><hi>[sic: pages 114 and 115 do not exist]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>A brilliant day, but unhappily we had abandoned our purpose of motoring, and so spent it in the railway carriage!</hi></p>
<p><hi>Bp. Talbot &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Talbot motored with us to Darlington. They booked to London we to Ipswich. Save for their physical disadvantages, (which made conversation clamorous, ineffective, &amp; exhausting) they were pleasant guests: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but they have certainly reached a stage of debility, which ought to prohibit visiting. Happily, they do not seem to realise this.</hi><hi> We travelled very comfortably, having the carriage to ourselves after York. There was a change at Peterborough, and another at Ipswich, but good connexions. We arrived at Wickham Market at 6.58 p.m., where the car met us, &amp; carried us to Campsea Ashe where we were welcomed by our host &amp; hostess. As we approached the house, the fawns &amp; does in the drive showed the utmost indifference, &amp; would hardly move out of the way.</hi></p>
<p><hi>Sir Evelyn and Lady Cecil are here, and an Irish lady, whose name has escaped me. The party at dinner was very pleasant. I had much talk with Lady Ullswater. There are many water&#8211;colour paintings by Lord Ullswater's mother on the passage walls, and the rooms are garnished with excellent family portraits.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
