<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I complete 64 years today. There was snow on the ground which was frost bound. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><hi>, &amp; the clergy of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Mary's, Tynedock sent me telegrams of congratulation. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Purvis</hi><hi> of Stockton, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rudd</hi><hi> of Trimdon Grange, and my godson, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Spelling</hi><hi>, wrote to me. Also </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Clayton</hi><hi>. I spent most of my working day in making for my use in S. Giles's next Sunday a typed copy of the sermon on "</hi><hi rend="underline">Evil Days</hi><hi>" (Ephesians v. 15&#8211;17) which I preached in Durham Cathedral on May 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1921.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fulller</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Norton, came to see me about the appointment to S. Michael's, Norton, which is in his gift. He wants to appoint his son </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric</hi><hi>, but I was decisively hostile to a gross act of nepotism. I sent him off after lunch, a sadder, if not a wiser, man, bidding him reconsider the whole question in the light of our conversation.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I walked around the Park. The fineness of the weather and the freshness of the air made walking very pleasant.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Adderley</hi><hi> writes to ask my advice. He is a member of the Churchmen's Union, and very discontented re the letter which the Council of the Union has sent to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi>. What ought he to do? Resign? or content himself with a protest? I told him to tell Ralph how he felt, and determine his course by the nature of the answer he received.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
