<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

<p><hi rend="bold">[232]</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi></p>
<p><hi>This foolish pledge to contribute a sermon to a volume of sermons composed on the supposition that the preachers were, &amp; knew that they were, preaching for the last time, is extraordinarily difficult to redeem. I think, perhaps, I should desire to insist after the manner of Bishop Butler on the awfulness of Religion if true, &amp; the gross folly of treating it as a matter for jesting.</hi></p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I spent most of the morning on the Speech for the House of Lords. Probably I should succeed best by making a purely debating speech i.e. by finding my materials in the debate itself</hi><hi>. But I feel that the occasion is important, &amp; may give the change for making "a great speech".</hi></p>
<p><hi>After lunch I went in to Durham, &amp; attended a meeting in the Castle of the Senate of the University. Lord Durham was there, &amp; we discussed the state of the Castle for 2 hours. We drew up a list of a Committee, &amp; undertook to invite the persons contained on it.</hi></p>
<p><hi>I went over to the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; talked with him, forgetting my obligation to confirm in Darlington. However, by reckless driving I managed to get to S. Luke's only 13 minutes after the "scheduled time". There were nearly 130 candidates, of whom more than half were males, &amp; among them </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">David Harold Brigden</hi><hi>, whose recovery from what was thought to be tuberculosis seems almost miraculous. But the poor lad has no work to do, &amp;, I fear, small chance of getting any.</hi></p>

</body></text></TEI>
