<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Waking early, I occupied myself in making some notes for this "19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century &amp; After" Article. I desire to raise the question of Disestablishment with some completeness, so that it can hardly be hustled aside by some loudly applauded archiepiscopal platitudes, which are as irrelevant as they are welcome. I want </hi><hi rend="italic underline">inter alia</hi><hi rend="italic"> to show that the old arguments for the Establishment have mostly lost validity, and even meaning. The State has taken over so much from the clergy that they do not any longer play in the life of the people any such considerable rôle as they played up to the end of the XIX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century. Education, the organisation of recreation, the oversight of health, the rendering of many social services were once the sphere of the parson's activity. They are no longer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[struck through] <hi rend="italic">He is tied nakedly to his religious function, and there his sphere of activity is sadly curtailed by the growing secularisation of life. The old ideal of "an educated gentleman in every parish" was never even approximately realized. It is now a ludicrous travesty of the facts.[end]</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[struck through] <hi rend="italic">After breakfast I left the Deanery, and went to the Athenæum. Then I had my hair cut &amp;c and called in at the bookseller, where I provided myself with mental provender for my journey in the shape of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lytton Strachey</hi><hi rend="italic">'s "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Elizabeth &amp; Essex</hi><hi rend="italic">", and</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mary Webb</hi><hi rend="italic">'s "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Gone to Earth</hi><hi rend="italic">". Returning to the Club, I had an interview there with an Ordination candidate – Harry Legg Clothier. Then I went to King's Cross, &amp; took the 1.15 p.m. express to Darlington. Here Lionel met me with the car. I found D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Rawlinson<persName xml:id="5538"></persName> already arrived. He looks rather amiable than strong</hi>.[end]</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
