<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hamilton Thompson</hi><hi rend="italic"> belongs to an old&#8211;fashioned type of Anglo&#8211;Catholick, which hates impartially both Popes and Dissenters, speaks respectfully of the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Via media</hi><hi rend="italic">", &amp; waxes almost enthusiastic over the Church of England as "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">the bridge Church</hi><hi rend="italic">", uniquely qualified to bring Christendom into ecclesiastical unity. But he is too good an historian to accept the time&#8211;honoured Anglican fiction about Anglican independence of Rome before the Reformation. He was at the pains of emphasizing the true reference of the clause in Magna Carta,</hi> 
<hi rend="italic underline">Ecclesia Anglicana libera set</hi><hi rend="italic">, but he compensated himself by some severe strictures on papal corruption. He hardly appreciates the religious significance of the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">English Reformation, which was essentially the repudiation of a conception of the Catholick Church, even more than a revolt against the Papacy</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">By what authority was the Church of England made a completely autonomous &amp; independent unit, &amp; the traditional system of doctrine and discipline drastically revised &amp; re&#8211;cast?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The report on the King's illness is distinctly bad. A great fear begins to grow in the public mind.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Charge most of the day. It will be mortally dull, &amp; not particularly useful! In the afternoon I walked for an hour in the rain, and then wrote to Rudd of Trimdon Grange offering him nomination to Evenwood: and to Petrie of S. Barnabas, Sunderland, to offer him Holy Trinity, Stockton.</p>
         <p>That foolish youth, Herbert Crozier&#8211;Smith, writes to me from the Mirfield Hostel at Leeds, saying that he is now persuaded that he has no vocation to the clergyman's life, and asking for advice! I could not but counsel him not to be in too great a hurry, and to consult his relations.</p>
         <p>I set my mind on what I should say to the School in Durham tomorrow, when I go to the Cathedral for the annual Confirmation. The range of suitable material is narrow, but the occasion is one of unique interest, and, perhaps, of unique. Importance: for "the thoughts of a boy are long, long thoughts".</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
