<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bunyan Commemoration in Westminster Abbey</hi>:</p>
         <p>A brilliant day, and distinctly colder. I motored to Darlington, and <hi rend="bold underline">took the 11.21 a.m. train to King's Cross</hi>, deceiving the road by reading Lapsley's book on "The County Palatine of Durham", <hi rend="bold">[</hi>[struck through] and by talking with the Hon: &#8211; Churton, a tall man <hi rend="italic">fresh&#8211;coloured &amp; with flaxen hair, whom I judged to be about 30–40 years old. He was intelligent, vivacious, &amp; well&#8211;informed. He got in at York and got out at Peterboro.</hi>[end]<hi rend="bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> I drove to the Deanery at Westminster. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archbishop Lang</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to tea. He is putting together his speech to be delivered at the Enthronement, an important deliverance. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I told him that he had the chance of his life, &amp; ought to make a great pronouncement. Old Cantuar, his predecessor, had had his chance, &amp; failed to take it. I cannot feel very hopeful about it</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The service in the Abbey was of a "popular" character, that is to say, there was no choir, &amp; nothing sung save well&#8211;known hymns. There was but a small congregation, perhaps as many as 500 people. Of these, however, an unusually large proportion was men. Still it was undeniably disappointing, &amp; I was disappointed. A reporter from the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> carried off the MS. of my sermon, but I doubt if he will make much use of it. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">I had a good deal of talk with the Dean before going to bed. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is clear enough that the Bishop of London is becoming a great embarrassment to his friends, &amp; indeed lives so completely in a "fools paradise" as to </hi><hi rend="i bold strikethrough underline">me</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be almost impossible</hi><hi rend="bold">.]</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
