<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lang's oration in Canterbury Cathedral was of course very eloquent, and conceived in ample terms of sonorous platitude, which could neither wake criticism in the hearers, nor bind obligations on the orator. It was, I suppose, precisely what pleased everybody, and alarmed nobody. Reading it, I cannot wonder that the Speaker has arrived at his present altitude, while at the same time, I feel – not I trust in vulgar jealousy, which would be equally wrong and absurd – a kind of insuppressible resentment. The framework of elaborated ceremonial annoyed me, &amp; the copious eulogies of the newspapers even give me offence. Yet I cannot dispute Lang's competence, nor his unique "claim" to the Primacy, nor the truth of what he says so impressively, nor the dramatic suitability of his oracular eloquence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Great is the facile conqueror </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yet haply he, who, wounded sore,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Breathless, unhorsed, all covered o'er</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">With blood &amp; sweat,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Sinks foiled, but fighting evermore –</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Is greater yet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I don't feel that our third Scottish Primate is morally equivalent to his two predecessors.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read through once more the Article, which I have suggestively headed, "Disestablishment by Consent", and, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">having introduced into it a brief extract from Lang's Enthronement Address</hi><hi rend="italic">, I despatched it to the Editor of the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Nineteenth Century &amp; After</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then I paid the household accounts, &amp; revised the Palatinate Lecture.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Eldon, where I consecrated an addition to the Churchyard. The Vicar, Greenway, produced the wrong paper for me to sign, and (after a mighty perturbation) found the right one in his own pocket! We returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>At 4.45 p.m. I left the Castle, &amp; motored to Harrogate (c. 55 miles). There I dined with the Mayor, a bustling little bald&#8211;headed man named Whitworth. After dinner we went to a Hall, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">I lectured on "The Palatine Bishoprick of Durham" to a large &amp; attentive audience</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I returned to Auckland immediately after the lecture, traversing the whole distance in 1 hour &amp; 12 minutes. This is fair travelling.</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
