<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The post brought me a letter from Lord Davidson of Lambeth, addressed from 10 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, S.W.3.</p>
         <p>My dear Bishop and Friend,</p>
         <p>I have – in the odd conditions of our new and strangely curtailed life – been reading all reports I c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> find about your Charge, for I need not say how deeply I am interested in, and care for, what <hi rend="underline">you</hi> say on a subject you have so often handled. When it is published in authentic fullness, I shall voraciously read it. It is of course a remarkable &amp; rather striking historical event, that you should have said what you now say as to Church and State.</p>
         <p>I shall want you someday ere long to explain to me in conversation how your present view fits in with what you said with masterly force, just twenty years ago. I don't say the two utterances cannot be reconciled, but to me the reconciliation is not obvious.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I have always regarded you as one who was in sympathy with my own view as to the distinction between a situation or "constitution" logically unassailable – and a working system falling far short of logical rotundity. But I did [not] mean to write about it, still less to ask you to do so.</p>
         <p>You will know long ere this reaches you about Cosmo Cantuar's sudden &amp; alarming illness on Saturday night. [struck through] The accounts today seem to show it to have been correctly diagnosed (tho' not at first) as in the Gall Bladder which I suppose is less serious than what they feared. They say he must in any case lie up for a fortnight at least.[end]</p>
         <p>I am overpressed with letters &amp; have no Chaplain. So pardon my brevity.</p>
         <p>All highest &amp; best Xmas blessings be yours.</p>
         <p>I am, yours affec<hi rend="superscript underline">tly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Davidson of Lambeth</p>
         <p>Abp.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>This letter settled me in the decision to preface the Charge with a personal "Apologia", explaining how I have come to urge the duty of seeking Disestablishment after having steadily opposed that policy. Not that I think any formal explanation ought to be necessary: for during the last 20 years the whole situation has changed dramatically. It suffices to name but 4 new factors. 1. The Great War. 2. The Enabling Act. 3. The Extension of the Franchise. 4. The Anglo&#8211;Catholic Movement. Add, what is, perhaps, the gravest of all, the Rise of "Labour" to political power. Let these 5 factors be realized in their whole implication, and it is apparent that the old case for Establishment has broken down.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cardew from Bournmouth came to see me, about the distress among the miners. He was at Marlborough and Keble. I referred him to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Morgan and the Vicar of W. Auckland. He stayed to lunch.</p>
         <p>Jimmie walked round the Park with me. He seems happy &amp; hopeful.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Earl of Harrowby and his son, Lord Sandon, arrived about 6 p.m. Ella had hastily improvised a dinner party. Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Headlam, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hadley, Captain &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Morley and ourselves made up a company of 11 persons. Lord H. is a vigorous man of 64, nearly bald &amp; with a brusque hearty manner. He has travelled much in the Empire, &amp; is evidently an ardent Imperialist. He possesses, so he told me, a fine collection of pictures including one which is by some experts held to be a Holbein, but not by all. His son, Lord Sandon, is tall, dark, meagre, &amp; melancholy. I noticed that he did not turn to the East at the Creed in Chapel, and I inferred that he was addicted to Protestantism. On referring to the Parliamentary Report (Hansard), <hi rend="bold underline">I see that he voted against the Prayer Book Measure</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Our conversation was more discursive than, perhaps, was serviceable to the object which occasioned their visit to Bishop Auckland, but we carried ourselves with courtesy, &amp; parted for the night with compliments. I doubt whether these excellent Evangelicals have any perception of the formidable repercussions of their self&#8211;indulgence in fanaticism. They cannot yet analyze the enthusiasm which carried them forward, nor have the "loud &amp; prolonged cheering" yet faded from their memories!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
