<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">2</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">nd</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Quadrennial Visitation</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>Another brilliant day, but frost&#8211;bound. I had a bad night dyspeptic and sleepless, with the result that I felt utterly unequal to my day's tasks. The reports in the papers of yesterdays are rather disappointing, &amp; indicate (what I expected) the unpalatableness at this juncture of any reference to Disestablishment.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Darlington, &amp; there I celebrated the Holy Communion in S. Cuthbert's Church. There was a good attendance of the clergy of the Auckland Archdeaconry. <hi rend="bold underline">I delivered the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> part of my Charge, dealing with the question of Discipline</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I spoke for about 45 minutes. Then followed the Lunch in the King's Head Hotel, and <hi rend="bold underline">I made two speeches, first, in proposing the King's health, &amp; next, in responding for my own</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Old Canon Croudace proposed the toast of me &amp; my wife with flatterous facility.  On the way back to Auckland, I called on Colonel Siward Surtees.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[33]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received from Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Longden &amp; Mann, a firm of solicitors in Sunderland, formal intimation that, under the will of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henry Stokoe, the diocese would benefit, the bequests taking effect only <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the death of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Stokoe. I haven't the least notion how old this lady may be.</p>
         <p>A brief note from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> includes the declaration "if I fail this time, I will never be happy again in this world." "Never" is a word of little meaning, and frequent occurrence on the lips of Eighteen! But, if he does fail, the situation will certainly be very difficult. He could hardly be maintained in Oxford after he had demonstrated his incapacity to pass examinations! The humiliation would be bitter to bear, but possibly as salutary as bitter. He has been led to believe himself a heaven&#8211;born genius, when clearly his powers are something less than average. Then the practical question how best to dispose of him is not easily answered.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
