<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ordination in the Cathedral</hi>
         </p>
         <p>What ought I, as their Bishop, to do with respect to the refusal to take any food before their Ordination which marks some, and in some respects the best of the candidates? Their refusal seems to be equally unreasonable and unwise. It is clearly the first, for on what ground of reason can physical discomfort be sought as an aid to devotion, which it must inevitably disturb? It is not less clearly the last, since the strain of so long and emotionally intense a service as that of Ordination is severe, and there is also the likelihood that it may induce fainting. But what can I do? Unquestionably the consciences of the young men have been engaged in the matter: and if, in deference to my authority, they were to take breakfast like rational Christians, they would feel inwardly uncomfortable as if they had betrayed their principles, and inaugurated their ministry with a moral collapse! Almost anything would be better than that. Yet it is perturbing, and in a sense, humiliating to find one's self compelled meekly to follow the lead of the fanaticks, generally the chaplains, who get hold of the youth in the Seminaries.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On the few occasions when I have allowed myself to remonstrate with the candidates, my counsels have been received with visible alarm, and set at naught with resolute conscientiousness! The only result of my paternal solicitude is to compromise my spiritual character! And so one has to "<hi rend="underline">take it lying down</hi>": and the young "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" realizes at the start that his Bishop's opinions need count for nothing, and that his wishes and counsels are negligible as weighed against the admonitions of Father So&#8211;and&#8211;So! That the Bishop should himself so far outrage the vital principles of Catholicism as to take his breakfast before the Service, in which he is both to Ordain and to celebrate, only illustrates for the young clergyman the painful paradox of his position as an English Churchman, member of a church which professes an Episcopate equally Apostolical and un&#8211;Catholic, indispensable to the Church's being and incompetent for the Church's direction! The roots of all subsequent disobedience are securely planted at the start.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Only six candidates appeared at breakfast. The absentees were certainly the best of the company, viz. Bishop, Capron, Pike, Cornwall, Ross, and Grayson. The first four are all Cuddesdon men. </p>
         <p>The weather had mended during the night, and the morning was bright, calm, and with a frost&#8211;bite in the air.</p>
         <p>The service went through without hitch, and was, unless I deceive myself which is woefully possible, edifying &amp; full of consolation. The candidates looked very good &amp; earnest: &amp; the congregation, largely composed of relatives and friends, was devout and sympathetic. After the service, we all had lunch in the Castle, numbering about 24. Then we returned to Auckland. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nigel Cornwall</hi> came back with us to stay the night. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Aubrey Pike</hi> brought his uncle, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Monsell</hi>, to see the Castle: &amp; they also stayed to dinner. I showed the whole party over the House, exhausting myself superfluously.</p>
         <p>N.B. I gave the following Christmas Boxes in Durham.</p>
         <p>Green, Gates, &amp; "Charles", a pound a piece. To the other waiter 10/&#8211;, and the house&#8211;maid 5/&#8211; = &#x00A3;3:15:0</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
