<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">2</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">nd</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Quadrennial Visitation</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>A calm morning after the storms of yesterday. I motored into Durham for the Visitation. The service in the Cathedral started at 11.15 a.m., and ended at 1.5 p.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion. It had been expected that the clergy would communicate, &amp; I consecrated accordingly: <hi rend="bold underline">but most of them did not come up to the rail</hi><hi rend="bold">, </hi>so that there was much of the consecrated Elements left over. After the Celebration, Lazenby made a few observations, and <hi rend="bold underline">then I delivered my Charge from the Throne</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> When this was finished, we all went to the Castle, where I entertained the clergy in the Hall, and made a speech in response to the toast of my health. Then we dispersed, and I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The evening paper says that D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henson said that "we ought not to allow considerations of national advantage to weigh in the scales against our spiritual franchise." What that gentleman did say, was, not national, but material, which is hardly the same thing. But it don't matter. To the readers of that journal the sense, or nonsense, is the same!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi> sends me the draft of an appeal to parliamentary candidates, begging them not to pledge themselves to particular courses of action on ecclesiastical questions, &amp; suggesting that it might be adopted for use in this county, but I told him that I would have none of it. I gather that, in view of the next Election, the Government would like to retain "the defence of the Established Church" in its programme!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
