<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent. February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>["] I incline to the view that, despite its drawbacks, <hi rend="underline">old age is preferable to youth</hi>. Friendships continue in it, but in a form adapted to the years of the friends. Anyhow, speaking for myself, I want nothing further now, either of public recognition or of private relationships. What I possess of the latter, whether with relatives or with friends, are affectionate &amp; sufficing.["]</p>
         <p>Lord Haldane. "Autobiography" p. 341</p>
         <p>The water in my bed&#8211;room was frozen: and, after I had taken my bath, the water would not run off because the exit&#8211;pipe was frozen.</p>
         <p>There are reports of great mortality among wild birds &amp; beasts through the bitter cold: and the mortality statistics are mounting weekly through the epidemic of influenza which is sweeping over the country.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants, including Rufus.</p>
         <p>Ella and I walked in the Park, &amp; were surprised to see the tracks of rabbits &amp;, perhaps, hares in the neighbourhood of the Deer&#8211;house.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to Arthur, Leslie, and Brooke. I motored to Gateshead Fell, and preached at Evensong to a congregation largely composed of boys and girls. The church is an unattractive building, hardly better than a barn, and, in the matter of acoustics, atrocious. Something was amiss with the organ, and the harmonium was more audible than helpful! There were only 4 men in the choir, which surprized me. The lay&#8211;helper, whom I refused to accept as a candidate for Ordination, read the 2nd lesson. Ought I to connect the absence of choirmen and resentment against Carlton's rejection? Undoubtedly, the people find it very difficult to understand why anybody should be refused Ordination at a time when the shortage of candidates is being spoken about with ever deepening emphasis. Yet, experience is in my judgment decisive against ordaining men over 30, who have had no congruous education, &amp; whose wives are impossible.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
