<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent. March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>For the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> day in succession there is a white frost with a brilliant sun, and a rising temperature. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants.</p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Acton</hi>'s review of <hi rend="underline">Döllinger on the Temporal Power</hi>, originally published in the Rambler in 1861, and included in the volume, "<hi rend="underline">The History of Freedom &amp; other Essays</hi>". It makes curious reading in the light of the recent agreement between Mussolini and the Vatican. Döllinger's review of Protestantism is, of course, coloured deeply by his religious prejudices, but it contains a disconcertingly large element of truth.</p>
         <p>The carriage&#8211;road is in a fearful state of mud. Ashton despairs of keeping the people off the turf, which already bears unmistakable signs of their trampling.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Whitworth, where I confirmed 53 candidates in the little parish church. There were only 16 males against 37 females. Why should this discrepancy exist, and even be assumed as inevitable? The parson, Groser, served in Australia as a "Bush Brother" for 3 years, and then was in charge of a district for 8 years, This may explain, perhaps excuse, the crudity of his manners. </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
