<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ash Wednesday, February 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 8 communicants.</p>
         <p>I received from Lady Durham a beautiful walking&#8211;stick which had belonged to the late Earl, with whom for 16 Years I had been on terms of affection. The gift both touched &amp; pleased me. In spite of the bitter cold, Lionel and I walked round the Park together,</p>
         <p>The Evening Paper announces the death at Lambeth of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winfrid Burrows</hi>, Bishop of Chichester. He is one of my oldest clerical acquaintances: and I felt his refusal to assist in my consecration to the Episcopate more than that of anybody else. But he was a rigid Tractarian in his personal religion, and regarded me with profound suspicion. He was 71 years old. I had speech with him last week at the Church Assembly.</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi rend="bold" style="font&#8211;size:12pt">[</hi> 
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Adminicle =</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">1. Anything that aids or supports.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;"/>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">2. (Law) Supporting or corroborative evidence.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;"/>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">3. (Archaeological) Ornaments which surround the figure on a medal or coin.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Buchan</hi> uses the word, which was new to me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi> used it in the "Heart of Midlothian". It is surely on the way to becoming obsolete, &amp; has a pedantic appearance.<hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
