<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>This day was completely wasted. I went through my Journal in 1919 and 1920 in order to recall my attitude towards the Enabling Act, which I joined Bishop Knox in opposing. Its inconsistency with the Establishment was my constant theme. But I cannot make up my mind as to the form of the personal Apologia which I meditate. To quote my <hi rend="underline">Journal</hi> at length would be most convincing, but also less interesting. Probably it would be best to aim at a literary effect, and reserve extracts from the <hi rend="underline">Journal</hi> for an Appendix.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip Baker&#8211;Wilbraham</hi> offering him the Chancellorship, which old P.V. Smith's death has vacated. The objection to Phil. is that he already holds 3 chancellorships – York, Truro, &amp; Chester. He may find that he has no time to add a fourth.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Tony Chute</hi> went off to Hartlepool after lunch. Lionel left for a fortnight's holiday at Torquay.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi> has a long &amp; effective criticism of Sir Lewis Dibdin the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>. It fits in quite well with what I wrote, though it contemplates the facts from another point of view.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
