<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fair and frosty day, healthy &amp; good for work. Lionel returned about prayer time, &amp; later went through the bag of accumulated letters. I worked at the Preface, &amp; wrote to George Macmillan suggesting that, as his firm published "The National Church" twenty years ago, so it should publish the epilogue on Disestablishment.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Charles Ian Pettitt</hi>, a student from S. Chad's, came to lunch, and afterwards walked round the Park with me. He applies for Ordination, &amp; offers as his title the Assistant Chaplaincy of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Chad's.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Preface, which becomes more unsatisfactory, the longer it grows! <hi rend="underline">Now</hi> it occurs to me to divide it into two portions, of which the first will be apologetic, and the last expository. It seems unadvisable, since I have cast the fat into the fire, not to grasp the nettle boldly (what a mixture of metaphors to be sure!) and strip the conventional effectiveness from the stock arguments against Disestablishment. I shall certainly make myself get once more the most odious person in the Church, but that is after all a familiar situation: and I must not "fall between the two stools", by standing at last for <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
