<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<hi rend="bold">[173]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A wet day, and much warmer.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Barnard Castle, where I confirmed 19 boys in the Chapel of B.C. School. This is the smallest number yet presented at the annual confirmation; &amp; it is an indication of the continued decline of the School. We returned to Auckland, and then motored to Escomb where I confirmed 50 persons from the parishes of Escomb, Witton Park, &amp; Etherley, with a combined population of about 6000 souls. The service was more seemly and reverend than I had expected.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The death of Marshal Foch is reported</hi>, &amp; the papers overflow with obituaries and eulogies. This melancholy intelligence divides attention with the reports of Prince Olaf's marriage to the Swedish Princess, Martha, at Oslo.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The Chronicle Protestant Episcopal</hi> which declares itself on its title&#8211;page to be "progressive&#8211;liberal" arrived from America. Its "London Correspondent" would appear to have a mean opinion of the Bishop of Durham, who, <hi rend="italic">he thinks "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">finds himself with few friends</hi><hi rend="italic">". It is good enough to lament the fact: "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">And this is a great pity for he is a good straight man with</hi><hi rend="underline"> a first class mind</hi>". This paper has been very fierce against the Revised Prayer Book.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
