<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I thought much of "Eos". Its monstrous estimates of space &amp; time disturb the imagination, but really bring no new factor into the essential argument. It was before, and is even more plainly now, <hi rend="bold underline">quite impossible to fit the Universe, as Science is disclosing it, into any tolerable theological scheme</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> We must leave that matter under the mantle of a painful but, in the circumstances, indisputable <hi rend="doubleunderline">agnosticism</hi>. Two points, however, emerge which are not only <hi rend="underline">not</hi> prohibitive of Christian belief, but are even harmonious with it. <hi rend="underline">This vast enigmatic universe is not made to last for ever</hi>:</p>
         <p>"The universe is like a clock which is running down, a clock which, so far as science knows, no one ever winds up, which cannot wind itself up, &amp; so must stop in time." v. p. 52.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Moreover, life is only possible on a tiny part of this enormous universe, perhaps only on our planet</hi>.</p>
         <p>"The planets are the only places we know where life can exist ….. On any scheme of cosmogony, life must be limited to an exceedingly small corner of the universe" v. p. 85</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Within these two conclusions there is, perhaps, room for Christianity</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella and Lionel motored with me to Sunderland, where we attended the wedding of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ruth Squance</hi> in Bishopwearmouth Church. The large building was completely filled by an interested &amp; sympathetic congregation. The Rector himself "tied the knot": his predecessor, Canon Gouldsmith, read the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> part of the service, and I gave the Address and pronounced the final benediction. Then we all went to the reception in the Palatine Hotel, and drank the health of the newly&#8211;married, after which we returned to Auckland. We overtook and passed a number of men in shorts who were walking from Sunderland to Darlington. Great crowds had gathered at certain points to witness the passing of the walkers.</p>
         <p>This wedding is interesting for the qoalh of the parties concerned: for the piety of the homes from which both have come: for the evident goodwill of the parishioners: and for the union of reverence and popular interest in the ceremony.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At the last moment yet another Bill! I find that in the 8 months, Sept. 1928 to April 1929, I have paid Henry Walker for coke, breeze, carting, &amp; coal, &#x00A3;201:15:8. For the 12 months preceding I paid him &#x00A3;268:7:5. Adding what is paid for fire&#8211;wood, &amp; timber from the Park, it is evident that the fuelling of Auckland Castle now costs not less than &#x00A3;300 per. ann. This seems to me a very large sum.</p>
         <p>Then the dolorous business of packing had to be faced. There never was a more helpless traveller than I. The nearest approach to my practical incapacity that I can recall is dear old   Dicey, who looked and was infantine in his helplessness! When one has to add to the normal equipment alternative working "fakes" for the natural faculties, the risk and anxieties of travelling are increased indefinitely: and there is always the perilous horror of <hi rend="underline">mal de mer</hi>!!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
