<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We completed our arrangements for departure, and left the Castle about 10.30 a.m. Lionel went with us to Darlington. We travelled very comfortably to King's Cross, having the carriage to ourselves. The train, in spite of the holiday, was by no means crowded. We drove to the Grosvenor Hotel where I had arranged for rooms to be reserved. <hi rend="italic">I went to the Oxford &amp; Cambridge Club, and looked at the portrait of Lord Grey, painted by Speed. Then I went to the Athenæum, &amp; wrote to Lillingston, giving my opinion of the portrait, but disclaiming all wish to dictate to the Committee in the matter of selecting a painter. </hi>I went to Hugh Rees, and bought a Baedekher for Southern France. Then I returned to the Hotel.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My letter appeared on the front page of the Times. Both Lord Sumner and Lord Crawford, whom I encountered at the Club, spoke to me about it. They seemed to have small notion of any special significance attaching to the collection for the poor at the Eucharist: but when I pointed out to them the rubrical directions, they agreed that these could not be ignored</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I notice that the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> has an article by the Bishop of Liverpool, signed and garnished with his picture. It would appear that my cessation has occasioned his emergence as a journalist.</p>
         <p>We dined in the Hotel comfortably. The food was good and sufficient. But the literature in the Lounge was lamentably small. It is the interval between dinner and bed that is so ill&#8211;provided for in an Hotel. Of course, one might have gone to the play. This, indeed, would appear to be the normal arrangement.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
