<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[104]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very boisterous night and a misty cold dismal day. Will February Fill&#8211;dike justify its ill reputation? <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. I limited myself to the parts assigned to the Bishop by the Rubrick. There were 8 communicants.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to <hi rend="underline">Fatfield</hi>, where before going to the parish church, I called on old <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Reeman</hi>, who has been Vicar for 52 years; he was ordained in 1867, just twenty years before me. He must be nearly 86: and has been hors de combat with bronchitis and nerves. I preached and celebrated the Holy Communion. There were about 80 communicants, so that I more than suspected a "whip up"!</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Nigel Harrison</hi> condoling with her on old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kirk</hi>'s death. She is his daughter. As he was over 80 years old, his death cannot be matter for surprize: but he was so alert &amp; interested in affairs that it was difficult to realize his age. As these old Churchmen pass away, they leave no successors.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[105]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There is a highly laudatory notice of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Marshall</hi> in the "<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>", headed "<hi rend="underline">The beloved Vicar</hi>". The Bishop of London seems to have adopted the very undesirable practice of pronouncing a eulogy at the funeral. "In an impressive tribute to his memory, he declared that in the whole of his experience he was the best parish priest he had ever known". <hi rend="italic">Gerald was a loveable and devoted man, who persistently outraged every rule of health, read nothing, bestowed endless labour on trivialities, and smoked countless cigarettes. Affectionate and loyal, he was preserved by his character from the fanaticisms into which his ecclesiastical proclivities &amp; meagre education might otherwise have immersed him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, &amp; sent him the Bpk. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Peter Richardson</hi> came to tea. He has passed his examination, &amp; now dreams of marriage.</p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, and preached in S. Stephen's, Ayres Quay, at Evensong. The Jubilee of the Church was being commemorated. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Yates Moor</hi>, the Vicar, seems to be "making good".</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
