<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Jarrow refers to me a request that he has received viz: that he should change the baptismal name of a candidate</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The bishop has authority to do this (v. Phillimore, Vol. i. p.673: and Cripps, vii<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> ed., p.567. Dale, p.201.) but hardly for so slight a reason as mere personal preference. Lyndwood, p.245, quotes Paccham's Constitution</p>
         <p style="text&#8211;align: justify;">"attendant etiam Sacendotes, <hi rend="underline">ne lasciva nomina, quœ scilicet mox prolata sonent in lasciviam</hi>, imponi permittunt parvalis baptizatis, sexus proecipue foeminini: et <hi rend="underline">si contrarium fiat</hi>, per confirmantes episcopus corrigatur." </p>
         <p>This would seem to limit the Bishop's powers to the single case of improper names: <hi rend="bold underline">but Lord Coke seems to have understood it quite generally</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Bishop Kennett in his notes on the Prayer Book records a case in 1707, and there are later cases.  The parish minister was ordered to register the person in the parish book under the new name. Civil registration of births was not required before the xix<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. If once the precedent of altering Baptismal Names were set, and had become generally known (the press would see to that!) I might be inundated with requests from Confirmation candidates. At least it can do no harm to establish the rule that such an exercize of episcopal authority will only be made in cases which are gravely important.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Spiritual Direction, an essay in Pastoral Theology in the light of present&#8211;day needs</hi>, by T.W. Pym, Canon Missioner of Southwark, Chaplain to the King. London, Student Christian Movement, 1928.</p>
         <p>I finished reading through this little book, which is certainly important as disclosing the notion of the Christian minister's work which is now accepted at the centre: for the Author is now so highly praised &amp; so confidently recommended, that his pronouncements are almost official. Its publication by the Student Christian Movement discloses the milieu in which it has taken shape. The general impression made by it on my mind is that of remoteness from actuality. How many clergymen could honestly acknowledge that the picture of popular demand &amp; pastoral service which it draws has any recognisable resemblance with that which their own experience presents? Where are the lay people who besiege their clergymen with spiritual problems, frequent the confessional, and clamour for "direction"? This may, probably is, the picture of pastoral work which is accepted in "group" discussions, "missions", and "retreats", but it is unknown outside them. And where are the clergy who, morally or intellectually, are competent for such pastorate? The Bishops know nothing of them.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We motored to Bishopton where I confirmed 36 persons in the parish church: &amp; afterwards had tea with the Vicar &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Reilly. There were also present M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sharp, an official of Barclay's Bank &amp; his wife, who have bought a house, &amp; settled in the parish. Then we went on to West Hartlepool, to inquire of the state of Canon Knowlden. I saw him, &amp; said prayers with him. Then we went to Stockton, where I instituted Petrie to the charge of Holy Trinity parish, in succession to Purvis. I was pleased to see an unusually numerous gathering of the clergy. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p>The wintry weather has returned. Last night there was a considerable fall of snow. All through the day snow fell at intervals, and as night drew on, there was a heavy snow&#8211;fall. We motored home in a mild blizzard.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
