<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">He who knows most is most persecuted by doubt</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">(an aphorism of Pius ii. v. Creighton "Popes" ii. 483)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The list of "proverbs" which Creighton attributes to Pius ii., is certainly impressive, and raises one's opinion of that many&#8211;sided &amp; rather enigmatic pontiff. It is Bishop Blougram's position, perhaps the position of</hi> every keen&#8211;witted &amp; well&#8211;educated man who finds himself, by some process he can hardly understand, committed to the affirmations of the Christian creed, and the obligations of the Christian ministry.</p>
         <p>With me, faith means perpetual unbelief</p>
         <p>Kept quiet like the snake 'neath Michael's foot</p>
         <p>Who stands calm just because he feels it writhe.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 o'clock. There were only 5 communicants. The challenging Gospel, "Which of you convinceth me of sin?", is impossible as history, but as the dramatic summary of history of Faith it is irresistible. The moral uniqueness of the historic Jesus was the first, has always been, and must for ever remain, the rock on which the Christian discipleship can be built. But these corrosive critics no longer respect even <hi rend="underline">that</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I motored to S. Cuthbert's, Cleadon Park, and preached at Evensong. In spite of the fact that my coming had been advertised by posters, the congregation was not very impressive, &amp; largely consisted of young women. There were, however, 30 men &amp; boys in the choir. Cecil Booth seems to be keen and cheerful: but the prospect of establishing a parish is not very bright.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Francis Underhill</hi>, Warden of Liddon House, has written a booklet – "<hi rend="underline">The New Spirit in Anglo&#8211;Catholicism</hi>" – designed to "<hi rend="underline">plead for a new attitude on the part of the official Church towards Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, &amp; on the part of Anglo&#8211;Catholicism towards the rest of the Church of England, in view of the coming of a most serious crisis in the life of the Church</hi>". He was good enough to send me a copy, and I have read it through with attention. The writer's excellent intention and temper are apparent, but also his complete unconsciousness of the problem which "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" raises.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
