<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A comfortable night in an astonishingly quiet bed&#8211;room, and a good bath in the morning. So far, so good. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But it is a disconcerting reflection that a single night in London should cost as much money as a pitman earns in two or even three weeks</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi><hi rend="italic"> The actual amount of the bill was &#x00A3;4.2.9 [for 3 persons]: but the tips will add to it. Many pitmen are not earning more now than 30/&#8211; weekly, &amp; have to maintain a family. Of course, many of them have a house &amp; coals supplied, either wholly or partially: and, on a favourable estimate this may be valued at 10/&#8211; in addition. Even so, their income only amounts to 40/&#8211;. And at the present values of money, I doubt if that is more than the equivalent of 28/&#8211; in 1914. The discontent is deep, general, and growing. If there be – as some persons affirm, though on no very sufficient grounds – a revival of industry, there will surely be a strike in the minefields. The parade of luxury &amp; profusion which the employing classes exhibit seems to contradict too grossly the lamentable assertions which, as capitalists, they continue to make. The men are resolutely sceptical.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Somebody writes to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> in answer to my letter. <hi rend="bold underline">I found time before leaving the Hotel to write a brief rejoinder, adding that I was leaving England today</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then we got away by the 11 a.m. train, &amp;, in due course, traversed the Channel, &amp;, after a horrible conflict with the customs (mainly because I couldn't open most of the bags, nor shut my own when I had opened it!) got into the Paris train. I gave 25 francs to a porter, &amp; 20 to another fellow who was convenient in directing &amp; assisting me. He earned the money. Then Ella, (embodying the moral Law of a past age.) protested vainly against the smoking of a female who shared our carriage. She had a face of resolute incivility which could defeat any protest <hi rend="underline">O tempora! O mores</hi>! Time was when to smoke without seeking permission from any ladies present would have been reckoned an intolerable rudeness: but <hi rend="bold underline">now</hi>? The tables are turned, &amp; the ladies themselves blow their tobacco smoke into our reluctant nostrils! Very reluctant: for even when the sea is relatively calm, one emerges from the steamer with a sense of acute repugnance to tobacco smoke. And this from the lips of a hard&#8211;faced female is doubly repulsive. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Trotman sent me a telegram which he had received from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Glen, the contractor for the dilapidations. It ran thus:</p>
         <p>Tender sent from Jarrow</p>
         <p>Thursday last one hundred </p>
         <p>And thirty two pounds, sending </p>
         <p>You copy today.</p>
         <p>This he (Trotman) accompanied with a letter saying that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Glen was anxious to proceed with the work, and asking me to send a telegram. Accordingly, I sent a telegram authorising the contractor to go on with the work, &amp; accepting the tender of &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">132</hi>.</p>
         <p>This with his original tender for the dilapidations will make me responsible for about &#x00A3;800.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On arriving at Paris we had a hectic moment at the Gare du Nord, where my ladies lost me, and only appeared at the last moment! We drove to the Gare de Lyon, and dined at the Buffet. At 8.30 p.m. <hi rend="underline">we left for Avignon</hi>, where we were due to arrive at 7.35 a.m., but did not actually do so until nearly 9 a.m. We had two stout Frenchmen in our carriage, but, in spite of them, I succeeded in keeping the window open through the night: so that we were not asphyxiated, nor handicapped by headache. At Avignon the <hi rend="underline">hotel d'Europe</hi> omnibus carried us from the station to the hotel, which is an old&#8211;fashioned house, not very efficiently equipped, but it seems to be fairly quiet, &amp; clean.  </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
