<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Modern Churchman</hi>" arrived this morning. It has some curiously interesting articles, e.g. an account of the 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Quadrennial Conference of the Student Christian Movement held last month in Liverpool. The subject of the Conference was "<hi rend="underline">The Purpose of God in the Life of the World</hi>": and "the answer to the purpose of God was given to the conference on the first evening by the Chairman, the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> R.O. Hall, in the one word, <hi rend="underline">friendship</hi>".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Professor MacMurray</hi>, "in a paper which set the tone of the conference", "recaptured, in all its simplicity and in all its difficulty, what this word should mean. <hi rend="underline">He bid the conference set as the standard, both of the love of God and man, their friendship with their closet friend. It was then apparent that such love as Christ intended had no place for duty or self&#8211;sacrifice</hi>, that it could not be replaced by friendliness or kindness, that it was above all the sworn enemy of sentimentality. <hi rend="underline">The idea of duty flies right out of Christ's conception of the Kingdom</hi> &amp;c. &amp;c." "<hi rend="underline">Self&#8211;sacrifice has no place in the true Christian view of life.</hi>" "At the concluding service the Bishop of Liverpool spoke again on this theme, reading into the character of God the one essential condition of friendship, that God himself will not force his love on men, but waits with the courtesy of love till men turn to him."</p>
         <p>What is all this but sentimental pietism in excelsis? We have travelled far from "<hi rend="underline">The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom</hi>", far, indeed, from "<hi rend="underline">I will warn you whom ye shall fear</hi>"! Is this indeed the Religion of Christ?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "Student Christians", who have formed a taste for this spiritual provender, are little likely to find much attraction in the Church with its Lenten demand for discipline.</p>
         <p>"The <hi rend="underline">Student Christian Movement</hi> professes, as an interdenominational society, to make its members loyal, each to their own denomination; it is not the fault of the movement if the charge is true that it is not always successful in this policy: <hi rend="underline">it is not surprising that in a conference such as has been described, some students find a more pure fellowship and a more real religion than in the services of the Church</hi>."</p>
         <p>The Church has certainly never simplified the Gospel into "<hi rend="underline">Friendship</hi>", nor commended it by frankly repudiating "<hi rend="underline">Self&#8211;sacrifice</hi>". S. Paul before Felix "<hi rend="underline">reasoned of righteousness, and temperance, and the judgement to come</hi>", and '<hi rend="underline">terrified</hi>" the governor. He might have presented a more attractive Gospel had he been a "Student Christian"! <hi rend="underline">The truth is, that in all these modernist essays at re&#8211;casting Christianity, the notions of "sin" and "redemption" have no place, while they are prominent in the New Testament, in the Theologies of Christendom, and in the appointed forms of Anglican worship</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Guillaume</hi> came to lunch, and afterwards came to my room, and expounded divers difficulties in his personal arrangements. Finally I gave him permission (since there is no residence house) to live within the two mile radius. He told me that the Literary Committee of the E.C.U. were contemplating fresh publications dealing with social issues (e.g. marriage) on which the modern State collides with the Christian tradition: but he did not intend personally to take any part in the venture.</p>
         <p>There were predictions of a thaw in the morning papers, but these proved to be illusory, &amp;, though the sun shone brightly during the day, the frost was as hard as ever at nightfall. The reports from the continent are filled with strange happenings e.g. 11 recruits on the march were set upon by a pack of 50 wolves, &amp; torn to pieces. This gruesome story comes from Albania.</p>
         <p>I tried to put together some notes for the address at Kathleen's marriage tomorrow. There is surely in these ill times nothing more difficult than to speak suitably, sanely, and sincerely at a marriage. The time &amp; occasion prohibit any serious handling of the subject, yet one must say something, &amp; what one says ought to be relevant &amp; religious.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
