<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Still the glorious weather: but my cold is too heavy on me to admit of my enjoying it. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 13 communicants, including Major Wills, John, Rufus, &amp; the 4 Brydens.</p>
         <p>I went to South Church, and confirmed 137 persons from the parishes of Bishop Auckland and Coundon. The fine church was completely filled, and everything seemed reverent and edifying.</p>
         <p>Some cranky papist who calls himself "Bishop" Howarth, having received some kind of consecration from an eccentrick named Matthew "Anglo&#8211;Catholic Archbishop of London", has written "A Protest against the Tyranny of the Roman Inquisition &amp; of His Holiness Pope Pius X, addressed to His Eminence Cardinal Bourne", of which he sends me a copy. So far as I can understand his complaint, he appears to have been excommunicated by the Roman Catholick Authorities, and no doubt for adequate cause.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]It is the most astonishing instance of the irony of events that the Lateran Council should have been dissolved (1517) with promises of peace <hi rend="underline">on the very verge of the greatest outbreak which had ever threatened the organisation of the Church</hi>. It may be pleasant to be free from demands of reform, but it is assuredly dangerous. The quiet of indifference wears the same aspect as the quiet of content: but <hi rend="underline">it needs only a small impulse to convert indifference to antagonism</hi>. …. It was a time of material wellbeing and eager striving after riches. The increase of knowledge had brought self&#8211;complacency, &amp; the pride of superior wisdom separated each man from his fellow. Old objects of common effort had passed away, &amp; none had taken their place.["]</p>
         <p>v. Creighton. "Papacy" iv. 235.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
