<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>How fragile is the foundation of all human plans! The first result of inoculation for influenza is to send Fearne to bed with what seems to be taking the aspect of a serious illness!</p>
         <p>Sir Timothy Eden &amp; his mother lunched here. He is now meditating a novel.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Philip Baker Wilbraham</hi> wrote to accept my offer of the Chancellorship of the diocese.</p>
         <p>I wrote a letter of condolence to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Reeve, the widow of the porter of the Cathedral, who died of cancer two days ago, &amp; is to be buried tomorrow. He was a gentle, courteous, industrious man of the old&#8211;fashioned type of gentleman's servant. I became really attached to him during my years at the Deanery.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with the two dogs, and had the company of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullough on my return. He told me that he had come across  <hi rend="italic">a reference to old Bishop Shute Barrington in the Faringdon Diary. The Bishop, then past 80, attributed his excellent health to his habit of riding daily, &amp; to his abstemiousness. For he never drank more than 2 glasses of wine at dinner, and 4 afterwards!</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
