<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Eve. March 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Vicar of Amesbury (Parish of Stonehenge) writes to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> expressing his satisfaction at the completion of the Stonehenge Preservation Fund, and adding:&#8211;</p>
         <p>"I propose having a special <hi rend="underline">Te Deum</hi> after Evensong on Easter Day: and a donation from the alms at the Eucharist to the National Trust."</p>
         <p>Ought the "alms" presented at the Altar to be devoted to such an object? In the rubrick there is mention of "the Alms for the Poor, and other devotions of the people", and, in the Prayer for the Church Militant, the Almighty is prayed "to accept our alms &amp; oblations". The Rubrick at the End of the Order for H.C. provides that "the money given at the Offertory shall be disposed of to such pious &amp; charitable uses, as the Minister &amp; Churchwardens shall think fit". If they disagree, the Ordinary shall "appoint the objects for which it shall be expended. Would the "National Trust" be properly regarded as "<hi rend="underline">pious &amp; charitable</hi>"? </p>
         <p>v. Cripps. p. 580. cf. Canon S4</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>["]There would appear <hi rend="strikethrough">to</hi> from the directions of the rubric, and also from the sentences to be read at such times, to be two purposes for which such collections are to be made, viz., alms for the poor and oblations, which latter word is commonly used to denote what is given to the minister. But in Aycliffe's Parergon it is said that the oblations made at the communion were at the Reformation changed into alms of charity for the poor parishioners. And practically there w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> appear almost insuperable difficulties if any other course were to be adopted.["]</p>
         <p>Cripps. Law relating to Church &amp; Clergy. Ed. VII. p.580</p>
         <p>I felt strongly enough on the matter to write and despatch a brief letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>. If the Offertory Alms may rightly go to the National Trust, a wide door is opened.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The paged proofs of the Charge only now begin to come in. I shall have to entrust the revising of them to Lionel.</p>
         <p>Ella and Lionel went with me to Horden, where I dedicated bells in the parish church. There was a large congregation, and several of the neighbouring incumbents were in the procession. I gave an address on bells, which was listened to very attentively. After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Charles Pattinson, the assistant&#8211;curate of S. Andrew's, Roker, came to lunch</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He has already consented to stay on under the new incumbent. This seems to me both precipitate and undesirable.</p>
         <p>The Evening paper reports an unusual occurrence. A large dog otter made its appearance in Durham, where it crossed the market&#8211;place, and was killed by a policeman in Claypath with his truncheon!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
