<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 8 communicants including John. The Collect for the day is exactly congruous with our present situation. It prays that we "may both perceive &amp; know what things we ought to do, and also may have grace &amp; power faithfully to fulfil the same." We are now doubly disadvantaged by a real perplexity as to our duty, and a conscious shrinking from any cause, however obviously right, which entails humiliation and loss. As a Church, and as individuals, we are so placed. Our private preferences and interests thrust themselves unbidden &amp; unrecognised, into our public policies, and inject them an element which is alien and mischievous. When we speak of the Church, &amp; when we plead her necessities, we may be really seeking our own gains. "<hi rend="underline">The heart of man is deceitful &amp; desperately wicked. Who can know it</hi>?"</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The notion of writing a personal Apologia, &amp; making the "Charge" no more than the peg on which to hang it, persists and takes shape in my mind. <hi rend="italic">I wrote to Geoffrey Dawson asking him whether he could arrange for me to have transcripts of the letters which I have written to the Times in the course of nearly 40 years. </hi>They would supplement my Journal and my published works, and thus provide a fairly complete &amp; trustworthy record of the movements of my mind. The Articles in the Edinburgh Review must be added. I have no list of them, but copies of that Journal which I have include the following:&#8211;</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Jan</hi><hi rend="superscript underline" style="font&#8211;size:12pt">y</hi><hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt"> 1920</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">The Church and Socialism</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Oct. 1926</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Religion and Economics</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">April. 1927</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">The Composite Book</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Oct. 1927</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi style="font&#8211;size:12pt">Quakerism.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>None of these has any direct bearing on the problems of Establishment.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
