<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday in Holy Week, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I would not enter on my list of friends</p>
         <p>(Though graced with polish'd manners &amp; fine sense,</p>
         <p>Yet wanting sensibility) the man</p>
         <p>Who needlessly sets foot upon a worm.</p>
         <p>An inadvertent step may crush the snail</p>
         <p>That crawls at evening in the public path:</p>
         <p>But he that has humanity, forewarn'd,</p>
         <p>Will tread aside, &amp; let the reptile live.</p>
         <p>Cowper excepts "the creeping vermin" that disturbs our domestic comfort. "A necessary act incurs no blame." But if the insects nowise incommode us, they have a right to live.</p>
         <p>The sums is this. If man's convenience, health,</p>
         <p>Or safety interfere, his rights and claims</p>
         <p>Are paramount, &amp; must extinguish theirs.</p>
         <p>Else they are all – the meanest things that are</p>
         <p>As free to live, &amp; to enjoy that life,</p>
         <p>As God was free to form them at the first,</p>
         <p>Who in his sovereign wisdom made them all.</p>
         <p>How far could the advocate of "blood sports", who are plainly hard pressed for a moral excuse for their pleasure, build a case for hunting &amp; coursing on the healthful exercise which it provides?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I changed a cheque at the Bank: and then corrected the lecture on a 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Rector of Purleigh, named Washington, which Macdonald sent to me. It is to be published in U.S.A., and is quite accurate enough for that country. Then I resumed the dreary &amp; dirty job of clearing up my room. Much was destroyed: much hustled away into available recesses, there to lie unheeded until some general upheaval sends them also to destruction!</p>
         <p>During the afternoon Lionel and I walked round the Park together. The brilliance of the day, and the warmth, more suggestive of summer than of spring, made the open&#8211;air delightful. Lambs are beginning to appear in the fields, and the trees are receiving a waxing appearance of verdure. Who would exchange the country for the city, who has once known both?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Evening Paper, commenting on some observations that I made about quill pens and their relation to handwriting, observes that "like few clerics – and, incidentally fewer doctors – his own handwriting consists of extremely well made &amp; carefully formed outlines". This is one of the very few compliments which I can endure to receive.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
