<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">1929</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The world is white with snow under a clouded sky, and there is great stillness in the air. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 13 communicants including John, Harry Leng, and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Elland. I used in addition to the Collect for the Circumcision the little collect in the Revised Prayer Book for New Year's Day.</p>
         <p>"O eternal Lord God, who hast brought thy servants to the beginning of another year: Pardon, we humbly beseech thee, our transgressions in the past, and graciously abide with us all the days of our life: through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         <p>There is everything bound up in that single petition that God will "graciously abide with us", save only that we would add, since we are so weak &amp; forgetful, "that we may be conscious of His abiding Presence".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[66]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella and Linetta motored with me to Hartlepool in the afternoon. We went first to S. Hilda's Church, &amp; inspected the work of restoration which Car&amp;#x00F6;e has been carrying out. The new chancel is exquisite: the very difficult work on the Tower is in progress. Then I deposited the two ladies at Christ Church Vicarage, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">went on myself to S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Aidan's where Knowlden, with legitimate pride, showed me his fine new schools</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I went back to the Vicarage &amp; had talk with Canon &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Poole, with whom were their sons. Then we returned to the Castle, where Eric Fuller had arrived on a visit.</p>
         <p>This precious doctor who essays to cure my dyspepsia has succeeded in giving me a headache.</p>
         <p>William writes to tell me that he hopes soon to enter into the holy estate of matrimony.</p>
         
         
</body></text></TEI>
