<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The bitter weather continues. I spent the morning in visiting the great chemical works at Billingham which Lord Melchett controls. Sir Guy Wrightson was there, and four of the leading officials. After explaining the scheme of their production on a large map in the office, we made an inspection of the works, a vast and complicated spectacle of multifarious activities, in which some 11,000 men are employed. Then I was shown the attractive&#8211;looking houses in which the workmen live, the playing&#8211;fields, and Infant&#8211;Welfare Centre. Everything seems to be taken thought for, and provided <hi rend="underline">except</hi> Religion. The old tower of Billingham <hi rend="strikethrough">Church</hi>, in which <hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>parish<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> the works are situated, is everywhere visible, &amp; seems to be meditating on a scene which at once insults &amp; challenges it. Our inspection being finished, we went to Norton Hall, and had lunch very pleasantly, after which I thanked my entertainers and came home.</p>
         <p>These artificial manures are exported to all parts of the world, &amp; notably to the far East. I saw numbers of sack&#8211;fulls being stitched &amp; sent off, all labelled in Chinese and Japanese characters.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Much to my surprise I received a letter from Londonderry asking me to consent to the painting of my picture, [and suggesting Edmund Brock as the painter.] Of course, I could not but acquiesce, though I don't like either the process of "sitting", or the probability of collecting funds for an object of that useless and personal nature</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Even the completion of the series of episcopal portraits in Auckland Castle has lost much of its public importance now that we have drifted into a probability of Disestablishment.</p>
         <p>The agreement between the Pope and the King of Italy was signed yesterday, and with it a concordat regulating ecclesiastical procedure in Italy. Thus <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi> takes a leaf out of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Napoleon's</hi> book, and no doubt strengthens his position considerably. Whether the Roman Church has acted wisely is not so apparent. It has bound itself rather conspicuously to the cause of anti&#8211;democratic reaction.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
