<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macmillan</hi> a letter saying that his firm would "be happy to publish the Charge with your long preface on the usual half&#8211;profit basis".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi> asked me to introduce him into the House of Lords, but I had to refuse as I was already pledged to an interview with Downing.</p>
         <p>The new <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi> telegraphed to ask me to officiate at his father's funeral next Monday, but I had to refuse as I must be at the Assembly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> &amp; I motored into Durham, where I presided over the special meeting of the Diocesan Preventive &amp; Rescue Association. We accepted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Maud</hi>'s resignation, &amp; we adopted as an interim arrangement the proposal of the Women's Committee that we should entrust the direction of the work to the Deaconesses. Then we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Young <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stott</hi> and I walked round the Park in a downpour of rain. <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi> joined us on the way. He says that he notes more rabbits in the Park than he had supposed, but the squirrels seems to have disappeared.  He had seen none for the last two years.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
