<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked to the Church House, and spent a dismal morning listening to the dullest conceivable of debates on Patronage. I lunched at the Athenaeum. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Lytton</hi> came to the next table, &amp; started talking very interestingly about India. He said that on one of his official inspections, he had found a widow serving a sentence of 2 years imprisonment for child&#8211;murder. On inquiry he found that she had borne 4 children, all of whom had died in infancy: when her 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> child was born, she had recourse to the leaders of the sect, who told her that <hi rend="underline">if she presented it to the sacred crocodile in the Temple tank, it would be given back to her strong &amp; healthy. She followed this fatal advice, &amp; the babe was gobbled by the reptile</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lytton</hi> caused the poor creature to be set free, &amp; lamented his inability to punish the ill&#8211;counsellors. I interviewed two ordination candidates in the afternoon, &amp; then had tea in the Club. Lord Crawford &amp; Balcarres walked with me almost to Park Lane: where I dressed for dinner with the Club.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I dined at the Club: there were present:&#8211;</p>
         <p>Lord Sumner</p>
         <p>  "     Crawford &amp; Balcarres</p>
         <p>  "     Hugh Cecil</p>
         <p>Austen Chamberlain</p>
         <p>Hugh Macmillan</p>
         <p>Sir Henry Newbolt</p>
         <p> "   Charles Oman</p>
         <p>John Bailey</p>
         <p>Professor G.M. Trevelyan</p>
         <p>Bishop of Durham</p>
         <p>The Secretary (Kenyon)</p>
         <p>I sat between Lord Sumner &amp; Hugh Macmillan, and had a very pleasant evening. Our conversation was vivid &amp; well&#8211;sustained. It ranged over a great variety of subjects, &amp; contained an uncommonly large number of witty &amp; original utterances: but, when I seek to recall what interested me so much, I find nothing but a vague &amp; mingled mass of reminiscence, out of which nothing of lasting worth emerges!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
