<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Bitter cold, and snow falling at intervals. The morning was occupied in writing letters, among them one to Kenneth discussing "ways &amp; means", a subject which the youth hardly remembers sufficiently. In the afternoon Lionel &amp; I motored to Egglescliffe where I confirmed 44 persons in the parish church.</p>
         <p>N.B. S. Mary the Virgin is the dedication, not as was long maintained, S. John the Baptist. There is much woodwork in pulpit, screen, choir&#8211;stalls &amp; pews belonging to the period of the Restoration, when Isaac Basire was Rector. There are also two chained books – Jewel's Apology &amp; Eikon Basilike. In the porch (Norman) are some Anglo&#8211;Celtic fragments.</p>
         <p>After tea &amp; repose at Egglescliffe we went to Holy Trinity, Stockton, where I confirmed 105 persons. Then we returned to Auckland Castle, where we found that Major Fraser &amp; his wife had arrived. They both seemed extremely well&#8211;pleased with themselves, which is no doubt a proper state of mind for persons on their honeymoon. They sail for the East in a fortnight. Their married life will begin at Mandalay, where Major Frazer has received an appointment. I gathered that his work would mostly consist of training troops; and that there would be some English society – officers and their wives – to provide Kathleen with interests.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
