<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]In Roman Catholic countries persecution hardened into a necessary principle, which no man might question. In Protestant countries it was a matter of national policy.["]</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Creighton</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">Persecution &amp; Tolerance</hi>" p. 113</p>
         <p>["]Catholic intolerance is handed down from an age when unity subsisted, and when its preservation, being essential for that of society, became a necessity of State as well as a result of circumstances. Protestant intolerance, on the contrary, was the peculiar fruit of a dogmatic system, in contradiction with the facts &amp; principles on which the intolerance   actually existing among Catholics was founded. …. The only instance in which the Protestant theory has been adopted by Catholics is the revocation of the Edict of Nantes.["]</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Acton</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">The History of Freedom</hi>" p. 169</p>
         <p>In this Essay on "<hi rend="underline">The Protestant Theory of Persecution</hi>", Lord Acton produces some amazing opinions of all the leading Reformers in support of persecution.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella, Lionel and I motored to Sunderland, and, after picking up Wynne&#8211;Willson on the way, went to S. Andrew's, Roker, where I formally opened, and dedicated the fine Parish Hall and buildings connected therewith. The donor, Sir John Priestman, has expended &#x00A3;7,500 on the fabrick. There was a numerous company which filled the Hall for the opening service. I delivered an address, and afterwards was shown over the building. Then we all had tea with Sir John, and Lady Priestman, after which we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>There I found another batch of proofs from Macmillan.</p>
         <p>Spedding came, and resumed his difficult and comfortless efforts to adapt what he calls "dentures" to my preposterous jaws! In view of a cross&#8211;channel passage, the stability of one's teeth is a matter of equal uncertainty &amp; importance! The Channel&#8211;Tunnel will come too late for my use.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
