<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>This Arctic spell continues with a waxing list of deaths &amp; casualties, more or less caused by it. The Bishop&#8211;suffragan of Lewes (Streatfield) has soon followed his chief, the Bishop of Chichester. He died suddenly in the train.</p>
         <p>Knowlden slipped yesterday, &amp; broke a bone. He lies in the Hospital at York.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Myers of South Moor offering him the Rural Deanery of Lanchester in succession to Fedden. Briggs of Hunwick writes to accept Consett.</p>
         <p>I started to read Mackinnon's Luther &amp; the Reformation, of which 3 substantial vols. have now appeared. It appears to be learned, honest, &amp; dull.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote to <hi rend="underline">William</hi>.</p>
         <p>During the afternoon I walked round the Park: the frozen snow is beautiful but hard on the eyes. Drury &amp; his helpful parishioner M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> White called &amp; (though Ella was absent in Durham) had tea. <hi rend="italic">He wanted to consult me about the replies he had received to his advertisement for an assistant curate. I definitely refused to sanction his employment of a man who was stated to be in debt. That is the one clerical fault which these northerners will never condone. Drunkenness &amp; whoredom provoke comparatively little censure: are they no the common failings of humanity? But failure to pay one's debts is unpardonable!</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
