<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Carcassonne</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Before getting up I read a book by an American Professor of History (Princeton), Paul van Dyke, which seems a serious piece of work. – "Catherine de Médicis 2. vols. published by John Murray.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="bold underline">Robin</hi> and <hi rend="bold underline">Archbishop Davidson</hi>. Also to <hi rend="bold underline">Alexander</hi> and the <hi rend="bold underline">Bishop of Worcester</hi>. </p>
         <p>We walked into the City carrying the camera, and intending to use it. But our incompetence was too extreme, &amp; we did nothing: We fell in with <hi rend="bold underline">Dawson Walker</hi> &amp; his son with <hi rend="bold underline">Wallis</hi>, who were returning slowly to England after visiting Majorca. [struck through] Then we returned to the Hotel and lunched. The air became sultry, and the sky grew clouded. I did not feel disposed for any exertion, &amp; remained indoors, writing, reading, and SLEEPING! It occurred to me that it might be both kind and judicious to write to the new Archdeacon, <hi rend="underline">Rawlinson</hi>, who is keeping his first residence in Durham. He is a more convinced "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" than the position might seem to require: but he is able and amiable: and one must risk something. Also, I wrote to Lionel.[end]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Carcassonne</p>
         <p>There is no doubt in my mind that my decision to abandon the Establishment as no longer defensible has startled and alienated mist of those who might fairly have been described as my supporters. They are, indeed, unable to dispute the grounds on which that decision is based: but it is repugnant to their traditions, habits of thinking, preferences, and (as they suspect) interests. They are not accustomed to think out the reasons for political courses, nor are they disposed to consider the implications of any situation which matches their convenience. <hi rend="bold underline">Moreover, it cannot be denied that there was very little real desire for the Revised Prayer Book, and very little real regret at its rejection. There is a great volume of accumulated exasperation against the "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks", which predisposes even moderate Anglicans to acquiesce easily in anything that may be regarded as a defeat of their hopes. Accordingly, there is more indignation at the muddle into which the action of the House of Commons has brought the Church, than any genuine resentment at the humiliation inflicted on the spiritual Society</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Carcassonne</p>
         <p>Then I think it is the case that the general public has formed a gravely mistaken estimate of my actual opinions on the subject of Establishment. My books, as I know but too well, have never had a large <hi rend="strikethrough">publication</hi> circulation, but they have always attracted a good deal of attention, and been "reviewed", (generally with hostile bias) in many papers. <hi rend="bold underline">It is from these reviews, not from the books themselves, that the most part of men have formed their estimate of me: and thus they have failed to realize the reservations under which my defence of the Establishment has been made</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Then my conspicuous and protracted opposition to the Enabling Act tended to mislead people: and, in short, the extensive resentment which my present course provokes is equally explicable and unmerited. It is certainly highly significant that the Dissenters, who might have been expected to exult in the "conversion" of a prominent advocate of Establishment, are quite clearly embarrassed and chagrined. They shrink from the prospect of applying their principles in practice.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[231]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Carcassonne</p>
         <p>The final stage of every sojourn in a hotel includes the melancholy, &amp; sometimes dismaying, experience of paying one's reckoning. Both adjectives were appropriate to my sentiments when I learned that 3 days in the Hotel de la Cité had cost no less than 2104.30 i.e. nearly &#x00A3;16.!! The excellence of the rooms, fitted with bathroom &amp;c accounted for much, &amp; the inflation of all prices by the ceaseless flood of Americans explained the rest. After paying the bill I have 3330 f. left.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Our journey to Pau was prefaced by a somewhat hectic departure, for the omnibus was so filled with Americans that we had to be sent from the hotel to the station in a taxi: &amp;, by consequence, I was much hustled in getting the tickets (415 f.). We changed at Toulouse, &amp; had a hasty &amp; horrid dejeuner on the station. We arrived at Pau about 4 p.m.: &amp; went to the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hotel de France</hi>, where we had engaged rooms. The last stages of the journey were relieved by <hi rend="underline">fine views of the Pyrenees, on which much snow was lying</hi>. Ella and I strolled into the town, and bought ink and soap.</p>
         <p>Before leaving Carcassonne we went into the Church of S. Nazaire, which adjoins the Hotel de la Cité: and admired the exceeding beauty of the medieval glass in the Apse, which the morning sun illuminated magnificently. This church impressed me greatly. It reminded me in some respects of Durham with which I suppose it was coeval: and it has been well preserved. I wrote my name in the Hotel book with some flattering words.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>

