<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I did not feel well, indeed I suspected that I had caught a chill. But I stayed in the Athenæum all day, &amp; shook it off sufficiently to dine in the Carpenters' Hall, and give a lecture on the Castle. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi> presided, &amp; there was a large attendance. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>I spoke on the Palatine Jurisdiction and the History of the Castle – repeating much of the lecture I gave some weeks ago at Harrogate – and  then acted showman to the slides. After the Lecture, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Tait</hi> spoke to me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi> gave me a lift in his car to Park Lane, and talked to me about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi>. I fear the outlook in that quarter is not promising.<hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to young Lacey, declining his rather cheeky suggestion that I should discuss Disestablishment with him: and also to J.G. Wilson, condoling with him on the death of his friend &amp; coeval, Kirk.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Buchan</hi> joined me at lunch in the club, and we had some talk. He, and all these Scots, is very confident that they have found a solution of the problem of church &amp; State: &amp; thinks that we in England may build our policy on their precedent. Herein I am persuaded they are gravely mistaken. "<hi rend="underline">You have a great following</hi>", he said, referring to my declared policy of "<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment by consent</hi>". The Athenaeum is a nest of clever Scots. Buchan, Hugh Macmillan, Archie Fleming, George Macmillan, the Moderator, &amp; a host of others were all in the lunching room together!</p>
         <p>I fell in with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of Wales</hi>, &amp; talked of ecclesiastical matters. I asked him how the Welsh Church was faring under Disestablishment. "It has transformed the country", he replied. "For good? or for ill?", I inquired. "Oh, for good", he answered, adding that no one would desire to return to the former régime. When it is remembered that the Archbishop was a vehement opponent of Welsh Disestablishment, this testimony cannot but be regarded as very impressive <hi rend="bold">[</hi>though, indeed, I do not set a high value on the honesty of the witness! Yet why should he not say the truth in the matter?<hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
