<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]While the undisputed orthodoxy of the University of Paris set it above bishops and synods, and gave it influence enough even to organize a general council, the prestige of Oxford was lost through its support of Wyclif, and it became the handmaid of the episcopacy.["]</p>
         <p>Creighton. Hist. of the Papacy, i., 112.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Henry Martin Gillett</hi>; from S. Chad's College, came to lunch, and to be interviewed with a view to Ordination. He had been in America, &amp; had heard Bryan in the Dayton trial. He had also met Hoover, the new President of U.S.A., when engaged on organizing relief for the victims of the Mississippi Flood. He expressed himself with modesty, intelligence, and candour, so that I was agreeably disappointed, since I had not expected to find such qualities in a student of an Anglo&#8211;Catholic seminary. Finally, I promised to ordain him at Trinity, if he passed the Examining Chaplains' examination.</p>
         <p>Lionel &amp; I motored to Darlington, where I discussed the S. Cuthbert's School problem with Cosgrave, &amp; then went on to Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne, where I confirmed about 50 candidates. After the service had ended, we returned to Auckland.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
