<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>I know how dangerous it is to follow truth too near to the heels; yet better it is that the teeth of an historian be struck out of his head for writing the truth, than that they remain still and rot in his jaws, by feeding too much on the sweetmeats of flattery.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fuller</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="underline">Church History</hi><hi>. ix. 28 (v.227)</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>It is not the fear of giving offence that betrays the modern historian into falsehood, but reluctance to undergo the prolonged &amp; tiresome labour of ascertaining truth. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fuller's</hi><hi> entertaining pages owe their charm &amp; sparkle to the lack of research which they betray. He retails the fresh gossip of contemporaries, and brightens the story with little personal touches and impressions: &amp; these give his narrative the freshness of witty conversation. When he handles records, he tumbles them into his record bodily to the disgust of his readers. The modern historian is haunted by his authorities. They are so many, so various, so conflicting, &amp; often so inaccessible, that he despairs of getting into touch with them all.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 am. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was indisposed, and kept her room: so we numbered but 5 communicants.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After breakfast, I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; sent him both the letter which was returned through the "Dead letter Office", and one of the "Durham Castle" tracts. I started to read Angus's new book, "The Mystery Religions &amp; Christianity", and found it very interesting. In the afternoon, the brilliant weather tempted me to walk round the Park. I picked up three youths, engaged in some sort of improvised Sunday game, and carried them with me for the rest of the walk. They covenanted to come next Wednesday to see the Castle. Will they come? I note their names, Alfred Kitchen, George Robert Rison, Albert Burnham. I left the Castle at 4.45 p.m., and was delayed by a puncture at Croxdale, but none the less reached Hanton in good time for the service at 6.30 p.m. I preached to a congregation which barely filled the little church. The Vicar (Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> G. H. Ashworth) has held the parish for 24 years. He was ordained in 1886. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bowcock, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Oswin's, S. Shields was there &#8211; an arid, cantankerous man.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>