<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The problem of reconciling Christianity, as distinct from religion of any other kind, with science must needs take the form of reconciling it with historical science, with which perhaps the science of criticism may be coupled. So far as Christianity is concerned this, unquestionably, is the point where shoe pinches most severely at the present time, and I have no hesitation in saying that </hi><hi rend="underline">unless Christianity can gain the approval of historical and critical science for the alleged historical facts on which it reposes, notably the fact of the Incarnation, the reconciliation with physics &amp; biology, however complete, will not save it from intellectual collapse, at least in the official form of it</hi><hi>. So far as I can learn from the essay in the volume before me the neo tendency contributes nothing to the reconciliation of Christianity &amp; Science at this critical point.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Principal L. P. Jacks</hi><persName xml:id="320"></persName><hi>. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Religion &amp; Science</hi><hi>" in the "Observer" Dec: 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1925.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This is an unpleasant but unavoidable inference from the volume, "Science, Religion, &amp; Reality."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At 10.30 a.m. I left the Castle, and motored to Durham, where I confirmed 55 boys of Durham School, and 5 of the Cathedral choristers. The service was attended by a considerable number of the relatives &amp; friends of the candidates: and, on the whole. I though it a very impressive service. After the confirmation, I went to the Castle, &amp; licensed 3 clergy, of whome one, Wilkinson, was licensed to the newly formed district Chilton. Then I lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in the Country Club. He introduced me to his son&#8211;in&#8211;law, Major Atkinson. After lunch I went to the Cathedral, &amp; sate in my Thorne while Brahms's Requiem was reduced by the Choir. Then I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, &amp; talked over some questions of diocesan policy. At 5.45 p.m. we left Durham, and motored to Dalton&#8211;le&#8211;Dale, where I dedicated an [sic] Chancel Screen, &amp; other gifts. I gave an address to a congregation, which was reduced by the inclement weather. After the service we returned to Auckland, where we arrived shortly before 9 p.m. Thus a whole day was expended in a series of functions, no one of which can be described as important, yet of which none could have been declined without neglect of duty.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>