<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>It is the heart, and not the place, that worshippeth God. The kitchen&#8211;page turning the spit, may have a purer heart to God than his master at Church: and therefore worship God better in the kitchen than his masters at church</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tindale</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Answer to More's Dialogue</hi><hi>["]. p.88.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>There was a reluctant thaw with threatenings of fog, and very chilly. I thought it prudent to send a telegram to Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, "crying off" my promise to attend the Pageant in Sunderland tonight. And I was the more inclined to this pusillanimous course since I was afflicted with premonitions of lumbago. So I kept indoors, &amp; read much of, and about Tyndale. Also, I despatched [sic] copies of the "notes" to Bishop Lawrence, Bishop. Mann, Anson Phelps Stokes<persName xml:id="1565"></persName>, Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName>, &amp; Harold<persName xml:id="1097"></persName>, all in North America.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> E. &amp; I sent me a copy of the report of the Sub.&#8211;Commission on Durham Cathedral. My scheme is "dammed with faint praise"</hi><hi>! The Dean of Gloucester<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> wrote to me in some perturbation about signing it.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It is not easy to be fair to the Reformers. All the conditions, under which they were led to frame their great protest, have passed away, &amp; the protest itself stands out in unrelieved crudity &amp; violence. Then it is the case that their governing principle, the sole &amp; sufficient authority of the Scriptures, no longer commands our acceptance. We look back on the Medieval Church from a point distant enough to conceal its scandals, &amp; yet near enough to disclose its amazing achievements. The magnificent courage of the first Reformers is not remembered, only their fanaticism and brutality. In the controversy between More and Tindale [sic], the modern vote is cast on the side of the fascinating &amp; courtly litterateur: &amp; yet when the two men are fairly considered, and the circumstances in which they lived &amp; laboured taken into account, can it be denied that the Reformer merits the greater homage? Both men were heroes. It is hard to say which of the two has left a nobler story of martyrdom: but while More had every secular advantage, Tindale [sic] had to work in the teeth of every obstacle. And, when all is said, the English Bible is a greater achievement than "Utopia".</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>