<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>&#x3C4;&#x3B7;&#x3BD;&#x3B5;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B1;, a word formed by Archil (Fr. 106) to imitate the twang of a guitar&#8211;string: he began a triumphal hymn to Hercules with &#x3C4;&#x3B7;&#x3BD;&#x3B5;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B1;, &#x3C9; &#x3BA;&#x3B1;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B9;&#x3BD;&#x3B9;&#x3BA;&#x3B5; &#x3C7;&#x3B1;&#x3B9;&#x3C1;&#x3B5; &#8211; and so the words &#x3C4;&#x3B7;&#x3BD;&#x3B5;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B1; &#x3BA;&#x3B1;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B9;&#x3BD;&#x3B9;&#x3BA;&#x3B5;</hi></p>
         <p><hi>became a common mode of saluting conquerors in the games, a kind of Hazza.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Liddell &amp; Scott.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName><hi> sends me a post&#8211;card from Hereford inscribed significantly &#x3C4;&#x3B7;&#x3BD;&#x3B5;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B1; &#x3C9; &#x3BA;&#x3B1;&#x3BB;&#x3BB;&#x3B9;&#x3BD;&#x3B9;&#x3BA;&#x3B5; &#x3C7;&#x3B1;&#x3B9;&#x3C1;&#x3B5; this goes to show that Hereford is in fighting form.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wasted the whole morning cleaning up my room, destroying much "exhausted" material, &amp; preparing for my exit. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived at lunch time, and went with me into Durham for the Ordination. I had the candidates in the Castle, which is now equipped with electric light.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Captain Carter came to see me. His report on the Bishoprick is encouraging. I do not think the loss on the first year's working will exceed &#x00A3;35. But the contributions for the Diocesan Fund are not coming in at all satisfactorily.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I interviewed the 7 candidates. It is difficult to know what can most wisely be said to them. Probably they find me </hi><hi rend="underline">very</hi><hi> hard and unsympathetic, though truly I desire to help them. It is in this part of my episcopal duty that I feel myself most completely inadequate. An unconquerable reticence comes over me whenever my own religious experiences are in question, &amp; I find it difficult to understand a generation which </hi><hi rend="underline">loves</hi><hi> to discuss its inner life!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Canon Cosgrave<persName xml:id="5313"></persName> gave the address at Evensong. It was certainly better than I expected both in form &amp; substance. He said some useful things, and said them well.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came over, but did not spend the night at the Castle. He expressed much approval at my letter on the Hereford Bishoprick. I told him that I would write in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi> on "Religion &amp; Education", and thus make clear to the diocese the line which I intend to pursue in the matter of the Church Schools. He confirmed what Stephenson told me last night as to the revolt of C.E.T.S.<orgName xml:id="188"></orgName> against the Bishop of Durham, engineered by the Dean of Durham. Well, well!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>