<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Eve, Thursday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The bitter weather continues with unlessened severity. The papers are filled with reports of casualties caused by the storms and snow&#8211;drifts.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I received from D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Wallis his report on Jimmie's<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> conduct and work, together with his papers. In some respects both are certainly disappointing. I am specially surprised that emphasis should be laid on his lack of discipline. The Principal expresses some doubt as to his being fit for Ordination at Trinity. He must not be hustled, but it will complicate matters if he has to wait until Advent.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch I walked around the Park with Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>. The snow was crisp, and the sky clear. A red sunset presaged a continuance of the frost.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Vicar brought in his Choir &amp; others to sing carols in the Chapel. They sang very sweetly. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> gave them coffee, and I bestowed &#x00A3;1. on the "caps". How shrunken &amp; heartless are our Christian observances now by comparison with the full&#8211;blooded hilarity of former times! Still, so far as it goes, our meagre festivity is worth preserving.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I paid the monstrous sum of &#x00A3;50 in tax for my two motors for the coming year.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>






