<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The prevalence of asceticism on any large scale has invariably been coincident with social upheavals and economic confusion, and such conditions as drive men out of the old ways &amp; discredit the working theories of a corporate life. In such periods the burden of family &amp; social ties becomes oppressive. The birth–rate declines. Men eschew marriage in the bitter struggle against hunger, &amp; because of the universal sorrow over the sufferings &amp; loss of children which makes celibacy desirable, which again often conduces to the </hi><hi rend="underline">perversio vitae sexualis</hi><hi>. The comforts of life are denied &amp; the world is given up in despair.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Angus</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi><hi> p.224</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This is no untrue description of the present age. The post–war world discloses a falling birth–rate, a growing dislike of marriage, and an alarming increase in "unnatural" vice. The popularity of Communistic theories may be regarded as the modern equivalent of ancient asceticism.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Several inches of snow smothered the landscape. I started to read a volume of essays edited by Professor Hearnshaw, "The Social &amp; Political Ideas of some Great Thinkers of the Renaissance and the Reformation". At 3.30 p.m. I left the Castle, &amp; motored to Stockton. where I attended a meeting convened by the Mayor of Stockton (L. Ropner) in the interest of the Church Extension Scheme. It was, as I could see, not a large, I conjecture that it was not an influential meeting. The days of church building are past. All the parish clergy, except Loney, who is ill, were present, &amp; a number of ladies. We were unanimous, and mutually complimentary, but what else we were that is good or helpful I know not. After the meeting I returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> sends me a review which he has contributed to "The Nation" on Loisy's<persName xml:id="1083"></persName> "L'Église et la France". I notice that the common and confident affirmation of a great religious revival in France since the war is flatly denied. "With regard to the effect of the war upon religion, our own experience should secure us against deception. In France, as in England, there has been no revival, but a general, an alarming, decline."</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>