<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>From first to last his style and his interpretation are his own, &amp; in the originality of Tindale is included in a large measure the originality of our English Version. For not only did Tindale contribute to it directly the substantial basis of half of the Old Testament (in all probability) and of the whole of the New, </hi><hi rend="underline">but he established a standard of Biblical translation which others followed.</hi><hi> It is even of less moment that by far the greatest part of his translation remains intact in our present Bibles than that his spirit animates the whole…….</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">His influence decided that our Bible should be popular &amp; not literary, speaking in a simple dialect, &amp; that so by its simplicity it should be endowed with permanence. </hi><hi>He felt by a happy instinct the potential affinity between Hebrew &amp; English idioms, &amp; enriched our language &amp; thought forever with the characteristics of the Semitic mind.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="1047"></persName><hi>. </hi><hi rend="underline">Hist: of Eng: Bible</hi><hi>. p.158.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Yet, so far as I know, there has been no general movement to commemorate fittingly the 400</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of the publication of Tindale's New Testament.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hoskyns</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="underline">the Bishop of Southwell, died yesterday. </hi><hi>He had for some time past languished under that fell disease, cancer, so that his death had been expected. I first came into personal touch with him in 1887, when he was Rector of Stepney, &amp; I was Head of the Oxford House in Bethnal Green. He was a conventional High Churchman, hard, unimaginative, hostile to ideas. Still I was rather startled when he joined in the opposition to my consecration, &amp; refused to take part in the ceremony. And I resented deeply his attempt to represent me as having recanted my heresies. He actually used the offensive word, which was as unmerited on my part, as it was injurious on his. Well, he knows where truth lies now.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Dean of Westminster elect, Foxley Norris, wrote to tell me that his son&#8211;in&#8211;law, Rolt, had had a severe stroke, &amp; was reported by the doctors to be stricken irrecoverably. I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Rolt.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Dean of Hereford went away by the morning train. I tramped round the Park through frozen snow. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Monkwearmouth, where I "collated" the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> J. K. Hawke to vicarage of the old church of Benedict Biscop<persName xml:id="5320"></persName>. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>