<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Without a single lecture, either public or private, either Christian or protestant, without any Academical subscription, without any episcopal confirmation. I was left, by the dim light of my Catechism, to grope my way to the Chapel and communion table, where I was admitted without a question how far or by what means I might be qualified to receive the sacrament. Such almost incredible neglect was productive of the worst mischiefs. From my childhood I had been fond of Religious disputation: my poor aunt has been often puzzled by my objections to the mysteries which she strove to believe; nor had the elastic spring been totally broken by the weight of the Atmosphere of Oxford. The blind activity of idleness urged me to advance without armour into the dangerous mazes of controversy and at the age of sixteen I bewildered myself in the errors of the Church of Rome.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gibbon's</hi><hi> </hi><hi rend="underline">Autobiography</hi><hi> p.83 </hi></p>
         <p><hi>ed. Murray.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The wintry weather continues. There was more snow last night, &amp; snow&#8211;storms at intervals during the day. I did not leave the house, "nursing a cold", but I took some exercise by walking in the Chapel and its approach. An internal gallery is clearly a requisite in the northern latitudes. Beyond writing letters, &amp; reading the papers nothing was done. Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> arrived from Birmingham. She seems as vivacious and cheerful as ever, but clearly finds the society of the midland metropolis rather oppressive. There is a solid &amp; vainglorious materialism about the Birmingham people, before which the things of the spirit fail &amp; pass. She thinks that the Bishop is winning in his conflict with the "Catholicks", though somewhat fatigued by the conflict.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I sent a copy of my book to Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> sent a Christmas card from Java. He says the temperature there is 100° in the shade, and 140° in the sun. There is something morally beautiful about the fidelity of such simple natures as his. I received a letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, conceived in a more cheerful vein than heretofore. He is now 25 years old, and has been 16 months in Johannesburg.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>