<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The uneducated are spiritually less independent than the reflective, and are less able to bear the burden of sin and the guilt of conscience. To them something corresponding to the Roman confessional is an imperative necessity. State religions in their heyday might repress this tendency, but in their decay, when the beautified temple and the elaborate ceremonial only testified to the splendour they had departed, the populace went its own way in search of religion.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Angus</hi><hi>. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Mystery Religions</hi><hi>" p.161.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The writer has in his view the process by which the mystery&#8211;religions won their victory over the State Religion of imperial Rome, but his words have an uncomfortably modern relevance. Methodism, Salvationism, this new debased sacramentalism of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, are illustrations of the same phenomenon viz: the victory of popular superstition over reasonable religion. Resisting the process is as hopeful as proceeding as Dame V. Partington's effort to stay the Atlantic with her broom! The outlook for considering men, who would have Religion intelligent, is sufficiently gloomy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[24]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>More snow fell in the course of the day, and the general outlook continues very wintery. I revised and sent to the Editor of the Times the letter on the Disruption of Hereford, but not without hesitation, as I can't quite make out what is being arranged by the gerrymanders. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had convened the Knutsford Men who have been ordained in the diocese to a service &amp; lunch. I gave them every one a copy of Lightfoot's<persName xml:id="1817"></persName> Ordination Address. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I essayed to walk in the Park, but soon returned, as it started to snow again. Then I returned to reading Angus's book on the Mystery Religions, and finished it. I am not surprised to see that it has been already re&#8211;printed. It is full of information excellently arranged, and the author has a pleasant style. The pronouncements of the Bishop of Birmingham<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> have directed public attention to the connexion between Christianity and the mystery&#8211;cults which it vanquished and replaced. Many good folks are curious on the subject, and Angus gives them precisely what they want. He is fortunate in having published his book so appositely to the time.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A rather denunciatory article, "D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Henson &amp; Lourdes Miracles" appears in "The Catholic Times".</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>