<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The Papacy in particular, under such Popes as Sixtus IV, Alexander VI, and Julius II, forgetting its sacred nature, and ignoring its international responsibilities, made itself notorious for its violence, selfishness, treachery, and mendacity. Machiavelli came to regard it as the root cause of Italy's disunion and debasement.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hearnshaw</hi><hi> on Machiavelli in "The Social &amp; Political Ideas &amp;c" p.97.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The debasement of the papacy is a recurrent phenomenon in the History of the Church. In the 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Century, and again in the 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and yet again in the 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>&#8211;16</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, the foulest factor in Christendom was the Papacy. Is it really possible to harmonise this dolorous fact with </hi><hi rend="underline">any</hi><hi> theory of the Popedom which could make it integral to the well&#8211;being of the Christian Church? Yet, the doctrine of the Roman Church makes the Papacy essential, and clothes it with the Divine attribute of infallibility. It is the very perversity of unreason. Divine&#8211;right is nowhere else so closely bound to its own disproof.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I finished the volume of Essays. The 3 essays on Erasmus, Luther, &amp; Calvin are excellent, especially perhaps, the first. Then I wrote the names of the candidates in the Testaments &amp; Bibles. They are the following:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Deacons:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>John Savage (Shotton.)</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Reginald Christopher Union (S. Gabriel's S.)</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Priests:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Thorwald Coates (S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Hilda's H.)</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Rodolphus Thomas Heselton. (Gateshead)</hi></p>
         <p><hi>George Doyle Simmonds (S. Mary, Tyne&#8211;dock)</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The three lads (v.p. 22) kept tryst, and went round the castle with me. I gave them tea before they departed.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I left the Castle at 5.45 p.m. and motored to Dawdon, stopping on the way through Durham to see Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> who had returned from Northumberland, &amp; affirmed with unconvincing positiveness that he was completely recovered. I instituted Duncan to the incumbency of the parish. There was a considerable congregation, a large &amp; energetic choir, &amp; a dignified service. I was particularly pleased to see Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName> in the congregation as I feared he might still be resentful of my refusal to appoint the curate. After the service I returned to Auckland, arriving about 9.30 p.m.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>