<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather was mild and blustering, not favourable to work. I laboured at the Article, but not at all to my satisfaction. Is it the effect of advancing years that my brain is so reluctant, &amp; my composition so slow and halting? I suffered so much from the tooth ache [sic] that I betook me to the dentist, who patched me up, &amp; arranged to remove the offence on February 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. Then I looked in at the Edgar Hall, where the Rural Dean was entertaining the children of the Deanery. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><persName xml:id="3220"></persName><hi> sent me a civil letter thanking me for my book, which, he said, interested him the more as a friend of his had fallen under </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson's</hi><hi> influence. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Shaftesbury</hi><hi>, as President of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName>, writes impudently to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, declaring what course his precious society is taking in Birmingham, where it appears that a kind of informal schism is being organized! And </hi><hi rend="underline">this</hi><hi> is Catholicism!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName><hi> writes:&#8211; "I see in his pamphlet on Reservation. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Father Bull</hi><hi> says that it is the unbelief of the bishops which makes them refuse to sanction the Cult: &amp; that if in the Revision settlement this is not conceded, it is doubtful whether the Federation of Catholic Priests will obey."</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>