<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 12 communicants. Then there was a reception and distribution of Christmas gifts. What children we are, and what toys delight us! The post brought me a letter from the Bishop of Birmingham<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>, which indicates fresh trouble in his quarter. The lawless clergy, pressed by the law, are retorting on their inexorable rulers that he also is breaking the law by allowing dissenters to preach in parish churches. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi> turns to me for legal justifications of his conduct. But I doubt if there are any, only larger pleas of reason &amp; religious. I sent him the volume "</hi><hi rend="underline">Christian Liberty</hi><hi>", which contains my correspondence with Ingram in 1918: but it is a pity to have given an advantage to the Fanaticks at his juncture. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>In the afternoon we all motored to Durham and attended the Evensong in the Cathedral. Afterwards we went to a reception at the Bishop of Jarrow's<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. Then we returned home, &amp; I read that most entertaining book, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maitland's</hi><hi> </hi><hi rend="underline">Essays on the Reformation</hi><hi> until dinner, after which I read aloud to my family Milton's Ode on the Nativity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"It is a grave matter that some thousands of religious teachers throughout the country, men whose position demands that their utterances should be treated with respect by those to whom they speak, should, in the interests of a quite modern conception of what the Church of England really is, be now insisting on a minimizing account of what happened at the Reformation, such as no historian would accept as even nearly accurate. And the gravity lies, not in the mere holding of a mistaken estimate, but in the proceedings that are based thereupon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A. W. Hutton's Introduction to the reprint of Maitland's Essays on Subjects connected with the Reformation. 1899.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This is true, and well expressed. We have to reckon now with a generation of Anglicans which has been reared on the fictions of Wakeman, Hutton<persName xml:id="2511"></persName>, and a host of such–like writers of false history, and both law and religion are handled in the light of a fundamental perversion of the facts.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>