<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>They will say haply, the scripture requireth a pure mind and a quiet mind: and therefore, the lay&#8211;man, because he is altogether cumbered with worldly business, cannot understand them. If that be the cause, then it is a plain case that our prelates understand not the scriptures themselves: for no layman is so tangled with worldly business as they are. The great things of the world are ministered by them: neither do the lay&#8211;people any great thing, but at their assignment.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tindale</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Obedience</hi><hi> &amp;c" p.146.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>In the XVI</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century the secular activity of the higher ecclesiastics was forced on public attention at every turn. The retort which Tindale [sic] makes was not only effective but just. It was not normally possible for the politician&#8211;bishops to concern themselves with sacred study, or with pastoral work, or with ecclesiastical discipline. For them to object against the layman's reading of the Scripture that his absorption in worldly affairs was disqualifying was almost ludicrously indecent. But in the XX</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century the bishops are still absorbed in business, only not the large affairs of State, but the squalid details of clerical policy!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>An iron frost holds the earth, and the birds are clearly hard&#8211;pressed for food. I celebrated Holy Com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> in the Chapel at 5 a.m. After breakfast I put together notes for a sermon on Tindale [sic] for Belmont. "Bible Sunday" suggests a commemoration of that excellent man. I motored to Belmont, &amp; preached at Evensong. The little church was mortally cold. I took the opportunity of speaking to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maish</hi><persName xml:id="5213"></persName><hi> in order to suggest that he should give Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> a title at Trinity, and let him read for a degree in Durham. He seemed to be attracted by the suggestion, but was doubtful whether a house could be obtained within the parish. Would I approve of his living outside the parish? I replied that I would do so, if the house were near enough to enable him to do his work efficiently. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> joined me after the service, &amp; we returned to Auckland together. The people at Belmont, who have been mostly on the "dole" for a year past, are now overjoyed at the tidings that the Sherburn House pit will re&#8211;open on Monday. This means, of course, that a fresh draft will be made on the subsidy. What will happen next May, when the subsidy ceases, it is not difficult to conjecture, for there are no real evidences of any improvement in the prices in the coal&#8211;trade.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>