<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">As I expected, I feel uncommonly fit this morning, &amp; could travel quite well, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">have to keep up the farce of illness by remaining until tomorrow</hi><hi rend="italic">! The "Times" has a fairly reasonable report of last night's performance, though the Heading &#8211; "The Bishop of Durham. Fainting Fit while Preaching" &#8211; has an alarming appearance. The "Morning Post" gives prominence to the interesting fact that the Bishop of D. had "a fainting seizure in a London Congregational Church".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Price </hi><hi rend="italic underline">of 133 Harley Street</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to see me. I did my best to convince him that physically I was the arrantest humbug in the world: &amp; that, in spite of my ghastly aspect last night, I was "as fit as a fiddle" this morning. But he would have none of it. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The fainting fit you had last night was a very serious one, not an ordinary faint at all</hi><hi rend="italic">". He evidently has the notion of a possible stroke running in his head: &amp; insisted on my going to him tomorrow to have my blood&#8211;pressure taken, &amp; my heart examined. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yet he assured me that I was the kind of man to live to be 90</hi><hi rend="italic">! A fine prospect in such a world as this is becoming!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In the course of the afternoon a telegram arrived from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Buckingham Palace</hi><hi rend="italic"> in these terms:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The King &amp; Queen are concerned to hear of your illness but trust that you can give a good account of yourself today".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote what I conceived to be a suitable reply to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><persName xml:id="3220"></persName><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi rend="italic"> called to inquire of my state, &amp; there were other callers. The publicity of petty personal calamities adds enormously to their gravity. An announcement in the great London papers starts a journalistic snowball, which goes on waxing, until it becomes something actually alarming. Then there is the unfortunate impression of physical weakness which is conveyed, &amp; which continues to hang about your name long after it has lost all justification. But, I suppose, this untoward episode </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> a warning which I ought not to neglect. Of course I am no longer young. My contemporaries are dying off quickly. And "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">in his 63</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rd</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> year</hi><hi rend="italic">" would read normally in an obituary notice! It is a woeful reflection that I have no more to show for my life than this Journal presents.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>