<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[141]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in revising the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Tyndale lecture, which I had undertaken to deliver to the Newcastle Theological Society. It was really hardly worth my while to bestow so much labour on the precious thing, for there were no more than 50 persons who turned up to hear it, when I read it in the lecture&#8211;room at Armstrong College at 5.30 p.m. The Bishop of Newcastle and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Wilde were there. Of course the pressure of work in Lent may have affected the attendance of the clergy, and the rain was falling so pitilessly that no one who had not a keen interest in the subject would be likely to turn out. But I must needs grudge the expenditure of time &amp; toil.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After the lecture, I proceeded to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Edmund's Church, Gateshead, and confirmed about 100 candidates. Then I picked up </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="5385"></persName><hi>, &amp; carried him back with me to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I advised Brooke to decline the offer of a small country parish: to make his wife's health the first consideration in deciding his movements: to consider with the physicians whether she could be safely sent to live at Lumley: &amp; to take on another curacy if she must go south.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>