<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>There was a rapid thaw during the night, and such snow that remained at day&#8211;dawn had vanished before the evening fell. But the wind was keen, &amp; the temperature very low.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My new chaplain and I cleared off the accumulation of correspondence, a task which left small time for any other.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Manchester Guardian gives prominence to the report of a "discovery" in the Ryland's Library on which Rendall Harris has reared a considerable argument leading to the conclusion that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">as early as the 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> century, or even the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> there was a tradition in the Church, independent of any interpretation of Isaiah 53, that our Saviour was of little stature, indeed only 5 feet 2 inches in height</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I meditate an article on the suggested Tax on Betting, and lightening it with some references to the curious treatise on "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Nature &amp; Use of Lots"</hi><hi> by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Gataker</hi><hi> published in 1619. It is full of curious interest, and gives a favourable impression of the author. He evidently belonged to the elect company of Puritans who were neither morose, nor conceited.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>