<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[291]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The days since the operation have been very hard to live through. At first, it seemed to me, that I was in a state of semi–delirium. Always I was in a car racing along between rows of watching miners. At night especially my misery was great. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> came to see me, &amp; bought me flowers, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but the darling's deafness made conversation very exhausting</hi><hi>.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi> came, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but he smelt of tobacco, &amp; I got rid of him quickly</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> On Saturday, old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir David Drummond</hi><hi> had half an hour's talk – a delightful old man.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[292] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After a sleepless &amp; troubled night, I felt tired out before the day began. But I am assured that I am making good progress to recovery; so I must hold on.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Drummond</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke of his experiences in France. He said "I went out as C.O.E: &amp; came back as Presbyterian". I asked the reason. He replied that when he first was in France his Hospital was served by 2 chaplains, C.O.E &amp; Presbyterian. They were good men, &amp; worked heartily together. Their combined services were well attended; but then there was a change: the C.O.E. chaplain was replaced by a younger man of a different spirit. He broke up the united service: w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have no dealings with Presbyterians with the result that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nobody</hi><hi rend="italic"> at all went to his orthodox services, while about 130 held on to the Presbyterian. I enquired further whether he had ever had any heart–to–heart talk with the youth on the matter: &amp; he replied that he had, but found him hopeless. He took high ground &amp; c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not be reasoned with. This was an experience which, I fear, was but too common in the case of our Chaplains. Lionel &amp; the Bishop of Newcastle came to see me during the afternoon.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> The latter told me that he had himself had his appendix removed: &amp; was in the nursing home when the offer of the Bpk. of Newcastle was made to him. That was early in Sept: &amp; he was consecrated on Nov: 30</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>