<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Mercier's</hi><persName xml:id="3626"></persName><hi> death is given great prominence in the newspapers. He was a man who owed much to the War, for then he disclosed the qualities of character &amp; courage which have secured for him a place among the greatest figures of that immense disaster. Had his death befallen in July 1914, he would only have been remembered in England as the typical Roman hierarch, hard, bigoted, unimaginative, whom Father Tyrrell's<persName xml:id="1084"></persName> invective had made notorious. Now his place is among the immortals, the patriot&#8211;prelate </hi><hi rend="underline">par excellence</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the morning in writing an Article for the Evening Standard on "A Tax on Betting", and despatched [sic] it by the afternoon post</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In the afternoon I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Board for Church Building. I walked into the town, &amp; visited Rushworth's furniture shop. There were many things that I coveted badly, but the prices were prohibitive. I had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon Derry</hi><persName xml:id="3688"></persName><hi> &amp; returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Page&#8211;Gourlay came to pay us a final visit before leaving this district, and going south. I paid taxes for male servants &amp; dogs.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>