<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[219]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 21 communicants including the following:&#8211; Ashton, Lang, Harry, George Laws, Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName>, &amp; James. I used the Cosin plate.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The doctor came to see me about 10 a.m., &amp; stayed chatting for half&#8211;an&#8211;hour. Except to maintain the fiction of my being ill, there was no reason for his calling. In the course of his conversation, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he mentioned that Hodgson's<persName xml:id="5274"></persName> brother is the care&#8211;taker of an institute in the town. This circumstance adds to my astonishment that my predecessor sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> have been so foolish as to appoint him to Escombe. He ought to have had sufficient knowledge of the world, &amp; of human nature, to know that, in the case of a man of the labouring class who has been pushed forward into Holy Orders, the one chance of his acquiring some proper consciousness of the clerical office, &amp; some decent gravity of deportment, is his removal from the too&#8211;familiar environment in which he has been reared. I doubt if anything could have made H. a reverently mannered clergyman. In constant contact with his family, &amp; allied to the Labour Party, the possibility is remote indeed. Ordination and the administration of patronage are the tests of episcopal capacity, &amp; this diocese has suffered from bad failure in both.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[220] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I read much of</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pastor's</hi><hi> </hi><hi rend="underline">History in the course of the day</hi><hi>. The record of that ghastly old bigot, Paul iv sets one thinking. He was the complete embodiment of the Counter&#8211;Reformation, and, as one reads of his remorseless severities and utter contempt of justice &amp; mercy, the question rises in the mind inevitably whether, indeed, the Counter&#8211;Reformation &#8211; in spite of the Jesuit saints &#8211; was "of God." Which Pontiff did the greater violence to the character of a Christian Pastor &#8211; Leo X, or Paul IV, the easy&#8211;going, self&#8211;indulgent dilettantist, or the gloomy, ferocious bigot? Pastor evidently regards the savage old Pontiff with dislike. He is a modern apologist for the Papacy, and the savageries of Paul iv are particularly difficult to present in a tolerable guise. Yet he admires the Jesuits, and never wearies of exalting the Counter&#8211;Reformation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather continues to be brilliant &amp; very warm. Large numbers of people were in the Park during the day. They are all well&#8211;dressed, and almost all well&#8211;mannered. Many of the young men are unemployed, &amp; have been unemployed for a long time past. Will they ever be regularly employed again in this county?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>