<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[236]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> sent me a long type&#8211;written list of names, all links in a "chain" of luck, on which he had the impudence to inscribe my name, &amp; to send the precious document with solemn admonition that I should in turn extend the absurdity in like manner. And all under the most terrible warning that ill&#8211;luck would follow any breaking of the "chain" by my negligence! &#8211; Well, well! and I thought him an unusually level&#8211;headed young Englishman! I cast the foolish paper into the w.p.b., and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">sent him a few lines of censure</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After visiting the dentist, and making my final arrangements for departure, I left the Castle about 11.30 a.m., and motored to Darganch in Bishopton, Renfrewshire, a distance of about 200 miles. We travelled by way of Barnard Castle, Appleby, Penrith, Carlisle, Dumfries, Kilmarnock, and Paisley. The weather was magnificent, sunny and nearly windless: the roads were almost empty: and the country was in the fresh loveliness of early spring. We lunched very comfortably in Appleby.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[237]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A nephew of mine hostess, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dan Maxwell</hi><hi rend="italic">, a young soldier from Iraq became very communicative in the smoking room after dinner, and I encouraged him to talk as, on the principle that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ex ore infantum</hi><hi rend="italic"> there is truth, I hoped to learn something about that most mysterious country. He has been commanding Assyrian levies, to whose military capacity he bore a stronger testimony than I had expected. His disgust at the Turkish oppression of the Christians was all that could be desired, but his dislike of the Armenians was quite up to the normal standard. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The prevalence of paederasty among the Eastern peoples, Christian as well as Moslem [sic], seems to have made a great impression on him. Boys are even more eagerly sought after than girls in the Turkish raids on Christians, &amp; for the same reason. In the Salonika campaign a large proportion of the Levantine mule&#8211;drivers &amp;c were diseased a </hi><hi rend="bold underline">^[word unknown]^</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">. Russians, for whom he had a hearty contempt, were addicted to this odious vice: but, of course, the Turks had a primacy in this, as in other iniquities. Their only redeeming trait was military courage, &amp; for this he had something like enthusiasm</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>