<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>This day was given to discursive but perhaps indispensable talk. A series of 3 resolutions had been tabled by 9 bishops viz. Gloucester, Bristol, Birmingham, Worcester, Norwich, Bradford, S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Edmundsbury &amp; Ipswich, Sodor&amp; Man, and Exeter. The 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> committed the Episcopate to a series of interviews with all and sundry who desired to expound their views: the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> pledged us to determine nothing respecting the Communion Office unless we were unanimous: the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> postponed all dealing with Holy Communion indefinitely. These were really "wrecking" propositions. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName><hi> moved the first: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pearce</hi><persName xml:id="636"></persName><hi> the next: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nickson</hi><hi> the last. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spoke twice, and apparently succeeded in expressing the general mind. The Archbishop thanked me twice over almost with effusion</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I was able to get hold of the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi><hi>." in which Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> has a characteristic article on Goudge's<persName xml:id="815"></persName> recent pamphlet in defence of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks. He deals faithfully with the Regius Professor, but surely his severity is well&#8211;merited. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He couples Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> and me as the two "Liberal Evangelicals" on the Bench, &amp; more Evangelical than Liberal</hi><hi>!!!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>January 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Ferens,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Before I can approve the appointment of a Nonconformist Chaplain, I must satisfy myself that there are sufficient reasons for changing the arrangement which has hitherto prevailed, &amp; which, so far as my information goes, has been found satisfactory.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I shall be obliged, therefore, if you will inform me whether there has been such an increase of Nonconformist inmates as would render the appointment of a Nonconformist Chaplain reasonable and even desirable; and, if not, what good reason there is for departing from the normal system.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours very faithfully.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>