<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In obedience to the doctor's request I remained in bed, and Lionel celebrated in the chapel in my stead. I read </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pastor's</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Popes</hi><hi rend="italic">. The account of the proe&#8211;Tridentine essays at Reformation made by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Paul iii</hi><hi rend="italic">, through a small Committee of Reforming Cardinals, of whom </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Contarini</hi><hi rend="italic"> is the most distinguished, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Carafa</hi><hi rend="italic"> the most influential, is the most illuminating. There was no lack of courage, or, (at least in the leaders,) of sincerity, but they wholly misconceived the nature of the Church's malady, which was quite incurable by the methods which they employed, and on the assumptions which determined their diagnosis. The German rebels, especially the mountebank </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Luther</hi><hi rend="italic">, in spite of their ribaldry and violence, had at least realized that the medieval conception of Christianity, ascetic, sacerdotal, sacramental, could not be maintained under the new conditions, which had come into being. Their exaltation of the Scripture was exaggerated, and therefore irrational, but at least it recognized one, and not the least important, of the new factors which had to be reckoned with. With the Scripture read in the vernacular versions, &amp; circulated everywhere by the printing press, it was altogether impossible to command acceptance for conciliar and papal procedures.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"If things are to be bettered, the Pope required suitable fellow&#8211;workers. This was the object of the famous nomination of Cardinals of the 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> of May, 1535, by which the bad impression [impression] caused by the bestowal of the purple on the 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> of December 1534 on the two youthful nephews of Paul iii, Alessandro Farnese and Guido Sforza of Santafiora, was effaced."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pastor's</hi><hi rend="underline">Popes.</hi><hi> vol. XI. p.138.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The first of these pampered youths was "</hi><hi rend="underline">at this time entering on his 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> year</hi><hi>": the last was "</hi><hi rend="underline">only in his 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> year</hi><hi>." Both of them were loaded by their Papal Relative with "</hi><hi rend="underline">a multitude of benefices, bishoprics, abbeys, priories</hi><hi>." These scandalous nominations were made by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Paul iii</hi><hi> at a time when all the world was talking of reform: when their shocking character was clearly perceived &amp; openly censored: when the Pontiff himself was pressing the necessity [necessity] of Reforming action on Christendom. Was it only the wickedness of the Protestants, and the cynical statecraft of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles V</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis I</hi><hi> that made them doubtful of the Pope's sincerity and competence for the Reformer's r&#x00F4;le?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel and I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Castletown</hi><hi>, where I confirmed 36 persons in the parish church, which was filled with a very attentive congregation. The local mine manager, whose daughter had been confirmed, came to tea in the vicarage after the service. He was an intelligent man, who spoke in an interesting fashion about the Coal Commission's Report. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He thought the subsidy would have to be continued, if a crisis in May was to be averted</hi><hi>. The parson, the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">H.E. Clark</hi><hi>, was ordained in 1905, and had charge of Durham School Mission for 2 years, before coming (in 1919) to his present parish. The population, which is stated to number 3185, is wholly occupied in mining. The number on the electoral roll is only 265. We got back to the Castle about 5.45 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Professor </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Watson</hi><persName xml:id="250"></persName><hi rend="italic"> has an excellent, &amp; highly characteristic sermon in the current issue of the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church of England Newspaper</hi><hi rend="italic">" on the "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Periodicity of Church Movements</hi><hi rend="italic">." It is rather sardonic, &amp; tends to obliterate the frontiers of truth &amp; falsehood, but it carries a sound lesson, &amp; one which is too easily forgotten when controversy runs as high in the Church as it is running now. It is a typical "University Sermon" in such an age of decadent fanaticism as this.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>