<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[227]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent nearly an hour and a half with the dentist enjoying the most disgusting experience in the world &#8211; getting wax and plaster moulds made up of my jaws! Thus my morning was broken up, and, save for the writing up of a few letters, I did nothing. An Ordination candidate, named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Welch</hi><hi>, came to see me, and stayed to lunch. He is an enthusiast for the League of Nations, of the working and </hi><hi rend="underline">personnel</hi><hi> of which he knew much, having been a correspondent in Geneva for 3 years. After he had taken his departure, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi> arrived, and walked round the Park with me. He is, I think, ardent and industrious, but he knows little, and probably has little knowledge of the method of working. It will be very unfortunate on many grounds if he fails to get ordained at Trinity, but, of course, I </hi><hi rend="underline">cannot </hi><hi>ordain him if he comes to grief in his Examination.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName><hi> a very interesting letter, enclosing a cutting from the </hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi><hi>, in which "a Special Correspondent" described his visit to Hoxton on Easter day. In 4 parishes containing 37,000 people, he found fewer than 450 persons, mostly children, in the churches!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>