<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I think we ought to have a new Preface explaining the reasons which have determined our choice of names for insertion or retention in the new &amp; much enlarged calendar which we propose to include in the revised Prayer Book.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We laboured harmoniously enough at the Collects, Epistles, and Gospels all day long. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName><hi>, who had been absent yesterday, was in his place, &amp; took a small but perverse part in the proceedings. He is certainly very difficult to understand, and altogether impossible to work with.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Bishop of Hereford told me that he had received a letter from Sir John Cotterill, the Lord&#8211;Lieutenant of Herefordshire, saying that, if the Shropshire Bishoprick measure, passed, he would absent himself from the 1250</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary Commemoration. There seems some likelihood of many others following his example, and indeed, the Commemoration could hardly be anything but a farcical performance in the situation which would have been created. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I offered to withdraw my promise to be the preacher on the occasion, &amp; he seemed rather to jump at the suggestion</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>