<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[336]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It is precisely 4 weeks today since my operation took place, and now, save for the inconvenience &amp; boredom of confinement to bed, &amp; extreme physical weakness when I attempt to walk, I am restored to the community of living people. Is there no cause for thanksgiving here? Why then am I as captious &amp; discontented as the veriest disgruntled worldling that ever disturbed the peace of a home, &amp; lowered the temperature of society? I do not possess the bovine complaisance of a lethargic temperament, and I have never attained to the severe equanimity of the philosopher or the calm resignation of the saint. My religion only suffices to add the disturbance of the conscience to the discontents of discomfort!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The news of the Strike has no suggestion of peace. Cook &amp; Smith are more obstinate &amp; unreasonable than ever</hi><hi>. It is now evident that the Russian money was no voluntary contribution of the Russian Trade Unionists, but the calculated gift of the Soviet Government, designed to promote revolution in Great Britain. There is something unspeakably humiliating in the spectacle of British working men accepting with eagerness money which is confessedly sent from foreigners in order to weaken Britain. Patriotism &amp; loyalty are on the way to becoming "bad words" with the British worker.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[337] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The '</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi>' champions the cause of </hi><hi rend="underline">Lloyd George</hi><hi>, and the fact indicates the effect of the local socialism on the party which once gloried in its individualism. There seems to be no essential difference between the "Right" wing of "Labour" and the "Left" wing of Liberalism. Why then should the notion of an amalgamation of the two under the leadership of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi> be so vehemently repudiated in both camps? Much must no doubt be allowed for the apprehensions, jealousies, and resentments of individuals especially in the "Labour" party. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The personal quality of the Labour leaders is very poor: &amp; in any junction with the Liberals would become distressingly apparent</hi><hi>. Then the singular organisation of the "Labour" party could hardly be tolerated by a Coalition. Yet any attempt to alter it, and thus to make the position of the Labour party consistent with the Constitution would be passionately resisted by the rank &amp; file of "Labour", which has no respect for Parliament, &amp; a vast regard for its power to control the action of Labour members. It is objections of this kind, which have no relation to the avowed objects of both Labour and Liberalism, which are the principal obstacle to amalgamation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I am half&#8211;inclined to think that the abortive "General Strike" will have the effect not merely of breaking up the Liberal Party through a quarrel of the leaders, but also of disintegrating the Labour party by a schism in the rank &amp; file</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[338] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">A prize in some newspaper guessing competition of no less than</hi><hi rend="italic underline">&#x00A3;10,000</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">has been won by a girl of 14, the daughter of Wilson's<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> partner, a solicitor named Cadle</hi><hi rend="italic">. The competition implied no kind of ability, still less any distinction whether of character or of achievement. It was mere luck. What moral right has the young maiden to that not inconsiderable property? What effect on the public mind must such an illustration of the complete divorce between property and any respectable title to it necessarily have?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>There was a considerable thunderstorm during the afternoon. Afterwards I was dressed, &amp; carried into the garden. Beck discovered a thrush's nest with young birds in it in the old pear&#8211;tree in Butler's Walk. Spurrier<persName xml:id="5431"></persName> from Staindrop came to see me. He says that the mine in his parish is thought to be permanently closed, &amp; that if this be the case, the population of his parish will be halved.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I received a letter from the Archbishop of Canterbury, with reference to my letter in the Newcastle Journal, which he had read. He is evidently moved by what I said, and characteristically suggests that there are circumstances which justify his action</hi><hi rend="italic">. "I should like to talk to you about it all, for I think you do not fully appreciate what was the situation." It is difficult to imagine anything that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">could</hi><hi rend="italic"> justify such action at such a time.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>