<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Tunstall and Tyndall embody the two movements which approached so closely, &amp; then parted so decisively &#8211; the Renaissance and the Reformation. They exhibited on the narrower arena of England the same phenomenon as that which on the larger theatre of Europe was exhibited by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Erasmus</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Luther</hi><hi>. Perhaps it would not be excessive to continue the parallel by pointing to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Craumar</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Melanethon</hi><hi> as respectively indicating the middle or mediating position. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tunstall</hi><hi> was the friend &amp; correspondent of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Erasmus</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndall</hi><hi>, the friend &amp; correspondent of Luther. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tunstall</hi><hi> was the older man by as much as 16, perhaps even 20 years. He entered Oxford, when </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndall</hi><hi> was in his cradle: but he outlived Tyndall by no less than 23 years. The Reformer perished at the stake in 1536; the Bishop died in 1559. His long life of no less than 85 years, had begun in the reign of Edward iv. and ended in that of Elizabeth. It included the whole process of the Reformation. Tunstall himself played a prominent, and on the whole an honourable part in that process. In that age few men steered a straight course. His course was certainly straighter than that of most of his contemporaries.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I was surprised and annoyed at receiving a very impudent letter from that foolish Vicar of Shildon, to whom I had written in terms of grave but kind remonstrance. But his intimacy with organized "Labour" is having the usual effect, &amp; illustrating the aphorism, </hi><hi rend="underline">"Evil communications corrupt good manner"</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I made some notes for my </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndall</hi><hi> lecture, and then motored to Durham, where I instituted some curates in the chapel of the Castle, &amp; lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. After a short interview with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName><hi> I returned to Auckland, and wrote forthwith to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Adam Smith</hi><persName xml:id="244"></persName><hi>, asking him to address the clergy in July. Then I made more notes for the lecture until dinner&#8211;time, which was unwholesomely early in order to facilitate the Servant's Party, which was more numerously attended than ever.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&#x00F6;e</hi><persName xml:id="648"></persName><hi> thanking him for the drawing of the War&#8211;Memorial in the Cathedral which he had sent me as a Christmas gift. I placed it in the Ante&#8211;chapel where it shows to advantage.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather became much warmer; as the day proceeded rain fell, and the wind rose, until by 10 p.m. it was blowing a gale.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>