<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I came away from Farnham with my colleagues after breakfast, and travelled to Waterloo, getting to Lambeth in good time for the Session at 10.45a.m. We worked at the Collects, Epistles, &amp; Gospels all day with much harmony, &amp; made good progress. Just at the end, Frere<persName xml:id="2021"></persName> raised the question of the Calendar, &amp; then for </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the first time a controversial issue disclosed itself</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName><hi> told me that he had been asked to deliver the Gifford Lectures, &amp; professed to be doubtful as to his accepting the proposal. I urged him strongly to do so: "You are the only bishop now on the Bench to whom the invitation could have been reasonably sent. You will add distinction to the Episcopate by giving these lectures, &amp; we shall all be indebted to you. I think you will win through at Birmingham, and in ten years [sic] time, you will be spoken about as a second </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Thirlwall</hi><hi>. Set everything else aside, &amp; give these lectures." These were my words as clearly as I can recall them. The Evening Papers reproduce a ill&#8211;tempered canard vented from Birmingham to the Sunday Journals to the effect that Barnes was about to institute legal proceedings against the rebel clergy in his diocese!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>