<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[59]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The real strength of the Catholic Movement is that the pressure comes from below.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Church Times. January 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. 1926.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This pronouncement of the Anglo&#8211;Catholick journal has the unusual distinction of being true.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I worked at a sermon for tomorrow, but sermon composition is for me almost a lost art, &amp; I made but little progress.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. N. J. Burgess</hi><hi> came to see me, &amp; remained to lunch. I said that, in negotiating with any incumbent, he was bound to tell the story of his departure from Marley Hill two years ago. I said also that when he had completed five years in good service, I should consider that he had purged his record, &amp; had regained his position in the ranks of the working clergy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch four of us &#8211; Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and I &#8211; walked round the park with Beck.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> J. C. M. Collier</hi><hi>, who is changing from the curacy of S. Margaret's, Durham, to that of Stanhope, came to spend the week end [sic]. He has been in Orders since 1914, and might well be sent to a benefice, but he is shy, not physically robust, and without ambition. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Loisy</hi><persName xml:id="1083"></persName><hi> gives a woeful account of the Roman Catholic Religion as it now exists in France, with the Papacy enthroned on the ruins of Gallican Liberty, with the French bishops reduced to complete helplessness, lesson&#8211;bound by the ecclesiastical newspapers. </hi><hi rend="underline">La Croix</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="underline">Le P&#x00E9;lerim</hi><hi> embarrassed by the failure of Ordination candidates, and committed against their own judgment to a conflict with the State which is as unnecessary as it is ruinous. He accuses the Papacy as being the very "</hi><hi rend="underline">fous mabram"</hi><hi>. He describes Lourdes as the very citadel of "the new Catholicism". It is "</hi><hi rend="underline">une pouss&#x00E9;e de basse religiosite où la suggestion &#x00E0; haute dose produit certains effets extraordinaires, mais dont la r&#x00E9;sultat le plus clair, le plus imm&#x00E9;diat, la plus g&#x00E9;n&#x00E9;ral, le plus certain, est un avilissment de la religion</hi><hi>".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>He seems to admit the expediency of having a French ambassador at the Vatican in order to facilitate the arrangement in affairs in Alsace&#8211;Lorraine &amp; in the East: but he resents the existence of a Nuncio in Paris, because it seems to imply a recognition of the Pope's claim to interfere in the internal affairs of the Republic. It is clear enough that the Papacy is too potent to be ignored.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>