<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[268]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Let us pray especially at this time for the Nation, and therein for all who hold office in Church &amp; State, and for the leaders of Industry, as well employers as workmen, that they may be guided to wise decisions, and preserved from selfish and violent courses.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I used this "bidding" before the Prayer for the Church Militant when I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We were in all 10 Communicants. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">On the whole I prefer such special "biddings" to new prayers whenever there are occasions which call for some notice in the religious assembles</hi><hi>. Not only are the emergency collects almost invariably ill constructed, but also they are invariably unfamiliar to the congregations. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>Lionel &amp; I left the castle at 9.45 a.m. &amp; motored to Dunston, where I preached in connexion with the Jubilee celebration of the Church. I promised M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Intosh, the Vicar, to subscribe &#x00A3;20. towards the new church. I lunched at Gateshead Rectory, &amp; rested there during the afternoon. We motored to South Shields, where I preached in S. Oswin's Church. After the service we returned to Auckland, arriving at the Castle about 9.45 p.m.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>