<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi><hi> went back to Gateshead after breakfast. I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brudenel</hi><hi> telling him that I had advised the rejection of his offer. This business of giving advice with respect to personal decisions is to me most unpalatable: yet I cannot dispute the title of any clergyman in my diocese to seek his bishop's counsel. I never ask advice myself, &amp; I don't like anybody asking advice from me! A pastoral attitude! I wasted the morning writing letters &amp; reading. After lunch I walked in the Park, &amp; then motored to South Shields where I confirmed 90 candidates. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ashworth</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Harton, presented </hi><hi rend="underline">one</hi><hi> candidate. I inquired where he proposed to present the main body of his candidates, &amp; I was informed to my extreme surprise, that this single candidate was the entire presentation for the year. Harton contains more than 1600 people. On a reasonable estimate not less than 30 persons reach the age of 14 years in Harton every year: &amp; the Vicar seemed rather hurt that I was not as satisfied as himself! M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lane&#8211;Davies</hi><hi>, Vicar of South Westo, presented about 60 candidates out of a population of more than 23,000. Certainly not less than 450 persons in that parish reached the age of 14 last year.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>