<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>But let them believe as they list, yet this will I be bold to say for myself, although they should call me Pharisee for the boast and Pelagian for my labour too, that how bad so ever they reckon me, I am not yet fallen so virtueless, but that of mine own natural disposition without any special peculiar help of grace thereto. </hi><hi rend="underline">I am both over proud and over slothful also to be hired for money to take half the labour and business in writing that I have taken in this gear since I began.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas More's</hi><hi> </hi><hi rend="underline">Apology c.X.</hi><hi> (Works, p. 867).</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>More evidently felt and resented the suggestion that he had "made money" out of his apologetic labours. To Tyndale and his associates he was particularly odious, as in their view one who "sinned against the light". He had started as a brilliant exponent of the new learning, &amp; no doubt there were current on men's lips many of his brilliant sallies against the monks. Was he not the friend of Erasmus, the </hi><hi rend="underline">malleus monachorum</hi><hi>? What would explain his transformation into the chosen champion of the hierarchy? In that evil&#8211;surmising, evil&#8211;speaking age, only one explanation would suggest itself. He must have been </hi><hi rend="underline">bought</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 7.45 a.m. and, after breakfast, motored with Lionel to S. Gabriel's, Sunderland, where I dedicated a new organ, and preached a sermon. The two curates &#8211; Hall and Unwin &#8211; seem bright &amp; happy: but the Vicar, Scott, is still ailing. I lunched with Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, with whom was Gadd, who had been preaching in Bishopwearmouth Church. After lunch, I motored to Gateshead, where I left Lionel, and then went to Lambton Park, and had tea with Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, &amp; his brother D'Arcy. After this, I returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote my fortnightly letter to William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi>. Then I finished a rather hasty reading of Godfrey's<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> book "According to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John", and wrote to him thereupon. It is certainly a creditable piece of work as the </hi><hi rend="underline">parergon</hi><hi> of a layman. Why is it that our true interest always lies elsewhere than in our professed work? Theology bores me terribly, but it has an evident fascination for some laymen. Godfrey has a parson's temperament, &amp; mine, whatever else it is, cannot be described as parsonic! He is plainly much influenced by Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, and tends to think in the same way. I suspect that the tragic death of his little son, Christopher, cut more deeply into his heart than most people knew: &amp; this book is the result.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>