<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I motored into Durham, and presided at the meeting of the Diocesan Conference. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">When I entered the Chapter House I was welcomed with a good deal of cheering, which at least indicated a kindly disposition towards me</hi><hi rend="italic">. I addressed the Conference very briefly, making allusion to the Report of the Coal Commission, &amp; directing the clergy to preface the Prayer for Parliament with a brief reference to the special need for Divine guidance of the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> &amp; his colleagues. I gave lunch in the Common Room of the Castle to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Priestman, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Parry&#8211;Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName>, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName>, Miss Headlam, &amp; Lionel. Delegating the chairmanship of the Conference during the afternoon to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, I returned to Auckland, &amp; wrote letters.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi><hi rend="italic"> told me that his foolish neighbour, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Watts</hi><hi rend="italic">, had showed to him, &amp; to others his insolent letter to me, of which apparently he was very proud, but that in every case he had been told honestly that, in writing thus to his superior officer, he had behaved indefensibly. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Watts</hi><hi rend="italic"> does not appear to have also shown the letter from me which had occasioned his outburst. I fear the foolish fellow is as unteachable as he is insolent. What precisely to do with him is not quite easy to see.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>