<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Il ne m'est pas tr&#x00E9;s facile de vous fournir les renseignments que vous me demandez. Je n'ai jamais etudi&#x00E9; specialement I'histoire de la R&#x00E9;forme. Autant que j'en puis juger, notre production n'est pas tr&#x00E8;s abondante sur le sujet, ni peutetre de qualit&#x00E9; bien sup&#x00E9;rieur. Il ne me souvient pas d'avoir vu signaler de publications importantes dans les derni&#x00E8;res ann&#x00E9;es. Je doute qu'il existe en français une histoire gen&#x00E9;rale du protestantisme. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Imbart de la Tour</hi><hi>, qui vient de mourir, a &#x00E9;crit en 1908, 1909, deux volumes sur </hi><hi rend="underline">L'origines de la Reforme</hi><hi>. Il existe une </hi><hi rend="underline">Historie des protestants de France</hi><hi>, par </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">G. de Felice</hi><hi>, en un volume, qui a eu plusieurs editeurs. J'ai vu souvent cit&#x00E9; </hi><hi rend="underline">La France Protestante</hi><hi>de </hi><hi rend="underline">Haarg</hi><hi>, grand receuil qui comporte une quinzaine de volumes et qui, je crois, n'est pas achev&#x00E9;, c'est, j&#x00E8; crois bien, une collection de documents et de materiaux historqùes en patois de Canaan, plut&#x00F4;t qu'une histoire. Nos protestants font grand &#x00E9;tat </hi><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi><hi> de </hi><hi rend="underline">la vie de Jean Calvin</hi><hi>pas </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Doumergue</hi><hi>(non Gaston).</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A. Loisy<persName xml:id="1083"></persName> to A. Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>. Dec: 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1925.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I asked Fawkes to consult Loisy on the subject of recent French work on the history of the Reformation, &amp; the above is his disappointing reply. The rather scornful tone suggests that the eminent French Modernist does not think the Reformation in France a subject of much interest or importance!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The boiler of the heating apparatus for the Chapel was reported inoperative and irreparable. I ordered M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Waine to provide a new one at a cost of &#x00A3;62.8.0. Everything in the Castle that was installed by my predecessor appears to have reached its term.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked round the Park during the afternoon. The weather was mild &amp; spring&#8211;like: the sun shone from a cloudless sky. It was difficult to imagine that a few days ago everything was frozen &amp; snow&#8211;mouthed.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Brooke Westcott<persName xml:id="5385"></persName>, Hughes &amp; his son Peter dined and stayed the night.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received letters from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> &amp; Cecil Fortescue<persName xml:id="4760"></persName>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>