<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lang, Williams, and I left Oxford by the 8.33 a.m. train, and arrived at Lambeth in good time for the session at 10.45 a.m. The Archbishop of Canterbury presided, &amp; seemed none the worse for his dental troubles. We continued all the morning on the Baptismal Offices. After lunch we received a deputation of the House of Laity. There were 12 men, and 1 woman &#8211; the inevitable M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Creighton. Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName>, Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName>, Sir Thomas Inskip<persName xml:id="4783"></persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Albert Mitchell, and Sir G.A. King were the principal speakers. It was soon sufficiently obvious that the House of Laity was sharply divided into two factions. After tea we resumed work on the Baptismal Office for half an hour. I sate next to the Archbishop of C. at dinner, &amp; had some talk with him about the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Shropshire Bishoprick Measure. He is himself opposed to it, &amp; thinks that it would be very proper for Parliament to intervene, &amp; refuse to pass it</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I understand that the Resolution asking for the King's consent is to be moved by the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> probably on March 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He promised to let me know as soon as possible when the actual day has been fixed.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>