<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Never did the love which Christ brought down from Heaven, the Divine fire which He kindled in the hearts of His disciples, burn more ardently than during the time of the Renaissance. Not only were most of the older foundations better supported than ever, but a great number of new ones were added to them.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>These numerous charitable &amp; pious endowments bear eloquent testimony to the fervent love to God and man which glowed during the Renaissance, in the hearts of the Italian people.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Pastor's History of the Popes. v. 64.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>A list of charitable foundations established in Italy prior to 1399, and between 1400 and 1524, is appended as giving authority for this statement. The numbers are:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Before 1399..258</hi></p>
         <p><hi>1400&#8211;1524..334</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Of course these figures could only be fairly appraised if we knew (α) the population of Italy, (β). the wealth and (c). how far the Foundations were the work of a small number of pious or penitent individuals.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I did some more work at this tiresome lecture: and I read some more curious &amp; curiously biassed [sic] "history" in Pastor's "Popes".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ivan Selwyn Thornton</hi><hi>, South Bank Cottages, Coundon, came to see me. He had asked for an interview. His business was to tell me that he desired to be a clergyman. He will be 19 in March, and clearly knows </hi><hi rend="underline">nothing</hi><hi>. I said that he must see the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, to whom I at once wrote respecting him.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received a polite reply from the mulish youth whom I refused to accept for Ordination to the Priesthood. He thanks me for my counsel, but I suspect there is more juvenile sarcasm than genuine gratitude in his words! However, </hi><hi rend="underline">on paper</hi><hi> there really was no ground on which I could trample on every disciplinary consideration: &amp; in justice to the blustering bigot at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Alban's, I believe he really intends to be just.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Nan Lawrence suggesting the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> of May at Easington for George's Confirmation: it is flattering, but highly inconvenient, that the dear Boy should have taken it into his head to insist on being confirmed by me! But I can't make special arrangements for </hi><hi rend="underline">anybody</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>