<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[288]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi>Let us pray especially at this time for the Nation, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>and therein for the Prime Minister and the other </hi></p>
         <p><hi>members of His Majesty's Government, that they </hi></p>
         <p><hi>may be granted wisdom, sympathy and strength </hi></p>
         <p><hi>for their difficult duty:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Let us pray for the men now unhappily on strike, that </hi></p>
         <p><hi>they may be led to a worthier sense of their duty as citizens, and may be </hi></p>
         <p><hi>preserved from violence and crime.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I used these "biddings" before the Prayer for the Church Militant when I celebrated the Holy communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Then I turned to preparing a sermon for tonight, when I have to preach in Sunderland. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is, perhaps, inevitable that I should say something about the Strike, &amp; what can I say which will be honest, useful and safe? How can I express my abhorrence of the whole conception of the "general Strike" without giving the impression that the Bishop of Durham is precisely what M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook says he must always be, the paid apologist of the Capitalists? The task of the</hi><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">preacher of righteousness</hi><hi>"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">would certainly be made vastly more easy if one were, like the Baptist, a dweller in the wilderness, clothed in leather &amp; camel's hair, and feeding on locusts and wild honey</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[289]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Bradford</hi><hi>, who is in command at Durham, sent me a bundle of papers setting forth the arrangements that had been made. The special messenger drew his packet from a secret place of concealment behind his waist&#8211;coat with so much solemnity that I was disposed to think that some communication of real importance had arrived, &amp; I think that he himself thought as much. But there was nothing that mattered.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>