<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[350]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A beautiful morning. While I was being "washed" a thrush placed itself conspicuously on the very top of a tree outside my window, and poured out a glorious song. Was this a public declaration of territorial rights? or, was it just the irrepressible confession of "joie de vivre"? or, was it a tribute of affection to the sitting female?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A correspondent informs me that "in the many open&#8211;air meetings in London" my name is "so often mentioned re this unfortunate Miners' dispute." The allegation is that "the Lord Bishop of Durham last year received from the earnings of the Durham miners sixpence per ton for every one of the 3,000,000 tons.</hi><hi>" I sent him an assurance that the facts were probably as stated! But how hopeless the whole situation is becoming! Year in and year out the doctrines of Communism are being instilled into the miners: and the position, not only of the Bishop of Durham, but of every other property&#8211;holder, is going to be regarded as morally indefensible. There are not lacking clergymen (e.g. the notorious Father Bull) who approve this view, &amp; urge that the Church ought to "give back" the royalties to the miners! They seem to be quite incapable of thinking out the consequences of their altruistic flights. The community is being silently (for the most part) and almost unconsciously prepared for revolution, for the factors which normally ought to correct the anarchic elements are becoming auxiliary to them. When the battle is joined at last, the result of this process will become apparent. The industrial r&#x00E9;gime &amp; with it the fabric of civilized order </hi><hi rend="bold">[351]</hi> <hi>[symbol] will fall "like a pack of cards". So far as experience goes, there is nothing to take its place. We should be cast into all the miseries of economic experimentalizing, during which, the boundaries of right and wrong having become obliterated in the general mind, &amp; society surrendered as a prey to the ambitions of groups &amp; individuals, the most part of men would fall into the extremes of wretchedness. Then by degrees mankind would collect its energies, &amp; begin slowly to emerge from the Dark Age into which it had been thrust. The old paths would be re&#8211;found and re&#8211;traced. A new civilization would grow on the ruins of the old, &amp; vaunt itself after the former fashion as unprecedented &amp; incomparable! </hi><hi rend="underline">Infelix genus hominum!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I left my bed about noon after dictating some letters, including one to the Archbishop on </hi><hi rend="underline">Restoration</hi><hi>. After lunch, I was carried into the Garden, where I remained for more than an hour. Old D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Cullagh came to see me &#8211; a fine&#8211;looking &amp; intelligent man, who sweetens his hale old age with reading books.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>, &amp; others have addressed an appeal to America begging for funds to maintain the families of the miners on strike: I find it impossible to approve this action. The more deserving victims of this criminal refusal to work are those whom it throws out of employment in the industries which are dependent on coal. Yet no one raises a finger to plead their cause, or assist their necessity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[352]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have wasted time in reading "</hi><hi rend="underline">Une grande Mystique. Madame Bruy&#x00E8;re Abbesse de Solesmes (1845&#8211;1909) per Albert Houtin</hi><persName xml:id="1876"></persName><hi>". It is an unpleasant revelation of the inside of monastic life. Mysticism appears to be a queer blending of imbecile devotion, physical disorder &amp; personal ambition. The furious passions finding expression in so petty a sphere, &amp; passing under the guise of such exalted spiritual pretences provide a spectacle which is equally repulsive, amazing, and pathetic. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Tantum religio potuit suadere in alorum</hi><hi>". It is not to be wondered at that the breaking away of an intelligent and self&#8211;respecting individual from a system which could exact from its victims such frightful degradation should be violent. I notice that the highest ecclesiastics, Cardinals &amp; even the Pope himself, appear to be mixed up, more or less discreditably, with this sordid superstition. The more normal perversions of primitive Gnosticism are renewed in these mystical essays. "Illuminism" unites the degradation of the intelligent with the exploitation of the passions. But the Roman Church survives all scandals. The papers report the triumphal entry into New York of the Ecclesiastic, a Cardinal, who is to represent the Pope at the Eucharistic Congress in Chicago next week. Everything seems to turn to the advantage of Rome. The War discredited &amp; ruined the rival churches: the dread of Communism predisposes thousands to favour a religious system which has strength enough to control the masses: &amp; modern democracy easily works out in Despotism.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>