<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[230]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>The poet Browning attempted an unfavourable interpretation of Wiseman's character in his "Bishop Blougram's Apology" (first published in Browning's "Men and Women" 1855): "Sylvester Blougram", Browning's bishop, was undoubtedly intended for Wiseman, but Blougram's worldly &amp; self–indulgent justification of his successful pursuit of the clerical career in the Roman catholic church [sic], although dramatically most effective, cannot be accepted as a serious description of Wiseman's aims in life or conduct. According to Father Prout, Wiseman in "The Rambler" temperately reviewed "Men &amp; Women" on its publication, &amp; favourably noticed "Bishop Blougram's Apology" as a masterly intellectual achievment [sic], although he regarded it as an assault on the ground–works of religion.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Dict. of N.B. Art. "Wiseman."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Robertson of Brighton died two years before "Bishop Blougram's Apology" was published. He was the precise contradiction of that comfortable prelate.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[231]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Whatsoever the world thinks, he who hath not much meditated upon God, the human mind, and the </hi><hi rend="underline">summum bonum</hi><hi>, may possibly make a thriving earthworm, but will most indubitably make a sorry patriot and a sorry statesman.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Bishop Berkeley. Sirio 350.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>These words are printed as a kind of text on the first page of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tawney's</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="5035"></persName> Religion &amp; the Rise of Capitalism</hi><hi>," a very notable &amp; admirably written book which I finished reading through today.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I worked at the Brighton Sermon most of the morning, but with woefully small success. After lunch I walked in the Park with Lionel, &amp; looked on at a football match.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spedding</hi><hi> came to see me at 6 p.m., &amp; did some more "adjustment" in my comfortless jaws.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I read again </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Browning's</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Bishop Blougram's Apology</hi><hi>," &amp; was more than ever impressed by its power &amp; insight. Indeed, could I reasonably resent the substitution of "Henson" for "Blougram", and the application of the cynical argument to the case of the present holder of the see of Durham?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>