<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName><hi> writes: "I hope you will read the life of Bishop Ullathorne &#8211; a most instructive illuminating book: &amp; Shane Leslie's book "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Cantab</hi><hi>" &#8211; an amazing work to come from the Editor of the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Dublin Review</hi><hi>". I see that he has withdrawn it from circulation &#8211; owing to the Bishop of Northampton's letter, but his (Leslie's) words are cryptic &#8211; &amp; I wonder what will come of it. The book is clever, blasphemous, &amp; indecent: it should show the authorities that "</hi><hi rend="underline">Modernism</hi><hi>" is neither the greatest nor the most prevalent enemy which they have to face."</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" today has, under the heading "</hi><hi rend="underline">Alleged Obscene Book</hi><hi>" a reference to "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Cantab</hi><hi>" as the subject of an intended prosecution. In view of the author's alleged purpose of withdrawing the book from circulation, the legal proceedings were postponed. The magistrate, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Chartres Biron</hi><hi>, stated that he had read the book, &amp; that he had found in it "</hi><hi rend="underline">two or three passages of so gross a kind that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="underline"> have had no hesitation &#8211; had it been necessary &#8211; in issuing process</hi><hi>". So for a whole week the book will be purchasable, &amp; no doubt will be purchased in great numbers by a public which is both eager to read all available filth, &amp; willing to prohibit its sale. Meanwhile, the author gets off without punishment, &amp; with "</hi><hi rend="underline">the reward of iniquity</hi><hi>" swelling his Bank balance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Westminster Chapel folk sent me 20 more</hi><hi> copies of the sermon. I sent away 6 of them to Spencer Wade<persName xml:id="5332"></persName>, Brooke Westcott<persName xml:id="5385"></persName>, Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName>, Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName>, Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, and Canon Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. Miss Haldane<persName xml:id="1386"></persName> wrote about the subject of my sermon. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">From her letter I gathered that she &amp; L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> were somewhat perturbed by it. She said that she had been discussing it with the Duchess of Atholl. So the leaven works</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>During the afternoon &#8211; the weather being wonderfully warm &amp; sunny &#8211; I walked round the Park with Bishop Hornby. He is no doubt a good &amp; friendly man, but he is getting deaf, &amp; could never, I think, have been other than mortally dull. And of course, he grows old. Time blunts &amp; lessens what is good &amp; attractive in us: &amp; what is bad &amp; repugnant it emphasizes &amp; magnifies. Who could really wish to grow old? Yet, how few are willing to die!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I picked up a company of Barrington School boys in the Park, and took them into the Conservatory to show them the camellia which is in full bloom. Most of them I learned on inquiry had never been vaccinated.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>