<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[317]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A bad night, and, by consequence, a feeling of depression &amp; dilapidation all day. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi> came to see me, &amp; was quickly followed by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Sykes</hi><persName xml:id="3470"></persName><hi>. In the afternoon, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Stephenson</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">the Bishop of Newcastle</hi><hi> preceded </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName></hi><hi> arrival. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><persName xml:id="2818"></persName><hi> writes in much irritation from Ireland, that Duncan at Dawdon has been writing letters about the Strike of an offensively Socialistic character. </hi><hi rend="italic">I have not myself seen the letters, &amp; it is probable enough that the Marquess judges them unfairly: but it is a very serious matter that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Duncan</hi><hi rend="italic"> should have "got across" the proprietor of the Dawdon pit, &amp; will make his work in the parish vastly more difficult. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This unhappy practice of interfering in labour disputes has spread from the bishops to the working clergy, and the consequences in both cases cannot but be unfortunate</hi><hi rend="italic">. Of course the position of the parson in these mining districts is extremely difficult at such a crisis as the present. It is easy to go into one camp or the other: very hard to maintain any measure of independence. And, unfortunately, few of the clergy are big enough to take a line of their own: &amp; many of them are hopelessly bewildered by their ignorance, the vigour of their prejudices, &amp; the strength of their sympathies.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>