<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote letters all the morning: walked in the Park during the afternoon: &amp; read Pastor's history of the Popes when I returned &#8211; there is the day's record. During the morning, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ogilvie</hi><hi>, the painter, called in order to "rectify his colouring" of my face, which he had painted from one of the photographs which he took in the large dining room some weeks ago. He painted while I proceeded with my letter&#8211;writing. The sketch he showed was recognizable, &amp;, perhaps, clever, but not amiable or anywise attractive! But that was not the artist's fault. He stayed to lunch where he disclosed the disconcerting fact that </hi><hi rend="underline">he was a vegetarian</hi><hi>! However, he professed himself to hold sound views on Prohibition.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The League of Nations has adjourned until September, with its avowed purpose, the admission of Germany to a seat on the Council, unachieved, &amp; with an immense, perhaps a fatal, loss of prestige. This lamentable situation has been created by the subterranean intrigues of France, the brutal cynicism of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi><hi>, and the pig&#8211;headed weakness &amp; obstinacy of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Austen Chamberlain</hi><persName xml:id="343"></persName><hi>. It is rumoured that the Vatican has been busily pulling strings for the discomfiture of Geneva.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>