<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[263]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Fortescue</hi><persName xml:id="4760"></persName><hi> arrived. After five years in the East he has come back for 8 months leave at home. He has grown to be stout, &amp; even more self&#8211;confident than he was as one of my incumbents in Hereford, but he has a frank, breezy manner, which (like charity) covers a multitude of sins.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName><hi rend="italic"> writes that he had read a report of my Brighton Sermon in a Sussex paper:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"What you say about the homogenous culture of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Robertson's</hi><hi rend="italic"> time, &amp; heterogeneous culture of ours, is the key to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> our troubles: if I were an ordination candidate, it would make me </hi><hi rend="italic underline">very</hi><hi rend="italic"> doubtful: &amp; it is a question whether such preaching as his is now possible. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I never think you quite fair to Modernists</hi><hi rend="italic">! What you criticize is a matter of temperament, &amp; it is true that the critical, historical, legal temper is seldom mystical. But the orthodox temper is frequently not so."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I have felt so dilapidated today, (partly because I slept very badly last night, partly because my cold is heavy on me, partly because it was a damp close day) that, beyond writing a few letters &amp; talking with Cecil Fortescue, I achieved </hi><hi rend="underline">nothing</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>