<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Hodder &amp; Stoughton on the matter of publishing the lecture on Tyndale. After wasting so much on the wretched thing, I find it difficult to cast it without more ceremony to final oblivion!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to lunch, and afterwards talked with me about providing a successor to himself as legal secretary in the person of Cecil Ferens<persName xml:id="4218"></persName>. I left the whole business in his hands.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel and I walked round the Park in the rain. The coroner's jury have returned a verdict of suicide in the case of young Ponsonby. It is most lamentable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Spectator</hi><hi> has a politely&#8211;expressed review of my "Notes on Spiritual Healing". The writer has evident hankerings after the superstitions which he hardly ventures to defend.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray</hi><hi> telegraphed to say that both her daughters were engaged to be married, &amp; begging me to perform the double ceremony on a day at the end of June. I wired to say that the only date possible for me was June 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. So the world marches. Vivian and Eleanor were small children when first I knew them. Now they are about to marry.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> suggesting that he should come over from Wynyard, lunch, walk, &amp; talk.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>