<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The local Sectaries sent me the following letter which I acknowledged civilly through my chaplain:</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My Lord Bishop</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At our monthly meeting of the Bishop Auckland Evangelical Free Church Ministers' Fraternal held at the house of Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> W. Towers Garrett B.A. Princess Street on 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> inst. I was instructed as Secretary to write expressing our sympathy with you in the affliction which recently overtook you while preaching at Westminster Chapel, London.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We note the two pathetic circumstances that you then engaged in preaching the Great Gospel we all love so dearly, &amp; that you were preaching it in an Evangelical Free Church Pulpit.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We trust that under our heavenly Father's gracious Providence, you will soon be restored to your wonted health, &amp; be equipped afresh for the onerous duties of your large &amp; important see.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The following were present.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Rev. Henry D. Purdy M.A. Presbyterian Church</hi></p>
         <p><hi>W. Towers Garrett B.A. Wesleyan Methodist</hi></p>
         <p><hi>R. Laidler, Primitive Methodist "</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frank Rhodes, United " "</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> E. Hardin, Baptist Church</hi></p>
         <p><hi>George Parsons, Wesleyan Methodist.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I remain,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My Lord Bishop,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your Lordship's most obedient servant.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frank Rhodes</hi></p>
         <p><hi>(Secty.)</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">No doubt this is meant kindly. It is strange that some malignant &amp; seemingly irremovable paralysis lies upon us so that we can never get beyond such charities of tongue and pen! Why should this be?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel and I left the Castle at 4 p.m., and motored to Sunderland, where we had tea with the Wynne&#8211;Willsons<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, &amp; then went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's Church. Here I confirmed 43 candidates from the two parishes &#8211; Christ Church &amp; S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's. Then I went on to S. Hilda's where I confirmed about 160 persons from several parishes. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The odd Vicar, Plummer, who is scarcely intelligible when he speaks, had evidently taken pains over the arrangements</hi><hi>. The church is commodious and stately. We got back to the Castle a little after 10 p.m.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>