<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>And so the priest (sc. William Tyndall) came to me again, and besought me to help him, and so I took him into my house half a year: and there he lived like a good Priest, as methought. He studied most part of the day and of the night, at his book; and he would eat but sodden meat by his good will, nor drink but small single beer. I never saw him wear linen about him in the space he was with me. I did promise him &#x00A3;10 sterling, to pray for my father &amp; mother their souls, and all Christian souls. I did pay it him when he made his exchange to Hamburgh [sic]. Afterwards he got of some other men &#x00A3;10 more, the while he left with me. And within a year after he sent for his ten pounds to me from Hamburgh: &amp; thither I sent it him by one Hans Collenbecke, as I remember is his name, a merchant of the Steelyard.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Humphrey Monmouth's Petition. May 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1528</hi></p>
         <p><hi>App. LXXXIX to Strype's Eccl. Mem: vol. I. pt. ii.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A beautiful day, mild and almost spring&#8211;like. I began to write the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndall</hi><hi> lecture, but made little progress before I had to go to Durham for the Service of Commemoration which, in order to suit the Preacher's convenience had been postponed from its proper date, the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; the Chaplain accompanied me. We all lunched at the Deanery before the service. I sate beside </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Theodore Morison</hi><hi>, &amp; had some interesting talk with him. There was a considerable muster of hon: canons: the University and the City were well represented: the school attended: &amp; the congregation was considerable. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Wakefield</hi><hi> preached the sermon, taking as his subject, the life &amp; character of Bishop </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lightfoot</hi><persName xml:id="1817"></persName><hi>. We had tea in the Deanery after the service, and then returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> skated on thin ice when he spoke about the situation in the mining industry at Sunderland last night: but he succeeded in speaking at sufficient length without saying anything. This in the circumstances &#8211; for he was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry's</hi><persName xml:id="2818"></persName><hi> guest, &amp; had his Lordship for chairman &#8211; was no mean achievement.</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Baldwin's</hi><persName xml:id="4118"></persName><hi> tact and resource are being gradually disclosed, &amp; they are now seen to be very considerable.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>