<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[305]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The great heat of yesterday continues, and makes the comfortless condition of lying in bed still more woeful.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Papers are full of the correspondence between Lord Oxford and Lloyd&#8211;George, the two ex&#8211;Prime Ministers, who affect to lead what calls itself "the Liberal Party." It is significant that Lloyd&#8211;George emphasizes his approval of the Archbishop of Canterbury's luckless essay in peace&#8211;making. There hardly seems any possibility of L.G.'s surviving this crisis: &amp; if, as seems inevitable, he is thrust forth from the Liberal Party, to what camp can he betake himself? He was born in the same year as myself, and he has lived strenuously. Yet his ambition seems to be insatiable, and his energy not incommensurate with his ambition. If he were accepted as Leader by the Labour Party, he might yet regain power to the infinite peril of the country</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Chief Constable from Durham, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Morley</hi><hi>, came to see me. He suggested that I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> join in asking the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> to keep the Police Fund Subscription open for awhile [sic] in order that North&#8211;country contributions might come in. This I consented to. During the afternoon, I received visits from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson Walker</hi><persName xml:id="3161"></persName><hi>, and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi>. There was thunder &amp; heavy rain.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>