<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[269]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I confirmed </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">George Lawrence</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the Chapel before breakfast, and afterwards gave him </hi><hi rend="italic underline">S. Augustine's</hi><hi rend="italic"> '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Confessions</hi><hi rend="italic">' in the Loeb Classics. The household were present, and, with ourselves &amp; our guests, made up a little congregation. I don't like making special arrangements for individuals, because it tends to develop spiritual conceitedness an odious disposition: but I think it requisite that he and his mother should get home while the trains are still running, and this would not be possible if he waited (as had been arranged) for the Confirmation at Easington tonight.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pestle</hi><persName xml:id="5238"></persName><hi> Came to lunch, &amp; to talk to me about the school buildings in his parish. He spoke about the strike with such fatuity that my patience was strained. He maunders about "the children" as if </hi><hi rend="underline">they</hi><hi> could be benefitted by a total cessation of their parents' earnings.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">A mischievous letter in the "Times" signed by the Bishops of Winchester &amp; Southwark can but encourage the miners to regard themselves as injured party, when the truth is that the Nation has made immense &amp; unprecedented sacrifices to save their industry. The Subsidy up to date has cost more than &#x00A3;22.000.000</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[270]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The London "</hi><hi rend="underline">Daily Mail</hi><hi>" has failed to appear by reason of a strike of the workmen, who disapproved of the articles on the strike! And this is liberty!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I motored to Easington, &amp; there confirmed a sick girl in bed, after I went to the parish church, &amp; there confirmed about 120 persons. The fine building lends itself to a function, for it is not only extremely beautiful, but also its acoustics are perfect. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>This is one of the "fat" livings in my gift. It is set down as &#x00A3;1485 net: and the Rectory is a small modern house, the large mansion belonging to the benefice having been sold by the present incumbent, who is a man of small ideas, Socialist professions, and reputation which waxes with the distance from the parish!</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi> After the service I returned to Auckland, </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>picking up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in Durham on my way.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert</hi><hi> told me that Crook was adored in his parish. The venomous windbag is apparently taken at his own valuation of himself. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The evening paper contains what purports to be a caricature of the Bishop of Durham, but is so utterly unlike that gentleman that it cannot even suggest him to anybody who has ever got near enough to see him. Yet it is thought worth producing</hi><hi>!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>