<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[356]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Turner</hi><hi> sends me an acknowledgement of my book on "Spiritual Healing" which I sent him last week. He has but glanced at it, but seems favourably impressed. He notes "the amount of information the work contains, the critical way in which you deal with the problems involved, and especially the beautiful language which you use." This is civil enough, but what I had hoped to elicit was the informed &amp; deliberate judgement of an eminent surgeon on the main question, &amp; on my manner of answering it. But the haste in which men live, &amp; the pressure of immediate duties have destroyed the old responsible handling of even important issues. We take refuge in conventional generalities, and vague compliments which are worthless!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The publishers send me a substantial volume of 723 pages &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">History of England</hi><hi> by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macaulay Trevelyan</hi><hi>. It covers the whole period "from the Earliest Times to the Great War." I read through the account of the English Reformation, and was delighted with its just perspectives, insight, &amp; fine feeling. He does justice to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cranmer</hi><hi>, whom he rightly presents as the true founder of Anglicanism. The character&#8211;sketch of Q. Elizabeth is admirable, &amp; the close connexion between the triumph of the Reformation in England, and in Scotland is well shown. In both cases the movement was patriotic as well as religious, and owed its triumph to the fact. Papistry implied for England subjection to Spain: and for Scotland subjection to France. The Reformation guaranteed independence.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[357]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I adventured to walk unassisted, &amp; managed better than I expected. If I could resume my normal mobility, I should soon shake off this nightmare fiction of illness!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Alderman Pattison</hi><hi> of Durham has just died. He was a quondam Chorister of the Cathedral, and wonderfully devoted to the great Church, where he regularly attended the services. He took infinite pains in transacting his business, &amp; my personal relations with him were invariably most pleasant. He, and old </hi><hi rend="underline">Rushworth</hi><hi>, the furniture dealer, who died a short while ago, stand out more clearly than other townsfolk in my recollections of life in Durham.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I paid the terminal account for </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie's</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi> residence at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's College. This concludes my expenditure on that account. I received a characteristically affectionate letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><hi>, who is to preach his first sermon in July. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">How well I remember my first sermon on June 12</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 1887 &#8211; 39 years ago almost exactly. My text was </hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I could not see for the glory of that Light.</hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> I recall my alarm at seeing M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">E. Talbot, the wife of the Warden of Keble, sitting under the pulpit</hi><hi rend="italic"> in S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul's Oxford. At that time, I think, the Oxford Tractarians thought they had gained a recruit, who might be worth making a fuss with. But I knew better even then, though at that stage the full extent of the chasm which parted me from what they called "Catholicism" was but dimly perceived even by myself. But I knew myself to be "a man of another spirit."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[358]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Is it really necessary that the miners should have no other organ of expression that Mess</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook and Smith? Everyone so far as I can learn, who has any personal contact with the miners, reports them as being extremely anxious to resume work, by no means unable to understand the necessity of reducing the cost of production if the mining industry is to be saved, and not unwilling to concede an increase of the working day if an honest effort to reorganise the industry be made. The Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> proposals are so violently denounced by the Labour Party in Parliament &amp; by M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook outside, that the thought inevitably suggests itself that both are extremely anxious to prevent the miners having a chance of considering them without prejudice. The Prime Minister's attitude, strong, conciliatory, and persistently helpful, is certainly making an impression on the rank &amp; file of the Trade Unions, who are growing impatient of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook's violent &amp; barren negations, &amp; is rather ashamed of becoming the recipient of Russian funds, contributed confessedly with no goodwill to the prosperity of Britain</hi><hi>. If left to themselves, &amp; given liberty to express their genuine opinions, I think it not improbable that Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Cook &amp; Smith might be found to represent no more considerable opinion than their own. Cannot some way be found for getting access to the mind of the miners through some trustworthy and less prejudiced channel?</hi></p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>