<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. I assisted, but did not communicate. Collier and Harry Leng communicated bring the total number of communicants to 11. After breakfast we all motored into Durham in order to attend the morning service in the cathedral. I preached from Acts XIX. 13. "</hi><hi rend="underline">About that time there arose no small stir concerning the Way</hi><hi>." The sermon was very short, taking no more than 20 minutes in delivery. I celebrated the Holy Communion, at which all the choirmen received the Sacrament, but very few others, &amp; of course none of the Cathedral clergy. Ernest carried the staff. The singing was very beautiful. Indeed I think that the choir was never so efficient as it is now. This at least is a feather in the Dean's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> cap. After the service we all returned to Auckland in a deluge of rain.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At tea, Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> started a discussion about the Anglo&#8211;Catholic theory of the Church of England, &amp; the arguments by which the Reformation was in such wise explained, &amp; explained away, that the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks can pose as loyal members of the Reformed church. I was carried into declaring my opinion with a vigour &amp; frankness which were, perhaps, injudicious in the presence of one of my clergy, who probably himself holds the Anglo&#8211;Catholic view!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>