<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[264]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi>My heart leaps up when I behold</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A rainbow in the sky:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>So was it when my life began;</hi></p>
         <p><hi>So is it now I am a man:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>So be it when I shall grow old,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Or let me die!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Child is father of the Man:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>And I could wish my days to be</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Bound each to each by natural piety.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Wordsworth. 1802.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>What is it fitting that I should write in the "Evening Standard" about Inge's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> Hulsean Lectures? If the Editor had not himself sent me the book with the suggestion that I should take it as the text of an article, I should not have thought it anywise suitable. But as Inge was himself a regular contributor to the E.S. for some time, I suppose there is a certain fitness in noticing anything that comes from his pen. And, perhaps, there is a certain piquancy in bringing the gravest question of religion into the columns of a typically modern popular journal. But one's freedom of utterance by the circumstance is not a little restrained.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[265]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the whole morning in writing the article for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi><hi>, and finished it. After lunch I walked in the Park accompanied by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vivian Jackson</hi><hi>, a lad of 16, whom I picked up in the drive, &amp; found interesting enough. He told me that he was the son of a solicitor at Consett, that he was himself a schoolboy at Scarborough, &amp; hoped to go on to Durham University with a view ultimately of becoming a solicitor. This was his first visit to Bishop Auckland, so I gave him a copy of the Tyndale lecture after showing him the Chapel. He was a very natural &amp; ingenious lad; &amp; looked to be confirmed next year.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName><hi rend="italic"> returned from Scotland about 7 p.m., they brought an evening paper, which had ominous news of the coal&#8211;negotiations, which appear to have all but failed. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There is some sinister influence at work among the miners which defeats every effort to effect a settlement. It is, of course, just possible that the mining leaders are "bluffing", and intend to surrender at the last moment, but I hardly think this is probable. Another great economic conflict at this moment will throw back the recovery of our trade for an indefinite period, &amp; might well ruin us wholly. There is neither patriotism, nor intelligence, nor "horse sense" among these workmen</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>