<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I made a final revision of the lecture, &amp; added a brief conclusion. After dinner I read it aloud to my family, and it required 54 minutes to read through in a room; this means that, if the hall be large or the audience dispose to applaud, the lecture will take an hour &amp; a quarter to deliver, which is too long.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dashwood at last sends me his statement of charges for his services during the last five years in dealing with the income tax authorities. It runs up to the rather alarming amount, &#x00A3;157. I told him in future to let me have the statement annually. I paid the income tax due on January 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> &#8211; &#x00A3;514.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Punch</hi><hi> contains an excellent full&#8211;page drawing of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph Inge</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName><hi>, with some descriptive lines which emphasize sub&#8211;acidly his journalistic activities. I find it hard to determine whether he has gained most, or lost most by writing to the papers. He has certainly earned a considerable sum of money.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I motored to Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Bede College Committee: &amp; returned to Auckland afterwards. Miss Lawrie &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me, &amp;, while I was at the meeting, made a visit to the Cathedral &amp; Chapter House.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>