<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The country lay under a mantle of snow when I motored to Darlington to catch the early train. I travelled to King's Cross without companion, &amp; deceived the way with reading. On arriving in London I drove to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; then went to the barber, deeming it advisable to be "combed &amp; trimmed" before presenting myself in the House of Lords. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The debate on the Shrewsbury Bishoprick Measure was vigorously carried on in a fairly large house, from 4.30 p.m. to 7 p.m. My speech occupied 27 minutes, &amp; was said to have been successful. The Lord Chancellor told me that it restrained him from voting, whereas he had intended to vote for the Resolution. The Archbishop of Canterbury made a rather non&#8211;committal speech in which he came down on the side of the Resolution. In spite of this the Resolution was negatived by 61 to 60. I was much congratulated on the division, which, I was assured, was owing to my speech. The Old Adam in me was, of course, much gratified, but I shall become more odious than ever. I went</hi><hi> to 20 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; dined pleasantly with mine hosts. After dinner I had talk with Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The debate in the House of Lords was, perhaps, notable in some respects</hi><hi>. It was not insignificant that the Peers should have "broken away" from the Archbishop's leading, which, though moderately expressed, was quite decisive. I think it is not untrue to say that there was considerable disposition, not merely to listen to what I had to say, but also to follow my counsel. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My speech disappointed myself: [if I had not been "bored stark" by Lord Forester's prosing, I could have spoken far more effectively:] but I was assured on all sides that it was the decisive speech of the evening. The Marquess of Lincolnshire sent across a note of warm congratulation, [but he is a man whom I do not greatly regard.] Lord Salisbury was very hearty in approval of the speech, but he voted against me! Several peers said that my speech determined their votes: &amp; when the numbers were read out, &amp; it was known that the Resolution was lost by a single vote, there was a general disposition to regard it as my victory! Now, of course, this is pleasant enough, but whereto does it lead? The real forces that are controlling the Church of England are not in the House of Lords</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>