<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[251a]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather improved during the night, and the day was fine throughout so that the Commemoration was effected under the most favourable conditions. I attended the function at 11 a.m. A procession through the streets of the Mayor &amp; Corporation followed by the choir &amp; clergy in robes was watched by a large crowd with that half&#8211;amused politeness, which is the normal Englishman's nearest approach to reverence when he is confronted by ecclesiastical parade. The Church was densely crowded, but I observed with surprise that the congregation was almost altogether composed of women. Save for members of the procession &amp; the church&#8211;officers there was hardly a male in the place. Of course at that hour most men w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be engaged in their work, but even so, the spectacle was rather disconcerting. The Bishop of London preached for 45 minutes at least, and was in his worst &amp; most characteristic style &#8211; discursive, anecdotal, egotistic, slangy. I doubt if he was heard, though the acoustics of the church are perfect. Bishop Blomfield's description of a certain preacher as "having a considerable power of sustained remark" came to my mind as I listened to this strange out&#8211;pouring. The service ended, we proceeded to the Dome, </hi><hi rend="bold">[252] </hi><hi>[symbol] where 302 persons lunched under the chairmanship of the Mayor. The proceedings began at 1.30 p.m. and did not end until 4 p.m. A collection was made, which added &#x00A3;450 to the fund for building a Robertson Memorial Hall which is to cost &#x00A3;14,000. A grandson of Robertson, Sir George Shuckbury Bt. made a short speech, both his cousins, who bear their grandfather's name, were abroad, the one serving as a soldier in India, the other as British Minister in the Angentine. Sir Oliver Lodge responded for "The Guests", &amp; took the opportunity to deliver a carefully prepared oration on his spiritualistic hobby, which was as unsuitable to the occasion, as it was to many of his hearers objectionable. Campbell expressed his surprise &amp; regret at this propaganda to me as we walked home. But there is no restraining fanaticks. At 8 p.m. I preached in the Church, which was well&#8211;filled with a congregation in which the sexes were more reasonably proportioned. Sir Oliver Lodge arrived during the sermon, &amp; was shown into the stall which the Incumbent vacated. Campbell expressed much approval of the sermon, which he asked leave to send to the "Church Family Newspaper."</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>