<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">,1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A tragedy happened in the Park this morning. Edward Bryden discovered a man with his throat cut, &amp; near to die. The police were fetched, and removed him to the Hospital, where he is thought to be dying. It is suspected that the motive of this attempted suicide was some squalid entanglement with his neighbour's wife.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel and I motored again to South Shields, where I confirmed 105 persons out of the 4 parishes of Holy Trinity, S. Francis, S. Jude, S. Mark, with a total population of over 33,000 souls. This is not more than one sixth of what it should be.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Harry Verne</hi><hi> sends me a note thanking me for a copy of "The Bishoprick" which he had received "as a member of the Church Assembly Education Commission". He adds: "I am afraid the Commission is not very likely to adopt your views, but perhaps you can persuade the Assembly as to the hopelessness of the present attitude of the average Churchman towards religious education in schools." I infer from a postcard which reached me that the "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">British Weekly</hi><hi>" has had some notice of my article, but otherwise it appears to have attracted no attention. As usual with my writings, it falls in with nobody's interest!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>