<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A villainous toothache harassed me great part of the night, and did not improve my efficiency all day. I received the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We got into the controversial area, when the question of a Festival of Corpus Christi was proposed, for the suggestion of a Festival of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Joseph was summarily rejected much to my relief, &amp; more to my surprise</hi><hi>. The Bishop of Southwark move a resolution conceding the Festival but disallowing the Roman date, &amp; this was seconded by the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>. As the discussion proceeded, it became apparent that the general sense of the bishops inclined to this course, &amp; that it commanded the approval of the Archbishops. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It was opposed by the Bishops of Durham, Worcester, &amp; S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> E. and I., &amp; rather less decidedly by the Bishops of Ripon, Peterboro, and Exeter</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I dined at the Holborn Restaurant at the annual dinner of University College, Durham. Lord Burnham was the other "principal guest". </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He reminded me that he and I were in the same class in the same honour list at Oxford in 1884</hi><hi>. I proposed the toast of the Castle, &amp; he that of the College. Hogge, who is organizing the appeal, said the &#x00A3;15,000 had already been collected.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>