<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather is almost unseasonably mild &#8211; a welcome change after the rigours &amp; deluges of the last weeks.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received the Holy Communion at 8.30 a.m. in the chapel. We spent most of the morning in discussing whether we would revise the existing Prayer&#8211;Book, and produce a revised Book which should be for awhile [sic] an alternative, &amp; ultimately the only Prayer book; or leaving the existing book unrevised, should supplement it as seemed advisable, printing our additions &amp;c in the same volume. We decided (fatuously) on the latter course. After lunch we went into the Library, &amp; witnessed the conferring of Lambeth doctorates on the Deans of York &amp; Bristol. The afternoon session was devoted to Puire, connected with which was the larger issue of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Quicunque Valt</hi><hi>. After tea Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> &amp; I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. Jean Bruce<persName xml:id="1221"></persName> came to dinner, but she had to recall herself to my memory. Also, the Bishop of Mombasa &amp; his wife. He said that matters had improved in Kenya &amp; that Norman Leys' book was rather the speech of an able prosecutor than an impartial statement of the facts.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>