<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[331]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Auckland Castle.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I slept well, and feel much more vigorous. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi><persName xml:id="5214"></persName><hi> shows himself to be a skillfull [sic] as well as an attentive nurse: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> discloses the monopolizing solicitude of wife–hood. The view from my bed is fair &amp; restful, and a Sabbatic calm glows in the sunlight. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName><hi> writes to say </hi><hi rend="underline">inter alia</hi><hi> that the Archbishop's chosen counsellors were the Bishop of London, Iremonger<persName xml:id="4290"></persName>, Kirk of the Industrial Christian Fellowship, and Woodward, the new Canon of Westminster! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He also tells me that he is giving up journalism having now secured his object. In four years he has saved £14,000, i.e. an income of £700 per annum</hi><hi>! It is very creditable to the British Public to invest its money so well.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bryan Bourke</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishop Maltby's grandson</hi><hi>, who came on a temporary employment to Durham some while back &amp; so made my acquaintance, writes dolorously to say that the Strike has taken away his job, and that he is at his wit's end to earn his own living. It </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi><hi> monstrously hard on him, &amp; the many others who share his fate. Public sympathy &amp; assistance are freely given to these pig–headed miners, who would ruin the country rather than work 8 hours out of the 24, but neither are available for those who only want to be allowed to work!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[332] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> of Worcester</hi><hi> writes about P.B. Revision. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop is evidently exerting himself to induce the Bishops to grant Reservation for Communion, without limitation to the case of the Sick. This I cannot see my way to accept</hi><hi>. Reservation for the Sick may, perhaps, be defended on the ground of charity to the physically infirm, like the indicative absolution in the office for Visiting the Sick; &amp; does not, therefore, necessarily involve any principle or theory about the Sacrament. But any other Reservation does to my mind carry the assumption that Christ's Presence inheres in the Elements, apart from the faithful Communicant &amp; outside the covenanted Sacramental reception. And, if this be conceded, there is no reasonable halting–place between the English &amp; the Roman treatment of the Lord's Supper. It follows that, if I do really intend to resist the Roman doctrine &amp; practice, I must take my stand at this point. In view of the actual situation in the Church of England, it does not seem to me expedient to depart from the existing situation i.e. no reservation for any purpose whatever: and, therefore, I shall so vote: but, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">if reservation for the Sick only be agreed upon, I shall not think it necessary to carry my opposition beyond a negative vote. If, however, the majority decide to allow Reservation for Communion, or even for Adoration, I will carry my opposition to the point of resisting the Revised Prayer Book both in the Church Assembly, &amp; in the House of Lords</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[333] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>About noon I was dressed, and carried into the garden, which is luxuriant in the beauty of early summer. This hateful strike has had the effect of clearing away the normal smoke, &amp; showing everything in an unaccustomed clearness and colour. The "Observer" reports Lloyd George's speech in Manchester. It is a vigourous &amp; rather embittered defence of himself, and, as such, is certainly effective. But it will not assist the restoration of peace in the poor little faction which calls itself the Liberal party. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">However he declares himself a Liberal, &amp; repudiates with energy the suggestion that he meditated any junction with "Labour</hi><hi>". Unfortunately, his reputation for veracity stands so low. that nobody will be much influenced by his statements. They must, one would suppose, make any future approaches to "Labour" more difficult. The negociations, if there are any, between the coal–owners and the miners are proceeding in a very leisurely manner, as if nothing turned on expedition, when every day of continued idleness in the minefields were not bringing the total ruin of British industry nearer. I suppose the villains who are pulling strings in the background are reckoning on creating a situation so desperate that even the most reluctant Government must adventure the folly of nationalisation. The railways will hardly escape bankruptcy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[334] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to see me this afternoon. He is the youngest man for his age – he is nearer 80 than 70 – that I know: &amp; his interest in affairs, small &amp; great, is vivid &amp; insatiable. </hi><hi rend="underline">He expressed approval of my letter in the "Newcastle Journal', &amp; said that he thought the Archbishop of C. was evidently being "rushed" by others, his juniors in age, &amp; his inferiors in wisdom</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I finished reading again Kingsley's "Yeast", which was published in 1851</hi><hi rend="italic">. It has a very obsolete appearance now. His theory that the social salvation of England lay with the squires &amp; the parsons reads oddly today, when the first are bankrupt &amp; the last are rapidly dwindling both in number &amp; in social consequence. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Wilson said that in his judgment</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> Bishop Westcott's</hi><persName xml:id="1047"></persName><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">intervention in the coal–strike of 1895 was the most unfortunate events of his episcopate. Certainly that intervention was much exaggerated at the time, and has been magnified almost grotesquely since. In fact it has grown into a legend, &amp; serves as the classic instance of Christian Socialism in practice. Its influence has undoubtedly been very great, and I must needs think, very unwholesome: for not only has it been the grand precedent for episcopal meddling in economic crises, but also it has tended to conceal from Anglicans, &amp; especially from Anglican ecclesiastics, the enormous changes which have taken place in the conditions of industry. "Labour" is becoming nakedly secularist in temper, and international in organization</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>