<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>God is that only which he testifieth of himself, and to imagine any other thing of God than that, is damnable idolatry. Therefore saith the 118</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> psalm, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Happy are they which search the testimonies of the Lord</hi><hi>:" that is to say, that which God testifieth and witnesseth unto us. But how shall I that do, when ye will not let me have his testimonies, or witnesses, in a tongue which I understand? Will ye resist God? Will ye forbid him to give his Spirit unto the lay as well as unto you? </hi><hi rend="underline">Hath he not made the English tongue? Why forbid ye him to speak in the English tongue then, as well as in the Latin</hi><hi>?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Tyndale. Preface to "Obedience of a Christian Man."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This reasoning is quite irresistible. Its weak point, of course, is the assumption that the Divine Self&#8211;Revelation is </hi><hi rend="underline">only</hi><hi> made in the Scripture: yet it might fairly be urged that so far as it is made in Scripture, the message is final. The Church, Science, History &#8211; these may elucidate, even supplement, the teaching of Scripture, but can they ever disallow or replace it? To add Tradition to Scripture on equal terms is to enthrone Tradition.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>There was a considerable snow&#8211;fall during the night, but much of the snow disappeared in the course of the day. In the forenoon I dictated to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> some of the lecture which I am pledged to deliver next week in Newcastle. The Curate of Shildon, a weird creature called Sumner, came to lunch. He is like the conventional stage&#8211;curate, but he has no small opinion of his capacity, &amp; is hag&#8211;ridden by the delusion that he has been "ignored", whereas the fact is that he has been considered &amp; set aside! He illustrates one [missing word] our most perplexing problems &#8211; what to do with the virtuous incompetent! He stayed to lunch, &amp; would have stayed for ever, if I had not edged him out! I walked round the Park with Lionel, &amp; then resumed work on the lecture, but to little purpose.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Ed. H. Leale, Vicar of S. Stephen's, Bexhill&#8211;on &#8211;Sea, writes to say that he has just read a review of my book on "Spiritual Healing" in the "Spectator", and rejoices to find that I am as much opposed to the movement as he is. He also sends me a copy of "The Outlook", which contains an article by himself on "Spiritual Healing". I am curious as to the number of copies of my book which have been sold. I fear they are but few. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>