<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[259]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Since March 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, when I came to London for the debate in the House of Lords until now I have been almost entirely idle, and mostly absent from my diocese. The only conceivable justification for this protracted failure in my duty is that I return to duty more able in body, more resolute in purpose, more consecrated in spirit. Can I honestly assure myself that in any measure this will be my case? "</hi><hi rend="underline">Depart from me, for I am a sinful man, O Lord</hi><hi>." The range &amp; difficulty of my obligation grow ever clearer, and more appalling; and my own inadequacy in character, learning, power, and physical strength, is brought home to me ever more plainly. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Who is sufficient for all these things</hi><hi>?" If only with the Apostle could I answer humbly but boldly "</hi><hi rend="underline">Our sufficiency is from God, who also hath made us sufficient as ministers of a new covenant, not of the letter, but of the Spirit</hi><hi>." I might still find courage to renew the warfare of duty, but can I? The course of the world seems ever to grow more hostile. I am filled with fear as to the possible developments of this Coal&#8211;Strife. In the best event, it means further dwarfing of all that the Bishop of Durham symbolizes, represents, and expresses in that great population. And in the worst event?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[260] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in Holy Trinity Church. There were 41 Communicants, mostly women. It was not without emotion that I found myself ministering this in Robertson's old church. Yesterday I contracted a slight chill, so I took the prudent course of remaining indoors. In the course of the morning, I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Drummond, a son of the Principle of Manchester College, Oxford, came to lunch and stayed to tea. He is a loquacious and far&#8211;travelled man, who is evidently mixed up in many of these religious &amp; philanthropic cosmopolitanisms, which Americans so greatly favour: but he spoke intelligently, &amp; said some interesting things. Campbell, who had been preaching to Labour men in the parish Church, joined us at tea&#8211;time &amp; spoke very amusingly about his Transatlantic experiences. He agrees in rating American religion very low, but maintains that there are Americans who perceive and lament its low level.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Gilbert during the afternoon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather degenerated as the day advanced, and at Eventide was raining &amp; sleeting woefully.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>