<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[192]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent the whole morning writing to Canon Streeter<persName xml:id="3230"></persName> and the Bishop of Liverpool with references to the letter which 4 Oxonians intended to send to the Times on the difficult subject of Clerical Subscription. They want the Bishops publicly to say that disbelief of the Virgin&#8211;Birth and "physical" Resurrection shall be no bar to the Ordination in the Church of England. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This seems to me hardly a fair demand: &amp; certainly I could not concede the point without important qualifications</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch I motored to Barnard Castle, and attended a meeting of the school governors. They civilly re&#8211;elected me to the chair. Bircham<persName xml:id="5380"></persName> made himself as offensive as he could, but I ignored his rudeness, &amp; he went off "with is tail between his legs"! After tea I returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Phillip Strong</hi><persName xml:id="5382"></persName><hi> who is about to leave the diocese in order to take up work in Leeds, came to see me. He is a good lad, and the kind we want in this diocese. I ordained him both to the diaconate, and to the priesthood in the chapel here, &amp; I had built hopes on his service in the diocese, &amp; now he takes wing for Leeds.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>