<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>This day was not so exciting as yesterday, but perhaps not less useful, for we worked at the Service for Confirmation, and then went through the Marriage Service. We swept away a foolish ceremonial of blessing the ring, which the Clergy desired to introduce, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but we expunged the salutary word "obey" from the bride's vow &#8211; a foolish concession to an unreal &amp; mischievous agitation. But the celibate bishops are deeply infected with feminism, &amp; some of their married brethren have the mischief formidably presented within their own homes, so formidably that they have no courage to resist it</hi><hi>! I bade M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Davidson goodbye at lunch. Rather to my surprise, she pressed me to promise to be her guest when we meet again in June. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Your presence here is such a comfort to any husband.</hi><hi>" The dear lady grows old, and her words in January may not fairly be held to bind her in June, but she means well. I drove to Adeney, and tried on clothes: I looked in on Hugh Rees, &amp; bought "Heloise &amp; Ab&#x00E8;land" by George Moore, as a stay&#8211;stomach on my journey: &amp; then I went to King's Cross, &amp; caught the 5.30 p.m. train to Darlington. I got to the Castle about 11.30 p.m.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>