<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[318]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I had some sleep last night, and am the better for it this morning. It is just three weeks since the operation, and I am assured that I have made good progress. How strangely dead one is to the risk one ran, and the deliverance one received!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The excitement of the morning was my getting out of bed and into an armchair, wherein I sate for 45 minutes, using the time for writing a letter to Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>. Then I went back to bed, as I thought, rather precipitately.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel came during the afternoon. I wrote cheques for the monthly wages, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">sent &#x00A3;5 to the "Save the Children Fund" run by the Editor of the "Northern Star"</hi><hi>, and drew &#x00A3;15 for myself. The draft for &#x00A3;12:10:0 dividend on War&#8211;Loan arrived. I dictated letters to the Bishop of Wakefield, the Bishop of Oxford, Kitty Inge<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, Dolphin<persName xml:id="2798"></persName>, Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Wild paid me a visit about 7 p.m. She is very confident that the Bishop, her husband, is really better, but everybody else seems to be confident to the contrary. And, if indeed he be suffering (as is now generally asserted) from</hi><hi rend="underline">paralysis agitans</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">any real restoration to health must be impossible. It is very sad indeed. She tells me, &amp; the Bishop himself said as much, that 3 of their sons have declared their resolve to be Ordained</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>