<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I adapted the sermon on "</hi><hi rend="underline">Christianity as the Way</hi><hi>" for use in Westminster Abbey next Sunday morning: &amp; wrote some necessary letters. Old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Greenway</hi><hi> &amp; his daughter came to lunch. He brought me a piece of a marble statue from (as he alleged) the Temple of Ephesus, &amp; talked with irrepressible volume &amp; persistence all the time he was here! I walked in the Park; &amp; then motored to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hebburn</hi><hi> for a Confirmation. There were about 107 candidates from the parishes of S. Cuthbert, S. John, &amp; S. Oswald, of which the combined population exceeds 26,000 souls. This means that about one in five of the children of suitable age is presented for Confirmation. There is a considerable Roman Catholic population to be reckoned with, &amp;, of course, the varigated [sic] sectaries are in the sum numerous. It would be a liberal estimate to allow for Papists and Sectaries another fifth. </hi><hi rend="underline">This leaves three fifths of the people outside organized Christianity</hi><hi>. It is a dismaying &amp; humiliating reflection. Of the 3 incumbents in Hebburn, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marr</hi><hi> was ordained in 1890 &amp; has been 25 years in his present parish. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi><hi> was ordained in 1906, &amp; has held his present benefice for 3 years. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Birtwhistle</hi><hi> was ordained in 1896, and has held S. Oswald's for 5 years. Marr is the best &amp; most effective of the three.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>