<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[290]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold"> Drummond's Nursing Home. Newcastle.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I take up the story of my life from the point at which the record was broken off on Sunday afternoon May 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. In the course of the afternoon I found myself feeling extremely ill. Nevertheless, I determined to make an effort to carry out my promise to preach at All Saints, Monkwearmouth. Accompanied by Lionel, I left the Castle shortly after 5 p.m., &amp; motored to the Church. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I was in much pain, which the motion of the car did nothing to relieve. However, I robed, &amp; sat in the Sanctuary while the service proceeded. But my pain increased, and when it was time for me to preach, I was quite unable to do more than crawl out of the Church on Lionel's arm. I got into the Car, &amp; was carried back to the Castle in agony. There I went at once to bed, &amp; sent for M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Cullagh. He gave me some remedies, &amp; bade me remain in bed on Monday. Then, however, my state was worse: he suspected appendicitis, &amp; asked to be allowed to send for M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Turner, the Newcastle specialist. Happily Turner was accessible, &amp; came over at once. He confirmed the diagnosis, &amp; ordered an operation</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[291]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">He insisted on immediate action. So, accompanied by M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Cullagh &amp; Lionel, for the 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> time in succession I traversed the 25 miles between Bishop Auckland &amp; Newcastle. It was truly a</hi><hi rend="underline">via dolorosa</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. Groups of strikers were about the roads, &amp; as we passed through Birtley we were stoned. At last we reached our journey's end, &amp; I was received into the Nursing Home, where on Tuesday morning I underwent the operation, which (as the appendix was "virulent" and "gangrenous") probably saved my life</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>