<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926. Lambeth Palace.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A rapid thaw during the night had removed most of the snow before morning. Laus Deo! I did not attend service in chapel, but read Beard's admirable Hibbert Lectures on "The Reformation of the XVI</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Century". </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The morning's discussion was uneventful save for an episode which disclosed the remarkable change which has come about in the episcopal attitude towards the Creed</hi><hi>. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The question has been raised whether the Creed should be interrogative or indicative in the service for baptizing adults. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">The Bishop of Manchester</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName><hi rend="italic"> objected to the interrogative form as emphasizing the separate articles of the Creed, &amp; instanced the case of those who, while willing to accept the Creed </hi><hi rend="italic underline">generally</hi><hi rend="italic"> as a statement of corporate belief, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">could not profess belief in the Virgin Birth</hi><hi rend="italic">. I said that I held, and always had held with D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sanday</hi><persName xml:id="359"></persName><hi rend="italic">, that such general assent was consistent with an </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ex animo</hi><hi rend="italic"> acceptance of the Creed. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pearce</hi><persName xml:id="636"></persName><hi rend="italic"> said that no bishop could accept without explanation </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> the articles of the Creed. The Bishop of Chichester </hi><hi rend="italic underline">alone</hi><hi rend="italic"> made a protest, which was received without sympathy by his brethren. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Compare this with the declarations of the Bishops in 1918, just eight years ago</hi><hi rend="italic">, when I was consecrated to the Episcopate.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch we were free until 5 p.m., and scattered on various ends of business &amp; pleasure. I went to the hair&#8211;dresser, &amp; was "trimmed" &amp; cleansed. Then I went to Hugh Rees, and ordered some books, among them Pastor's Popes, which will cost me about &#x00A3;10. Then I went to Whippell, &amp; ordered shirts, vests, pants &amp; collars. I proceeded to Adeney, &amp; ordered a suit of clothes: finally, I returned to the Club, and had tea. Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> and I drove to Lambeth in time to attend the resumed session at 5 p.m. We were concerned with the Confirmation service, &amp; sanctioned a good many changes. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Bristol succeeded in getting a reference to the age of the candidates inserted into the rubrick which affirms the Bishop's right to "approve" the candidate presented to him for Confirmation</hi><hi>. Bishops and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Talbot came to dinner: also, Geoffrey Dawson<persName xml:id="2709"></persName> &amp; his wife. I took M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Dawson in to dinner, &amp; found her very agreeable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received a long letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi>, who appears very keen to get ordained, &amp; into work at Belmont. The sudden change of weather brought to me an uncomfortable attack of lumbago.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>