<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Women be no meet vessels to rule or to preach, for both are forbidden them: yet hath God endowed them with his Sprit at sundry times, &amp; showed his power &amp; goodness upon them, &amp; wrought wonderful things by them, because he would not have them despised. We read that women have judged all Israel, &amp; have been great prophetesses, &amp; have done mighty deeds. Yea, &amp; if stories be true, women have preached since the opening of the new testament. Do not our women now christen &amp; minister the sacrament of baptism in time of need? </hi><hi rend="underline">Might they not, by as good reason, preach also, if necessity required</hi><hi>? If a woman were driven into some island, where Christ was never preached, might she there not preach him, if she had the gift thereto? Might she not also baptize? </hi><hi rend="underline">And why might she not, by the same reason, minister the sacrament of the body &amp; blood of Christ, and teach them how to choose officers &amp; ministers?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Tyndale. "Answer unto Sir Thomas More's Dialogue" p.18 (Parker Society).</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A beautiful day, sunny and calm yet fresh. I worked all the morning at the lecture. There came to lunch a young man, named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Neill</hi><hi>, who meditates Ordination next Advent: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Warth</hi><hi>, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke's, Darlington, who desires to add a chancel to his church: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi><persName xml:id="4218"></persName><hi>, who came for a walk in the Park. After lunch, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil</hi><hi> &amp; I walked in the Park for an hour and a half. I was much pleased with his conversation. After tea I resumed work on the lecture, of which I have now written rather less than half.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi><hi> prints a new account of the execution of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles I</hi><hi> "written by one of the earliest of English journalists, &amp; rediscovered within the last few weeks in the British Museum." It is by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Dillingham</hi><hi> "author" of </hi><hi rend="underline">The Moderate Intelligencer</hi><hi> issued on February 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> 1649. There is a reference to the king's dogs which I do not remember having seen before. "</hi><hi rend="underline">That night he commanded his dogs should be taken away and sent to his wife, as not willing to have anything present that might take him off from serious consideration of himself</hi><hi>." There is a description of the block as "a little piece of wood, flat at bottom, about a foot and a half long" which settles a controversy.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>