<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[243]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Could I wisely point a moral from Robertson's life for the elucidation of the present situation? His message does not lose relevance because it was based on the factors which never fail in English Christendom &#8211; Christ and the Conscience. In so far as English folk continue to be Christians at all these are the supreme things in religion for them. Sacramentalism with its environment of ceremony and its sacerdotal doctrine may appeal to Latins: it does not appeal to the nations which have traversed the experience of the Reformation, i.e. of Calvin's Reformation. Is this a tenable proposition? I think it </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi><hi> roughly true, but where are its evidences? The continued sale of Robertson's sermons two generations after his death is but a slender basis for so large a generalisation. But may that circumstance not fairly be offered as a thought&#8211;provoking fact, without actually presenting it as an argument? Sacramentalism &amp;c may be well enough in its way: &amp; it </hi><hi rend="underline">does</hi><hi> appeal to some phases &amp; types, but unless it can connect itself with a genuine discipleship to Christ, and a strong personal morality, has it any chance of winning serious Englishmen?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[244] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We left Dargarvel at 11.30 a.m., &amp; motored to Helensburgh, where we lunched with <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> ancient aunt at Leaside, where also we left Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, who was to visit the old lady. Then we went on to Row Lodge, &amp; saw Olive<persName xml:id="1686"></persName> &amp; her children. They are vigourous &amp; cheerful, but plain bairns. At 3.30 p.m. we left them, &amp; motored to the Moss, Killearn where we were to stay with Miss Laurie. The road lay beside Loch Lomond, and we enjoyed a succession of ravishing prospects. After the wind and rain of last night, the weather was brilliant and uncertain, the most favourable in the world for disclosing the beauties of the scenery. We reached the Moss shortly after 4.30 p.m., and were warmly welcomed by our hostess. After tea, &amp; a short walk in the garden, I betook myself to writing. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote at some length to Duncan on the subject of C.L.B.<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> emphasizing the necessity of avoiding controversial terms like Mass in teaching religion to the boys</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I must needs suspect, however, that by "definitely Church lines" he means nothing else than this queer "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" which is now the fashion.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>