<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Remember ye not how in our own time, of all that taught grammar in England, not one understood the Latin tongue? How came we then by the Latin tongue again? Not by them, though we learned certain rules and principles of them, by which we were moved and had an occasion to seek further; but out of the old authors. Even so we seek up old antiquities, out of which we learn, and not of our church; though we received many principles of our church at the beginning, but more falsehood (among) than truth.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. Tyndale "Answer" p. 55.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>What the classical authors were to the student of Latin, that says </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndale</hi><hi> is the Scripture to the Christian &#8211; his model, standard, and final authority. The teaching Church has as much authority, and no more, as a pinched pedagogue of the medieval grammar schools, whose utmost achievment [sic] would be to make their pupils as able to write dog&#8211;Latin as they were themselves!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In the letter </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndale</hi><hi> wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frith</hi><hi>, and which reached </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frith</hi><hi> in prison, he describes himself as "evil&#8211;favoured in this world, and without grace in the sight of men, speechless and rude, dull and slow&#8211;witted" and indicates that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frith</hi><hi> could supply his deficiencies:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>"Your part shall be to supply that lacketh in me, remembering that as lowliness of heart shall make you high with God, even so meekness of words shall make you sink into the hearts of men."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Foxe</hi><hi> describes his manner of life in Antwerp, but says nothing of his "preaching", but much of his charities, &amp; (on Sundays) his reading of the Scripture. "In the wily sublilties [sic] of this world he was simple and unexpert." The officers who arrested him "said to Poynty, when they laid him in prison, that they pitied to see his simplicity when they took him". He is described as "a man of no great stature." According to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Foxe</hi><hi> (who is not the most trustworthy of witnesses when blackening a Papist or exalting a Reformer) </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndale</hi><hi> so carried himself in prison as to convert the keeper, &amp; his daughter, and others of his household. On the whole I incline to think with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Beard</hi><hi> that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndale's</hi><hi> is the "noblest name" of the English Reformation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[104] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I had a letter from Baily asking me to restore to his license, that woeful curate of his. But I could not. I spent the morning over Tyndale very fruitlessly. A young man, named Davy, came to lunch, and afterwards walked in the Park. He is an enthusiast for social improvement, &amp; pullulates with projects for raising the standard of life among the miners. After he had taken his departure, I returned to the lecture. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> John Hunter Blair, a young man of 22, who is meditating Ordination came to consult with me thereon. A serious lad, perhaps a trifle heavy, but carrying himself as a gentleman. I shall be pleased if he finally determines to be ordained in this diocese.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to thank me for last night's sermon, &amp; to tell me the following story:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">During the War a Scottish regiment was informed that within an hour or two the men were to go over the top, &amp; there was also circulated the announcement that, previously to doing so, a short Communion service w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be held. Four young officers, thoughtful &amp; well&#8211;living men, attended, &amp; when kneeling amongst their comrades were informed by the Chaplain that they c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic">. not receive it. In face of the terrible ordeal which these Officers had in front of them &amp; their attitude </hi><hi rend="bold">[105] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi><hi rend="italic"> in regard to the issues involved, they were obliged to withdraw, sore in heart.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi><hi rend="italic"> tells me that this "painful episode was told him a few weeks ago by the father of one of the young men concerned." Thus it comes to me at two removes. But the really dreadful thing is that I cannot sweep it aside as altogether incredible. There is so much perverted conscientiousness among the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" clergy where the Holy Communion is concerned that I cannot deny the probability that some of them would act in that way in the circumstances. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The time cometh</hi><hi rend="italic">", said our Lord, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">when he that killeth you will think that he doeth God service</hi><hi rend="italic">". And, of course, this bigotry receives encouragement from such an incident as that reported from the diocese of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Alban's. On the whole, I incline to think that I did the right thing in stigmatizing his Lordship's conduct last night. It is at least something that the bigotted [sic] action of one Bishop should be promptly rebuked by another. Both the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic">" and the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" express approval of the Bishop's refusal to sanction the admission of the Non&#8211;conformists to Holy Communion.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>