<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I remained indoors all day, and wrote many letters. I received a very kind letter from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName><hi rend="italic">: he writes:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"There are many of us who feel anxious at the least sign of your ill&#8211;health. We cannot afford to lose, even temporarily, your advocacy of sound theological learning. If the body proves a rebel when the spirit drives it too fast, concentrate on the big issues, &amp; let others do routine work. Only the unthinking will grumble at such action: your friends &amp; admirers &#8211; a multitude of silent &amp; often anxious people &#8211; will rejoice."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Other letters from unknown correspondents suggest the same thing viz: that large numbers of people in the country "see light in my light", and would regard my failure as a considerable calamity. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury ever maintains that I express the lay mind in an unusual degree, and carry more influence among the ordinary lay folk than other ecclesiasticks. On the whole, I think, this is probably true; but then ordinary lay folk have ceased to count in the Church of England. They have been edged out by the clericalist laity, who dominate diocesan conferences &amp; the Church Assembly</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>