<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I motored to Durham, and, after leaving <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> at the Station, proceeded to Bede College, where I confirmed two students in the chapel. It was a very impressive little service, which may, perhaps, be of real service to the College. After an interview with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, whom I found engaged with his class of deacons, I returned to Auckland for lunch.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I paid a cheque of eight guineas to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Hornby</hi><hi> in remuneration for his services in taking 4 confirmations for me. He made a decent resistance, but acquiesced without serious difficulty in that prosaic but equitable proceeding! I walked in the Park, &amp; there had some talk with five very pleasant young men, out of work, who were engaged in kicking about a football. I brought them into the Castle and showed them the camelia, &amp; some other objects of interest. I wonder what their candid opinion of the Bishop of Durham is!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Worcester</hi><persName xml:id="636"></persName><hi> writes &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">The lay peers with whom I consorted last week were emphatic in praise of the Bishopric speech when they voted the other way</hi><hi>". He adds that "the proposal for the division of episcopal incomes was unanimously sent to blazes by the Ecclesiastical Committee". So far: so good.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>