<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[223]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Bishop of Liverpool writes to me about the essay of the Four Liberals, and sends me a letter which he has received from one of them. After explaining that, though all members of Ripon Hall, they do not pretend to represent that institution, the writer proceeds:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"We write as individuals faced with difficulties in seeking ordination, and we think we represent many others, who are presented by similar difficulties from becoming ordained. </hi><hi rend="underline">We feel strongly that these difficulties are not such as can be solved by any private conversations before Ordination</hi><hi>… We feel that we want an open recognition by the Church of what is, I think, already in private the case, that it is possible frankly and honestly to be ordained, with a very liberal attitude towards orthodox formuloe."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>After stating that such an open recognition is necessary in order that congregations may be under no misunderstanding, &amp; that liberal&#8211;minded &amp; educated men may not find themselves unable to seek Ordination, the writer explains that the letter was written after much </hi><hi rend="bold">[224] </hi><hi>thought and consultation with others, the writer proceeds:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"We feel that Ordination would for us involve a measure of dishonesty, only justifiable if at all, for the gain of giving ourselves to work in the Church: and that our protest against that dishonesty w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> lose much of its force, if we waited to make it till after we were ordained. We feel too that it is essential to make our appeal for an open recognition of the honesty of a liberal attitude in the Church before the new Prayer Book presents what will be taken by many as a final statement on the question… We are now acting on our own responsibility in attempting to voice an appeal for Freedom. We feel that it is easy for us as ordinands to make that appeal: and that it may be easier for those who are in authority, &amp; who represent the Church as a whole, to answer the appeal, when first an explicit statement of the burden of dishonesty for some liberal ordinands has been made."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[225]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The writer, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey Allen</hi><hi>, gives no indication that he and his friends are prepared to modify their action in deference to advice however weighty.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It is clear to me that the Bishops cannot reasonably be asked to declare that Ordination candidates are free to deny the Virgin Birth and the Physical Resurrection. To do so would be equivalent to formally breaking away from the comity of all Orthodox Churches. The Lambeth Appeal presents the Creed of Nicaea as "</hi><hi rend="underline">the sufficient statement of the Christian faith</hi><hi>", and makes "</hi><hi rend="underline">the whole&#8211;hearted acceptance of</hi><hi>" the said Creed a condition of "</hi><hi rend="underline">the visible unity of the Church</hi><hi>." How could the English bishops now declare that for the clergy of the Church of England a good deal less than the Nicene Creed would suffice? And how could it be reasonably possible to limit the new liberty of repudiation to precisely those two articles? In seeking to satisfy the scruples of individuals, should we not be alienating the general mass of believers? And how long would even the scrupulous individuals, for whose satisfaction so heavy a risk had been accepted, remain satisfied? Is it not more than likely that we should "make the worst of both worlds"?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[226]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I had an interview with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Jameson Holme</hi><hi>, the son of the Rector of Penshaw and, after some discussion, and not without hesitation, accepted him for the September Ordination. He is a heavily built man of thirty, with an awkward manner, and an uncertain utterance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Peter Richardson</hi><hi> came to go with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> to the Raby Ball. I took him into the Chapel, &amp; showed him the Cosin plate, which was displayed on the Altar. He was properly appreciative. There was also at dinner the young Russian prince who is staying with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Lightfoot, &amp; was also going to the Raby Ball. He is a small man, with a quick manner, a voluble tongue, &amp; a decided opinion on many subjects.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to the Bishop of Liverpool on the subject of clerical subscription. In order to make sure that I was not departing from the position on that subject which in prae&#8211;episcopal days I had taken up, I read again what I said in my Lyman Beecher Lectures delivered in Yale in 1909. I can still endorse what I then said.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>