<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>It may not always be to the advantage of the Church that so much Church property is also national property: but the fact has to be faced, and the rights of parishioners, of the City and of the nation, which takes its pride in the City and its monuments are not imaginary, but can be defended with cogency and reason.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>v. The Times. March 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1926. "City Churches."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This article on the Union of Benefices &amp; Disposal of Churches (Metropolis) Measure is conceived in a very different spirit from that which inspired the Article on the rejection of the Shrewsbury Bishoprick Measure.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>N.B. For Suffrigan [sic] Bishops see the Following:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Phillimore's</hi><persName xml:id="1940"></persName><hi> Ecclesiastical Law.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gibson's</hi><hi> Codex.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stubbs</hi><hi>. Reg: Sac: Angl: p.142</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hardwick</hi><hi>. Ch. Hist: Middle Age.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>p.238 note on Bps in partibus</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Makower</hi><hi>. Const&#8211;Hist of C. of E. p.309f.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>For their prominence in the Vatican Council see</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sparrow Simpson</hi><hi> "Papal Infallibility"</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pomponio Leto</hi><hi> "Eight months in Rome."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote letters, &amp; worked at the annotations of my speech in the House of Lords for the Bishoprick. Also after lunch</hi><hi>, I wrote to Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> of Worcester saying that the puppy was now ready to travel.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I left the Castle at 5.20 p.m., and motored to Seaham Harbour, picking up Lionel in Durham on the way. There were 220 candidates for Confirmation from several parishes. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Before the service I examined 3 boys who who were under 14 from Duncan's parish</hi><hi>. They seemed woefully ignorant, and even Duncan could evoke very little. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Finally I consented to confirm them on the understanding that they were not admitted to the Holy Communion until Christmas, &amp; were further instructed</hi><hi>. But I was unpleasantly impressed by the kind of questions which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Duncan</hi><hi>put to them, &amp; which, of course, disclosed the range &amp; character of their "preparation." </hi><hi rend="underline">The one matter on which the candidates were instructed was the Altar, &amp; the instruction was marked by the crudest simplicity</hi><hi>. They certainly could </hi><hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi> say "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Creed, The Lord's Prayer, &amp; the Ten Commandments" in the vulgar tongue: &amp; certainly had only been "further instructed" in the Church Catechism so far as that formulary gave a foundation for the crude sacramentalism which had been drilled into them.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>