<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lionel came with me to Darlington, where I caught the early train, &amp; travelled to King's Cross in the luxury of an unshared carriage. The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi>" has an account of an astonishing conference of Young Communists held in Manchester. It would be laughable were it not so profoundly sad to read of the absurdities of the children. By a significant coincidence, the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" reports the embarrassment caused to the Soviet Government by the myriads of diseased &amp; undisciplined children, which are now requiring some kind of treatment by the State.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After leaving my bags in Park Lane, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and there found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Buckle</hi><persName xml:id="322"></persName><hi>. He spoke of the dinner given to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wood</hi><hi> by his 3 colleges &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">Eton</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="underline">Christ Church</hi><hi>, &amp; </hi><hi rend="underline">All Souls</hi><hi> &#8211; &amp; wondered at my absence. I said that I had deliberately kept away, lest my presence should bring an incongruous factor into the function. In view of my "strained relations" with his father, to whom he is said to be devoted, I thought he might be glad not to have me there. Otherwise, I would gladly have joined the party, for I like him well, &amp; none the worse for being a good son. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Buckle</hi><hi> said that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Oman</hi><persName xml:id="2141"></persName><hi> had commented on </hi><hi rend="bold">[131] </hi><hi>the fact that of the six clerical fellows, or ex&#8211;fellows of All Souls, who are now living, one was Archbishop of York, another Bishop of Durham, a third Bishop of Gloucester, and two of the remaining three were Headmasters respectively of Eton and Winchester. It is, perhaps, rather a notable record.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I went to the Hair&#8211;dresser, &amp; was duly discipline. As I was returning to the Club, I fell in with John Murray, who spoke about the projected "double wedding" of the Murray sisters. He said that there were grave superstitions against double weddings, which he was rather surprized to note had been either unknown or ignored.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At 4 p.m. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Daly had an interview with me in the Club. He will be an accession to the diocese, if he is as good as his "references" affirm!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Then I walked to Burlington House, &amp; saw the Sargent pictures. They include the portraits of a portentous number of rich Jewesses! I like his drawings much better than his paintings.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Evening papers announce the illness of H.R.H., &amp; the consequent cancelling of her engagement to lay the foundation stone at Sunderland on Ash Wednesday.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I dined in Park Lane. Mine hostess had a small party for cards &#8211; Lord &amp; Lady Islington and young Shannon. We had some interesting talk during &amp; after dinner. I was interested in the remark of our junior &#8211; "What I hear everywhere from men of my own age, who probably wouldn't say it to you is, How I wish I </hi><hi rend="underline">could</hi><hi> be a Catholick !" Probably it </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi><hi> the case that Protestantism has a very unattractive aspect to his generation &#8211; so arid, so divided, so uncertain, so unlovely. The Church of England has neither the intellectual strength of Protestantism, nor the almost overpowering historical impressiveness of Papistry. It halts between two opinions, and never continues in one stay. The marvel is that the poor thing continues to live at all! Is it only the sheer weight of hereditary prejudice, reinforced by the coarse argument of personal advantage, that keeps me an Anglican, and an Anglican Bishop? Papistry is, of course, clearly impossible for a man of my temperament &amp; training: and any form of Nonconformity is quite obviously out of the question. For me, the issue in my remaining an Anglican, is necessarily identical with the issue of my remaining a Christian. And how can I contemplate turning my back on Christ after all these years?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>