<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1097</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m., using the form issued by the Archbishops.<note xml:id="406" n="1"></note> Very few communicants, &amp; I myself rather overwhelmed by the consciousness of my own failure. S. Paul's fear that "after having preached to others he himself should be rejected" was a feeble sentiment compared with the dread which clouds my own mind when I reflect on myself. "<hi rend="underline">O give me the comfort of Thy help again: &amp; stablish me with Thy free spirit</hi>."</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Was the trial sore?</p>
         <p>Temptation sharp? Thank God a second time!</p>
         <p>Why comes temptation but for man to meet</p>
         <p>And master and make crouch beneath his foot,</p>
         <p>And so be pedestaled in triumph? Pray</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">Lead us into no such temptations, Lord</hi>!"</p>
         <p>Yea, but, O Thou whose servants are the bold,</p>
         <p>Lead such temptations by the head and hair,</p>
         <p>Reluctant dragons, up to who dares fight,</p>
         <p>That so he may do battle and have praise!<note xml:id="405" n="2"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>I attended Mattins, and read some of the intercessions after the third collect. The editor of the local paper came to ask for my MS., &amp; to explain that he lost money when I sent anything <hi rend="underline">directly</hi> to the "Yorkshire Post"!!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The meeting in the Market–place was fairly successful. There was a considerable gathering, &amp; the speeches were, I think, both audible &amp; well–received</hi><hi rend="italic">. I spoke at more length than I had intended, but <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham's</persName> absence rather emphasized my speech. On the fringe of the crowd I caught sight of <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName>, beaming sympathetically.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked to the station, &amp; met <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arriving from Cheltenham. The train, timed to arrive at 6.23 p.m., was 20 minutes late. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> arrived from Blanchland to spend the week–end. After dinner I read the account of the immortal Chadband from 'Bleak House'.    </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
