<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1021</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The day was damp and chilly to start with, but it improved steadily &amp; by lunch time the sun shone brilliantly. The afternoon &amp; evening were calm &amp; beautiful. I attended Mattins and Evensong. <persName xml:id="2918"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Capt. Apperley</hi></persName> came to lunch. Also <persName xml:id="1916"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Morgan</hi></persName> who hopes to continue at school for the Michaelmas term also, and evidently assumes that we shall find the money! <hi rend="bold underline">That is the worst of helping boys: it is impossible to limit the liability</hi>. We &#8211; <persName xml:id="3223"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gaisford</hi></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I &#8211; motored to Sunderland, and there I preached in St Gabriel's church, where the Dedication Festival was being observed. <persName xml:id="4304"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lasbrey</hi></persName> the Vicar, is a young man, &amp; looks delicate. <persName xml:id="4104"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Allwork</hi></persName>, the Curate, was ordained in the Cathedral 3 years ago, &amp; is an old Dunelmian. Both men gave me an impression of ardour &amp; sincerity. There was a very large congregation. The service was of an unusual type. A large surpliced choir led the singing, which was heartily congregational, but there were no candles on the altar, and the "North End" was taken. I preached from <hi rend="underline">S. Mark XI. 17</hi> "<hi rend="underline">He taught, &amp; said unto them, Is it not written, My house shall be called a house of prayer for all the nations? But ye have made it a den of robbers</hi>". The sermon was perhaps, too severe in form for such a congregation, but they listened with close attention. I was interested in finding that these young clergymen appeared sympathetic with the notion of exchanging pulpits with Nonconformists. The leaven works, though slowly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I succeeded in writing a few letters during the day viz: to <persName xml:id="3128">Arthur</persName>, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2056">Elsie</persName>. </hi><persName xml:id="590"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Watkins</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> completed his preaching as "canon in residence", for next Sunday, being Whitsunday is a "Dean's Day" by statute. His delivery is so bad (combining, I think, all the known faults of English preachers in an intense form) that his substance doesn't for the most part reach the congregation at all; but my stall was near enough to the pulpit to make it possible for me to hear most of it, &amp; truly it was very sorry drivel, mere rant &amp; rhodomontade. It is very unfortunate that he will insist upon choosing his residence months in full term, so that the unhappy school boys have the full benefit of his pulpit ministrations!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
