<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">975</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yesterday <persName xml:id="2814">President Wilson</persName> made his statement to the Senate in circumstances of the utmost popular excitement. He announced America's entry into the War without limitation of action. The speech was nobly conceived and admirably expressed. If it can find entrance into Germany, it ought to waken whatever sentiments of reason &amp; justice yet linger there. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He differentiated the nation from its government most clearly &amp; impressively</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">A tract on democracy issued from the White House in the course of a War with the last of the autocrats, and leading up to the declaration that the greatest Republic of all history (at least in scale &amp; power) has itself resolved to draw the sword, will have many readers. I must needs think that the discredit which has fallen upon Monarchy generally will have its effect on our own: and that the most innocent of Sovereigns will share the suspicion which now attaches to the whole class. A sign of the tendency in this direction is a letter on the front page of the "Times" calling for an end to foreign marriages for our princes. I have long desired to see the P. of W. marry an English girl.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
