<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1048</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I presided at a meeting of Chapter. We appointed a Committee (Dean, <persName xml:id="590">Sub&#8211;dean</persName>, Treasurer, <persName xml:id="2806">Bailey</persName>) to consider the question of coal supplies for the College, and to take such action as might seem advisable.</p>
         <p>I fell in with Smith the forester. He is now employed in afforestation work in Yorkshire where he has control of a number of German prisoners. He said that his first batch were Bavarians &amp; Saxons, and gave no trouble, but recently 80 Prussians had arrived, &amp; they had caused much friction and discontent. After lunch we travelled to Ripon <hi rend="bold underline">to spend the week with <persName xml:id="2069">Sir John</persName> and <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Lady Barran</persName></hi>. The train was running over with khaki&#8211;clad officers &amp; men, &amp; the streets of Ripon "crawled" with them. We were met at the station, &amp; motored to Sawley Hall where we arrived in the midst of a tea&#8211;party. Afterwards mine host &amp; one of the ladies carried me off to a little lake in the woods, where they caught two trout. The beauty of the scene was most restful &amp; refreshing. We dined pleasantly, and had much conversation, in which I find myself hampered by the state of my throat. After dinner we had coffee in the garden. The rhododendrons have passed their full glory, but they are still magnificent. This house stands about 500 feet above sea&#8211;level, &amp; commands a noble prospect in which, when the weather is clear, the towers of York Minster can be distinguished.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
