<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1053</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received the Holy Communion in S. Gregory's Chapel, and wrote a short article for the "Sunday Pictorial" on "The War and Convention". Then I attended the Committee of Chapter on the subject of coal supplies for the college during the coming winter. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came in to show me a letter he had received from the shipping firm, and I kept him to lunch, &amp; gave him a copy of "Rob Roy". The boy is certainly taking a great place in my thoughts, but he will be off to sea, if all goes well, by the beginning of August. <persName xml:id="2360">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Soltau&#8211;Simmons</persName> came to lunch. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to Dryburn, &amp; had tea with the <persName xml:id="3512">Darwins</persName><persName xml:id="3813"></persName>, with whom were a relative, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lloyd&#8211;Baker, and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ball. On our return to the Deanery, I found a letter from <persName xml:id="1611">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hider</persName>, one of the choirmen of <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, Westminster, telling me that his son, <persName xml:id="1613">Leslie</persName>, had been killed in battle. <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to <persName xml:id="1173">Temple</persName>, asking him to send me a ticket for his much&#8211;advertised meeting in the Queen's Hall on July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, adding that I thought he &amp; his friends were altogether on the wrong tack when they sought "Liberty in the Church" along the way of Disestablishment</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p></body></text></TEI>
        
