<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[102]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1074</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have promised to lecture to the Newcastle "Lit &amp; Phil" on "The Art of Biography". It confesses my present embarrassment over the "Life" w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">in a moment of rashness I undertook. At least I shall clear up my mind on the point of biographical method. Among the ancients I may consider Suetonius' "Cœsare": Tacitus' "Agricola": Plutarch's "Lives": in the Middle Ages there are some hagiologies &#8211; Adamnan's Life of Columba, &amp; Bede's Life of S. Cuthbert, would have a local interest. Then Joinville's S. Louis: Cavendish's "Wolsey": &amp; Bacon's "Henry VII", would bring me to the "golden age" of biography and auto&#8211;biography. Walton's Lives: Strype's &amp;c. Heylyn's Land, Hacket's "Williams". A distinction must be made between the compositions of contemporaries which provide first&#8211;hand materials to later biographers: &amp; the purely literary compositions of the latter: also between biographies which were designed with an edifying or polemical purpose; and biographies which were directed to the single object of portraying an individual. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The bulky records, stuffed with letters, &amp; filling volumes, which now pass as biographies have hardly any claim to the character of works of art. They are rather blue&#8211;books than literature.</hi>
         </p>
<p>I carried <persName xml:id="2161">Ruth's</persName> portmanteau to Holborn Victoria Station, &amp; there parted with her &amp; with her <persName xml:id="383">father</persName>. They returned to Canterbury, &amp; I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; wrote letters. There I had some speech with <persName xml:id="645">Sir Courtney Ilbert</persName>. He told me that he was Fellow of Balliol &amp; Tutor of Corpus, &amp; that he tutored <persName xml:id="228">Sir W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Anson</persName>. He said that in the H. of C. the Warden made no great figure, but that he was very popular among the members. I returned to the Deanery for lunch, &amp; afterwards walked &amp; talked with <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> in the Temple Gardens, where batches of recruits were being drilled. We walked on to the Club, where I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Radford</persName> and <persName xml:id="2936">Jack Boden</persName>.<note xml:id="398" n="1"></note> We all dined with <persName xml:id="2712">Miss Mundella</persName> very pleasantly. The party consisted of the <persName xml:id="2688">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, <persName xml:id="1181" display="no">Lord Channing</persName>, <persName xml:id="4442">^Whittuck^</persName>, <persName xml:id="977">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Buchanan</persName>, <persName xml:id="831">Prof: Baillie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4116">his wife</persName>. I took down Lady C. &amp; talked to her both during dinner, &amp; afterwards. We were back in the Deanery by 11.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
