<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">966</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">My first business was to return to the <orgName xml:id="37">City Templars</orgName> the cheque for &#x00A3;15.15.0, which was handed to me enclosed in a letter last night. I did this politely, but peremptorily</hi><hi rend="italic">. Then I went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>. On my way I fell in with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="344">Sir Henry Craik</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, who assured me pleasantly that I had "given much pain to my friends" by my proceedings yesterday! I went on my way reflecting that I c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> hardly pinch my liberty to the measure of a Scottish Tory's prejudices. I went to the barber, &amp; (though the wind was mortally keen) I had my locks shorn. Then I joined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and we went together to lunch with <persName xml:id="2244">Sir John</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2708">Lady Struthers</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="566">Fleming</persName> &amp; his <persName xml:id="4224">wife</persName> were there. Our conversation turned on that most versatile of men,</hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="984">John Buchan</persName></hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">. F. said that he was one of his elders, and that he retires at frequent intervals into "rest&#8211;cures", which, however, he uses for the composition of his romances</hi><hi rend="italic">. After lunch, we returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, "took up our carriages", and took our departure for Eastbourne, where we arrived soon after 5 p.m., &amp; proceeded at once to the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Park Gates Hotel</hi><hi rend="italic">, where we were to be the guests of <persName xml:id="642">Sir Peile</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="925">Lady Thompson</persName>. This is a new hotel, built by our own host a year ago, and furnished by the tasteful skill of the long lad, his son <persName xml:id="2564">Miles</persName>, who is now a 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lieut: somewhere in Essex. The furniture reflects credit on Miles, who deserves a larger sphere in his artistic efforts.</hi>
         </p>
         
         </body></text></TEI>
