<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1011</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>This day being <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> Birthday we went both together to the Gregory Chapel, and there received the Holy Communion. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. The morning was spent in going through the MS. of <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes'</persName> book, &amp; in writing to him a series of criticisms, mostly petty. I wrote to <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Radford</persName> condoling with her on <persName xml:id="2221" display="no">her brother's</persName> death: and to <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3542">Norman Henderson</persName> from whom I received a pleasant letter, contained one passage of special interest</hi>. He had described the disabling of his aeroplane by a German shell, &amp; then proceeded:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Somehow or other as I came whirling down through space at about 100 miles per hour, knowing an inevitable crash at the bottom, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I had a feeling God was with me, &amp; I think I was right"</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
<p><persName xml:id="923"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Newsom</hi></persName>&amp; his wife came to see us. He dined with <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>: she remained with us. I had some talk with him. He desires to take a liberal course, but he is not very clear&#8211;headed, &amp; his traditions incline him to the "High Church" faction. He is a good fellow in the main. There are rumours that the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> meditates resigning his bishoprick, having drifted into an impossible situation over this matter of 'Reservation'. But there is little likelihood of any such proceeding on his part, though it is hard to perceive a way out of his difficulties. <persName xml:id="2068"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Cobham</hi></persName> wrote civilly in reply to my letter, &amp; <persName xml:id="359"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sanday</hi></persName> sent me an interesting account of <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName> as an undergraduate. About 7.30 p.m. when the telegraph office was closed, I received a telegram with answer prepaid to the following effect: &#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Great Thanksgiving Service commemorating Battle Jutland London Opera House Sunday afternoon June third Admiral &amp; Lady Jellicoe Admiral Sims United States Navy Irish Guards Bank taking part will you kindly consent to be principal speaker <persName xml:id="4298">Admiral King Hall</persName> <orgName xml:id="300">Sailors Society</orgName> telegraph Sailordom London."</hi></p>
         </div>
<p>I particularly wished to be here on Trinity Sunday, when the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> will be here. Yet it is difficult to refuse to go since I <hi rend="underline">can</hi> go.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
