<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[14]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">979</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Victorious and reigning Christ, stretch forth Thine Hand, and lift me from the deeps of sin &amp; failure. Heal by Thy cleansing touch the foul diseases of my soul, and draw me to Thee with power which I cannot resist. Thou knowest all my fault, my folly, and my infinite distress of mind. Thy compassions fail not: Thy purpose is unchanging: Thy Might is supreme. Have mercy on me, I beseech Thee, and in Thy Light let me see Light. Let a ray of Thine Easter glory shine inwards on my spirit, &amp; purge it of shadow and sin, that I may worship Thee this day in joy &amp; purity.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated at 8. a.m. There seemed a fair number of communicants, among whom the choir&#8211;boys were conspicuous. But there were no soldiers, which disappointed me, though of course they may have been on duty. The weather, which had been dull to start with, improved as the day wore on. By Mattins the sun was shining brightly. There were but few communicants at the Choral Eucharist. I preached one of the sermons published in <ref xml:id="8">"Godly Union &amp; Concord"</ref>. <persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName> came in afterward. I gave him <ref xml:id="1013">"The Fortunes of Nigel"</ref>, as he leaves this term. Then I showed Lady Robinson the Library. I attended Evensong. The <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> and <persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName> came to tea: and afterwards the <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkners</persName><persName xml:id="3554"></persName> called. I had a long talk with M. F. about the careers of the Choir&#8211;boys.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
