<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1075</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="4442">Whittuck</persName> said that he had been with <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName> at Eton; that Anson was not a prominent person in the school: that his later success was a surprise to his contemporaries: that his law&#8211;books were admirable as text&#8211;books because his special ability lay in teaching, of which he was very fond; but that they nowhere disclosed the range of <persName xml:id="403">Dicey's</persName> knowledge, or the power of Dicey's mind. I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, and spent the morning in writing letters to Gilbert, <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, and <persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName>. From the last I had received a long &amp; informing letter on the shipping interest. I lunched in the Club, and then fell to reading the Hibbert Journal, which contains several articles criticising <hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="614">Sir Oliver Lodge</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The foolish book "Raymond"<note xml:id="343" n="1"></note> is said to be selling like wildfire, and becoming the Bible of a new religion. <persName xml:id="3581">Barnes</persName>, the Master of the <orgName xml:id="79">Temple</orgName>, had much talk with me on matters ecclesiastical</hi><hi rend="italic">. I walked back to the Deanery for tea, whereat <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> had drawn together several of our friends.</hi> <persName xml:id="4229">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gamble</persName> has some circumstantial ghost stories from 20 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>. <persName xml:id="4427">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> George Trevelyan</persName>, <persName xml:id="4013">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Roby Thorpe</persName> &amp; her daughter, <persName xml:id="2712">Miss Mundella</persName>, <persName xml:id="4128">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Belloc Lowndes</persName> &amp; others were there. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I dined with <persName xml:id="290">Charlie Parker</persName> at the Automobile Club, and afterwards went to the Apollo Theatre, &amp; saw a performance of "Within the Lines". It was a pleasant &amp; amusing play, of which the interest was well&#8211;sustained throughout, and the d&#x00E9;no&ucirc;ement, unsuspected &amp; effective. Kitty &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> had been in the pit, and joined us outside the theatre. We walked home to the Deanery and got there about 11.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "Church Times" has a rather violently worded, but anonymous, letter denouncing the Dean of Durham as the apostle of Erastianism &amp; so forth. This presumably is a little bit of "tuning up" before the orchestra of autonomists strikes up in the Queen's Hall on Monday. It is plain enough that the determined clique, to which we owe the Report of the Archbishops' Committee, is resolved at all hazards to press forward during the distracting interval of the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
