<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">965</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Holy Communion in the Abbey. <persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie</persName> celebrated. Then we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, <persName xml:id="2109" display="no">Miss Pearce</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1820">Canon Charles</persName>) went to the <orgName xml:id="37">"City Temple"</orgName> for the fell purpose of kicking down one old rotten convention which blocks the way of Christian fellowship. There was a vast congregation which filled the building from floor to topmost gallery. The Service, which was semi&#8211;liturgical, was </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">conducted by <persName xml:id="4466">Principal Garvie</persName> of Hampstead</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was devotional &amp; even dignified. Even the extemporaneous prayer was inoffensive. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then came the sermon. It took 45 minutes in delivery</hi><hi rend="italic">. In the afternoon </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, &amp; baptized Miranda Catherine Tallents, Bridget's daughter</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; then went back to Little Cloisters, and lay </hi><hi rend="italic underline">perdu</hi><hi rend="italic"> until it was time to go forth again to the "City Temple". The building was again crowded to its utmost capacity. D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="393">Shakespeare</persName>, the President of the <orgName xml:id="199">Free Church Council</orgName>, conducted the service. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I preached for 35 minutes. <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty Inge</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1178" display="no">Clarence Stock</persName> were present, &amp; expressed themselves with their wonted enthusiasm</hi><hi rend="italic">. Thus was concluded a memorable day, which must needs have consequences, but whether for good, or for ill, God only knows. I had an amused consciousness of triumphant paradox in </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">wearing the "Aaronical vestments" in the midst of the "Brownists"</hi><hi rend="i bold">!<note xml:id="342" n="2"></note></hi> <hi rend="italic">It was, I think on reflection, the right thing to do in the interest of my purpose.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Shakespeare told me that he conceived the idea of attempting to unify the Nonconformists at Portsmouth, when he heard my address to the Congregational Union there</hi><hi rend="italic">. That address was subsequently <ref xml:id="633">published</ref>. I remember that I was much disappointed at the time because it seemed to have failed of any result: but I may have been mistaken.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> R. J. Campbell came into the vestry after the morning sermon</hi><hi rend="italic">, and spoke to me. She had come up from Birmingham, perhaps expecting that some reference w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be made to her <persName xml:id="392">husband</persName>. But I eschewed him altogether, and made no allusion to his <persName xml:id="4342">successor</persName>, who yet lingers on the other side of the Atlantic torpedo&#8211;bound.</hi>
         </p>
         
         </body></text></TEI>
