<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1063</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful morning, bright and fresh. If only this cloud of carnage were lifted from our lives, how happy we might still be! But now it seems a base thing to be at home in security, while the young are being sent to the shambles abroad. <hi rend="underline">Usquequo, Domine</hi> [for how long Lord]? <hi rend="bold underline">My letter on <ref xml:id="930">"The Clergy &amp; Military Service"</ref> appears in the "Spectator", where it is accompanied by three other letters, of which two are from Chaplains strongly supporting my view of the question, and one, which is anonymous, sets forth the "priestly" view</hi>. I cannot believe that the latter can be other than repulsive to most healthy&#8211;minded Englishmen.</p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. Service very restful and yet moving. After breakfast, we motored to West Hartlepool, and I preached in S. Paul's church to a large congregation. After lunch <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> brought me the form of apprenticeship which had been sent to <persName xml:id="4344">his father</persName>. It seemed to need an amendment, so I decided to return it myself to <persName xml:id="3655">Lawrence Holt</persName>. I attended Evensong, and afterwards motored to Bearpark, &amp; preached in the parish church. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3572">Edgar Dobbie</persName> went with me. I gave him <ref xml:id="931">"Redgauntlet"</ref></hi> as a <hi rend="underline">douceur</hi> for carrying my bag. The High Sheriff, <persName xml:id="3718">Cyril Liddell</persName>, came to dinner: &amp; afterwards <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> came in. He is rather depressing about the War, of which indeed he says that he can see no probable end for years to come. I walked with these good people as far as the gate, &amp; saw them safely out of the College. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
