<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1108</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">That foolish boy <persName xml:id="2118" display="no">Charles Fairlie Cunningham</persName>, having become a Papist has grown weary of Papistry, and now meditates returning to the C of E as "an Anglican and a Catholic". He writes to tell me of his purpose, and to solicit my approval</hi>. I replied thus:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Charlie,</p>
         <p>Of course, as you know, I am myself a Protestant, &amp; must needs think the Roman Catholic version of Christianity deeply mistaken, but it seems to me greatly more reasonable than the hybrid "Catholicism" which is current among those who used to be called "High" Churchmen in the C of E &amp; therefore if by describing yourself as "an Anglican <hi rend="underline">and</hi> a Catholic", you mean that you purpose to join yourself to the Romanising Anglicans, I think you had better stay where you are. Sooner or later you will find that the C of E <hi rend="underline">must</hi>, as a Reformed or Protestant Church, express a version of Christianity which is not what men call "Catholic", though truly it is far more deserving the name than any other.</p>
         <p>But, my dear boy, do not be in too great a hurry to change your religious description. It is a very serious thing to move from one church to another. If I were in your place, I should postpone any decision for another year, &amp; in the interval try to put all controversy on one side, &amp; devote my whole mind to doing my duty as a good Christian in the Army. Say your prayers, attend Mass, make your Confession, &amp; receive the Sacrament, but don't argue over the controversial matters. These can wait until the War is over, &amp; you will be in a far better state to come to a final decision after a year of steady work at your duty. With very good wishes,</p>
         <p>I am affectionately yours.</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson </p>
         </div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[148]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="3655">Mr Holt</persName> telling me that <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> had been appointed to the S.S. Titan, and that he would probably sail next week for the Far East. In the course of the morning George himself came to say goodbye. </hi>We talked together and then we knelt down &amp; prayed together. I gave him my photograph, &amp; a letter of introduction which he could present to the clergy in the foreign ports where his ship would land, &amp; so we parted with much affection.</p>
         <p>Rain fell almost continuously for great part of the day. While Evensong was proceeding in the Galilee, a violent thunderstorm broke over Durham, &amp; raged for about two hours. The lightning flashes were frequent, &amp; the thunder seemed incessant.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
