<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1126</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The sun shone brightly in intervals between cloudy &amp; dark times, &amp; from a stormy sky. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were about a score of communicants from whom I missed the familiar figure of <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName>, who is now, I suppose, tossing about in the Bay, &amp; probably very sick! <persName xml:id="3496"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dennett</hi></persName> is back from the holidays, &amp; with the return of the choir, we move one more stage towards the normal. After breakfast I wrote a letter of condolence to <persName xml:id="2540"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir William Osler</hi></persName>, and a letter to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> answering his that was torpedoed &amp; belated. I attended Mattins, &amp; heard from <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> a sermon on the hackneyed text, "Are not Abanah &amp; Pharpar etc." which reminded me overpoweringly of the oratory of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Chadband<hi rend="italic">! Yet I suspect that the people thought </hi>^<hi rend="italic">it</hi>^ <hi rend="italic">rather uncommonly fine! It is simply torture to be forced to sit &amp; listen to the greatest &amp; most urgent problems of this tragical time </hi>^<hi rend="italic">being</hi>^<hi rend="italic"> dealt with in the pulpit as just so much good stuff for effecting a "thrill", and to know the while that the receptivity of the people, (that priceless &amp; most precarious asset of the teacher) is being rapidly destroyed, in fact that the pitch is being spoiled in advance of the match!</hi> 
<persName xml:id="2817"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi></persName> appeared at Evensong with the little <persName xml:id="4206"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Feversham</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4311"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Serena Lumley</hi></persName>, &amp; an anaemic young man, the boy's tutor. She brought them into the Deanery, &amp; had tea, after which I shewed them the house, library &amp; cathedral. Then she suggested that I should return with them to Lumley to dine &amp; sleep. This I did, not being able to find a plausible excuse for declining. The fineness of the evening shewed Lumley Castle to perfection. We mounted to the battlements, &amp; enjoyed a noble prospect. After dinner, Lady Londonderry proposed a walk in the moon&#8211;light, &amp; took us to a view&#8211;point at some little distance from the Castle from which the great building had a most romantic appearance. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Scarborough</persName> not inaptly calls this view Camelot. We had some conversation about War memorials in the Cathedral. Lady Londonderry definitely offered to give a processional cross of silver in memory of her <persName xml:id="2816">husband</persName>, who was at one time Mayor of Durham. I told her to write to me formally.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
