<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1018</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright morning. I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. All the <persName xml:id="1898">Canons</persName><persName xml:id="2798"></persName><persName xml:id="473"></persName><persName xml:id="2803"></persName><persName xml:id="2785"></persName> were present, and a fair number of communicants: including <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName>, &amp; two other choirboys. The attendance of choirboys on this day for Communion is, I think, a new departure: but it is, perhaps, a good one. I worked at the sermon for next Sunday until it was time to go to the Cathedral for the Choral Eucharist. Only six persons communicated beside the Celebrant. The set of the tide in the direction of the Mass is very strong. <persName xml:id="3497"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Gaisford</hi></persName> lunched with me. She is full of political gossip, mostly, I should judge, worthless. I attended Evensong, &amp; then attended a meeting of the Freemasons' Lodge, where no less than two hours were wonderfully expended while thus engaged. <persName xml:id="3223"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Gaisford</hi></persName> arrived, &amp; when I returned to the Deanery, I found him engaged in assisting <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Driver in divers gardening activities. He is now out of military employment, for the day of the "dug&#8211;out" is over, &amp; there is a plethora of wounded officers from the front, for whom it is requisite to find employment at home, &amp; who are fully equipped with knowledge of war in its most recent developments. The evening was wasted in talk, not very interesting or informative.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
