<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1073</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We left Carlton&#8211;on&#8211;Trent by the early train (8.57 a.m.), and travelled to King's Cross very comfortably without change, arriving at 12.30 noon. We reached the S. Paul's Deanery in good time for lunch. <persName xml:id="2161">Ruth</persName> &amp; Miss Ward were there. Also <persName xml:id="383">Archdeacon Spooner</persName>. After lunch I walked to Westminster, and, after having my hair cut, went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; there found the <persName xml:id="31">Bishop of Exeter</persName>, with whom I had much talk. He said that the county was opposed to the division of the see: that the extreme sacerdotalism of some of the clergy caused Nonconformity to gain ground: <hi rend="bold underline">that many Nonconformist ministers applied for Ordination, but not, he suspected, from the highest motives</hi>. He liked visiting the country parishes. The Cathedral was unduly weak. He wanted an effective &amp; efficient Dean, &amp; would like to have <persName xml:id="3584">Edward Lyttelton</persName>. This would certainly be regarded as another family job. I observed with regret that he referred to the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName> with a deference which showed but too plainly that he has fallen within the governing ring! I had some talk with the <persName xml:id="356">Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's</persName>, who looks very ill. Then I walked back to the Deanery.</p>
         <p>There came to dinner a varied &amp; pleasant company. <persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName> &amp; his sister, <persName xml:id="4424">Lady Tollemache</persName>, <persName xml:id="3706">Bailey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3707">his wife</persName> (sister of <persName xml:id="777">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Alington</persName>), <persName xml:id="1261">Violet Carruthers</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3876">her husband</persName>, Micklejohn &#8211; these with the house&#8211;party were sufficient entertainment. <hi rend="bold underline">I had a good deal of conversation with Lord Haldane, who was very interesting</hi>: also with Violet Carruthers, who now frequents the <orgName xml:id="37">Temple</orgName>, &amp; finds comfort in the ministrations of the current Master &#8211; <persName xml:id="3581">Barnes</persName>. She protests that she is abundantly happy in her married life, &amp; has never had a cross&#8211;word with her husband. This is well enough. Ruth is vivacious &amp; pleasing as always. <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> is triumphantly successful as a hostess. The Archdeacon, her father, regards his daughters with a demure satisfaction, which discloses their merits through the medium of his taciturnity!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
