<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1067</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName> replies to my letter about <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> by sending back the indenture to have the inserted clause cancelled, and explaining the reason. I suppose it must be all right, so I caused the requisite change to be made, and returned the indenture. I finished the Eton sermon: wrote a number of cheques for quarterly bills: &amp; attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. <persName xml:id="3652">Colonel Herne</persName> &amp; his wife came to lunch: also <persName xml:id="3487">Miss Cooper</persName>, &amp; her one&#8211;armed <persName xml:id="4174">brother</persName>. The good man has come out of the war with the loss of an arm, but he is cheerful, &amp; becoming very self&#8211;sufficing. I lent him a volume of Symond's Italian Renaissance. After Evensong I went to Bow School, &amp; looked on at a cricket match between the Cathedral Choir, &amp; the boys of Bow School. The latter were altogether over&#8211;matched.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Before going to bed, I read through an effective though brief criticism of <persName xml:id="614">Sir Oliver Lodge's</persName> "Raymond" (<ref xml:id="932">"Reflections on 'Raymond', an appreciation and analysis"</ref> by Walter Cook &#8211; Grant Richards.). It conveys a vivid impression of the credulity &amp; mental debasement into which a man of science can fall, when he allows himself to abandon the scientific habit, &amp; dabbles in that amalgam of fraud &amp; folly, Spiritualism. How any self&#8211;respecting man can tolerate the unspeakable gibberish of mediums, especially in connexion with their own relations, baffles me. Yet it is said that this book "Raymond" is becoming the "Bible" of a new religion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
