<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1061</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>This is S. Peter's Day. The good folk at Peterborough are keeping some kind of festival in memory of the foundation of that great church 800 years ago. Three years ago thousands would have thrilled at the thought of that long history, but now, with a world falling into ruins about us, who cares? The 'British Weekly' professes to have consulted the leading authorities, English, French &amp; American, on the probable duration of the War. The conclusion is sufficiently depressing. On the most favourable view, the War will continue for two more years! If that conclusion be sound, the War will end, not in victory drawing a period of peace in its train, but in a peace which opens the chapter of revolution &amp; "servile" wars at home.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
<p>I received the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> celebrated. The post brought me a long &amp; interesting letter from <persName xml:id="2841"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi></persName>. He encloses a pencil copy of a note addressed by the Senior Chaplain to a chaplain named <persName xml:id="4423">Todd</persName>, whom he describes as 'distinctly broad church, but perhaps a little apt to rush in where angels fear to tread'. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Todd's offence appears to have been caused by 'certain articles in the Balkan news' which Ernest had not read. The letter is curt &amp; explicit enough:</p>
         <div type="letter">
<p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Todd</p>
<p>I regret that I am unable to accept your renewal of contract with the British Salonika Force.</p>
<p>The reason is that <persName xml:id="4334">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Moreton</persName>, Senior C. of E. Chaplain B.S.F. refuses to recommend your re&#8211;engagement, <hi rend="underline">on account of your religious views</hi>.</p>
<p>Passage to England will be arranged for you in due course.</p>
<p>Yours very truly</p>
<p>William Keelinge P.C.</p>
         </div>         
<p><hi rend="italic">Ernest writes: "I am sending you a copy of a letter sent to our chaplain here by the Principal Chaplain who peculiarly enough is a Roman Catholic under whom C. of E. chaplains serve. For a matter of fact I understand that this R.C. is a far more liberal fellow than many of his C. of E. subordinates who are mostly very narrow "catholicks" of the S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic">Charles I school! M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Todd feels very badly about being sent home like this, &amp; in discussing the matter with me, I advised him to seek your counsel …. Officers &amp; men are very sorry to lose M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Todd for he has done good work here. He is sincere &amp; energetic. I have not met a better or more practical military chaplain since I have been out here". All this has rather an unpleasing appearance. Probably Todd is a fool, and the persecuting fellow&#8211;chaplains fanaticks of the now familiar type.</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3178"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi></persName> came to lunch. As <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had gone to Newcastle we were alone, &amp; had much talk. After lunch the Committee met, &amp; sate for two hours. We had an engineering employee named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scope</hi> as a witness. He was interesting enough while he described proposed methods for determining wages, but when he proceeded to set forth what he conceived the clergy could do, he was conventional and unhelpful.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
