<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[165]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1124</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3733"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stuckey Coles</hi></persName> sent me a very interesting and useful letter in response to my appeal for materials for the <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref>. He suggested that I should write to the <persName xml:id="4242">Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">B. S. Hack</hi></persName>, who was chaplain of the Oxford Prison while the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> was Chairman of the Quarter&#8211;Sessions, &amp; could tell me about the Warden's generous concern for prisoners. I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hack this morning. I sent what I had written about the Wardenship election in 1881 to <persName xml:id="22">W. P. Ker</persName> in order that he might pass his judgment. <persName xml:id="552"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="553">his wife</persName> lunched here, &amp; came back for tea afterwards. He said that he had private reason for thinking that the War would end this year, but he did not disclose what those reasons were. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. As I returned across the Prebends' Bridge, <hi rend="bold underline">I fell with six nice&#8211;looking Belgian girls of a superior class, &amp; found that they hailed from Alost, that their parents were in Belgium, &amp; that they were staying in Newcastle for a holiday. I shewed them the Deanery, and the Library</hi>, which greatly delighted them. I dined with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>. <persName xml:id="3805">Fearne</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3706">Bailey</persName> made up the party. Then I went home &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</p>
<p><persName xml:id="4107"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Anson</hi></persName> wrote to me to ask for "the historical instances in the XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century of the non&#8211;requirement of episcopal ordination in the Anglican Church". He said that he was writing "a popular essay on the subject from the same point of view for a book by C. H. Matthews". In reply I sent him a copy of the <ref xml:id="376">Lee Lecture</ref>, and added in a letter the fact that <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> had succeeded in unearthing the formal record of de Laune's institution to the parish of Redenhall. Thus confirming the statement of <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName>, which the Tractarians so persistently belittle. There is something odd about reverting to these old controversies in present circumstances, and yet one can go but a little way in religious discussion before one is brought up against them. Muddle&#8211;headedness and good feeling together may evade them for a time, but only for a time. Sooner or later they must be faced.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
