<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1060</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Manchester sermon. My morning post brought an ill&#8211;written &amp; ill&#8211;spelt ^letter^ from a miner (as I suppose) who signs himself George Britton, No 6 South Street, Langley Park, Durham. It is a rather wild screed of the usual Socialistic type. He encloses a newspaper cutting referring to <persName xml:id="166">Ingram's</persName> statement that &#x00A3;70,000 was annually wasted on Deans.<note xml:id="397" n="1"></note> The amount of the Dean of Durham's income appears to have deeply shocked him. This probably represents the main consequence of Ingram's speeches. They stir up appetite, and create a mass of unnecessary prejudice. The "Times" contains a very short and ineffective letter from <persName xml:id="1173">Temple</persName> declining controversy with me, &amp; parading the support of the <persName xml:id="1170">Master of Balliol</persName> &amp; the <persName xml:id="4188">Headmaster of Rugby</persName>. For other purposes these functionaries might carry weight, but neither has any knowledge or experience of ecclesiastical affairs. <persName xml:id="2709">Geoffrey Robinson</persName> wrote to say that I might make what I w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> of <persName xml:id="228">Anson's</persName> letters to the "Times", adding an expression of approval of my last letter to the "Times". I sent a subscription of one guinea together with a flatterous letter to the Fund for making a presentation to <persName xml:id="4260">Private Michael Heavyside V.C</persName>., the Durham miner. The money is probably wasted.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
