<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1084</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Just at breakfast time the syrens gave warning of an approaching air&#8211;raid. It was at first feared that this disturbance would prevent the holding of the Parade, for which considerable preparations had been made. The Parade was held, but many people were hindered from attending. However it was an excellent service. The soldiers filled most of the floor, &amp; the western gallery was full of their friends. I preached more extemporaneously than is my wont. The singing was very hearty. At Mattins I preached again. There was by no means a large congregation, but the raids have driven away the visitors, disbanded most of the schools, &amp; emptied many of the houses even of residents. <persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> motored from Birchington, &amp; attended both services. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> stayed to lunch at the Vicarage. She also visited the caverns underneath the garden.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After lunch I had an hour's talk with <persName xml:id="4371">Canon Pryor</persName>. He expressed himself with much vehemence on the practical uselessness of Evangelical Bishops. "They say you are going to Hereford", he observed. I laughed for that kind of fool&#8211;talk has played about my name for the last ten years.</hi> The General sent his car to convey us back to Birchington where we arrived about 3.30 p.m. I preached at the parish Church of Birchington at Evensong. There was quite a good congregation including a party of the officers to whom I had already preached at Margate. I asked the Vicar whether he intended to read the "cursing psalm",<note xml:id="402" n="1"></note> which was included in the psalms for the day. He decided to have the 108<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> psalm only, &amp; so announced to the congregation. I was really glad that the Psalmist's horrible imprecations were not forced on the notice of the men with whom I had been discussing "Reprisals" yesterday afternoon. I preached the sermon on Jacob's Dream, which has already been preached in England &amp; America no less than 10 times! The congregation were certainly very attentive, and I must needs indulge the hope that they were also edified.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
