<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1122</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>The morning post brought me pleasant letters from <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName>, who is waiting at Lamlash for a convoy, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi> who has received his well–merited promotion to the captaincy of his company, &amp; <persName xml:id="3542"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Norman</hi></persName>, who by way of assisting his recovery from nerve–shock is riding a motor–bicycle in the Isle of Wight! Also a letter from <persName xml:id="3655"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lawrence Holt</hi></persName> enclosing a very vivid narrative from the Master of one of his firm's ships which had been torpedoed or struck a mine. This with three requests to preach made up my whole "post" for this morning. I attended Mattins. While sitting at work in my study I was invaded by an irate parson in lay clothes who complained that he had not been allowed to enter the Galilee without paying 6<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> and on principle he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> pay nothing, etc., etc. I placated him, &amp; took him into the Galilee myself. This man was named <persName xml:id="4161"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carter</hi></persName>, &amp; is the vicar of S. Dionis, Fulham. <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarbrough</persName></hi> &amp; her daughter <persName xml:id="4311"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Serena</hi></persName> came to lunch, and <persName xml:id="3706"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bailey</hi></persName> joined us. The rain fell in torrents during the afternoon, so I abandoned my intention of going to Ramside. <persName xml:id="3813"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darwin</hi></persName> was at Evensong, &amp; came in to the Deanery afterwards &amp; talked with me for an hour. Then I tried to do something at the <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref>. <hi rend="italic">The "Times" is filled with grievous reports of damage to the crops by the great tempest and deluge of the last two days. It certainly is extraordinarily unfortunate that this year of all years the harvest should be ruined by the weather. The fanaticks will be pointing the moral that a Sabbath–breaking spring ensures a disastrous autumn. A foolish parson from Devonshire sends me a printed paper in which it is gravely affirmed that in order to win the war, there is one thing needful viz. the appointment of a day for Public Prayer! If one were a bishop, would it be considered necessary to treat that kind of nonsense with respect? I see that <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName> is organizing a great mission to the Munition workers of the Southwark Diocese, &amp; that a great company of bishops &amp; other clergy are announced to take part in it. Among these is the notorious <persName xml:id="3802">"Father" Paul Bull</persName>, who seems, in spite of everything, to be able to command entrance wherever he wills to go. It puzzles me greatly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
