<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>  	 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1148</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received a letter from <persName xml:id="4412">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Clair Tisdall</persName>, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's, Deal asking me to inaugurate a public movement to secure the abrogation of the legal exemption of ministers of religion from military service.<note xml:id="415" n="1"></note> I replied as follows:</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>September 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1917</p>
         <p>Dear D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Clair Tisdall,</p>
         <p>It needs no saying that I heartily approve the attitude disclosed in your letter, &amp;, if I do not think it wise to act on the suggestion it contains, you may be sure that my decision is solely due to practical considerations.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130">Archbishops</persName></persName> have blundered grievously, but they have "burned their boats", and will not, even if they could, go back on the course they have taken. It is too late to do anything now, &amp; the attempt would only provoke controversy &amp; to that extent do more harm.</p>
         <p>The Archbishop of York's letter in Saturday's "Times" will convince nobody who knows the facts, &amp; is one more example of the "tall talk" with which the Episcopal Bench is too fond of investing simple issues. Nor do I think I am the only English clergyman who resents deeply the assumption, more Roman than English, that the clergy ("priests") are not citizens, but a separate variety of Englishmen who are to be dealt with <hi rend="underline">indirectly</hi> "through their bishops". The assumption is offensive to civic self–respect and really unprecedented. Its adoption by the Episcopate goes far to explain the rapid fall in credit &amp; value of the English clergy. Let me say how deeply I sympathize with you in losing your sons, &amp; yet I could almost find it in my heart to envy them &amp; you. Your clerical son's view is not only sound in itself, but also shared by most clergymen of military age.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Sincerely yours</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p>
         </div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
