<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1093</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read another <persName xml:id="936">Gifford Lecture</persName> before breakfast. It is wonderfully comforting to find an admirably written philosophic justification of the assumptions of one's own theological position! <hi rend="bold underline">If I were beginning life again, I would go deep into philosophy, &amp; specialize in the Study of Comparative Religion. History is too rapidly becoming an affair of documentary specialists</hi>. I attended Mattins, &amp; then made an attempt to write a sermon for next Sunday, but with no success, for I am not really clear in my own mind as to what I ought to say. I attended Evensong, &amp; tried the experiment of a hymn. The piano from the Song School had been brought into the Gallilee [sic], &amp; the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> played. A lieutenant from the Headquarters at York came to make a report on our buildings with a view to their occupation by the military if necessity should arise. I dined with the <persName xml:id="3553">Mead&#8211;Falkners</persName><persName xml:id="3554"></persName>. He is in a more cheerful mood, but could give no definite reasons for his optimism.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
