<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Low Sunday, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">986</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant morning but cold. I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. and received the Holy Communion. The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> was the celebrant. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> alone represented the choir boys. They go home tomorrow for the 'inside of a fortnight'. There were nearly 200 men at the parade, most of them raw recruits, and (as I judge) of a poor type. I preached from notes, &amp; was woefully molested by the coughing of the congregation! At Mattins <persName xml:id="437">Knowling</persName> began his sermon with an allusion to the death of <hi rend="bold underline">the Weslyan scholar, <persName xml:id="4337">Moulton</persName>, who died from exposure after the ship in which he was returning from India had been torpedoed</hi>. The sermon was, as always with this preacher, admirable. I attended Evensong, which was preceded by a procession round the Cathedral. The choir halted in the Nine Altars, and sang there a verse of the processional hymn. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle. The evening was still and fine. We indulged the hope that at last, after so many disappointments, the spring had arrived. The Cathedral was filled to its utmost capacity. I preached an old sermon, on "Jacob's Vision", which fitted in fairly well both to Easter, and to the War. The congregation was very attentive, and (though many bad colds were sufficiently evident in the service) there was no coughing. <persName xml:id="3875">Geoffrey Heseltine</persName> was waiting to greet me after the service. After a pleasant motor&#8211;run home, we arrived in the Deanery about 9.15 p.m. Next Sunday, it was announced, the Preacher is to be <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName>. <hi rend="italic">It is odd to cast back one's mind to the year 1885 when first I made Headlam's acquaintance on the occasion of his election to the All Souls Fellowship. We little thought then that our ways in life would have brought us after 32 years into our present situations. He was then an uncouth creature, amazingly rude in his manners: he is so still. And I suspect that his carriage does little justice to his true nature. For I judge him to be kind&#8211;hearted, and honest at bottom, though of a tyrannous spirit, and incapable of being just to opponents. Only his bad temper can avail to keep him off the Bench, to which he has evident titles, &amp; which w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be the stronger for his presence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
