<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1125</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At last a fine morning with cooler temperature, &amp; a blue sky. But the promise was delusive, &amp; rain was falling when I went to Mattins. After service I walked through the rain to S. Giles' in order to attend the funeral of old <persName xml:id="4165">Alderman Charlton</persName>. The Wesleyan minister, a large hairy man, read the lesson. As I passed through the Cathedral I fell in with a youth who looked intelligent, &amp; talked with him. He was a Papist from Preston on the verge of the military age, &amp; worked as a clerk in the municipal office. He was bicycling through the country on his holiday, &amp; was now making his way home. I showed him the Nine Altars &amp; the Galilee, &amp; then the Library &amp; the Deanery. Then I sent him over to the Castle, &amp; bade him return for lunch. This in due course he did, &amp; we lunched in much friendship: &amp; so parted. His name was John Caton. He told me that there more Catholics than Protestants in Preston &amp; that there was no ill&#8211;feeling between them. I attended Evensong. As I came out of the cathedral a young man with a pleasant&#8211;looking little boy in tow accosted me. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">They were little <persName xml:id="4206">Lord Feversham</persName> and his tutor who are staying at Lumley with <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> <persName xml:id="3891">Gilbert Darwin</persName> came to fetch me for a walk. The rain fell in torrents, &amp; the wind blew a hurricane before we reached Dryburn. There I had tea with <persName xml:id="3813">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin</persName>. <persName xml:id="3512">Colonel Darwin</persName> came in, &amp; afterwards accompanied me as far as the station on my way home. He says that our casualities are now about 5000 daily: that recruiting is in a bad way: that Sir Wm. Robertson has asked for 500,000 men, &amp; only succeeded in getting 200,000! I see with very deep regret that <hi rend="bold underline">the <persName xml:id="3717">only son</persName> of <persName xml:id="2540">Sir William Osler</persName> has been killed</hi>. The young man was for a while stationed at Newcastle, and I remember <persName xml:id="3716">Lady Osler</persName> bringing him here for lunch. Thus daily the blood of our sons, the best promise of our nation, is poured out, and still the victory tarries. <hi rend="underline">Usquequoque Domine</hi> [‘always oh Lord?']? <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> arrived from Blanchland for the weekend. After dinner, I wrote up my journal, and also wrote my daily letter to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. The tempestuous day ended with a still eventide.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
