<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1000</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The night was tempestuous. I noticed that one of the six rook's nests had disappeared: but the temperature continues high. Altogether very comfortless weather, bad for mind &amp; body. I celebrated at 8 a.m. All the college were present except <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> and <persName xml:id="2803">May</persName>. <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="underline">George</hi></persName> was there. He is very steady in his weekly communion, and it is altogether a self&#8211;imposed rule, save perhaps that he divines that it pleases me to see him at the Communion rail. Most acceptable to the Almighty must be the prayers of the young. <hi rend="bold underline">There were about 300 soldiers at the Church Parade</hi>. I preached on Eph. V. 15, 16, and the men were fairly attentive, but they are very crude &amp; rough as yet. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowling</hi> preached at Mattins, a good sermon but less good than it might have been by reason of some rather superfluous denunciations of Germany and eulogies of America. I cannot think it edifies our people thus to echo, sanction, &amp; in a measure consecrate their prejudices &amp; resentments.</p>
         <p>After lunch (at which <persName xml:id="3652">Colonel Herne</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3651">Captain Slade</persName> were present by way of saying Goodbye before leaving Durham) <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to Sacristan where I assisted at the unveiling of a tablet to <persName xml:id="4141">Lieut: Brass</persName> and preached. After the function we had tea with <persName xml:id="3833">Colonel</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3834">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Blackett</persName>, &amp; so home.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The Rev. <persName xml:id="4297">Edward S. Kiek</persName>, Minister of Square Church, Halifax, wrote to me asking that I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> undertake to preach in his church wh. he describes "as one of the most famous of Congregational Churches at any rate in the North of England". I replied thus:&#8211; </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>April 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1917</p>
         <p>Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I am greatly obliged to you for your letter, &amp; for the kindly&#8211;expressed invitation to preach in your church. In the present circumstances of the nation I am very unwilling to bind myself by promises wh. I might find it inconvenient to fulfil when the dies fatalis sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have actually arrived. It is sufficiently well&#8211;known that I desire what is called an "exchange of pulpits" between the Christian Churches as a step towards a better mutual understanding: and I am myself very willing to accept invitations to preach in Non&#8211;Anglican Churches, provided that I have reasonable ground for believing that my doing so will promote religious harmony, and not have the untoward result of occasioning local friction. Halifax is to me terra incognita: &amp;, therefore I am wholly dependent upon the assurances of others for my knowledge of its ecclesiastical conditions. It is indeed lamentable that it sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be necessary to advance with such vigilant timidity along the path of evident Christian obligation, but S. Paul's counsel, "<hi rend="underline">Let not your good be evil spoken of</hi>", can never prudently be ignored. It may interest you to read the enclosed, which you will please observe is marked "Private".</p>
         <p> With all good wishes, I am, Yours very faithfully</p>
         <p> H. Hensley Henson</p>
         </div>
         <p>I enclosed with this letter a copy of my correspondence with the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>. I wrote to <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName>, <persName xml:id="318">Ridley</persName>, <persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName>, and <persName xml:id="4107">Harold Anson</persName> thanking them for their willingness to assist me in preparing a <ref xml:id="996">memoir</ref> of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>. Unfortunately their power to provide materials does not appear to be considerable: &amp; it is lack of materials which is the real problem.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
