<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1090</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> and to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> before breakfast: attended Mattins: had some talk with <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> about organising a great theological school in Durham, and wrote a series of letters including one to <persName xml:id="508">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Balfour</persName>. <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName> came to see me, &amp; to report progress. He has been to Liverpool, &amp; tried on his clothes. <hi rend="bold underline">He is to sail before October</hi>. This delay is on some counts regrettable, but the activity of the German submarines reconciles one to it. Later I wrote a cheque (&#x00A3;29.3.2.) for his kit, &amp; gave it to him to be posted. I lunched with the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruikshanks</persName><persName xml:id="4180"></persName>, with whom <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName> is staying. Also I attended Evensong.</p>
         <p>After dinner I read <persName xml:id="1619"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pringle&#8211;Pattison's</hi></persName> <ref xml:id="936"><hi rend="underline">"The Idea of God in the light of recent Philosophy"</hi></ref> (The Gifford Lectures for 1912 &amp; 1913). The book was warmly recommended both by <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName>. Hadow also spoke highly of it. I found it very interesting. It is written in an admirable spirit, &amp; (what is not less important in a philosophical work) in an admirable style.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Changes in our conception of nature may be fatal to one formulation after another; accidents of expression may drop away in deference to historical criticism, nay, much that <hi rend="underline">seemed</hi> of the very essence of religious faith may have to be left behind. But each time that the earthly body of a belief is laid in the dust, it receives a more glorious spiritual body, in which it continues to function as of old in the heart of man. Timid theologians who tremble for the ark of God at every advance of scientific knowledge do but repeat the sacrilege of Uzzal in the sacred legend, smitten by the anger of heaven for his officious interference. Faith, which is an active belief in the reality of the ideal, is the very breath by which humanity lives, and it will reconstitute itself as long as the race endures." P. 81, 82.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is finely conceived, and finely expressed. Such philosophy as this makes one begin to pluck up heart again!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
