<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">972</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wintry morning, with showers of sleet, &amp; snow&#8211;flakes in the air. I prepared a brief introductory statement, with which to introduce my sermon in S. Sepulchre's, and to explain its total irrelevance to the proper subject of Palm Sunday. It ran thus :&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">"Last Sunday, in the responsible exercise of my legal rights, I preached in the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName></hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; appealed as earnestly as I could for a recognition of the essential agreement of all Christians who accept sincerely the principles of the Reformation. That agreement, indeed, was for generations the postulate of English Churchmen, but within the last century it has been challenged, and is now openly denied by many. It is the case that the Great War had seemed to draw a measure of discredit on the Reformation, &amp; there have not been wanting those among us who have insisted that now at last the older Christianity of the Medieval Church has been vindicated, &amp; the revolt of the Reformers condemned. It seemed desirable, therefore, that I should supplement my argument of last Sunday by some consideration of this subject: &amp; I have to thank the <persName xml:id="4176">Rector</persName> of this Church for giving me the opportunity of doing so today. I must beg leave to desert the proper theme of Palm Sunday in order to complete my message by the present discourse".</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <persName xml:id="4418">Tallents</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to S. Sepulchre's. The Church was nearly filled, which, in view of the abominable weather, surprised me. I preached my sermon on <hi rend="bold">"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">The failure of Lutheranism, no disproof of the Reformation</hi><hi rend="bold">"</hi>; and felt the while that it was abominably like an Extension Lecture! I remained to the celebration of the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I lunched with <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>. The <persName xml:id="4128">Belloc Lowndeses</persName> were there. Ralph told me that he had read both my sermons, &amp; greatly approved &amp; "admired" them! Then I walked with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, had tea with <persName xml:id="2688">Charles</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2768">Dorothy</persName>, and called on the <persName xml:id="42">Steele&#8211;Maitlands</persName><persName xml:id="701"></persName>.	</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
