<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1101</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather continues to be thunderous and sultry while the sky is overcast. We were called at 7 a.m. &amp; breakfasted at 8.30 a.m. I spent most of the morning in going through transcripts of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> letters to the "Times". After lunch we walked across the moors. The flies are numerous, persistent, and exasperating. The local vicar, <persName xml:id="4374">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pybus</persName> &amp; his wife called and chatted with us for best part of an hour. He says that his parish is 6 miles long. The parish church consists of the northern transept of a great monastic church, of which the greater part has been wholly demolished. Even in this little rustic community he says that there are many dissenters. <hi rend="italic bold underline">I asked whether the National Mission had done any good, &amp; he replied that he had not observed any effects in his people. </hi><hi rend="italic">This appears to be the general verdict, yet the fiction persists in Lambeth that the Mission was an event of the utmost importance, &amp; the attempt is actually being made to build on it a reconstruction of the Establishment. <persName xml:id="128">The Abp</persName>. Has surrounded himself with enthusiasts who live in a world of their own &amp; hear nobody else's voice. They "compare themselves with themselves", &amp; are not wise.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
