<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1154</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful autumnal morning. I went to the cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> celebrated: there were but two of the cadets from the school present. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> "gabbled" the confession so that I could not easily keep pace with him. Why will the parsons do this? They make penitence &amp; devotion appreciably more difficult.</p>
         <p>I attended Mattins, &amp; heard from <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> an extemporaneous sermon on the text from which my evening sermon has been taken. It was trying but the congregation (which seemed to be rather unusually large) appeared to like it. After service I walked with <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> as far as his house. He gives an account of feeling in Ireland. <hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Wilkinson came to lunch. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I showed him the rather unfriendly account of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> career as Educational minister which I had received from <persName xml:id="2180">Morant</persName>.</hi> He thought it "valuable material". After attending Evensong, we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, <persName xml:id="4357">Elizabeth</persName> and I) motored to Roker, taking with us <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> who was due to preach at Monkwearmouth. I preached in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's Roker, a modern church built in the likeness of a capsized ship, but not without effectiveness as a parochial church. There was a very large choir, &amp; a good organ. <persName xml:id="4367">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Priestman</persName>, a ship builder, who built the church, is an enthusiast for music and has established himself as organist. He has also married the vicar's sister &amp; thus created a domestic intimacy with the ecclesiastical management. The Vicar (the <persName xml:id="4366">Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> A. de P. Pownall</persName>) is a young plump man, with a good voice, a secure manner, &amp; a Cambridge hood. There was a dingy looking curate also, who, I was informed, was about to leave the parish. The congregation was very large, and joined heartily in the singing. The acoustics of the church were fairly good: for <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Elizabeth, though thrust back almost as far as the western wall, were able to hear everything without difficulty. We returned to Durham as soon as the service was over, picking up Lillingston on the Sunderland bridge, and arriving in the College about 9 p.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
