<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1009</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>Grey &amp; chilly day. Long &amp; very interesting letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, who is making the most of his opportunities in Salonika. Also, from <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>. <persName xml:id="4289">Inskip</persName>, the Rector of Southport, writes to borrow my "Edinburgh Review" Article.<note xml:id="316" n="1"></note> I wrote the following in reply:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Dear M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Inskip</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Herewith I send the E.R. wh. contains the article wh. you refer to. It is my only copy, so I shall trust you to return it. The Evangelicals sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">consider carefully the actual situation. At present they are in danger of losing all influence on the policy of the Anglican Communion: &amp; that policy is now definitely assuming a character, which will finally be incompatible with their membership of the Anglican Church. It is really time for them to ask themselves very seriously '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Quo tendimus</hi><hi rend="italic">?' My own belief is that the most hopeful direction in wh. to make an effort is that wh. w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">commit the C. of E. to such a course of action as c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">not be explained away, &amp; w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">demonstrate her essentially Evangelical (Reformed or Protestant) character. This is the importance in my eyes of that "Exchange of Pulpits" wh. the Evangelical Bps might secure at once if they had but a fraction of the insight and courage wh. mark the Bps of <persName xml:id="49">Oxford</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="105">Winchester</persName>. As it is, they keep silence &amp; do nothing while the Anglican Communion is being organized on principles wh. they cannot really accept, &amp; the Anglican conscience is being 'taught' deliberately on "Catholick" lines. The enclosed may, perhaps, interest you.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
 <p>I sent him with this letter a copy of the Correspondence with the <persName xml:id="166">B. of L</persName>. [Bishop of London] The "Edinburgh Review" was sent to him.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
