<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1069</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I presided over a very amicable meeting of Chapter, at which we provisionally decided to substitute an electricity&#8211;driven fan for the present organ&#8211;blowing apparatus. I undertook to ascertain from the Deans of the Cathedrals, wherein this device has been adopted, whether it has been found satisfactory. The <persName xml:id="3897">Mayor</persName> came to see me about a meeting on August 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> in the Market place to commemorate the anniversary of the declaration of War. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I "took up our carriages", and travelled to Manchester, where we were to be the guests of <persName xml:id="3746">Canon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4400">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Scott</persName>. There came to dinner <persName xml:id="114">Bishop Welldon</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="4458">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4459">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray Wrong</persName>. The latter is the daughter of the <persName xml:id="1170">Master of Balliol</persName>, &amp; very pretty, but <hi rend="bold underline">an ardent suffragist</hi>.</p>
         <p>The evening paper ^reports^ another air&#8211;raid on London, more formidable in number of aeroplanes &amp; persistence of attack than any previous raid. This will give actuality to the observations on 'reprisals', which I propose to make tomorrow. Our conversation at dinner turned on this subject, and moved on naturally to that of the Quakers and their religious attitude. <hi rend="italic">Welldon seems to me to have an inadequate sense of the obligation of Christians, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">a fortiori</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Christian ministers, to resist the onrush of the baser motives, which takes place in these moments of natural exasperation, and finds expression in the agitation for "reprisals". The very fact that it </hi><hi rend="italic underline">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> so difficult to distinguish between legitimate military methods, and immoral methods of revenge, adds to the obligation. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">We</hi><hi rend="italic"> must not play the casuist in the interest of natural passion, and suffer ourselves to drift into the situation of becoming Apostles of Hatred. No one who is not a preacher can realize how strong is the pressure in that direction. It seems so poor a thing to bleat of forgiveness from the "coward's castle" of a protected pulpit. The temptation is very strong not to echo the prevailing cry for vigourous &amp; immediate retaliation. Nevertheless the duty of doing this unpalatable thing seems to me plain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
