<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1119</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi> before breakfast. The post brought me from <persName xml:id="1820"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi></persName> an invitation to preach in Westminster Abbey on October 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">This I accepted straight away</hi> in spite of the fact that I am "in residence" in October. <persName xml:id="437"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowling</hi></persName> preached an admirable sermon at Mattins. I celebrated the Holy Communion. There were but 6 communicants beside myself, &amp; these included <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>. <persName xml:id="3553"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Meade Faulkner</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3554">his wife</persName> came to lunch. He was very full of a certain Hospital at Kirk Leatham near Redcar which contains the books of the founder an ex&#8211;Lord Mayor of London, tempore Charles II: among these are many interesting M.S.S. He said that he had heard from Paris that no literary loot had so far arrived from Belgium &amp; the parts of France wasted by the enemy. This is surely surprising. &amp; suggests that German thoroughness extended to organising the transference of all valuable loot to Berlin. I attended Evensong. Major &amp; Miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">White</hi> and <persName xml:id="4205" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duff</hi></persName> came to tea. When they had departed I started to walk with Craik, but we had not gone far when the rain came on again. So we returned to the Deanery, and I spent an hour &amp; a half in showing my guests to the library.</p>
<p>After dinner we sate in my study, and talked about many things. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Craik told me, on the authority of <persName xml:id="292">Lord Rosebery</persName>, that Lord North was the natural brother of George III, to whom he unquestionably bore a remarkable facial resemblance</hi><hi rend="italic">. This circumstance "caused Frederick, prince of Wales to suggest to the first Earl of Guildford that one of "their wives must have played them false". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Dict: of N.B. makes this statement on the authority of Wraxall</hi><hi rend="italic">. But, if there had been truth in the suggestion, even a gross fool like Frederick could hardly have made it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">However Craik says that Lord R. is evidently convinced of the fact, and has the pictures of George III and Lord North arranged side by side</hi><hi rend="italic">. The unacknowledged facts of history are sometimes far more illuminating than those which adorn the pages of history's record. This may be case in point.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
