<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">963</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful day, bright &amp; cloudless, but with a cold south&#8211;easterly wind. I got up for breakfast, though feeling rather dilapidated. Save for a walk with <persName xml:id="2685">Godfrey</persName> to the post before lunch I kept indoors all day. I wrote to <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> for her birthday tomorrow, &amp; to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. Also I read some interesting personal sketches by <persName xml:id="2083">Gosse</persName>. <ref xml:id="944">That</ref> of <persName xml:id="118">Bishop Creighton</persName> accords with my own impressions of him. <hi rend="italic">On the whole I suspect that he deteriorated as the exigencies of episcopal office compelled him to conform to the demand of the religious public for what is called "spiritual&#8211;mindedness", though, indeed, he never had great success in that direction. His was essentially a secular mind, &amp; the aspects of ecclesiastical office which appealed to him most were secular. The sketch of <persName xml:id="4404">Shorthouse</persName>, the author of "John Inglesant" is very amusing. I remember seeing him once in Oxford walking beside the chair of the Warden of Keble, who is the present <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName>. His romance has probably been an effective auxiliary of the Ritualists. There came to tea the <persName xml:id="4362">Principal</persName> of the Clergy School &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Phillips, and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Palmer. I learned with some surprise that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the senior verger of Lichfield Cathedral is now the Mayor of the City. This, I should suppose, must be an unique combination of characters</hi><hi rend="italic">. Our conversation at dinner tended to concern itself too much with the conduct &amp; reputation of living politicians, &amp; was perhaps more interesting than either just or charitable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
