<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1020</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Sunderland sermon: attended Mattins: and presided at a meeting of Chapter, where the business was mainly formal, &amp; all over in 25 minutes. Then I wrote to <persName xml:id="633">Sir Henry Graham</persName> accepting his suggestion that my letter to him sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be shown to <persName xml:id="1591">Lord Lansdowne</persName> with the view of gathering his Lordship's view of my theory as to the decisive effect of <persName xml:id="4108">Sir John Anson's</persName> death on the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> career. Then I took <persName xml:id="3223">Col: Gaisford</persName> for a constitutional before lunch, &amp; later attended Evensong. I wrote to <persName xml:id="1301">Clarence Tait</persName>; walked again with Gaisford, &amp; talked till dinner&#8211;time. The atmosphere was sultry and thunderous (last night there was a sharp thunderstorm with deluges of rain); &amp; this circumstance may go some way to explain the utter failure to do any adequate work. This, added to the inevitable distraction of a guest, explains a good deal.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I received a cheerful letter from <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName>, who writes rhapsodically about the <persName xml:id="65">Viceroy</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, a fellow&#8211;Wykhamist. How potent is the bond which membership of a public school creates! Eton dominated Anson's life, &amp; really coloured his judgment. I doubt if he could quite believe that an Etonian was on a level with other men. The superiority was too evident &amp; too assured. The development of this intense &amp; limited loyalty has been brought to the pitch of a fine art: and it operates powerfully within society. How far is it a genuinely good influence? The affirmative answer is not quite so obvious as one w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> like it to be. But public schools are only large, artificial families; and the nepotism of school patriotism is not intrinsically different from the nepotism of family affection. Both hardly make for justice, or, in the long run, for efficiency.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
