<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">989</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Snow lay on the ground until breakfast time, when it began rapidly to disappear. In the afternoon the temperature rose, and we even dared to suspect a spring&#8211;like feeling in the air! I wrote to <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> before breakfast: attended Mattins: worked at the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> journal all morning: attended Evensong: went with <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> to the potato patch, and worked for 1½ hours. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came to tea. I gave him a letter to his <persName xml:id="4344">Father</persName> suggesting that he should come to see me about George's going to sea. Also I gave the boy <ref xml:id="950">"The Bride of Lammermoor"</ref>. <hi rend="bold underline">The afternoon post brought me two melancholy letters</hi>. The one from Mrs Hayward told me that her son Cyril, one of the old <orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's</orgName> choir boys had been killed in the Battle of Arras. The other from <persName xml:id="3836">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pater</persName>, telling me that his son, who was usher at our <orgName xml:id="270">choir school</orgName> had been killed in a flying accident here at home. <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote letters of condolence to both my correspondents</hi>. <persName xml:id="318">Edward Ridley</persName> sent me an informing letter about the late Warden. After dinner I read more of his journal for the years 1902&#8211;1905, when he held office in <persName xml:id="508">Balfour's</persName> administration as Secretary of the Board of Education. It is evident that his relatively subordinate situation was as practically inconvenient as it was intrinsically absurd. His chief was <persName xml:id="2816">Lord Londonderry</persName>, a kindly soul enough, but grotesquely ignorant of educational affairs, and of mediocre political capacity. The mutual regard of the two men alone made the situation tolerable or effective.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
