<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1115</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>A little after 1.30 a.m. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Berry came to our bedroom door to tell us that the "first warning" of an air&#8211;raid had been received. We did not think it necessary to get up, but decided to "take it lying down"! I worked away very fruitlessly at the <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref>: the warm heavy atmosphere renders work extraordinarily difficult. After Evensong <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked languidly, &amp;, when we came in, there were the two men from Spennymoor waiting for me. They wanted me to come out, and preach twice in the interest of their local Fund for sending relations to visit their wounded friends. These men &#8211; John Haile and <persName xml:id="4138">Councillor Blenkin</persName> &#8211; were dissenters, the one a "Primitive", the other a Wesleyan, &amp; they possessed the oleaginous fluency which makes Dissenters so trying, but they did not appear to me humbugs, &amp;, certainly, they expressed very sound sentiments about Stockholm. I introduced them to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who gave them tea: and I promised to reserve September 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> for them.</p>
<p>The evening paper reports two air&#8211;raids, the one near Hull, the other in the Isle of Thanet. No appreciable injury was done in the first, but in the last some civilians were slain, &amp; two of the enemy machines brought down. It is reported that our naval forces have destroyed a Zeppelin in the North Sea. On the whole the Hun did not prosper in the air last night.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read with much interest D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3402">Ross's</persName> account of his nephew, a Scottish minister who joined the Army as a soldier &amp; was killed in France. ("</hi><hi rend="italic underline">A Scottish Minister and Soldier, the Rev. Peter Ross Husband M.A. 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> Lieut. Black Watch</hi><hi rend="italic">.") It adds confirmation to my belief that the clergy of military age ought to be in the ranks. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Husband was, perhaps, a unique instance of a man, physically &amp; temperamentally ill&#8211;qualified for the military life, who yet felt so strongly the moral obligation of this War with Germany, and the intrinsic indecency of the Christian minister's exemption from the risks &amp; hardships of campaigning, that he persistently forced himself on the authorities until he was accepted for military service, trained, &amp; sent to the Front.<note xml:id="415" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
