<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
		 <p>15</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1082</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant summer day. We strolled on to the cliff after breakfast, &amp; there witnessed a little accident. A soldier lolling on the cliff with a vesta exploded a loaded revolver which was in his pocket, &amp; blew off his finger. I spent the morning in looking through the sermons for Sunday, and walking with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. In the afternoon there was a tea&#8211;party during which I succeeded in giving the mightiest offence to a good woman of the "onward &amp; upward" type. Then we walked on the cliffs. On returning I found a letter from <persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName> which contained the unwelcome news that there would be delay in <persName xml:id="3571">George's</persName> departure:&#8211; "The fitting up of young Nimmins' ship is being upset by a prolonged strike of the Mersey boilermakers' (not in the papers) but he is happily unconscious of this fact and will have made all the more progress in mathematics, swimming etc. by the time another one is ready." I am sorry for this delay. It is very undesirable that George should be hanging about in a state of suspense. After dinner I walked with <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> on the cliffs. The sky is rarely destitute of noisy aeroplanes, and at intervals there are heavy sounds of gun&#8211;firing &#8211; all very sinister and disturbing.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
