<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1091</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Apart from conscious results which the process may condition, it is hard to see what interest lies for God or man in the infinite shiftings of the cosmic dust".<note xml:id="403" n="1"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>Set beside the philosopher's dictum this word of an Apostle:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">"All chastening seemeth for the present to be not joyous, but grievous: yet afterward it yieldeth peaceable fruit unto them that have been exercised thereby, even the fruit of righteousness".<note xml:id="404" n="2"></note></hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>"Finem respice" [Look to the end] is still the word.</p>
         <p>I went to the Holy Communion and [the] 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> celebrated, &amp; read the wrong collect. <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> followed with the wrong Epistle: &amp; the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>, reverting to the right Gospel, emphasised their errors. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3572">Edgar</persName> were among the communicants. It is their last Sunday at the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir&#8211;school</orgName>, where they have spent the last five years</hi>. Their experiences here will have made, or marred, them. God grant it be the first. They look happy and good. The congregation was mainly composed of school boys. I attended Mattins. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruikshank</persName> ended his sermon by reading the account of <persName xml:id="4323">Justin Martyr's</persName> trial &amp; execution. It reminded me of the too familiar scenes with Conscientious objectors. Then I lunched with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3805">Fearne</persName>. Cruikshank &amp; his niece were there, and <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName>. We had much talk about the War. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1916">Arthur Morgan</persName> came to see me, &amp; said Goodbye. He goes immediately to a cadet school at Farnborough to learn flying</hi>. I attended Evensong. Afterwards <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> came to see me, and had tea. We talked together for an hour, and then I walked with him as far as S. Giles Church, &amp; there turned back home. <hi rend="italic">There are notices posted in the town announcing a meeting in the Market place next Saturday in order to pass a patriotic resolution declaring "inflexible determination" to go on with the war until the victory has been won. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName>, the <persName xml:id="3718">High Sheriff</persName>, and the Dean are to be speakers. This is all well enough, but one cannot shut out the doubt as to our power to live up to these valourous declarations. There is a limit even to the fighting power of Britain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
