<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1051</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I revised the letter on <ref xml:id="930">"The clergy &amp; Military Service"</ref> &amp; prepared it for post, then "tossed" on the point whether it should go, &amp; then decision being adverse, I tore open the envelope, &amp; withheld the letter. To such straits &amp; vacillation have I now fallen! </hi><persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came in to tell me about his new prospects, very pleased with himself. After his departure, I re&#8211;read the rejected letter, &amp; examined the motives of its rejection. These seemed to me probably to be selfishly prudential i.e. the publication of such a letter would probably be held injudicious by any intelligent counsellor, &amp; likely to prejudice my chances of a bishoprick!! Accordingly I placed it again in an envelope, &amp; sent it off!!! What can be done with this variety of weather&#8211;cock, which turns with the wind not of advantage but of risk? I attended Mattins, had an interview with <persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> about the latter's "mortgage" taken over from <persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">walked with <persName xml:id="3542">Norman Henderson</persName></hi> as far as the Framwellgate Bridge, &amp; then bade him farewell. Finally, I discussed George's affair with <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>. <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> came to lunch. I attended Evensong. He reports that the King's visit to Sunderland was very successful. He has a theory that the notorious jealousy of Newcastle against Sunderland derives from the ancient discords of the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, when Newcastle went for the King, &amp; Sunderland stood for the Parliament. Such discords die hard.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
