<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1014</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Before breakfast I wrote a letter to the "Record" under the heading' "Exchange of Pulpits &amp; the Rights of the Laity". The post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, and also one from Hutton. At Mattins <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> preached a sermon which was almost inaudible to me in my stall. After the Benediction I read the King's Proclamation. I attended Evensong, and afterwards the <persName xml:id="2920">Gees</persName><persName xml:id="3484"></persName> called with <persName xml:id="423">Simpson</persName> of S. Paul's. I spent an hour in shewing him over the house &amp; the cathedral. I wrote to <persName xml:id="4248">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hamilton&#8211;Hoare</persName> in answer to his very civil letter about the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>. He is evidently an ancient man, but not unwilling to have a hand in a <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref> of an old friend. There is, perhaps, some danger of my being submerged by reminiscences, which are too general &amp; discursive for my purpose. However, <hi rend="underline">that</hi> is preferable to a total lack of material, which at present seems the more prob1able fate. I am reading <persName xml:id="1153">Jowett's</persName> <ref xml:id="957">'Life of Letters'</ref>. <hi rend="underline">His</hi> letters are admirable compositions; they abound in <hi rend="underline">dicta</hi> of permanent value; &amp; treat freely of subjects which will always engage the attention of serious men. But the Warden's correspondence, so far as I have yet gone, had not this character. It limits itself to the immediate point, generally some business matter, &amp; hardly ever goes into anything of general interest. The Journals are equally destitute (save for a few passages) of biographical value. He was devoted to his friends, but does not seem to have "opened out" to them on paper. Perhaps, one reason for this was their proximity. Willert, <persName xml:id="1171">Raper</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2471">Strachan&#8211;Davidson</persName> were his closest friends, and they all lived in close &amp; frequent personal intercourse. They were within conversational range. In All Souls he was on terms of friendship with <persName xml:id="39">Doyle</persName>, <persName xml:id="652">Compton</persName>, <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray</persName>, &amp; some of the younger men, but he met them at short intervals, stayed in their houses, shot &amp; travelled with them, rarely wrote them letters of intimacy &amp; value. This, I think, must be the reason for the disappointing quality of his letters, at least of those which I have seen.</p>
         <p>The day became sultry towards the close: there was thunder &amp; rain about 10 p.m.   </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
