<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[34]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1004</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The fine weather continues. Life indoors will become intolerable! I attended Mattins; &amp; worked at the <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref>. The <persName xml:id="3897">Mayor</persName> called to announce that he &amp; his municipal colleagues w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> come in state to the Cathedral on Whitsunday, May 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, being the Sunday after <persName xml:id="3020">"Empire Day"</persName>. The latter Festival is no doubt more intelligible to the bulk of citizens than the former. He had never seen the chapel or the kitchen, &amp; was much interested by both. <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName>, <persName xml:id="3187" display="no">Jevons</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> lunched with me (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had gone to Newcastle): <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; later they returned to the first meeting of the Committee on Social Problems, appointed by the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName>, with Hadow as Chairman</hi>. We decided to meet fortnightly at the Deanery, &amp; made Lillingston Secretary. After the Committee had dispersed I walked with Logic. There arrived a letter from <persName xml:id="1266">Prof: Edward Moore</persName> of Harvard. He expresses the utmost satisfaction at America's entrance into the War, though his distrust of <persName xml:id="2814">Wilson's</persName> leadership remains as strong as ever. "I feel that I can come to England again. At times in the last year I have felt that I never could. Your nation is very good to welcome us as you do, &amp; not to criticize us as we deserve". This represents a mood far removed indeed from the "spread&#8211;eagleism" which we commonly associate with U.S.A.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
