<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1140</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. Only one canon, <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName>, &amp; one minor canon, <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>. About a score of communicants including three men, and three choir boys. <hi rend="bold underline">I thought of <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> &amp; the lengthening list of names of "old boys" from Barking, Ilford, Westminster, and now Durham. They symbolize the fact that one's life grows ever emptier of hopes and riches in memories. And of those memories, how many are regrets! </hi>After breakfast I wrote to George. As next Tuesday is D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Johnson's birthday, it occurred to me that I might vary the too–familiar type of preaching by speaking about him, &amp; saving myself the pains of writing a sermon by repeating the substance of the discourse which I delivered in Westminster Abbey on Sept. 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1909 when the bi–centenary of his birth was observed in the place where he lies buried. There was a very small congregation. Apart from the clergy &amp; choir I do not think there more than a score of grown men in it! I learned afterwards that there had been a route march of the "National Volunteers": this, perhaps would have taken away a few: &amp; some were absent from Durham on holiday. There were, of course, no members of school or university. Still it was not a satisfying or consolatory congregation to preach to. I walked with Elizabeth before lunch. We fell in with <persName xml:id="4344">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nimmins</persName> who showed me an excellent photograph of George in his uniform. He said that he was omitting the formula "viâ Siberia" from his letters, as <hi rend="underline">that</hi> route was probably closed. I regret now that I followed George's direction in using it. I attended Evensong. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> brought his brother–in–law, <persName xml:id="4157">Campbell</persName>, an incumbent in Essex, to have tea. <hi rend="italic">The latter gave no very encouraging account of the ecclesiastical situation in Essex. <persName xml:id="2462">Watts–Ditchfield</persName> is said to model himself on <persName xml:id="166">Ingram</persName>: ("</hi><hi rend="italic underline">If the blind lead the blind, shall they not both fall into the ditch?</hi><hi rend="italic">") to give offence by "scolding" the clergy: to disconcert the educated laity by his vulgarity: &amp; to have followed Evangelical precedent by appointing his son–in–law, a colonial–bred clergyman, to the living of Prittlewell, which, though not very valuable, is regarded as important.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
