<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1080</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName> spoke in the highest terms of <persName xml:id="1619">Pringle&#8211;Pattison's</persName> <ref xml:id="936">Gifford Lectures</ref>. He thought that they indicated a mode of presenting Christianity which might appeal to the modern mind. He said that <persName xml:id="588">Caird's</persName> influence had greatly decayed. I asked him whether he thought the Disruption had benefitted religion in Scotland, &amp; he replied in a decided way that it assuredly had, though men were now weary of the divisions it had caused, &amp; eager to re&#8211;create the union, which he [it] had broken up. He thought the re&#8211;union of the two great Presbyterian Churches would be affected, &amp; that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">as a consequence each of them would lose 25 per cent of its following</hi><hi rend="italic">! In all this, perhaps, there was some admixture of the hereditary sectarianism. We spoke of "after&#8211;war problems". He took a grave view, agreeing mainly with <persName xml:id="30">Arthur Shadwell's</persName> article, which, however, he had not read. He thought all our institutions would come under severe criticism, &amp; be either swept away, or drastically re&#8211;ordered. The Church of England would certainly enjoy no exemption from the process. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He had come to think that the "Establishment" was a great assistance to religion in England, &amp; that its destruction would injure religion gravely. He thought Arnold's view of widening the basis of the National Religion was still a sound policy</hi><hi rend="italic">. I was distressed to hear both at <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry's</persName> table and at the table of <persName xml:id="2708">Lady Struthers</persName> strong denunciations of the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. Of Canterbury's</persName> attitude towards "reprisals". In both cases I conceived myself bound to champion his Grace, with whom in this matter I am entirely agreed. Lord Haldane suggested that a collection of the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London's</persName> speeches translated into German might well seem very like "Hurrah and Hallelujah"! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There can be no doubt that Ingram has spoken very foolishly, &amp; unfortunately his position as Bishop of London gives a prominences</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">[sic]</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> to his utterances altogether greater than their intrinsic importance merits. We have learned to know our Ingram, &amp; to discount him: but abroad this is not yet the case.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
<p>I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, read the papers, and wrote to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>. <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> came into the club, &amp; had some talk with me. Then I walked to Westminster, &amp; visited the Abbey church. The Wolfe monument is gay with Canadian flags. I called on <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName>, &amp; talked with him for more than half an hour. He says that <persName xml:id="2916">Ronald Knox</persName> is reported to be in a strange state of mind. His friends await his next step either into papistry, or into agnosticism. Either event seems probable. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me at luncheon with <persName xml:id="344">Sir Henry</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="793">Lady Craik</persName>. They are both very discontented with the present r&#x00E9;gime at <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. With parliamentary gossip and more serious talk the time passed until tea&#8211;time. We called on <persName xml:id="542">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gow</persName>, and then on <persName xml:id="4376">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Radcliffe</persName>. <persName xml:id="2291">Marcus</persName> came in, a fine&#8211;looking boy of 13, who is much cast down at being rejected for the navy on account of defective eyesight. Then we walked to 108 Eaton Square, where <persName xml:id="2768">Lady Charnwood</persName> gave us tea. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="4455">Sir Almroth Wright</persName> was there to meet us. With him I had a long conversation. He is a strange creature, engaged on a book about Morality, &amp; anxious to talk with "experts". If he took me for an "expert" moralist, he was woefully mistaken. However I was pleased to have speech with him</hi>. We returned to the S. Paul's Deanery, &amp; there dined with <persName xml:id="427">our hosts</persName><persName xml:id="1209"></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>. After dinner we had much mixed conversation. A note from Miss Mills was brought to me after I had retired. It said that <persName xml:id="2709">Robinson</persName> could not lunch with me in the Club tomorrow. This is, perhaps, well, as I might have pledged myself to write something about <persName xml:id="1173">Temple's</persName> <note xml:id="399" n="1">meeting,</note> which had really best be left alone. <hi rend="bold underline">Ralph tells me that the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName>, who was present at the meeting, reports that Temple's speech was admirable, also that Temple and <persName xml:id="3611">Sheppard</persName> are entirely delighted with the meeting</hi>. The daily papers with the single exception of the "Times" contained no report of the meeting. This surprised me, but no doubt the ecclesiastical press will make amends for this indifference of the secular newspapers. Besides Temple has in the "Challenge" his own trumpet on which to blow his loudest!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
