<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1107</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> bk of the Prelude there is a fine description of the impression made on him by London, as one of the great scenes of history. He owns himself little affected by history, especially by English history, but unable to withstand its appeal in London:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>And less</p>
         <p>Than other intellects had mine been used</p>
         <p>To lean upon extrinsic circumstance</p>
         <p>Of record or tradition; but a sense</p>
         <p>Of what in the Great City had been done</p>
         <p>And suffered, and was doing, suffering, still,</p>
         <p>Weighed with me, could support the test of thought;</p>
         <p>And, in despite of all that had gone by,</p>
         <p>Or was departing never to return,</p>
         <p>There I conversed with majesty and power</p>
         <p>Like independent natures.</p>
         <p>…………………………………………….</p>
         <p>The effect was, still more elevated views</p>
         <p>Of human nature. Neither vice nor guilt,</p>
         <p>Debasement undergone by body or mind,</p>
         <p>Nor all the misery forced upon my sight,</p>
         <p>Misery no lightly passed, but sometimes scanned</p>
         <p>Most feelingly, could overthrow my trust</p>
         <p>In what we <hi rend="underline">may</hi> become;</p>
         </div>
         <p>Thus the exalted view of Man to which he had been led by Nature, as he had held constant communion with her in his native mountains, was confirmed in his mind by his contact with the mingled and multitudinous life of a great city.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished reading the Prelude, in which my interest had been rekindled</hi> by the use of it which <persName xml:id="1619">Pringle&#8211;Pattison</persName> has made in his admirable <ref xml:id="936">Gifford Lectures</ref>.</p>
         <p>Rain fell heavily last night. The sky wears a threatening countenance still. On the whole we have not been favoured in the article of weather. Nevertheless, Blanchland has pleased us, and we have found the "Lord Crewe Arms" a pleasant enough hotel.</p>
         <p>In Shotley Church the following inscription over one John Hunter is found:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>My anvil and hammer lies declined</p>
         <p>My bellows have quite lost their wind</p>
         <p>My fire's extinct, my forge decay'd	</p>
         <p>My vice is in the dust all laid</p>
         <p>My coals is spent, my iron gone</p>
         <p>My nails are drove, my work is done</p>
         <p>My mortal's part rests nigh this stone</p>
         <p>My soul to heaven I hope is gone.</p>
         </div>
         <p>On Oct 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1828 Archdeacon Singleton's Minute contains an interesting account of Blanchland which it calls "the very gem &amp; emerald of the mining district".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The general character of the population is good, they are moral and sober, &amp; neither the registers nor public fame give any credit to the idea that the average of human life is shortened in mining societies. In spite of all that is done for them in the way of church &amp; schools, there are some ranters &amp; more Methodists. The inn is large &amp; good, &amp; there is a good picture of <persName xml:id="4178">Lord Crewe</persName>."</p>
         </div>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Forster's car arrived about 3 p.m., and carried us back to Durham in about 1½ hours. Rain fell heavily most of the way, but could not wholly obliterate the landscape, which, in brighter weather would have been ravishingly beautiful. The heather was in full bloom, and the sight of it brought back to memory that wonderful motor drive we had with <persName xml:id="1608">Bishop Mann</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1607" display="no">his wife</persName> in the far&#8211;distant days before the "great tribulation" had fallen on us.<note xml:id="411" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
