<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">987</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Snow began falling about 8 a.m. I was interested, and perhaps also amused, by receiving the following by the morning post:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Chesham Bois Rectory</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Chesham, Bucks.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Dear M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dean,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At our Easter Vestry this week I had the honour of bringing forward your sermon at the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName> on the morning of March 25</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; on the motion of the people's warden &#8211; a gentleman formerly resident in the City, &amp; for many years greatly interested in Church matters &#8211; the following resolution was passed nem. con. "That this Vestry thanks the Dean of Durham for his sermon &amp; for his action, &amp; desires to convey to him its sympathy with the views expressed on the subject of re&#8211;union between the reformed churches."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I am, Sir, Yours truly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="4222">T. H. Fitzpatrick</persName>. Rector</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This epistle comes from within the diocese of Oxford, which is deserving of notice. I have been engaged for most of the day in reading the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Diary. It is fuller &amp; more interesting from 1887 onwards. The number &amp; variety of his activities therein disclosed are truly wonderful, &amp; make me feel very contracted and indolent by comparison. I wrote to <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="318">Ridley</persName> asking for assistance in the work. I received a letter from <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> saying that permission to quote letters must be obtained from all writers. Perhaps the fewness of letters worth quoting makes this a matter of no importance. <persName xml:id="2031">Drummond's</persName> <ref xml:id="948">"Natural Law in the Spiritual World"</ref> seems to have made a great impression on the Warden. "I count the reading of it one of the best things I've done in 1884" he writes, and adds that it caused him to read <persName xml:id="505">Stanley's</persName> <persName xml:id="949">'History of the Jewish Church'</persName> and some books on Biology. This is the nearest approach to a sidelight on his religious development, which I have yet discovered.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
