<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1054</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>Heavy thunderous weather, withal chilly and damp, bad for body and mind. I spent the morning after Mattins in writing a number of letters, among others to <persName xml:id="1611">Hider</persName>, <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, <persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="4344">Nimmins</persName>. <hi rend="italic bold underline">This weeks ecclesiastical papers point unmistakeably to anarchy in the Church of England. <persName xml:id="1748">Lord Halifax</persName> &amp; the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U</orgName>. will go to the stake for unrestricted 'Reservation', let the Bishops say what they will. <persName xml:id="1173">Temple</persName> &amp; his team are out for Disestablishment. The "Record" continues in the old canting, prosecuting style! The <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> pleads for the abolition of Deans! </hi><hi rend="italic">I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked for an hour and a half with the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>. A letter from </hi><persName xml:id="1399"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">S</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Loe Strachey</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> tells me that my letter on "The Clergy &amp; National Service" had arrived too late for insertion, &amp; would appear in the "Spectator" of next week. That letter is accompanied by many sinister circumstances of vacillation in the sending, &amp; delay in the publishing!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">June 22</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Dear M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nimmins,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I think everything is now fairly arranged for <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> to start as a midshipman in August or thereabouts in the service of Mess</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic">Holt &amp; Co., a first–class Liverpool Firm.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Holt wrote to me yesterday to say that the boy's outfit should not be purchased until he gets another notification, but that he ought to have everything matured for immediate action thereafter: &amp; that a sum of £4 or £5 would be the right amount to deposit with the Master for his use during an ordinary voyage to the East.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I hope you will allow me to bear these charges. George has been a good boy with us, &amp; I am much interested in him. It would please me to do this for him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Holt adds that he should learn how to wash clothes. Perhaps M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic">Nimmins will take this in hand.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">If only the War would end, &amp; sea–faring brought back again to its normal state, we sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">all rejoice: but over this we have no control, &amp; so far as war–risks go, it is hard to say whether it is safer to be on sea or on land.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours v. sincerely</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
<p><persName xml:id="4131">Bethune–Baker</persName> has a very sensible letter in the "Times" under the heading "The Church &amp; Liberty"; he draws attention to the miserably inadequate franchise proposed by the <persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130">Archbishops'</persName></persName> C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee's</hi> Report. He claims that a place in the new consultative and legislative assemblies of the Church should be given "to all its members by baptism who care enough to claim it". This cuts at the main root of the whole sacerdotalist plan for transforming a National Church into an Episcopalian Sect.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>