<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1092</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Ideals must speedily wither if they are consciously realized to be but the cloudland of fancy; to a true idealism they are <hi rend="underline">an intense vision of the foundations on which the universe is built</hi>."</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a suggestive definition indeed. <persName xml:id="1619"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pringle Pattison</hi></persName> draws an inference later:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Hence the ideal is precisely the most real thing in the world: and those ranges of our experience, such as religion, which are specifically concerned with the ideal, instead of being treated as a cloud&#8211;cuckoo&#8211;land of subjective fancy, may reasonably be accepted as the best interpreters we have of the true nature of reality" (p. 251&#8211;2).</p>
         </div>
         <p>I read the <ref xml:id="936">Gifford Lectures</ref> for an hour before breakfast. Just before Mattins, a <hi rend="bold underline">knock at my door revealed <persName xml:id="3572">Edgar Dobbie</persName> who came to thank me for my kindness to him. Probably his parents had enjoined this upon him as a duty</hi>. I attended Mattins: &amp; then spent the morning in making selections from the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Journal. I attended Evensong, took Logic for a walk, &amp; resumed work on the Journal until dinner. Then I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Gilbert, and <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
