<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1016</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Heavy rain, much needed in the country &amp; therefore welcome, but woefully dull none the less. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The paper announces the appointment of <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName> to be Dean of Carlisle</hi><hi rend="italic">. So far as personal merits go, and the claims of learning, he ought long ago to have received preferment, but he will hardly strengthen the cause of Anglican liberty by being banished to a remote corner of England: and, of course, his appointment will strengthen the claim of the Fanaticks to have the next bishoprick. Still, for itself &amp; for the indication it offers as to the way the patronage&#8211;wind blows, it is not unwelcome. While the appointment to York certainly (as I judge) expressed the mind of the <persName xml:id="130">Northern Archbishop</persName>, the appointment to Carlisle probably represents that of the <persName xml:id="128">Southern</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A p.c. [post card] from the <persName xml:id="4251">Dean of Chichester</persName> tells me that the Deans have resolved by a large majority to postpone the Decanal Meeting in view of the extraordinary circumstances created by the War. This decision coincides with my own wishes. The meeting would have been difficult to organize &amp; carry through here in Durham.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> asking him what were the circumstances of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> resigning the diocesan Chancellorship, &amp; also begging permission to use three letters of his which are among the Warden's papers. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> called nominally to talk about the Fire&#8211;protection scheme, but really to ease his restlessness over the appointment to <hi rend="bold underline">Durham</hi>. We are poor creatures in these things! I attended Evensong, &amp; took Logic for a walk. On my return <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName> came with a letter from the shipping company in Liverpool: I was pleased to see that <persName xml:id="3655">Lawrence Holt</persName> offers to put him up for the night. This looks well: if the lad can get a good start, I shall feel that one good deed goes to the credit side of my account! </p>
         <p>The afternoon post brought a letter from <persName xml:id="1301"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clarence Tait</hi></persName>. He encloses a type&#8211;written "Extract from General Routine Orders", to the following effect:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Cases have recently occurred where Roman Catholic Churches &amp; Chapels have been used for C. of E. services. This practice must cease. Even where a Roman Catholic Church is in ruins no services other than R.C. are to be held therein."</p>
         </div>
         <p>Clarence writes: "I have attended many services in old ruined churches out here, &amp; it has always struck me as very sensible the way our C. of E. padres carry on their services in the remains of old Churches once used by the French." It is an odd reflection, that such bigotry is actually admired by a considerable &amp; waxing section of the English clergy, who, within the comparatively restricted opportunities of the Established Church, endeavour to imitate it.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I were fetched soon after 7 p.m., &amp; carried to Birtley, where we witnessed the performance of a "Revue", composed, staged, and acted by Belgian munition workers. <persName xml:id="3849">General Montgomery</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3850">his wife</persName> were there, &amp; <persName xml:id="4302">General Lambton</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4303">his wife</persName>. There were some speeches, which protracted the proceedings, &amp; we did not return to the Deanery until 12.30 midnight! The acting was vigorous &amp; enthusiastic: the audience appreciative &amp; eager.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
