<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1039</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Really the only achievement this day is the election of <persName xml:id="3572">Edgar Dobbie</persName> to a King's Scholarship (&#x00A3;50.). I read his papers: interviewed <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, Fairley, &amp; <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName>: &amp; finally proposed him for election to the Chapter. Happily the boy has commended himself to everybody, &amp; his election was welcomed. The fact is important as representing a serious effort to give reality to the preference allotted in our statutes to deserving choirboys. If Dobbie acquits himself well, he may make the arrangement pleasing to the School. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. Walking with Logic after tea, I fell in with <persName xml:id="3512">Colonel Darwin</persName>, &amp; strolled with him for more than an hour. The day which began with rain ended in brilliant sunshine. I have never seen the cathedral &amp; banks reflected in the river more wonderfully. Old <persName xml:id="4177">Miss Crawhall</persName>, an amiable virgin residing in the Banks, is reported to have died. She was an excellent good creature &amp; will be lamented. I attended a meeting of the Library Committee. There was little business, &amp; we soon made an end of it. The morning post brought me from the author a copy of "The Invasion &amp; the War in Belgium from Liege to the Yser, with a sketch of the Diplomatic Negotiations preceding the Conflict by <persName xml:id="4429">Leon van der Essen</persName>, Professor of History in the University of Louvain". He writes from Oxford, where he resides as a refugee.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
