<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1132</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p><persName xml:id="552"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi></persName> came to lunch bringing with him <persName xml:id="2926"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brightman</hi></persName> and a Serbian student from Oxford, who had been in the great retreat. He spoke English fairly, and seemed to understand what I said to him. He said that Germany was regarded with respect in Serbia, for most educated Serbians had gone there for their education: that the German troops had treated the country well: &amp; that the hatred of the people was poured out on the Austrians &amp; Hungarians. I showed the house &amp; the library: he seemed to be interested, but expressed himself with Oriental sedateness.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Headlam showed me a letter from his cousin who is on <persName xml:id="4097">Haig's</persName> staff. It was on the whole cheerful, dwelt on the heavy slaughter of Germans in the recent fighting, &amp;</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">confirmed by reference to actual instances the horrible report that the German Government was organizing the breeding of children by requiring unmarried women to have intercourse with selected men</hi><hi rend="italic">. Two governesses in Germany had written to their friends to say that they were enceintes, and to explain the fact. This seems almost too horrible for belief, &amp; yet the facts seem to be well&#8211;authenticated.</hi>
         </p>
<p>I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong: walked through Houghall wood: and made some sort of a beginning with the Liverpool sermon.</p>
<p>Me<hi rend="superscript underline">ssrs</hi> Twining send [sic] me the invoice for 50 lbs of tea: and <persName xml:id="4244">Haisman</persName> has sent in about 30 out of the 45 tons of coal which he has undertaken to deliver. With a fire &amp; tea one can stand much. There is scarcely anything else that, in present circumstances, one can store in advance.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">After dinner I wrote several letters including one to </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling's</persName> father</hi><hi rend="italic"> inquiring where that young man is, &amp; how he fares. There is, perhaps, none of the old <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> boys whose career in the Army seems to me more fraught with peril. He has many amiable traits, but also many grave faults, &amp; while the first are little likely to be strengthened in military life, the last are but too germane to its lower aspects.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
