<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1146</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was almost a hurricane during the night. The morning post brought me no less than 3 letters from <persName xml:id="2841"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi></persName>, containing a very full description of the fire in Salonika, which he witnessed. Also a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi> describing the process of his restoration of discipline in his company. The governing qualities disclosed in some of these young men are wonderful.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2748"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wilson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> came in to see me during the morning. He told me that some wag had suggested a motto for the new Jewish regiment:&#8211; "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">No advance without security</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi> He thinks my scheme for getting rid of the advertisement&#8211;hoardings near the railway station will be carried through. I spent the morning in preparing a lecture for tomorrow afternoon, &amp; in writing letters: after Evensong <persName xml:id="4357"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Elizabeth</hi></persName> and I walked to Neville's Cross &amp; on in the direction of Dryburn. The views of the Cathedral were superb. We returned through the city in order that I might shew her the doomed hoardings.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">Salmon in the Wear</hi><hi rend="italic">: <persName xml:id="2787">Bishop Quirk</persName> told me yesterday that he had seen a dead salmon on the river bank, &amp; that some of the townsfolk informed him that they had seen two fish in the river this week. Nutton, the senior lay&#8211;clerk, tells me that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">when he came to Durham the jumping of the salmon was a fine spectacle</hi><hi rend="italic">. They ascended the two salmon&#8211;ladders which yet survive. I remember that the old farmer at Finchale assured me that he had seen the river full of dead fish, poisoned by chemicals from the mines.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2463" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nimbus</hi></persName> writes to say that his time has come, &amp; asks me to sign his application for a commission. It seems but yesterday that I was signing poor <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie's</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" contains a long letter from the <persName xml:id="130">Archbishop of York</persName> to the <persName xml:id="3507">Chaplain General</persName> on the work of the clergy. It is more plausible than convincing. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">These ought ye to have done, &amp; not to have left the other undone</hi><hi rend="italic">" will be the comment of any critic who is both candid and well&#8211;informed. It is not true that the War has increased the work of the home&#8211;clergy generally, for much normal activity has ceased altogether (e.g. clubs, classes, services, &amp; entertainments), and much has been curtailed. The lighting arrangements have told in this direction. So far from the clergy being needed for the new kinds of work created by the war, it is the case that numerous lay volunteers have come to the front, so that in many places the practical difficulty is how best to use them. The alleged indispensableness of the clergy can only be true of their administration of the Sacraments, for preaching &amp; conducting services have long been entrusted to laymen, and might be widely performed by them at this crisis. If that unhappy exemption had not been inserted into the 'Military Service Act' these frequent and humiliating explanations and apologies from the Episcopal Bench would not be necessary. The <persName xml:id="128">Abps</persName>, having made a blunder, have not the courage to admit it.<note xml:id="415" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
