<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1029</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<p>A glorious day. Tourists – in spite of the war – wandered about the Cathedral, and in the Banks. Yet the War 'left not itself without witness', for a flock of five aeroplanes, gleaming in the sun, passed overhead. I attended Mattins, and afterwards told <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> that I could not sanction Brown's continuance in the Choir–school as assistant. <persName xml:id="4407">The doctor's</persName> report on his health appears to be decisive.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="4289">Inskip</persName>, the Vicar of Christ Church, Southport, writes as follows:</p>
         <div type="letter">
<p><persName xml:id="4409">"Gipsy Smith</persName>, who I believe is a Wesleyan, to speak at Christ Church on Thursday evening apropos of the <orgName xml:id="239">Y.M.C.A.</orgName> War Work. There is no hall large enough, and the Y.M.C.A. people appealed to me, &amp; after consultation with the Churchwardens I agreed to let them have use of the church. The Mayor, who belongs to the one extreme church here, will preside, or else the President of the Y.M.C.A., who is a Diocesan reader – a very fine man. I hope that this will not create any disaffection, &amp; at the same time that you will feel it to be a step in the direction indicated by yourself." </p>
         </div>
<p>I replied as follows:–</p>
         <div type="letter">
<p><hi rend="italic">Dear M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Inskip,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"Gipsy Smith", I suppose, is not an ordained minister at all, and, therefore, the question raised by the meeting, at which he is announced to speak, being held in Church is not that of "exchange of pulpits", but the more general question of allowing meetings other than those directly contemplated by the Law to be held in a parish church. Here, I apprehend, that your general precedent w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be the custom, w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">was widely existing until the 19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century, of holding meetings of vestry in the parish church: &amp; your particular justification w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be the recent action of the <persName xml:id="166">Bp. of London</persName> in sanctioning the use of a London church by the Presbyterians. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">You w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> claim within your own parish the same right to consider an extraordinary situation </hi><hi rend="italic underline">on its merits</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; to decide, in the circumstances of this dreadful time, that you were justified in making a new departure. It is obvious that very great care must be taken to guard against anything happening at "Gipsy Smith's" meeting w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be, or w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be generally felt to be, unseemly in the House of God. The standard of external reverence varies in the non–liturgical churches, but in </hi><hi rend="italic underline">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> it is, I think, lower than with us; &amp;, therefore, some special care on this point w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> seem to me requisite. That is the main point on w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> fear some danger; on the general grounds of your action, w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">seems to be Christian &amp; neighbourly, I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be of course in sympathy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. Hensley Henson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">P.S. I am very glad you consulted the Churchwardens. That is entirely right. The proceedings in S. Martin's, Trafalgar Square, where laymen of many types have been allowed to give addresses, might serve as a parallel to your permission to "Gipsy Smith".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to Bishop Auckland to be the guests of the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> for the night in order that we might see the gardens of the Castle in their beauty</hi><hi rend="italic">. <persName xml:id="3688">Archdeacon</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3689">Derry</persName> came, <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName> from Edmundbyers &amp; his wife were also there, &amp; of course M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="4194">De Vere</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="4139">Miss Bothamley</persName>. We sate in the garden &amp; talked until Dinner. After dinner I had a little conversation with the Bishop, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">mentioned my notion of inviting <persName xml:id="244">George Adam Smith</persName> to preach on Jan</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">y</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 27</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> next. Moule is a very timid man, and evidently nervous of getting into difficulties, but he professed approbation in vague terms; &amp; I said that, if I determined to invite the Principal, I w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> let him (the Bishop) see the letter of invitation before it was sent</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
