<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1085</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters including one to <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName> in answer to one from him on the difficult subject of the Church's duty in the matter of agitating for peace. <hi rend="bold underline">I think Justice is more important than Peace, &amp; that until Germany has been compelled to restore her conquests &amp; recompense her victims, the victory of Justice has not been won</hi>. After lunch we all went to Ramsgate, and drove about the town to see the damage caused by the air&#8211;raids. It was considerable, but far less so than I had been led by the newspaper descriptions to expect. We went on to Pegwell Bay, and there had tea comfortably in a little garden over&#8211;looking the Bay. It was high tide so that the wide expanse of the bay was covered with water. We could observe the evidences of great activity at Sandwich, where an army of negroes and German prisoners is employed in creating a submarine base. We returned to Birchington by the 5.30 p.m. train. The appearance of the crops on either side of the line, &amp; indeed in every direction is excellent. Ramsgate Harbour was filled with shipping, mostly fishing smacks. There were several patrol boats. Outside at a little distance lay at anchor the well&#8211;armed monitor, which is said to be the objective of the air&#8211;raids. The town has a deserted &amp; woe&#8211;begone appearance. No visitors have arrived, &amp; many residents have gone away. A good many convalescent soldiers were in the streets, &amp; on the front. Artillery horses were picketed in the fields on the way to Pegwell Bay, and a considerable force of soldiers occupied the Terrace on the West Cliff. I noticed in Pegwell Bay with much interest a commodious &amp; almost palatial Working Men's Club, containing accommodation for many residents. This is owned by the Trade Unions, and is maintained for the use of their own members, who pay a very moderate sum for the advantages they obtain. I reflected on the significance of so great a venture of corporate self&#8211;help, &amp; on the whole was pleased.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
