<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">993</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fine day, comparatively warm. There were about 300 men at the Parade, when I preached on S. George. There were but 3 choir&#8211;men, &amp; 2 Boys &#8211; <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> and Coyne. The coughing was again very trying. Most of the men are recruits of a low social type, &amp; the intellectual level is not a high one. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> preached an excellent sermon at Mattins from the words "Leaving us an example". I celebrated the Holy Communion, and attended Evensong. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went a short walk after service, calling at the Robinsons on our way. Then I wrote some letters; &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">sent (at the <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol's</persName> suggestion) a copy of my correspondence with <persName xml:id="166">Ingram</persName><note xml:id="344" n="1"></note> to <persName xml:id="2099">Arthur Benson</persName>, who is said to be intending to follow my example by preaching in the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName></hi>. The reception of my action is a little hard to understand. There appears to be a general determination to treat is [sic] a practically normal episode, raising no issue of principle, &amp; calling for no special treatment. Since condemnation in the present disposition of the public mind is not to be thought of, perhaps belittlement is the wisest policy. Yet the mere circumstance that my preaching was unhindered must have some effect: and the wide publicity given to my sermons cannot be without influence on the general mind. Besides, the sermons themselves give matter for reflection. On the whole, I incline to think that some lasting good will result. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
