<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1005</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Another warm bright day. If agriculture doesn't make the pace now, we deserve to starve presently. Another British transport is reported to have been lost &#8211; torpedoed in the Mediterranean with great loss of life. Two transports in as many days is alarming enough. I followed what has become my normal programme. Mattins, the <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref>, Lunch, the Potato Patch, Tea, Letters &#8211; voila tout! <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3999">Charles Abbey</persName></hi> came to see me. He makes fair progress at school, &amp; will be 18 in October. <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> informed of the highly inconvenient fact that Brown the assistant master has developed measles! <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> came in after dinner. He told me that he had been to Downing S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>, and seen the <persName xml:id="2461">Patronage Secretary</persName>, who made inquiry about <persName xml:id="423">Simpson</persName> of S. Paul's as a suitable Dean of Carlisle. It is evident that my good friend's thoughts still run on 'preferment'. I understand also that there is a hitch about<hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="3919">Philip le Mesurier</persName></hi>'s coming to University College. The difficulty is in the matter of his military service.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
