<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1096</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull wet morning. The villainous weather has arrested our offensive, &amp;, of course, given the Germans full time to recover their wind. However the weather improved as the day advanced, &amp; the afternoon was fine.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I finished <persName xml:id="1619">Pringle&#8211;Pattison's</persName> <ref xml:id="936">Gifford Lectures</ref></hi>. They are certainly very admirable both in form &amp; substance. His criticism of <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall's</persName> view of a limited deity is cogent. On the whole his philosophy is a possible foundation for Christianity, though, perhaps, hardly for orthodoxy. I attended Mattins, &amp; worked at the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Journal. <persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName> came to see me, and stayed to lunch. He came with me into the cathedral, to see what could be done with <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> flags. We decided to have them arranged by Jopling on the chancel screen. We had much talk together about his future, &amp; parted at <persName xml:id="3191" display="no">Jepson's</persName> door, where I had to enter for the meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Governors</orgName>. This was the first meeting of the newly constituted Board. <persName xml:id="3628"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Greenwell</hi></persName> proposed <persName xml:id="2837"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pemberton</hi></persName> as Chairman. <persName xml:id="1659">Burdon</persName> seconded. I said a few words in support, &amp; he was elected without opposition. We sate for nearly 2 hours, for some of the new Governors are fine specimens of the traditional "new broom", and are evidently bent on living up to the character.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3504"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Ann Lambton</hi></persName> writes to say that <persName xml:id="3462"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi></persName> "has been in bed for 3 days suffering from influenza" and therefore cannot attend the meeting tomorrow or the service on Sunday. This is rather disconcerting. I told the <persName xml:id="3718">Mayor</persName>, and he replied "Then you must make a longer speech"! It pleased me to see Colonel Burdon at the Sherburn Meeting, &amp; that he was elected Vice&#8211;Chairman. I asked him to come to the service on Sunday, &amp; he noted the hour in his pocket&#8211;book. The <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName>, rather to my surprise, made no appearance, but sent a letter in which he designated Greenwell for the chairmanship. But Greenwell had himself resolved to decline the office as he possesses no motor.</p>
         <p>I took Logic for a short walk, &amp; then read the papers until dinner&#8211;time, after which I wrote this journal, &amp; frittered away the time until my bed claimed me. A badly wasted day.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
