<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1081</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="4455">Sir Almroth Wright</persName> is a large, loosely&#8211;framed man, with light hair, bushy eye&#8211;brows, an aggressive manner, &amp; spectacles. He cultivates a brusque almost brutal manner of speaking, &amp; perhaps he designed to shock any clerical conventions that I retained! He sketched his theory of morals which appeared to be purely physiological. He described his discussions with the French scientists &amp; politicians, who are much exercised on the subject of the birth&#8211;rate. They appear to take a very debased view of sexual relations. Woman is altogether regarded in this philosophy as the servant of man's gratification.</p>
         <p>I began the day by receiving the Holy Communion in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> celebrated. He speaks clearly but in a monotone, and very rapidly. The service with 8 communicants was over in less than 25 minutes. After breakfast I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, and there <hi rend="bold underline">fell in with <persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName>. He says that M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="2878">Pankhurst</persName> &amp; her crew drove the Government into conceding Female Suffrage, by threatening strikes etc. among the munition workers. So much for women's patriotism</hi>! I wrote to <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>, from whom the morning's post had brought an affectionate letter, &amp; to <persName xml:id="3223">Colonel Gaisford</persName>, who has a command in France. Then I walked to Westminster, &amp; lunched with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2109" display="no">his sister</persName>. He had just come from Lambeth, where he had been discussing army business with the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">His Grace said that <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName> had the acutest head on the Bench: that his was a "most valuable life": that it might be worth thinking over whether he sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> not go to Hereford</hi>. From all this, the sapient Ernest concluded that the Archbishop regards Burge as likely to succeed him. As we were leaving <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, we encountered the Archbishop &amp; <persName xml:id="404">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Davidson</persName>. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The latter said that she had been at <persName xml:id="1173">Temple's</persName> meeting,<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note> &amp; would have joined me in opposing the motion if she had not been the Archbishop's wife! His Grace gave me to understand that he had been snubbing Temple &amp; <persName xml:id="3611">Sheppard</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On my way back to S. Paul's Deanery I looked in again at the Club, and fell in with <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>, who is about to visit the Army in France. <hi rend="bold underline">He expressed agreement with me in the matter of Temple's movement, but we shall not go far together! I exchanged a few words with <persName xml:id="172">Bishop Browne</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="776">Holland</persName></hi>. Then I walked down the Embankment, perspiring profusely. We left the Deanery of S. Paul's in good time to catch the express from Holborn Viaduct to Birchington. <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> saw us off with much display of affection. We travelled easily &amp; without change. <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> was on the platform to meet us. <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> looks very well in spite of worries &amp; the alarms of life on the southern coast.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
