<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1143</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="4277"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hobhouse</hi></persName> writes to thank me for my letter in the "Times", and to suggest that the clergy sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> petition for the release of the "Absolutists".<note xml:id="414" n="1"></note> She enclosed the draft of a petition, &amp; invited suggestions for its amendment. I replied at once in disapproval of this scheme. The clergy might have acted with effect <hi rend="underline">if</hi> they had not been put out of action by that unfortunate "exemption". As it is, their petitioning for the release of men who refuse military service could only bear one interpretation viz. that they themselves sympathized with the <hi rend="underline">objection</hi>, &amp; not with the objecting <hi rend="underline">conscience</hi>. <persName xml:id="4143">Brocklehurst</persName> of Giggleswick, like <persName xml:id="3167">Savage</persName> of Hexham, has left his parish to take up work with the <orgName xml:id="239">Y.M.C.A.</orgName> But this does not seem to me <hi rend="underline">in pari materi&#x00E2;</hi> [equivalent]. The claims of one's own duties at home are stronger than <hi rend="underline">that</hi> kind of military service: at least, they very well <hi rend="underline">may</hi> be; &amp;, if one thinks they <hi rend="underline">are</hi>, there is clearly a duty not to leave them. But military service proper stands on another footing altogether. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[181]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>September 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1917</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hobhouse,</p>
         <p>I do not think it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be wise to present a Petition w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi>, in stating with some completeness the case for the "Absolutists", did by that very circumstance provoke opposition, &amp; provide a large surface for debate. Nor can I think that the clergy, albeit theoretically the most obvious, w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be actually the most effective persons for the purpose of framing &amp; presenting a petition.</p>
         <p>Would it not be a less provocative &amp; more effectual procedure to present a petition asking for the appointment of a small Commission to consider the case of the "conscientious objectors" in question, &amp; to recommend the exercize of the Royal Proclamation for their release, if in their judgment such exercize were desirable?</p>
         <p>I think you are yourself the person who sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> undertake this, or any other action designed for the same object, &amp; your invitation for signatures w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> probably be accepted by many. The quality rather than the quantity of signatures is important. In the present circumstances of the nation very many will just put aside as intolerable the suggestion that they sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> do <hi rend="underline">anything</hi> for conscientious objectors, although their own reason &amp; conscience, if brought into action, w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> certainly make them very zealous for the relief of these men.</p>
         <p>I return the enclosed as you may have use for it.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson.</p>
         </div>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="543"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray&#8211;Smith</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2563" display="no">his wife</persName> came to lunch: also a party from Ramside viz. <persName xml:id="2895">Penelope</persName>, Miss Savage, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bovill. I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked with <persName xml:id="4357">Elizabeth</persName> for more than an hour. The weather has been perfect, and the country looks its very best.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
