<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">969</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The wind has veered round, &amp; now blows strongly from the West. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; I went out before breakfast, &amp; bought newspapers. There is nothing unusually startling in them, save that the loss of ships from mines laid by submarines seems to increase, which is a very grave matter. We walked again for 2 hours before lunched</hi> [sic]<hi rend="italic">, &amp; on returning to the Hotel I wrote to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">A bundle of copies of the "Christian Commonwealth" arrived, containing a verbatim report of my Sunday morning sermon in the <orgName xml:id="37">"City Temple"</orgName>. The afternoon post brought me a friendly letter from the editor of the "Guardian"</hi><hi rend="italic">. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked the whole length of the parade eastwards. After dinner we had much talk of ghost stories, communications with the departed, &amp; such&#8211;like alluring but rather unwholesome subjects. Mine host expresses more confidence in </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="614">Sir O. Lodge</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> than I can myself feel, but he cannot bring himself to accept the machinery for posthumous communications set forward in "Raymond".<note xml:id="343" n="1"></note> Not the least argument against all this theorising is the trivial &amp; worthless character of the messages which are alleged to come from 'the other world'. These would disgrace the authors, had they been still living in the flesh: it is difficult to suppose that the conditions of the post&#8211;mortem life are more unfavourable to intelligence than those of the life present.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
