<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[152]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1113</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A glorious morning. Durham has a very fascinating aspect in the clear sunlight. It would be hard to leave it in any case, and perhaps also a mistake. Anyway this awful <ref xml:id="996">Memoir</ref> <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be finished. <hi rend="bold underline">I ordered <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName> to open the large western doors which part the Galilee from the Nave of the Cathedral. The effect was excellent, far more so than I had expected. It surprised me to hear Freeman say that the doors had never been opened in his recollection</hi>. I attended Mattins and Evensong: also I walked with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Logic. The rest of my time was devoted to the "Memoir". The <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> letters from Oxford while he was an undergraduate give the impression of a very happy life. He rejoiced in his friends, in his work, in his games, above all, in his home. The tone, contents, and frequency of his letters to his parents, and of their letters to him leave a very pleasing impression on they [sic] mind. Evidently the habit and atmosphere of his home were thoroughly wholesome. <persName xml:id="4108">Sir John Anson</persName> expected his son to consult him about everything, and followed his course with detailed and intelligent interest. The project of his son's going to Berlin as a teacher to the Crown Prince's children greatly fluttered the excellent Baronet, &amp; its abandonment gave him great satisfaction.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
