<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1045</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The morning post brought a protest against hustling female suffrage through without a referendum both to men &amp; to women. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I signed it, &amp; returned it to the Committee forthwith.</hi> The newspaper reports the death of <persName xml:id="4198"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Principal Denny</hi></persName>. I had much talk with him on shipboard returning from Canada in 1909. He was in many respects a notable man, but latterly he was very fanatically prohibitionist. <persName xml:id="2806"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bayley</hi></persName> came to lunch. I attended Evensong, in the course of which a thunderstorm broke over the Cathedral. Immediately after service I baptized <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anthony Peter Wilkinson</hi>. While I read the Baptismal Service the candidates for Confirmation were assembling in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> held my book at the Font. After tea I took my guests over the Cathedral. As we concluded our tour, we encountered old <persName xml:id="3628">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Greenwell</persName>, and had some talk with him. <persName xml:id="3652">Colonel Herne</persName> came to dinner. I gave a provisional promise that I would preach to his men at Barnard Castle on the 29th of July. Open&#8211;air speaking is a great strain on me now. Thirty years ago I thought little of it, but now &#8211;.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
