<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">967</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright morning, but bitterly cold. After writing some letters <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I wandered forth onto the parade. We walked the length of the pier. It has a glass screen protecting from the East wind &#8211; a generous &amp; almost indispensable provision. We bought some stationary &amp;c., and got back to the Hotel for lunch. After the meal I retired to my room, &amp; rested. Before tea I wrote to <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Radford</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName>. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> arrived about tea&#8211;time, having travelled from Norwich</hi>. We went for a walk on the sea&#8211;front until it grew too cold for such frail elderly gentlemen as we have now both become. The afternoon post brought a friendly letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName></hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Beeching</hi> tells me he uses the "revised Psalter" in Norwich Cathedral. This is nothing more than a scheme for a revised Psalter suggested by the Committee which the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C</persName>. appointed from the members of the Convocations: nevertheless Beeching holds himself free to treat it as sufficiently authoritative to replace the statutory Psalter in the Prayer&#8211;book. I told him that his position was in my view quite untenable, and c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not but prove in effect quite anarchical. He retorted rather feebly by pointing to <hi rend="bold underline">the non&#8211;use of the copes in Durham Cathedral</hi>. But I replied that the disuse dated from 1759: that to restore a canonical practice abrogated by disuse required on canonical principles something more than individual authority: that canons were not of perpetual obligation as are statutes. These contentions he was unable to rebut, &amp; had to plead that in the extraordinary circumstances of the C. of E., and with respect to indisputable &amp; undisputed matters such as the mistranslations in the P.B. Psalter, wh. the revised version of the Abp's C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi> corrects, there was a sufficient justification for his confessedly illegal procedure. But all this appears to me no better than special pleading. <hi rend="bold underline">At all hazards we must cling to the plane of law</hi>: once driven from that, we are on an inclined road, &amp; must be driven downwards into anarchy.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
