<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1102</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I finished <ref xml:id="938">"Higher Education</ref> and the War" by <persName xml:id="4151">John Burnet</persName>, Dean of the Faculty of Arts in St Andrew's</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was strongly recommended to me both by <persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName> and by <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName>, and I think with good reason, for it is an unusually informing &amp; thought&#8211;provoking book. Mainly it consists of a careful examination of the German system of education, and a severe condemnation of it. This leads up to a comparison with the Scottish system, and some valuable suggestions for improvement. His </hi><hi rend="italic underline">obiter dicta</hi><hi rend="italic"> are illuminating. <persName xml:id="1153">Jowett</persName> would hardly have endorsed his verdict on the value of translations. He holds that "there is not and never will be any possibility of contact with the spirit of antiquity except through the language", and adds, "people who talk about learning it through translations only show that they do not know what it is". It would be an ill thing if translations were equally useless in the case of the Scriptures, and yet, if the argument be sound, it is hard to see why they should not be.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked at the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Life until the post came bringing a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. Then I wrote to him, &amp; to <hi rend="bold underline">the flying&#8211;boy <persName xml:id="3542">Norman Henderson</persName></hi>.</p>
         <p>The weather has been bad today. All night it rained, and continued raining all day. However we would not be wholly confined, but donned our mackintoshes &amp; walked on to the moors after lunch. The water&#8211;courses are everywhere in a plethoric bubblement, and the Derwent has grown into a considerable stream. We put up a brace of black&#8211;cock, and several companies of grouse &amp; returned to the hotel very wet &amp; well content.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, and then started to read <persName xml:id="4321">Lady Markby's</persName> monograph on her <persName xml:id="4320">husband</persName>, which has been published by the Clarendon Press in a form which suggests itself as suitable for my account of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">One great defect as a biographer is becoming daily more apparent to me. I instinctively criticize where I ought merely to describe, or relate, or record. But the indiscriminating &amp; invariable laudation into which biographers commonly drift offends my sense of truth and generally provokes a disgust in my mind.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
