<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1040</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended Mattins, and had an interview with an official from the Labour Department who wanted my advice as to the choice of chairmen for various committees it is proposed to set up with a view to the questions created by demobilisation. <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3470">Canon Sykes</persName> came to lunch. I presided at a lecture on Proportional Representation which had been arranged by the Unionist Agent, but which professed to be non&#8211;partisan. The lecturer, Humphreys, was portentously dull, &amp; the audience, which filled the room at the County Hotel, was visibly bored. From this I went to the lecture room on Palace Green, &amp; heard a very interesting lecture on the Monastery of Durham by old <persName xml:id="3666">Canon Fowler</persName>. The large &amp; closely attentive audience attested the lecturer's popularity. In proposing a vote of thanks, I made a few observations on past &amp; present. The news from the Front is good. Another British offensive has captured 6000 prisoners, &amp; captured some strong positions in the neighbourhood of Ypres. The attack was prefaced by the most extensive mine explosions of the War: &amp; this was heard in London.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
