<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">983</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">More snow. The winter is endless. I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. Then, the newspaper not appearing, I went into town, &amp; fetched it. The disastrous weather is paralyzing everything at the Front. I started going through the <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName> letters. They are not rich in biographical material. Rather an unexpected effect of my <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName> sermons was a letter from the Serbian Minister in the following terms:&#8211;</hi> 
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Sir, I noticed in the papers some weeks ago reports of sermons preached by you on the future union of the churches, &amp; I have recently had some enquiries from our high ecclesiastics, who are very interested in the matter and wish for particulars. I should be very much obliged to you if you could inform me if your sermons have been published, &amp; where I can obtain them, in order to get the information we want. We consider the subject a very important one for the future, &amp; would like to support the idea among our church people. I should be very grateful for any information you can give me, &amp; remain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours truly</hi>	  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">For W. Firanovitz.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Serbian Minister.</hi>
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">It is not altogether easy to explain that I was concerned with the divisions of English Christianity, &amp; incidentally to fasten his attention on the distressing unreality of the "national" character of the Church of England. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Our Ritualists have been making a desperate effort to persuade these good Serbians that the English Church professes a version of Christianity kindred to their own: but, it would appear that suspicions have entered the Serbian embassy as to the truth of this representation</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
