<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1079</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold underline">At the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaenum</orgName> I found <persName xml:id="225">Archbishop Bernard</persName></hi>, &amp; had some interesting conversation with him about the state of Ireland, and ecclesiastical affairs. He is not very hopeful about the Convention, and expects that within a few weeks there will be an insurrection in Ireland, not in Dublin, but sporadic in the country.<note xml:id="400" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">He professed himself a resolute opponent of the feminist movement, but admitted that he was the only member of the Irish bench who took this view</hi>. He said that he had <persName xml:id="3831">Kempthorne's</persName> name mentioned for the succession to the Primacy. I extracted from him a promise to be the preacher on Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> next,<note xml:id="240" n="2"></note> if no Irish crisis intervened to hinder him. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I wrote to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> an account of last night's meeting</hi>.<note xml:id="401" n="3"></note> I walked back to S. Paul's &amp; lunched with <persName xml:id="427">mine hosts</persName><persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. After luncheon <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> &amp; I walked together as far as S. James's Park, &amp; there sate &amp; talked together. Then I called on <persName xml:id="2416">Lady Ilbert</persName>, where <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me, &amp; we had tea. <persName xml:id="645">Sir Courtenay Ilbert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2107">Fisher</persName> came in, &amp; we had some talk. I returned to the Deanery &amp; found <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName> awaiting me. Later, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I dined with <persName xml:id="2244">Sir John</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2708">Lady Struthers</persName>. The company consisted of <persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName>, <persName xml:id="2688">Lord</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2768">Lady Charnwood</persName>, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hanbury, besides ourselves. I had much interesting conversation with Lord Haldane &amp; with mine host. Haldane spoke much, and freely, about Germany. He thought it impossible for an outsider to form a judgment on the recent developments in Germany, but 'as a matter of speculation' was of opinion that the war might end this year. He said that he had interrogated many of the returned prisoners, &amp; that he come to the conclusion that the ill–treatment alleged against the Germans had probably been greatly exaggerated. Our men hardly ever knew a word of German; they gave far more trouble than any other prisoners: &amp; generally made themselves a nuisance. Add, that the Germans were undoubtedly short of provisions, and it was not necessary to ascribe the hardships of our prisoners to the deliberate malignity of their captors.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
