<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">995</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful day, &amp; so warm that my study&#8211;fire was unlighted, &amp; I felt no discomfort. I attended Mattins; &amp; afterwards, settled to work at the <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName> letters. [The following, wh. I noticed by chance in turning the pages of a dull book, may still hold good:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"After dinner I had renewed conversations with <persName xml:id="4317"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Macintosh</hi></persName>. Alluding to the style of speaking in the House of Commons, he characterized it by saying, that 'the true light in wh. to consider it, <hi rend="underline">was as animated conversation on public business</hi>'; and, he added, it was 'rare for any speech to succeed in that body wh. was raised on any other basis'." (v. Rush. <ref xml:id="952">"A residence at the Court of London. 1819&#8211;1825[^"^]. 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> series. vol I. p. 44.)</ref> </p>
         </div>
         <p>From the strangers' gallery I have listened to debates in the H. of C. from time to time during my residence in West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> (1900&#8211;1912), and I am disposed to accept the phrase "animated conversation" as a fairly faithful description of the speaking.]	</p>
         <p>After lunch I went to the potato&#8211;patch, &amp; laboured for rather more than two hours. My letter on <persName xml:id="2688">Horton's</persName> Sabbatarianism appears in the <ref xml:id="986">"Times"</ref>, and is followed by a letter from <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName>. I amused myself after dinner by looking at <persName xml:id="4286"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Huxley</hi>'s</persName> <ref xml:id="953">'<hi rend="underline">Life</hi>'</ref>. Many of the letters, there published, are quite undeserving of publication, but there are some good things. He was severe on <persName xml:id="337">Newman</persName>: ("<hi rend="underline">That man is the slipperiest sophist I have ever met with. <persName xml:id="3629">Kingsley</persName> was entirely right about him</hi>.") He could not stomach Positivism<note xml:id="345" n="1"></note>: "<hi rend="underline">Of all the sickening humbugs in the world, the sham pietism of the Positivists is to me the most offensive</hi>." He has a strongly&#8211;expressed letter (vol. III. p. 121) in answer to a correspondent who had asked his views about "alcohol as a stimulant to the brain in mental work".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The circumstances of my life have led me to experience all sorts of conditions in regard to alcohol, from total abstinence to nearly the other end of the scale, &amp; my clear conviction is the less the better, though I by no means feel called upon to forgo the comforting and cheering effects of a little."</p>
         </div>
         <p>On the whole, I think, that is about my own opinion. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
