<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[11]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">974</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Snowing heavily. It cleared up about noon, &amp; there was sun, &amp; a thaw. But the aspect of everything is wintry indeed. I attended Mattins: paid the wages: wrote letters: read the papers &amp;c. &#8211; an ill&#8211;spent day. After dinner I read to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> extracts from the Official Report of the Armenian massacres. The scale and intensity of the cruelty are almost unbelievable: but the performances of the Germans in France are fully equal in barbarity. <hi rend="bold underline">A certain number of insulting letters come to me daily, most are evidently the work of "shop&#8211;boy ritualists"</hi>, but some indicate a superior social type. <hi rend="italic">I wrote to Hodder &amp; Stoughton suggesting that they should publish the "trilogy" of sermons preached in the <orgName xml:id="37">"City Temple"</orgName> and in S. Sepulchre's with an "Introduction". The occasion was of sufficient interest to make it important that as much emphasis as possible should be placed upon it. I attended Evensong. The poverty of the male voices was painfully apparent in the Handel Anthem. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> told me that he had read the "City Temple" sermons, and thought them very good. On the whole I think the general verdict on those discourses is quite as favourable as I have any right to expect. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
