<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1163</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I made a beginning of the "Trafalgar Day" sermon: and wrote the ‘topical' exordium, which brings me, or ought to bring me, to my real subject. At this point, of course, the real difficulty begins, for I am not quite clear on the point <hi rend="underline">what</hi> precisely I propose to preach about. The contrast between 1805 and 1917 suggests many reflections, but none seems to lead naturally to an apologia for the idea of a National Church. War brings a severe strain on the framework of national life. Institutions are sternly tested, &amp; either perish altogether or emerge transformed. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> seem reasonable to strengthen whatever factors make for national harmony, by mitigating the sharp divisions of class &amp; interest, or by positive service of an unifying nature. War emphasizes the divisive factors, &amp; exasperates the normal antipathies. It creates an atmosphere of uncertainty and insecurity &#8211; &amp; stimulates a gambling disposition in men's minds. There is something more than the common desire for change, &amp; something less than the common reluctance to run risks.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
