<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1156</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A glorious morning. The hilarity of the rooks was extreme &amp; contagious! There were air raids on London last night. <persName xml:id="601"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Muir&#8211;Mackenzie</hi></persName> writing to me on Sunday a letter wh. reached me this afternoon, says: "<hi rend="underline">Things are much worse than the papers represent, &amp; I think that there is a good deal of danger or demoralization</hi>". I attended Mattins, &amp; then spent the morning on the <ref xml:id="996">"Life"</ref>. <persName xml:id="807"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Helen Beeching,</hi></persName> quite unrecognisable &amp; now called <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Fanning</hi>, came to lunch. A young Wesleyan minister from Stockton, named <persName xml:id="4258">Harvey</persName>, called to inquire about library facilities in Durham. He said that his sect was working at the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. In conversation he disclosed the fact that his sect is rent with a controversy between "obscurantists" &amp; "progressives". I was surprised to hear him speak of <persName xml:id="3261">Maitland</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName> as the men who pointed out the road to liberty by their doctrine of corporations. I attended Evensong, and then walked with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>. <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName> reports that there is a good crop of potatoes in the chapter&#8211;field. Under one root no less than 84 potatoes were lifted. He estimates that the total crop will exceed two tons of potatoes; this will suffice for the consumption of the choir&#8211;school for the next year, i.e. until the new crops come into use.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
