<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1160</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> before breakfast. <persName xml:id="636">Ernest</persName> went off to Manchester. I attended Mattins, &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="277">Lord Portsmouth</persName>. Then I presided over a meeting of Chapter, at which <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry's</persName> offer to present a Processional Cross was accepted. Old <persName xml:id="3206">Victor Williamson</persName> brought two military friends to the Cathedral, &amp; lunch. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> acted as guide, as I was too busy. At 2.30 p.m. I attended a meeting of the Ruri&#8211;decanal Conference, &amp; addressed the members on the Archbishops' Committee's Report on "Church &amp; State". There was an interesting discussion in which <persName xml:id="3854">Bothamley</persName> distinguished himself! Finally they came to an unanimous vote deprecating action during the War. I walked with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; then wrote letters to Lady Londonderry and to <persName xml:id="66">Frank Pember</persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" announces the death of <persName xml:id="4099">Edward Pember</persName>, aged 19, flying in France. It is a lamentable occurrence. I baptized the boy, &amp; was hoping to get a better knowledge of him. And now he too is gone, &amp; his father has no son left</hi>. "What is good for a bootless bene?"</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2768">Lady Charnwood</persName> arrived about tea&#8211;time. After an early dinner <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's Institute, where I was pledged to preside at a magic&#8211;lantern lecture given by Byron&#8211;Dolphin on his experiences in Belgium. The lecture was too long &#8211; more than two hours &#8211; and the slides were rather monotonous, but Byron&#8211;Dolphin is a fluent speaker, and he had many stirring experiences to relate. We got back to the Deanery about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
