<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1161</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was a sudden change in the weather early this morning, and, when I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. rain mingled with sleet was falling. When, after the celebration, we returned to the Deanery, it was snowing hard! An early winter is probably unfavourable to our military plans, though it saves Russia from the possibility of invasion. <persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> brought a message from <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> that the <persName xml:id="234">School</persName> would not come to the Cathedral on account of the inclement weather! So I had to preach my Eton sermon, which had been selected for the special benefit of the Boys, to a handful of women and 10 elderly men! Byron Dolphin came to lunch. He is much cast down at the smallness of the audience at his lecture last night, but the spectacle of the empty cathedral this morning rebuked the exorbitance of his expectations. An old clergyman, named Young, who had been commended to us by Lady Lawrence, came to lunch. He too was amazed at the smallness of the Cathedral congregation. It <hi rend="underline">was</hi> very mortifying to the Dean's importance, &amp; the Preacher's vanity!!! Perhaps these experiences are best regarded as disciplinary or purgatorial. We motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring calling at Ramside on the way, where we had some talk with the <persName xml:id="2837">Pembertons</persName><persName xml:id="2843"></persName>. Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, the parish of <persName xml:id="4232">Bernard Gilpin</persName>, whose tomb is a conspicuous feature in the large parish&#8211;church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Michael, is one of the most famous, &amp; perhaps the best endowed parish in the county. It has been greatly reduced in area by the formation of new parishes, but still contains no less than 9000 parishioners. The Rectory, built in 1667 is a commodious house standing in 7 acres, mostly garden. The people are almost entirely miners: there are many Dissenters; and the Roman Catholics are numerous. <hi rend="bold underline">The Rector, <persName xml:id="4101">Adamson</persName>, an elderly &amp; depressed man with a weak manner &amp; a venerable beard, spoke in a hopeless way of place &amp; people. </hi>There was a crowded church, and I preached about the War. We returned to the Deanery immediately after the service. </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
