<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1165</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I received the Holy Communion in S. Gregory's Chapel. I attended Mattins, and then worked at the Trafalgar Day sermon. I wrote to <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName> inviting co&#8211;operation at the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative C. Council</orgName>. After lunch I spent an hour in showing a party of wounded soldiers over the Cathedral. Then I attended Evensong. I wrote to the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> offering to contribute &#x00A3;5. towards the cost of sending copies of his "Address" to the lay&#8211;members of the R.C.C., &amp; suggesting that some of us Northerners might send a signed letter to the "Times" protesting against the meeting in November. Also to <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> on the same subject &amp; to the <persName xml:id="2416">Bishop of S. David's</persName>. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> came to see me; he is rather vexed at the refusal of the <persName xml:id="3897">Mayor</persName> &amp; Corporation to undertake his housing project. We dined with the <persName xml:id="2810">Pooles</persName><persName xml:id="3482"></persName> to meet <persName xml:id="4316">Mackenzie</persName>, the late Headmaster of Uppingham, who was formerly Headmaster of Durham. We went with Poole to the House prayers, and I gave the benediction. The boys look pleased &amp; happy: but I could wish the Examiners' Reports were more satisfying.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
