<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We went to S. Gregory's chapel, &amp; received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. After breakfast we walked to the station, &amp; caught the 10.29 train to York. The weather, which had been threatening, became definitely hostile: &amp; we arrived in York under heavy rain, which continued most of the day. I spent the afternoon in a long talk </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">with the new Dean</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><persName xml:id="4346"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Foxley Norris</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, on affairs ecclesiastical. He is a man with an interesting heredity; of artistic temperament; of varied parochial experience: of good presence: &amp; good intentions. He has been a Tractarian by training, &amp; counts still as a High Churchman: but he has no sympathy with the new "Catholics", &amp; is taking a "wider" attitude. He told me that in his whole experience as a parish priest, he had never known a case in which the reserved sacrament was necessary. The <persName xml:id="130">Archbishop of York</persName>, he says, suffers stick from his unfortunate speech about "sacred memories" of the Kaiser.<note xml:id="416" n="1"></note> So deeply is it resented that, when his Grace preaches, the people will not come to hear him. This is an illustration of the irrational dourness of Yorkshiremen. I preached in the Minster at the Harvest Thanksgiving which was held at the inconvenient hour, 5 p.m. The service was held in the Choir, which was fairly filled. Acoustically York Minster has an evil reputation, but I was assured that everybody could hear. We returned to Durham after dinner. On the way I had much talk with a wounded officer, who told me that his name was Brown, that he was a nephew of the popish Canon Brown, &amp; that he had been educated at <placeName xml:id="90">Ushaw</placeName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
