<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather had cleared during the night, and became quite fine and warm. We went into York for the Celebration of Holy Com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> at 10.30 a.m. It was very impressive: out of the very large congregation, only nine persons communicated. No one could fail to see that it was "High Mass". But the Prayer Book service was faithfully rendered, &amp; there were few 'tricks', no incense, and a great display of copes. The singing was excellent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">At 12 noon the nave was completely filled by a congregation of Free&#8211;masons and members of Friendly Societies. I preached my sermon, and was assured by many persons that the "loud speakers" worked effectively, &amp; that I spoke suitably, so that the sermon was well&#8211;heard. The people outside the Cathedral declared that they could hear everything</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Ella and I lunched at the Deanery, and then I went off to London. On arriving at </hi><hi rend="italic">King's Cross, I went to the Athenaeum, where </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I found the Archbishop of Canterbury, who was very insistent that I should speak in the Assembly, &amp;, perhaps, answer</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Joynson Hicks</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">who will be a protagonist against the Measure</hi><hi rend="italic">. This was also </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic">'s view, so that I shall probably have to speak.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">I found the Archbishop reading the article headed</hi><hi rend="italic"> "</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">The Passing of National Churches</hi><hi rend="italic">" </hi><hi rend="italic underline">which I have written in the July number of the "Nineteenth Century, and After". He expressed approval, and said it was very interesting. My reference to the Enabling Act as an Act of Disestablishment had evidently impressed him with the notion that I was coming to concede the inevitability of that Act: and I conceded that the development of "Labour" was having a considerable effect on my mind</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined in the Club, and had much talk with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenyon</hi><hi>, who sate at the next table. Like most members of our English </hi><hi rend="underline">intelligentsia</hi><hi> he speaks dogmatically about social &amp; economic matters, concerning which he has, and can have, no more than a theoretical acquaintance. This explains the </hi><hi rend="underline">vogue</hi><hi> of Communism in Oxford. Men like the Master of Balliol have read &amp; talked incessantly, but they know little of popular life as it actually proceeds in the great industrial centres. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Deanery at Westminster, and was hospitably received by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Norris</hi><hi>, just returned from Sweden.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
