<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored into Durham, and admitted two probationers in the Diaconess's Home to be "Church Workers', and gave them an address. The Warden, a Mirfield Father, named D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Drury was there. He told me that Mirfield was "running over" with aspirants to the Ministry.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The afternoon post brought me a request from the Archbishop of Canterbury that I should send to him Stephen Allen's dossier, which accordingly I did, having first arranged the 14 documents in order for his Grace's convenience</hi><hi>. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The Archbishop adds a note thanking me for my "Diocesan Magazine with its exceedingly valuable P.R. papers</hi><hi>". I asked Carter whether he had reason to think that my gibes against the Evangelical party had given offence, and he replied in the negative. Probably the Evangelicals, who are supporting the book, are being much badgered by the "Protestant underworld", &amp; not unwilling to be publicly dissociated from it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Cox</hi><hi> sends me "</hi><hi rend="underline">A Quaker Saint of Cornwall Loveday Hambly and her guests" by L.V. Hodgkin</hi><hi>," and invites me to use it as a peg on which to hang an article on Quakerism. He leaves me free to make a longer article, but that does not mean as much as it once did, for he adds, "</hi><hi rend="underline">I like to look upon 18pp. as an outside limit</hi><hi>." When the venerable quarterlies themselves yield to the modern craze for brevity, the old literary stateliness has indeed come to an end. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
