<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Rogation Sunday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dull morning, with threatenings of rain. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 6 communicants including Lionel and James.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left the Castle at 9.40 a.m., &amp; motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Stockton</hi><hi> through wind and rain. There I read the lessons &amp; preached in the new Church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul. The Mayor &amp; Corporation attended: there was large congregation: and a hearty service. There were no "Labour" protests though I spoke severely about the Atheism of the Russia revolutionaries.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Frank Brown</hi><hi> &amp; his daughter. He talked much, and (so far as I could understand his speech, which his tongue&#8211;operation has grievously affected) interestingly. He is a very devoted Liberal in politics, but has no use for L. G.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">West Hartlepool</hi><hi>, where I had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Poole</hi><hi>. His wife was in bed with a small operation on her foot, but, in spite of it, was as cheerful &amp; talkative as usual. Then I went on to </hi><hi rend="underline">S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Oswald's</hi><hi>, &amp; had some talk with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilburne</hi><hi> before Evensong. I read lessons, and preached. There was a large congregation, but the church was not crowded. The day had cleared &amp; the fineness of its later hours tempted many into the country. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There can be no doubt about the ill&#8211;effect which the cheapness of motors is having on church attendance. The procession of a motor seems to cancel duty in this matter. Even choirmen and other church workers yield to the prevailing fashion. It seems to be understood that only when the weather is bad or threatening can a motor&#8211;owning Christian be expected to worship his Maker!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
