<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left the Castle at 10.30 a.m. and motored to Darlington where I caught the 11.21 a.m. express to King's Cross. I left my bags at 21 Park Lane, &amp; went on to the Club. After visiting the hair&#8211;dresser, I had tea in the Club, and read a novel until it was time for me to return to Park Lane to dress for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The papers announce the voting in the London Diocesan Conference, where the Revised Prayer Book was approved by a majority of 64. There were large minorities both clerical and lay. The division in the lay house was 176 to 168. This is the first really serious 'set&#8211;back' which the Book has received. The voting shows how greatly Ingram's influence has waned in London. In the quarter of a century, during which he has held the See, discipline has completely broken down, and he has quite plainly lost all control over the clergy. Hence this vote of no&#8211;confidence</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined at Grillions. It was a small party viz: </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Sir George Murray</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lord Hanworth</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lord Haldane</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Archbishop of York</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Edmund Gosse</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop of Durham </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>One more whom I don't know (? De Bunsen)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We talked a good deal on subjects ecclesiastical and religious. The subject of the Quakers came up, and the Unknown said that he came of Quaker stock, being connected with the Gurneys and the Frys. His mother had known, and travelled with, Elizabeth Fry. Lord Hanworth was evidently uncomfortable in my company, and took himself off to sit by Abp. Lang on the first decent plea! He has not been behaving well over the Revised Prayer Book, and we shall probably come to an open collision over it before long. I came away from the Hotel Cecil soon after 10 p.m., and returned to Park Lane.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
