<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Quakers in the American Colonies</hi><hi>". On the whole, the narrative is rather disconcerting, for the Friends seem to have been as fertile in expedients for explaining away the severe precepts of the Gospel as other Christians who made less profession of exact obedience. Their refusal to fight themselves went along with a willingness to fight by deputy which robs it of moral impressiveness: and their domestic disputes do not seem to have been markedly inferior in pettiness, frequency, &amp; venom to those of the less "spiritual" sects. The one thing they can claim is a curious </hi><hi rend="underline">flair</hi><hi> for anticipating the directions of Christian development, and this </hi><hi rend="underline">is</hi><hi> a very striking phenomenon, and goes some way to explain, and even to justify, the large attention bestowed on so small a sect. In their condemnation of war, in their emphasis on the social expressions of Christianity, in their hostility to any established Church, in their emphasis on the ministry of women, in their contempt for religious observances, the Quakers were "blazing a trail" which in later generations Christians generally would follow. Among the denominations of Christendom they are the tack&#8211;finders.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[154]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Scarbrough</hi><hi> expressed himself warmly in praise of my speech. </hi><hi rend="underline">He said that many peers stayed on "to hear the Bishop of Durham"; and that the general opinion was flatteringly favourable</hi><hi>. If any conceited thoughts were bred in my mind by these compliments, they were quickly banished by an inspection of the morning papers, which gave scant notice of his lordship's oration! They do, however, report at some length the speech of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Dawson</hi><hi>, which was a valuable contribution to the discussion of the whole problem of sobriety. I sent him a note of thanks, asking him to send me a copy, if he published it as a pamphlet. I wrote to the Secretary of the Anti&#8211;Prohibition League declining a </hi><hi rend="underline">very</hi><hi> civil request to dine with that society. But, though I am strongly opposed to Prohibition, I do not care to associate myself with an association over which Lord Lonsdale presides.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Also I wrote to Wilson of S. Edmund's, Gateshead: and to Llewelyn, a rash youth who tells me that he is to be married in August, though he is not yet ordained to the priesthood.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to Auckland by the 1.15 a.m. [sic] express: and found that Richards had arrived about an hour before. After dinner we had some conversation about the Professorship. He will send me his answer in a few days.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
