<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Di Darling sent me a note explaining the absence of her father and herself from yesterday's sermon. He was out of town, and she had a headache.</hi><hi> Also I received a letter from Richards saying that he would come to Auckland on Wednesday. His son–in–law, the Master, tells me that he will probably accept the professorship: and I hope that he will, for, if he doesn't, I shall be "shut up to" Arbuthnot Nairne, whose wife is described to me as a "terror". !!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Master was good enough to take me to task on my use of the word "considering" which has become in his judgment a mannerism, &amp;, as such, to be avoided. These be critical times. My wife told him that my gesture of raising the hand in preaching was most effective, but done too often! Well, well! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I revised the notes of the speech which I proposed to make tomorrow against the Bishop of Liverpool's Bill: and then I talked to </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Harris</hi><hi> the little Fellow of All Souls who, being disappointed of a don's career at Oxford, is now working for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>. He stood as a </hi><hi rend="bold">[148]</hi><hi> candidate for Parliament in one of the Durham constituencies, &amp; was, of course, awfully beaten.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The oily Methodist Secretary, (whose name I cannot remember, but who edits the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Contemporary Review</hi><hi> and has the duplicated conceit of a Dissenting Minister and of an Editor) sate at my table when I lunched. He said that his wife has been in the Temple yesterday, &amp; had brought him an account of my sermon! We discussed P. B. Revision, and he said that </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Carnegie Simpson</hi><hi> &amp; himself would not let the Dissenters take a hand, in what he thought was properly described as a domestic affair of the C of E. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He spoke quite strongly against the Bishop of Norwich &amp; Bishop Knox, who had almost jockeyed the Dissenters into assisting their movement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I drove to 30 Grosvenor Place, and looked at the portrait of </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Bishop Butler,</hi><hi> which Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi>. William Dyer &amp; Sons are prepared to sell for £100. They say that it was painted by Joseph Highmore (1692–1780), but it is not signed. It depicts Butler as a young man, &amp; is rather less pleasing that the picture in the Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to the House of Lords, and wrote to Ella. Then I talked to divers peers who chanced to come in – Desborough, Summer, Carson, Salisbury, Damesfort, &amp; some others. I attended the first stage of the grand debate on the Reform of the House of Lords. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Earl Fitz–Alan</hi><hi> introduced a motion in favour of Reform: &amp; the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Duke of Marlborough</hi><hi> moved an Amendment. I was particularly interested to hear the latter. He made a very thin, declamatory, insolent speech: but he had a good voice, &amp; the tricks of a practiced debater. The </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Earl of Arran</hi><hi>, a dull noisy speaker, also moved an amendment. Then the Lord Chancellor stated the intentions of the Government, and did so in a very clear, persuasive manner. I went to the Woolsack, &amp; told him so, adding that he had persuaded me to follow him. "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">You have so often made me change my opinion that it is only fair that I should do the same by you</hi><hi>": he replied pleasantly. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Haldane</hi><hi> spoke, but was heard with difficulty, &amp; then </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Selborne</hi><hi> rose. I had by this time had enough, and came away. After dining at the Club, I went to Park Lane.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
