<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Pelham had to go off to an education meeting immediately after breakfast. I left about 9.15a.m., and motored to Lake End, where M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Quirk received me kindly. We mounted the hill, and got very hot, but were rewarded by noble prospects of the Lake &amp; Mountains. The effect of an almost complete abstinence from physical exertion such as perforce marks my normal course of life is felt but too plainly when one climbs a hill, &amp; at every step brings under strain some effete muscles or other! In the afternoon we went up the Lake in the little steamer, &amp; were met at Coniston by Leng with the car. Thus we returned to the house in time to receive at tea a party of neighbours, including M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>&amp; Miss Gaisford, whom we met originally at Linburn, &amp; during the War, when General Gaisford was stationed in Newcastle. We walked round to the next house to see Miss Brydson's garden, which is her own design &amp; handiwork. She impressed me as amiable, versatile, and intelligent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The reports of my sermon at Furness Abbey are meagre enough, though a reasonable degree of prominence is given to the Commemoration. I regret the absence of any adequate account of what I said because Cardinal Bourne follows close on my steps with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">his</hi><hi> interpretation of the facts!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
