<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I travelled to King's Cross very comfortably, having the carriage to myself from York. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Col. Headlam</hi><hi> was on the train, &amp; had some talk with me. On arriving in London I went </hi><hi rend="bold underline">to the hairdresser, &amp; then</hi><hi> to the Club. The Archbishop of Canterbury came in, looking </hi><hi rend="italic">very well in spite of his recent indisposition. He is, I think, rather nervous about the fortunes of the Revised Book. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Sumner</hi><hi rend="italic"> had some talk with me. He seemed by no means friendly to the revision. This maybe the influence of the Master of the Rolls, who will stand by his brother of Norwich. About 5p.m. I made my way to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Londonderry House</hi><hi rend="italic"> where I was warmly welcomed by Lady L. and Robin. They went to the play, and I set to preparing a speech for tomorrow. I had promised to go with them, but suddenly remembered that it was the season of Lent, and that the spectacle of the Bishop of Durham going to the play might attract attention &amp; cause scandal, so I craved pardon of mine hostess, &amp; declined to attend her to the theatre. The episode reflected little credit on me whether as a Christian or as a bishop.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
