<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
      
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[11]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant morning with a slight frost. I wrote some more of the Conference Address, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">and then had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Ferguson, the Vicar of Collierley, who wished to consult me about a living which had been offered him by some Patronage Board in the diocese of Lichfield.</hi><hi> He is a terribly conceited fellow, &amp; excessively polemical, but in his own way works hard, &amp; would be hard to replace. On the whole I counselled him to stay where he is. He stayed to lunch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Eaglescliffe, &amp; there I confirmed 46 persons in the parish church. The Anglo&#8211;Catholik eccentrick, Milner, Vicar of Elton, brought some candidates. The Vicar of Egglescliffe [sic], M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Dingle, is, I think, a widower, &amp; displays the decent melancholy proper to that description. We went on to St. John's, Stockton, &amp; there I confirmed 111 persons. The parson, Batt, is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick. The service pleased me. Harlow, the Vicar of St Peter's, told me that it was his birthday, &amp; asked me to write his name in the copy of 'Church &amp; Parson in England', which he had today received from the publishers. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Thus I learned that the poor thing had actually been distributed. Will it do any good? Will it not rather cause additional offence</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi><hi> I was a jackass to send it out!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
