<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Archbishop of York writes quite urgently to say that I must attend the Meeting of Convocation. "I hoped, a hope that I know the Abp. of C. shares, that you w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi><hi>be ready particularly to answer Norwich &amp; others, who support the plea that the measure ought to be divided &amp; the Communion &amp; Reservation Rubrics left out." I suppose I must go.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Royal Literary Fund Anniversary C</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">tee</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> write to ask me "to propose the Toast of "Literature" at the Annual dinner on May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, when Lord Byng of Verring will preside. If my memory deceives me not, that toast is generally proposed by the Chairman. I remember responding for it once, when Curzon presided &amp; proposed it. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">This invitation I declined</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Newcastle, and addressed the officials of the Tyneside branches of the League of Nations Union. After this performance, I returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a series of letters, including my fortnightly letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My letter on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Paradoxes of Fanaticism</hi><hi rend="italic">' appeared in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> where it was given the place of honour. It may, perhaps, direct attention to two facts of some importance which have not received sufficient attention on the discussion of the Composite Book, viz 1. the squalid character of the most vocal opposition, and 2. the generally favourable opinion of the parochial clergy. It will, of course, make the more prominent critics of the Book very angry since they find themselves lumped in with such obviously contemptible fanaticks as faith–healers and anti–vaccinationists!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
