<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was much rain today, &amp; it was cheerless. I motored to Barnard Castle, &amp; presided at a meeting of the School Governors. The Headmaster reported a further reduction in the number of boys. The future of the School is more doubtful than I care to realize.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On my return to Auckland, I visited Spedding, &amp; then motored to Durham, where I confirmed 192 persons in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t. </hi><hi>Cuthbert's Church. The Vicar, Glynne, is a very fumbling &amp; futile person, but the service was not displeasing.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent copies of the Loch Lecture to Robin &amp; Lord Barnard.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><hi> was very eager in assuring me that he would accept to Composite Book, but he "</hi><hi rend="underline">would have much difficulty with his friends.</hi><hi>" This means that these </hi><hi rend="underline">soi&#8211;disant</hi><hi> Catholicks think they can see their way to twist the new rubricks as they have twisted the old, but that they mean to make a mighty pretence of self&#8211;sacrifice in abandoning open opposition. How can they go straight who are accustomed to go crooked? I fear that the restoration of discipline in the Church of England will be as remote as ever: nevertheless, we were bound to make the attempt.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
