<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A white frost, and. In the afternoon, rain. I worked on the Conference Address. The post brought a good many acknowledgements from the clergy who have received copies of "Church &amp; Parson in England". </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Most of them are wise enough to thank me, before reading my book!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed 148 persons in St Cuthbert's Church. They came from the parishes of S. Cuthbert's, S. Paul's, Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne, and on the whole I was pleased with the service, though the officiousness of the churchwardens in bringing up the candidates was amazing. Why these good men cannot leave the candidates to the unassisted guidance of their own common sense, I cannot imagine.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Gouldsmith, who ranks as a Low Churchman, expressed his great satisfaction with the Composite Book. If this diocese is representative of the country, the noisy agitations, who are renouncing the Bishop, have little support in the parishes. Nonetheless, they may have sufficient following in the Assembly, to make it impossible to maintain that the Revision commands the general approval of Churchmen, without which the acceptance of Parliament becomes doubtful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
