<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Editor of the Nineteenth Century</hi><hi> &amp; After returned the MS. of my Glasgow lecture, and with it sent a letter suggesting that I might tinker it up so as to disguise its original character &amp; thus qualify it for publication in his journal. Accordingly, I wasted the morning over the attempt, &amp; sent back the </hi><hi rend="underline">tinkered</hi><hi> lecture. If it is published, it </hi><hi rend="bold underline">cannot but be interpreted as indicating that I am reconciling myself to the abhorred necessity of Disestablishm</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. The fact is that I cannot endure the possibility of the Crown patronage in the hands of a Labour Prime Minister.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Partridge</hi><hi> writes from Austria to ask me "to write the first article in the June issue of the Church Assembly news". He emphasizes the importance of my doing this in view of the meeting of the Church Assembly in July.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ernest motored with me to Tow Law, where I confirmed 54 persons in the parish church. They came from the parishes of Tow Law, Thornley, and Sasley. We had tea in the Vicarage, and then returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi><hi>, the Rector of Jarrow, lunched here. He came to consult me about the division of his parish. In view of the shortage of clergy, and of the great sum of money which the creation of a new parish would require, I dissuaded him from embarking on this project.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Headlam</hi><hi> arrived on a short visit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>N.B. I told William Bryden that he might continue at work in the garden for another fortnight. By that time George out to be equal to his duties.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
