<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[172]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>The heat last night was very great: and the day continued the tradition of the night. The Assembly began at 10.30 a.m., &amp; after disposing of a point of order, the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Archbishop</hi><hi> of </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Canterbury moved that the Prayer Book Revision be approved</hi><hi>. His Grace spoke with great force &amp; dignity for half an hour, and was loudly applauded at the close of his speech. Then Darwell Stone spoke for 23 minutes, &amp; Sir Joynson Hicks for half an hour. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop passed down to me the following note</hi><hi>:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Joynson Hicks</hi><hi rend="italic"> wants to speak immediately. Are you prepared to follow him? It is, I think, important that you should if possible: but, of course, it must not be done at my request. R. J. C.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="underline">So, of course, I followed on, and spoke 'large' for half an hour. The speech was applauded, &amp; many thanked me for it, but it had all the faults of extemporaneous speech, and I was ashamed of it</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>I went to the House of Lords, where </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> reading debate on the Trades Unions Bill was continued</hi><hi>. Lord </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">De la Ware</hi><hi> spoke for 45 minutes with much parade of vehemence, but neither knowledge nor conviction. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Askwith</hi><hi> followed for 15 minutes: &amp; then </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spoke for 20 minutes. My speech was very well received, &amp; many peers congratulated me afterwards. Lord</hi> 
<hi rend="bold">[173]</hi><hi> [symbol] </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Sumner made one of his fatal speeches, &amp; then Lord Salisbury wound up the debate</hi><hi>. I was the only Bishop who voted in the division. The 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> reading of the Bill was carried by 152 to 27. Then, without changing, I drove to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Skinners' Hall</hi><hi>, and dined at the </hi><hi rend="underline">Apposition Dinner</hi><hi> of S Paul's School. The Mercers are exiled from their own Hall by the death watch beetle! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I proposed the toast of the School</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Thus I made no less than 3 speeches in one day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selbourne</hi><hi> sate beside me at dinner. He professes considerable anxiety as to the fortunes of the Revised Payer Book in the House of Lords, and attaches much importance to the effect of my speaking on it. I am not so sure of this myself. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Hitherto I have spoken on subjects respecting which my views were in harmony with those of the majority, or such as the majority did not feel strongly about. The real test would be if I spoke in the teeth of the general feeling</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> In any case the goodwill of the House is an asset worth possessing.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
