<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8a.m. It being S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Barnabus's Day, I used the Collect, Epistle &amp; Gospel for that Festival, using also the Collect for Whitsunday. After breakfast I gave copies of Lightfoot's Ordination addresses to the 4 candidates for the Priesthood. Then I completed the addresses for the Conference &amp; the Candidates respectively.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Durham, and presided over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference in the Chapter House. The </hi><hi rend="italic">motion in favour of the Revised Prayer Book was introduced by </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Prof.Heawood</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">in an excellent speech. An amendment</hi><hi> was moved by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Purvis</hi><hi> of Stockton &amp; seconded by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi><hi> of Darlington: but it received little support, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the motion being carried by 248 votes to 30.</hi><hi> This was a better division than I had expected. I was pleased to see </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Lord Barnard</hi><hi> in the Conference. He has just been elected a member. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Pemberton &amp; How</hi><hi> came to me at the Castle as a deputation from the University about the Greek Professorship. I presided at the taking of vows by the candidates: &amp; then a meeting of the Lightfoot trustees. I dined with the Bishop of Jarrow, and then delivered my Charge in the Deanery Chapel.</hi>
         
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
