<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My venerable chancellor, P.V. Smith, whom I have ever reckoned to be a stalwart Evangelical, writes to tell me that "</hi><hi rend="underline">he agrees with every word of my valuable address to the Diocesan Conference &amp; Article in the April </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edinburgh Review</hi><hi>'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wasted the morning in preparing an oration for the Presbyterians. It is these persistent "side&#8211;shows" of many&#8211;sided oratory that fritter away a Bishop's energies, and defeat his main purpose. In the afternoon I motored to see Cruickshank, who is evidently very ill. I saw </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><hi> and told him my decision respecting </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephen Cellan</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was very anxious to impress me with his "loyalty": and told me that he had joined the League of 'Order &amp; Loyalty'. But I am not greatly impressed.</hi><hi> Ella &amp; Fearne arrived from Edinburgh in time to accompany me to the Presbyterian meeting. The church was crowded, &amp; the atmosphere fearful. My address was not, I think, very acceptable. I spoke severely of Bolshevism, &amp; very frankly of the anti&#8211;Christian tendency of latter&#8211;day Democracy. Probably, most part of the audience were members of the Labour Party, &amp; didn't care to have it so faithfully dealt with! We got back to Auckland about 10.30 p.m.</hi> 
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
