<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I slept badly, and in the course of the night read most of the history of Louis XV</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th </hi><hi>'s calamitous reign in "The Eighteenth Century" by Casimir Stryienski.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I walked to Downing Street, &amp; had breakfast with the Prime Minister.</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">He wanted to talk to me about the appointment to Newcastle. I said that it would be unfortunate if either an Anglo–Catholick or a Socialist were sent there, &amp; he assured me that he would see that my wish in that respect was fulfilled. We had a good deal of interesting conversation, and again he impressed as a sincere and simple–minded man. I went back to Lambeth, and sate in session with my Brethren from 10.30 a.m. to 7 p.m. with intervals for lunch &amp; tea. We shall make very small concessions to the Convocations. An attempt was made to extend the use of the Reserved Sacrament to others beside the Sick.</hi><hi> The Bishops of Chester, Truro, Southwark, S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t.</hi><hi> Alban's, Chichester, and some others, in all (I think) nine, voted for this extension, </hi><hi rend="underline">which I opposed strongly, going so far as to say that, if it were adopted, I should find it difficult to defend the revised book. Its rejection by a large majority gave me great relief and satisfaction</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
