<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Forster of Spennymoor sent us a salmon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I made a beginning of an address on the Composite Book for the Diocesan Conference. Ford, the Curate from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t.</hi><hi> Cuthbert's, Darlington, came to see me. He wants to get married, &amp; has an offer of a curacy in Cheshire, which would enable to [sic] marry. I advised him to accept it. He stayed to lunch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Sedgefield, where I confirmed 55 persons in the parish church, &amp; then had tea with the Rector &amp; his family. Then we went on to Norton, where I confirmed 111 persons in the parish church, &amp; afterwards dined with old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Kirk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Both these Confirmations pleased me. The sexes were not too unequally represented in the candidates. There was evidence of care in the preparation. Sedgefield and Norton are ancient parishes which possess noble churches. My addresses were listened to with attention.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Canon Parrish, Douglas of Stockton, and Fuller, the Vicar of Norton, were all agreed in approving the 'Composite Book'. These are normal parish priests of experience, intelligence, and good sense, who may fairly be taken as representatives of the general body of working clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
