<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but 7 communicants including Miss Headlam and James. After breakfast I wrote my "Collins" to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Davidson, and my fortnightly letter to William. Then I revised the Empire Prayer, &amp; sent it on to the Bishop of Wakefield.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked in the Park after lunch, and talked with some of the youths who were walking there. Four of them became very friendly, and were so eager to see the inside of the Castle that I promised to shew it to them, &amp; invited them to tea next Saturday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the story by W.B. Maxwell, "The case of Bevan Yorke", which I read in the train yesterday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Harold Cox tells me that he has read my article on the Composite Book with great interest, and sent it to the printers. He also gives me permission to reprint it in the May issue of '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Bishoprick</hi><hi>'. Whether I shall avail myself of this permission is, however, doubtful: for, if I address the Diocesan Conference on Prayer Book Revision on March 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I must write new stuff: and, if I print anything in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>, it had probably best be what I shall have spoken to the Conference.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Almighty God, Who by Thy Providence ordereth all things in heaven and earth, regard with Thy favour, we beseech Thee, the peoples of divers races, languages, and customs, who own allegiance to Thy servant, our Sovereign Lord, King George. Draw them together in true fellowship that, bearing one another's burdens and working together in brotherly concord, they may fulfil the purpose of Thy Providence, and set forward Thine everlasting Kingdom. Keep far from us all selfishness and pride, and give us grace to employ Thy good gifts of order and freedom to Thy glory and the welfare of mankind, through Jesus Christ, Thy Son our Lord, to Whom with Thee and the Holy Ghost be all glory and dominion world without end.Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The final form which the Prayer took (v. p. 9) included a petition for Pardon for "our sins and shortcomings".</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
