<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Boutflower</hi><hi> has sent me a copy of "The Contemporary Review. Dec: 1903" which contains his article "</hi><hi rend="underline">Some Sayings of Bishop Westcott</hi><hi>". They are extremely interesting, and deserve a more secure record than that of a magazine.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a rather melancholy letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">James</hi><hi>. The boy is plainly rather startled at the environment in which he finds himself and is probably as homesick as the situation requires. I wrote to him at Valparaiso.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Firth</hi><hi> &#8211; he is 70 today &#8211; came to lunch. He deserves to resign his living, though, from his own account, he appears to have nothing on which to live save what we can give him from the living and from the Ecclesiastical Commissioners.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fanning</hi><hi>, who was once </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Helen Beeching</hi><hi>. She is now settled in South Africa where her husband grows oranges, and she has three children. She says that she still keeps up her music.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening paper announces the death of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Ritson</hi><hi> who until recently commanded the 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> D.L.I. He sent me a history of the Battalion, &amp; my acknowledgement of his gift was only posted this morning.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent some time in reading about Furness Abbey; with a view to my sermon next Saturday: but I did not get much to my purpose. There is much about the Cistercian Order in </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Coulton's</hi><hi> '</hi><hi rend="underline">Five Centuries of Religion</hi><hi>' but the occasion hardly lends itself to anything that could even plausibly be described as 'controversial'!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
