<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>I spent the morning in writing ^a^ sermon for the youth whom I was pledged to address in the evening, being interrupted by the Vicar of Barnard Castle, who arrived with another clergyman, an applicant for the vacant assistant&#8211;curacy. Sykes came to lunch, with the object of making the final arrangements about the Auckland Brotherhood meeting on June 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. I bade him settle everything with Lionel and Alexander, &amp; promised to "honour the bill"! Then I walked in the Park, and had some pleasant talk with some miners whom I encountered. Evidently there have been fresh discharges from the pits.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, where I preached to a crowded congregation of Church Lads Brigade, Boy Scouts, Girl Guides, &amp;c &amp;c, assembled to inaugurate a "Council of Youth" for the Rural Deanery. After the service the lads &amp; girls who were in uniform lined the Churchyard, and I spoke to them. Then I dined at the Rectory. On the whole, I was pleased with the service, and, save for some coughing by the younger children, the attention was close. We returned to Auckland Castle in time to get speech with Caröe, who had arrived in order to attend the function at Escomb tomorrow.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
