<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Peter's Day, Wednesday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">,1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 4.30 a.m. I got out of bed to see what kind of sky would frame the much&#8211;advertized "total eclipse" of the sun. Bilbrough and Kempthorne came with me to the roof. Most of the party went to the high ground in the Park, &amp; some sate with my wife in the dining room. But all saw very little to reward their effort. Beyond some glimpses of the sun's rim through the clouds, we saw nothing. The papers had built up expectations in our minds which were disappointed. We descended from the roof, or returned from the Park, or retired from the window in a somewhat chastened mood.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I had a bath: and then wrote a cheque for the new Austin car (&#x00A3;775). Also I send a cheque to Durand for the amount of the offertory at the Holy Communion in the Chapel viz. &#x00A3;8:1.6. Then I revised my address. This was delivered at Mattins, &amp;, perhaps, was more interesting than pleasing to the Brethren. Then came lunch, after which we were photographed in the garden.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I felt so tired that I retired to my room, &amp; rested until tea&#8211;time, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">when the hostesses of the Brethren who had been put up in the town came to join the party</hi><hi>. After tea everybody played games, or walked about until dinner. After dinner, the Bishop of Wakefield proposed "an informal vote of thanks" to Ella and me, &amp; spoke very flatterously. I made a short reply, &amp; then we retired leaving the company to themselves, until Compline, after which we all went to bed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather was fine throughout, and this fact contributed not a little to the success of the reunion. The household worked with much devotion, and thoroughly merited the praise that was showered on them by our guests. The following bishops were here:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>1. The Bishop of Wakefiled (Eden)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>2. The Bishop of Lichfield (Kempthorne)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>3. The Bishop of Rochester (Harmer)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>4. The Bishop of Newcastle (Bilbrough)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>5. The Metropolitan of India (Westcott)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>6. The Bishop of Guiana</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>7. Bishop Chatterton</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>8. Bishop King.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
