<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I prepared a speech which (if opportunity occur, and need require) may be delivered in answer to the Bp. of N.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An anonymous letter in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> states that "many hundreds of clergy" in the diocese of Norwich "feel very unhappy indeed" about the Bishop's attitude on P.B. Revision. Yeterdy the Bishop addressed a gathering of Nonconformists on the Revision. He was supported by Bp. Knox. The meeting was presided over by Sir Thomas Inskip. This is, I judge, a mistaken move, which will prejudice the Protestant opposition in Churchmen's eyes. There is a good deal of resentment at the notion of the </hi><hi rend="bold">(</hi><hi>Sectaries</hi><hi rend="bold">) </hi><hi>interfering with our business!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The car took me to the Abbey, where a good muster of bishops from the two provinces were robing in the Jerusalem Chamber (Perkins, the Sacrist, muddled things for me by contradictory instructions.</hi><hi rend="bold">)</hi><hi> I read the Gospel nd administered the Consecrated Bread. Then we went to the Church House, and the Archbishop introduced the subject in a telling &amp; dignified speech. I lunched at the Deanery. After luch, the Bishop of Norwich read his speech, of which he gave me a printed copy. </hi><hi rend="underline">It contained so many quotation's [sic] from various pronouncements of mine that I claimed a large share in its composition.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[33]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It was well delivered, and well received. There was, I think, a feeling in the audience that the Bishop was "sticking to his gun". I followed him immediately &amp; spoke for about 25 minutes. The Speech was well listened to, and applauded, but I was not myself satisfied with it. </hi><hi rend="underline">But the Bishops of Chester, Carlisle, Wakefield and Bristol assured me that it was the best speech I had ever made, a judgement which at least indicates that they themselves approved it</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Darwell Stone</hi><hi> followed me, but was very dull. Then came the Bishop of Oxford who was curiously ineffective. I went off to get tea, and in my absence a vehement attack on the Bishop of Birmingham appears to have been made by a certain </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Long</hi><hi>. The Bishop made a brief &amp; dignified reply. A rambling oration from the Bishop of Exeter didn't contribute much of value: he was followed by the Bishop of Truro, who was speaking well when I came away.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi><hi> publishes my article on revision under the rather provocative title "</hi><hi rend="underline">Wine pulling in the Church</hi><hi>" which has nothing to do with my contribution.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
