<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[215]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I began the day by paying my Income tax &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;464:5:5</hi><hi> making, with super&#8211;tax, a total payment of </hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;1330:14:0</hi><hi>. When I add the sums paid on account of rates, rents, mortgages, Insurances, &amp; the Cost of Collection, I find that at least </hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;2000</hi><hi> has to be written off my nominal income.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I wrote a difficult and important, but obviously necessary letter to F.B. and made a copy for future use.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel went off on his holiday, which he has fairly earned, leaving me to the risks &amp; inconveniences of official </hi><hi rend="underline">dereliction</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I paid wages, and counted my travelling money &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;54:18:5</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Northern Echo publishes two more letters, both hostile, and one offensive. It is clear that this attack is organized, &amp; probably reflects, less any special fault of mine, than the resentment of the ''Protestant Underworld'' against my attitude towards Prayer Book Revision. They have found occasion in my address to the Auckland Brotherhood, but the cause is deeper and different.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left the Castle about 11 p.m. and motored to Newcastle. Alexander went with us, &amp; it was well that he did so. For the crowd of Bank&#8211;holiday excurtionists was large, &amp; we needed his help with the luggage. Our seats were reserved, so that we travelled in comparative comfort. There was a delay of 2 hours at Stranraer, and another hour was lost but reason of a slight fog. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We finally reached Mount Stewart about a quarter past 12 0'clock on Saturday, the 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> and had just time to wash before lunch</hi><hi>. The sea was smooth so that we suffered no distress from mal de mer: but the steamer was thronged with holiday folk, and we endured a wild scramble both going on board and coming off. In the afternoon we loafed about the ground, which are extremely beautiful. The combination of good taste, keen interest in gardening, and large resources of money freely drawn upon have created in Mount Stewart gardens a wonderful union of art &amp; nature. [No journal entry for Saturday, 30th July, 1927]</hi>
         
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
