<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful morning and a blackbird singing nobly as I dressed. Laus Deo. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8a.m. There were 8 communicants and Ernest, who did not communicate because he had to celebrate in the parish later. The thought of Cruickshank was in my mind as I prayed for "the whole state of Christ's Church". He is no more 'militant here on earth', but not even death can tear him from Christ's fellowship. He knows now much that puzzled him greatly once.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I prepared notes for an address to the Freemasons, &amp; wrote to </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The annual service of Freemasons in the chapel was not so well attended as in former years. I have no doubt the reason is that which is emptying all the churches &#8211; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">motoring</hi><hi>. Excursions are arranged months ahead, &amp; no religious claim can indicate itself if these arrangements conflict with it. I preached from James I.19 and took occasion to speak about the sinister growing tendency to break up meetings, that is, to make government by discussion impossible. Shaddick &amp; Marsh had tea with me afterwards.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella with Fearne, Miss Headlam, and Lady Eden motored into Durham in order to attend the memorial service for Canon Cruickshank, which was held in the Cathedral at 2.30pm.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Two lads &#8211; William Stubbs and John George Lancaster, both aged 16 and neither yet confirmed, but intending to be &#8211; walked round the garden with me.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
