<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me from the clergy another batch of acknowledgements. Old Boddy writes:&#8211; "I am hoping that your Lordship will find opportunity </hi><hi rend="bold underline">within the next few years to write your Autobiography. A sense of humour such as possessed by our Bishop will make it very good reading, &amp; I trust that that sense of humour will be allowed full play"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am surprised that he should discover humour in a very demure little edifying book.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The proofs of the Edinburgh Article arrived. I corrected and returned them. Then I finished the Conference Address.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Brooke and Fosca came to lunch. He is a quaint little fellow, with a good deal of intelligence &amp; independence. Like all his generation he regards with a good deal of sympathy every "Labour" movement, &amp; even the hateful system in Russia.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella, Lionel and I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed about 100 persons in S. Hilda's Church. After the service we all had supper with the Vicar and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">re</hi><hi>. Bell. S. Hilda's is rather a dull red&#8211;brick church on the main street. It serves a population of more than 10,000 people, tightly packed into a small area. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bell is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but he is fond of sport, and breeds game&#8211;cocks. He is a vigorously looking man to look at, &amp; expresses himself sensibly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[14]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Copies of "Church &amp; Parson in England" were sent to the following:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>1. Sir Edward Clarke</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>2. Sir Lewis Dibdin</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>3. Sir Hugh Cecil</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>4. The Dean of S. Paul's</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>5. Bishop Knox </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>6. The Bishop of Manchester</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>7. " " " Birmingham</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>8. " " " Salisbury</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>9. " " " Norwich</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
