<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Buchan</hi><hi><persName xml:id="984"></persName>, thanking him for his new romance 'Witch Wood', of which he sent me a copy, &amp; which I finished reading through this morning before I got up. It is extremely interesting, &amp; gives a very excellent picture of the Calvinistic Fanaticks of 17th century Scotland – cruel, sensual, &amp; conceited. It is easy to understand the mingled scorn &amp; loathing which they provoked in generous minds.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Also, I wrote to the aged Quakers who protested against the parallel between the Cistercians &amp; the Quakers, which I suggested in my sermon at Furness Abbey.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> F. B. Bates</hi><hi>, Rector of Redmarshall, came to see me. He is 47, and wants more work than he can get in his little parish with only 314 people. The patronage is in the Crown. I suggested the possibility of an exchange with the Vicar of Sacriston (Hutton) which is also a Crown living. He did not repudiate the suggestion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Billingham where, in very bad weather, I consecrated an addition to the churchyard. On the way home we called at Sedgefield Rectory.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a request from the League of Loyalty and Order to write a covering letter to a bundle of papers on the Revised Prayer Book which that society proposes to issue to every Peer. This is rather a dubious proposal.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
