<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wasted this day utterly, for, beyond writing letters, and presiding over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference Committee, I did nothing.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The notes of my speech in Newcastle were returned to me with a pencilled message as follows:&#8211; </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My Lord Bishop.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Herewith the Notes. Thanks. I have been thinking ever since, &#8211; &amp; I suppose that is what a man like you lives for.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours faithfully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>George I. Ogilvie.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received an impudent letter from Councillor Thatcher of Stockton, threatening to make a scene in S. Paul's Church, when I come to preach there if I "attack" Labour in my sermon! He ends thus, smugly:&#8211; </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'I hope you will appreciate my point in this letter and kindly understand I do not hate you for your criticism as we even hope to convert you some day to our policy which will not break up family life, but give a little more of the Kingdom of God upon earth".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The time is coming when the shocking rowdyism, which now is habitual in the House of Commons, will be extended to the parish churches. "Labour" will suffer nothing to be audible except the echo of its own voice!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
