<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">And 'till we are persuaded to stop, &amp; step a little aside, out of the noisy crowd and incumbering hurry of the world, &amp; calmly take a prospect of things it will be impossible we should be able to make a right judgment of ourselves, or know our own misery. But after we have made the just reckonings which Retirement will help us to, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">we shall begin to think the world in great measure mad, &amp; that we have been in a sort of Bedlam all this while.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">(Wm. Penn. Preface to Reflections &amp; Maxims)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather is heavy &amp; thunderous, very unfavourable to every form of honest effort. I fooled away the morning in my study, and, in the afternoon, went into Durham, &amp; attended a meeting of the Playing Fields Association in the Town Hall. General Surtees presided. On my return to the Castle, I had an interview with Sinnamon, which relieved me of much anxiety.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through Penn's preface to Fox's Journal. It is admirably written, and gives as clear an account of the Quaker Gospel as I know. His description of the Founder of Quakerism is vivid, attractive, and drawn from life.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
