<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A comfortless blustering day. I cleared up my room, and wrote many letters, preparatory for my departure tomorrow.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> lunched here, and afterwards walked with me in the Park. He will be 17 on the 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> July, and is 6 feet in height. He goes to try his luck at Wadham next week.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> J. Robson</hi><hi>, Vicar of All Saints, South Shields, came to see me by appointment, bringing with him a young man, </hi><hi rend="italic">named </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bailey</hi><hi rend="italic">, who had been sent away from Kelham, after 4 years residence there, and told that he had "no vocation", and must not put hand to spiritual work. He narrated the history of his "retirement", and a very squalid &amp; sinister history it was. I gather that "psychology" with the usual obsession about sex reigns also at Kelham.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from the Headmaster of the English School at Cairo such an answer to my inquiries about S.A. that I was relieved from any doubt as to my duty with respect to him, and told him at once that I would not accept him as a candidate for Holy Orders.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi><hi>" has long [sic] article on Durham Cathedral, which contains an almost violent attack on the Dean and Chapter. No doubt, if judged by the standards of Chester and York, Durham is woeful enough: but, it allowance be made for the different circumstances, I do not think it can be justly condemned.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
