<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant fine day, but the wind bitter. The </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> has a pontifical letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edwin Bombay</hi><hi> in the "God&#8211;Almighty&#8211;to&#8211;a&#8211;blackbeetle" style: and a little small&#8211;typed sinister epistle from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mackay</hi><hi> &amp; another Anglo&#8211;Catholick announcing their determination not to have the Revised Prayer Book on any terms. Also, the Vicar of Islington, an Evangelical opponent of the said book, gives expression to his disgust at the performance of the Protestant underworld in publicly insulting the Archbishop of Canterbury.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">William Suthren</hi><hi>, the student from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Chad's, who is being assisted by the diocesan Fund came to lunch, &amp; afterwards accompanied me to Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the Lay Workers Association. After talking over diocesan business with the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; having tea with Wilson, I returned to Auckland, where </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi><hi> was awaiting me. He accepted appointment to South Westoe very cheerfully. It is an evidence of the difficulty into which the shortage of clergy has brought us that I am compelled to move a man who has only been four years in his present parish. Now the problem of filling up New Shildon presents itself.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>James was 18 on Tuesday, &amp; will soon be leaving "to better himself". I gave him Stevenson's '</hi><hi rend="underline">Kidnapped</hi><hi>' as a Birthday Present. I shall miss him when he has gone.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
