<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
      
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Copies of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Tablet</hi><hi> and the </hi><hi rend="underline">Record</hi><hi> arrived by the morning post. Both have leading articles concerned with the demolition of the Bishop of Durham! Also, several parish meetings send resolutions in favour of the Revised Book, &amp; even in some cases add expressions of loyalty to the Bishop!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> sends me a letter announcing his visit to Wadham. He is very well satisfied with his own performance, but we have yet to hear what the college authorities think of it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Stanley</hi><hi> &amp; opened a Missionary Exhibition in the Co&#8211;operative Hall. There was a good muster of the local clergy, &amp;, considering the inconvenience of the hour, a fair number of people. After I had walked round the Show, I came away, &amp; returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to Bryden's lodge &amp; saw </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold</hi><hi>, who goes into the Sanatorium at Wolsingham on Monday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Much of today has been spent in reading </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Streeter's</hi><hi rend="italic"> '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Reality</hi><hi rend="italic">'. It is a remarkable book, admirably written and well argued. There is a ring of sincerity, which is very attractive, and the note of personal devoutness cannot escape any careful reader. I am not astonished to see that it has already been re&#8211;printed several times. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><hi rend="italic"> is certainly a strong man, stronger than I realized when I used to see him at Hereford. To have produced in so short a time two such books as "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Four Gospels</hi><hi rend="italic">" and "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Reality</hi><hi rend="italic">" is a great achievement. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
