<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Faith in democracy as a basis for government and society, once almost unanimously accepted in this country, now stands challenged openly and powerfully throughout the world because of the inefficiency of democratic governments … Only if the people of America make their democratic institutions efficient, can this nation ward off the absolute State as the basis of government and life, with consequent loss of individual liberties, as in the Soviet and Fascist experiments.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">President Nicholas Murray Butler</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At Celebration by the University of Virginia of the 184</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of Thomas Jefferson's birth. v. The New York Times April 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This is a pronouncement which sets one thinking, and the more 'furiously' since it comes from the most self&#8211;confident democracy of the world, which condescended to fight for no other reason than "</hi><hi rend="underline">to make the world safe for democracy</hi><hi>". The President names as one of the conspicuous evils of modern democracy "</hi><hi rend="underline">the abstention from voting of large percentages of the electorate</hi><hi>." Is this evil largely the result of the lowering of the franchise, and the multiplication of elections?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I made a start on the Cathedral sermon for May 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. In the afternoon Brooke walked with me round the Park, and then returned to Gateshead.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Colonel &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Cuthbert Headlam with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bell came to dine, also Lady Thurlow. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He apprehends that there may be some serious opposition to the Revision Meaure in the House of Commons. He says that the Archbishop of York made a very favourable impression on the Members when he addressed them on Revision. He was not present when the Bishop of Norwich spoke on the other side, but he understands that he was not very effective.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He says that the Prime Minister is plainly feeling the strain of the work in Parliament: he dislikes the situation into which has come, and feels the hostility of the Labour folk. We discussed the probable successor, if Baldwin could not continue in office: &amp; were reluctantly driven to the conclusion that </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Austin Chamberlain</hi><hi rend="italic"> was probably inevitable. </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Churchill</hi><hi rend="italic"> ought to be Prime Minister if ability and achievement determined the appointment: but the country would not suffer it. </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Colonel Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke with energy against the folly of giving votes to the "flappers"; and said that doing so would probably lose him his seat.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Lady Thurlow</hi><hi rend="italic"> was very cheerful. She says that the Bishop of Liverpool would be preserved from many blunders if he had had some parochial experience.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
