<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi> contains a short account of my speech last night: and so does the </hi><hi rend="underline">Northern Echo</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi>In the latter there is a curious error "God and Mammon" being substituted for "God and Man". I thought it worth correcting, and sent a note to the Editor. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to the Bishop of Oxford about Ernest, suggesting that there might be a suitable assistant curacy in the Oxford diocese.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. M. N. Coates</hi><hi>, Vicar of Forest &amp; Frith, came to lunch. I told him that I should have work for him later in the year, and dissuaded him from leaving the diocese.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi><hi>, from Darlington came to consult me about curates. I told him that his parish was not suitable for a deacon, being in certain senses abnormal.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi><hi> came to lunch, and afterwards motored out with me to Barnard Castle, where I confirmed 51 persons, and then consecrated an addition to the churchyard. The latter function was carried through in a thunderstorm. I read the prayers in the chapel on account of the rain. After this function we had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi><hi>: and then returned to Auckland. The weather had [sic] beautifully fine &amp; warm until about 3.30 p.m., when it became sultry, &amp; developed into a wet evening. A Northumberland Vicar, named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stenhouse</hi><hi>, sent me a resolution of protest against the Revised Prayer Book adopted by his parish meeting.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
