<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to the Dean inviting his counsel in the matter of the vacant professorship. So much seemed to me due to his scholarship, to his position as Head of the Cathedral Foundation, of which the new professor will be a member, and to the general fitness of things.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wasted much time in putting together notes and "ideas" on the subject of the Revised Prayer Book, and then motored to Sunderland where I discussed it with the clergy of the Rural Deanery in Monkwearmouth Rectory. There was a very friendly tone in the gathering, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">an attitude towards myself which was almost affectionate!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to the Rectory of Bishop Wearmouth, and had an hours talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wynne Willson, </hi><hi rend="italic">who is undergoing some kind of drastic disqualifying treatment for his intolerable rheumatism. Then I went to S. Helen's, Low Fell, and admitted the new Vicar, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Wood to the perpetual curacy of that parish</hi><hi>. There was a good muster of the Gateshead clergy, including that wonderful old man Mitchell who approaches 90, and was thought to be dying a few months since. Brooke also was there. The congregation was considerable, &amp; everything seemed well enough: but </hi><hi rend="underline">the new vicar seemed cold &amp; unresponsive</hi><hi>: after the service I had an interview with the curate Fryer in the vestry, &amp; told him that he must betake himself to another diocese.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
