<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ A most beautiful day, warm and bright. The Park was a gay scene, so many young people enjoying themselves in orderly fashion. James and I walked round the Park after lunch. I called to enquire after Harold Bryden, and saw him for a few minutes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ Charlie Lillingston came to lunch. He is full of King's Cambridge, where he has completed his first term. He and James were able to discuss Cambridge together.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ Ernest returned to the Lodge in a state of physical collapse. Happily Worth had returned, &amp; was able to take the Easter duty. But the incident is disconcerting.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a letter from Earl Grey suggesting that I should join in some concerted effort to educate the Peers on the subject of the Revised Book. It is evident that the "Church Party" in Parliament are "getting the wind up" about its fortunes. It is possible that the subterranean activities of the Fundamentalists have had more effect than I should have thought could be the case, and it is certain that there is a great accumulation of resentment against the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, which, if it could be brought into play against the Revised Book, might be strong enough to defeat it. The position of the English Episcopate will be indeed humiliating if the result of their labours is thus contumeliously cast aside!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>

         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
