<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The heavens grew black about noon, so that it was necessary to use the electric light, and there was a considerable thunderstorm with heavy rain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I received a letter from Sir W. Joynson&#8211;Hicks, the Home Secretary, asking me to be a member of a Committee, which he is setting up, to inquire into the working of the law about solicitation!</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">Of all conceivable subjects this is assuredly the one with which I would least care to be connected. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Nevertheless, I returned a rather ungracious acceptance, simply because I don't think it prudent to disoblige the H.S</hi><hi rend="italic underline">. </hi><hi rend="italic">in view of parliamentary contingencies presently when the Measure legalising the Composite Book comes before the House of Commons.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Barnard Castle School, where I confirmed 22 boys in the Chapel. Later, we motored to Croxdale where I confirmed about 70 persons in the parish church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received, and declined, an invitation to stay at Lambeth for the Convocation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>200 copies of the Loch Memorial Lecture on "</hi><hi rend="underline">the Problem of Private Benevolence in the Private State</hi><hi>" arrived. How anaemic &amp; futile this kind of composition looks when it re&#8211;appears months after the occasion which led to its being originally undertaken! Then it was tolerable, even successful: now it is so much waste paper, &amp; wasted money!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
