<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in Ryhope Church</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>There were more than 210 communicants. The service which was choral pleased me much by its simplicity, reverence and congregationalism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I returned to Auckland, where I set to work on a very short Presidential address for the Diocesan Conference. The Park was closed, and the castle Gardens opened in the interest of the Queen Victoria Nursing Fund. There did not seem any great rush of visitors.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Lord Thurlow asking whether he could help me in the matter of getting James onto a liner in the steward's department. Also I wrote to Hugh Rees, asking him to obtain for me the volume on Australia which I looked at in Knight's study this morning viz:&#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">The Australian Aboriginal by Herbert Basedow. Adelaide. F.W. Preece &amp; Sons. 1925.</hi><hi> It seemed to be a very careful, detailed, and first&#8211;hand description of that fascinating but fading race. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Ordination candidates &#8211; 7 in number, for one was hindered by sickness &#8211; arrived on the scene in time for Evensong at 7 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
