<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most glorious summer's day. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 10 communicants, including William, Edward, and Florrie Bryden. Is there any goodlier sight on earth than that of young people, in the arduous &amp; simplicity of youth, presenting themselves at the Altar of the Redeemer? </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a service of Church Lads Brigade in the garden. The fineness of the day, the beauty of the place, &amp; the appearance of the lads made the spectacle attractive. It did in fact attract a considerable company of the townsfolk. Save for the fainting of two of the boys, everything passed (passed) off well enough. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Sunderland, &amp; preached at Evensong in All Saints Church. The last time when I appeared there was in May last year, when I could not preach, &amp; had to go home in agony. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Before beginning my sermon, I said a few words on that episode, and thanked the people for their sympathy</hi><hi>. My text was taken from the Gospel of the Day – "</hi><hi rend="underline">With what measure ye mete it shall be measured to you again</hi><hi>." My sermon was very short so that I was back at the Castle by 8.45 p.m. The number of motors on the road is suggestive of anything but Church–going: and we are yet only at the beginning of the motoring–epidemic. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
