<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fine warm day, almost summerlike in its mild brilliance. I worked at a sermon on the Lord's Day, and in the afternoon walked round the Park, into which young women in charge of baby&#8211;filled perambulators had come in force.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Miller</hi><hi>, the local editor, came to explain to me that he was not responsible for the offensive article in last night's 'North Eastern Daily Gazette' headed '</hi><hi rend="underline">1,300 Years old &#8211; York Minster Anniversary Link with Roman Catholicism</hi><hi>', against which I had sent him a note of protest. It appears that part only of the paper is edited in Bishop Auckland, the other part, in which the offending article was printed, being edited in Middlesborough. The Papists are evidently doing their best to 'spoil the show' at York, just as they did at Bishopwearmouth in 1924.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">James Parker Smith</hi><hi> with his wife and daughter arrived from Berwick in their car which Kathleen drove.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Frederick J. Cutts</hi><hi>, Chaplain of the Sunderland branch of the Missions to Seamen, came to see me about the opening of the new Institute. It is amusing to note the absorption of these excellent folk in their own corner of the Lord's Vineyard. They are surprised and even wounded to discover that the Bishop of Durham has other parts thereof to visit &amp; care for!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
