<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent to Hodder &amp; Stoughton the amount (&#x00A3;90.) which I had promised for the book.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning was frittered away in writing letters, &amp; reading newspapers. In the afternoon I made a beginning with the Confirmations. We motored to Bishopton, where I confirmed 36 persons: and then we went on to Stockton, where in Holy Trinity Church I confirmed about 100 persons from the two parishes &#8211; Parish Church &amp; Holy Trinity. Among the candidates was Leonard Ropner's son, a weedy youth, whose health still causes anxiety.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was interested and pleased to observe that four very different parsons &#8211; Reilly (Bishopton), Bate (Redmarshall), Morris Young (Stillington), and Purvis (Holy Trinity, Stockton) &#8211; spoke very favourably of the Composite Book. I doubt whether these fulminating fanaticks in London have any considerable following among the parochial clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Prayer for the British Empire</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This God is our God for ever and ever.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He shall be our Guide unto death.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Almighty God, Who rulest in the Kingdom of men, and hast given to our Sovereign Lord, King George, a great dominion in all parts of the world: draw together, we pray Thee, in true fellowship the men of divers races, languages, and customs, who dwell therein, that, bearing one another's burdens, and working together in brotherly concord, they may fulfil the purpose of Thy Providence, and set forward Thine everlasting Kingdom.</hi><hi> Pardon, we beseech Thee, our sins and shortcomings. </hi><hi rend="underline">Keep far from us all selfishness and pride, &amp; give us grace to employ Thy good gifts of order and freedom to Thy glory and the welfare of mankind, through Jesus Christ, Thy Son our Lord, to Whom with Thee and the Holy Ghost be all glory &amp; dominion world without end. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
