<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi> renewed his onslaught on the Church of England last night and mentioned me by name. A reporter from the </hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi> came to see me: &amp; I dictated to him some observations on his Eminence's outbreak. Also I wrote a short letter to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Northern Echo</hi><hi>. It is evidently the deliberate policy of the Papists to make themselves as offensive as possible. They care nothing for the scandal to religion which their controversy entails: and they count (often successfully) on our reluctance to make play for the scoffers by crossing swords with them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert</hi><hi> and his brother came to lunch. The latter was once a chorister of Durham cathedral, has been an engineer in U.S.A. and now aspires to Ordination. He is 37, and has no degree. As he has served in the War, I might dispense with the age&#8211;limit &amp; the degree: but </hi><hi rend="underline">some</hi><hi> training he must have: &amp; I gather that he will be unable to maintain himself.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">James</hi><hi> &amp; his ladies went off to Harrogate after lunch. Ella and I walked to Bryden's house to enquire for Harold, who was sitting up. I said that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William Bryden</hi><hi> might work for me in place of George for the next month.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Earnest</hi><hi> sent me a becoming letter, &amp; the incident is closed: but the </hi><hi rend="underline">dies fatalis</hi><hi> holds.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather continues to be fine and very warm. Greasy paper and orange peel marked the holiday&#8211;making of yesterday, &amp; made the Park sad to look upon.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
