<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>I spent all the day in the Church Assembly </hi><hi rend="bold underline">listening to the Debate on the Revised Prayer Book Measure</hi><hi>. Most of the speakers were Evangelicals who were for the most part almost incredibly arrogant, and ignorant. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Inskip</hi><hi> wound up for the opposition in a rattling Parliamentary speech which took nearly an hour to deliver. He "went for" me over '</hi><hi rend="underline">the Protestant underworld</hi><hi>', and rent the Bishops. The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of York </hi><hi>concluded the debate </hi><hi rend="bold underline">in a speech of more than half an hour, which had</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">at least</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">three perorations</hi><hi>. Then the vote was taken viz</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>ForAgainst</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>Bishops 34 4</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>Clergy253 37</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>Laity </hi><hi rend="underline">230 92</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>517 133</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">This is a considerably better majority in the House of Laity than any of us had dared to hope: and ought to be sufficient to carry the measure through the Houses of Parliament</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">At the desire of the Archbishop of Canterbury there was no cheering when the figures were read out: but there was very intense feeling both in the House, and in the Crowded galleries</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We hastened away to get dressed for the Lord Mayor's dinner at the Mansion House. Ella and I sate between the Archbishop of Wales and his daughter (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Bramston) on my side, and the Bishop of Winchester and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Woods on hers. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishops were in excellent form, thought the younger Primate was, as usual, too long&#8211;winded</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Metropolitan of India (Westcott), replying for the over&#8211;seas Bishops was interminable. Mistaking the lassitude of his hearers for interest, he meandered on for, I suppose, half an hour.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
