<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 8 Communicants, including James. After breakfast I set to work on preparing notes for a sermon in the little mission at Cleadon, of which Cecil Booth has charge. The Bicentenary of Isaac newton's death (March 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1927) formed a peg on which to hang a discourse about the Revelation of God in nature as revealed by science. And the glorious verse in Proverbs XX.27. "</hi><hi rend="underline">The spirit of man is the candle of the Lord." provided a text.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I left the Castle at 5p.m., &amp; motored viâ Gateshead to Boldon, where he preached, and then I went on to the Mission Church in Cleadon, which was keeping its anniversary. I preached the sermon, which I had prepared, but which was not particularly well&#8211;suited for the occasion. I was pleased with the behaviour of the choir, which was un&#8211;surpliced. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Booth</hi><hi> seems to be making a good start. He is engaged to be married, but is not yet able to "afford a wife". But he is 31 years old, and every year's delay will endanger the success of an experiment which, in the most favourable circumstances, cannot but be precarious.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
