<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[84]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Storr</hi><hi> writes to me:– "I think the proposals (sc. for P.B. Revision) will go through. I hear on good authority that the Labour Members have taken their cue from an organization of 500 clergy with Labour sympathies, &amp; will either vote for the new book or abstain from voting on the ground that it is a question for experts."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selborne </hi><hi>writes to me:– </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Unless the majority of the House of Laity has changed greatly from the position it held two years ago, which I have no reason to suspect, the measure ought to pass by a good majority. At that time they sate silent and steadily voted down both sets of extremists. My anxiety lies in the two Houses of Parliament, not because the Protestant or Roman drum stirs any response in the bosoms of M.P.s or Peers, but because of the strong conservative instincts of the majority working in sublime ignorance of the subject. Also there is the wholesome feeling that law–breakers ought to be punished and they think that the Anglo–Catholics are the only law–breakers. Also there is smouldering resentment at the action of the Christian Socialist group of Bishops during the Coal Strike".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a pleasant letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Monty Bere</hi><hi>, who was once a close friend, but has rather dropped out of my life since we both left London &amp; married.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
