<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Review</hi><hi> arrived. My article reads rather savagely, and, perhaps, after the vote in Convocation the savageness has a gratuitous aspect! The great disadvantage of writing for Quarterlies is that the situation which shaped one's work has disappeared, so that what one writes is obsolete before it is read!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'Artifex' (Canon Peter Green) has a very kind reference to my little book in the </hi><hi rend="underline">'Manchester Guardian'</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Durham, where I licensed the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Owen</hi><hi> to Gateshead Fell, and then lunched with Wilson. After lunch I had a short interview with the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; then returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I picked up two decent lads, &amp; had some talk with them &#8211; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Kells</hi><hi>, aged 18, a chemist's assistant, and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ronnie Watson</hi><hi>, aged 19, a draper's assistant. I confirmed them both, and both now attend S. Peter's.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Some Protestant parson sends me a printed sermon in which he speaks of the 'caddish language of the Bishop of Durham'. There are many hostile adjectives to choose from, why should he select 'caddish' which seems to me equally pointless and offensive? I seem to have the ruinous power of piercing the pachydermatous!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
