<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went into the Abbey Church for the early celebration, and there received the Sacrament. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><hi> was there. He also is an ex&#8211;canon. After breakfast I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; recovered my bag with robes. On the way to Buckingham Palace, I picked up a small boy (</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Young</hi><hi>, 14 1/2 years old, and employed at the Conservative Club.), &amp; covenanted to give him a shilling for carrying my bag to the Palace. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I was interested to notice that the child wanted to refuse payment, when we parted</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I preached in the private chapel, a truncated version of the sermon on "The Way", which has done much duty. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">After service I had some talk with their Majesties</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> "I was very pleased with what you said about those dreadful Bolshevists" was the King's opening remark. I suppose he must have read some report of my sermon to the Mothers' Union. There was a crowded congregation at the Chapel Royal, including the Duke &amp; Duchess of York, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">with whom I had a pleasant chat after the service</hi><hi>. My sermon was that which I preached at Stockton from the words: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Take heed &amp; keep yourselves from all covetousness, for a man's life consisteth not in the abundance of the things which he possesseth</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Shall I speak tomorrow in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Trades Disputes Bill</hi><hi>, if there be opportunity to do so? In any case, if the division be then taken, I shall vote for the Bill.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>During the afternoon I rested, and wrote letters to Gerald Rainbow, Brooke Westcott, Heseldon, and William Suthren. Then I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; returned to the Abbey in time to hear (with difficulty) a sermon from Gamble. There was to be a later service broadcast in lieu of the usual service at S. Martin's, but this I did not attend.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><hi> came to supper, &amp; we had much pleasant conversation, which, however, left no deposit of worthy reminiscence. The Dean, who went off to be broadcast in the interest of the Abbey Funds, returned in good talking form. After everybody had gone to bed, he told me of an unpleasant interview he had had with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="underline">who came to ask for the use of Westminster Abbey for the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Congress. When this request was refused</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">lost his temper, &amp; bounced out of the Dean's study, banging the door behind him</hi><hi>! This sipclay f temper was equally discreditable &amp; disconcerting!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The episode is rather suggestive of a design on the part of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, who profess their readiness to accept the Revised Prayer Book, to make their acceptance the occasion of a mighty demonstration of the victory for </hi><hi rend="underline">their</hi><hi> principles which the Book may plausibly, perhaps fairly, be represented as providing. This policy could not but have the effect of embarrassing the Bishops still more.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">N. P. Williams</hi><hi>, the new Margaret Professor, who has hitherto been looked upon as an extreme Anglo&#8211;Catholick, has announced his intention of accepting the Revised Book, and (even more significantly) of </hi><hi rend="underline">taking to himself a wife</hi><hi>. The last would seem to seal a rift with the faction, for the 'celibacy of the clergy' is one of the new "Six Points" of "Catholick" requirement!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><hi> pointed out that in my Article in the "Nineteenth Century &amp; After", I have referred to the "</hi><hi rend="underline">centurion</hi><hi>'s" citizenship, which he purchased '</hi><hi rend="underline">with a great sum</hi><hi>'. It should have been rather the '</hi><hi rend="underline">chief captain</hi><hi>'s".</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
