<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A very hot day. I read Rufus Jones on the American Quaker in bed before getting up. After writing to Ella, I had breakfast, and then walked to the Athenaeum, where I found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Adam Smith</hi><hi>. He said: "As a Presbyterian I can honestly say that I find nothing to object to in your new Communion Service. It seems to me a very beautiful service". I walked to Lambeth, and spent the day until 4 p.m. with my fellow bishops. It is plain enough that we shall have endless troubles on interpretation if ever the revised Book is legalized. I had tea in the Athenaeum, &amp; then returned to Park Lane: where I rested </hi><hi rend="underline">in puris natualibus </hi><hi>until it was time to dress for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">I dined at 32 Wimpole Street with Lord Dawson of Penn</hi><hi rend="italic">, in order to meet an American statistician Professor R. Pearl. The company numbered 16 altogether, &amp; included Arthur Shadwell, Sir B. Mallet, Moon, &amp; Harold Cox. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I sate between mine host &amp; J. M. Keynes of King's Cambridge</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Keynes</hi><hi rend="italic"> is rather an unattractive fellow to look at dark with heavy features. He talked freely, and not uninterestingly. He had been in Russia recently, attending some academic Conference, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">and as his wife was Russian, he had been able to see a good deal</hi><hi rend="italic">. The worst feature of the present regime was the constant fear, in which men lived. The Cheka or Ogpu deserved its infamous reputation. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Dawson</hi><hi rend="italic"> chatted pleasantly. He was reading 'Elmer Gantry', and spoke of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the intimate connexion between emotional religion and sexual indulgence as an established and familiar fact</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Moon</hi><hi rend="italic"> recalled himself to my remembrance, and said that he had consented to stand as a Liberal Candidate for Oxford City. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> F. C. Chance said that he used to meet me when I wrote for the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Saturday Review</hi><hi rend="italic">. That is a distant memory now. I came away at 10.30 p.m. &amp; returned to Park Lane.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
