<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>July 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1927</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear Sir</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am obliged to you for your letter of July 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, in which you are good enough to invite me to enter into a public disputation with you on the subject of my speech on the Trades Disputes Bill, with which I understand you find yourself unable to agree.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>If you will inform me more precisely what are the points to which you take exception, I will carefully consider whether they are such as could be usefully discussed in that way.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>If, however, you merely wish to express your dissent from my opinions, I cannot think any useful purpose would be served by a public disputation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very faithfully,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Joseph Batey Esq. M. P.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went into the City, and had an interview with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Arthur Hird</hi><hi> in Warwick Square. He was as usual very friendly and communicative, amusingly, self&#8211;conscious &amp; world&#8211;patronizing! I walked back to the Athenaeum stopping at Partridge &amp; Co. to order some stationery. After lunching at the Deanery, I wrote some letters including one to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Batey M.P.</hi><hi>, who sent me a kind of challenge to a debate in Spennymoor in which he could "answer" my speech on the Trades Disputes Bill! This could not but be a futile performance, yet it is hardly judicious to decline a public discussion (discussion). Then I walked to the Athenaeum, and had tea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>&#8211;&#8211;We dined with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Struthers</hi><hi> to meet the American Ambassador (Ambassador) &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Houghton</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicksee</hi><hi>, the President of the Royal Academy, was there, at divers other folks, whose names I cannot recall. We had, after the ladies had withdrawn, some interesting talk with the Ambassadors about Bolshevism, American students of Life &amp; Business, the question of reducing naval forces, and Prohibition. He showed himself intelligent, god&#8211;tempered, and unflinchingly patriotic. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Ambassador (ambassador) was very positive that Prohibition was a great social reform, and an important factor in the extra&#8211;ordinary commercial prosperity of the Republic. He was himself, I observed, drinking champagne and port</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He said that he was convinced that Germany would soon adopt Prohibition: and that Great Britain might be forced into doing so in economic self&#8211;defence. He had never heard of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Periscope</hi><hi>, but opined that it must be one of numerous publications financed by the Anti&#8211;Prohibitionists. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Revelry</hi><hi>" he had not read, but understood that it was a libellous book beneath the notice of self&#8211;respecting men! </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sinclair Lewis</hi><hi> was one of a band of writers who dwelt on the weak points of American life, &amp; ignored all others. He knew Chicago well, and it was as safe as London, yet, </hi><hi rend="underline">he could not deny, that there was nearly a murder a day in the place</hi><hi>. I could not reconcile these statements. He described the methods by which American working men were held in fairly harmonious unity with their employers: but these did not proceed beyond a great system of material bribes. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
