<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright warm day, very delightful everyway. I finished the University Sermon: and had a lesson in golf from Lionel. Afterward, I wrote letters, and interviewed young Talbot, the eldest son of the late Vicar of Aiden's Annfield plain, who aspires to Ordination at Trinity. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Editor of the Nineteenth Century &amp; After, wrote to say that my lecture would be published in the July issue of his paper. </hi><hi>Ernest of Worcester sent me a learned tract on </hi><hi rend="underline">S. Oswald of Worcester &amp; the Church of York</hi><hi>. It is rather a piece of antiquarianism than of history: but it seems to be well done. I sent him &#8211; a Roland for his Oliver &#8211; my Earl Grey Memorial Lecture.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Old Bishop Knox sends me a civil note in reply to my letter. I suspect that he is becoming conscious of the general resentment which his militancy has provoked &amp; is therefore grateful for civility from a Bishop! </hi><hi>He has started an agitation which he may find it impossible either to direct or to terminate. His approaches to the various Nonconformists have been much resented by Anglicans and not very ardently welcomed by the Nonconformists themselves. </hi><hi rend="underline">The rude interruption of the Archbishop of Canterbury at the Religious Tract Society opened the eyes of the Public as to the quality of the Protestant Zealots, who have ranged themselves under Bishop Knox's banner.</hi> 
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
