<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a short address for use at the dedication of windows to which I was pledged, basely seizing the opportunity to parade the sad case of Durham Castle. Lionel and I motored to Gateshead for the function at 1 p.m. The Mayor &amp; Corporation attended as well as the members of the Newcastle &amp; Gateshead Chamber of Commerce. After the service the Rector entertained the company at lunch in 'the Anchorage' (i.e. the Anchoress's house) which adjoins the church. I sate between </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Joicey</hi><hi> and the Mayor. There were speeches of course. Lord J. replying for the Visitors said that he had been a child in the Anchorage School, &amp; owed all his success in life to the effective teaching of 'the three R's' which he received. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Renwick</hi><hi>, proposing my health, </hi><hi rend="underline">said that he had been a Member of my Congregation in S. Margaret's, Westminster</hi><hi>. Altogether, it was a very friendly company, but not one window was open, &amp; the atmosphere was deadly! We went on to the Goldsmith, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Reid</hi><hi>, &amp; left the Pastoral Staff to be repaired. Then we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> came to show me the Warden of Wadham's letter which he had just received accepting him for admission in October, &amp; expressing himself very agreeably about his work in the examination. The boy was radiant. I gave him a sovereign, &amp; my blessing. I begin to indulge the hope that he may have enough in him to justify my wasting money on his course at Oxford!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am concerned to hear that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><hi> is seriously ill. He is not the kind of man to stand much physical buffeting!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
