<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A calm, bright morning, of which I gained full advantage in the very comfortable bedroom "Wake", in which I had been placed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>What is the precise importance of Lent in the year of grace, 1927., to an English Bishop? It adds something probably to his official engagements: &amp; reduces the engagements which are not official: but is there anything which cuts deeper, and could be called religious?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We sate steadily at work all day, the afternoon being occupied by </hi><hi rend="bold underline">a deputation from the House of Laity</hi><hi>, who were very plainly at sixes and sevens among themselves. We sate on after tea, and, on the whole, made fair progress. It is, however, doubtful whether we shall finish our work this week. In any case I think I shall get off. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Inskip</hi><hi rend="italic"> wound up with a politely expressed, but clearly indicated, threat, that 'perpetual reservation' would send the Evangelicals into revolt: and of course </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Phillimore</hi><hi rend="italic"> was as threatening on his side. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Yet I doubt whether there is any volume of opinion in the country behind either fanatick. There is a good deal of 'bluffing' on both sides. Our only course is to go straight forward.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
