<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="underline"> B. F. R. Willcox</hi><hi>, assistant curate of Greenside, came to lunch. He is 40 years old, &amp; has been 17 years in Orders. I suggested that he should transfer himself to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, where the need of clergy is more urgent: and when he consented, I wrote forthwith to the Rector of that parish.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Sunderland, and there, in the parish church of Bishopwearmouth, I "commissioned" Canon </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Woods</hi><hi> to act as Missioner during the Ten Days Mission, which has been arranged in that parish. Before actually giving the Commission I made a short speech to the congregation. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Woods</hi><hi> has just been appointed Vicar of Croydon. He has a fine presence, an admirable voice, &amp; an aspect at once dignified and sincere. He is, I suppose, a "Liberal Evangelical", and separates himself sharply from both the prosecuting Protestants represented by Bishop </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knox</hi><hi>, and the unctuous gospellers who have no longer any leaders known to the public. He is now exerting himself to organize support for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Composite Book</hi><hi>, &amp; expresses the utmost disgust at the agitation against it. After the service we returned to Auckland. The weather today has been almost like summer, but it worsened at night fall.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
