<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through an acute &amp; well&#8211;planned brochure, which was sent to me as to all other members of either House of Parliament: &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">Is Britain over&#8211;populated? by R.B. Kerr</hi><hi>. It is an earnest plea for "Birth&#8211;Control" as the only method of avoiding the most fearful disasters? </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The subject is discussed as if it raised no moral issues at all</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> In relation to no other subject is the chasm which parts the Churchman from the ordinary Citizen more grossly apparent. The considerations which for the former are decisive have no place in the argument which determines the latter. They live in different worlds, and are mutually unintelligible. What must be the outcome of this profound dissidence? The Church can hardly convert the world: it can only make terms with it. But what terms? </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The History of Christianity is so full of paradox, that no extreme of self&#8211; contradiction can be said to be inaccessible to the Christian Hierarchy. Yet the fate of the salt which has lost its savour cannot be supposed to lie outside the possibilities of the Church's future</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from old Bishop Talbot the following acknowledgement of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>45 Lexham Gardens<lb/>Cromwell Road<lb/>W8.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The little "H. D." in the corner revealed to me whence came the 'Bishoprick'. I am really grateful for these little bits of remembrance, &#8211; &amp; I have read with interest your fine words about Bishop Lightfoot &amp; the relation of the Diocese to the Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I don't think I am </hi><hi rend="underline">so</hi><hi> deep in "the morass of an incapacitating despondency" as you are, partly because things are easier (in some ways) in the South &#8211; but perhaps more because the generation (about) which divides you and me has given me perhaps even greater reason for the "O pass: graviora' temperament, &amp; for the humble confidence that He who has led C. of E. so far will not leave her now.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>What are your plans? My wife has a great wish which I share to see Auckland by your hospitality once more. Would anything of the kind be possible in the last days of Sept. or first of Oct.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very sincerely<lb/>E. S. Talbot.<lb/>Bp.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[231]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Princess went away before dinner. She is an amiable and active lady, who plays her little part in the world with strenuous determination.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The papers announce that Nicholson, the Organist of Westminster Abbey has resigned, but give no indication of the reason. It is certainly the case that much dissatisfaction with the choir exists, &amp; may have come to his ears. His council might easily manufacture a pretext for resignation out of the fact.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Fenwick have arrived. He told me that he was a director of a mine in Sunderland. He is interested in History, &amp; expressed much admiration of Trevelyan's books.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi><hi> told me that the cost of the Duke of Marlborough's suit for the annulment of his marriage with Miss Vanderbilt was &#x00A3;8! </hi><hi rend="underline">I could but observe that no one supposed that the payment to the Vatican had taken the form of a legal charge</hi><hi>. It is suggestive that conversation tends to deal with the marriage problem with impressive regularity. Divorces are now so frequent, that the subject has become a matter of personal interest. There is no longer any social stigma on Divorce.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
