<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A gloomy morning with delusive intervals of sunshine which soon subsided into the comfortless depression of a wet day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Communion at 8 a.m. There were 13 communicants, including both my chaplains, both the visitors, and six of the household. This will probably be the last communion which James makes in the Chapel before he goes to sea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The military service in South Church was very well&#8211;arranged, impressive, and (I allow myself to hope) edifying. The centre of the church was filled by the soldiers in khaki, and other representative men. Lord Barnard &amp; his wife were present, and the City Fathers. My discourse was well listened to, but, perhaps, too elaborate for such a congregation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The chapel was filled to its utmost capacity at 3 p.m. when I confirmed about 80 persons, mostly adults. Among them were William and Edward Bryden. Parry&#8211;Evans was in command, &amp; his choir was very useful. Miss Mowbray was at tea, as were also several of the clergy, who had brought candidates. By this time, the weather had improved so that the congregation gathered &amp; dispersed in comparative comfort.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to George Nimmins.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
