<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from Canon Partridge a request to write the first article in the June issue of the Church Assembly News, and suggesting as a subject the discussion of the Deposited Book in the Church Assembly. Accordingly I expended the morning in writing an article, &amp; sent it to the Assistant Editor at the Church House. It is a wonderful surrender to the dominant influences that I should have anything to do with Partridge &amp; his press!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><hi> came on a short visit. He and Lionel walked with me to Binchester, where we looked at the Roman remains.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The National Laboratory of Psychical Research writes to the Council to ask whether I would consent to the opening of Joanna Southcott's box "now in their possession". "Joanna Southcott &amp; her alleged revelations have become in some quarters a semi&#8211;religious cult: if, on opening the box nothing of any Divine significance is discerned (which is highly probable), the fact will do much to explode a superstitious myth. In any case no good purpose will be served by continuing the atmosphere of mystery, &#8211; upon which superstition thrives."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On the other hand, by going to such a meeting I should contribute to the preposterous notion that importance attaches to the raving of this demented female!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Brooke &amp; Lionel accompanied me to Ousefield Plain where I confirmed about 80 persons in Dick's iron church. There were only 15 males among them. Linnell was there with other local clergy. He finds that preparation for his degree is practically impossible in his present situation. I hardly think his Vicar, Ferguson, is likely to make things easy for him</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
