<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A heavy atmosphere with gusts of hot wind did not facilitate the securing of a good night. I emerged on the day feeling rather dilapidate. For some while I read before getting up Rufus jones's account of the American Quakers. Their attitude towar(d)s military duty &amp; oaths was extraordinarily difficult to fit in to any working theory of good citizenship in the actual circumstances of colonies, always menaced by the Indians, &amp; necessarily involved in the wars with France &amp; Holland. Nor do the Quakers themselves appear to have been consistent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in the Temple Church at 11 a.m., and remained to the Celebration of Holy Communion. There was, of course, a large congregation, but the Benchers and Judges were conspicuous by their absence. The fact that it was Hospital Sunday, &amp; that the Judges were going to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's in state during the afternoon, may have gone some way to explain their absence, but I suspect that there is some resentment against the Bishop of Durham in connexion with his Lordship's attitude on the Prayer Book Revision. At least I know that the Master of the Rolls assigned his own absence to this cause. I noticed how significantly senior the men in the congregation were. All bald heads and grey beards, nowhere anything young. Why is this? and what does it portend?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My sermon was listened to with attention, but it did not "bite". Perhaps, the people were disappointed at having a sermon on "Tolerance", when they expected an appeal for Hospitals. Anyway, I felt baffled. After the services, we lunched in the Middle Temple. The company was small &amp; uninteresting. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice Banks, a heavy man, presided, &amp; was civil enough. Then I returned to the Master's House, &amp; rested until tea&#8211;time: after which the Mater &amp; I walked to the Priory Church of S. Bartholomew only to find it locked. Then we called on Hine&#8211;Haycock, and had talk with him. &#8211; We called also at the deanery, &amp; found Kitty at home, but Ralph absent. Catherine was there, a blooming girl of 17, so pleasant &amp; unaffected. Crawford comes of age on July 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, &amp; I promised if I could to look in on the family party. As we passed through the garden on our way home, the master called my attention to the lawn&#8211;tennis which was being played by some young men, &amp; told me that it had but recently been permitted. The secularist leaven is working throughout the entire mass of English life.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined quietly with the Master &amp; his wife: and after dinner he and I had a considerable palaver before going to bed.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
