<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>''The important question, as Phillips Brooks used to say, is whether, in our admittedly checker&#8211;board world of black and white, the black squares are on a white back&#8211;ground, or the white squares on a black background. It is a deep&#8211;seated Quaker faith that the permanent background is white, not black, &amp; that the ultimate nature of the Universe backs the aims that are true &amp; the things that are good''</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Rufus M Jones. ''The Faith &amp; Practice of the Quakers''. p. 167</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Arbuthnot Mairne</hi><hi> would appear to covet mightily the appointment as Professor of Greek, for he again writes to me sending a translation into Latin which he made of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Buffon's</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">Discours sur le Style</hi><hi>. It has been accepted by the Société des Belles Lettres and published in Paris. If it were merely a matter of scholarly qualifications, he would do excellently, and his age is more suitable than the age of Richards, who is almost too old; but the doubt enters when the question of temperament is raised. Would he fit in to the little society of the College? This is a consideration equally important and difficult to formulate or to justify. For, I am empowered to appoint a Professor of Greek, not a pleasant comrade, nor a saint, nor a good preacher!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I only realized this morning that I was expected to preach twice at Ryhope. So the morning was occupied in putting together the scheme of a second sermon. This is an infamous method of performing the teacher's office, but I have no remedy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Ryhope, where I consecrated a new aisle which had been added to the parish church, &amp; divers gifts which individuals had presented. I preached from the words of Psalm 119.96 </hi><hi rend="underline">''I see that all things come to an end, but thy commandment is exceedingly broad''</hi><hi>, and began my sermon by pronouncing a high eulogy on the Vicar, whose ministry in Ryhope for more than 24 years was crowned by the completion of the church. After dining in the Vicarage, where Knight's sister, as garrulous as himself, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Wynne Willson made up the party, we returned to the church for Evensong, &amp; here preached again, taking for my text S. Matthew iv.4 '</hi><hi rend="underline">Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the Mouth of God'</hi><hi>. There was a large congregation, but not so large as I had expected. We returned to the Vicarage, where Knight and I talked until past midnight. I suggested to him that he might go to Seaton Carew, which will be almost immediately vacated by Beavan's retirement: but he did not seem very eager!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
