<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">While we were collecting for breakfast, a messenger from Durham brought the tiding of Cruickshank's death. He was just over 65 years old. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I made his acquaintance in connexion with the Layman's League, which I founded in Oxford in 1885</hi><hi rend="italic">, and I kept in occasional touch with him until, when I came as Dean to Durham at the beginning of 1913, we were brought into close and continuous intercourse. He was an odd, impulsive, very sincere person, with a sensitive conscience, a warm heart, and a quick temper, very loveable and very impracticable &amp; was sometimes absurd. He was a fine scholar, and had "the ball at his feet" when he took his degree: but he could neither keep discipline nor take a just measure of relative importance. Hence he was practically futile, and, being both highly&#8211;strung and lacking in humour, apt to shrink into himself, and fret over rebuffs which a differently constituted man would have discounted and dismissed with a jest. Religiously he had traversed the familiar road which leads out of Anglo&#8211;Catholicism to Modernism; but his heart ever yearned for the consolations of Sacramental Christianity. I judge him to have been a humble and genuine believer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Partly his delicacy of health and partly, I surmise, the circumstances of his early upbringing made him very dependent on women; &amp; this circumstance also reacted on his character not, perhaps, wholly to its advantage.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella and I attended the meeting of the Prevention and Rescue Association of which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Cruickshank is the Head of the Council. I prefaced the meeting with a few words of regret and condolence. Then we lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow, and returned to Auckland. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> came to see me. He looks supremely happy and healthy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Knox</hi><hi> sent me his latest fulmination, a booklet entitled. '</hi><hi rend="underline">Will the Deposited Book Restore Order in the Church? Some startling facts'</hi><hi>. I wrote to him at some length in reply, and sent him a copy of "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishoprick</hi><hi>". Neither the letter nor the enclosures will phase the old man. In becoming the demi&#8211;god of the Protestant Underworld, he has made it difficult for him to change his course, and impossible for him to acknowledge his errors.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Manchester</hi><hi>, or rather his publisher, sends me his latest volume, "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Essays in Christian politics and kindred subjects</hi><hi>". In the Preface he alludes to an article of mine in the</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bishoprick</hi><hi>, &amp; says he was delighted "to find how close was our agreement."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Nigel E Cornwall</hi><hi>, who has offered himself for Ordination with a title to S. Columba's, writes to me very nicely in acknowledgement of my letter welcoming him to the diocese. He expresses himself with a frankness and modesty which allow me to form a good estimate of his quality.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
