<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Low Sunday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">c</hi><hi rend="italic">Clelland tells me that, when D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hunter retired from the ministry of Trinity Church, his succession was offered to D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Orchard, and, when he would not come, the offer was made to himself. When Campbell left the City Temple, there was a notion that a double ministry might be established there: &amp; he &amp; D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Orchard were actually sounded on the subject.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He was very interesting last night when </hi><hi rend="bold underline">he described his experiences in the underworld of Glasgow</hi><hi>, which he visited disguised as a tramp. What he saw and heard has convinced him that revolutionary forces of the worst conceivable kind exist and are gathering strength within our great cities.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I preached twice in Trinity Church</hi><hi>, and was interested both in the service and in the congregations. This is a Congregational church of the new model, and, though the minister disclaims agreement with D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Orchard and the "Free Catholics", he has evidently much in common with them. The service was of a similar character to our Mattins, only more fretfully broken up, and far more "ethical" &amp; sentimental.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a choir in mufti in the gallery at the end of the church, which sang well enough in the familiar professional manner. Evidently much pains is bestowed on the music. There was a large cross on the wall behind the Communion table, and a crucifix in the pulpit. The service&#8211;book was very similar to the Presbyterian Book of Common Order. I was impressed by the hearty and reverent singing of the hymns by the congregation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The congregation was not so large as I had expected, considering the efforts to advertise my coming, &amp; the piquancy, still considerable though diminishing, of an English Bishop in a congregational pulpit. In the morning there were a good many empty seats especially in the galleries, not so many in the evening. There were a good many men, old &amp; elderly for the most part in the morning, but younger in the evening. The congregation, as I was told, came from far and near. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">"If the tramway system broke down in Glasgow," said the Minister himself, "my church would cease to exist!"!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[63] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There came to supper two of the leading local sectaries &#8211; a Baptist minister named Roberts, and a Congregationalist Minister, named Hill. The latter has a curious resemblance in face &amp; form to Abraham Lincoln, &amp; is evidently proud of the fact. In America the people freely observed on it. He posed and thundered in full pulpit&#8211;wise, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; was the most ludicrous figure of a preaching man that I have ever chanced to see. He spoke very scornfully of Dissenters, and possibly imagined that by doing so he impressed me with his intellectual superiority: but I thought all the worse of him for it.</hi><hi> The Baptist was less remarkable, and on the whole impressed me more favourably. We had a great talk over the economic problem. He disclosed the nebulous &amp; futile semi&#8211;Socialism which now prevails in the Nonconformist ministry. But he seemed to me probably more muddle&#8211;headed than insincere.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Donald Stevenson</hi><hi>, a wealthy &amp; benevolent coal&#8211;importer, came to tea. He is "a lifelong Liberal with strong leanings to Labour", and was the author of an excellent letter to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, which appeared on the 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> April.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
