<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>The Annual Reunion of the men whom I have myself ordained began with a celebration of the Holy Communion in the Chapel ^at^ which 32 of the clergy communicated. This was somewhat better than I expected as the new insistence on Fasting Communion is spreading here as elsewhere. About 50 men accepted my invitation. We numbered 53 at lunch, but the house party contributed 5 to the total. After luncheon, the men played games &amp;c. until 4.30 p.m. They were photographed during the afternoon. At 5.15 p.m. there was Evensong in the Chapel, and I gave them a short address on Prayer Book Revision. When they took their leave I gave every one of them a copy of the Loch Memorial Lecture. We were favoured with fine weather throughout. The men seemed to enjoy themselves. The Bishop of Jarrow talked over divers matters of diocesan interest. He tells me that a small committee has been appointed to fix the duties of the Greek Professor, and that they will inform me of their decision in a few days. It appears that there will be no lack of candidates for the chair, though I doubt whether they know the type of work which it involves. Arbuthnot Nairne, Richards, and Bate are anxious to be appointed, and any one of the three would make a creditable professors. Whether any of them would make also a good Canon of the Cathedral is more doubtful.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
