<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella went off to London by the early train, with the purpose of spending the week&#8211;end with her cousins at Canterbury, and then attending the court. Fearne accompanied her to the station at Darlington, and then went to pay a visit to Miss Headlam at Whorlton.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I prepared notes for an address to the men at Gateshead, since Stephenson was very clear that some "extemporaneous" effusion would be more effective, &amp; certainly more acceptable than a written composition.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left the Castle at 1.45p.m. and motored to Gateshead, where I preached to a congregation of men, members of that most futile society, the C.E.M.S, in the parish Church. Then I had tea with Stephenson, and much talk. After this, I went to Ryhope and spent a garrulous hour with P.Y. Knight, who showed me the enlarged Church, and arranged the details of the Consecration Service. Then I returned to Auckland having travelled 69 miles.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lord Ravensworth has sold his property, save only the Castle &amp; Park, to some speculator: and there seems some uncertainty on the point whether the advowson of Lamesley has, or has not, been sold also. The school, &amp; schoolmaster's house are claimed by the purchaser, and a field rented by the Vicar at a nominal rent, &amp; essential to his comfort, is now, unless he can purchase it, likely to be taken away. It is a woeful business.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
