<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started to read </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Anderson Scott's</hi><hi> new book. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Christianity according to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Paul</hi><hi>" and was well pleased with it. After lunch, Lionel and I motored to Monk&#8211;Heseldon, where I consecrated a small piece of ground to be an addition to the existing burial ground. It was a cheerless performance. We had tea at the Vicarage. The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. J. A. Little</hi><hi> has now been 2 years in charge of the united parish and seems to be contented and useful in his work. His wife assured me that they were very happy there. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi><hi>, who attended the consecration as Registrar, is a strong Protestant of the old prosecuting type. I think he was rather disconcerted at my defence of the Revised Book.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">All the parties in the Church have built hopes on me, and all have in turn been disillusioned. First, the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics"; then the Modernists: now the Evangelicals, have had to discover that I do not belong to them. It is not that I am a false man, or, in any marked degree, a coward, but that I have no capacity for partisanship. I dislike the 'rag&#8211;tag&#8211;&amp;&#8211; bob&#8211;tail' of party too much, and cannot endorse the restrictions of party&#8211;discipline. I am just an ecclesiastical Ishmael!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
