<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After the excitements of yesterday, the Assembly was a scene of somnolence and boredom. A large proportion of the members had gone home: &amp; the important business of Finance was gone through with expedition and with little criticism. Somebody passed me the following lines:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The tumult and the fighting dies</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">
               <lb/>The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Inskips</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Iicks</hi><hi rend="italic"> depart:<lb/>The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Stone</hi><hi rend="italic"> by </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> inertly lies.<lb/>The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Sparrow</hi><hi rend="italic"> soothes the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Pearcéd</hi><hi rend="italic"> heart.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The flashing sword of gay </hi><hi rend="italic underline">DUNELM</hi><hi rend="italic">
               <lb/>Is sheathed: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Gloucester</hi><hi rend="italic"> gnaws his knuckles:<lb/>The careworn </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Hugh</hi><hi rend="italic"> deserts the helm,<lb/>And </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Manchester</hi><hi rend="italic"> his belt unbuckles.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went across to the House of Lords, &amp; listened to the concluding stage of the debate on the Bishop of Manchester's Bill. It was thrown out on the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> Reading by 144 to 36.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Earl Russell spoke for the Bill, which, however, he praised very tepidly: and Lord Birkenhead made a brilliant, discursive, impudent and destructive attack on it. Both speakers referred to my speech, and both very considerately. As we passed into the lobby, Lord Balfour spoke to me in high terms of compliment of my speeches, which he had not heard. "Everybody is talking to be about them", he said. This was flatterous, &amp; pleasant to hear. We spoke of the division in the Church Assembly, and he seemed to think that the Parliamentary prospects were favourable. But there are elements of danger in both Houses. Carson and Danesfort look coldly on me: but they are the "Die&#8211;Hards" of traditional Protestantism, who can hardly be very numerous. There are the extreme Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, like L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Halifax and the Duke of Argyll: and there are the lawyers, like Hanworth, Sumner &amp; others. There are also the Liberal &amp; Labour Oppositions. Could all these combined bring into the lobby 100 peers against the Book? There are at least a score of episcopal votes against them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There was a dinner party. Sir E Brooksbank &amp; his wife Judge Tobin, Canon &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="italic">Donaldson, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="italic">How dined here.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
