<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the Furness Sermon, and made a (slightly abbreviated) copy for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi>, which I sent to Patrick Lacey.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Heselton from Gateshead came to lunch, and afterwards discussed with me the situation in which he stands. He is evidently "restless", but I advised him to remain at S. Mary's until I want him for more independent work.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A deputation from the little parish of Hamsterley came to represent the needs of their parish, to which I must shortly appoint a new vicar. They want a young man, married, musical, not a politician, a sportsman, and all for &#x00A3;300 per annum!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I interviewed a lad from Shildon who aspires to the succession of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">James Wilson</hi><hi>. He is highly recommended by the Socialist, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watts</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It appears probable that the Function at Furness Abbey will be made the occasion of another unedifying parade of the standing conflict between England and Rome: for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Lancaster Daily Post</hi><hi> announces that the Anglican Commemoration on the 16</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> July is to be followed by a Roman Commemoration on the 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. I make no direct reference to the controversy in my sermon.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
