<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi> contains an extract from an article in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Tablet</hi><hi>, in which the writer takes up the cudgels on behalf of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi>, but not, I think, very effectively. However, I thought it well to write to the Editor for a copy of the issue containing the aforesaid article.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the whole morning in writing letters, &amp; in going through the diocesan list of clergy with a view to making an appointment to South Westoe. It is truly disheartening to note how many of the clergy are incapacitated by their age, or their poverty, or their proved inadequacy, or the known extravagance of their opinions, or their ill health.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch Lionel &amp; I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Hurworth</hi><hi> where I confirmed 37 candidates. The advowson has recently been purchased by the Church Association, through the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> A. T. Faber</hi><hi>, who for 22 years past has held the Vicarage, is not a Low Churchman. After the service we had tea with the three </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Misses Forster</hi><hi> in their very pleasant &amp; well&#8211;appointed house. Then we motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Billingham</hi><hi> where I instituted the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev F.C. Tymms</hi><hi> to the Vicarage. There was a good muster of the local clergy, and the congregation filled the fine parish church. The service was impressive, and will, I hope, do good. The parish has been greatly neglected in recent years, and if Tymms can restrain his Anglo&#8211;Catholic ardours, he ought to do well enough. We returned to Auckland after the service.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
