<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This "covering letter" occupies my mind. It must be as little polemical as possible, and as much informing. I am not greatly attracted by the literature, which it is designed to "cover", nor am I so much in love with the Revised Prayer Book as to commend with enthusiasm to anybody. It is no more &amp; no less to me than a </hi><hi rend="underline">pis aller</hi><hi>. As such I have advocated its adoption, but it is not easy to write convincingly or winningly about a </hi><hi rend="underline">pis aller</hi><hi>! It is an odd reflection that Lord Holmes, who is urging me now to come forward so prominently as the mouthpiece of the Episcopate, wrote very insultingly about me in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi><hi> and in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times,</hi><hi> when I was appointed to Hereford. Is the change in him, or in me? or, is it, perhaps a change in both of us? I do not think that anything could possibly justify his treatment of me in 1918, but I am more disposed now than I was then to make allowances for his youth and prejudices, and to admit that I must have appeared an entirely odious &amp; unworthy person to such men as he.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered altogether 9 communicants among whom was our Swiss guest, and the new butler's&#8211;boy, John. All was very solemn, still, &amp; consolatory.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I wrote the "covering letter", and sent it to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Oldham</hi><hi>. Then I wrote to my three boys &#8211; George Nimmins, William Badham, &amp; James Wilson &#8211; addressing the letters severally to Java, South Africa, and Peru. That is an evidence of the dispersion of the English.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon we all motored to Durham, and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. The ladies went to tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Denny, &amp; I went to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Meade&#8211;Falkner. There was an artist lady, Miss Hodgson, also at tea, &amp; she shewed me her sketchbook, with many admirable pen drawings of "Saxon" sun&#8211;dials, Norman doorways, etc. Meade&#8211;Falkner walked back to the College with me through the Cathedral. He insisted that Durham is the most impressive church in the world, &amp; repeated my dictum that it is "</hi><hi rend="underline">the Dies Irae in stone</hi><hi>" as precisely true &amp; adequate. We spoke of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><hi>, but rather to my surprise, he disclaimed any special affection for him. Both men were possessed of certain feminine characteristics, which militate against mutual understanding, large views, &amp; generous interpretations. They were too much alike to appreciate one another.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
