<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension Day, May 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 9 communicants including Colonel Marsh and Lionel. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then, before going to Durham, I wrote to William.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>We all, except Fearne, motored to Durham for the service in the Cathedral, when I preached the University Sermon to a large congregation of students, male &amp; female, cadets from the school, ladies from the College, &amp; the general public. The sermon was well listened to, &amp; occupied 32 minutes in delivery. After the service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>Lionel and I left the Castle at 5 p.m., and motored as far as Sunderland together. Then, leaving him to preach in Bishopwearmouth, I went on to </hi><hi rend="underline">Jarrow</hi><hi>, and preached on Prayer&#8211;Book Revision in S. Peter's Church, taking occasion from the historical associations of 'Oak&#8211;apple Day' to speak of the Restoration Settlement of which the new Prayer Book is the revising. The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Chapman</hi><hi>, is a 'rough diamond', and not unlikely to "get across" his Parochial Church Council. After service I returned to Auckland Castle, stopping at Bishopwearmouth Rectory to pick up Lionel on the way.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
