<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, April 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant morning, but an uncertain sky. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.a.m. There were seven communicants including James. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to William, &amp; sent him a copy of the Loch Memorial Lecture. I motored to Sunderland, &amp; lunched with Wynne–Willson. The whole family were assembled – goodly company. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I motored to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Gabriel's, and addressed about 90 or 100 young men in an institute adjoining the church. This was Hall's "crowd", and pleased me well. I spoke about the Revolt against Christianity which marked both the French and the Russian revolutions, and examined the reasons. After this meeting I walked for nearly an hour with the vicar (Scott).</hi><hi rend="italic"> He showed me the very pretty park, the existence of which I had not suspected. Both Unwin &amp; Hall came to tea. The two children, Ronnie &amp; Dorothy, were there also. We got into a Christological discussion in which I was rather startled to hear Scott express opinions which were extremely modernist. Add this disclosure to the similar one from Spencer–Wade, and it becomes difficult to doubt the abandonment of the orthodox faith by the younger Evangelicals. They have no doctrine of the Church wherewith to mitigate the effect of the collapse of Biblical authority. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Quo Tendimus</hi><hi rend="italic">? I preached at Evensong to a crowded church. The new organ (a harsh instrument) was used to the utmost, &amp; everybody sang at the top of his or her voice! After service I returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
