<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A gusty day with sudden storms of rain. We started at 10.30 a.m., and motored to Carlisle without misadventure, arriving at 1.15 p.m. The distance is about 74 miles. We lunched in the County Hotel, and then walked up to the Cathedral. We fell in with the Dean, and exchanged civilities. Then we returned to the station, where I took train for Glasgow, &amp; Ella &amp; Fearne motored to Murraythwaite.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At the Central Station I was met by mine host, &amp; brought to his house. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">c</hi><hi rend="italic">Clelland is a vigourous man of 45, with a strong chin &amp; a somewhat aggressive aspect and manner. There came to meet me at dinner D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Russell, a medical man who was recently Chairman of the Congregational Union &#8211; he also is a reviewer, mainly I gathered, of medical books &#8211; &amp; D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Patterson, a minister of the Church of Scotland, a grave, demure respectable man who said little. After dinner there came in a novel&#8211;writer, named John Ressick, a large, self&#8211;important man, who spoke oracularly, &amp;, of other novel&#8211;writers, somewhat severely. But all four men &#8211; mine host &amp; his friends &#8211; were in their several ways notable men, of a stronger type than one is accustomed to meet in clerical society in England.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
