<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The refusal of the younger clergy to accept the conditions of ministry in these industrial districts is becoming general. Yesterday, I learned from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Kay </hi><hi>that he has arranged to go to India: now Prideaux writes to warn me that he is in treaty to go to Africa. These are young men, and among my best. The withdrawal of the more vigorous &amp; efficient clergy is telling disastrously on the Home Church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote great part of a sermon for the Men's Service at Gateshead next Saturday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch, Lionel and I motored to Stanhope where I confirmed 57 persons, of whom only 4 were presented from Stanhope itself, which has a population of 2500, and two resident clergy!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On our way to Stanley by Crook for the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Confirmation we turned aside at Wolsingham to visit Harold Bryden in the Sanatorium. He was in bed, &amp; unable to speak above a whisper. At Stanley I confirmed about 70 persons. The Church was crowded, the candidates attentive, &amp; the congregation reverent. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The fineness of the day and the beauty of the country made our confirmation tour exceedingly enjoyable. There can be no disputing the claim of Durham to be a very beautiful county. Polluted by smoke &amp; defaced by slagheaps as it is, it can yet show scenes of wonderful loveliness.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
