<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My letter appeared on the front page of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, and I received from the Editor the following epistle:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Henson</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your admirable letter has cheered a strenuous Friday night, and relieved a dull paper. If the Catholic revival ever deprives you of your Bishopric, I hope you will come and be a leader&#8211;writer on "the Times"! Meanwhile I take it as a welcome sign that you are feeling fairly robust.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours ever.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>G. D.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Also, I received from Geoffrey Fry a letter saying that the Prime Minister wanted see me "on the matter which he discussed with you some weeks ago". This is the vacancy in Newcastle, &amp; I shall be glad to know what is decided. I walked round to Downing Street, but the P.M. had gone into the country, and Fry had not appeared: so I went to the Club, and sent him a note. Then I called on Vernon Storr, and had some talk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Abbey was crawling with C. L. B. boys, who had come up to London from all over the country, to be inspected by the Prince of Wales this afternoon. I was recognized by two sets of them &#8211; one from Durham, and one from Canterbury.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was told the following story of President Harding:&#8211; The President meeting a prominent Senator is at once asked for a favour. With his usual benignity he expressed his willingness to oblige. "M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> X., a notable boot&#8211;legger, has been arrested: he must be released". The President's face was clouded. "But that is impossible: you have asked the one thing I simply can't do". "M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> President, it is really important: you must release him"…. "I really cannot". "But M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> President: </hi><hi rend="italic underline">he is our boot&#8211;legger</hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="i bold">!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">George Adam Smith</hi><hi>, who has recently been visiting his American son&#8211;in&#8211;law, gives an ill of the working of Prohibition in the States. He was himself invited to drink wine quite openly, and prively was offered whisky as a compliment to his nationality. To his astonishment he was introduced to a Judge who was drinking the smuggled spirit without shame. He was told of one man who having paid nearly &#x00A3;3. For a bottle of Scotch, discovered when he uncorked his purchase nothing more exhilarating than cold tea!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My letter to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> appears to be much approved. </hi><hi rend="underline">Evelyn Cecil</hi><hi> was quite effusive: and the Master of the Temple thought it admirable. </hi><hi rend="underline">Selby&#8211;Bigge</hi><hi> said. "You've wiped the floor with them again: you must have enjoyed doing it," </hi><hi rend="underline">Vernon Storr</hi><hi> thought it most effective. It is always interesting to know what other people think of one's work.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I arrived in the Temple shortly before 6 p.m. and was kindly welcomed by the Master &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Draper. Their little boy is now 4 years old, and seems an ingenious child. I had not realized that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Draper was the daughter of my Greek Professor Designate. The master and I walked in the Temple Gardens for an hour before dinner, and had much talk. He says that the opinion of the Benchers regards Lang as likely to be the next Archbishop of Canterbury: and this agrees with my own opinion. He thinks that Inge is losing influence by going on writing articles for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi><hi>. It is difficult to determine the truth of this. Inge is certainly placing a considerable strain on the loyalty of his friends, &amp;, though his resources of knowledge and ability appear to be almost limitless, it is impossible to refuse admission to the doubt whether he is not running the risk of exhausting both by such incessant journalism. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
