<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left Lake End at 10a.m., and motored to Bishop Auckland by way of Penrith and Appleby, arriving at the Castle about 10 minutes before 2p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The papers announce that the new Regius Professor of Modern History in Cambridge is to be </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macaulay Trevelyan</hi><hi>. It is an excellent appointment and I was able to send him an entirely sincere letter of congratulation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Buchan</hi><hi> sends me 'with the Author's compliments' his new novel, '</hi><hi rend="underline">Witch Wood'</hi><hi>. He is certainly the most versatile genius of my acquaintance: and also one of the most loveable of men. In this combination he is the true successor of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter</hi><hi>, with whom in his type of mind &amp; composition he presents many points of likeness. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Bolshevism is the result of the transference of Jesuit maxims to revolutionary tactics: its spirit is the same as that of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ecclesia militans</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Ignatius Loyola. In both we find the principle that the end justifies the means: with the Jesuits the existence &amp; prosperity of the Order and of the Church, with the Bolsheviks, the Soviet régime &amp; the dictatorship of the proletariat is the end to be attained by all means …. If we are really to call Bolshevism a branch of Jesuitism, we should have to style it perhaps 'a barbarous Jesuitism'".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Fülöp-Miller. P. 283</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
