<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That queer wide fanatick </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ferguson</hi><hi> who takes the Revised Prayer Book very seriously to Heart, writes to thank me for my "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">absolute fairness and kindness to those who felt bound in conscience to speak &amp; vote against the Resolution at Saturday's </hi><hi>Conference."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I revised and partially re&#8211;wrote the sermon on </hi><hi rend="underline">Tolerance</hi><hi> which I preached to the University in Durham Cathedral on May 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, with view to repeating it in the Temple next Sunday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke&#8211;Westcot</hi><hi> came to lunch, and discussed with me </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">whether he ought to accept the benefice of Corby</hi><hi>, which the patron desires to offer him. It has a gross income of &#x00A3;1219 and 1449 parishioners. He is 30 years old, and has been in Orders no more than 5 years. If he were alone I have no doubt that he ought to decline this benefice, but in view of his wife's health and his 3 small children, </hi><hi rend="italic">I dare not dissuade him. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I counselled him to see the patron, inform himself of every relevant circumstance, and take the advice of his uncle, the Metropolitan of India, who is coming here for the Auckland Reunion on S. Peter'sDay.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I think it is a grave disadvantage that Corby is adjoining his father's benefice.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[134]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Instigante diabolo</hi><hi> I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> William H. Robinson to say that, if the copy of More's English Works, which he offers for &#x00A3;60 in his catalogue of 'rare &amp; valuable books' be in good condition, I am disposed to purchase it!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I wrote to the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Edmund's, Gateshead, (Rev. John Wilson) inquiring whether he would accept Stillington, if he were offered it. The gradualness of the process by which benefices can be filled up, is a plaguey nuisance when one is trying to carry out a general shuffle!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Also, I wrote to Arnold, the Rector of Wolsingham, telling him that David Harold Bryden is in the County Sanatorium in his parish, &amp; suggesting that he might arrange to prepare him for Confirmation. If necessary I promised to confirm him privately.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>These American ladies, with their shrill tuneless voices and transatlantick accent and idiom, get on my nerves. I gather that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Sayre is a connexion of the late President Wilson, whom I hold in abhorrence, though she shares my loathing for the Prohibition policy.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
