<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[78]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I decided to take 'Tolerance' as the subject of my sermon in Durham Cathedral on May 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>: and, for my text, the passages in Acts, which describe the treatment of the Christians by two types of tolerant persons, the Rabbi Gamaliel and the pro&#8211;consul Gallio. The historical associations of the day will provide an illustration of the folly of intolerance. I made some notes for my sermon in the course of the morning.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Sykes came to lunch. He discussed the arrangements for the gathering of the Auckland Brotherhood here on June 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. The main problem is how to provide lodging for the Brethren. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Sykes told me that Lightfoot had found out the character of Watkins before he died</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He came to the diocese without any experience of ecclesiastical administration, &amp; fell an easy victim to the archdeacon's wiles!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Anglo&#8211;Catholick opposition is gathering strength: and the Protestant underworld is in full cry. </hi><hi>I am not without anxiety as to the future of the Revised Book. However, Professor Heawood, who is himself an Evangelical, has undertaken to introduce a motion at the Diocesan Conference on June 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, approving the book. He is a little sore over my gibes at the Evangelical Party in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>, but has gone too far to oppose the Book now!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He came to discuss the case of the Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
