<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Tuesday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful morning. The views on every side are seen to great advantage. Mine host &amp; hostess carried me off to see a curiously interesting church &#8211; Cartmel Fell. It had a three&#8211;decker pulpit, a medieval chancel screen adapted to enclose a faculty pew, some fine medieval glass in the East window, and the figure from the Rood, probably 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Kennedy drove us in his car: I sat beside him &amp; had some talk. The view of Windermere was superb. Curlew, circling and whistling, added to the charm of the scene. Oliver Stanley finds the double allegiance, to Parliament and to the City, rather difficult. He evidently inclines to devote himself altogether to the latter, where he is now making much money. I left Witherstock Hall about 2.45 p.m., and reached Auckland at 6.45 p.m. Going and coming I travelled 161 miles. Save for a thunder shower at Sedburgh, where I had tea, the weather was excellent, &amp;, after I had got away from the Lakes there was no traffic on the road. On the whole, I enjoyed this little jaunt as much as I am capable of enjoying anything.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Beavan, the Vicar at Seaton Carew, wrote to inform me that he had accepted a living in the diocese of Canterbury. He expressed himself very properly. He vacates a benefice which is in my patronage, and comparatively desirable as there are no more than 2500 parishioners, and the income is stated to amount to &#x00A3;450 net.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
