<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
        <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Patriotism, philosophy and the indifference of the rural masses – these were the causes that gave pause to Christianity. Would they have been finally successful if the violence and destruction had continued? One thing is certain, that at the said period </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the greater part of the French nation had managed to do without religion, the habit of centuries had been broken, and if the historian had bent however keen an ear, no general groan, no great popular wail of grief and anguish, would have audible to him</hi><hi rend="italic">. If the victories which saved France, which reduced to impotence alike the foreign foe and the anti–revolutionaries whose accomplices the priests seemed to be – if these victories had been long delayed, if patriotism had been the stay of philosophy for a longer period, if there had been any reason for the continuance of violence, who can say that such a course of events might not have proved fatal to Christianity in France.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">v. Aulard, 'Christianity &amp; the Fr. Revn. p 123</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The extinction of Christianity in England will not be attended by any terrifying circumstances of violence and persecution. Insensibly and very gradually the nation will have abandoned its immemorial religion. For the most part the people will be unconscious of any change, for the industrial multitude, detached from local loyalties and ever moving to and fro on the tides of commerce, has never possessed a religion worthy the name. Education has been generally secularized, and the "neutral" teaching of the schools imparted by teachers who are largely leavened with anti–Christian sentiment, is taking an anti–religious colour. The popular habit is mainly secular. Even nominally the Christians are but a petty fraction of the population, and of these nominal Christians a large proportion lives in the complete neglect of religious observance. If the parish churches were closed, and all the offices of organized religion ceased, the great majority of English people would not be required to alter the accustomed procedure of life. The ideas which sustain churches have perished from the public mind, and no fragment of authority invests the preaching of Christianity. It is only a question when the apparent abandonment of religion shall be formally acknowledged.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the Kazan Government, at the very time when the Communists were making reports on the astounding progress of the atheistic enlightenment propaganda, the whole Kheremiss tribe officially renounced Christianity and returned to the old pagan faith. The same thing happened in the Belovzevsk district, there, too, part of the population is organized on atheistic lines, while the other part has gone over in a body from the orthodox Church to paganism. In many districts pagan sacrificial feasts have been revived, oxen and rams are slaughtered and the flesh is cooked in special cauldrons and eaten with peculiar rites. Sometimes it even happens that the peasants find a compromise between the contradictory opinions by holding a joint festival to celebrate the pagan gods, the saints of the orthodox church, and the new heroes of communism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Fùtöp–Miller, "The Mind &amp; Face of Bolshevism". P. 218</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M. Aulard observes that the destruction of Christianity 'would not have implied the success of "natural religion". 'The peasant, who was at that time quite illiterate, would no doubt have relapsed for a while into his old pre–Christian habits, to the practices of magic and witchcraft, which were absorbed by Christianity (1.e.121). Roman Catholick France in the 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century and Orthodox Russia in the 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> are nearer the primitive paganism than Protestant England, but there will be some queer resurrections here also.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am beyond question very tired. My study has become odious to me, and every emergent demand is resented! Old Canon Croudace came to lunch bringing with him an unconfirmed grandson, whom I promised to confirm privately in September. I went into the Park, &amp; picked up two young men, both out of work, to whom I showed the Chapel, etc.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The '</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Northern Echo'</hi><hi rend="italic"> has a fiercely–worded leader headed "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Bishop of Durham and his clergy</hi><hi rend="italic">", which seems to be inspired by a personal resentment. I suspect that the ex–missionaries feel particularly angry at my disapproval of the flight abroad &amp; nobody cares to admit that he is either ailing or aged! The article says that I am in "the prime of life", and in 3 months time I shall be 64! The effusion seemed likely to give pain to many, and, therefore, I set aside my extreme dislike of noticing personal attacks, and sent a short letter to the Editor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I wrote to the Rector of Newtownards declining his request that I should preach next Sunday. Why should I not be free from the necessity of prating in my holiday. I am dead sick of the sound of my own voice.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
