<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A wet day until about 7 p.m. when the sun shone, and as we sate at dinner the sky was spanned by a rainbow.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received a letter from D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Richards announcing his acceptance of the Greek Professorship.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Sykes</hi><hi> came to see that everything was in trim for the Auckland Brotherhood next Tuesday. He said that I should be expected to preach a regular sermon to the Brethren. This adds another, and a very formidable, speech to be got ready for next week.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch Lionel and I motored to Stockton, where I consecrated an addition to the cemetery. There was a surpliced choir, and a procession of clergy &amp; others including the Mayor. The rain fell pitilessly all the time, so that the aspect of the company at the close of the proceedings was woeful indeed. We returned at once to Auckland, and arrived in good time for tea. There arrived to see the Castle </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">J.R. Buchanan</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bolitho</hi><hi>. The latter spoke to me somewhat confusedly about the project of endowing two bursarships for Ordination candidates.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to the Dean announcing the new Canon's appointment: and to William. The last letter was much belated for my visit to London hindered my writing then, and I have been abominably hustled.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Grant, O Lord, of thine infinite goodness to all who have suffered and sorrowed in the Great War such faith in thy Fatherly Providence, that they may not sink into doubt and despondency, but may believe that Thou reignest in the affairs of men, and turnest even the faults and follies of mankind to the service of thy blessed Will: and give them the comfort of thy Holy Spirit, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote this prayer for use at the service in South Church. It presents an aspect of the great tribulation viz. the dangerous strain on individual belief which it involves, not recognized in such prayers as I have seen. These are concerned with the peace of the world, the consolation of the bereaved, and the souls of the departed.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
