<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought the Bishop of Bombay's Charge, "Christ and Catholicity", which I spent much of the morning in reading through. It is, perhaps, marred by a rather "superior" tone, but it has much that is excellent and excellently spoken. He handles the whole subject of Reservation with great ability.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Editor of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi><hi> sent me an article which has appeared in his paper commenting on some observations in the Preface to the new Crockford anent the growing shortage of Ordination candidates. I was fool enough to dash off a short letter in response to his request.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished reading "</hi><hi rend="underline">A Quaker Saint of Cornwall</hi><hi>", and was interested, not least by the Epilogue, in which the authoress makes some observation on Quakerism. She emphasizes the fact that "it was not only, or mainly, those of lowly birth who responded and 'were reached ' by the truths he (Fox) preached", and says that the Society of Friends was 'never meant to subside into a middle–class &amp; lower middle–class community'. The spread of Anglo–Catholicism may, she suggests, create a demand for 'the message of the Inward Light'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel instructed me in the mysteries of playing golf. Ella &amp; Fearne motored to Harrogate. Ernest brought a young parson named Howard, an S.P.G. missionary in India to stay here for a few days. He appeared an intelligent and well–mannered young man.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
