<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning was brilliant. I dressed with my window wide open, so that I could enjoy the spectacle and hear the singing of the birds to the best advantage. I worked at the Glasgow Lecture, which grows ever duller as it extends! Has my right hand lost is cunning? Lilburn of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Oswald's, West Hartlepool, came to lunch, and afterward poured out the full stream of his parochial woes. His assistant curate Royale has left him, but left behind a legacy of Anglo&#8211;Catholick extravagance, which threatens to divide his flock! There is little enough of the Spirit of Christ in these fanaticks. After he had gone his way, I walked to Bryden's House, and saw Harold, who really seems better.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Sunnybrow, and there I confirmed about 100 persons, two&#8211;thirds of whom were females, from the three parishes of Sunnybrow, Willington and Hunwick. The population is as follows:</hi>
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>1.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>Sunnybrow</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>with 5,800 inhabitants</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>2.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>Willington</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>" 5,358 "</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>3.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>Hunwick</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>"  </hi><hi rend="underline">3,000 "</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>&#8211;</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi>&#8211;</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
<hi rend="doubleunderline">14,158</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi>About 280 persons reached the age of 14 last year in those parishes. Hardly more than one&#8211;third of them were presented for Confirmation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Miss Headlam arrived for a short visit.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
