<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious morning, leading in a veritable 'Day of the Sun'. May the Power of Christ's Resurrection be upon us in our Ministry today as we serve at the Altar, and preach to his People! The brightness of the morning will fill our hearts even though it empty our churches. And even for that emptying, He in his boundless clarity will give forgiveness. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 20 communicants, including our 3 guests &amp; Florence Bryden.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I went to South Church where I read mattins and preached, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. 81 com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Later, I motored to Annfield Plain, and had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi><hi> and his wife in their little house, around which they are striving to create a garden out of the prairie. He assures me that there is no chance of the pits failing in his district: on the contrary new pits are opening. But at Collierly, the pits are nearly exhausted, and that parish ought in the near future to be reunited to S. Aidans. This is an argument for building the new church on generous lines so that it may supply adequately the needs of the united parishes. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi><hi> gives a bad account of his predecessor, a canting and covetous Puritan, Talbot. I preached at Evensong in the iron church, &amp; was pleased with the service, but rather disappointed in the size of the congregation which did not fill completely even the iron church. But this parish is called ''Little Russia''!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
