<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wasted this day laboriously. Two letters from clergymen connected with the diocese of Norwich assured me that the Bishop misrepresented the feeling of his clergy, in has attitude towards Revision. I gather that the Bishop is announced to address a meeting of Nonconformists in London next week, and that this proceeding is particularly objected against by his own clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"It is deplorable that those outside the diocese should get a wrong impression, as if the Bishop represented the diocese's views, anyone who has inside knowledge realizes what a sad state of affairs exists: I will not go into details - always courteous and gentlemanly in his behaviour to his clergy, he is a man apart from us: we are ready to believe that his 'vision' is blurred by the unfortunate state of his bodily health."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This coincides with much that I have heard from other sources.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel and I motored to Hartlepool, where I confirmed 190 persons in the noble parish church, which was densely crowded. I heard with regret that two assistant curates, Royle from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Oswald's, and Coles from S. Hilda's were about to leave the diocese, the one because he cannot endure his vicar, the other because he finds himself unfitted for parish work! The reasons are as contemptible as the conclusion is unfortunate. We returned to Auckland after the service.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
