<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>I wrote a sermon for use at Ryhope next Wednesday. Jimmie came to lunch and stayed to dinner. A numerous company came to play tennis. D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Spooner with a party of friends came to tea, and were shown the Castle. Mead–Falkner came also, &amp; I had much talk with him about the appointment to the Chair of Greek. </hi><hi rend="underline">He had just received the gratifying announcement that he had been elected an hon: fellow of Hertford</hi><hi>. We went through the names which I had collected, &amp; agreed that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Richards</hi><hi> of Oriel was plainly the best of them. I wish he were not an Anglo–Catholic and a Welshman. For the first there is always the white sheet: but for the last, the dolorous question of the prophet holds, </hi><hi rend="underline">Can the Ethiopian change his skin? or the leopard his spots?</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Rogers, a grand–daughter of Bishop Maltby has deceased, and in her will has left to the See of Durham a picture of Auckland Castle by J. W. Carmichael.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>James Wilson Carmichael (1800–1868), marine painter, was born at Newcastle–upon–Tyne in 1800. At about the age of 10 or 11 he went to sea. He returned, &amp; was apprenticed to a shipbuilder, who employed him in drawing and designing. His early works are in water colours, but about 1825 he began to paint in oils. Between 1838 and 1862 he was a frequent exhibitor at the Royal Academy, at the British Institute, &amp; at the Suffolk Street Gallery. About 1845 he left Newcastle for London. Probably about 1862 (at which date he ceased to exhibit in London) he went to Scarborough, &amp; there died on 2 May, 1868. In the north of England his work was highly thought of. He appears as an author, having published '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Art of Marine Painting in Water Colours</hi><hi>'. 1859, and '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Art of Marine Painting in Oil Colours</hi><hi>'. 1864.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>(v. Dictionary of National Biography)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Professor Bury died two days ago. I remember meeting him years ago when he was a young Irishman with red hair, a high complexion, and an alert manner. He is said to have been an atheist, &amp; the statement receives confirmation from the offensive little volume on "</hi><hi rend="underline">The History of Free Thought</hi><hi>" – which he contributed to "The Home &amp; University Library".</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
