<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the Scott lecture after some fashion. It is a poor performance, but must serve.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev. G. R. Wilkinson</hi> <hi rend="italic">, Vicar of Ingleton, came to lunch. I suggested to him the possibility of his effecting an exchange with one of the Vicars of large parishes, who is finding his work excessive. He received the suggestion favourably, and I told him that he might be approached on the subject shortly. Then I wrote to the </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev. H. G. Cobb</hi> <hi rend="italic">, Vicar of Holy Trinity, Hartlepool, suggesting the possibility of an exchange with Wilkinson. I don't like exchanges, but they are sometimes the only method available for effecting an indispensable transference. The 'spiritual' objections to them are removed when the Bishop himself takes the initiative.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After lunch I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Lord Buckmaster has another long and vehemently worded letter in the "Times" on Divorce. His method of parading 'hard cases' is singularly unconvincing to those who insist that 'hard cases' make bad law', and argue that to relieve them by multiplying causes for divorce would create more hardships than it would remove. The whole subject is extraordinarily baffling. On the whole I incline to think that some alteration of the Law is needed, but I am quite unable to see any prospect that the Church generally will be persuaded to go with me. All the stream flows in the direction of the Roman dogma of indissolubility.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>