<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A beautiful day. I went to the parish church and celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There was a considerable number of communicants. Two hymns were sang, and the whole conduct of the service pleased me. <hi rend="bold underline">Hudson Barker prides himself on the character of being a "Prayer–Book Anglican", an unpopular and almost unintelligible type of Churchman in these days!</hi></p>
         <p>At 10.30 a.m. the Mayor &amp; Corporation marched in procession to the parish church, which was filled to its utmost capacity. I preached on the Divine authority of civil governors, repeating the sermon which I preached last year at Gateshead. After lunch I went to S. Stephen's and dedicated War Memorials. Also I preached another sermon. I had tea with the Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thurlow</hi> &amp; his sister, who seemed pleased with their exchange of Horden for S. Shields. I wound up the day by preaching at the military hut which serves as the Parish Church of S. Francis. <hi rend="italic">This is the "</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Anglo–Catholic" centre, and its mind</hi> <hi rend="italic"> is much disturbed by the sudden fall of the late Vicar, </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Hiram Craven</hi> <hi rend="italic"> into the pit–fall of matrimony! The poor man felt it necessary to explain to the flock that they must no more address him as "Father"!! The deacon, Wright, has carried on the parish single–handed &amp; developed considerable power. The only eccentricities at Evensong were that a hymn was thrust in before the 'Magnificat', and the choir &amp; congregation sate while they chanted the Psalms to Gregorian Music.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p>After Evensong I was taken to the adjoining school room where some hundreds of children were gathered together. I expounded to them the pastoral staff, which I had with me, &amp; blessed them. There was a simplicity, and a devotion about the congregation which could not but please me. The churchwardens, two very young men, and the choirmen, all apparently under 20, seemed very ardent &amp; not as impertinent &amp; 'cocksure' as "Anglo–Catholics" commonly are. They have evidently been governed by the clergy with a rod of iron. On the whole I was pleased with what I found at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Francis, but of course the direction is distinctly Romeward. That the Sacrament is reserved was indicated presumably by the lamp suspended before the altar: but I made no inquiries as I did not wish to be confronted by any more problems! To shut one's eyes to illegalities &amp; to appear ignorant of indiscipline are indispensable episcopal habits!</p>
         <p>We motored to the Castle arriving at about 9.45p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Miss Mundella's</hi><persName xml:id="2712"></persName> death is reported. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> says it was mentioned in yesterday's "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>". She was very kind to us, &amp; it is sad to think that we shall no longer be able to come under her hospitable roof. I made her acquaintance when Rector of <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> for she was a regular member of my congregation. Her religion was a curious blending of Tractarianism and Secularism. At bottom she was, like most Italians, thoroughly mundane with a secret dread of the Papacy, of which she felt the attraction.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>