<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Boxing Day, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A bright but very cold morning. At 9.30 a.m. we left the castle, and motored to Sunderland, where I had undertaken to dedicate the War&#8211;Memorial. A procession was formed, not without some confusion, at the Town Hall, &amp; marched to the memorial, an imposing column sustained a winged figure of Victory. A clergymen repeated the Lord's Prayer: a hymn was sung: a Rabbi read a lesson: a Secretary offered a Prayer. The monument was unveiled by Col: Vaux<persName xml:id="4022"></persName>. I dedicated it, &amp; blessed the crowd. Then a minute's silence, &amp; short speeches from the ex&#8211;Mayor in handing over the monument; and the mayor in accepting it. Then "God save the King", and the function concluded.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edgar Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to see me, and stayed to tea. I gave him a copy of the "Scott" speech.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went home for a short holiday after the function at Sunderland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> said Goodbye. He goes off by the early train tomorrow and is pledged to return on Thursday next week. It is a perilous situation to be without a car for so long.</p>
         <p>I read with much interest most of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Hicks's</hi> Life, which has just been published. He was a man of great ability, great courage, and great piety. But he was handicapped by 2 disadvantages which held him back for years – lack of family influence, and a strong twist towards fanaticism.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>