<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked at a sermon for next Sunday all the morning. In the evening I motored to Darlington and had an interview with <hi rend="underline">Cosgrave</hi> with respect to the foolish deacon, <hi rend="underline">Hill</hi>, who, I think, has best chance of 'pulling himself together' if he be transferred to another parish, &amp; subjected to another incumbent. I made <hi rend="underline">Cosgrave</hi> read the relevant correspondence, &amp; asked him if he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> make the experiment of having <hi rend="underline">Hill</hi> on his staff for 6 months 'with permission', and then, if found satisfactory, under license. He said he would do this if, after a personal interview, he found it possible to arrange with <hi rend="underline">Hill</hi>. To this course I agreed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Then I went to a meeting of the Bible Society. The Chairman was a vulgar creature, who said he was some kind of Methodist, &amp; roared at some length, but I found it difficult to understand his speech, for he had a strong brogue. Then I spoke for half&#8211;an&#8211;hour: there was a collection, &amp; a vote of thanks, some more vulgarities from the Chairman, and the Benediction! The audience numbered precisely 72, of whom two&#8211;thirds were female, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">nobody</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> under 60 years old! </hi> <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Sinnamon</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">, the curate from the parish church, was the solitary representative of the local clergy. This reflects the vehement dislike with which they regard any religious association with Nonconformists.</hi> After the meeting, I returned to Auckland. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove furiously, &amp; we were at home by 9.30 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>