<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>My 'visitation' of the Sunderland Deanery began with a celebration of the Holy Communion in the Parish Church. I celebrated, and 35 clergy communicated, including (I was pleased to see) the leading 'Anglo&#8211;Catholics'. We were entertained at breakfast by the Rural Dean in a Restaurant conveniently near the parish church. At 10 a.m. there was Litany, and I addressed the clergy on the subject of the Christian Ministry. Then at 11 a.m. followed the Conference in the Vestry. Out of a possible 52, there were 47: and the absentees were satisfactorily accounted. I introduced the subject of the Marriage Law, and spoke with the utmost plainness. The discussion mostly took the shape of a conversation in which I answered a number of objections, and was able to say a good many useful things. On the whole, I incline to think that this meeting did good. I lunched at the Rectory, and at 2.30 p.m. had an interview with old Canon Hopkinson on the subject of his resignation of Whitburn. We fixed a distant date of July 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1923! At 3.30 p.m. I went to S. Agatha's Rescue Home, &amp; therein dedicated a Prayer Room. At 7.30 p.m. there was a meeting of about 300 parochial Church Councillors, whom I addressed at length on Prayer Book Revision. They seemed to be interested, and asked a good many questions which kept me engaged until about 9.30 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> was waiting with the car at the Rectory. We had a pleasant ride home, and arrived at 11 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>