<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">St Thomas's Day, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Ordination</hi>. The morning was calm after yesterday's storm. A brilliant star shining from a background of velvety purple sky, above an orange&#8211;rimmed sky&#8211;line, arrested my gaze when the curtains were drawn. The extraordinary beauty and simplicity of the <hi rend="underline">magnalia Dei</hi> in Nature are amazing. How untrue is it that "one scattered star seems nothing", as a poet sings. On the contrary, the loneliness is integral to the effect.</p>
         <p>The process of the Ordination began with the taking of the Oaths &amp;c at 10.15 a.m before the service in the chapel, and ended with the taking of the Oath of Canonical Obedience afterwards. The chapel was mortally cold, and this circumstance did undoubtedly affect me: but there was no serious mishap, &amp; everything was very solemn, as it should be. Davison preached well, though, perhaps, too discursively.</p>
         <p>Bishop Lightfoot died on December 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1889, and was finally (after a great funeral in Durham Cathedral.) interred in the Chapel on December 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> reminded me of the fact this morning, giving it as his reason for attending the Ordination.</p>
         <p>Four pheasants arrived from John Noble Esq, Wrelham, Thetford, a gentleman known to me only by name, though I know some members of his family. I sent him by way of return a copy of the Scott speech!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>