<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Darlington, where we lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Havelock&#8211;Allen</hi>, and his wife. He is the grandson of the Indian mutiny hero. After luncheon he showed me over the house, a substantial mansion of the late 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, and considerably enlarged later. I then went to the new Home for Waifs &amp; Strays, and dedicated it with suitable prayers. Pretty <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Barnard</hi> opened the House: and then was an asphyxiating meeting in one of the rooms.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi><persName xml:id="5293"></persName> took me off to his house, &amp; told me the woeful story of the collapse of C.L.B.<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> in his parish. What precautions is it possible to take against moral disasters of this kind? <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I went on to Stockton, where, first, I had an interview with the Vicar and his churchwarden with respect to the disputed legacy for enlarging the parish church, and then <hi rend="bold underline">attended a meeting in the Baptist Chapel convened in support of the Bible Society.</hi> There was a considerable attendance. I spoke for about 40 minutes. <hi rend="bold underline">My speech was, perhaps, rather disconcerting to a number of Plymouth Brethren, who were present, but they made no audible protest!</hi> After the meeting we motored back to the Castle, arriving about 10 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Ely has a letter in the "Times" in reply to mine.</hi> It is not a strong letter, but it will be extremely welcome to the religious public, who were beginning to feel uncomfortable, &amp; will now be re&#8211;assured!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>