<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922. </hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing my Sunday's work. After lunch I motored into Durham, and had an interview with Hill in the Chapter Office. He has the aspect of a whipped hound, and evidently feels that he has made an ass of himself. I suggested that he should be transferred to another parish, and he 'jumped' at the prospect. So I determined to see if Cosgrave can take him.</p>
         <p>Then I instituted Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> to his Durham Canonry. After tea with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, I motored to South Shields, and put up for the night at the Rectory.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">My letter appeared prominently in the 'Times', and reads rather like a wail from a distant past, so decayed has the idea of national Christianity now grown to be. I cannot think that there is any resisting power left in the Church of England strong enough to defeat a direct attack on the Establishment.</hi></p>
         <p>I had much talk with Hudson Barker. He is an odd man in some respects, and I think probably more 'advanced' in his churchmanship than he would like me to know. But he reads, thinks, and works: he is, moreover, in some respects old&#8211;fashioned. Thus he professes a strong belief in the value of parochial visiting, and Bible Classes: of the last he appears to have several very flourishing examples in his parish.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>