<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent. December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, and instituted the Reverend H. T. C. W. Walters to the vicarage of that parish. There was a fair congregation. I preached from 2. Corinthians IV.5, and celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 97 communicants. After the service the new Vicar and his wife lunched at the Castle.</p>
         <p>We all motored to Durham after tea. There <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> stopped off to dine with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, &amp; to attend the Advent Music in the Cathedral. I continued my journey to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, where I preached in the parish church. After service I had supper in the Rectory. The two churchwardens were also there. We picked up the ladies and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> in Durham, &amp; returned to Auckland, arriving about 10.15 p.m.</p>
         <p>Evensong at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring was a pleasing service. There was a considerable, though not a crowded congregation. It was explained to me afterwards that the Wesleyans had arranged a musical performance on that evening, and that this had drawn away some of the people. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> read the service and the lessons, clearly &amp; reverently. Hill acted as my staff&#8211;bearer. An anthem was sung very effectively by a large choir – 20 men and 22 boys. I noted with pleasure that the congregation contained a contingent of young men &amp; young women.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>