<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I am at a loss how best to address the clergy when I have them face to face tomorrow. To be quite frank, quite direct, and quite controversial is almost beyond the wit of man. I want to get in touch with them 'spiritually' and that implies contact at a level above controversy. To treat any Scripture devotionally must mean to treat it on some assumption, however vehemently challenged, which is not brought into debate. The method of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics is to present Christianity as a logical scheme in which the least ceremony is properly linked with the fundamental truth, so that nothing is really optional or indifferent. To the informed "Catholic" nothing is other than essential for to abandon even a ceremony would involve rebellion against authority, the authority of "the Church", an exercise of "private judgment" which is the original sin of Protestantism. Thus the old charitable distinction between Adiaphora and Essentials, which is at least as old as S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Epistle to the Corinthians <hi rend="underline">practically</hi> disappears. "The appeal to history is itself a heresy" said Cardinal Manning, and that is what our "Anglo&#8211;Catholics" now maintain, <hi rend="bold underline">though they do not often confess it</hi> <hi rend="bold">. </hi>There can really be no agreement between them &amp; the English Churchman who, however "High Church" is yet loyally accordant with the Prayer&#8211;Book, and who accepts the authority of the C. of E. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing materials for my visit to the Gateshead Deanery, and then, after lunch, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Gateshead. I had tea with the Rector, and then was taken to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Faith's Rescue Home, where I dedicated a "prayer&#8211;room".</p>
         <p>There was a gathering of more than 200 parochial church councillors in Christ Church Schoolroom at 7.30 p.m. when I addressed them on the subject of Prayer Book Revision. I asked that no reporters should be present, and on that supposition I spoke with much frankness on the subject. My audience was attentive, but undemonstrative. I was assured that representatives from the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" churches were present. If so, they must have found material for thought in what I said. I stayed the night at the Rectory, &amp; had much talk with Stephenson on men &amp; things. He says that Parry and McKitterick ought to be given lighter work: both of them are good men, but physically inadequate to the requirements of their present parishes. I sympathize, and promise to do what I can: but what does that amount to? The Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement does not seem to have made much headway in Gateshead as yet. Chad's is its principal centre. <hi rend="bold underline">The Vicar, Ellwood, is much disturbed by my insistence on a reasonable age for Confirmation</hi> but he had the good sense to refuse to take part in getting up a protest on the subject. I should certainly refuse to make any concessions there.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>