<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I prepared notes for my functions later in the day. Neither function is agreeable to me, for the "ordination of a deaconess" seems to commit me to beliefs and policies which I do not accept, and the dedication of a War memorial compels me to labour an exhausted theme.</p>
         <p>We motored to Durham, and I went at once to the cathedral, and "ordained" the deaconess. We lunched with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>. I heard with much relief and satisfaction that the fatuous proposal to lease the Pebendal House to the Ladies College had been defeated in chapter. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> and Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName> voted for it: the Sub&#8211;dean, the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> voted against. Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> abstained from voting. This ought to put an end to that folly. After lunch we motored to South Shields, dropping <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> on the way at Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, and, picking her up there on the return journey. I dedicated a chancel screen as a War memorial in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Simon's church, and preached. The congregation was small &amp; listless: and the atmosphere was foul and stifling. After the service, we went into the Vicarage, and had tea with some of the parishioners. The parson – a lugubrious man called Laverick – drew me aside in order to renew the appeal for a change, which he made to me some while since! He has no degree; and was ordained in 1895 by the Bishop of Manchester. He has been 14 years in his present living.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>