<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Lord, raise up (we pray thee) thy power, and come among us, and with thy great might succour us; that whereas, through our sins and wickedness, we are sore let and hindered in running the race that is set before us, the bountiful grace and mercy may speedily help and deliver us, through the satisfaction of thy Son our Lord, to whom with thee and the Holy Ghost be honour and glory, world without end. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. Five of the Household, including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, communicated. After breakfast I finished the Christmas sermon. <hi rend="bold underline">A post arrived about noon bringing several acknowledgments of the Scott lecture. Several of these were complimentary, &amp; this circumstance pleased me the more since it at least showed that the writers had read my speech!</hi> After lunch we all motored to Durham, and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName> was awaiting me in the Cloister after the service. We had tea pleasantly with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, and then returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The normal course of life in Bishop Auckland was disturbed by a lurid occurrence. An Italian stabbed a man and cut his throat last night! This tragical incident caused much excitement.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>