<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spend the morning in preparing the sermon for the Westminster secretaries. It was a revised edition of the address I gave at Gateshead last Passiontide on Christian Citizenship. As the weather was fine I played bowls again with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. The boy is becoming indispensible. I should be lost without him. After tea I wrote a sheaf of letters until dinner time.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Strong sent me the Address on 'Reservation' which he addressed to his diocesan 'Synod'. It is excellent in form &amp; substance. I shall certainly have to revise my opinion about him, for no "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" could get much comfort out of this pronouncement.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'Bishop Barrington, who loved to encourage literary men to take holy Orders, in vain held out to him (i.e. Rob<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Surtees), as an inducement to take that step, the <hi rend="underline">otium cum dignitate</hi> of a stall in Durham Cathedral.'</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a note by Sir Cuthbert harp v. Life of Surtees p. 224.</p>
         <p>May we connect this proposal of Bishop Barrington to Surtees with Scott's declaration that he had once dreamed of a canonry:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Yet gazing on the venerable hall,</p>
         <p>Her flattering dreams would in perspective ope</p>
         <p>Some reverend room, some prebendary's stall,</p>
         <p>And thus Hope me deceived a she deceiveth all.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>