<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote a brief answer to the Bishop of Ely's letter</hi>. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> came with me into Durham. There I confirmed 55 boys in the Cathedral, and gave an address from the words of Christ to S. Peter. "<hi rend="underline">Verily, verily, I say unto thee, When thou wast young, thou girdedst thyself, and walkedst whither thou wouldest: butt when thou shalt become old: thou shalt stretch forth thine hands, and another shall gird thee, &amp; carry thee whither thou wouldest not.</hi>" I always enjoy this school Confirmation; &amp; this time particularly I did so, for the boys were attentive, the arrangements were well&#8211;made, and there was a numerous attendance of the parents.</p>
         <p>From the Cathedral I went to the Castle, &amp; instituted Boddy to Pittington, &amp; Asher to Wilton [sic] Gilbert. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas</hi> from Stockton joined Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> &amp; me, &amp; discussed his matter. I undertook to have a personal interview with the executor. Then Clayton and I lunched with Wilson. After this I attended a conference of the Diocesan Messengers: and then had an interview in my room at the Castle with Hepple, an Ordination candidate.</p>
         <p>Clayton and I dined at the Castle. A Gaudy was proceeding, &amp; there were speeches which prolonged the meal until 10 p.m. Gee was the principal guest. I was more than ever impressed by the petty scale of the University. The present fashion of "Durham men for Durham posts" stereotypes this pettiness.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>