<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter on 'Divorce' appears prominently in the 'Times' and will no doubt provide the text for more abuse in the "Church Times"</hi> <hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I called on Downing at the Ecclesiastical Commission, and communicated my anxieties about the subsidences in the Bowling Green. He promised to call Wood's attention to it.</p>
         <p>Then I called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, &amp; discussed ecclesiastical politics with him. He is an attractive and sensible man.</p>
         <p>I lunched in Park Lane, &amp; then went with Lord Scarbrough to the House of Lords <hi rend="bold underline">and was "sworn in"</hi>. Then I picked up my bags at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, went to King's Cross, &amp; returned to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car at Darlington.</p>
         <p>I went into Rees's shop, and bought the following books:</p>
         <p>1. The Epistle to the Hebrews by E. F. Scott.</p>
         <p>2. The Church in America by William Adams Brown.</p>
         <p>3. The Belief in Immortality by I. G. Frazer, vol. II.</p>
         <p>4. The Population Problem by A. M. Carr&#8211;Saunders.</p>
         <p>5. Progress in Religion by T. R. Glover<persName xml:id="3000"></persName>.</p>
         <p>6. Liberalism, Modernism and Tradition by O. C. Zuick.</p>
         <p>7. The Revolt against Civilization by Lothrop Stoddard.</p>
         <p>These will provide provender for the rest of this year, and perhaps indigestion afterwards!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>