<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1822.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for the Cathedral. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and walked in the Park with the dogs. The recent rains have swollen the Gaunless &amp; its ancillary streams into respectable torrents.</p>
         <p>The Patronage Secretary in Downing Street writes to say that S. Francis is still vacant, the latest nominee having withdrawn his acceptance. I cannot regret this, as I judge the man to be unsuitable. I wrote to the Secretary suggesting that the living sh<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> be offered to Wright: and asking whether the other fellow might do for Boddy's successor. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Wilkinson writes to say that he wishes to "back out" of the exchange which he had agreed to make with Cobb. A friend had pointed out to him that he had no right to take his three motherless children to such a parish'! I sent him a curt reply , telling him that in my judgement the plea was inadequate. Cobb sends me a brief correspondence which has passed between himself and Wilkinson, from which it is evident that the latter has behaved very badly. Here, then, is a significant example of the disadvantage inherent in the marriage of the clergy. A whole set of powerful but irrelevant interests is brought into existence, and these may, and often do, come into direct and obvious conflict with the parson's only legitimate concern – his spiritual ministry. In that conflict it is plain enough where the victory will commonly, all but invariably, lie. The Church of England is dominated by the claims &amp; needs of the parson's home!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>