<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of S</hi> <hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">David's, whom I have judged to be a sane &amp; tolerant person, tells me that he refused to ordain a man to the priesthood because he had married an innocent divorc&#x00E9;e.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> "There was nothing against him here except his marriage … He gave me the usual references, and as the replies were satisfactory &amp; the impression left on me by him was favourable I ordained him deacon. Afterwards a friend hinted the desirability of further enquiry before he was ordained priest but gave no details. I sent for J&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;s, &amp; asked him to be frank with me. He then told me that his wife was an 'innocent divorc&#x00E9;e'. </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop appears to ground his action on the opinion that marriage with an innocent divorc&#x00E9;e 'would prejudice his usefulness as a clergyman' </hi> <hi rend="italic">But is this a fact which a Bishop ought to acquiesce in, &amp; allow to determine his action?</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Durham where I took train for Edinburgh. Leaving at 11.48a.m. I arrived at 3.38p.m, &amp; drove at once to 41 Drumsheugh gardens where Eunice &amp; Kathleen welcomed me. My companion on this journey was M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Ropner the Ship builder from Hartlepool, who was on his way to Edinburgh to take part in some discussion between 'Capital and Labour'. He said there has been a slight movement of recovery in the ship&#8211;building industry, and he was not without hope of a general revival: but the way would be a long one before any genuine recovery of our trade could be effected. Gordon &amp; his wife came to tea, and also Clayton's<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> sister. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I went to the North British Hotel, and presided over a meeting of the club. When <hi rend="doubleunderline">the</hi> normal business was transacted and on my proposition, <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Buchan</hi> was elected President for 1923. Then I took the chair at the annual dinner. There was a numerous company, about 200 it is said. They were all men save for about half a dozen ladies. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Richard Lodge</hi> sat beside me, &amp; was very pleasant. I spoke for exactly 45 minutes, and was closely listened to. On the whole I incline to think that the speech was successful. If I believed the flatterous things that were said about it, there can be no doubt on the subject. <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi> <hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fisher</hi> in proposing my health was, of course, abjectly adulatory, but then he doesn't count in these matters. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lodge</hi> thanked me, &amp; he does count. </p>
         <p>The dinner &amp; the speeches to say nothing of the tobacco&#8211;smoke disturbed me so that I had a sleepless night. In the course thereof I read a small book which happened to be in the room – '<hi rend="underline">Letters and Recollections of Sir Walter Scott by W</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">m </hi> <hi rend="underline">Hughes (of Uffington) edited by Horace G Hutchinson. Th</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">os</hi> <hi rend="underline"> Nelson &amp; Son</hi> – Here I found some very interesting references to Durham and to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Van Mildert</hi> told Scott that the Mayor of Durham, who had come out to the Castle on a deputation to the Bishop, mistook one of the patriarchs in the large dining room for Robinson Crusoe. This clearly is the origin of Bishop Maltby<persName xml:id="5302"></persName> and the curate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>