<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Archbishop left after breakfast. I motored him to Darlington, &amp; continued the conversation of last night. He is certainly disposed to associate himself with the more liberal elements in the church: but he has rather a difficult past to get over before he can do so effectively.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Gainford</hi><persName xml:id="2216"></persName> and his daughter <hi rend="doubleunderline">Faith</hi> came to lunch. We had some talk together. He expressed agreement with my letters in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" on the Divorce question, and admired my "courage" in saying openly what most clergymen thought it prudent to conceal. I suppose it is the fact that prudence would suggest silence, since the main currents within the Church of England are setting so strongly in the homeward direction: but I prefer my liberty even at the price of abuse and calumny. The "<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>" contains a fresh instalment of these in its latest issue where it prints a very offensive paragraph, which will provide more provender for clerical disaffection within the diocese, and give much pleasure to my ill&#8211;wishers, but I shall ignore it, because not only is it utterly hateful to me to embark on personal controversy, but also because I think my persistent refusal to treat that paper as deserving my notice is probably the most damaging retort I can provide. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang </hi>agreed with me that the influence of the "<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>" on the clergy is very considerable &amp; very mischievous. Many of them read nothing else: few of them are capable of criticizing its statements.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>