<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in clearing off a number of letters. Heawood, the Professor's son, came to lunch, and afterwards talked to me, and with me, about the Student Christian Movement, in which he holds office as a secretary of the London branch. I find it extraordinarily difficult not to think that the Movement is a spiritual mare's nest! But so many enthusiastic people are enthusiastic about it that I shrink from accepting that verdict.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham to see J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> about my insurances: and happening to call in at the late Mayor's shop to enquire how that excellent man had fared after his operation. I found him <hi rend="underline">in viv&#x00E2; persona</hi>. He escorted me into his sanctum, &amp; after explaining his desire to make a small private thankoffering for his recovery, he wrote me a cheque for &#x00A3;30 for the poor clergy at my discretion. Then I looked in on the philosophic draper, Gray, who, I found, was much shaken &amp; depressed by the death of his brother, killed by a motor&#8211;car in the streets of London this summer. I had never heard of it. Finally, I visited Caldcleugh, who was in a conversational mood.</p>
         <p>Wilson gave me a copy of "King Edward's School Chronicle" which contains an obituary notice of Bishop Lightfoot. The issue is dated March 1890.</p>
         <p>I sent the following cheques:&#8211; Shaddick &#x00A3;25: Butler &#x00A3;20: Firth &#x00A3;15: Rainbow &#x00A3;15:. They may possibly inject a little cheerfulness into their Christmas ministrations!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>