<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I returned to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, arriving about 2.30 p.m. just as Sir Arthur Wood, accompanied by his brother and J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, were beginning their inspection of the apparent subsidences in the bowling green. He agreed that some movement was certainly taking place, but was in some perplexity both as to its origin and as to its gravity. Afterwards they all had tea here.</p>
         <p>I wrote to the Bishop of Newcastle suggesting that the parish of Hunstanworth in my diocese, and the parish of Blanchland in his diocese should be united. The combined incomes would hardly reach &#x00A3;350: and the combined populations would be less than 450 souls.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The "Times" gives great prominence to the reports of a remarkable 'find' in Egypt, which is said to be very illuminating &amp; valuable</hi>. There is always the chance of some really revolutionizing discovery taking place. But can anything really important to the spiritual duties and destinies of man turn on the chances of the antiquarian's skill and industry and 'luck'? Can any truth certified to be such by the arguments of antiquarians possess any title to a considering man's acceptance? <hi rend="underline">"We walk by faith, not by sight"</hi>, but surely not faith in Flinders [Petrie]! Perhaps the most formidable objection to an historical revelation is precisely the circumstance that it is historical!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>