<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Before going off to breakfast, Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> inspected the wall containing the bowling &amp; obviously took a grave view of its condition. There is an evident land slide in process, &amp; it is carrying down into the 'Gaunless' both the road and my wall! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> motored to Shincliffe for lunch: &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> bicycled into Durham in the afternoon. I took Cuttie for an hour's walk in the Park. Hardly had I returned before I received a call from D<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi> Walter J. K. Braunholy who is engaged as a chemist in the service of Pease Partners. He is the son of a Cambridge Professor of Modern Languages, &amp; has two brothers, one at the British Museum, &amp; one teaching at Wellington. He told me that he was 27 years old, &amp; is a fine good&#8211;looking young man. I asked him whether his German name had been a cause of trouble to him during the war: &amp; he replied in the affirmative. He and his brothers had served in the ranks, but were not suffered to receive commissions. Many acquaintances had broken away from them, and they themselves were now unwilling to resume acquaintance with those who had disclosed their quality.</p>
         <p>Eight more volumes of the Loeb Classical Library arrived, including some more Herodotus, and a volume of [^written in Greek^]. Also [^written in Greek^]. If but there were time to read! But we have the books when we have lost the time.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>