<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a sermon for the Rescue &amp; Preventative Association which meets next week in the Cathedral, and I wrote letters. After lunch I played bows with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and for a wonder had something the better of him. He gave his first vote as a citizen this morning, and the new responsibility may have affected his game!</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">"He had thus gathered a respectable chass of accidental knowledge"</hi> This is Henry Cockburn's description of the result of L. Hermand's unmethodical reading. <hi rend="bold underline">I fear nothing more could be said with justice about the present Bishop of Durham. Systematic reading on any fixed principle is almost impossible in such a "hand to mouth" life as that which a modern bishop is compelled to live.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"On looking back at those times, it is impossible not to be struck with the apparent absence of enlightened public views &amp; capacities all over the community. I do not recollect a single Scotch work of any permanent, or almost of any respectable temporary value, which even the excitement of that age produced".</p>
         </div>
         <p>This opinion of Henry Cockburn must be balanced by the fact that a cultivated but self&#8211;centred society existed &amp; was producing not merely antiquarian monographs but a great literature. Political life has for the time being been quite paralyzed by the Revolution &amp; its wars.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>