<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Visitation (informal) of the Rural Deanery of South Shields</hi>:</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hilda's at 8 a.m. There were 16 clergy who communicated. After breakfasting together in the Rectory, we returned to the church at 10.15 a.m. where, after the Litany had been read, I addressed the clergy. The number present was 19 or 20. Then followed the conference in the 'Song Room'. I introduced the subject of "Marriage &amp; Divorce", and then the clergy in order spoke &amp; asked questions. It interested me to notice that four clergy took up an attitude of bigoted and almost insolent opposition. They were the following:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Leake</hi>, the Vicar of Boldon, an advanced Anglo&#8211;Catholic, whose curate, Jubb, recently seceded to Rome.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Jackson</hi>, the Vicar of S. Jude, S. Shields, whose only degree is the pitiable 'L.Th.' of Durham. He was ordained in 1902, and served as a private during the War.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Richardson</hi>, a Curate of the Parish Church, a Mirfield man, whom I myself ordained to the priesthood in 1921.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Wright</hi>, Curate of S. Francis, S. Shields, whom I ordained to the Diaconate last year, &amp; who is not yet in priest's Orders.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The older men </hi> <hi rend="bold">were by no means so fanatical. Several of them expressed gratitude to me,</hi> &amp; admitted that they had never really faced the questions at issue. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 3 p.m. I addressed about 150 parish councillors on the subject of Prayer&#8211;Book Revision.</hi> They were very attentive, and, I think, interested, but they refrained from asking questions. They gave me the impression of having been 'worked upon' by the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholic' movement which has been 'running strongly' in Newcastle. No doubt my letters in the '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>' – subtly twisted by the 'Church Times' – have been much used. After tea at the Rectory, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I returned to Auckland. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The papers announce that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName><hi rend="italic"> has been appointed to the Bishoprick of Gloucester. This, I think, is satisfactory. He is a hard man, and fundamentally a 'High' churchman, but he is learned, courageous, and independent. He can hardly give a whole&#8211;hearted support to the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics", who regard his '</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">Bampton Lectures</hi> <hi rend="italic">' as a very dangerous book! He has cultivated friendly relations with Non&#8211;conformists, though he has never, so far as I know, given any encouragement to any religious association with them. He has strong personal antipathies, but is capable of personal loyalty. His 'feuds' with </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dibdin</hi><persName xml:id="909"></persName><hi rend="italic">, </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="italic">, and </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName><hi rend="italic"> are well&#8211;known. But as he has grown older, he has certainly mellowed: &amp; he is so masterful &amp; energetic a personality, that I anticipate for him a very distinguished career on the Bench. His orthodoxy is unimpeachable, but he is no bigot. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>