<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>This morning I received a disconcerting letter from Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> curate, Hill, postponing 'indefinitely' his ordination to the priesthood on the ground that he could not again 'at least at present' make the legal declarations of assent &amp; belief. "I have ceased to look upon the Resurrection as an event, &amp; regard it as a process. Thus, though I can still subscribe to the Creed, even to the words 'resurrectio carnis' I cannot endorse the interpretation the church puts on it in her "formulas". After lunch I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring and discussed the matter with Knight. He expressed surprise at the averment of doctrinal difficulties, for of these Hill had made no mention while declaring his desire for a more 'Catholic' regime. But Hill's behaviour had been in so many respects unsatisfactory that Knight doubted whether he was really fitted for the Ministry. He was frivolous, idle, and insubordinate. This makes the incident still more perplexing. I asked K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> to get in touch with Hill's family, and find out whether there was any reason for suspecting mental instability.</p>
         <p>Lady Palmer &amp; her daughter lunched here. She had come to Auckland to open a parochial sale of work.</p>
         <p>The weather became suddenly warm, but as the temperature rose, the wind rose also. In the afternoon and evening there was something like a hurricane.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>