<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>At 8.15 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's Church. Stephenson and Blackwall assisted, and about 20 clergy of the Deanery communicated. We all breakfasted at the Rectory, and then went again to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's where we read the Litany, sang 3 hymns, and I addressed the clergy on "Our Ministry". We returned to the Rectory, and I held a conference with the clergy on "Marriage and Divorce". This went on for two hours, &amp; was frank, good&#8211;tempered, and informing. After lunch I interviewed an Ordination candidate, Davis, who hopes to be ordained next Trinity, &amp; then William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me back to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>. <hi rend="bold underline">Thus I accomplished the first of my informal visitations to the Rural Deaneries. I hope it will do good</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Guardian'</hi> has a leader on my letter in the Times about Divorce, and, rather to my surprise, gives a cautious approval to my proposal that a Conference of Christian Leaders should be brought together in order to consider how the principles of Christianity ought to find expression in the marriage law. The "<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>", however, has an abusive paragraph, attacking me as demonstrably heretical, and it reports some vehement language against me employed by that very foolish person, the Bishop of Woolwich. He was consecrated with me on February 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1918, and no doubt shudders at the thought of his involuntary association with the Heretick!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>