<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Barrington Trustees. Then I went to the book shop &amp; ordered some books for giving as Christmas presents. I returned to Auckland in time for lunch. In the afternoon I motored to Norton, and had an interview with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> William Kirk, with respect to the legacy of &#x00A3;3000 to the parish church of Stockton made by his late brother. Canon Scott came in to see me, &amp; we talked privately together in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kirk's study. The old man is now fourscore, and desired to know my opinion as to the duty of resignation. I told him that, if he felt himself unequal to his work, he ought to resign. He seemed rather disturbed at my decisiveness, but I could say nothing else. I returned to Auckland, sitting with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> on the box, rather rashly for the wind was keen.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" publishes an unpleasant correspondence between the late Prime Minister and the American syndicate which had agreed to purchase for &#x00A3;40,000 the copyright of his Book on the War. That agreement has now been cancelled, since the Syndicate refused to adhere to it in view of the fact that M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Lloyd George had covenanted with some American newspapers to contribute a series of articles, which, it was naturally assumed, would prejudice the sale of the promised Book. The whole incident is very humiliating and disconcerting. The Marconi scandal at one end of a ministerial career, and a squalid conflict with American publishers at the other, gives an evil impression.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>