<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I motored to Sunderland, and there instituted Romans to the vicarage of St Mark's Millfield. The church is rather depressing, and, though the parish is said to contain 10.000 souls, the congregation did not exceed, if it reached 250. However, there were no less than 115 communicants. Perrott, the curate, (whom the Parochial Church Council asked to have appointed vicar, &amp; were snubbed for their pains) read the service. I preached and celebrated the Holy Communion. On the whole, I was pleased with the service. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> returned to Durham in the car, and I stayed at the Rectory. During the afternoon Raine the late Mayor, who headed the poll at the General Election, came to see me. He has taken his seat, and is beginning to realize that the House of Commons, seen from within is perhaps hardly equal to its promise as seen from without. I remained in the house instead of attending Evensong, and made preparation for my speech tomorrow. McCullagh, the Vicar of Christ Church, and his wife came to supper. We discussed the recent Anglo&#8211;Catholic Conference in Newcastle, and agreed that the Bishop's action in becoming President was very regrettable. Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> showed me a copy of the recent Conference which includes an illuminating account of the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholic Movement'. None the less (but, perhaps, we had not read it) the Bishop has written a commendatory Preface.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>