<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[24]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">O Lord, we beseech thee, absolve thy people from their offences, that through thy bountiful goodness we may all be delivered from the bands of those sins, which by our frailty we have committed. Grant this, O heavenly Father, for Jesus Christ's sake, our blessed Lord and Saviour. Amen</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">'a peccatorum nostrorum nexibus quae pro nostra fragilitate contraximus'. Leonine</hi></p>
         <p>A very fit prayer for a Birthday. I was glad to see William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> among the communicants in the Chapel when I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. He is 22 years old today, a wonderful age when the powers of one's manhood are in hand, and its possibilities are still undisclosed. I gave him a tobacco pouch in order to wean him from cigarettes to the humble and wholesome pipe, and a copy of the sermon on "Christian citizenship" in order to remind him that he is now a full&#8211;fledged citizen. How far do the counsels of the old really influence the mind, or shape the character of a young man!</p>
         <p>I worked at the Scott lecture instead of going to church. Bishop King, who had been preaching in the parish, came to lunch. He was a student here under Bishop Lightfoot. I wrote to Ernest.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>