<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A letter from Buff<persName xml:id="836"></persName> told me that his father had died at a hotel in Beaulieu. Willie Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName> first came into my orbit in 1887, when I was appointed Head of the Oxford House. He was one of the young Oxonians who, from time to time, visited that outpost of culture in the barbarous district of East London. He conceived a strange admiration and affection for me, which developed into a steady friendship was has lasted until his death. He was a pure and upright man, deeply religious in a way of his own, and extraordinarily sensitive in conscience. We received him here with his wife, and spent a pleasant week at his house last August. It is difficult to realise that I shall never see him again. I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray<persName xml:id="666"></persName>, Buff, and Vivian.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to West Hartlepool. Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName> took me to a poor paralysed woman, whom I confirmed privately as she could not come to church. Then I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's and confirmed 166 candidates of whom at least two thirds wore petticoats. There was much coughing which annoyed, and a collection which displeased, me. I told the Vicar that the latter must not be repeated in future confirmations. He was, I think, genuinely surprized that I should object to so obvious an effort to "raise the wind"! We returned to Auckland after service, arriving about 9.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>