<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Conversion of S. Paul, Thursday, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I walked to the Abbey for the Consecration. There was an unusual, and indeed unprecedented, assemblage of Bishops. I read the Gospel, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">S</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"> Clair Donaldson</hi> the Epistle. Also I administered the Paten to the congregation. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> carried himself well. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nairne</hi> preached an excellent discourse. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Masterman</hi>, the new suffragan of Plymouth, was also consecrated. I could not but contrast the scene with that which was presented 5 years ago, when I was myself consecrated. Then all was suspicion, uncertainty and apprehension, and all these fell tempers centred in, and on, the central figure – myself!</p>
         <p>I lunched in the Deanery very pleasantly: and then proceeded to Lambeth for <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">the Bishops' meeting</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Archbishop told us that he had seen a copy of the Roman Catholick journal '</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">L'Information</hi> <hi rend="italic">', which contained an article exulting in the Turkish victory, and expressing the utmost hostility to the Greek church. It would prefer to see the Crescent above S</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Sophia than the Greek Cross. This precious journal is supposed to be "inspired" by the Vatican. </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Curzon</hi><persName xml:id="1018"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had told him that the Vatican was dead against us at Constantinople. His Grace read out a correspondence between himself and Lord Halifax, between Lord H. and Cardinal </hi> <hi rend="bold">[100]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="italic">Mercier, and finally between Cardinal Mercier and himself. It appears that the negociations for Reunion, begun by </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Halifax</hi> <hi rend="italic"> on his own initiative, are to be continued with the cognizance and approval both of the Vatican and the Archbishop. The representatives of the Church of England are to be Lord Halifax, "Father" Frere, and Dean Armitage Robinson<persName xml:id="44"></persName>. </hi> <hi rend="italic underline">I objected that these gentlemen were not properly competent to speak for Anglicanism, since the first had declared himself in agreement with the Roman Church; the second was one of the new "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks": and the third was a very advanced type of Anglican</hi> <hi rend="italic">. There was a discussion which led to nothing, but I think that a good many of the Bishops felt rather uncomfortable. The Archbishop nominated a Commission of Four Bishops to examine into the theological and ecclesiastical aspects of the Divorce Question viz: Ripon (chairman), Durham, Carlisle, and Gloucester. His Grace stated that these Bishops had consented to act, but, so far as I am concerned, this was in excess of the truth, for I had only undertaken to talk the matter over with him, and, if I was satisfied as to the range and personnel of the Commission, to accept nomination thereto. I had a splitting headache all the afternoon.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>