<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The snow is melting but there is much to melt, and the process implies an infinitude of slush.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Wallis called again with reference to the deplorable Gibson. He had received an immense communication from Haslewood, and brought it for me to see. I told him that he must write at once to the Bishop of L., and send either the communication itself, or the substance of it. I wrote to the Bishop myself. This incident is very disquieting, for the fellow was to be ordained next Sunday. How he managed about his papers is baffling. Did he actually fabricate them?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Morris, Vicar of S. Oswald's, writes to ask permission to get rid of his curate Jones, on the ground that he refuses obedience to his directions</hi>: He enclosed a preposterous correspondence which had passed between them. I must needs suspect that there is more behind Jones's behaviour than has yet appeared. I summoned him to meet me in Durham on Thursday.</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington. On the platform I fell in with Ferens, the benevolent plutocrat of Hull. We travelled together as far as York. At Bishopthorpe I found most of the bishops. After dinner I had some talk with the Archbishop about the procedure to be followed when the House of Bishops meets on April 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> to consider Revision of the Prayer Book on the stage of General Revision.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>