<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"A distinguished Frenchman was asked to give his impression of our American universities. 'You Americans,' he said, 'respect scholarship: but you do not respect the conditions of scholarship.' We like the results of thought, but we are too busy doing things to pay the price of thought."</p>
         <p>"The Church in America", p. 332.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored into Durham, &amp; instituted Wreford Brown to the Vicarage of S. Hylton. Then I lunched pleasantly with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in the Club. Then I motored to Hartlepool, &amp; attended a Conference at the Labour Exchange, presided over by Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>. We discussed the proposal to arrange classes for unemployed lads &amp; girls under 18. <hi rend="bold underline">Later I attended the Meeting of Parish Church Councillors in the Town Hall. There was a large attendance, others besides the Councillors being invited. I addressed the assembly on the subject of 'Prayer&#8211;Book Revision', and afterwards answered a few questions. The attention seemed to be close, &amp; the interest sustained, but the subject was too remote from the general levels of my hearers' ordinary ways of thinking &amp; speaking. Probably they were more puzzled than edified.</hi> However, Macdonald expressed himself well&#8211;satisfied with the meeting, and certainly the whole business of Prayer Book Revision has been brought within the range of these people's perception.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>