<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Rain fell during the night and swept away all traces of the snow. The temperature rose, and the birds, cheated by the softness of the air, began to sing lustily. Precipitate optimists!</p>
         <p>I wasted my whole morning on the Edinburgh Article. Then Wallis, the Principal of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's, came to see me about the man Gibson whom I refused to ordain. It appears that he has satisfied the <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Antigua</hi>, and will shortly be ordained by the <hi rend="underline">Bishop of London</hi> in that bishop's behalf. There has been no reference to me which is unusual. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wallis</hi> stayed to lunch. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Boutflower also lunched.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi><persName xml:id="5274"></persName>, the Vicar of Escombe, came to see me. He breathed vengeance against the author of the anonymous letter sent to me, and sent on to him by me. He had identified the man, &amp; would do tremendous things! I told him to burn the note, &amp; forget the incident. The dogged persistence with which the common people of Northern England pursue their personal feuds is only equalled by the meanness of their methods of exhibiting hostility. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi> is a miner's son, and he feels and acts with his class. His education at Cambridge, whither some kind patron sent him, has neither refined his manners nor disciplined his character. He looks, feels, speaks, and acts after the manner of his class.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>