<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[163]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Our task is to do what in us lies to make the Church the very truest and fullest exponent of humanity.'</p>
         <p>v. Hort's Life &amp; Letters i. 112.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This was written to a friend when he was 21 years old. Did Hort every write anything more sound or more mature?</p>
         <p>I worked at the Penrith sermon. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Hart, where I confirmed 24 candidates in the little old dilapidated church. This is really a very interesting building: the chancel arch is Norman, but it is inserted into a "Saxon" wall, and the smaller arch which it replaced yet thrusts a surviving fragment above its rival. The 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century font, elaborately carved, is unusually fine. We went on to Hartlepool, and had tea with Canon Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>. About 50 of his unemployed men gathered to "welcome" me. Two of them were confirmed later in S. Oswald's, whither I proceeded in time for the service at 7 p.m. In spite of the wet and stormy weather, there was a large congregation. I confirmed 170 persons, of whom 7 were deaf mutes from an adjoining Insitution. Egerton, the curate of S. Oswald's, has engaged himself to marry a prosperous middle&#8211;aged female of the district! Chute meditates looking out for another curate to take his place. I told him to get me a Wykhemist like himself. We returned to the Castle after service, arriving about 9.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
