<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant unto me this day, O Christ, the help of Thy holy Spirit, that I may speak words of truth and wisdom to Thy Servants. Pour in their hearts, and into mine, the grace of Thine own charity, that we may be drawn closer together in brotherly love, and a zeal for Thy Cause in the World. Open our eyes that we may see the wondrous things of Thy Law, and, as at the first to Thine Apostles, make Thyself known to us in the Breaking of the Bread. Grant, O Saviour, that we, who bear the Yoke of Thy Ministry, may so carry ourselves in this strange &amp; puzzling world, that men may take knowledge of us that we have been with Thee. Fulfil to us this day Thine own Promise that where two or three are gathered together in Thy Name, there Thou wilt be in the midst of them, and make us glad with Thy Presence. In Thy Light may we see light, O Light of the World, Who livest with the Father and the Holy Spirit, ever one God, world without end.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's Church at 8 a.m. Nine of the clergy attended and communicated. I had breakfast with the Rural Dean. Nineteen clergy came to the service at 10 a.m. when the Rural Dean read the Litany, and I gave an address. At 11.30 a.m. twenty&#8211;one clergy came to the 'conference' on Marriage and Divorce. I spoke for 45 minutes, and then they all spoke in order. On the whole I was pleased. There was a complete absence of fanaticism, and a very reasonable spirit. I think everybody felt that the time had not been wasted. I lunched with the Rural Dean. The two young men, Herbert &amp; Collier, were there.</p>
         <p>At 7.30 p.m. I addressed a considerable meeting of the Parochial Church Councillors from the Rural Deanery on Prayer Book Re vision. Hayward and Bothamly asked questions, and added an element of excitement to the proceedings. I hope some good was done. Watson, the Rural Dean, expressed himself as well satisfied. Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName> walked back with me to the Castle, where I found William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> with the car. I was back in Auckland by 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>The general feeling of the Meeting, so far as I could discover it from the applause with which some of my observations were received, &amp; from the silence which followed others, was distinctly hostile to the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, while very reluctant to accept the necessity of excluding them from the C. of E.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>








