<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a sermon for use next Sunday, when I have to institute Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName>, to the Rectory of Sedgefield. After lunch we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; I) motored into Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the Board of Training and Maintenance. Then we had tea with the Meade Falkners<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, with whom were Sir Lawrence &amp; Lady Jones &amp; Miss Noble. After this we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The curious thing about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ambassador Page</hi> was the combination of large &amp; even generous views of European politics &amp; an extraordinarily keen sense of humour with <hi rend="bold underline">an almost childish confidence in the intrinsic superiority of all things American.</hi> His letters are full of blatancy and brag along with so much wisdom, kindness of heart, and evident candour that they do neither wound nor disgust the English reader. He would, perhaps, have been even more distressed by the behaviour of America since the War than he was during the years before America entered the War. He was really, in his conception of 'liberty' and 'progress', what his countrymen call "a back&#8211;number": and his judgments on English people &amp; institutions have something more than an echo of the '<hi rend="underline">Martin Chuzzlewit</hi>' type of Yankee, although he disguises the fact by so much generous admiration for individuals, &amp; such evident liking for the nation that one cannot be as offended as on ought to be.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>