<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The Convocation began with a choral celebration of the Holy Communion in the Minster at 10 a.m. All the Bishops (except the Bishop of Chester) communicated, <hi rend="bold underline">though none were fasting</hi>. This might, perhaps, go to show that Anglo&#8211;Catholic convictions are not strong on the Bench! We voted the Address to the King after making some small amendments. Then we talked about patronage on the motion of the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>. There being nothing more on the agenda, I returned to Auckland, being met by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> at Darlington, and motored to the Castle through a snow&#8211;covered country.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Liverpool gave me a type&#8211;written copy of a memorandum drawn up (if I understood him correctly by </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Inskip</hi><persName xml:id="4783"></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Solicitor General), and indicating the attitude taken up by Evangelicals towards Prayer&#8211;Book Revision. It </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">distinguishes between</hi> <hi rend="italic"> the proposals which modernize and make additions to some of the services, and the changes </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">suggested in the Communion Service</hi> <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"We therefore invite all, </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">who are satisfied with the doctrinal</hi> <hi rend="italic"> basis of </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">the exisiting Office, and who think that the Service</hi> <hi rend="italic"> is such as the whole Church </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">may fitly use, to resist any</hi> <hi rend="italic"> alteration lest we fall into error, and into a greater accentuation of our differences."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The immediate danger, however, is a perpetuation of the existing situation in which the Anglo&#8211;Catholics are winning 'hands down'.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>