<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Owing to the deceptiveness of words, credulity is popularly imputed to those only who land themselves on the Christian side; though the same impatient indolence of investigation, the same willingness to choose and espouse or neglect evidence in obedience to proclivities of outward association, may lead equally in different temperaments &amp; circumstances to any one of the three positions. <hi rend="underline">But it is from the credulity of Christians that the Christian faith suffers most in days of debate</hi>: &amp; it is well when any who might have helpfully maintained its cause among their neighbours, had they not been disabled by too facile acquiescence, are impelled to plunge into the deep anew. There is not indeed &amp; cannot be any security that they will emerge on the Christian side: in human minds truth does not always gain the present victory, even when it is faithfully pursued…Hort.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Accompanied by the Archdeacon and Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> I motored to Hunstanworth, in new American (open) car, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> sitting beside the chauffeur in going, and acting himself as chauffeur in returning. I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nairne Clark to the Vicarage, &amp; the Archdeacon instituted him M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Edward Joicey, the patron, &amp; his wife met me at tea in the Vicarage. On returning to the Castle, I announced my decision to purchase the car for £375.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>