<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went with me in the motor to Darlington. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> traversed the distance from the Castle to the Station in 35 minutes, a fact which hardly suggests that the sweet youth heeds the statutory speed limit. I journeyed without incident to King's Cross: &amp; then made it my first concern to have my hair shorn. <hi rend="bold underline">In the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I encountered Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName>, who is full of his last abominable crusade in favour of limiting population! I am largely in agreement with him, though I doubt the wisdom of pushing an open door with such ardour. The separation of sexual intercourse from any other purpose than that of carnal enjoyment is a matter that hardly requires the concerted efforts of the Bishops</hi> <hi rend="bold">! </hi> <hi rend="italic">The Bishop of S</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic"> David's told me that the Welsh Bishops had met in conference about the Monmouth Use, and had spoken faithfully with the Bishop of Monmouth: that the said Bishop had taken time to consider what course he should adopt: and that at his last Ordination he had refrained from the ceremonies objected against, and had used the Prayer&#8211;Book service</hi>. I dined at a table with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. He says that it is not unlikely that the offer of the Rede Lecture will be repeated next year. Lord Balfour was dining in the club, but I got no speech with him. He looks whiter and is getting stout.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>