<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923. </hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Yesterday's vote in the assembly disclosed the real cleavage between clergy and laity within the Church of England. The latter are so ignorant about all theological and ecclesiastical matters that they are unable clearly to perceive what really ought in their own interest to be resisted, or intelligently to oppose even what they dislike. <hi rend="bold underline">Nothing could well exceed the religious ignorance of the Evangelical laity. They have been bred on a diet of pious phrases &amp; vehement antipathies; where these are concerned they feel strongly &amp; speak violently: but they know little of Christian doctrine, and nothing of Christian history. Their religious life is directed in the groove of a narrow convention, never in obedience to any deliberately accepted authority. The Bible literally interpreted and pietistically applied is the Alpha and Omega of their personal religion. For the rest they follow blindly their party&#8211;chiefs, who are neither saints nor scholars</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Moule</hi> was the last Evangelical who could advance a respectable title to either description, &amp; his sainthood was tinged with mawkishness, while his scholarship was largely obsolete. <hi rend="bold underline">But the laity long for power over their parish clergyman, and this can never be conceded to them without deplorable consequences both to the religious life of the parish, and to the credit of the Ministry as a whole. It is unfortunate that lay expectation has been directed to this false objective.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wasted another day in the Assembly but made no speech. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I met at 21 Park Lane, &amp; lunched with the Scarbroughs. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Knowling</hi><persName xml:id="113"></persName> came to me in the Club, &amp; wanted to carry me off to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Buchaman</hi>, but I did not feel disposed to go, as the Archbishop was wanting to see me. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Perkins</hi> ran up to me as I was passing through <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> in order to thank me for my letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>! <hi rend="doubleunderline">Athelstan Riley</hi><persName xml:id="213"></persName> did the same yesterday: &amp; this afternoon the old Dean of Canterbury expressed the warmest approval. All this has value as 'showing the direction in which the wind is blowing'. </p>
         <p>The Archbishop of Canterbury came into the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; finding me there, invited me to share his motor back to Lambeth. On the way, he discussed the situation in the Church. <hi rend="bold underline">I told him that my 'policy' was to deal with the practical proposals for Prayers Book Revision at once, then to deal with the Courts, and as soon as this problem has been solved, &amp; the Church is equipped with an effective machinery for enforcing the Law, to complete the Revision. Then the Revised Book must be enforced coute que coute. He said that this was a positive policy which at least could be understood &amp; respected. </hi>The Lord Chancellor &amp; Lady Cave came to dinner: also Lord Wolmer<persName xml:id="1028"></persName> &amp; his wife. Dibden was very insistent that the reform of the Courts was impracticable. But I am not sure that he talks sincerely. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>