<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923. </hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The proceeding in the <hi rend="doubleunderline">National Assembly</hi> were more important than interesting until the afternoon, when there was quite a brisk debate on the Parochial Church Council (additional powers) measure. I made a speech against it which was loudly applauded by the clergy, and by the gallery. Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wolmer</hi><persName xml:id="1028"></persName>, who was much chagrined by the latter, called the Archbishop's notice to it, and was prettily snubbed for his pains. The voting was interesting. Of the Bishops 15 voted for, and 15 against: of the clergy 95 for, and 103 against: of the laity a very large majority voted for the measure. <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">My letter appeared in the 'Times'</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">, and, I think, attracted a good deal of notice. In spite of it, however, I was well listened to, and much applauded when I spoke. Several people e.g. Lord Ernle, &amp; Sir George Younger, came to me in the Club, &amp; expressed agreement with it.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridgeman</hi>, the Home Secretary, dined at Lambeth: I have some conversation with him. He said that, after a stormy meeting this afternoon, the Cabinet had agree to accept the American terms for funding the debt inz. 3% for ten years, and then 3 1/2 %. There appears to be much division of opinion as to the wisdom of accepting these terms. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridgeman</hi> is a strong supporter of the scheme for a Shropshire bishoprick. He insists on the strength of county feeling: on the convenience of Shrewsbury: and on the desirableness of bishopricks ' being small enough to enable a genuine pastorate by the bishop. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>