<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent all the day, save for a walk with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> after lunch, on the "Open Letter", but I cannot satisfy myself. It seems so difficult to avoid the rut of conventional "Protestantism", with which I have small sympathy, and which is certainly as dead as a door–nail. I want to write in such a wise that the sober 'High' churchmen are not offended, while these new "Anglo–Catholics" are shown to be impossible. But this is no easy matter since the former have all the weakness, as well as all the obstinacy, implied by the fact that they illustrate an arrested development. The latter are arrested also, but at a more advanced stage in the development. Relatively to the older type of sacerdotalist, the Anglo–Catholic has the advantage of superior logic. Then I must needs lie open to the accusation of practical futility, for what have I to offer as a practical policy? Even if all my contentions prevail, how am I advantaged? The Anglo–Catholics remain in possession of the field. </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">In the final event, the Bishops must dance to the tune called by the theological colleges. These colleges are quickly passing into the control of Anglo–Catholics: and they are leavening the clergy. Probably I should act most wisely, if, like the majority of my episcopal brethren, I 'kissed the rod', and affected to approve a movement which I am unable to restrain or control</hi> <hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>