<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">Pray don't suppose me to be against your action in the matter of a Rubricks' debate. Probably to a very great extent I am with you on the larger questions</hi> <hi rend="italic">."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>This was the message that Cantuar passed down to me this morning when I had insisted, in the teeth of his very evident desire, on the necessity of another debate in the National Assembly on Prayer Book Revision. I said that the Anglo–Catholic Movement and the publication of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> proposals had changed the situation. It was now evident that there was a concerted Revolt against the English system. <hi rend="bold underline">I returned to the charge on a motion concerning the age of Confirmation, and I think an impression was made on the Bishops</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Those who had associated themselves with the Anglo–Catholics looked particularly foolish. The Patronage Committee met at 5 p.m. <hi rend="italic">I walked with the Solicitor General (</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Tho</hi><hi rend="i sup u">s</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inskip</hi><persName xml:id="4783"></persName> <hi rend="italic">) as far as the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and told him that I had reached the conviction that we cannot avoid a disruption of the church if we are to be loyal to our principles. He will probably tell his friends, and their attitude will, perhaps, be stiffened.</hi> I received a long letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Albert Saxton</hi><persName xml:id="222"></persName>. He is now 37 years old. Time moves!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>