<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[148]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I sent the telegram to the Vicar of Medomsley. Rain fell heavily until lunch&#8211;time. I walked down to the stone bridge to see the Gaunless. It was a swollen &amp; turbid torrent, quite impressive in volume and violence, like the post&#8211;prandial patriotism of an Alderman!</p>
         <p>I wrote to the Solicitor General inviting co&#8211;operation in the matter of Prayer Book Revision: and also to the Bishop of Carlisle. </p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Darlington, where I had an interview with Cosgrave, who gives a good report on the man Hill. I suspect the link between them is a tendency towards Anglo&#8211;Catholic folly. Then we went on to S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's, where I confirmed nearly 150 persons, of whom about two thirds were females. The church was filled, and the service was reverent, and, I trust, edifying. <hi rend="bold underline">Among the male candidates was that queer creature, Sir Henry Havelock Allen</hi>. Very foolishly, Drary brought him to supper together with the architect Moscroft &amp; his wife. What could be more unsuitable than to have to move from the solemnity of the confirmation, to the frivolous talk of the supper table? We returned to Auckland after supper. Water lay across the road in several places, not deep enough to arrest travelling, but certainly noteworthy as indicating the quantity of the rainfall. It was raining hard as we returned. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">That worthless fellow Gibson, finding his Ordination stopped, now 'shows his teeth' at his quondam friend, Haslewood</hi>!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>