<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather improved during the night: and the day was mild and spring&#8211;like.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Sedgefield where I confirmed 63 persons, mostly female. Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> finds that during the long failure to get a curate, the boys have been much neglected. I don't think that this circumstance is confined to Sedgefield. The shortage of clergy is beginning to tell badly on the parochial machine. After having tea in the Rectory, we motored to S, James's, Stockton, where I confirmed 82 persons. This is a poor church, and the parson, Loney, is a rough type of cleric, &amp; drops his h s deplorably, but he loves the people, and works hard. On the whole, I was pleased with this confirmation. The candidates were of a suitable age, &amp; they gave me an impression of great earnestness. I think that, of all the oblations which poor humanity offers to its Creator, the hopes and fears of confirmation candidates are perhaps the most acceptable. Girl Guides and Boy Scouts were prominent in the congregation. After service we returned to Auckland, arriving at 9.15p.m.</p>
         <p>I began the sermon for Penrith on March 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and wrote the first section. It is a double commemoration, millenary and bicentenary, for the date of the old preaching cross, locally known as the 'Giant's Thumb' is assigned by the experts to the beginning of the 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, and the existing parish church was consecrated on March 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1723.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>