<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[160]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Better to learn through mistakes than to remain ignorant by never placing ourselves within the possibility of error.</p>
         <p>v. Philomythus, p. 97.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the castle at 9.20 a.m., and motored to Durham for the 'Business Meeting' of the <hi rend="underline">Diocesan Conference</hi>. We attended Mattins in the Cathedral, before going to the Chapter House for the meeting at 11.30 p.m.[sic] My Presidential Address took at least half an hour in delivery. It was well listened to, and, I think, as well received as I had any right to expect. The business went through without delay, &amp; with very little discussion. I lunched with Bishop Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>. We were back in Auckland by 5.30 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There is certainly a "Life &amp; Liberty" element in the Conference, of which, perhaps, Cosgrave is the spokesman</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> The diocesan representatives in the National Assembly naturally desire to 'magnify their office': and I think the standing controversy in the parishes with the Sectaries has led churchmen generally to brag of the "self&#8211;government" bestowed by the Enabling Act. There is, perhaps, a measure or resentment against my opposition to the Parochial Church Councils (Additional Powers) Measure, for there are many indications that the laity had set their hearts on getting some control over appointments, &amp; they perceive that therein I am their resolute antagonist.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>