<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[164]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the Penrith Sermon, and wrote letters. Then, seduced by the fineness of the day, for the sun shone, &amp; the air was balmy as in the spring, I went out into the garden. A young man was at the gate sketching. He asked permission to sketch in the garden, and being in an amiable mood for the weather pleased me, I not only gave him leave, for which he asked, but also showed him the Castle itself, for which courtesies he was most grateful. Dolphin<persName xml:id="2798"></persName> came to lunch, &amp; spake much of the late Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName>, but nowise to his credit. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham, and saw Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> at his office. We went next to Brancepeth, where we had tea in the Rectory, before going to the Church for the confirmation. I confirmed 85 candidates, of whom a substantial proportion were C.L.B.<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> lads from Willington. But the congregation coughed mercilessly, &amp; disturbed me badly. From Brancepeth we motored to Brandon, where I confirmed 103 candidates, all from that parish. I was pleased with reverence of the service, and the attention of the candidates. We returned to the Castle, arriving shortly after 9 p.m.</p>
         <p>Evelyn Cecil<persName xml:id="4163"></persName> wrote to thank me for m reference to the Divorce Court reports, which, he said, would help him in his effort to prohibit the publication of such reports. The lawyers &amp; the baser pressmen are the principal opponents.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
