<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>'<hi rend="underline">Arguments are shadows where monuments appear'</hi>. This striking sentence appears in a very shallow &amp; turgid discourse preached at the consecration of Penrith Church on March 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1723 by the Rev. Thomas Wearing. Burney, one of the curates at Ferryhill, came to consult me about a change of curacy. He is very loyal to his eccentric and exacting chief, Lomax<persName xml:id="5279"></persName>, but he wants more money, and not unnaturally since he only receives pounds&#x00A3;225, out of which he has to pay house&#8211;rent. As he has to maintain a wife and five children, he may well feel discontented. He says that the shortage of houses in Ferryhill in very great. Young people when they marry, commonly board with parents, to the discomfort of both.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Norton, where I confirmed 55 persons in S. Mary's Church. It is one of the finest &amp; most interesting parish churches in the diocese. The candidates were attentive and looked very serious and devout as they came up for the laying on of hands. I addressed them from the words, "<hi rend="underline">We must work the works of Him that sent me while it is day, the night cometh when no man can work</hi>". But all confirmation addresses tend to a certain inevitable identity, be the text what it may! After service we motored back to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, where we arrived at 9.15p.m. The rain was again falling steadily.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>