<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in Christ Church, at 8 a.m. There seemed to be most of the Incumbents of the Rural Deanery present. We breakfasted in the Vicarage. At 11 a.m. the Litany was sung by Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>, and I addressed the clergy. After the service I went for a brief walk. Canon Parish was at lunch. At 3 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">I addressed the clergy on the subject of Divorce</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> There was an animated discussion, which protracted the meeting, until past 5 p.m. On the whole I was pleased with general willingness of the clergy to listen and to consider. Most of them expressed their approval of my proposal that a Commission should be appointed to consider how Christian principle ought to find expression in the marriage law of the modern state. </p>
         <p>I preached in S. Oswald's Church, where the dedication Festival was being observed. Then Macdonald took me &amp; Knowlden to see some strange wireless&#8211;telegraphy machinery, which I don't understand &amp; which therefore disconcerts rather than interests me. <hi rend="bold underline">Finally, we attended the concert of the Unemployed, the crowd which sent me a Christmas Letter in 1921</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> There was a short religious service, &amp; I pronounced the Benediction. A moving spectacle. Then we got home about 10 p.m. having been "at it" for at least 14 hours with hardly a breathing space. If 'hustle' could hasten the Kingdom, Macdonald would manage it!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>