<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[179]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Even the best theological literature of that age (the Ancient Church) contains much that cannot possibly be true, <hi rend="underline">and it is difficult to imagine how the study of Councils has been found compatible with the theory which requires us to find Conciliar utterances Divine</hi>. But the great Greek Creeds of the fourth century, and the 'Constantinopolitan' Creed most, will bear severe testing with all available resources of judgement after these many ages of change. Assuredly they do not contain all truth, even within the limits of subject by which they were happily confined. <hi rend="underline">But their guidance never fails to be found trustworthy, &amp; for us at least it is necessary</hi>. Like other gifts of God's Providence, they can be turned to deadly use, but to those who employ them rightly <hi rend="underline">they are the safeguard of a large and progressive faith</hi>. (Hort ii:176).</p>
         </div>
         <p>Would Hort, in 1923, have written as he wrote in 1876? I doubt it.</p>
         <p>That woeful motor having gone out of action through the cracking of the steel frames for the tires, I inspected two cars, both American, with the idea that I would buy a supplementary machine to cover these recurred failures. In the afternoon I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>