<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The total absence of any specific influence of Greek theology upon the Oxford movement, notwithstanding the extensive reading in the Fathers possessed by its more learned chiefs, is a very striking fact. On the other hand, I think it was a leading cause of the largeness of mind found, along with much rhetoric &amp; incoherence, in the greater English divines from 1550 to 1650.</p>
         <p>Hort to Westcott. July 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1865 (ii. 38)</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Newcastle, and had my hair cut before presiding over a meeting of the Governors of the Barnard Castle School. They elected me Chairman for the ensuing year. Knowlden had tea with me in the Hotel after the meeting. I motored to Horden, picking up Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> on the way at Durham, and confirmed 176 candidates. After the service Brigstocke carried me off to a house in the place, where I confirmed a miner, who could not get to church because a stone had fallen on his foot, &amp; broken his great toe! I told Brigstocke that, if he hadn't arranged his future otherwise, he might come to me as "Diocesan Chaplain" for awhile. He is in negotiations with Newsom<persName xml:id="923"></persName> for the curacy at Newcastle Cathedral, &amp; may go there. But, in any case, I don't want to lose him from the diocese if I can help it. We arrived back at the Castle shortly before 10p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>