<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">To the best of my knowledge there is no evidence for the practice of Non&#8211;Communicating attendance in at least the first four centuries, except either as a penal privation inflicted on one class of penitents, or as a popular abuse rebuked by authority. The doctrinal grounds on which it is defended appear to me to receive no support from Scripture or from any formulary of the Church of England; and the results to which it naturally leads are in my belief disastrous.</hi></p>
         <p>v. Hort. Jan.14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1886 (Life ii. 338)</p>
         </div>
         <p>A beautiful spring day. I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> for two hours in the afternoon.</p>
         <p>I finished the Freemasons' Sermon, and started to read the volume of essays – '<hi rend="underline">Liberal Evangelicalism, an Interpretation'</hi> – which was sent me by the publisher yesterday. Its main interest, perhaps, is the list of Authors, for in these days men are not very willing to label themselves. They are the following.</p>
         <p>Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> H. A. Wilson, Guy Rogers, E. A. Burroughs, V. F. Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, R. J. Howard, H. B. Gooding, J. W. Hunkin, F. S. Guy Warman (Bp. of Truro), M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Linton Smith (Bp. of Hereford), E. S. Woods, A. W. Davies, and E. W. Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>. Except the two Westminster Canons it does impress me as a strong team:</p>
         </body></text></TEI>