<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>After writing a few indispensable letters, I embarked on the almost hopeless task of tidying my study. It is a dreadful reflection that in my 60<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year I have not yet mastered the elements of the clerk's business of keeping books &amp; papers in an intelligible or at least serviceable order. The waste of time, temper and energy that flows from this single fact is sad to reflect. I might have done some good work in the world if but I had possessed the secret of organizing myself rationally: now it is too late for reformation, only soon enough for regret.</p>
         <p>The Rev. James M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Gill, curate of Shotton, came to lunch. He had been offered the living of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Francis, South Shields, and, having seen it &amp; resolved to decline it, came to ask my advice! He is one of the men trained in Kelham Theological College, and his loyalty to Anglicanism is beyond question. He has married his Vicar's daughter! I had some talk with him on the question of obedience to law, and he expressed himself more reasonably than I had expected. The reputation of Kelham in the matter of law&#8211;breaking is better than the character of its churchmanship would suggest. "Father" Kelly, the Superior, is said to be a born teacher, &amp; I have heard Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> speak with decision as to the excellent results which he obtains from material which might be described as unpromising. M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Gill is the first product of Kelly's system whom I have encountered, and he does not impress me unfavourably.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[141] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>February 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1923.</p>
         <p>My dear Macmillan</p>
         <p>I received from the publishers a few days ago a volume of "Anglican Essays", which I have read through with much interest. It is, of course, like all such works by various authors unequal, and perhaps a little inconsequent. It lies open to the criticism that its general drift is rather that of a polemic against Rome, than an apologia for England. In our present circumstances, however, <hi rend="underline">both</hi> are apparently &amp; even urgently required.</p>
         <p>The volume is timely and valuable. I trust that it will have a large circulation.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Murray's Essay is full of knowledge, and if his style were less eccentric, would be an unusually impressive piece of work.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Paige Cox's Essay on Communion or Mass might be very usefully circulated as a pamphlet.</p>
         <p>The least satisfactory Essay is, surprisingly, that of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Raven, who thunders &amp; raves in the manner of the prophets only to land us in a poor little plea for an United Mission of Anglicans &amp; Nonconformists! <hi rend="underline">Parliriunt montes</hi>. Raven is a very able man, and, if he doesn't wear himself out prematurely, will go far. But I don't think that he has as yet 'found <hi rend="bold">[142] </hi>his feet' either in economics or in religion.</p>
         <p>I am much concerned about Prayer Book Revision. <hi rend="italic">The rise and rapid development of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement have given it a new and decisive importance. </hi> <hi rend="italic underline">It is not, indeed, improbable that the Revision will fail before an unnatural alliance of unyielding Protestants and unscrupulous "Catholics"</hi> <hi rend="italic">: but, if it escapes this rock, it will have to answer the vital question, </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">What does the Church of England really stand for in Christendom</hi> <hi rend="italic">? Has it any distinctive principles at all, or any authority to enforce them if it has?</hi></p>
         <p>I have just sent Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> an Article on this matter: but I am not sure that it conforms sufficiently to the Edinburgh norm. If it doesn't, I shall issue it as a pamphlet.</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>George Macmillan Esq.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>