<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The heavy tempest which raged yesterday still continues. I received an extraordinarily foolish letter from Jones asking my advice as to his manner of celebrating the Holy Communion in St Oswalds. I sent him a curt reply directing him to take instructions from his vicar. It is almost incredible that an intelligent and self&#8211;respecting young clergyman should behave as he is behaving. Ex uno disce omnes. This is a specimen of Anglo&#8211;Catholicism.</p>
         <p>I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and the dogs in the Park for an hour after lunch. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Malcolm Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName> lunched here. He wished to consult me about ecclesiastical re&#8211;arrangements in the district of Seaham, where Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> is sinking a new pit. A colony of 500 houses will be built for the miners. This will bring a population of at least 2000 into those parts. He spoke of Seaham Hall, which Lord Lo has presented for use as a hospital. He said that it was rich in personal associations. Not only had Lord Byron been married there: but Lord Beaconsfield, who was thought to have designs on the old Marchioness, was a frequent visitor.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName><hi rend="italic"> asked me to dispense his students &amp; their guests from the obligation of the Lenton Fast on Friday, March 2</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi> <hi rend="italic">, which happen to coincide with the patronal festival of S. Chad's College. I acquiesced in the farce, &amp; sent him the dispensation he asked for!!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>