<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We beseech thee, Almighty God, look upon the hearty desires of your humble servants, and stretch forth the right hand of thy Majesty, to be our defence against all our enemies, through Jesus Christ our Lord</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated. After breakfast I wrote a sermon for use at Consett, where most of the miners recently killed at Medomsly had their homes. I hate everything of the nature of funeral sermons. </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> accompanied me in the motor as far as Durham. I went to Lambton, and had tea with Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, with whom was his brother D'Arcy. Then I went to Consett, and delivered the sermon to a very large congregation. The relatives of the deceased pit&#8211;lads sate immediately under the pulpit rather disconcertingly. After the service they came into the Vestry to see me. I made an ass of myself and wept with them! Then I returned to Auckland stopping in Durham on the way in order to recover the ladies. There was enough fog to embarrass William in driving, but not enough seriously to delay or endanger us.</p>
         <p>This is my first tragedy: in scale petty &amp; in character rather specially alarming. I am glad it occurred to me to show some personal concern.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>