<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, who seest that we have no power of ourselves to help ourselves; Keep us both outwardly in our bodies, and inwardly in our souls; that we may be defended from all adversities which may happen to the body, and from all evil thoughts which may assault and hurt the soul, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a translation from the Gregorian collect which runs thus:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Deus qui conspicis omni nos virtute destitui, interius exteriusque custodi: ut ab omnibus adversitatibus muniamur in corpore: et a pravis cogitationibus mundemar in mente. Per</p>
         </div>
         <p>The English rendering owes to the Latin only the idea &amp; the antithesis. It is practically an original composition. The Epistle connects the prayer with the specific duty of sexual purity. "<hi rend="underline">For this is the Will of God, even your sanctification, that ye should abstain from fornication &amp;c.</hi>". How des S. Paul's teaching agree with the notions about sexual morality which are implied in the advocacy of the use of contraceptives as a normal procedure in married life? Would the Apostle have allowed that sexual intercourse, thus facilitated and conditioned, was an adequate version of the Christian's duty to '<hi rend="underline">know how to possess his vessel in sanctification &amp; honour; not in the lust of concupiscence &amp;c</hi>.'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mark Pattison's</hi> Memoirs are unpleasant reading, but their very unpleasantness has a certain evidential value, for it indicates how deeply '<hi rend="underline">the iron had entered into his soul'</hi>, that is, how filled with rage and scorn was his mind when he recalled the prostration of personality into which the Tractarianism had brought him in those days of earlier manhood, when his mental powers were hardly known to himself. Probably he was more deeply affected than he knew, and his conscience was not quite easy over the decisions of his mind. The freedom and naturalness of his intellectual movement were permanently impaired by the early bondage to sacerdotalism. It is perhaps always a very great calamity to be caught in youth by causes which one cannot champion in later life, and to be swept by convictions which one has finally to abandon. The scene in the Gospel is re&#8211;enacted, the violence with which the spirit leaves its human residence is disclosed in havock &amp; desolation. '<hi rend="underline">Having cried out, and torn him much, he came out: &amp; the child became as one dead: insomuch that the more part said, He is dead</hi>.' When we remember how deep &amp; divine a thing is a young man's repentance, there is something horrifying in such a sentence as this: "I once, and only once, got so low by fostering a morbid state of conscience as to go to confession to D<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Pusey". I apprehend that there is no greater wrong that one man can work against another than to hustle him by emotional pressures into doing violence to his intelligence, for the reaction is desolating.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[147] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated Holy Communion in The Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and Bishop Cameron Mann. The Judge, the Commissioner, the High Sheriff, their ladies, the two marshals, and a little girl came to tea, &amp; were shown over the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The paper reports a serious accident in a pit at Medomsley in this diocese. Eight men have been dashed suddenly into destruction. I decided that I would send a telegram to the parson in these terms</hi>:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Have just learned of terrible accident at Medomsley. Am deeply concerned and distressed for loss of eight valuable lives. Please assure bereaved families of my sympathy. Inform me of funeral arrangements."</p>
         </div>
         <p>If the parson be a sensible man in touch with the people such a telegram will give him an entrance into their hearts &amp; homes at this juncture, and he will make full use of it. If there be any general plan for the funeral of these victims, it will probably be well advised on my part to attend, and, perhaps, if the families wish it, to take part in the service. These Northerners are very sensitive on the subject of funerals, and they would probably appreciate my presence. On the other hand, one shrinks from, so to speak, 'thrusting one's self in' to a great sorry.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>