<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I packed, and came away, resigning my latch&#8211;key rather ruefully. It is horrid to be thrown back into the "changes and chances" of hotels</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="underline">In the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I set myself to writing a letter to the Times on "Prayer Book Revision" in which I drew into prominence what I hold to be the "salient point" of the new Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement viz. its repudiation of all Anglican authority</hi>. Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> coming into the club, I showed him what I had written, &amp; he approving it, I gave it to the post. Then I walked to Westminster, and attended the meeting of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">National Assembly</hi>. There seemed a fairly full attendance of members. Sir Lewis Dibden introduced in a speech of 45 minutes the Union of Benefices Measure, a dull theme for a dull man. The "debate" occupied the rest of the session. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey Charnwood</hi><persName xml:id="2685"></persName> took me off to the Club for tea. There we found <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Murray</hi>, &amp; had some talk. I made my way to Lambeth, where I found <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who had created a mild sensation by fainting in the gallery of the Church House, where she had been attending the debate</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> I took down to dinner <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi> <hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"> Lisle Carr</hi>, the wife of the Bishop of Coventry, a pleasant unimpressive lady by nature earmarked for an ecclesiastical career. The Bishop himself is a plain hearty man, who has a considerable reputation as a "live" clergyman.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>