<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A new volume of the Surtees Society Publications arrived:&#8211; "Durham Protestations or the Returns made to the House of Commons in 1641/2 for the Maintenance of the Protestant Religion for the County Palatine of Durham for the Borough of Berwick&#8211;upon&#8211;Tweed &amp; the Parish of Morpeth."</p>
         <p>This 'protestation' was to be signed by "the Inhabitants of their several parishes, both Householders &amp; Others, being of Eighteen Years of Age &amp; Upwards." The names are all masculine, &amp; the number, on a rough estimate, appears to be about 20,000. This might indicate a population for the county of about 60,000.</p>
         <p>The weather became cold and rainy. None the less Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I walked for an hour in the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Servants' Party took place , and was kept up with much spirit till the small hours of the morning. A great variety of talent appears to have disclosed itself</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Music and the drama were both represented in the entertainment. Meanwhile, I read the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> volume of Page's Life &amp; Letters. It has an almost tragical interest, so vividly does it represent the fears &amp; hopes of that desperate time, when the possibility of defeat came very near to this country. Grey and Balfour are the Ambassador's heroes. They almost rise to greatness. President Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName> does not come out of the narrative creditably. He nearly 'lost the War' for us all.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>