<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There is nothing in the Catholicism of Canada, or Ireland, or Spain, to hold out against modern education: &amp; the clericals know that well enough, &amp; put all their trust in ignorance &amp; obscurantism. <hi rend="underline">Already, Ireland is developing a strong anti&#8211;clericalism of a French pattern</hi>: &amp; Spain is dry grass waiting to catch fire. I was struck yesterday by the truth of a remark by an Italian liberal, that the conflict was less between Catholicism &amp; Science than between Catholicism &amp; Christianity; that is, I fancy, between the pagan &amp; the Christian elements of Catholicism.</p>
         <p>Tyrell. Letter. March 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1904 (p. 95).</p>
         </div>
         <p>The anti&#8211;clericalism, which was already visible to an acute Irishman in 1904, has grown into a strong, possibly a decisive, factor of Irish life during the last 20 years.</p>
         <p>The Times reports the death of my God&#8211;daughter, Paula Inge<persName xml:id="2067"></persName>. I wrote briefly to Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, who will feel her loss deeply. Also, I leaned of the death of my cousin, Frank Henson's only son, Ellis, in India. I wrote to the boy's father. I went through the Communion service with John, the Butler's boy, who will communicate for the first time tomorrow I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and to Cecil Fortescue<persName xml:id="4760"></persName>.</p>
         <p>The weather, brilliant in the early morning, worsened rapidly, and settled down to a steady rain.</p>
      </body></text></TEI>