<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Still the fine weather, and the cold cutting wind. We left Rose Castle at 9.30 a.m., and motored to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, arriving at 1.50 p.m. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear, where I confirmed 52 candidates in the parish church. Then we had tea with the Vicar and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wilkinson in the newly&#8211;built Vicarage, a small but sufficient house. We returned to Auckland, only to go out again to a Confirmation at Shildon. Here I confirmed 112 candidates. The service was hearty, the candidates were earnest &amp; devout, and the considerable congregation sympathetic &amp; attentive. I think such a service can hardly be wholly unblessed to the parish. We went back to Auckland after the service, arriving shortly after 8.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>The demand for super&#8211;tax was awaiting me. The amount – &#x00A3;502:4:0.&#8211; was considerably less than I had anticipated. I sent a cheque with comparative satisfaction! The half&#8211;year's Income tax is &#x00A3;684.1.6. i.e. &#x00A3;1368:3:0, making up a total for the year of &#x00A3;1870.7.0, which is certainly a substantial reduction on last year, when I paid Super&#8211;tax &#x00A3;739.1.6 and Income Tax &#x00A3;1446.6.0 = &#x00A3;2185.7.6 a total gain of &#x00A3;315.0.6. I also paid on March 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> &#x00A3;69.6.2: and on July 17 &#x00A3;58.16.4, a total of &#x00A3;127.2.6 on account of taxation. If this sum be not exacted this year, my gain will be by so much increased: but the ways of the Commissioners for Income Tax are 'past finding out', &amp; I dare not be optimistic.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>