<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Some, it may be, will knit the Brow, if I should say, that even Holy Scripture itself, sometimes requires an astronomical Interpreter: who else shall…decide the controversy about the Retrocession of the Shadow upon the Dial of Ahaz? When without a miracle that might be many ways done by the meer Fabrick of the Dial…Neither need we fear to diminish a Miracle by explaining it: this Retrocession of the Sun was given as a Sign, so was the Rainbow, which had it appear'd never since, had been miraculous.</p>
         <p>Wren's Parentalia p.26.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Christopher Wren</hi> was well beyond the obsessions of the XVII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century when he expressed himself thus in 1657, when he was but 25. I think I will preach about him to the Freemasons on April 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to the North Eastern County School, and there, in the school chapel, I confirmed 57 boys. After having tea with a large company of parents &amp; boys, we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wren's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Parentalia</hi> with a view to estimating the homiletic value of the great Man's Life and Character. On the whole I incline to thing that I "struck oil". He was certainly a 'miracle of a man'.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>