<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Worth of St Luke's, Darlington, wrote asking my counsel about admitting some Dissenters to Communion and arranging an exchange of pulpits with the local Baptist minister. I replied, &amp; copied my letter into my Register.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored in to Durham, where I presided over a meeting of the Finance Board. There was much business, and a large attendance. I got through the programme by 4.45 p.m. and then had tea with Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>.</p>
         <p>On the whole I was pleased with the temper of the meeting. After my frank condemnation of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics in connection with the Retreat House Scheme, and my speeches in the National Assembly, I was quite prepared for some evidence of resentment, but the appearances were all in the other direction. Two of the 'High' Churchmen were at tea with the Archdeacon – Canons Stack<persName xml:id="5290"></persName> &amp; Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> – and both were really more than commonly agreeable. I think they realize that I am quite frank with them, and that I have some good reasons for disliking the new Anglo&#8211; Catholicism.</p>
         <p>On returning to the study, I turned down from my shelves Magee's 'Life', and was immensely interested. He had a raciness of phrase and a vigour of thought which are never common, and in a bishop are very refreshing. His counsel to a clergyman as to the manner of teaching a penitent deserves to rank with Benson's letter on Confession in schools.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I am all for giving larger freedom to the Church to frame and enforce her laws. But freedom to the individual clergyman, to do as he pleases, means either tyranny for the parishioners – if you retain the present parochial system – or tyranny for the clergy, if you substitute it for the will of the congregation. So far regarding an act of uniformity as a restraint on the liberty of the glergy, I regard it as their only protection against the congregational tyranny of the Nonconformists or the episcopal tyranny of the Roman Church"</p>
         <p>Magee's letter to Earl Nelson. Nov.2.1878 (ii.100)</p>
         </div>
         <p>That was true in 1878, and it is no less true in 1923. We shall discover in the process of Prayers Book Revision which of the two contrasted tyrannies shall be established in the Church of England.</p>
         <p>Here is a sound maxim to be digested and applied:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"My maxims in governing are, 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, never hit if you can avoid it: 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, when you <hi rend="underline">do</hi> hit, <hi rend="underline">smash</hi>: 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, when the smashed man admits that he is smashed, then apply the plaster of forgiveness and civility". ii.203.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I think that on the whole Magee's maxims have been those on which I have acted during my life: and in the main I think they are sound.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>