<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The fulness of the conception of Confirmation – the open confession and the laying on of hands &#8211; seems to me to have been providentially committed to our keeping, &amp; we are bound to guard the trust jealously</p>
         <p>Westcott to Benson 1892 (Life ii.162)</p>
         </div>
         <p>So strongly did Westcott feel on the necessity of laying on of hands as part of a valid confirmation that he directed a clergyman in the diocese of Durham to insist on the confirmation of a Roman Catholic, although he had been confirmed in the Roman Church. I incline to think this insistence on a mere ceremony to be superstitious, &amp; more Roman than Anglican in principle!</p>
         <p>I finished the Presidential Address. It has grown into a more considerable pronouncement than I had originally intended. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hollwey, the organizer of the ex&#8211;Officers' settlement, came to see me. He wanted me to direct the clergy to preach on the subject on Easter Sunday! This I could not see my way to do, but I support him generally.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I walked with the dogs in the Park after lunch. I finished Neville Talbot's book. It is well&#8211;intentioned, and gives one a good impression of the author, but it is confused, slap&#8211;dash, and superficial. In his anxiety to be fair to objectors, he makes larger concessions than he knows.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>