<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>January 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1923.</p>
         <p>My dear Cox,</p>
         <p>I will write an article for the April issue of the <hi rend="underline">Edinboro</hi> on 'Prayer Book Revision' designing to draw out into clear view what is the real issue underlying the process viz. whether the type of religion expressed in the parishes is to be essentially altered, or not.</p>
         <p>Thank you for letting me know about the Walworth experiments, It is a very bold one, &amp; depends much on the manner of its working. In the amazingly free association of young unmarried people which now obtains in every rank of society, I suspect that abstinence from sexual intercourse is mainly secured by a three&#8211;fold fear – fear of the child, fear of the social disgrace, fear of disease. Take this restraining fear away by guaranteeing that there shall be no conception, that the whole process may be concealed, &amp; that there need be no apprehension of disease, &amp; what is likely to happen? And if that shall happen, as seems probable, what will its subtle, accumulating, &amp; continuing effect on human character be? Solve me this problem, &amp; you make the way easier to your practical policy.</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to Westminster, and attended a meeting of the patronage committee until lunchtime. We talked much, but made little headway. <hi rend="bold underline">I invited the Commission (for so we now call a Committee!) to hold its meeting from September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> – 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold underline"> at <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName></hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> If all the members turn up, it will be a tight fit!</p>
         <p>I lunched in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> for company. In the smoking&#8211;room Lord Cave sate himself beside me, &amp; we had a very interesting talk both about ecclesiastical maters, &amp; about the political situation, He evidently enjoys being Lord Chancellor. Also, I had some talk with Hill, lately member for Durham. He told me that a seat had been found for him somewhere in Lancashire. I walked into the City, and called at the Deanery of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's. A service was proceeding in the Cathedral – the dedication of candlesticks in memory of Lord Kitchener by the London Regiment. I had tea with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. Then I returned to the Athenaeum and wrote letters. <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop came in, and asked me to second Bell for election to the Club. This I did very willingly as I account Bell to be a good fellow</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> I dined with Lady Scarbrough. Lady Serena was there, and a fine young Oxonian, Edward Marjoribanks, who is heir to the Tweedmouth peerage. He seems to have met me at the Deanery, where he came with old Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>