<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The convulsions of our English Church itself, grievous as they are, seem to be as nothing beside the danger of its calm &amp; unobtrusive alienation in thought and spirit from the great silent multitude of Englishmen, &amp; again of alienation from fact and love of fact:– mutual alienations both.</p>
         <p>Hort to Benson, 1882 (ii. 290)</p>
         </div>
         <p>More than 40 years have passed since Hort thought thus, and today the Church of England is immersed in an "Anglo–Catholic" controversy! The nation no longer troubles itself about the national Church.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and had a meeting with the two Archdeacons<persName xml:id="2785"><persName xml:id="3688"></persName></persName>. Then I lunched with the Freemasons in the Castle Hall, and proposed the health of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ravensworth</hi><persName xml:id="3719"></persName>, the P.G.M. There was the presentation of a large piece of plate, and an illuminated address to <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"> Ravensworth's</hi> heir, now an undergraduate at Christ Church. The young man made a short, modest, &amp; sufficient reply. I returned to Auckland after the luncheon, &amp; walked with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in the Park. Beck distinguished herself by stampeding the ponies. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> has many excellences, but training a dog cannot be included among them. Beck is a sweet beast, but her disobedience could not be more absolute, &amp; her spirits are irrepressible!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>