<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> returned from Houghton about 10.30 a.m., and we fell too at the correspondence which occupied us all the morning. After lunch I prepared notes for the evening, and wrote letters. At 5.45 p.m. we left the Castle and motored to Sunderland. There I dedicated an altar and reredos in S. Peter's Church. These are designed to mark the 'Jubilee' of the parish. I preached from my notes which were greedily seized upon by a reporter. After servicewe motored back to the Castle in the teeth of a violent wind, arriving about 10 p.m. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName> sent me his little booklet "<hi rend="underline">Catholicism and Roman Catholicism</hi>" with the following characteristic note:&#8211; </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Beloved wretch.</p>
         <p>I send you the enclosed – only I think to annoy if you happen to look at it.</p>
         <p>Yours, Charles Gore.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I read through the booklet. It is thoroughly representative product of its author's mind. He believes himself to be entirely liberal and, in spirit, evangelical. He employs language which might appear to justify these descriptions: but his heart is with sacerdotalist claims and every sacramental development. His language about the Papacy is almost violent, but the assumptions of this own position are hardly less than papal, and the papal claim is perhaps more defensible from Scripture than the episcopal.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>February 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1923.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>I was pleased with business during my recent visit to London, and unable to arrange for an interview with you. Your letter interests me, and, if you care to explain your position more in detail, I shall consider with thought and sympathy what you say. It is, of course, always extremely difficult for men who are complete strangers to one another to enter with any real understanding into their respective difficulties: and in all situations of religious perplexity temperament and habit are more potent factors than reason or conscience though perhaps less often pleaded, and often not perceived.</p>
         <p>Believe me.</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm</p>
         <p>Capt<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> E. Morris Young</p>
         <p>Ex. Officers Residential Club.</p>
         <p>31 Leinster Gardens</p>
         <p>Lancaster Gate. W2</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>