<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I return to my diocese with a clear pledge to pursue the policy of which I gave notice to the Bishops yesterday and which they appeared willing to accept. <hi rend="bold underline">I have promised Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> to write an article in the April Quarterly on 'Prayer Book revision'</hi>, and this will, I trust, make its appearance before the House of Laity meets on April 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> . <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of London will preside over a great Congress of Anglo&#8211;Catholics next July during the session of the National Assembly.</hi> The coincidence is arresting and can hardly be unpremeditated. I thought the Archbishop referred to it yesterday with some asperity.</p>
         <p>I left Lambeth at 9.20a.m., and drove to King's Cross, where I took train for Darlington. As far as York I had the companionship of Sir Hugh Bell, who talked with his usual vivacity and intelligence of men and affairs. He seemed more cheerful than usual though professing an universal despondency. At Darlington Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me. On arriving at the Castle I at once went through an accumulation of correspondence.</p>
         <p>William had had utilised my absence in order to instal a wirless apparatus on room N<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi> 18. He fetched me from my room to hear a concert in Newcastle. It was no more than a ghost like taritering that met my ear, but even so it was recognisably a concert, and the strangeness of the whole incident flashed on me. At this pacw where will his generation stand before it too gives up the game?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>