<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 11 a.m., and motored into Durham, where I instituted and licensed several clergy in the Chapel of the Castle, and signed the commissions for the Rural Deans.</p>
         <p>Then I called on M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cruickshank<persName xml:id="2663"></persName> whom I found much dejected by the melancholy death of her nephew: the young man, in a strange fit of melancholy, had committed suicide.</p>
         <p>I lunched with J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. The new Chief Constable, an Oxford man, was there, a pleasant fellow.</p>
         <p>I presided at a meeting of the diocesan Conference Committee, and afterwards had a long interview with Wood, the Vicar of S. Mark's, South Shields. It was not very apparent for what reason he had desired to see me!</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> rejoined me at the College gate, &amp; we returned to Auckland, picking up D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Short on the way.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The afternoon post brought a letter from M</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Gow<persName xml:id="542"></persName>, telling me that my old friend<persName xml:id="216"></persName>, her husband, "could only live a few days at the outside." This is sad news. For more than 10 years he and I lived next door to one another in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and had converse together almost daily. His last years have been heavily clouded by physical weakness, but he has played the man, and kept cheerful in spite of all.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>