<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Lightfoot on Confirmation (Charge. 1886)</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I see one way indeed, by which our numbers might be swelled at once; but I cannot recommend it. By lowering the age we shall attain this end, for unquestionably young children will present themselves for Confirmation more freely than growing youths…There may be exceptional cases, whether of individuals or of whole classes, where circumstances render it advisable to present candidates at an earlier age, <hi rend="underline">but as a rule fifteen seems to me the best standard</hi>. It is one thing to secure a lad for Confirmation, and quite another to retain a hold over him when confirmed. The season of Confirmation is the one opportunity for the clergyman in the lives of most young persons, and this opportunity cannot be anticipated &amp; exhausted prematurely without serious loss."</p>
         </div>
         <p>What new factors have come on the scene which, if Lightfoot had been living now, might have led him to alter his opinion? <hi rend="bold underline">There is some psychological nonsense, &amp; the enormous approximation to Roman doctrine &amp; practice in the matter of Confirmation: but there is nothing else. Would he have yielded to these</hi> <hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[166]</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham, where I licensed curates in the Castle, and lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Capt<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> Apperley<persName xml:id="2918"></persName> was there, &amp; in excellent form. <hi rend="bold underline">He told a story of an old parson, Ridley, a relative of Lord Ridley</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> This old man was very sensitive to the odour of the <hi rend="underline">profanum vulgus</hi>, and when he ministered in the congregation he had his handkerchief well be&#8211;sprinkled with <hi rend="underline">eau de Cologne</hi>. On entering the pulpit his practice was to protect himself from annoyance by waving his scented handkerchief freely about him, and then in a nimbus of sweet scent, to give out his text. <hi rend="bold underline">Wilson followed this up by another story of the same old gentleman</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> It was his custom before retiring to bed to look round the kitchen and see that everything was safe. On one occasion he observed the covered dish in which his matutinal bacon was served standing in an unusual place. He raised the cover, <hi rend="bold underline">and to his horror and amazement found his housekeeper's false teeth on the plate</hi> <hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>From these stories we motored to Sacristan where I confirmed about 65 candidates. The parson, Hutton, came to the parish five years ago by exchange. He is an odd looking man with a queer feeble manner of speaking, and a furtive manner. He is reputed to be a Hebrew Scholar of some distinction, and seems to be well assured that he is making headway in the parish. Among the candidates was an old man of 72, and several miners. The church is a comfortless building of a cheap type.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
         <p>We returned to Durham Castle, where I had an interview with a young clergyman, who is being 'considered' in Downing Street for S. Francis, South Shields. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Warner is 34 years old, and has been about 6 years in Orders. Ordained in Manitoba, he soon forsook Canada, and came to England. He has been for some while past an assistant curate in London. I inquired into his opinions especially on the key&#8211;questions – Reservation and Confession. He expressed himself very dutifully, <hi rend="bold underline">but he does not give me the impression of a man who would stand up against opposition</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> However we must be thankful for what we can get, and it is something that he means well. Next came M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> John Lake, a Knustford candidate, who wanted advice as to whether he had better have additional theological training after taking his degree. He is the son of a skilled artisan living in Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees. Yet a third ordination candidate, Tooley, came to see me: and I exhorted him to be ordained in September, as he is nearly 27. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> carried the staff to S Margaret's, and we followed with the bags. I confirmed 134 candidates from four parishes. Both at Sacriston and in S. Margaret's the proportion of males to females was less unsatisfactory than usual. There was little coughing to complain of, and the service was reverent and (I trust) edifying. After service we returned to Auckland, where we arrived at 9.20 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
