<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at the Penrith sermon, &amp; paid the wages. Also I wrote to the Worshipful Master of the Wear Valley Lodge commending William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> application for membership.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Thorp Thewles (Grindon) where I confirmed 63 persons in the little church. The service was good, but the atmosphere was asphyxiating. M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Wlberforce Smith provided me with a quiet room where I remained undisturbed until it was time for us to go on to Stockton for the next Confirmation. I confirmed 194 persons in Holy Trinity Church. Here the service was certainly pleasing, but one can never really learn anything from one's own impressions. That unpleasant creature Milner, the Rector of Elton, presented two boys, whose ages were set down in his list as 13. He had not obtained my consent to this breach of the diocesan rule. This finishes the rural deanery of Stockton.</p>
         <p>The numbers confirmed are:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Norton</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">55</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Sedgefield</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">63</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Stockton (1)</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">82</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Grindon</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">62</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Stockton (2)</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">194</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">456</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>In every case the discrepancy of boys to girls has been marked. I doubt if there have been more than one third of those confirmed who have been males. There have been few candidates under 14.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>