<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We may believe that orthodoxy leads to truth, or truth to orthodoxy; but to identify them seems to me to involve the practical loss of either the one or the other. Moreover it is a sad fact that most orthodox criticism in England is reckless of truth, &amp; unjust to the authors of other criticism.</p>
         <p>Hort to Westcott, Sept. 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1871. (ii. 147)</p>
         </div>
         <p>Four foreign doctors, visiting England in connexion with the League of Nations, came here. I showered them over the Castle.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to West Hartlepool, &amp; picked up Canon Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>, who guided us to Bellasis, where I dedicated the Mission Church, a plain building seating about 400 people. Most of the clergy attended from the Rural Deanery, and many lay&#8211;readers. There were 4 choirs. Altogether, the procession included at least 100 men &amp; boys. We robed in the hut, &amp; then went on to the Church. The brilliant weather assisted the function. After tea in some kind of an institution, we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I have a letter from Ellison writing on behalf of the Bishop of Stepney to ask me to preach at a Men's Service in the Royal Exchange on Monday, November 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, the day after Armistice Day. That Monday is the day on which the National Assembly meets, and if I accepted the invitation I should have to come up to London on the preceding Saturday. Nevertheless, I incline to accept it. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>