<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"He passed the greatest part of the five last following years of his life in contemplation and studies, and principally in the consolation of the Holy Scriptures; cheerful in solitude, &amp; as well pleased to die in the shade as in the light."</p>
         <p>v. Parentalia. p. 229.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Thus the last five years of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Christopher Wren</hi> are summed up. Yet the old man must have felt keenly the treatment he received, but he was cast in a large mould, &amp; had more resources than men knew. And, after all, his work was done. None could see that so clearly as himself: and he was not only a great man, but a true Christian.</p>
         <p>We (Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I) motored to <hi rend="underline">Escombe</hi>, where I confirmed 62 candidates. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The baleful personality of the incumbent dominated everything, and I was glad to get away</hi> <hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Later, we motored to </hi> <hi rend="italic underline">Tudhoe</hi> <hi rend="italic">, &amp; there I confirmed 167 candidates, amid much coughing. Here also the situation was distinctly uncomfortable. The parson seemed to fill one's vision, &amp; he was not exactly helpful. The standing mystery of Christianity is the power for good and for ill of individuals. A good parson makes the whole parish throb with spiritual vitality: a dull, or cantankerous, or discreditable parson takes the life out of everything, </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; the parish church becomes what the Christians called the Serapeum, only a Sepulchre</hi> <hi rend="i bold">!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>