<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote letters all the morning. After lunch I went into Durham, and had an interview with an unusual kind of ordination candidate from the mining parish of Silksworth. He has working in the mine there since he was a boy of 13; and now, at the age of 37 he was still working. He had a pit&#8211;lads club of 60 members, was superintendent of a Sunday School, and now regularly carried on a children's service. He had long cherished the ambition to be Ordained. I accepted him provisionally, on condition that he read under K.'s<persName xml:id="62"></persName> direction for a year. Then, if he made good progress, &amp; K. reported favourably, he should be ordained.</p>
         <p>Next I attended a meeting of the Committee of this precious "Retreat House" which that pious fool Lomax<persName xml:id="5279"></persName> has got together. I told them bluntly that I didn't approve the appeal, &amp; couldn't trust the scheme. It would bring the mischief of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" into the diocese: &amp; make trouble in the future. There was a lively discussion: &amp; it became clear that there was a deep cleavage between the members of the Committee – some having in view an Anglo&#8211;Catholic venture, some aiming at little more than a Diocesan Retreat&#8211;House … with no resident warden. I said that if they made proposals for the latter, I would consider them. Then I retired from the meeting and returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>