<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is not an accident that absolute nationalism came to its climacteric in Germany, where Protestantism began. For Protestantism, without ever intending it, as an unexpected by&#8211;product of its fight for spiritual liberty, helped to break up Western Europe into nations, where nationalism absorbed the loyalty of the people. And now that little tiger&#8211;cub we helped to rear has become a great beast, &amp; its roaring shakes the earth.</p>
         <p>v. Fosdick l.c. 182</p>
         </div>
         <p>The weather was mild: the sun shone benignantly: there was a feeling of spring in the air.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to <hi rend="underline">Sadberge</hi>, picking up J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in Darlington. I instituted the new Rector, Williams; and the Archdeacon inducted him. Several neighbouring incumbents attended the service. The parish church is a mean modern building infamously ventilated. I was nearly asphyxiated, I returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Neville Talbot</hi>, the Bishop of Pretoria, sends me a book that he has just published called "<hi rend="underline">The Returning Tide of Faith</hi>". It is described on the cover as "a complete statement of the Christian Faith in a form which is not only arresting &amp; practical, but entirely intelligible to the non&#8211;theological reader". Well, well!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>