<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ash Wednesday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A heavy fall of snow during the night had covered the country with a pall of white. Snow fell during the day, but melted as it fell. In the evening there was a tendency to slush. </p>
         <p>I worked at the Edinburgh Article. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lighton from Ross lunched here, and viewed the house. He, poor man, is quite blind: she is a Dutch woman. I motored to Darlington, and met <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who returned from witnessing Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> enthronement in Gloucester Cathedral.</p>
         <p>Macmillan's sent me a considerable volume of "Anglican Essays", designed apparently as a counter&#8211;blast to the Anglo&#8211;Catholics. Its sub&#8211;title runs thus, "A collective Review of the principles and special opportunities of the Anglican Communion as Catholic and Reformed." It includes a series of "Extracts from the pastorals of the late Bishop Jayne." That prelate had an interesting history, for he developed out of Tractarianism into a position which might be described as liberal evangelicalism. His successor in the see of Chester will hardly welcome this volume, for he has made himself rather prominent as a patron and exponent of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Movement. Bishop Paget is handicapped by a narrow tradition and a "suffragette" wife! It requires all his considerable qualities of character and temper to outweigh these disadvantages.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>