<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Lord, we pray thee mercifully to receive the prayers of thy people which call upon thee; and grant that they may both perceive and know what things they ought to do, and also may have grace and power faithfully to fulfil the same; through Jesus Chris our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>This beautiful collect is taken from the Gregorian Sacramentary, compiled probably by Alcuin, and supposed to represent a revision &amp; reorganisation of the rite affected by Gregory the Great (590&#8211;604). Thus it derives from the age which witnessed the birth of English Christianity. It runs thus:</p>
         <p>Vota quoesumus domine supplicantis populi celesti pietate prosequere: ut et quoe agenda sunt videant: et ad implenda que viderint convalescant. Per dominum.</p>
         <p>The English collect expands as well as translates the Latin. Which is really the better devotional quality – terseness or rhythmical charm? It is a perfect prayer for the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> Sunday in the New Year. "<hi rend="underline">Show thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto thee</hi>". In Church and State, in the diocese and in the home, the outlook is extraordinary perplexing &amp; minatory. "If Thy Presence go not with me: carry me not up hence." It is at these times, the turning points of life, that the idispensableness of Religion discloses itself. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p>We motored to Durham, &amp; attended service in the cathedral. I preached to a very small congregation, and afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion. There were about a score of communicants. The beautiful musical service was transacted in an empty church. It is quite plain to me that this Choral Eucharist must either develop into "the Mass", or be given up altogether. It is really inconsistent with the Anglican doctrine of the Eucharist. Those who desire the Choral Celebration as "the principal service on the Lord's Day" are fanatically insistent on "fasting Communion", &amp; therefore will not communicate after breakfast: those who disregard that rule, &amp; are ready to communicate, would greatly prefer Mattins! We lunched with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>. Judge Moore and his wife were there, and Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> &amp; his wife. I attended Evensong, and pronounced the Benediction from the Throne. Then we had tea with the Quirks<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, &amp; returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>