<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Cobb from Holy Trinity, Hartlepool, came to see me, &amp; stayed to lunch. I could but advise him to hold on for the present.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Hamsteels, where I dedicated a window to the memory of a deceased parishioner, and preached a sermon. The parson, Rust, has been there for 11 years. He is a married man with one eye, and an inconsequent manner. After tea at the Vicarage, (750 feet above sea&#8211;level, &amp; utterly wind&#8211;swept) we returned to Auckland. Incidentally I learned from old Firth, to whom I gave a 'lift' back to Esh, that on Christmas Day he had employed the man X, whom I prohibited from taking duty in the diocese. He said that his name had been given to him at the registry in Durham.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I finished </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Page's</hi><hi rend="italic"> "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Life and Letters</hi> <hi rend="italic">". It is a book of enthralling interest, and throws much light on the course of events through those terrible years. If only we had such an Ambassador now! The Americans seem about to repeat history. As they delayed their entrance into the War until the world had become immersed in the most frightful disasters, so now they are postponing their assistance to Europe in the matter of economic recovery until it is almost doubtful whether recovery is possible. '</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">Bis dat qui cito dat</hi> <hi rend="italic">' was never so true as it is now. Every day worsens the situation, and prolongs the agony of the nations.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>