<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Report of the Royal Commission on Ecclesiastical discipline (1906) arrived, and I spent much of the morning in reading it. There is a distinct historical value in this document as registering the stage of degeneration which the Church of England had reached before the War brought about the final catastrophe.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Lanchester, where I took part in the strangest War Memorial Dedication I have yet experienced<hi rend="italic">. </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">It was really the public glorification of the Sadlers and the Ritsons<persName xml:id="3822"></persName>, local employers who had promoted the memorial.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> The hall was crowded, and the platform presented a striking assemblage of dignitaries, among whom M</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Sadler (a quaintly brilliant lady who reminded me of the gipsy woman who commonly divides with the monkey the public interest in a street&#8211;organ) shone resplendent. The Chairman was her son, the Mayor of Middlesborough, &amp; enormously vain of the fact. His vulgarity was too ludicrous to be offensive. My prayer and dedication were as congruous with the proceedings as a Quaker at a public dance! We returned to the Castle in Durham, where I interviewed 3 young men, aspirants to Holy Orders. They all pleased me, though </hi> <hi rend="italic underline">none</hi> <hi rend="italic"> satisfy my requirements. However times are evil, &amp; bishops are human. My decisions were more creditable to my heart than to my head. I returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>