<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Lady Eden with her two sons &amp; Miss Prendergast her prospective daughter &#8211;in&#8211;law came to lunch. They were shown over the Castle. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked in the Park, where Beck distinguished himself by chasing the pit&#8211;ponies.</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> returned in the evening. He said that he had enjoyed himself, but I was surprised and distressed to learn that he had not attended any religious service. It is clear that neither the thought of duty nor the sentiment which clothes the last day of the year with a certain solemnity and fills the churches for "Watch Night Services" on New Year's Eve, had any weight with him. Possibly I don't myself realize how much his religious observance has been determined by the influences, personal and local, under which he is living here. When these are suspended even for a few days, he reverts &amp; reacts to the naked secularism which in the general habit of his class. He had read through 'Marmion', and even committed to memory (more or less) the lines about S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's post&#8211;mortem wanderings.</p>
         <p>A complete or perfect copy of the Loeb volume, Herodotus III, came this morning, &amp; I read again the famous narrative of Xerxes' invasion of Hellas, and the sublime episode of Thermopylae. I must try William with this, and observe how far he feels its power. There is a disconcerting 'matter&#8211;of&#8211;factness' about the modern youth, which closes their minds to the greater voices.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>January 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1923.</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Archbishop.</p>
         <p>I cannot rightly or reasonably decline the proposal which you are good enough to make since for some while past I have been pressing for an honest &amp; thorough re&#8211;examination of the whole question of our duty as Christians in this most difficult matter of the Marriage Law.</p>
         <p>If only the small Committee your Grace projects be composed of "men with open minds", I must needs think that its efforts could not be wholly fruitless. But men who think like the Bishop of Ely, or give final value to the <hi rend="underline">choses juge&#x00E9;s</hi> of the Western Church like our "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" are only wasting their own time &amp; befooling the Church by going through the hollow force of investigating a question which they have already and finally answered.</p>
         <p>I understand that <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and I are to have the pleasure of staying at Lambeth for the next meeting of the National Assembly. Your Grace may, perhaps, be able to find an opportunity of explaining a little more largely your own views of the range &amp; method of the Commission. I am sure you will not need my assurance that on this matter I desire to be of whatever service I can.</p>
         <p>I am, my dear Lord Archbishop,</p>
         <p>Always sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Archbishop of Canterbury. </p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>