<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A most beautiful bright day, though very cold. After breakfast, we motored to Penrith, where I preached the sermon on which I had bestowed so much labour. It fell very flat: indeed, I think, the congregation was mainly bored. But this did not much surprize me when I met the Vicar, a windy fellow of the advertising type supremely illustrated by the Bishop of London. He evidently disliked my assumption that all was not well with the Church of England. His method was that of a Canadian speculator in 'real estate' – to boost the county! After lunch we attended the public dedication of the local war&#8211;memorial, which took the form of a gate into the old Castle garden. The Bishop performed the function &#8211; I stood on the platform with a collection of civic notables: there was a large crowd, some speeches, a very cold wind, and the fainting of a young woman conspicuously. We had tea with an old clergyman, formerly Vicar of Penrith, Canon Mounington. Then we motored back to Rose Castle.</p>
         <p>I read the new number of the <hi rend="underline">Modern Churchman</hi>, which reports at some length the Heresy&#8211;Hunt which is now creating some sensation in American ecclesiastical circles. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> P. S. Grant, Rector of the Church of the Ascension, New York, who is the heretick, has compromised himself by marrying a divorced lady! His Bishop, Manning, is very forcible, and very feeble.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>