<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A telegram from the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi> arrived to the following effect:&#8211;"<hi rend="underline">Would you care very kindly write for us signed article on the general questions of preservation of historic dioceses like Winchester</hi>". A pre&#8211;paid form was enclosed. I wired an affirmative answer, &amp; forthwith wrote an article, &amp; sent it to the Editor with my compliments by express post. Then I fell to work on my Edinboro article. I was interrupted by Miss Coleman, who had a doleful tale to tell about the finances of the Rescue &amp; Preventive Association. I undertook to see the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and promised that the quiet day should be held here in the summer.</p>
         <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and I played bowls in the afternoon.</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Church Times'</hi> contains a long article on the Oxford Movement, which is now ninety years old. The author is a well&#8211;known Anglo&#8211;Catholic writer named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ollard</hi>. He pictures the movement as having been the fertile parent of everything that is best in modern England. His whole picture is almost grotesquely out of perspective.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Magee</hi> <hi rend="italic">, the son of the famous orator, died yesterday at the age of 53. He started as an Evangelical but developed into an extravagant Ritualist. </hi> <hi rend="italic underline">He nearly came to me as a curate in Barking, but D</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic underline"> Vaughan, under whom he was reading at the time, dissuaded him on the ground that I was too 'advanced' in my Churchmanship</hi> <hi rend="italic">!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>