<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[170]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I left the Castle at 8.10 a.m., and arrived at Murraythwaite about 12.45 a.m. We motored by way of Durham, Lanchester, Leadgate, Ebchester, Hexham. We found the mourners assembled – M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray<persName xml:id="666"></persName>, her 3 daughters, her son&#8211;in&#8211;law, Major Galbraith, Hugh Murray and Fletcher. The Presbyterian Minister, Knowles, and I conducted the service. The first part of the Burial Service was read from the porch, a numerous company of mourners being gathered in the courtyard. I read Wisdom iii. 1&#8211;9 as a lesson instead of 1. Cor XV. 20. Then we proceeded to 'Repentance', the burying –place of the Murrays, about 4 miles distant. I read the grave&#8211;side prayers, &amp; pronounced the Benediction, bare&#8211;headed in a biting Scottish wind. There was a numerous concourse of mourners, including the Duke of Buccleugh and a contingent of Freemasons. The service over we returned to Murraythwaite and had tea. Then we resumed our journey to Rose Castle, where we arrived about 6.30p.m. Chancellor Campbell and his wife were staying there. The household is composed of ladies, who earn their own living as domestic servants: and the situation thus created is not without difficultly, as may easily be imagined, but I was certainly impressed more favourably than I had thought possible. Before going to bed I had some talk with the Bishop over the course to be followed in the matter of Prayer Book Revision, when the House of Bishops meets on April 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>














