<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The proof of my Edinburgh Article arrived, from Cox</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> I frittered away my morning in writing letters. </p>
         <p>After lunch I walked in the Park with the dogs, and picked up three young men, all unemployed. They said that they had been idle since the strike. I took them into the Castle and showed them round. They were extremely well&#8211;mannered youths, but plainly being spoiled by protracted idleness. <hi rend="bold underline">Lomax<persName xml:id="5279"></persName> came to see me about his curate, Birney, whom he wants to keep, but will not pay adequately! I spoke rather decisively to him, using his own canting phrase, 'a living wage', and indicating that I thought he kept his curates in an unwholesome dependence upon himself.</hi> Brigstocke came to talk over his projected marginalisation of Horden. On the whole it seems best he should go. I motored him back to his parish, and then went on to Hartlepool, where I confirmed 115 persons, of whom no more than 39 were males. The old church was crowded. This is a good sign. After service I returned to Auckland, arriving a little before 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>The morning paper reported on the defeat at the polls of one minister: Stanley: the evening paper reported the defeat of another, Griffith Boscawen. This double disaster is a severe blow to the prestige of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bonar Law'</hi>s government. In both cases, the decisive factor is said to be the exasperation of the electorate at the failure of the Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> to solve the Housing problem. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>