<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[139]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I revised finally the Article, &amp; then sent it to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Cox</hi><persName xml:id="2131"></persName> with an explanatory letter. Then I wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury on the question of procedure in the House of Bishops.</p>
         <p>After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, where I had an interview with Jones, and Trotman (an Ordination candidate). Colonel Bowes came to see me about the affairs of C.F.B. I had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, &amp; then returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My decision in Jones's case was more merciful than defensible: but the pig&#8211;headed fellow doesn't realize the magnitude of the catastrophe in which his folly is plunging him. I gave him a month's grace. If he behaves himself, and obeys his Vicar: then he may continue in the parish. If, however, he fails to do so, he must not only be given the statutory notice, but his licence must be revoked. I wonder how far Jones is representative of the younger Anglo&#8211;Catholics</hi>.</p>
         <p>He exhibits a blending of Socialism and Socerdotalism, which is sufficiently arresting. The first contributes a complete contempt of authority; the last contributes an enormous arrogance. He repudiates all subordination: and claims a personal infallibility. And he is a very ignorant and inexperienced young man, emerging from a narrow home and a Nonconformist <hi rend="underline">milieu</hi>. The weakness of his Vicar has completed the mischief which these ill circumstances have fostered.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>