<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The warm weather continues. For a fortnight past the temperature has suggested the spring rather than mid&#8211;winter. The foolish birds, unable to resist the suggestion, singing and mating as if, not February but May were beginning. 'We shall pay for it presently' is the sombre comment of the experienced. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8a.m. Six of the household communicated, and among them William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Then I lay 'perdu' in my study , writing letters and reading Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> new book until lunchtime. I walked in the park with Beck and Cutty. The beauty and brightness of everything were wonderful.</p>
         <p>The two boys – Arthur Watts and Jack Lawrence – both but little over 13, and desirous to be confirmed. I asked them a few questions from the Catechism, and made them repeat the Creed. In my belief they would be better treated if their confirmation were postponed for another year or even longer. They are now only children, then they might be adolescent. However I promised to accept them as candidates. I read a good deal of Pusey's life – the disturbed period when there were many secessions to Rome, and much excitement in the country. Would it not have been more advantageous to the Church of England in the long run if Pusey and Keble followed Newman and Manning to Rome? </p>
         </body></text></TEI>