<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName> took me to see the amazing devices wireless telegraphy. I was actually placed in connection with Rome, &amp; heard the tapping of messages from the Eternal City. Then we called on an excellent Wesleyan &amp; Freemason, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alderman Thompson</hi>. He showed me a segment of a beam of timber, which though sound enough on the outside was completely honeycombed by some destructive wood&#8211;insect within. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The timber&#8211;merchant in Finland, gambling on the chance of the cargo being sunk by the Germans, had not scrupled to send the worthless timber</hi> <hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic"> The consignment had, however, arrived: the fraud had been discovered: &amp; the fraudulent trader condemned to heavy payments.</hi></p>
         <p>At 3.30 p.m. I preached in the Wesleyan Chapel on the occasion of its Jubilee Celebration. There was a considerable congregation, mostly of middle&#8211;aged and old people. <hi rend="bold underline">The young men and women are conspicuous by their absence.</hi> I wore my red robes, &amp; preached on Unity. It pleased me to see some of the parochial clergy in the congregation. At 7 p.m. the Mayor presided over a public meeting in the Chapel, and I spoke 'large' for 45 minutes! Then I recovered my bags, and was met by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> with the car. We motored back to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, where I arrived about 10 p.m., having completed a rather arduous round of engagements in Hartlepool.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>