<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant, we beseech thee, Almighty God, that we, who for our evil deeds do worthily deserve to be punished, by the comfort of thy grace may mercifully be relieved; through our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>From the Gregorian:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'<hi rend="underline">Concede quesumus, omnipotens deus: ut qui ex merito nostrae actionis affligimur: tuoe gratie consolatione respiremus. Per do</hi>.'</p>
         </div>
         <p>The English rendering "desire to be punished" has a sterner suggestion than the Latin: and "ex merito nostrae actionis" doesn't seem quite so severe as 'for our evil deeds deserve'. 'We who through our frailty and folly are sorely distressed' perhaps carries the sense. The prayer is rather an acknowledgement of our utter helplessness, &amp; dependence on God's merciful protection than an entreaty that we may be 'let off' the chastisement we merit, though the confession of fault and the prayer for forgiveness are included. But forgiveness does not properly imply remission of punishment, save in so far as being unforgiven <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> punishment. But the truly repentant sinner would give the best, perhaps the only adequate, evidence of his repentance by insisting on bearing the full penalty of his sin. And for this reason the penitent murderer is required to 'give himself up' to the justice of the Law, which will send him to the gallows. Can it be otherwise with reference to the Divine Justice?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. I remained in my study reading and writing until lunch&#8211;time. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Cockfield, and there I confirmed 62 candidates. Of these no more than 22 were males. Nevertheless I was pleased with this confirmation. The church was crowded with a very attentive congregation, and the candidates carried themselves very reverently. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Bishop Middleham, where I preached at Evensong to a crowded congregation. The coughing during the lessons was so clamourous, that I had to interpose a protest. This was so far effective that I had nothing to complain of during the sermon. The parish church is a commodious building of the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century but ruthlessly restored. The Vicar, (Rev. W. G. Davison) was for five years at Allahabad, and then Curate at Holy Trinity, Darlington. He is a small mild man with a supplicating manner. We returned to Auckland immediately after the service.</p>
         <p>I read the four lectures, 'A century of Anglican Theology in relation to the general movement of European Thought', delivered to Clergy in the Diocese of Oxford in 1921, and published in the 'Modern Churchman'. They are interesting and suggestive, but far too generous to the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholic' movement, of which he regards Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> as the principal spokesman, and which he pictures as standing 'in the succession of the Christian Socialists, of Maurice &amp; Kingsley &amp; Westcott, as well as of the Tractarians'. This seems to be Shebbeare's<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> position.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>