<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I rewrote the concluding part of the Sunderland Sermon and made an abbreviated copy, which I sent to the Editor of the "Yorkshire Post". The Editor of the "Newcastle Journal" wrote to ask for a copy of the sermon, and enclosed a stamped envelope. Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> made a copy, which was sent to him. I wrote to Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> appointing a special psalm (46<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) and lessons – Ezekiel. Xxxvii 15&#8211;23 &amp; Galatians v.13&#8211;26. This arrangement will shorten the service, and tend to give its special character emphasis. It will also allow me more "elbow&#8211;room" in the pulpit.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> after lunch. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had a rather crowded tea&#8211;table: among her guests were the Pembertons<persName xml:id="2837"><persName xml:id="2843"></persName></persName>. Ella and I motored to Durham, and dined at the Castle, where the Ellershaws<persName xml:id="3459"><persName xml:id="3460"></persName></persName> celebrated the coming of age of their son. I had some talk with him about the prospects of the college. They are certainly not bright. There will be only 21 students in residence next term. Two years ago there were 60. The competition of Oxford and Cambridge is destructive. And while the numbers fall, the quality falls off.</p>
         <p>This must mean a very difficult financial situation, which, taken in conjunction with the necessity of undertaking costly work on the Castle, forms a practical problem, of which it is not easy to perceive the solution.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>