<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>A pastor is the Deputy of Christ for the reducing of Man to the Obedience of God. This definition is evident, and contains the direct steps of pastoral duty and authority.</p>
         <p>George Herbert</p>
         </div>
         <p>I worked at the "Charge" for the Ordination candidates.</p>
         <p>Wright, now vicar&#8211;designate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary Magdalen, Sunderland, came to dine &amp; sleep bringing with him a young Cantabrigian named Daly, who looks forward to ordination presently. I had some talk with Wright, who is a man of some strength of character, and pronounced (though not 'extreme') Anglo&#8211;Catholic opinions. He gives an ill account of the state of things in his old parish of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Francis, South Shields, where the "loyal" company of "Catholic" laymen have been dispersed by his successor, and have found a spiritual refuge in S. Mark's &amp; S. Mary's, Tynedock. Warner, the said successor, gives the impression of being absorbed in the single ambition of getting a Vicarage built for his own use, an object which, though harmless &amp; even laudable, does not wake enthusiasm in the people, who appear to see in it only the assurance of his continuance in the parish! Is there any church in Christendom so embarrassed by discordant conceptions of Christianity as the Church of England?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>