<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I motored to Whitburn, &amp;, after lunching with the Rector, officiated at the funeral of old Victor Williamson. The ashes of the cremated body were interred in the family vault. I used the Prayer&#8211;book service with alteration. Old Canon Hopkinson read the lesson, and the Rector the prayers. I took the service at the grave&#8211;side. A good number of Freemasons, including Lord Ravensworth<persName xml:id="3719"></persName>, attended. After tea with the family, I returned to the Castle. A copy of the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Manchester Guardian</hi>" was sent to me. It contained a letter under the heading of "<hi rend="underline">The Bishop of Durham and Continuity</hi>". The anonymous writer sets in contrast a passage from the Sunderland sermons and an extract from a paper which I read at the Manchester Church Congress in 1908; they appear effectively irreconcilable. I wrote a short reply pointing out that the discord was only apparent, and taking occasion to say that the sermon was being printed so that people interested in the subject could read it as a whole. I suppose this is the type of attack which I must expect to experience. In the course of nearly 40 years of public life one has said much, &amp; written much, which has passed wholly out of one's memory, &amp; may lend itself to uses which one did not contemplate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>