<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sykes</hi><persName xml:id="3470"></persName> sends me a pleasant little letter, thanking me for the sermon, which, he thinks, "will do a good deal of good". I prepared notes for this afternoon, and then motored into Durham, where, first, I called on Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName>, and made the necessary arrangements for the Visitation. I shall be fortunate if the expenditure does not exceed &#x00A3;150. Next, I went to the Castle and licensed six curates, including young Westcott<persName xml:id="5385"></persName>. Then we lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. After lunch we motored to Tanfield where I instituted Pestle<persName xml:id="5238"></persName> to that Vicarage. There was a full church, a considerable attendance of the adjacent clergy, and a reverent service. After tea in the schoolroom, we returned to Auckland, arriving a little after 6.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>That vivacious young egotist, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Webb</hi>, has married, and now calls herself M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Valentine Carlyle. She and her husband (a thin, mild, silent man) came here for the night.</p>
         <p>It appears from the letters that have reached me that reports of the Sunderland sermon appeared in the '<hi rend="underline">Westminster Gazette'</hi>, and in the "<hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi>". The Vicar of Downside writes inquiring where he can obtain a complete copy of the sermon. He, poor man, is hedged in by Papists. They are, he says, "in this parish numerous &amp; powerful &amp; wealthy. They have an abbey, &amp; a large school for boys, &amp;c., &amp;c. <hi rend="underline">I find the report of your sermon distinctly helpful and encouraging"</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>