<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">I think it very important to insist that the world as known to science is just as much a kingdom of values as the world known to religion. The difficulty is that the values are not the same.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">W. R. Inge<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. August, 1924.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>I left mine host's house in good time to catch the train, which Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> had appointed for me, but when I arrived at the station, I learned that the time&#8211;table had been changed last Saturday &amp; my train was "off". So I kicked my heels for more than an hour at Leeds before starting for York by a slow train. There another delay of half&#8211;an&#8211;hour, &amp; then another slow train to Darlington, where I arrived at 1.40 p.m., &amp; found Leng with the car.</p>
         <p>I corrected the proofs of the Sunderland Sermon, &amp; returned them to the printers.</p>
         <p>Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, who had been engaged at Eldon in instituting Greenway, the new Vicar, dined here, &amp; I had some talk with Knight about diocesan matters.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Anson Phelps Stokes<persName xml:id="1565"></persName> answering his enquiry about the charlatan parson, Fearn, and to Nicholas Murray Butler, thanking him for his anti&#8211;Prohibitionist paper. Also I wrote to inquire of his former vicar what might be the character of Mack.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>