<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The clocks were put back last night, so that we had an hour of broad daylight in bed before getting up. I read Trevelyan's 'Early years of Charles James Fox', &amp; was more than ever impressed by the author's combination of literary power, &amp; relentless partisanship. He seems quite unable to understand how offensive the assumption of a monopoly of patriotism, wisdom, &amp; virtue by the grasping and arrogant clique which George III broke up, must needs be to any candid &amp; considering man. It enables me to understand better than before the mental agony &amp; moral abasement which Trevelyan must have felt when for a brief space he was carried away from his party allegiance by Gladstone's Irish policy. To him, &amp; men of his type, political party has all the authority which a Catholic acknowledges in the Church, and a Protestant in the Bible.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. All our guests attended and communicated. They went away shortly after 10 a.m. to attend services in Durham Cathedral, &amp; then to go back to Murraythwaite.</p>
         <p>I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>: to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Thomas Reed thanking him for his gift of the reproduction of the Lindisfarne Gospels: and to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> de Cowrey Hamilton acknowledging receipt of his poem.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to Long Newton, where I read the lessons &amp; preached.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>