<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I read before the arrival of my tea the book of the <hi rend="underline">Confessions</hi> in which <hi rend="doubleunderline">S. Augustine</hi> describes the spiritual crisis in which he was "converted". Nothing could have been more gradual and deliberate than his passage from Manichaeism to the Catholic Church. The last phase had been prepared for by years of thought and conflict. And no doubt it was the same with his great master S. Paul. There is really nothing sudden in religion. Always there has been a <hi rend="underline">preparatis evangelica</hi>, though the man himself may hardly have been conscious of it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I left the Castle at 9.20 a.m., &amp; motored to <hi rend="underline">South Shields</hi> (32 miles), where I preached, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. There was a fair congregation &amp; perhaps as many as 60 communicants. The curate, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Griffiths</hi>, read Mattins very well, but I fear his voice is too weak for that church. We returned to the Castle after the service.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I stayed in my study, &amp; read a very interesting book by a Dutch Professor, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Huizinga</hi> on <hi rend="underline">"The Waning of the Middle Ages, a study of the forms of life, thought, and Art in France &amp; the Netherlands in the XIV</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> and XV</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> centuries".</hi> Also I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.</p>
         <p>After dinner I read aloud <hi rend="doubleunderline">Froude's</hi><persName xml:id="1409"></persName> account of the Oxford Movement.</p>
         <p>The weather was dull, misty, and wet all day long.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>