<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I received another letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. He has started work in Johannesburg, and is evidently feeling rather home&#8211;sick. And the work he is doing, as he describes it, sounds rather formidable. I wrote to him at once, as more than 3 weeks must elapse before a letter can reach him.</p>
         <p>The Murray&#8211;Smiths left after breakfast. He is most taciturn, and she is the most talkative of people. Possibly the two facts are not unconnected.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName>, and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> motored to Hexham, where they lunched. Fearne went on to Murraythwaite for a visit, and the others, after seeing the church and making some calls, returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>One of my principal pleasures in having <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ruth Spooner</hi><persName xml:id="2161"></persName> in my house is to hear her play the piano, which she does to admiration. But the absence of light makes it impossible to use the State Room, where is the piano. The workmen have started to lay the cable, and I am assured that the light will be available for the Ordination Candidates when they arrive on Thursday, but, after my experience of the men's delays, I dare not allow myself any confident expectation that their undertaking will "materialise". However, in the words of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Asquith, we must "wait and see"!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>