<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I prepared some notes for my opening address, &amp; then we started for Lumley Castle, where the Fête for the County Nursing Association was timed to begin at noon. The function of declaring the Fête open was held in the Great Hall. Lord Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3465"></persName> presided, &amp; made quite a good little speech. Then I spoke, &amp; there followed the usual votes of thanks. After this we had lunch, and then I returned to Auckland. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Roger Lumley</hi><persName xml:id="5410"></persName> and his wife were there. I was glad to make his acquaintance, as he is the heir–apparent. The weather improved as the day advanced.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, who had continued at the Fête all the afternoon, returned about 7 p.m., accompanied by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray, the two girls, and two young men. They stayed here for the night.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is difficult, increasingly difficult, successfully to harmonize private life and public life. In the case of most men the two things are held apart. There is the home in one place, and the office in another, and each has its appropriate activities and associations. Only in the case of the bishop, (and in lesser degree the parish priest) are the two combined in a single place. The Castle or Palace is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">both</hi> <hi rend="italic">the Bishop's home </hi><hi rend="italic underline">and </hi><hi rend="italic">his office. Here he entertains his friends, and here he receives his visitors, interviews his clergy, and transacts his business. If he be married a new &amp; formidable factor, which may be very disturbing, is brought into the problem.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>