<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I prepared an address for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Institution</hi> tomorrow, and <hi rend="bold underline">put the finishing touches to the Sunderland sermon</hi>. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham where, after vainly calling on Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName>, I went to Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> house and talked over diocesan business with him. After lunching there, we went to the Chapter House, where I presided over a special meeting of the <hi rend="bold underline">Diocesan Conference.</hi> The business was mostly formal, but a motion to give general approval to the Pension Scheme, introduced to the Church Assembly by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Phillimore</hi><persName xml:id="1940"></persName>, opened the floodgates of clerical eloquence. However, after I had summed up in a short speech, the motion was carried unanimously. There followed a meeting of the Board of Finance, and then another board. We returned to the Castle in time for a late tea.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After dinner, I read aloud to the ladies the sermon in answer to the Cardinal which I propose to preach tomorrow. It took 31 minutes, which means at least 45 minutes in delivery</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Then I wrote to my Godson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert Simpson</hi><persName xml:id="554"></persName>, and sent him a copy of my H. of L. speech, and the sermon to the Liverpool sectaries.</p>
         <p>I wrote a letter of condolence to the Vicar of Stanley, Crook, old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wilson, whose wife died this morning. Also, I wrote to Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> of Stanhope, advising him to have a curate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>