<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There is no form of personal example more sure to be observed and copied than that which a political leader presents to the younger portion of his followers.</p>
         <p>Trevelyan's Charles James Fox. P.79.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Northern Echo</hi><hi rend="italic">" gives great prominence to yesterday's sermon, and sets it out fairly enough, (though emphasizing rather excessively the severer portions) but for one very unfortunate blunder in what might perhaps be called the crucial passage. Where I wrote "We reply that our ecclesiastical identity consists in other and more fundamental matters", the report makes me say "in other than fundamental matters" which makes nonsense of the argument. The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">" has about 3/4 of a column on its front page, &amp; the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic">" has 2/3</hi><hi rend="i sup u">s</hi> <hi rend="italic">of a column. The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Newcastle Daily Chronicle</hi><hi rend="italic">" printed the sermon almost in full. What the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Sunderland Echo</hi><hi rend="italic">" has done I don't yet know.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Colonel Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> with his wife and brother, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Pilkington</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to lunch, and afterwards viewed the Castle. Then I took them in to Durham, and showed them the Castle &amp; the Cathedral. We returned to Auckland for tea, after which they took their departure.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The weather worsened steadily as the day advanced, and, as evening drew on, became wet and blustering. Much of the harvest is yet in the fields.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>