<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The papacy contrived murder and massacre on the largest and also the most cruel and inhuman scale. They were not only wholesale assassins, but they made the principle of assassination a law of the Christian Church and a condition of salvation.</p>
         <p>L<hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi>Acton to Lady Blennerhasselt: Feb. 1879.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Canon Brown writes to say that Cardinal Bourne's attack is "the culmination of propaganda which has been active for some time. It has now gained public attention and seriously disquieted Church people". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I told him that I would speak on the subject next Sunday</hi><hi rend="italic">. All day long I worked at a sermon but to no satisfactory result. The truth is that I don't want a controversy with the Papists: &amp; I want so to speak as to prevent one developing out of this mannerless attack of the Cardinal.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Bury</hi><hi rend="italic"> sent me a shambling kind of apology for the outrageous article in his "official gazette".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I played bowls after lunch.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kőrsteiner, &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> motored to Muggleswick and lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Poole. The day was brilliant though a touch of autumn was in the air.</p>
         <p>The MS. of the Charge was sent off to Hodder &amp; Stoughton duly registered. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>