<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Without commerce and industry there can be no middle class: where you had no middle class, you had no Renaissance and no Reformation. We find two examples in Poland and Spain.</p>
         <p>v. Pollard. Factors in Modern History p.41</p>
         </div>
         <p>Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hodder &amp; Stoughton are evidently perplexed as to the nature of a charge: but they write civilly enough, &amp; I suppose they must print the thing, though they can't get it out as soon as I expected.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi rend="italic"> has been the central figure in a Roman demonstration in Sunderland designed apparently to undo the effect of the Anglican celebration of the 1250</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> anniversary of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Benedict Biscop's</hi><persName xml:id="5320"></persName><hi rend="italic"> foundation at Monkwearmouth. His Eminence was in a combative mood, &amp; allowed himself to speak with small courtesy of Anglicans, even using the word "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">impertinence</hi><hi rend="italic">" of their claim to continuity with the pre&#8211;Reformation Church. I was turning over in my mind whether, as Bishop, I ought not to acquiesce in this attack, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">when a direct appeal to me to do so came from one of the clergy</hi><hi rend="italic"> – Knight<persName xml:id="4092"></persName> of Ryhope.</hi></p>
         <p>Somebody at Columbia University, New York, has sent me a copy of an Address of Nicholas Murray Butler (Apr. 29, 1924) entitled "Prohibition is now a Moral Issue". It is an extremely fierce denunciation of Prohibition as breeding vice, drunkenness &amp; lawlessness throughout the community.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>