<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I had a letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, reporting his safe arrival at Cape Town. He writes cheerfully, and is evidently looking forward to work in Johannesberg.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Churchwardens of Bishopwearmouth write to ask that last Sunday's sermon may be printed. I wrote consenting, and saying that I would add to it the earlier sermon preached on June 29</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> at Monkwearmouth</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Then I wrote to Hugh Rees, asking him to undertake the printing.</hi></p>
         <p>Lord Forester writes to tell me that he will move a resolution expressing regret at the decision of the Church Assembly giving approval to the measure for dividing the Bpk. of Hereford, and asking for "hints". I wrote to him.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The 'Sunderland Echo' prints the sermon in extenso</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shebbeare</hi><persName xml:id="5363"></persName> came to see me, &amp; we had an hour's rather painful conversation. I spoke to him very frankly, but of course, I cannot solve the financial problem. I walked round the Park with the dogs, and on my return to the Castle entertained two ladies – Miss Mowbray &amp; Miss Thompson – to tea.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Philps, Brown, and Drury write to ask that the sermon may be published</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Old Victor Williamson of Whitburn has died at the age of 87. He was Dean Stanley's<persName xml:id="505"></persName> friend and executor.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>