<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The Fiery Cross movement seems <hi rend="underline">almost</hi> idolatrous – and shows what the Party is out for i.e. a drastic and truculent propaganda. Our late Bishop – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Woods</hi> – would (I think) have taken part of it. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> will not. People turn out to see these shows in the spirit in which they would turn out to see a travelling circus: the religious impression is nil".</p>
         </div>
         <p>So writes <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName> in a letter received this morning. </p>
         <p>I spent the morning in finishing the address on Sermons for the Ordination candidates: &amp; (the weather becoming very wet and blustering) I wrote letters &amp; read during the afternoon. At 5.30 p.m. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I left the Castle, and motored to Durham, where we had tea with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, &amp; then went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's for the Institution &amp; Induction of the new Rector. In spite of the weather there was a fair congregation. Two former Rectors – Robson &amp; Watson – were present. Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName> carried himself like a sincere man, and the general impression of the service was hopeful. We returned to Auckland as soon as the service was over. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> has a considerable letter in the <hi rend="underline">Times.</hi> He is very much in evidence just now. Is the <hi rend="underline">'Times'</hi> running him for the Primacy? Well, there might be worse things, though I would rather see him at London. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>