<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">The Archbishop of Canterbury</hi><hi rend="italic"> wrote civilly about my sermon, which he had read "with keen interest". He asked for references on some points which I sent him forthwith.</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ruth</hi><persName xml:id="2161"></persName><hi rend="italic"> wrote a characteristic letter, very flatteringly phrased: and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName><hi rend="italic"> applied to me a description of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic">Wilfrid which he had found in some papist "Lives of the Saints" – "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">a quick walker, expert at all good works, &amp; never a sour face</hi><hi rend="italic">"! The proofs of my "primary charge" began to arrive, &amp; I wasted much time in revising them.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I walked in the Park after lunch. The brilliance of the day showed the autumnal colour to perfection.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Faith&#8211;healing Mission at Bradford began yesterday, and is reported at some length in the newspapers. One old woman is alleged to have been cured of rheumatoid arthritis, but the Vicar of Bradford is reported to have gone into hospital for an operation for appendicitis. The inevitable consequence of associating "mental healing" with Religion is that no limit can be placed to the healing claim. For the Divine power is infinite: &amp; Faith brings no lesser force into operation. The New Testament credits our Saviour with unlimited healing power and if it is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">His</hi><hi rend="italic"> ministry of healing which is now being revived, the attempt to distinguish between one kind of disease and another is disallowed.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>