<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The papists were highly offended, when they saw such an express declaration made against the real presence: and the duke told me, that when he asked Sheldon how they came to declare against a doctrine, which he had been instructed was the doctrine of the church, Sheldon answered, Ask Gauden<persName xml:id="5412"></persName> about it, who is a bishop of your own making: for the king had ordered his promotion for the service he had done.</p>
         <p>Burnet. History of his own Time. vol. I. p.333</p>
         </div>
         <p>The "Black Rubric" was evidently taken to mean something in the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century: and the Duke of York's interest in it indicates that then, as now, the controversy with the Papists was handled in diverse &amp; contradictory manners by the Anglican parties. Gauden's "service" was, of course, his composition of "Eikon Basilike".</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, plainly disclosing my anxiety as to his capacity to "make good", and describing the unpromising state of the "labour – market" in this country. Also I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and sent him a copy of the Sunderland Sermon.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The publisher writes to say that the Sunderland Sermon needs to be reprinted, as the first issue is nearly sold out</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>I remained all day in my room with a most evil &amp; degenerating throat, which, in view of my commitments tomorrow is sufficiently disconcerting.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>