<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and, after reading the papers and answering me my letters, made notes for the Bishops' meeting. Colonel Burdon behaves badly, for he need not have been driven to offer Horden to a deacon since I had suggested to him Lister the curate of Tanfield. Now, I fear, our relations will be more difficult than ever. After lunching in the Club, I walked to Lambeth, where I spent the afternoon at a <hi rend="bold underline">Bishops' Meeting</hi>. The loquacity of the two English Primates waxes continually, and when the platform rhetoric of the Bishop of London is added, the pace at which the agenda are disposed of becomes woefully slow. The Bishop of Bradford, in bringing forward the subject of 'clergy undertaking holiday duty' disclosed a paucity of clergy in his diocese which was quite as bad as that which afflicts us in Durham: and other Northern bishops gave the like testimony for their own dioceses. The Bishop of Newcastle made an appearance to the general surprise, for he was thought to be "done". I found him, however, very slow and sleepy when I talked with him: and he took no part whatever in the discussion. Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> was present, but I had no speech with him. I walked back to the Club, and there dined alone. After which I returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>