<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The morning post brought me cheerful letters from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and Frank, which relieved an anxiety which had been growing in mind. When a young man throws up his work in England, and goes to a distant colony to seek his fortunes, he must either "make good" or fail utterly.</p>
         <p>I motored in to Durham with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and attended the High Sherriff's luncheon, where I proposed his health in a more than commonly fatuous speech. But these little "side&#8211;talks" are the snares of the devil. Then we went on to West Hartlepool. I went to Grey's ship yard, and was shown over it by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maurice Gibb</hi>. He says that a certain amount of work has now come in, so that, of their normal staff of 2000, 1100 are at work. But for 3 years no dividend has been paid, and there is small probability of any being paid in the near future. This creates a situation of much difficulty for the new Baronet, who succeeds to a great property and no cash! W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Gray, Macdonald, and I had an early dinner with Gibb: and then I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James', &amp; instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prideaux</hi><persName xml:id="3181"></persName> to the Vicarage. There was a considerable congregation. After the service, we returned to Auckland arriving about 9.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>