<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I left the castle at 9.15 a.m., and motored to Sunderland, where I arrived in excellent time for Mattins in Christ Church at 10.30 a.m. There was considerable congregation, but the church was not crowded. I preached the sermon on the subject, which the unexpected announcement of a general election had rendered almost 'topical', of 'the Christian's civic duty'. After lunching with Canon and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> McCullagh, I went to Christ Church again at 3 p.m. and <hi rend="bold underline">preached to a great gathering of Freemasons. The appearance of a masonic congregation is not improved by the admixture of women, but this admixture is none the less becoming common</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> After this service, I went on to Bishopwearmouth Rectory, and had tea with Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>. Then I motored to Castletown, a mining parish on the outskirts of Sunderland, where I preached at Evensong. The parish is stated to contain 5000 people, but the little parish church only accommodates 300. It was on this occasion well filled, but I got the impression that the church was on a very small scale in that population. The parson, the Rev. H. E. Clark, seemed rather a feeble disheartened creature, handicapped by a slight stammer. However appearances are not always trustworthy. After the service I returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>