<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is certainly one of the greater privileges of a man's life that in early manhood he should have been brought under the influence &amp; into the familiar knowledge of a really distinguished man. Nothing else so effectively preserves from conceit in youth, and from cynicism in later life. Listening to their talk about Bishop Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName>, I found myself enjoying Baillie and Eden, for </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">my strange career never included the knowledge, intimate and continued, of a great man, and I feel that many of its worst mistakes have grown from that fact</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Lightfoot</hi><hi rend="italic"> loved you: </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="1047"></persName><hi rend="italic"> thought you a very interesting specimen</hi> <hi>–</hi> <hi rend="italic">thus the two great bishops were distinguished by their disciples.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I left Lambeth after breakfast, leaving my bag with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to be left at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and then went to Adeney &amp; tried on my overcoat. I went to Hodder &amp; Stoughton, and had some talk with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Arthur Hird who is in charge of the theological department. He was very communicative and spoke freely of Sydney Dark<persName xml:id="5418"></persName>, the new editor of the "Church Times," who does indeed, appear to be a cynically incredulous type of "Catholick". I caught the 1.40 p.m. train, and arrived at Auckland about 8 p.m.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>