<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I attended the Conference on "Disinterested management" organized by the 'True Temperance Association' at Donnington House, Strand, at 11 a.m., &amp; sate on until 1 p.m. Lord Plymouth<persName xml:id="5419"></persName> presided. Lord Salvesen<persName xml:id="5420"></persName> spoke, &amp; I made a brief foolish speech. The rest were trivial.</p>
         <p>After lunching at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I returned to the Deanery in time to read through my sermon before going with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> to Christ Church Vicarage. Here I met divers sectaries who were to take part in the service. In spite of the rain, which descended with a pertinacity worthy even of Baxter, there was a considerable congregation. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Eyres read a lesson; D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott Lidgett prayed; Hine Haycock<persName xml:id="122"></persName> read the prayers; &amp; I preached the sermon. The sermon took at least 40 minutes to deliver: &amp; once or twice moved the hearers to audible laughter! It was closely listened to, &amp; was much praised in the vestry! I gave the MS to Scott Lidgett, on the chance that it might go into the 'Contemporary'. A young man came to me, &amp; announced himself as M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Chesney. I could not recall in the hard–bitten man of 30, the small chorister of 12! After dining with Kitty at the Deanery, I drove to King's Cross, &amp; took train for York. Leaving at 8.25 p.m., I arrived at 12.59 a.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>