<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I think it is through insincerity in utterance that the Churches and clergies have lost credit. They are suspected of saying one thing and thinking another, not exactly with a conscious mendacity, but with a subconscious equivocation. I think it is the need and desire of saying the orthodox thing that leads to a certain inward insincerity or lack of open&#8211;mindedness, i.e. they force themselves to think what they feel they ought to say.</p>
         <p>Father Tyrrell<persName xml:id="1084"></persName> (v. Life.ii.vol).</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop beyond all others must feel "the need and desire of saying the orthodox thing", and more than the rest is compelled to say it.</hi> For his official duty carries him into situations where he must speak, and where, unless he speak after an orthodox fashion, the whole purpose of his speaking will be defeated. For instead of edifying and unifying, he will exasperate &amp; divide the people.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Accordingly, it has come to be the case, that of all declarations of men in authority those of bishops are least impressive. Even when they are thought to be sincere, they are seen to be inevitable, and felt to be calculated. This obligation at all hazards to bury the man in the office is the worst shadow on the bishop's lot.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote letters, and cleared up my study before going into Durham for the business of the Ordination. Also, I took the dogs around the park after lunch. An excellent enlarged photograph of Cosin's portrait in the State Room arrived.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> came with me into Durham in order to attend the School&#8211;concert. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to see me at 6 p.m. about the Monkheseldon Commission which was conducted rather cavalierly by the Ecclesiastical Commission's representative. When he had gone, it was time for Evensong in the Chapel, when Stephenson gave an address. It was extremely simple, but effective by reason of the man's evident goodness. Then we had dinner in the Hall – 15 candidates, Stephenson, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and myself. We conversed humanely. After dinner Stephenson came to my room and discussed with me (a) the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" tendencies of Gwilliam (b) the case of the curate, Peel: and (c) the question of the future of the Durham School Mission. At 9.45 p.m. there was compline in the Chapel, and then I retired to my room, there to indulge the mood of historical reminiscence until I turned into my bed. The weather continues warm, windy, and wet.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>