<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I perceive, that because it is taken for a shame, to doubt of our Christianity and the Life to come, this hindereth many from uttering their doubts, who never get them well resolved, but remain half Infidels within, whilst the Ensigns of Christ are hanged without: and need much help, though they are ashamed to tell their needs: and prudent Charity will relieve those who are ashamed to beg'.</p>
         <p>Richard Baxter. Reasons of the Christian Religion.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Prime Minister forces the pace. Parliament is already at an end, and the voting for its successor is fixed for October 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>! This is the very day on which I had arranged to deliver my Primary Charge in the Cathedral! I motored to Durham, and saw Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName> about postponing the visitation until November 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> &amp; 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Willie Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName><hi rend="italic"> sends me his new book, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Christus Veritas</hi><hi rend="italic">", which is the theological epilogue of his previous volume "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Mens Creatrix</hi><hi rend="italic">". It is impossible not to admire the industry, versatility and power which he displays.</hi></p>
         <p>I received from the Patronage Secretary inquiries about Watts of Shildon, and Hoyle of Blackhall Colliery: and I gave as favourable a report on both of them as in conscience I could.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>