<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I left the castle at 8 a.m., &amp; motored to Darlington, where I took train for London. On arrival I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; then to the hairdresser. I walked to Westminster, and took the oath in the House of Lords. The speaker came to the bar of the House, &amp; announced his election, which was confirmed by the Commissioners. A quaint ceremony which I was glad to witness. The Bishop of Hereford took his seat, being presented by the Bishops of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and Bristol. I had tea with Nickson at the House &amp; then went for a few minutes into the House of Commons, where the members were taking the oath in batches, as they were called up by the Speaker. I walked to the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum, &amp; had some talk with Sidney Lee about his life of Edward vii, which is nearing completion.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">He submits his proofs to His Majesty and Asquith.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> was in the Club. He expressed himself with</hi> some energy about the new canon (Donaldson) who appears to combine extreme Socialist opinions with a vehement insistence on what he supposes to be his claims! Then I made my way to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Deanery, where I was being entertained. Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> and Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> received me with the utmost kindness, and I dined pleasantly with them, going to bed early, as I was rather unusually fatigued.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>