<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I was engaged all the morning with two repulsive tasks: first, making income tax returns; next, with revising proofs. In the afternoon I had a little Committee meeting of the Archdeacon of Auckland<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, Parry&#8211;Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName>, &amp; Hodgson<persName xml:id="5274"></persName> to consider the state of Escomb Church. They stayed to tea, whereat came also Francis Priestman &amp; his wife. Our conversation took a turn which might have been edifying or exasperating to a violent "Labour" man like Hodgson!</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote to Willie Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>, thanking him for the gift of his book, "Christus Veritas", which I had finished reading. I took occasion to warn him that in my forthcoming charge, I should speak about "Copec"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>We gave a small dinner&#8211;party. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Forster, Olive<persName xml:id="1686"></persName> &amp; her husband, were the guests. In the drawing room Olive sang songs. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight told me that she had visited the prison in Durham on Sunday evening, and spent two hours with the prisoners, endeavouring to interest and edify them under the difficult condition that everything religious must be vigorously excluded! This strange rue expresses the anxiety of the prison authorities not to wound the feelings of Papists and Sectaries by impinging the grand principle of religious equality!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>