<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924., S. Luke's Day</hi></p>
         <p>The collect for this Festival was composed in 1549: and expanded but not improved in 1662.</p>
         <p>I received an intimation from S. Cuthbert's College, Ushaw, <hi rend="italic">that one </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">E. Towers</hi><hi rend="italic"> has written a pamphlet in answer to my "Reply" to Cardinal Bourne.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"It is my earnest hope that no trace of the odium theologian will be found in it. At any rate I can assure you that it has been written without a trace of bitterness or of unkind feeling towards your Lordship personally". If the author is as good as his word, he will inaugurate a new departure in Roman controversy!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Anson Phelps Stokes</hi><persName xml:id="1565"></persName> writes to me in defence of 'Prohibition', which he says 'would never have been thought of' but for 'the strong sentiment of a majority of the young leaders of the medical profession, who have become convinced of the ill effects of alcohol except when used under medical direction in relatively small does, or in the form of light wines or beers'. He adds an important observation:</p>
         <p>"It must also be remembered that we have never been a wine&#8211;drinking country. The evil in America has not come from wine. It has come from two factors: the saloon in politics, and the drinking of whiskey between meals". Both are certainly bad.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p>I walked in the Park with the dogs. The weather was absolutely still, but overcast and tending to rain. A football match was proceeding in the outer Park between S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's F. Club, and another club from the district. I talked with the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's goal keeper, a bright&#8211;looking lad named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ivan Thornton</hi>. In the Inner Park, the Barrington Boys were playing against Darlington School. A good many decent women with babies &amp; perambulators were comfortably "taking the air". I do not think the public has anything to gain by excluding the Bishop, except, perhaps, the sentimental satisfaction of removing from the social landscape the historic symbol of immemorial inequality. As I approached the Castle, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ashton</hi> emerged from the Chapel escorting a young man &amp; two females. The former he introduced as a police&#8211;constable from Sunderland. <hi rend="bold underline">He informed me himself that he was the last man to squeeze in to Bishopwearmouth Church, when I answered the Cardinal. He seems to have been greatly impressed by the sermon</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Meanwhile, I reflect on the widening breach between myself and my episcopal brethren on almost all the issues of the hour – the Enabling Act, "Copec", "Spiritual healing", Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, Liquor Restriction &amp;c. Indeed, there is hardly a single question on which I am in cordial agreement with the policy which commends itself to Lambeth and Bishopthorpe. What can be the outcome of such a state of things?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>