<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the parish church at 8 a.m. The church is just 100 years old. It replaced a medieval church, which was ruthlessly pulled down as being too small. The present building is equipped with galleries, and is destined to become the cathedral of the new Bishoprick of Blackburn. It accommodates about 2000 persons. I stayed in the Vicarage all the morning, and wrote to Ernest. At 2.30 p.m. I preached to a large assembly of men. Had the weather been more favourable the congregation would have been far larger. After service, many clergy &amp; others came to the Vicarage to meet me at tea. Among them was the Conservative member, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henn, and the Mayor, two intelligent &amp; interesting men, whom I was glad to talk with. The rain fell with increasing violence all the afternoon &amp; evening. Accordingly, the congregation at Evensong was not as great as had been anticipated. However the church was fairly filled, &amp; I preached on "Christian Citizenship". The attention was close, and well sustained. Several people came to supper: &amp; I talked more than was good for me. There seems to be a vigorous ecclesiastical life in Blackburn, and a good state of feeling between the clergy and the municipal and educational authorities. The Vicar spoke with much affection of Bishop Knox, whom he regards as a great prelate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>