<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant, we beseech thee, merciful Lord, to thy faithful people pardon and peace, that they may be cleansed from all their sins, and serve thee with a quiet mind; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>My "Primary Visitation" is now a thing of the past. What worry, labour, thought, and time went to its composition! How pitifully inadequate appears the outcome of all! At least, I am free of this obligation for the next four years.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The collect just expressing my mood: and the epistle from the Ephesians v1. 10f. was a direct message to me. The appeal for '<hi rend="underline">prayer &amp; supplication… for me, that utterance may be given unto me that I may open my mouth boldly to make known the mystery of the Gospel, for which I am an ambassador in bonds; that therein I may speak boldly as I ought to speak'</hi> might have been framed for me. ^[written in Greek, Ephesians 6:20]^. The 'chains' which outraged S. Paul's ambassadorial character, and limited his power of service were those of his Roman gaolers, but those which degrade and restrict the Bishop of Durham are of a worse kind. 'Surely life's chains are strong to bind. From morn till eve, Body and mind'. Freedom is the rarest and most desirable of all the conditions of ministry.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p>I revised an old sermon for use tonight, and then wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> in Johannesburg, and to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> in Java. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ivan Thornton</hi> came at 3 p.m., and I shewed him the Castle. He had evidently been carefully primed as to the right mode of addressing a Bishop, for every third word was punctuated by 'Your Worship' to my extreme disgust. I motored to West Hartlepool, and preached in the old parish church of Stranton, which is now serving a population of more than 20,000 souls. Before the service I had tea with the Vicar and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kirner. The vicarage is a very unpretentious 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house, situated on the street opposite the church. It is no more comfortable and commodious within than its modest exterior suggests. But in houses as in their occupants external appearance tells little of the essential truth. The church is a rather fine building, but is spoiled by a flat plaister ceiling, which both obscures the architecture and obstructs the ventilation. There was a very large congregation, &amp; the service was protracted so that the atmosphere became asphyxiating. I came near to fainting in the pulpit. I noted that announcement of an evening celebration of Holy Communion was made. After service I returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>