<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[59]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Am I to have the unpleasant and costly experience of a ritual law&#8211;suit? That depends on the point whether the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Milner, Vicar of Elton, does, or does not, obey the order which I sent him this morning viz. that he should forthwith discontinue the public devotions before the Reserved Sacrament, which are in all but name identical with the Roman service of 'Benediction'. The man is so rude and bigoted that I am not very sanguine.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dashwood</hi> on the hateful subject of the income tax. The forms of inquiry drive me to distraction: and the elaborate system of allowances, which has been created for the relief of bishops, baffles me. However, I did my best, and must acquiesce in the decision, whatever it may be.</p>
         <p>I wrote my fortnightly letters to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. After lunch I walked round the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> brought me a letter which Wallis had received from the Bishop of London's Secretary saying that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Haslewood</hi> had "made it up" with the man <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gibson</hi>, and now desired the Bishop to ordain him! What possible interpretation of this volte&#8211;face is there save one, and that the most dishonourable in the world to the Haslewoods? I suppose that I shall receive some communication from the Bishop of London.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>