<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>A woefully wet day from start to finish. And the atmosphere was stuffy and "muggy". I wasted the morning, and in the afternoon walked through the rain to 4 Marston Ferry Road, and called on the <persName xml:id="1204"><persName xml:id="3885">Radfords</persName></persName>. John<persName xml:id="3886"></persName> is now 8<hi>1/2</hi> years old, and beginning to distinguish himself at school. He is certainly improving in every respect.</p>
         <p>I dined with Chavasse<persName xml:id="5416"></persName> and his wife at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aldate's Rectory, and afterwards addressed about 40 undergraduates in a room adjoining the house. My subject was "<hi rend="underline">The Church and the Miner</hi>", and I introduced it by speaking for about 20 minutes. Then for more than an hour the young men asked me questions, and we parted in high good humour with each other. There were two men from Ruskin Hall there. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chavasse</hi> walked with me to All Souls. He says that there are evident indications that men are turning to the Ministry in greater numbers. He thought that the youth had been impressed by my words. I got back to the Warden's lodgings soon after 10 p.m., and went at once to my bedroom. The headache which had oppressed me all through the day had at last lifted, so that I went to bed more vigorous than I had been all day.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>