<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent most past of the day in the Assembly listening to a <hi rend="bold underline">debate on the Education question, to which I contributed a short speech in the course of the afternoon</hi>. The Bishops of Wakefield and Manchester made the outstanding speeches; the last especially spoke with great ability. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Parmoor</hi><persName xml:id="1736"></persName> made a worthless bombastick speech, denouncing the Cowper&#8211;Temple clause, &amp; was loudly applauded by the fanaticks. Several women addressed the Assembly, a shameful performance, which might well bring S. Paul from Paradise to rebuke the degenerate Church! </p>
         <p>I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi><persName xml:id="344"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Gow</hi><persName xml:id="216"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Salisbury, Lord Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>, Bishop Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, and the Archbishop's chaplains were loud in praise for my speech, which however was none the less a poor performance</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jean Bruce</hi><persName xml:id="1221"></persName> dined at Lambeth, She looks thinner, and more careworn, but very sweet and attractive still. <hi rend="bold underline">She said she heard my speech in the House of Lords on the Liquor Bill, &amp; was so excited that she nearly fell over from the Ladies' Gallery into the House</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The Dean of Windsor &amp; the Bishop of Wakefield told me many anecdotes about Bishop Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName>. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>