<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The first election returns are encouraging. There now seems to be a fair prospect of a sufficient Conservative majority. It is, perhaps, unfortunate, and it is certainly regrettable, that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Asquith</hi> should have lost his seat. This can hardly mean anything else than his disappearance from political life, in which he has played so conspicuous a part during many years.</p>
         <p>I received a draft for &#x00A3;700 from the Eccles: Commissioners on account of the mortgage (&#x00A3;800) for the electric light installation, and paid it forthwith into my bank.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Lay Helpers Association. Then I went to the Castle, and had interviews with two young men who aspire to become clergymen, and seek help from the Ordination candidates Fund, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Emery Lonsdale Richardson</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Mabey Carr</hi>, both from S. Gabriel's, Sunderland. When they had gone off, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi> arrived, &amp; I talked with him about the chaplaincy at Auckland. He is evidently reluctant, and I gave him a week to decide. I brought Booth back with me to the Castle.</p>
         <p>The later reports of the polling disclose a "landslide". There will be in the new house a Conservative majority of more than 140. The Liberal party has been almost annihilated: it will not muster 50 votes.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>