<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m.: and then continued in my study woefully incommoded by tooth–ache all he morning. <hi rend="bold underline">I sent copies of the Sunderland Sermon to the Archbishop of Canterbury, the Bishop of Chester, Canon Partridge, Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName>, and Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>.</hi> Also, I wrote to Downing, enclosing Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Drake &amp; Graham's receipts for £300, and asking for the mortgage money.</p>
         <p>I wrote the candidates' names in the Bibles &amp; Testaments, attended Evensong, &amp; listened to an excellent address from the Archdeacon. After dinner he returned to Durham.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Bradford has authorized Hickson to conduct a "mission of healing" in Frizinghall Parish Church, &amp; "hedges" judiciously in a letter to the diocese. Only those who desire "real spiritual blessing as well as physical health" are qualified to receive healing: and "no physical cures are guaranteed"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hickson<persName xml:id="5413"></persName> does not claim to be aught but the instrument of the healing power of the risen Christ, &amp; only those who are willing to be His disciples can expect a blessing, &amp; they will be the first to realize that, like S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul, a greater blessing may be theirs by the actual denial of the physical relief they seek".</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On these terms, Hickson's pretensions can never be brought to the proof of results, and the religious claim he makes is guaranteed in advance against disproof.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>