<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a long letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> remonstrating with him about the excessive multiplication of services which has marked his recent activity, and asking him to get himself overhauled by a doctor.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi> writes approvingly of the charge, and sends me his "Home University Library" volume on 'Music'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi> sends me a quite admirable lecture on "Liberal Education", which he delivered to the University of Liverpool. I really think he would be the best man for Canterbury.</p>
         <p>After walking round the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, I set out with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> for Wynyard; where we had been invited to see theatricals and dine. Snow flakes were falling as we motored, &amp; when we returned the ground was thinly crusted with snow. I had a good deal of talk with Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>, and I took in the Marchioness to dinner, having Lady Ilchester on my left. So I was well placed, &amp; had much pleasant talk. Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> has been in Rome, and returns thither on Saturday. <hi rend="bold underline">He has had several interviews with Mussolini, whom he regards with admiration as a vigorous ruffian.</hi> <hi>Lord Ilchester promised to show me Holland House in the summer. We came away about 10.45, and got home to the castle at 11.30 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[141]</hi></p>
         <p>1924</p>
         <p>This year must needs have a critical or decisive character, both in my personal and in my public life. For in it I lost my Step&#8211;mother, who was the last link with my earlier career. I feel that a chapter has been closed, and that the end begins to grow on my sight. <hi rend="doubleunderline">William's</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> departure created a considerable void in that circle of familiars, with whom my heart was engaged. I begin to feel that I am now too far on my journey to make fresh companions. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rashdall's</hi><persName xml:id="117"></persName> death removed a man with whom I had been more or less intimate for 40 years. When I attended the College Gaudy on All Souls Day, I looked round on a company of strangers, to whom I had become only a legend. The chill of a new loneliness struck my heart, and I almost vowed never to come there again. Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Quirk's</hi><persName xml:id="2785"></persName> sudden death was not wholly unexpected, and it compelled me to make the difficult decision whether I would withdraw <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> from Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, and make him suffragan, or abandon my intention of bringing him ultimately into that position. I adopted the bolder course, but thereby I gave grave offence to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName>, who expressed himself with gross impropriety. However the diocese generally seemed to approve the appointment, and I have no doubt that it will be speedily and completely justified. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
         <p>The year has been full of controversy. When it opened <hi rend="doubleunderline">Malines</hi> filled the ecclesiastical horizon. I expressed myself in opposition to the "Conversations" in articles which appeared in the "<hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century and After</hi>", and the <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Review</hi>, as well as in letters to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>. A speech to the Sunderland 'Rotarians' on the subject of '<hi rend="doubleunderline">Prohibition</hi>' brought me into open collision with the Total Abstainers, and when, on July 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I made a speech in the House of Lords against the <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Oxford's<persName xml:id="602"></persName> Bill</hi>, I aggravated my offence. My opposition to the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick of Winchester Division Measure</hi> made me odious to the zealots of the National Assembly, and this odium was intensified by my speeches in the Assembly against the division of Hereford. But the two speeches impressed the House of Lords, and to that extent strengthened my position. A rude attack on me by the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dean of Chester</hi> in the Lower House of the York Convocation disclosed, as well by its rudeness, as by the reception which it received from the members, how extremely unpopular I am with the clergy. I preached much both within and without the <hi rend="bold">[143] </hi>diocese. The following sermons were published:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. To the University of Cambridge on May 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>2. To the Nonconformists in Liverpool Cathedral on July 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>3. The reply to Cardinal Bourne in Sunderland on Sept 14.</p>
         <p>4. The Sermon on Baxter in Ch. Ch. Newgate St: on Dec: 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>I preached in Glasgow to the <hi rend="underline">World Sunday School Union</hi> on June 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>: to the <hi rend="underline">Advertising Association </hi>in Westminster Abbey on July 13: to the <hi rend="underline">American Bar Association</hi> in Gray's Inn on July 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>: and to the Presbyterians in South Shields on Sept: 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to Ireland May 30–June 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when we stayed with the Provost of Trinity College, Archbishop D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName>, and Lord Londonderry: and I preached five sermons in Dublin, Armagh, &amp; Belfast.</p>
         <p>I delivered the <hi rend="underline">Rede Lecture</hi> on '<hi rend="doubleunderline">Byron</hi>' in Cambridge on May 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>. The preparation of this lecture inflicted on me an amount of labour all together excessive, and, when the lecture was published, it aroused little or no interest.</p>
         <p>In July I visited <hi rend="underline">Barking</hi>, and was touched by the warmth of the reception which I received. It really appeared as if the people cared for a Vicar, who had left them nearly 30 years previously! I sacrificed my holiday in August to the preparation of a <hi rend="doubleunderline">charge</hi> <hi rend="bold">[144] </hi>which was delivered to the Archdeaconry of Auckland in S. Cuthbert's Darlington, and to the Archdeaconry of Durham in the Cathedral. I entertained the clergy to luncheon severally at the King's Head Hotel, and the Castle Hall. Hodder &amp; Stoughton published the charge, of which I caused copies to be sent to all the clergy of the diocese, as well as to all the Bishops of the Church. On October 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> I ordained <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi> to the Diaconate: and for the Advent Ordination, when 15 men were ordained (of whom 9 were ordained to the diaconate) I made use of the Castle in Durham.</p>
         <p>Politically, the year was extremely interesting, for it witnessed the entrance on the national arena of the first "Labour" Government, and also its exit. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> came into power at the head of a large &amp; homogeneous majority: but the Labour poll was increased by more than 1,000,000 votes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> was appointed to the Bishoprick of Birmingham, and immediately came into vehement controversy with the Anglo&#8211;Catholic clergy of his diocese.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>