<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Davidson, Lloyd Thomas, and Chas. J. Thynne.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with the dogs in the afternoon. On returning to the House I finished <hi rend="doubleunderline">Powicke's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Life of Baxter</hi>. It is a sound piece of discriminating &amp; sympathetic work. <hi rend="bold underline">The Quakers argued that Baxter had not the Spirit, because he read his sermon out of a paper</hi>. Baxter replied:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"As wisely do the Quakers argue, that because we use Spectacles, or hour glasses, and pulpits, we have not the Spirit. Its not want of your abilities that makes ministers use notes: but <hi rend="bold underline">its a regard to the work, and good of the hearers</hi>. I use notes as much as any man when I take pains; and as little as any man, when I am lazy or busy, and have not leisure to prepare. Its easier to preach three Sermons without notes than one with them. He is a simple preacher that is not able to preach all day without preparation, if his strength would serve, especially if he preach at your rates".</p>
         </div>
         <p>My own practice accords with Baxter's. Extemporaneus preaching is the product of idleness.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>