<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Edmundsbury and Ipswich</hi> writes to ask me whether he is right in the theological opinions he has been propounding to an Anglo&#8211;Catholic incumbent in his diocese. I wrote in reply pointing out that the Church of England was, perhaps, more tolerant of superstitious views of the Eucharist than he assumed, &amp; referring him to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Apb. Temple's</hi> Primary Charge. </p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and lunched in the Castle Hall, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Frank Brown</hi> was entertaining <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Islington</hi> &amp; the members of the "National Savings Association". I proposed the toast of the Ass<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> in an impromptu foolish speech. Then I went to the Cosin Library, &amp; joined the Board of Training. Next I interviewed a poor specimen of an Ordination candidate, &amp; afterwards had tea with J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Then I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Last night the Government was defeated in the House of Commons on a motion for a Committee to inquire into the circumstances in which the prosecution of the Communist editor, Campbell, had been begun and abandoned</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">It seems unavoidable that a General Election should take place within a few weeks.</hi> It is a wholly unnecessary, and merely mischievous, election. No great issue is before the country, only some illustrations of "Labour" incapacity which could not be surprising, which had done all the harm they could do when they had been provided, &amp; c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not provide an adequate excuse for an appeal to the country.<note xml:id="550" n="1"></note></p>
         </body></text></TEI>