<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Christ was sent to preach by his own life, &amp; to give an example to others, exemplum dedi vobis, which is the best kind of preaching, when all is done: that they which stand like idols and statues, to point out the way to others, &amp; yet stir not themselves to lead the way, they are by this very mark known to be none of Christ's ambassadors.</p>
         <p>Cosin in 1626. (v Works. Vol I p. 97.)</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a passage from the sermon preached in the Durham House Chapel at the consecration of the Bishop of Carlisle, in the presence of "many Deans &amp; Doctors with 500 persons beside". It must have been a very large chapel!</p>
         <p>I frittered away the day in writing letters, talking, &amp; reading. In the afternoon I walked round the Park with the dogs. An immense flock of birds, probably starlings, passed over, flying high, but with the rattle of their wings making a mighty noise. </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went into Durham, and met M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kenyon, to whom she showed the cathedral and castle, &amp; then brought back to Auckland. Major M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Cullagh came to dinner. They both hailed from India, and had a basis for conversation in the circumstance. It is not without impressiveness that <hi rend="underline">everybody</hi> who has had personal acquaintance either with India or Egypt is quite persuaded of the speedy failure of our democratic experiment.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>