<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and attended a meeting of the Barrington Trustees, returning to Auckland for lunch. An aspirant for Ordination, named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moore,</hi> came to see me: and Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived from Sedbergh. After lunch Ernest and I walked round the Park.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Maynard Smith</hi> wrote to say that he was engaged upon a Life of the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName>, and would be grateful for anything that I could say about him. I wrote him a letter, of which I kept a copy.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">George's</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName> present arrived &#8211; a brilliant Japanese jacket for <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and a photograph of himself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dillon</hi><persName xml:id="3784"></persName> sent me "<hi rend="underline">The Lost Dominion</hi>" by Al. Carthill, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Sands</hi> sent a volume of short stories by himself entitled "<hi rend="underline">Of the Chain</hi>".</p>
         <p>Ella and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went into Durham to attend the dance which Dawson&#8211;Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> gives to celebrate the coming&#8211;of&#8211;age of his son, Hervey. Ernest came to my room, and talked for two hours before going to bed</p>
         <p>Is it merely the surviving influence of an irrational Puritan prejudice that makes me restive whenever these dances come on the tapis or is it a legitimate and irrepressible movement of the Christian conscience to which I am morally bound to give heed?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>