<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">This is Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> birthday, and the recollection of the fact re&#8211;opens a bitter sorrow. How intolerable is all this ecstatic chatter about "spiritual healing" when set beside that poor child's martyrdom! What can I say? Happy if we can say with conviction; "The souls of the righteous are in the Hand of God, &amp; there shall no torment reach them, for they are in peace". It is well for Humanity that the Redeemer was not the embodiment of joyous health, but the "a man of sorrows &amp; acquainted with grief".</hi></p>
         <p>After writing some necessary letters, and preparing notes for the later functions, I set to work in restoring order to the chaos of my table, and though I destroyed much, I settled little!</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Barnard Castle, &amp; presided at the distribution of prizes by a M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Roscoe, who appears to have been a friend of the Headmaster, &amp; had evidently been brought to the function in order to sing authoritatively the new Headmaster's praises. Without staying for the entertainment which followed the speech&#8211;making, I returned to the Castle. At 5 p.m. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I motored to Norton, where I instituted Mr Fuller to the living. There was a considerable congregation, &amp; a good attendance of the neighbouring clergy. After service, we dined with old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kirk, and then motored back to Auckland, where we arrived about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>