<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Undoubtedly we are approaching a crisis, and a reaction, and one or two years will show what direction things are going to take – whether Rome will perish or reform.</p>
         <p>Father Tyrrell<persName xml:id="1084"></persName>. November 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. 1908.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Sixteen years have passed and Rome has neither perished nor reformed.</hi> On the contrary she has perished in her course of insolent bigotry, and is more firmly established in the devotion of her members, and in the wondering homage of the world than ever. Yesterday's "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" had an adulatory account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Gasquet</hi>, and the Papist Mayor of Durham goes in state to his mass&#8211;house!</p>
         <p>The Archbishop of Canterbury gives his blessing to an Anglo&#8211;Catholic embassy organized by that veteran anarch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halifax</hi>, which discusses "reunion" in the house of a Belgian Cardinal, and when the inevitable repudiation comes from the Vatican, 'takes it lying down'. </p>
         <p>The War which has destroyed the National Church, has only brought power and credit to the Roman Obedience, which stands up in unique &amp; impressive grandeur as the only rallying point for broken &amp; divided Christendom, yet remaining all the while as cynical, as unscrupulous, as corrupt, and as cruel as ever! So much for prophecy.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m. At breakfast I received a letter from Godfrey Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> enclosing a report of his speech on "Copec" at the Lichfield Diocesan Conference. He expressed himself with courage and excellent good sense.</p>
         <p>The clergy of the Church of England are still often described as belonging to "the classes". It is an interesting comment on this description to note the type &amp; origin of my 15 candidates.</p>
         <p>1. Berwick, a miner, son of a farmer.</p>
         <p>2. Hague, a clerk, son of a clerk.</p>
         <p>3. Crosby, an elementary schoolmaster.</p>
         <p>4. Heselton, ditto, son of a ship&#8211;broker.</p>
         <p>5. Coles, a soldier &amp; other things, son of a 'retired Archaeologist'.</p>
         <p>6. Hall, served as an ordinary seaman in the War, son of district Manager of an Insurance Office.</p>
         <p>7. Moore, Miner.</p>
         <p>8. Simmonds, journalist, son of a tea&#8211;dealer.</p>
         <p>9. Bamlett, son of a commercial traveller.</p>
         <p>10. Hamilton, son of an engineer.</p>
         <p>11. Horstead, son of an accountant.</p>
         <p>12. Petitjean, an electrician.</p>
         <p>13. Shore, son of a land&#8211;steward.</p>
         <p>14. Tooley, son of a merchant.</p>
         <p>15. Hill, son of a schoolmaster.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[125]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Here are four artisans, and eleven men of the middle&#8211;class. Not a clergyman's son in the list, nor (in the technical sense) a gentleman's. This, if it be representative of the Church generally, gives much food for thought. It may perhaps, explain the facility with which socialistic and even communistic opinions find acceptance among the Anglican clergy: and it gives us the reason why clerical controversy is so vehement and unscholarly.</hi></p>
         <p>I read the address on 'Sermons', and then interviewed some of the priests. After lunch I took Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> for a walk, and then attended Evensong in the Cathedral, where the Anthem was Purcell's <hi rend="underline">Rejoice in the Lord always</hi>. After service I returned to the Castle, and was joined by Boutflower<persName xml:id="3585"></persName>, who came to discuss the foolish dispute over parochial boundaries between the Vicars of Coxhoe and Cornforth. We had tea together, and then I had an interview with Petitjean. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> administered the Oath etc. in the Chapel, after I had emphasized the obligation implied. Then I had interviews with Shore and Tooley: &amp; signed the letters of Orders. At dinner I permitted talking. At 9 p.m. I delivered my Charge, emphasising strongly the obligation of pledges given in Ordination, &amp; warning the men against the sophistries of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>