<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and then had my hair cut. Then I walked to Westminster, where I called on Downing at the Ecclesiastical Commission. Then I called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, and talked with him for an hour. He gives but an ill account of the new Socialist Canon, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi>, who, he says, "exudes sentiment"! After lunching at the Club, I walked to Warwick Square, where I called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi>, and "fixed up" the publishing of my Charge. I returned to the Athenaeum, and had tea. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tallents</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> had some talk with me. After writing to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, I returned to the Deanery. There was a pleasant &amp; interesting party at dinner. I took down a communicative old lady – Lady Low. On the other side of me was M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Carruthers<persName xml:id="1261"></persName>, whom I knew well once as Violet Markham. After the ladies had withdrawn, I had some talk with young Baring, &amp; afterwards with his mother, Lady Cromer. Sir Maurice de Bunsen was friendly &amp; talkative.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Hugh Rees tells me that my Sunderland Sermon is selling well. He says that orders have come from all parts of the country</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1924.</p>
         <p>My dear Colonel Burdon,</p>
         <p>You are probably aware that one of the reasons for which the Bishop is entitled to reject a patron's nomination is the fact that the nominee has not been three years in Holy Orders. It would be difficult to waive this objection in the case of some small and easy case, but in the case of a parish of 10,000 souls, &amp; presenting so many problems as Horden, I must needs think that only the most unusual circumstances could justify the Bishop in sanctioning so grave a departure from normal procedure. And these circumstances do not appear to exist.</p>
         <p>It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi>, I think, create an ill impression of the diocese if I consented to the appointment of a man in deacon's Orders: &amp;, indeed, I cannot think it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be right for me to do so.</p>
         <p>If you will send me the usual particulars about the Rev. J. Ward, I will make the usual inquiries, &amp; if the result be satisfactory, I shall be pleased to grant him permission to take temporary duty in the diocese.</p>
         <p>Yrs. sincerely, Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>