<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Lord, we beseech thee, grant thy people grace to withstand the temptations of the world, the flesh, and the devil, and with pure hearts and minds to follow thee the only God; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>Rain fell heavily during the night, and the morning broke on a sodden world, infinitely depressing. Autumnal leaves are never so utterly significant of death and decay as when they fall under a leaden sky on to a rain&#8211;soaked earth.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 10 communicants, including all my guests but one.</p>
         <p>I spent the day in my study until the evening when I went to Tudhoe Grange, and preached at Evensong. My subject was suggested by yesterday's festival.</p>
         <p>The wet night did undoubtedly affect the congregation. Yet the church was fairly filled, and there were hardly less than fifty men and lads in the choir. Jimmie Dobbie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> read the lessons, and afterwards came in the car with me as far as the end of Spennymoor.</p>
         <p>Canon Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> expressed some apprehension in view of the increase of unemployment.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>