<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>One lesson, and only one, history may be said to repeat with distinctness: that the world is built somehow on moral foundations: that, in the long run, it is well with the good: in the long run, it is ill with the wicked. But this is no science: it is no more than the old doctrine taught long ago by the Hebrew prophets.</p>
         <p>J. A. Froude<persName xml:id="1409"></persName>. Short Studies. i. 14.</p>
         </div>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">In the long run</hi>" – but first "<hi rend="underline">the good</hi>" have perished in their martyrdom: and "<hi rend="underline">the bad</hi>" have 'slept with their fathers' after a long career of secular prosperity. <hi rend="bold underline">The great rectifications of History are effected with no regard whatever to the deserts of individuals. Not History, but Religion, teaches the moral government of the World: the most that History can do, is to offer some faint confirmations of the Witness which Religion bears.</hi> The crucial terms of the argument are coined in the mint of Religion. What are "<hi rend="underline">moral</hi>" foundations? By what rule are "<hi rend="underline">the good</hi>" distinguished from "<hi rend="underline">the wicked</hi>"? What is meant by "<hi rend="underline">it is well with the good</hi>"? The Hebrew prophets based themselves, not on History, but on the Divine Witness within the human spirit:&#8211; "<hi rend="underline">He hath showed thee, O man, what is good".</hi> But they were often confronted with the paradoxes of experience, their own &amp; that of others. "<hi rend="underline">Though He slay me, yet will I trust Him".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p>I motored with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> to <hi rend="underline">Heatherycleugh</hi>, and there instituted the new Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bailey</hi> from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's, W. Hartlepool. After having tea with the Baileys, I returned to Auckland by way of Durham, leaving Wilson at his own door. </p>
         <p>It is unusual in these days to receive a letter garnished with a quotation from Virgil. Nothing less has been my experience today. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Haigh</hi><persName xml:id="5411"></persName>, the successor of the Dean of Canterbury as chaplain to the Archbishop of Canterbury, writes to acknowledge receipt of the Sunderland sermon, &amp; he adorns his letter with 4 lines from the Aeneid, bk. ix.</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>sed magnum stridens contortum phalarica venit,</p>
         <p>fulminis acta modo, quam nec duo taurea terga,</p>
         <p>nec duplici squama lorica fidelis et auro</p>
         <p>sustinuit: conlapsa ruunt immania membra.</p>
         <p>which are thus rendered in Loeb's version:</p>
         <p>'but with a mighty hiss a whirled pike sped,</p>
         <p>driven like a thunderbolt. This not two bulls'</p>
         <p>hides nor the trusty corslet with double scales</p>
         <p>of gold could withstand. The giant limbs totter</p>
         <p>and fall'.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I trust that his Eminence realizes his controversial collapse in this fashion, but I think it more probable that he applies the lines to the Anglican bishop! </p>
         </body></text></TEI>