<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I met <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard</hi> in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> last Thursday. He at once began speaking about my Charge, which he had just read through. "It's the best thing you've ever done", he said: and he was quite enthusiastic in his approval. I was gratified, as I hold his judgement in high regard, but all the signs point to the Charge falling quite flat! Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knox</hi> writes that he has "read it with the very deepest interest from cover to cover".</p>
         <p>I received a lengthy tee&#8211;total protest from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bothamley</hi><persName xml:id="3854"></persName>, and was fool enough to reply to it. Also I spent some time in writing at length to Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> on the subject of his Ordination, that is, on the point whether, or not, he shall be ordained. If he is to be ordained, the decision sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be postponed, for he is 23 next May.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I became energetic as what the Americans call a "sleuth", writing with respect to the Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Nevill Hudson</hi><hi rend="italic"> to the Bishops of London and Manchester, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Philip's, Dalston, and the Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> F. M. Sykes.</hi></p>
         <p>My whole day was frittered away in writing letters, reading newspapers, and taking a 'constitutional' round the Park. It is difficult to see how and when I am to write the History of the Reformation.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>