<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The image of the stout Gibbon placidly contemplating the animated conflicts, the stirring pleadings of Fox and Burke, watching a revolution and heavily taking no part in it, gives an idea of the historian as he is likely to be. '<hi rend="underline">Why</hi>', it is often asked, '<hi rend="underline">is history dull? It is a narrative of life, and life is of all things the most interesting</hi>'. The answer is, that it is written by men too dull to take the common interest in life, in whom languor predominates over zeal, and sluggishness over passion.</p>
         <p>Bagehot. Literary Studies. ii. 223/4.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the morning in trying to lay the foundations of the address for the Historical Association: but my success was very slight.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Barnard Castle, &amp; had an interview with the Headmaster about the very perplexing case of discipline, which he has referred to me. I cannot say that I got much help. Equity is not always consistent with discipline, and hardly ever consistent with convenience. In questions of personal morality the way of justice is particularly difficult to trace, for it is confused by the question of charity. Would amputation ever take place, if the menaced limb had a voice in the decision? </p>
         </body></text></TEI>