<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to Robt. under cover to the Dean of York offering him the living of Christ Church, West Hartlepool. I don't suppose that he will take it. Then I read, Powicke's, Life of Baxter, which is a good piece of work.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I walked round the Park with the dogs. I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Levick promising to send him my charge. The young man interests me by his bumptiousness, ardour, and quickness of response, &amp; I am curious to see more of the movements of his mind.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to Mr Roper to thank him for the gift of a fine salmon which arrived during my absence.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Evangelicals appear to be extremely shocked &amp; aggrieved at my disapproval of 'Evening Communion'. The '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Record</hi><hi rend="italic">' has a paragraph on its front page, expressing both astonishment and resentment. There are letters of protest in the papers: and I am receiving angry communications through the post. One writer, a publisher named Thynne, addresses me 'more in sorrow than in anger' as one who has, so to say, admired me in the past "on false pretences". He tells me that "for more than 40 years he corresponded with my predecessor, Bishop Handley Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, acting for him in many literary transactions until the time of his death". Most of my correspondents are of that generation.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>