<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> returned to Oxford after breakfast. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off in the car to Murraythwaite, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> going with her as far as his purposes permitted: and I prepared some notes for the function later in the day.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I travelled by train to Durham, and lunched with Pemberton<persName xml:id="2837"></persName> in the Common Room of the Castle to meet Sir William Bragg, and others who were to </hi>take<hi rend="italic"> part in the function which followed.</hi> The hideous building which forms the home of the new Science Faculty was formally opened by Sir W. B., and then we all went in procession to a large marquee, where, after degrees had been bestowed, Sir W. B. delivered an address on chemistry, and then I proposed a vote of thanks to him, which was passed. After this Moulsdale<persName xml:id="3159"></persName> motored me back to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The electricians redeemed their promise after all, and the Castle was brilliantly lighted before Ordination candidates arrived. Certainly the improvement is very great. Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> gave the address at Evensong.</p>
         <p>I was bothered by an abominable tooth&#8211;ache, which made life a burden. Happily I had nothing to do beyond sitting in my stall. I read the "Hibbert Journal", which has a destructive article by Kirsopp Lake<persName xml:id="3172"></persName>, and an effective criticism of "Copec's" Theology by Mackenzie.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>