<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I have to confirm the boys – perhaps 50 – of the Durham School, and the question how I shall address them shadows my mind. What do I know about the mind of a boy? It is true that I was once a boy myself, but so abnormal were the circumstances of my boyhood that I cannot learn anything from cross&#8211;examining my own memory. <hi rend="italic">In truth I never recall a time when I thought or felt essentially differently from what I think &amp; feel now. This cannot but be a formidable barrier to any genuine understanding of the boy's mind.</hi> I shall take for my text the verse which Dean Stanley<persName xml:id="505"></persName> loved – "<hi rend="underline">I see that all things come to an end, but Thy commandment is exceeding broad</hi>". The two&#8211;fold character of all human experiences – immediate &amp; visible, and also remote and invisible – illustrated by the lessons and games of boyhood, but holding true throughout life: the essence of religion consisting in giving first place to the unseen aspect which alone persists: confirmation implying a confession of our loyalty to the Unseen, and, also, our receiving the pledge of that Power by which the Unseen finally prevails – these, perhaps, may serve as the ideas, which the sympathy born of contact may clothe with intelligible words. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi></p>
         <p>We all motored into Durham in time for the School Confirmation in the Cathedral. I confirmed 49 boys from the School, and 5 of the Cathedral Choir boys. I think the boys were attentive, and they seemed to be devout. Then I went to the Castle, and instituted Parry to his slum&#8211;parish, S. Stephen's, Ayres Quay, Sunderland, and licensed 10 curates. Among the latter was Fuller, who goes to his father's parish. After this, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>: &amp; then I went to the Cosin library and presided over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference Committee. <hi rend="italic">I announced my intention of addressing the Conference on the vexed and pressing subject of 'Spiritual Healing'.</hi> Then I went to the Cathedral and listened in my Throne to the rendering of Mozart's Twelfth Mass. The Cathedral was well filled, i.e. the Nave. After this, I picked up the two ladies, &amp; returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Wilson told me that he recollected one occasion on which Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName> had the Ordination candidates in the Castle at Durham. In view of the larger number which in the pre&#8211;War years were ordained, and the larger household at Auckland, where did the bishop find room for the candidates?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>