<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Church&#8211;boy "vocations" are, of course, analogous to the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">mariage de convenance</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, and defensible on the same principle…. Few are free to choose their walk in life, and the vocation "to which it has pleased God to call them" means, for most, that state into which inevitable circumstances have forced them, and which often entails celibacy, or other restrictions no less difficult to endure…… The Church&#8211;boy system is almost inevitable and therefore defensible. Few of those boys would ever have had any distinctive vocation of any kind, or have been shaped otherwise than passively.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline"> Father Tyrrell<persName xml:id="1084"></persName>, 'Autobiography' 196, 7</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>This is an unpleasant apology for an unpleasant procedure, into which, in spite of its unpleasantness, the Church of England is steadily and rapidly drifting. The <hi rend="underline">'Church&#8211;boy</hi>', who is carried into the Jesuit Society, has his analogue in the youths who crowd to Mirfield &amp; Kelham, &amp; pass thence to the Bishop to be ordained. 'Vocation' is difficult to bring into any intelligible and adequate connexion with their Ordination. The sincere but ignorant ardours of adolescence, dangerously associated with a manner, a relatively easy manner, of earning their living – are these enough? </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Then I set myself to preparing my sermon for Stockton. The people are so poor &amp; rough, that extemporaneous preaching – which I hate – is almost essential. </p>
         <p> The schoolmaster and his wife came to lunch together with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ledger the curate.</p>
         <p>"At least they have not put him into a bishop's apron, the emblem of our first parent's shame" was said by <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. A. Froude</hi><persName xml:id="1409"></persName> of a famous clergyman. It is one more illustration of the curious detestation of bishops which inhabits educated minds, though is not often so frankly expressed. Why is this? Is it that the office raises its holder so far out of his normal setting, that it provokes a kind of resentment, as a gross exhibition of the familiar but always exasperating discord between merit and reward? It must be admitted that the amount of 'make&#8211;belief ' in the conditions of episcopal office is excessive, even when judged by the standard of this hollow modern world. </p>
         <p>I motored to Stockton, and preached at Evensong in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James Church, which was, of course, crowded, but not with the regular congregation. Many Freemasons were there, and the Mayor, Ropner, and others from outside the parish. Loney, the Vicar, is plainly far from well. After service I returned to Auckland. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>