<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The remaining proofs of the Charge arrived, but I had no time to revise them, as I had to go into Durham for several engagements. First I attended a little Committee at the Castle, which decided to recommend a grant of &#x00A3;80 to Captain Carter for the maintenance of his car, &amp; &#x00A3;50 for clerical assistance. Then I licensed four curates. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I attended the Freemasons' lunch in the Castle – Hall, at which a presentation of plate was made to the Prov: Grand master, Lord Ravensworth<persName xml:id="3719"></persName> &amp; to Lady R. in honour of their Silver Wedding.</hi> Then I presided at a meeting of the Finance Board, which raised the grant to Capt. Carter to &#x00A3;100. After this, I had tea with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, &amp; walked with him in the banks. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who had gone on to Sunderland after the Freemasons' lunch in order to open a Bazaar, returned about 5 p.m., picked me up at the College Gate, &amp; returned with me to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Olive<persName xml:id="1686"></persName> and her husband arrived about 6 p.m.</p>
         <p>The afternoon post brought me an interesting letter from Nicholas Murray Butler. He speaks with admiration of the liquor legislation of Quebec. "In my judgement, the Province of Quebec has reached what is pretty nearly an ideal solution of the problem presented by the liquor traffic".</p>
         <p>The faith healing mission at Bradford continues to figure largely in the newspapers.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>