<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="underline">Little</hi>, the curate of Winlaton, offering him the living of Eighton Banks, which <hi rend="underline">Lister</hi> the curate of Tanfield has declined on account of the size &amp; dilapidated condition of the vicarage. Then we all motored into Durham, where I "admitted" several "Pilgrims" in the Deanery chapel, and had some talk with <hi rend="underline">Lillingston</hi><persName xml:id="3262"></persName>, to whom I offered the Rural Deanery of Durham, vacated by <hi rend="underline">Watson</hi> on his removal to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring: with the Precentor about the music at the Visitation: and with <hi rend="underline">Bailey</hi><persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, about an extremely interesting inquiry which he has received from a member of the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> respecting Bishop Cosin. <hi rend="underline">Lady Olga Montagu</hi> and her sister joined us, &amp; we brought them out to lunch at Auckland. After lunch I showed them the Castle, &amp; then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied them back to Durham, and I walked round the Park with Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName>, who is a most charming companion, as she not only talks with intelligence but so evidently enjoys the walk. On my return <hi rend="underline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to see me, &amp; I wasted an hour with him. He tells me, &amp; his view on the subject is likely to be shared by his contemporaries of the same type &amp; class, that the general view was that "The Cardinal had been put back into his proper place"! This is, so far as it goes, satisfying enough.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>