<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There could be no greater disaster than to identify Christianity, as some would do, with a political theory which happens to attract us for the time, and finally go the way of every other.</p>
         <p>v Ernest F. Scott The Ethical Teaching of Jesus p 82</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">R. H.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Aspects of Religious and Scientific Thought</hi>" 1899 has some useful observations on the problems of prayer. Especially c. xxxi Prayers for the Dead: &amp; c. xxxii 'Canon Kingsley on Reasonable Prayer', &amp; c. xxxiii 'Canon Liddon on Prayer &amp; Miracle'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Papist 'Reply' arrived. It is well&#8211;written, and, from its own point of view, not ineffective; but it evades the true issues</hi>.</p>
         <p>After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter Smith</hi> and I walked in the Park. We fell in with a party of five young miners, all out of work, and had some conversation with them. They seemed both intelligent &amp; well mannered. How long will they remain so?</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is 22 years since <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were married in the Abbey. We grow older, and are visibly expressing the fact.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">She grows deaf &amp; I grow cynical. Neither deafness nor cynicism makes for happiness. And the course of the world adds nothing to correct the inevitable sadness of waxing years</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Time is carrying away our friends, and we move forward in a strange land in an increasing loneliness. Old age will be a rather terrible experience</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>