<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName> went off after breakfast: and I settled down to the Baxter Sermon, but beyond reading through his sermon before Charles II, and <hi rend="italic bold underline">counting up the number of times he mentioned hell in it I did nothing effectual. It was an achievement to name Hell no less than 34 times in a single discourse</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was a public recognition of the "Merry Monarch's" personal concern with that locality! Baxter addressed the King and his courtiers in terms which would have suited his Kidderminster congregation, or indeed any congregation. Save for one "purple–patch" well garnished with Latin tags, there is nothing "special" about the sermon. His reference to the case of the Nonconformists is limited to a brief and guarded allusion at the end of it.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">He could certainly have taken no less than an hour and a half to deliver it</hi><hi rend="italic">, and may well have been longer. Cranmer warned Latimer not to exceed half an hour in preaching to Henry VIII.</hi></p>
         <p>I went in to Durham after tea, and examined 5 deacons in Jewel,<persName xml:id="3616"></persName> Hooker,<persName xml:id="969"></persName> and Butler<persName xml:id="1856"></persName>. They had all <hi rend="underline">read</hi> the books except the evangelical Horstead,<persName xml:id="5722"></persName> who is far too eloquent and spiritual to need illumination from such sources! After this function, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>