<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>A rather comfortless night led in a morning of London fog. The disturbing sound of detonators announced the fact. Of all conditions of the atmosphere fog is the most abhorrent. Discomfort, inconvenience, and insecurity are all involved in it. If you be so unfortunate as to be pledged to engagements which take you abroad, all these, realized in the streets of London, are at their malignant worst. </p>
         <p>I attended a shortened form of Mattins at 8.15 a.m. and received the Holy Sacrament at 8.30 a.m. Then followed breakfast in the Great Hall. After this I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and read the papers. Then I called on Hugh Rees, &amp; was told that only 200 were left of the second thousand of "Continuity". I went on to Adeney &amp; ordered an overcoat. Then I called at a leather&#8211;selling shop of one Davis, and bought a card&#8211;case for William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>: after this I walked to Westminster where I found the discussion of the Pensions Measure still proceeding. I lunched at the Athenaeum with <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macmillan</hi>, &amp; then returned to the Assembly, and took part in the discussion of the <hi rend="underline">Shrewsbury Bishoprick Measure</hi>. The Leicester Bishoprick Measure, being unopposed, was hustled through just before the Assembly rose. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p>I dined at Lincoln's Inn. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Edward Clarke</hi><persName xml:id="4002"></persName> took me in to dinner, and I sate between him and the treasurer, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Justice Eve</hi>. In the library afterwards I sate between <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Coward</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Justice Bankes. Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="3466"></persName> was there, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Danesfort</hi><persName xml:id="2092"></persName>. Also <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Pember</hi><persName xml:id="66"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barrington Ward</hi>. I had much agreeable conversation, and enjoyed the evening much. On returning to Lambeth, I had some talk in the <hi rend="italic">smoking room with Donaldson, Frere<persName xml:id="2021"></persName>, David, and Sir Lewis Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName>. They all profess to believe that the Enabling Act was a beneficent and timely measure: that the National Assembly has proved itself a great success: &amp; that, in short, everything is going on triumphantly. To me all things have another aspect.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Coward</hi> told me that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead</hi><persName xml:id="2508"></persName> had told him that he (Lord B) had made &#x00A3;15500. by his pen during the last year. This is, indeed a prodigious sum, and argues great industry. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winston Churchill</hi><persName xml:id="2441"></persName> are the two strongest 'personalities' of the Cabinet, and they are understood to be linked in close friendship. In combination they will be extremely formidable, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Baldwin</hi><persName xml:id="4118"></persName> will need a very strong back to hold his own against them. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>