<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">I wrote to Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> advising him to abjure political meetings now that he has become a parson.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The imminence of a General Election makes it probable that he will be in request as an anti&#8211;Socialist orator, and he would damage his religious influence by carrying his black&#8211;coat into the hurly&#8211;burly of the political arena.</hi></p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Richard de Bury's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Philobiblon</hi>, or rather <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Thomas's</hi> excellent rendering of it, with a view to choosing a subject for this tiresome "Inaugural Lecture" which I am pledged to deliver to the Historical Association in January. It might, perhaps, be possible to make up a sufficient paper on the theme of studying History by means of illustrative books, e.g. the Philobiblon, Salimbene's Chronicle, Baxter's Autobiography etc. "History read in Side&#8211;lights". It is astonishing how much time and labour are requisite for doing anything that lies outside the lines of accustomed work.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to the Archbishop's chaplain saying that I thought it desirable that the Faith&#8211;healing Mission in Bradford should be discussed at the Bishops' meeting, and that, if the Bishop of Bradford did not himself introduce it, and if no other Bishop had undertaken to introduce it, I would do so myself.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>