<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Princes and Nobles live not always. You are not the Rulers of the unmoveable Kingdom, but of a boat that is in an hasty stream, or a ship under sail, that will speed both Pilot &amp; Passengers to shore.</p>
         <p>Baxter preaching before Charles II "My Life of Faith" p. 45.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I finished the Baxter sermon; and then received the dentist. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilton</hi>, the new vicar of Thornley, came to see me, &amp; stayed to lunch. I walked in the Park, and put up a covey of five partridges. This is only the second time that I have started game in the Park since I have been living in the Castle. The two boys, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joe Bainbridge</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Nicholson</hi>, kept tryst, and Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> showed them the Castle. May come to my study before going off, and I gave them each a Waverley novel – Joe had the "Fortunes of Nigel", &amp; John "Anne of Geierstein". Is it really worth while to indulge an interest which must be transitory, and to evoke affections which cannot possibly hold? <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went to the play, and I busied myself in writing some overdue letters, and reading.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The small book – "Christian Beginnings" – by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi><hi rend="italic"> is a convenient summary of critical results so far as the New Testament goes.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">It does not leave much foundation for the Christian Religion</hi><hi rend="italic underline">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Christendom is reared on an ash&#8211;heap of hypotheses, not on the Rock of historic Fact!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>