<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, I beseech Thee, look with compassion on the faults and failures of the past forty years. Be with me still in the coming time, long or short, before the end. In the deepening sadness of old age, let Thy Presence be with me. Let me not fail under the trials of this difficult life. Shew Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee. Through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>At breakfast conversation was energetic, and ranged over many subjects. I mentioned Schweitzer's "On the verge of the primaeval forest", and found nobody had so much as heard of it! I must send it to Katherine<persName xml:id="4356"></persName>, who would be the better for a little enthusiasm for Christian service. She has grown to be a fine young woman, who just needs the hallowing touch of a religious allegiance to be extremely winning. But the atmosphere of Oxford, and especially female Oxford, is not favourable to the things of the spirit. The affectations of rationalism are never so offensive as when exhibited by young and charming women, whom nature has so evidently ordained to be the symbols and expositors of all that is gentle, trusting, and devout. Yet the very first&#8211;fruits of the new passion for masculinity which marks the females of our time is precisely a parade of rationalism, as unattractive as it is assuredly unnatural. Happily it is probably no more than a parade.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Katherine</hi> accompanied me to S. Aldgate's, where I preached to a congregation mostly composed of undergraduates. There was an orchestra in addition to a rather noisy organ. Chavasse read the prayers, and two students from Wycliffe Hall read the lessons. I was pleased with their reading, and told them so after service. My sermon was on "<hi rend="underline">Christianity, a man's religion</hi>", and I based it on the text cut on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Lightfoot's</hi><persName xml:id="1817"></persName> grave ^[written in Greek, section from 1 Corinthians 16:13]^. The congregation was very attentive, &amp; was, I venture to hope, interested. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Freddy Macdonald</hi> came into the vestry afterwards. Old Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chavasse</hi> was in the congregation. He is very lame, but seemed cheerful. I had a few words with him. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Katherine</hi> was enthusiastick in her flatteries, which must perhaps be charitably interpreted as indicating that she had been impressed. We were joined by <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Pember</hi>, &amp; walked around Magdalen walk before lunch.</p>
         <p>I lunched with mine host. Lang, Robertson, &amp; Cruttwell were there beside the ladies. After lunch I went to the Town Hall, and addressed a large meeting in the cause of the League of Nations. <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Selbie</hi> presided, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert Murray</hi> was on the platform. But there were no Heads of Houses present, though a good many undergraduates. I had tea with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spooners</hi><persName xml:id="383"></persName>: and then dined pleasantly in college. And so to bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>