<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> served and read the Epistle. The communicants numbered 17 altogether, as we had a <hi rend="underline">lev&#x00E9;e en masse</hi> of the garrison. Then the Town Band came outside the Castle, and played. I wished them 'a merry Xmas', and gave &#x00A3;1 to their box.</p>
         <p>After breakfast Ernest bicycled to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, Auckland, to preach, and assist Davison; and I motored to Spennymoor, where I preached and celebrated. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had started early on a round of celebrations &amp;c. So were all actively engaged in our ministry. We all motored in to Durham for Evensong &amp; Carol&#8211;singing in the Cathedral. I sate in the Throne, &amp; gave the Blessing. The singing was exquisite. After service I gave 'Christmas Boxes' to the vergers, and then we all had tea in the Bailey with Judge Moore &amp; his family. Their two sons were at home, the one has just left, and the other has just entered Cambridge. We got back to Auckland shortly before 7 p.m.</p>
         <p>Captain Hyslop came in to dinner, and had to endure the penance of listening to Milton's Ode on the Nativity, which, according to established custom, I read aloud afterwards, and also of attending service in chapel. But he did not display any repugnance, and carried himself very amiably. The weather through the day has been unseasonably warm, with occasional deluges of rain.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>