<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Darlington, and arrived at S. Cuthbert's in good time for the service at 11.15 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion, and was assisted by Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, the Rector, Macdonald, Knowlden<persName xml:id="5439"></persName>, and Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName>. Most of the clergy communicated. When the celebration was finished, I proceeded to the pulpit, and called upon the Registrar to read the "process general". When this had been done, I read as much of the Charge as I could get into 45 minutes. This was a good deal less than I had expected. Reporters were present. Then we went to the King's Hotel for lunch, which was well served. Most of the clergy seemed to take wine. I proposed the toast of the King, and then old Eade, the Vicar of Aycliffe, proposed the Bishop in a quaint speech. When I had responded, the company dispersed. I returned to Auckland immediately.</p>
         <p>My letter on "<hi rend="underline">Prohibition</hi>" appeared in the 'Times' under the heading "<hi rend="underline">Bishop of Durham's Reply</hi>". The quotations from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nicholas Murray Butler</hi> read very effectively. But Cannon's<persName xml:id="5417"></persName> attack on my speech in the House of Lords appears <hi rend="underline">in extenso</hi> in the local evening paper. I wonder whether that Journal will have the decency also to print mine.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>