<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning at Lambeth attending the Bishops' Meeting. <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop made a statement about the "Caution List" from which it appeared that at the present time there are more than 800 names on it</hi>. Of these some ought certainly to be renewed since death has removed them. It was agreed on my motion that all who had been ordained before 1880 might be presumed to have died. We agreed to defray the expense of re&#8211;printing the list after revision.</p>
         <p>I brought forward the subject of the "<hi rend="underline">Spiritual Healing</hi>" Mission at Bradford, and asked the Bishop to make a statement. The Bishop spoke with candour &amp; feeling. We were all inspired by his evident sincerity &amp; conviction. But he left on some, perhaps most, of us the suspicion that he was a weak good man carried away by his emotions. On the whole the discussion did good, &amp; will have the effect of warning our more sentimental bishops against a too facile surrender to the excitements of missions. I came away at the end of the morning session, &amp; lunched in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with Lord Muir Mackenzie. Then I returned to Auckland, travelling to Darlington by the 5.30 p.m. express. We arrived 1<hi>¼</hi> hours after scheduled time, having made a diversion to Lincoln as there was a stoppage on the main line.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1924.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Milner,</p>
         <p>I have received from one of your parishioners a letter in which it is stated that "during the past three or four years the rite of Benediction has been performed on some of the great Festivals" in Elton Church.</p>
         <p>I shall be glad to learn from you whether this information is correct, and, if so, what explanation you have to offer for so grave a breach of the law.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> H. S. Milner</p>
         <p>Elton Rectory Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Bishop of Ripon was my <hi rend="underline">compagnon de voyage</hi> as far as York. I read through Arnold Lunn's new book "Roman Converts". It is interesting, acute, &amp; suggestive. <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macmillan</hi> was in the train. He had some talk with me before we reached Darlington, where the car was waiting.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>