<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A most beautiful calm sunny late&#8211;autumnal day. I took the dogs round the Park, and revelled in its beauty. In the course of the morning I visited M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Spedding, the dentist. He seems to "shut the mouths" of many bishops! Then I prepared an address for use later.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> as far as Durham, where she went to Canon Cruickshank's<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> house to dine with the Judge; and we went to Hebburn, where S. Cuthbert's Church was celebrating its "Jubilee". <hi rend="bold underline">The incumbent – an undersized hirsute plain man named Marr – is, it is said, and I believe it, fashioned of the stuff whereof the calendared saints are made. He has toiled in that unlovely slum for 23 years, and remains a cheerful, good pastor at the end of the time, unsoured, unambitious, unfanatical. He is, indeed, an "Anglo&#8211;Catholick", but belongs to the relatively reasonable section of that faction. I was glad to go, and speak laudably of him to his people</hi>. Hard by the parish church is a rather conspicuous "Papist Chapel", and it was eagerly noted that a Papist had adventured himself into our service! On our way back to Auckland, we stopped at the College, and recovered Ella. I sate down for a few minutes and talked with Talbot. The Dean, vast and scowling, gave me but a sulky welcome!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>