<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I awaked with a bad headache, which oppressed me all day, and, together with the atrocious weather, went far to destroy my "enjoyment" of the service. The congregation, apart from the choir and the candidates, numbered about 50 persons. The disregard of Ordinations by the general body of church&#8211;people in Durham is very distressing, and argues a low standard of corporate religion. They seem to regard it a purely private affair with which they have no concern. I ordained 4 deacons and 4 priests. Among the former was <hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline">, who now, at the age of 37, carries through the purpose which, at 18, he had held strongly, but which he had all but relinquished in the interval. I gave him the "Jubilee" copy of the Bible, which Sir W</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">m</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Markby gave to me when I was myself ordained to the diaconate on June 5</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 1887, the year in which he was born.</hi></p>
         <p>We returned to Auckland immediately after the service, and, after lunch, I sent Ernest back to Sedbergh in the car. He enters on his clerical life at a relatively advanced age, but he has the powers of speech and temperament, which may, if rightly disciplined and directed, carry him far. For the present he remains a school&#8211;master.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>