<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The two main features of modern history are the development of nationalities and the growth of individual freedom. The interest which above all others is its own lies in tracing these processes, intimately connected as they are with one another.</p>
         <p>Bishop Creighton. Introduction to C.M.H.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Acton</hi> in his Inaugural Lecture at Cambridge in 1895 justified the stress he laid on Modern History <hi>"</hi>by the argument that it is a narrative told of ourselves, the record of a life which is our own, of efforts not yet abandoned to repose, of problems that still entangle the feet and vex the hearts of men".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Its study fulfils its purpose even if it only makes us wiser, without producing books, and gives us the gift of historical thinking, which is better than historical learning".</p>
         </div>
         <p>"Historical thinking" might serve as the subject for this "Inaugural Address", though I am not quite sure what it means! In any case I must needs concern myself with the students of History, not with the writers, and disclaim personally any higher character. The Historical Association has as its first aim 'the advancement of the study and teaching of History'.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>