<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>My birthday brought letters of goodwill from some of my old friends. <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName> sent a telegram from Java. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Radford</hi><persName xml:id="1204"></persName> wrote from Oxford. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tommie Hall</hi><persName xml:id="75"></persName> and my godson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Spelling</hi><persName xml:id="7"></persName>, and the ever faithful <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> wrote. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur</hi><persName xml:id="3128"></persName> wrote from Minehead: and a card brought "Many happy returns of the day from all at S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Hild's". <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me his good wishes, and added an election story. A female candidate was asked if she was in favour of a tax on bachelors, and immediately replied: "<hi rend="underline">I thought I had told you that I am not in favour of taxing any raw material</hi>".</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rudd</hi> of Trimdon Grange sent me a telegram of congrat<hi rend="superscript underline">tions</hi>. The local dentist came to see me, &amp; counselled the holding on to my surviving teeth as long as possible!</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with the dogs, stopping to look at the Footpath on my way. The lad <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ivan Thornton</hi> (v. p.47) was there, and we had some more talk. I invited him to see the Castle. He said he would come tomorrow at 3 p.m.? Will he?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nancy Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi> [sic] me a beautifully written letter from Bishopwearmouth, sending me "much love and a kiss". The young lady is, I think, aged eight; &amp; I sent her this doggerel:&#8211;</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Three times twenty and then add one,</p>
         <p>So old is the BISHOP at sixty&#8211;one,</p>
         <p>An old, old, very old man,</p>
         <p>So long is the time since he began</p>
         <p>His way in the world to pick and choose,</p>
         <p>To pick the nice, and the bad refuse.</p>
         <p>So when NANCY sent him a kiss &amp; her love,</p>
         <p>He returned the kiss, &amp; he kept her love.</p>
         <p>For kisses won't keep, but love keeps ever,</p>
         <p>When Bishops &amp; Birthdays have passed for ever.</p>
         <p>H.D.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Mayor and Mayoress of Hartlepool sent me a telegram of "heartiest congratulations &amp; best wishes" for my birthday. It is kindly meant.</p>
         <p>Whether it is a reaction from my recent activities, or whether it is a physical discomfort induced by my dental discomforts, or, finally, whether it is some special onset of the devil, I know not, but the fact cannot be concealed from myself, that I feel more dissolute, incapable of work, and capable of everything bad on this birthday than on any previous birthday! Yet no birthday was ever approached with a more solemn sense of waning opportunity and waxing obligations.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>I am pledged to move a resolution in the forthcoming session of the National Assembly, which affirms the rule <hi rend="bold underline">that the clergy should retire from work at the age of 70</hi>. If that rule should become part of the Church's law, I have only 9 years of active ministry left. Robertson of Brighton fulfilled his historic ministry in six years: but he was not a bishop, tied hand and foot by a futile and wearing system. I have now been a bishop for nearly 7 years, and I know how straight are the limits within which my life is now confined. Shall I be able to fulfil the engagements to which I am already committed? I have pledged myself to write for the Home University Library a volume on the Reformation. If that were well done, it might be a piece of work which would be of considerable public service, and might gain for me some reasonable respect. But I see my days are filled with tasks which, though of no enduring importance, have an irresistible immediate claim: and I dissipate in speeches and sermons, which evaporate in utterance, the mental power which, if conserved, concentrated, and applied, might have done something worth doing. It is a very difficult situation. I am Bishop of Durham, and so long as that is true, the Bishoprick of Durham must have the first claim on my powers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi></p>
         <p>This is a self&#8211;centred and unworthy way of looking at the facts. Let me take a humble and more suitable tone. Here am I at the age of 61, with a prospect of (at most) nine years more active life, confronted by the obligations of this Bishoprick. A million and a half of my fellow&#8211;men are living within the sphere of my "spiritual jurisdiction". What am I doing to justify my name &amp; claim? Some malignant necessity seems laid on me to stand out in opposition to my contemporaries, who are all supported by zeal and enthusiasm. "Life and Liberty", "Copec", "Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement", &#8211; I am against them all. What wonder that men should eye me with a certain repugnance, and mutter under their breath, that I am an "accuser of the brethren"? And yet, what can I do? Under the older conditions, I think my way would have been easier: but now my discord with my environment is emphasized at every turn. At least, I can resolve in the years that remain to seek for the harmonies rather than the discords, &amp; to magnify such agreements with my brethren as I can reach.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>