<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished reading trough the book given me by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dillon – "The lost Dominion" by Al. Carthill. It is brilliant, and, alas, convincing. India <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> a lost dominion. The attempt to rear a democratic system of the Western type on the foundations of child&#8211;marriage and caste is foredoomed to utter failure. I was sure of that before I read the book. The writer's tone is not pleasing, and he allows himself in [sic] occasional references to Christianity which are needlessly offensive. There are also some gratuitously gross expressions here and there. But it is on the whole a powerful piece of work. </p>
         <p>I sent out copies of the Charge to divers laymen, including Lords Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName>, Grey, Daryngton<persName xml:id="5400"></persName>, and Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>:</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me a china owl, similar to that which adorns his own table.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derry</hi><persName xml:id="3688"></persName> sent me "<hi rend="underline">Poems of Today</hi>", a volume of verse by contemporary "poets", published by the English Association. There is a deep shadow of sadness on its pages, for many of the names of the authors are familiar as those of young men who fell in the Great War. The first pages which arrested my notice carried poems by "E. Wyndham Tennant", and 'William Noel Hodgson'. I remember the first as a glorious boy of twelve, coming with his mother to see us in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>: the last was one of the older boys of Durham School, when I was Dean. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>