<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>An ingenious gentleman some months since in jest&#8211;earnest, advised me to make haste with my history of the Church of England, for fear (said he) lest the Church of England be ended before the History thereof. </p>
         <p>This History is now, though late (all church&#8211;work is slow), brought with much difficulty to an end. And blessed be God, the Church of England is still (and long may it be) in being, though disturbed, distempered, distracted: God help and heal her most sad condition.</p>
         <p>Thomas Fuller's Address 'To the Reader' in his 'Church History of Britain'. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The 'Church of England Newspaper' has a vigorously written article by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon V. F. Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, headed 'A Grave Crisis', in which he points out the very being of the Church of England is endangered by the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholic' movement:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'Is the Church of England to vanish and give place to a nebulous thing called Catholicism, under cover of which each minister may teach and practice what he likes? How the wheel has come full circle! The Oxford Movement began as a movement in favour of authority: it has ended in the sheerest individualism'. </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>On the death of Archbishop Potter in 1747 an offer of the primacy was made to Butler, who had in 1746 been made a clerk of the closet to the king (on the death of Egerton, bishop of Hereford). Butler is said to have declined it on the ground that '<hi rend="underline">it was too late for him to try to support a falling church'.</hi> One of his nephews, John Butler, a rich bachelor, had previously shown his appreciation of the 'Analogy' by exchanging a presentation copy from his uncle for an iron vice belonging to a 'shrewd Scottish solicitor' named Thomson. Hearing, however, that his uncle had a chance of the archbishopric, he came up to town prepared to advance &#x00A3;20,000 to meet his first expenses.</p>
         <p>v. Dict. of N.B. Art: 'Butler' by L.S.</p>
         </div>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">Is the Church of England Christian?</hi>" This is the title of an Article 'by M.A. (Oxon)', which is to appear in "The Review of Reviews", and to which the Editor asks me to make answer. <hi rend="bold underline">I was foolish enough to say that I would send him something!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="5385"></persName> came to lunch, and afterwards walked round the Park with me. I offered him Trimdon, but he seemed afraid of being unfaithful to the School Mission if he left the work in Gateshead so soon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>