<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The present writer knew a Hindu officer, of great shrewdness and very fair education, who devoted several hours daily to the elaborate worship of five round pebbles, which he had appointed to be his symbol of Omnipotence. Although his general belief was in one all–pervading Divinity, he must have something symbolic to handle &amp; address.</p>
         <p>Sir Alfred Lyall. Asiatic Studies. 1907 (i.13.)</p>
         </div>
         <p>What is the difference between this officer's religious position and that of our own 'Anglo–Catholicks' who cannot worship without the reserved sacrament in the Tabernacle?</p>
         <p>I worked at a sermon for Manchester Cathedral on Feb. 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when collections are made for the local hospitals. My text is the title of Hickson's<persName xml:id="5413"></persName> book – "Heal the Sick": and I disprove the statement that physical healing was an integral part of Christ's Commission to the church. The influence of Christ's Religion on the development of medical science has been powerful, when indirect for good, when direct for evil. In the evening of Feb. 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I shall preach again on the same subject, &amp; set out my reasons for refusing to bind up Religion with Faith–healing.</p>
         <p>It was the servants' party, and there was a brisk performance in which M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith's dramatick ability was displayed to advantage.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>