<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[280]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The John of the Apocalypse is less of the theologian than S Paul, and less of the mystic than the author of the fourth Gospel, but he surpasses both in his revelation of the unbounded power of the exalted Christ. Nowhere else in the New Testament are the personal activities of Jesus Christ present in His Church, the glories of His heavenly life, or the possibilities of his future manifestation so magnificently set forth. The Christology of the Apocalypse may evade analysis, but it meets the need of the Church in time of storm and stress.</p>
         <p>Sarete "The Apocalypse" p. clviii.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I began the day by paying my Super–tax, a modest sum of £517:0:6! Then I wrote a series of letters, &amp; finished transcribing the sermon for Good Friday. In the afternoon I walked in the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; the dogs: &amp; on my return worked on the Book very vainly.</p>
         <p>I received a pleasant letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. He has been making inquiry about Hickson's<persName xml:id="5413"></persName> Mission in Johannesburg, &amp; learns that "it caused a great stir, but he c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> only find one positive proof of faith–healing, &amp; that was rather doubtful". So he has not been impressed!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>