<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[221]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>In much that is written about the superiority of western races the underlying assumption is that the standard by which peoples are to be judged is their capacity to participate effectively in the political and economic arrangements of modern western civilization.</p>
         <p>Oldham. 'Christianity&amp; the Race Problem' p. 77.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I began the day by writing to those unhappy children, Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> and Elsie<persName xml:id="2056"></persName>. It was a melancholy and painful task</hi>. Then I spent the morning in trying to write the article for the Hibbert Journal on "Spiritual healing".</p>
         <p>I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Murray</hi> telling me <hi rend="italic bold underline">that I had been "unanimously elected a member of Grillion's Club". He expresses himself very pleasantly. It is, of course, a compliment which I must (being human) value, but the distance from London &amp; my many engagements make it almost impossible for me to dine at my clubs in London</hi>.</p>
         <p>I started reading a volume published for the Student Christian Movement – "<hi rend="underline">Christianity and the Race Problem</hi>" by <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. H. Oldham</hi>. It is excellent in substance, form, and temper. Considering that the author is the Secretary of the International Missionary Council this is as surprising as it is credible. I really must begin to reform my ways, and take Foreign Missions more seriously. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>