<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[240]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Confirm a child at twelve, &amp; he neither understands it intellectually nor finds it an answer to any moral or mental need. Delay confirmation till sixteen, and you may have missed the opportunity of putting a boy in the way of finding God's help real just when he needed it most…I believe, therefore, from my heart that this age of about fifteen in the second year of Public&#8211;school life is, for Public schoolboys or girls, the right time for confirmation.</p>
         <p>Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> H. Costley White<persName xml:id="5409"></persName>, Headmaster of Westminster</p>
         <p>'The spiritual life of the adolescent' in 'Education &amp; Religion p179.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I received from Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> another very interesting letter. He certainly writes with ease, &amp; has a pleasant epistolary style. Then I wasted the whole morning in a fruitless effort to make an actual beginning with the book. What has befallen my wits that I have become so helpless?</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I walked round the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p>The Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> speech in the House of Commons last night was a notable performance, and ought to have a harmonizing effect on the country. Even the Labour men cheered him when he sate down.<note xml:id="551" n="1"></note></p>
         </body></text></TEI>