<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[287]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Of all the speculations the soul of man can entertain herself withall, there is none of greater moment, or of closer concernment to her, than this of her own Immortality and Independence on this terrestrial Body. For hereby not only the intricacies and perplexities of Providence are made more easy &amp; smooth to her, &amp; she becomes able, by unravelling this clue from end to end, to pass &amp; repass safe through this labyrinth, wherein many both anxious and careless Spirits have lost themselves; but also (which touches her own interest more particularly) being once raised into the knowledge &amp; belief of so weighty a conclusion, she may view from this prospect the most certain and compendious way to her own happiness, which is, the bearing a very moderate affection to whatever tempts her, during the time of this her pilgrimage, and a careful preparation of herself for her future condition, by such noble actions &amp; heroical qualifications of mind as shall render her most welcome to her own country.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry More</hi>. <hi rend="underline">The Immortality of the Soul.</hi></p>
         <p>A.D. 1662</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[288]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The morning post brought me a cheque from the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>. Twenty guineas for article no. 1. Also the <hi rend="underline">Hibbert Journal</hi> sent me eight guineas for my article on "Spiritual Healing".</p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for Newcastle Cathedral. It is the melancholy fact that sermon composition has come to be an almost intolerable burden. Why is this?</p>
         <p>After lunch I walked in the park, &amp; falling in with some of the youths who were playing football. I watched them play long enough to get neuralgia in <hi rend="bold">[288]</hi> the jaws! What ails the church that it can do nothing with these lads? They are frank and civil, though rough. I cannot but think that a healthy minded young clergyman might do much with them. But, as it is, they are sheep without a shepherd. I picked up two boys, <hi rend="underline">William Richardson</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Alfred Dougall</hi> and showed them the flowers in the conservatory. They came from Auckland Park, &amp; were very well mannered.</p>
         <p>I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. Also to Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> thanking everybody for their assistance in yesterday's procession. This letter was worded for publication if thought desirable, these good people like to have their goodness noticed, and  <hi>̶</hi>  proclaimed!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>