<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172] [sic]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>In the doctrine of the Holy Ghost we may find a standing&#8211;place for this law of suggestion … The law of suggestion …… will help to lessen the strain which has often been felt by many in the belief in God as a mere external monarch. It bids us practice rational co&#8211;operation with Him in whom we live and move and have our being. It is, therefore, in the realm of religious faith that we shall and ought to expect the most valuable results of the use of this law.</p>
         <p>Pannell 'Miracles which happen' p. 159, 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast, I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. Also, I revised the sermon on Marriage which I preached in Sunderland to the Mothers' Union three years ago, and which seems suitable enough for this Sunday, when the Gospel for the day presents our Saviour as a guest at the Marriage Feast in Cana of Galilee. After lunch I walked round the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>.</p>
         <p>I motored to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's, Roker, and preached to a large congregation which included an unusually large proportion of men. The "boat&#8211;shaped" church is acoustically very bad, &amp; preaching was therefore a labour, but I was assured that the people could all hear, &amp; they were very attentive. I returned to the Castle immediately after the service, &amp; arrived about 9.30 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>