<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There is abundant evidence, sound and unsound, to prove that the alleged curative effects of strong emotion in healing disease are not confined to any one or more forms of religion or social custom, but are universal. Mana, the Medicine Man, and the big drum have in their societies what M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hickson and M. Cou&#x00E9; discover in our own. The alleged cures, which we admit to be in some considerable measure genuine, may apparently arise under any imposing ceremonial.</p>
         <p>Sir Clifford Allbutt. 'Guardian', Jan. 9, 1925.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The papers announce that Harry Davis has been appointed Regius Professor of Modern History in succession to Firth. It is an excellent appointment. I wrote to congratulate him forthwith.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the second Manchester sermon. Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> and his daughter came to lunch. Afterwards I walked round the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Archbishop S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> sends me a long, kind, and partly hostile criticism of my charge.</hi></p>
         <p>The Dean's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> encounter with the Railwaymen took place last night, and seems to have passed off better than I had expected!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>