<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[213]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I went to 114 Henrietta Street, and had an interview with Mess</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Williams &amp; Norgate. I told them that I c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not let them have the History of the Reformation for the 'Home &amp; University' Library until the end of the year, as I had to get the little book on 'Spiritual Healing' off my hands first, and offered them the said book for publication. They accepted with suspicious eagerness, &amp; I finally pledged myself (&#x3B1;) to deliver MS. of the book on Spiritual Healing by July 1</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> and (&#x3B2;) to deliver MS. of the History of the Reformation by December 15</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I was careful to guard myself against contingencies by pointing out that I was no absolutely my own master as to be free to make an absolute promise. If I failed to produce the MS., they were not to accuse me of ill&#8211;faith</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then I went to the Church House, and endured another day of the discussion on Pensions. It was mortally dull. Save for a two&#8211;minute speech, which was cheered by the clergy (!), I limited myself to "voting the ticket". I lunched with Canon and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Scott, who were somewhat embarrassed when I mentioned that</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had invited </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><hi rend="italic"> to address a meeting at the Deanery a week before I addressed the Diocesan Conference on Spiritual Healing. I went across to the House of Lords, &amp; had tea. Their Lordships were not sitting, so I went into the Library, and wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. Also, I wrote to Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> suggesting that he, as an old Dunelmian, might go with me to the Durham Mission on Sunday.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>