<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[281]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>You complain of those persons who judge of a revelation not by its evidence, but by its substance. It has always seemed to me that its substance is a most essential part of its evidence; and that miracles wrought in favour of what was foolish or wicked, would only prove Manichaeism. We are so perfectly ignorant of the unseen world, that the character of any supernatural power can only be judged by the moral character of the statements which it sanctions. Thus only can we tell whether it be a revelation from God or from the Devil.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Arnold to D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hawkins. Life, vol ii. p.226.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Rainbow</hi> sends me flowers for Easter, and a long letter, not ill expressed for a child of ten.</p>
         <p>I motored in to Durham, and attended the funeral service of old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nutton</hi> who for half a century sang in the cathedral choir. He was so conspicuous by his wig, and self&#8211;consequence that he will be much missed. I lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, and had some talk with him about the pressing subject of the failure of Ordination candidates. He is less lucid than confident as to the possibilities of changing our system. Then I motored to Howden&#8211;le&#8211;Wear, and called on the parson, Spencer, with reference to the queer letter from a parishioner of his which came to me yesterday. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>