<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[275]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The theory of demons enabled the pious to hold firmly by the popular belief in its widest extent, without coming into collision with the demands of reason, and even in its literal sense without having recourse to the violent and artificially allegorical interpretations of the Stoics, which were regarded with suspicion by the strictly orthodox. <hi rend="underline">In this roundabout way a large number of educated people returned to the 'legends &amp; marvellous stories' which seemed to have been finally disposed of by criticism</hi>, and, according to Strabo, were only necessary for the masses &amp; the female sex. The search for &amp; discovery of such a compromise between the popular religion and a more rational theology presupposes a widespread, indestructible attachment to the gods amongst the philosophically educated, an earnest longing to find satisfaction in the positive belief of former times which no abstraction, however sublime, could afford.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Friedl&#x00E4;nder</hi> <hi rend="underline">Roman Life &amp; Manners</hi>. iii. 93</p>
         </div>
         <p>All this has a curiously modern sound. Substitute for "the theory of demons" some such phrase as "new scientific theories of matter" and the parallel is extremely close. "Sacramentalism" is the 'blessed word' which helps the superstitious sceptics to "faith"!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[276]</hi></p>
         <p>For Christians in the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> century "the 'daemons' of paganism became demons in our sense". (Inge<persName xml:id="427"></persName>). Sarapis "had a great reputation for miraculous cures, and invalids often slept in his temples". Of Isis Inge says: "No other religion practised faith&#8211;healing, by passing the night in temples on so large a scale".</p>
         <p>Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> wrote another very interesting letter. He certainly has facility in writing, &amp; seems to be an intelligent observer. I worked on the Book, but to little purpose, perhaps because I was agitated by my conversation with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, to whom I communicated my decision that the state of his nerves made it impossible for him to continue in office after this year. It is a pity for he suits me well, but he has no power of self&#8211;restraint, &amp;, of course, the more jumpy he is, the more helpless he becomes.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I walked in the Park. We looked at a football match which was in progress. One fine young man of 24, the Police Inspector's son, told me that he had been on the dole for 2 years! What kind of citizen will grow from compulsory idleness in early manhood? Idleness used to be associated with extreme hardship, &amp; therefore it was abhorrent: but we have now endowed it, and by consequence made it even attractive!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>