<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A wet day becoming comfortless and blustering as it advanced. The congregation in the Cathedral, though swollen by the Lord Mayor and his party, was disappointingly small. The service had occupied about an hour and a quarter before I could get away with my sermon, which was listened to closely, and took about 27 minutes to deliver. Several people came to lunch including Sir Ernest Miers [Henry Miers], who spoke about Davis. He expressed satisfaction at his appointment to the Oxford Professorship. During the afternoon I rested, and then went again to the Cathedral for Evensong at 7 p.m. The rain fell in torrents, and, no doubt, caused the congregation to be much reduced in number. Nevertheless, the Church was fairly full, though by no means crowded. The Dean read the prayers after the Anthem from the pulpit. There were not less than 70 men &amp; boys in the (voluntary) choir. My sermon, which took exactly half an hour in delivery, was listened to with close attention. It appears that one of the clergy in Manchester is attracting some notice by holding healing services in his church. So my criticism of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson</hi> had more relevancy than I had expected. The Dean expressed his agreement with me, &amp; the churchwardens thanked me: but I received the impression from the demeanour of my host &amp; hostess that <hi rend="underline">they</hi> were not wholly pleased!!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>