<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[203]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi rend="underline">Macbeth</hi>: How does your patient, doctor?</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Doctor</hi>. Not so sick, my lord,</p>
         <p>As she is troubled by thick–coming fancies,</p>
         <p>That keep her from her rest.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Macbeth</hi>. Cure her of that:</p>
         <p>Canst thou not minister to a mind diseas'd,</p>
         <p>Pluck from the memory a rooted sorrow,</p>
         <p>Raze out the written troubles of the brain,</p>
         <p>And with some sweet oblivious antidote</p>
         <p>Cleanse the stuff'd bosom of that perilous stuff</p>
         <p>Which weights upon the heart?</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Doctor</hi>. Therein the patient</p>
         <p>Must minister to himself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Macbeth</hi>. Throw physic to the dogs: I'll none of it.</p>
         </div>
         <p>It is interesting that earlier in the play, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shakespeare</hi> has introduced a reference to '<hi rend="underline">Touching for the King's Evil</hi>'</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>How he solicits heaven,</p>
         <p>Himself best knows: but strangely–visited people,</p>
         <p>All swoln and ulcerous, pitiful to the eye,</p>
         <p>The mere despair of surgery, he cures;</p>
         <p>Hanging a golden stamp about their necks,</p>
         <p>Put on with holy prayers.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went off to North Berwick to visit the Parker–Smiths. I made a final revision of the sermons, and tried to set my room in order. Then, after an early lunch, I motored to Darlington, and took train for Manchester. At the station I bought the "Morning Post", and found in it not only my little article on Patronage, but also a picture of myself! Canon Scott met me on the platform at Manchester, and drove me to his house. There was a pleasant party at dinner. The Lord Mayor was there with his wife. He is a tall, rather heavily built man, slow of speech, but intelligent. Professor Tout<persName xml:id="5426"></persName> &amp; his wife were also there. He is engaged in the melancholy task of moving from Manchester to Hampstead. A distinguished surgeon, named Burgess<persName xml:id="5427"></persName>, &amp; his wife, who sate next me at dinner, interested me. He had been in Mesopotamia during the tragic period. After the party had dispersed, I talked for an hour with mine host. The new Dean, Johnson<persName xml:id="5428"></persName>, is evidently not very popular. In any case, it would have been difficult for a man to follow so popular a personage as M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Cormick, but Johnson is not personally attractive.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>