<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[257]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was a considerable fall of snow during the night, and when morning broke the sun shone from a cloudless sky on a wonderland of beauty. Geordie<persName xml:id="571"></persName> and her Austrian Countess took their departure by the early train.</p>
         <p>The morning papers contain long obituaries of Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> with his portrait.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Book, and wrote most part of a chapter, but woefully poor stuff.</p>
         <p>After walking in the snow for an hour I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brilioth</hi><persName xml:id="5198"></persName> thanking him for his book on the Oxford Movement. It is a creditable piece of work, &amp; indicates vast industry &amp; considerable intelligence. The volume is adorned by an Introduction by the <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Gloucester</hi>, in which the Movement is absurdly magnified. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> is a strange creature, so dogmatic, &amp; in some directions so <hi rend="underline">born</hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00E9;</hi>, and yet breaking out into unexpected vagaries of liberalism now &amp; again: a man better for a friend than an enemy, though infinitely trying in both characters.</p>
         <p>I "ran through" <hi rend="doubleunderline">S. Augustine's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Confessions</hi> with the object of noting anything that could illustrate his attitude towards illness. He mentions his own sickness in boyhood, &amp; later: speaks of a friend's sickness &amp; death, &amp; describes his mother's death after 9 days of illness, but never alludes to any healing power in the church, or any incompatibility between sickness &amp; Christianity.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>