<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[253]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>On the whole, then, I cannot doubt that the Holy Sepulchre was really discovered as Eusebius declares it to have been: and I am as little disposed to deny that the Cross was discovered also, <hi rend="underline">as that the relics of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi rend="underline">Cuthbert or the coffin of Bishop Coverdale have been found here in England, in our own day</hi>.</p>
         <p>Newman. Essay on Miracles. p 326</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I received invitations to preach from Edinburgh, Coventry, and Nottingham. Also, a proposal that I would write a monthly article for the "Evening Standard" for a fee of &#x00A3;20 guineas per article. Might I not do something for the restoration of Escomb church in this way</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Sacriston, and there confirmed 55 persons. The parson, Hutton, is said to be a Hebrew scholar, but he is one of the feeblest mortals that ever wore a surplice. Also, I consecrated a burial ground. Then I returned as far as Durham, &amp; had tea with Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName> at the Club. After this, I went back to Auckland, and, in S. Peter's Church, confirmed 99 persons.</p>
         <p>Geordie Gore<persName xml:id="571"></persName> and her friend, an Austrian Countess, arrived on a short visit. The weather was very fine and warm.</p>
         <p>Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> sent me a cutting from the 'Daily Graphic', headed 'Christ or Cou&#x00E9;<persName xml:id="5436"></persName>', in which my address to the Diocesan Conference was commented upon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>