<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[164] [sic]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Emmott described last night a remarkable silver dish which had been recently fished out of the Tyne, &amp; was now in the possession of the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName>. The experts assigned it to a date as A.D. 200. Lord S.<persName xml:id="3465"></persName> spoke of the relics of the Order of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John of Jerusalem, which had been carried to Russia by the Gar. Paul, were sent in to the South of Russia to avoid capture by the Bolsheviks, &amp; had now been deposited in a Church at Revel. He thought that the Roman branch of the Order would get hold of them.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning, &amp; part of the afternoon in the Commission<hi rend="italic">. On the whole we got nearer to the head of the practical problem than ever before, but the nearer we get the more insoluble does the problem appear. I scribbled on an envelope the following observation. "The truth is that on the "Catholick" theory of the Church, you can never get a final spiritual court out of national &amp; provincial authority", &amp; passed it to Justice Sankey<persName xml:id="3403"></persName>, Sir Lewis Dibden<persName xml:id="909"></persName>, &amp; Chancellor Errington<persName xml:id="5423"></persName>, who all agreed with my proposition.</hi> I lunched with Justice Sankey: Later I caught the 5.30 p.m. train at King's Cross. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Gainford<persName xml:id="2216"></persName> came into my carriage, &amp; talked for nearly an hour. He is not cheerful about the outlook for mining. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> joined the train at York, the car met us at Darlington, and we got back to the Castle about 10.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>