<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>My first business was the following telegram to the Historical Association in Newcastle. It explains itself:</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>"On returning from London late last night I learned with dismay that, by a gross and inexplicable error, for which I am myself alone responsible, the meeting of the Historical Association had been entered in my calendar under the wrong date. I am extremely sorry, and beg to offer my sincere apologies. Both myself and the manuscript of my address are at the disposal of the Committee".</p>
         </div>
         <p>This evoked the following response.</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>"Many thanks kind telegram. Can you possibly lecture Armstrong College today 5.30 p.m".</p>
         </div>
         <p>Of course I had to go, though I was feeling very ill, as I must have contracted a chill last night. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> accompanied me, &amp; I succeeded in delivering my lecture "<hi rend="underline">On the Gift of Historical Thinking</hi>". But it was too much for me, &amp; when I got back to the Castle, I went straight to bed. This was the more annoying as we had a dinner party. Davis &amp; his wife, Rawson &amp; his wife, Spurrier<persName xml:id="5431"></persName> &amp; his mother. They all stayed the night.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Among my letters was one from Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> definitely refusing to be ordained. It was expressed in a very sincere, modest fashion, which made me regret the more the decision it conveyed. He would have made a good parson</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>