<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[215]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Ballance</hi> came for me to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and carried me off to his house (106 Harley Street). <hi rend="bold underline">There I celebrated the Holy Communion in his wife's bedroom, and administered the sacrament to them both</hi>. Afterwards I talked with him for 3/4 an hour. He spoke interestingly of his experiences during the War, when he served as Superintendent of Surgical Operations in the Mediterranean Campaign. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Victor Horsley</hi>, who combined the characters of a distinguished surgeon and a fanatical total abstainer, was carried by his zeal for what he called 'temperance' <hi rend="bold underline">into telling the troops in Gallipoli that if they abstained from alcohol they need not bother about putting on their sun&#8211;helmets</hi>! If he had been less rigid in his own habit, he might have lived through his experiences in Mesopotamia. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ballance</hi> spoke contemptuously of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Freud's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Psycho&#8211;analysis</hi>, but did not appear to have any real knowledge about it. From Harley Street I proceeded to King's Cross, where I took the 1.15 a.m. train to Darlington. By way of prophylactic on the train I lunched, but it is against my liking. <hi rend="italic">The process of eating when one is being shaken by the motion of the train, and sickened by tobacco smoke, is by no means agreeable.</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Leng</hi><hi rend="italic"> met me with the car, &amp; I was in the Castle soon after 6.30 p.m.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>