<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[271]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Canonisation was one of the regular forms of popular protest in purely political quarrels: there was a constant stream of pilgrims to the tombs of Simon de Montfort, of King Henry vi, &amp; even of the selfish &amp; despicable Thomas of Lancaster, who worked far more miracles than many of his betters. While the soul of Martin iv was expiating in Dante's purgatory those surfeits of Bolsena eels and Vernaccia wine, his body was busily working miracles on earth. So also did the body of Gregory ix, a far more remarkable Pope, though he was believed by many to have had an illegitimate son, &amp; certainly did more than any other Pope of the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century to degrade the first Franciscan ideal.</p>
         <p>v. Coulton<persName xml:id="4746"></persName>. 'From S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Francis to Dante'. p. 309.</p>
         </div>
         <p>We may not forget that a miracle does not itself certify Divine action. It may proceed from below as well as from above. Beelzebub also casts out devils, and his wonders are such that they may deceive the very elect. Before the astonishing cures effected at Lourdes can be accepted as acts of Divine Power, we must know not merely their character, but the interest which they necessarily serve. And when this question is pressed what can the answer be save that the Lourdes miracles have served the interests of error, superstition, and an ignoble commercialism.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[272]</hi></p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and in the chapel of the Castle instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bothamley</hi><persName xml:id="3854"></persName> to his honorary canonry, &amp; licensed four curates. Then I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, &amp; afterwards presided at a meeting of the Durham Finance Board. There was but little business so that the meeting was soon over. I went to Calcleugh's shop, &amp; ordered a supply of envelopes. Then I went to the Cathedral for Evensong. After service I had tea with Wilson, &amp; then accompanied by Wilson &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, I motored to South Shields. Here I instituted the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> A. W. Lister</hi>, lately Vicar of Tanfield, to the Rectory of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Stephen, which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thurlow</hi><persName xml:id="5272"></persName> vacated when he went to Durham. The size and excellence of the choir surprised me. I suppose there were as many as 20 young men &amp; 30 boys. There is an enthusiastic &amp; very capable choirmaster, who is a volunteer, to whom the credit is due. There was a considerable &amp; very attentive congregation. I was pleased to see that a number of the neighbouring clergy attended the function. After the service we returned to Auckland, leaving Wilson in Durham on the way. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> told me that he had been appointed lecturer in Pastoral Theology in Cambridge. This is excellent for him, &amp;, perhaps, for the diocese.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>