<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[229]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The hand of Death is heavy on the diocese. At breakfast a telegram from Dobson arrived with the ill news that his Rector, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Little</hi>, had died last night quite suddenly. This is an untoward event, for Little was really a most valuable man, and a most efficient Rural Dean. The Deanery of Chester–le–Street is the weakest in clerical personnel of all the Deaneries. Thus two Rural Deans have died on two successive days. Hughes and Little are difficult to replace.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Address, and finished it. By the evening post, I sent it registered to the Editor of the Hibbert Journal, to whom it had been promised.</p>
         <p>In pouring rain I walked round the Park with the dogs. Beck found a hedge–hog, &amp; with mighty clamour not to say much discomfort of her nose carried it to the Castle.</p>
         <p>This morning as I was dressing a bird sang lustily so close that I looked for it. Suddenly within a few feet I saw the songster, a starling, singing from the window–sill.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Rainbow</hi> sent me some crocuses &amp; snowdrops with a well–written &amp; well–expressed letter. He signs himself, 'Your loving boy', and is evidently prepared to take that character. Well, I am not sure whether money spent on his schooling is not as well spent as on any other subject: &amp; Rainbow<persName xml:id="5557"></persName> is as poor as he is meritorious.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>