<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[278]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>In one respect alone have the miracles recorded by the evangelists a more real ground than the mass of miracles of which we have the relation. Medical science has never guaged [sic], perhaps never enough set itself to guage [sic] <hi rend="underline">the intimate connexion between moral fault and disease</hi>. To what extent, or in how many cases what is called illness is due to moral springs having been used amiss, whether by being over&#8211;used, or by not being used sufficiently, we hardly at all know, &amp; we too little enquire. Certainly it is due to this very much more than we commonly think, and <hi rend="underline">the more it is due to this the more do moral therapeutics rise in possibility and importance</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M. Arnold</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Literature &amp; Dogma</hi> pp 143&#8211;4.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bruce</hi> quotes this passage on p. 52 of his well&#8211;known book, "<hi rend="underline">The miraculous element in the Gospels</hi>', which was originally published in 1886. Psychotherapy has made great strides since then, and no really competent apologist would be able to adopt his unyielding attitude. Few now would defend the historicity of the "nature&#8211;miracles': and most would freely consent to identify the miracles of healing with the cures wrought by the faith&#8211;healers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[279]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> sends to me the letter "<hi rend="underline">A call to action</hi>" which is to be published shortly with signatures attached. It is, I understand, composed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Glazebrook</hi>, and it incorporates two sentences of mine. Of course, the importance of such a document will be determined by the names which it carries. Diocesan bishops are not included among the signatories. There are 7 deans: 7 Professors of Oxford &amp; Cambridge: 9 Heads of Houses: 7 Archdeacons: 5 Headmasters of Public Schools: 10 canons: 13 Members of the Church Assembly. This is really a poor show, and contrasts badly with long lists which the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks can produce. It really looks as if the Church of England has been definitely lost to Protestant Christianity.</p>
         <p>I chose a sermon which I preached on Good Friday in 1903, &amp; which has been published in the volume, "<hi rend="underline">The Value of the Bible</hi>", for use in Sunderland on Good Friday next: and my morning was wasted in typing it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitterick</hi> writes a grateful letter about my paying John's school fees at Leatherhead.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> A. G. Nash</hi>, Vicar of Whitworth, a sour little Anglo&#8211;Catholic, came to lunch. His predecessor, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hick</hi>, who takes a pension from the living, is reported to be garnering guineas by taking occasional duty. How does this remunerative activity consist with a pension granted on the ground of physical disability?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>