<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>In the year of our Lord 1514 the whole Church of God enjoyed peace, and her ancient privileges, all her princes with great devotion were nursing fathers and protectors of her; no storm did trouble her, no schism to break her unity: there was an harmony, a good correspondence (as to the matter of faith and religion) between the Church of Rome, and all the princes and states of Christendom: and till then, neither in England, nor in any other country of Europe, had there been such a question ever disputed viz. whether a Catholike might not be a good subject.</p>
         <p>Jerusalem and Babel: or the Image of both Churches, being a treatise historically discussing, whether Catholikes or Protestants be the better subjects, by P. D. M. 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> edition. London 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and caught the 8.33 a.m. train to York, which brought me there in excellent time for the choral celebration of Holy Communion in the Minster which inaugurated the session of the newly&#8211;elected Convocation. The Archbishop celebrated, &amp; I read the gospel.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi></p>
         <p>The proceedings in Convocation were not wildly exciting, and the torpor engendered by a dull programme was deepened by the unseasonable warmth of the weather. <hi rend="bold underline">We approved the ordination of Deaconesses</hi>, &amp; liberally defined their functions: and we unanimously "turned down" the proposal to revive the order of sub&#8211;deacons. This sensible decision surprised me, but even an Upper House of Convocations has its lucid intervals! We wasted much time in drafting an address to the King, an idle form which might well be dispensed with, but idle forms are, like Charles II, an unconcionable[sic] time in dying. We agreed on a form of inquiry preliminarily to the granting of a marriage licence: &amp; did some other trifling business. Then, our business concluded by 5.30 p.m., I had tea at the station, and returned to Auckland. My journey between York and Darlington was eased by a pleasant conversation with a young engineer, who lodged in Darlington. His name was Lionel Maddison, and he gave his address as 32 Cleveland Terrace, Darlington. He told me that he was 25 years old, and had been educated in Shrewsbury school under Alington. Leng met me with the car, and brought be back to the Castle in time for dinner. <hi rend="bold underline">The oculist sent me my new pince&#8211;nez glasses, but the spectacles for reading did not come with them</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>