<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>No one has more doubts than he can carry: the way of life is not found to stop and come to an end in the midst of a volcano, or on the edge of a precipice. Dangers occur, not from the disclosure from any new, or hitherto undiscovered, facts, for which, as for all other blessings, we have reason to be thankful to God; but from our concealment or denial of them, from the belief that we can make them other than they are; from the fancy that some a priori notion, some undefined word, some intensity of personal conviction, is the weapon with which they are to be met.</p>
         <p>Jowett. 'The Interpretation of Scripture'. p. 445.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey Fry</hi><persName xml:id="5424"></persName> about the division of the "split" patronage, enclosing my schedule of a division of the livings. Then I read until lunch, after which I motored to Durham in order to officiate at Captain <hi rend="doubleunderline">Apperley's</hi> burial. The service was held in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's Church, and the interment was in Bow cemetery. After the funeral I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The eclipse of the sun, which took place this afternoon, could not be 'observed' as the day was cloudy and wet.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir William Bragg</hi> thanking him for his book, "<hi rend="underline">Concerning the Nature of Things</hi>": and to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Justice Sankey</hi>y<persName xml:id="3403"></persName>, thanking him for his '<hi rend="underline">King's College Commemoration Oration</hi>'.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>