<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Archbishop D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> writes in very kind terms about the charge. He would not acknowledge the copy I sent him until he had read it:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Having done so, will you allow me to say how thoroughly I enjoyed the reading, &amp; how highly I value it, in view of present needs. It seems to me extremely important: &amp; I was delighted to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dean Inge's</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName> article on it in the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi>. Your examination of the Enabling Act and its working out seems to me to be very valuable. Surely an effort ought to be made to organise the laity. I was also deeply impressed by your criticism of '<hi rend="underline">Copec</hi>', &amp; your reference to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dougall's</hi> book".</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D'Arcy</hi> is a man of genuine eminence, &amp; I value his approval.</p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and caught the 1.34 p.m. express, arriving in King's Cross half an hour after time. I drove to Park Lane, where I found the <persName xml:id="3465">Scarbroughs</persName><persName xml:id="3466"></persName> at home. I went on at once to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; dined with the Brethren in de Candole's house – Inge, Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, Gilbertson, de Candole, &amp; myself made up the party. I returned to Park Lane about 10 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
         <p>The Fellows of New College are said to be in a quandary as to the choice of a Warden to succeed Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">They have, however, reached agreement on the one point that they will not have a clergyman</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> The choice seems to lie between <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fisher</hi> (who, however, is said not to want it, and is regarded as not wholly desirable on account of his professed agnosticism!) and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Matheson</hi>, who is, I think, a Nonconformist. The wheel has gone full circle. <hi rend="bold underline">After having enjoyed a monopoly, the Anglican clergy now find themselves held to be disqualified by their cloth. The fact sets one thinking</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>We had a good deal of talk about the ecclesiastical situation, which appears the more baffling, the more it is considered. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi> says that his Liberal Evangelical clergy now number as many as 700. But the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks claim as many as 5000: and the Federation of Catholick Priests has more than 1200 members. The "Fiery Cross" is entertained at York Minster, and the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> is able to announce that many of the theological professors &amp; other clergy of position have consented to take part in the new venture of publishing a Catholick Commentary on the Bible!!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>