<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[195]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Seven years ago I was consecrated Bishop of Hereford in Westminster Abbey, and today I review the time with humiliation and regret. Nothing has been achieved, and something has been lost. I might have taken the course which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> seems to be taking in Birmingham viz. made myself the fighting chief of "liberalism" against "Anglo–Catholic" obscurantism. But there is an important difference between my position in 1918 and that of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> in 1924. I had been attacked, insulted, and opposed. A considerable movement had been organised in the country and in the diocese with the view, first, of defeating my appointment, next, of making my position intolerable. <hi rend="bold underline">It seemed to me that the only possible position for me to adopt as Bishop was to ignore everything and exhibit an appearance of complete indifference.</hi> With <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> it was otherwise. He had not been generally attacked. No opposition was offered within his diocese. His appointment was generally welcomed as at least superior to what was understood to be the alternative. He "went out of his way" to emphasize his opposition to Anglo–Catholicks, and has continued to maintain an attitude of open antagonism. He may be right. I certainly have gained nothing by magnanimity. But in any just estimate of the episode, the difference must be recognised between the two cases.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p>In the Christian religion the cultus of the saints, of relics and of images, is a contribution of the masses. It is in the nature of things that religion should exhibit something of the character of those who practise it. Why should the masses not have set their mark upon it? The thinkers certainly set theirs, and it is a mark of a more perilous kind……</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>By the development of its worship and of its theology, the Church adapted itself to the feelings, customs, and prepossessions of the adherents of very varying degrees of culture, whom it received from all sides.</p>
         <p>Duchesne. Early History of the Christian Church </p>
         <p>Vol. III p. 12. (Translated by Claude Jenkins.)</p>
         </div>
         <p>What is "spiritual healing"? I spent the morning in seeking an answer to that question. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle, where she went to her dentist, and <hi rend="bold underline">I visited the oculist (Dr Wardale, 76 Jarrow Rd.) He examined my eyes, and recommend glasses which I ordered at Winter's in Grey Street.</hi> Then we had tea at the Railway Station, and returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The weather became milder as the day advanced, though the wind continued to be cold. But the trees are beginning to show the aspect of spring.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>