<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After leaving my bags at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I walked to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and had a long afternoon with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. He described the meeting at Birmingham as a great success, but admitted that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes's</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> speech was bitter and indiscreet. He said that 400 "sympathisers" were enrolled after the meeting. <hi rend="bold underline">I pointed out that it was essential he and his friends shd realise the consequences of defeating Revision.</hi> Had they made up their minds whether they were ready for disruption? I suggested that the heads of a pronouncement which they might issue with a view to rallying all those who believe in the Church of England as worth preserving, and promised to do all in my power to assist, pointing out, however, that the bishops were in a difficult position as having to give the final word on the proposals for revision. Then I walked to Downing Street and had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duff</hi><persName xml:id="5425"></persName> about the split patronage. He was, of course, friendly enough, but he alarmed me by some cryptic allusions to the propriety of consulting the parochial church councils. However, in the end he promised to do what he could. Then I walked to Londonderry House, &amp; lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady L.</hi> She wanted to talk to me about C. who is causing anxiety. Then I returned to the Athenaeum, had tea, and recovered my bags. I went to King's Cross and caught the 5.30 p.m. express. The train was nearly empty, so I travelled in comfort, and actually dined on board. Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> met me at Darlington.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>