<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The wind had fallen, and snow covered the land to the depth of several inches when the light of morning disclosed the scene. I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Patrick Wild</hi> was among the communicants. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> went into Durham by the early train to attend the service of the "Dons and Beaks".</p>
         <p>I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Then I read through an admirable little volume of Hibbert Lectures, "The Challenge of Life" by L. P. Jacks<persName xml:id="320"></persName>, which is full of good things, and yet leaves one with the inevitable question it raises only answered by a phrase. After lunch I took the dogs with me, and walked round the Park with Patrick Wild.</p>
         <p>In view of the Ecclesiastical Courts Commission's meeting this week, I read again <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maitland's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Canon Law in England</hi>, with the object of assisting myself to form a just estimate of the position taken up by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darwell Stone</hi><persName xml:id="4414"></persName>. He fails to indicate what authority would be superior to his own version of what Catholicism requires an English clergyman to do and teach: and no final Court that cannot possess that superiority in the minds of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" will serve the turn of the Church of England.</p>
         <p>After dinner I read aloud to my ladies Count Paul von Hoernsbr&#x00F6;ch's "Fourteen Years a Jesuit", which I have been re&#8211;reading with fresh interest.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>