<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[228]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The really beautiful story of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John and the Robber is related in the Treatise "The Rich Man's Salvation" by Clement of Alexandria. This writer died not long after A.D. 211. May we allow ourselves to believe that this is a genuine history? S. Clement describes it as 'a story that is no mere story, but a true account of John the Apostle that has been handed down, and preserved by memory'.</p>
         <p>I spent the day, save for my constitutional in the Park with the dogs, in working at my Address on 'Faith Healing' or, rather, 'Spiritual Healing', for the Conference: but I cannot satisfy myself. The Bishop of Bradford sent back the Manchester Sermons with a note in which he still harps on the old fallacy viz. that Christ commissioned &amp; endowed the Church for Healing.</p>
         <p>A telegram from Spurrier<persName xml:id="5431"></persName> announced the death of old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hughes, the Vicar of Winston, &amp; first Rural Dean of Barnard Castle. This is very regrettable.</p>
         <p>Thompson, the Minister of the new district outside Stockton, came to lunch, &amp; took away with him the chalice &amp; paten, which were held in trust here for his church.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Lord Balfour sent me a pleasant note acknowledging my letter.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>