<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[274]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Under the Empire Education, we may say, is the One, Religion is the Many. In the first we find a uniform system, which extends unchanged from farthest East to farthest West. In the second we find a sea of confusion.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bigg</hi>. '<hi rend="underline">The Church's Task under the Roman Empire</hi> 32</p>
         </div>
         <p>Might not this stand as a description of our modern world? The Educational Interest is becoming unified, and on the whole stands for one ideal of de&#8211;Christianised education. But Religion? What does it stand for? Was there ever such a Babel of answers to that question?</p>
         <p>I worked at the Book, not very fruitfully. After lunch I walked round the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. He is [sic] much confusion about his future, &amp; I think tends to flinch from the inevitable limitations of the parson's lot. It is the case that the outlook in the Church has now become beyond all precedents gloomy and uncertain. I cannot wonder that the young men of parts &amp; promise refuse to contemplate the career of a clergyman.</p>
         <p>An offensive paper – the Freethinker – was sent to me, presumably because it contained a ribald article on Faith&#8211;healing, in which abuse &amp; contempt were liberally poured upon the Bishop of Durham!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>