<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[263]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>What is a man,</p>
         <p>If his chief good and market of his time</p>
         <p>Be but to sleep and feed? a beast, no more.</p>
         <p>Sure he that made us with such large discourse,</p>
         <p>Looking before and after, gave us not</p>
         <p>That capability and god&#8211;like reason</p>
         <p>To fust in us unus'd.</p>
         <p>Hamlet.</p>
         </div>
         <p>An excellent &amp; a characteristic letter from Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> arrived. He approves highly of my Hibbert article, the proof of which I had sent him. "I wonder how our Healers get over our Lord's unwillingness to work wonders, &amp; the small value he attaches to them? – an <hi rend="underline">obviously</hi> genuine touch in the Gospels, which no editor could have put in. Are not Faith Healing and Numinousness both straws at which a drowning orthodoxy is clutching in despair?" <hi rend="bold underline">Fawkes shares my amazement at Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> preface to Brilioth's<persName xml:id="5198"></persName> book. It "reads like a mere exhibition of temper"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> In the 'Literary Supplement' there is a finely discriminating review of Brilioth's book, which makes no reference to the episcopal preface. I am wondering who can have written it. There are very few persons capable of writing with so much intimate knowledge, so much intellectual insight, &amp; so much literary finish. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Ernle</hi><persName xml:id="1394"></persName> or <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Bailey</hi> perhaps.<note xml:id="553" n="1"></note></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[264]</hi></p>
         <p>I turned away from the book on Spiritual Healing, and wrote a twenty&#8211;guinea article (1300 words) on the Church Assembly for the Evening Standard. This is the first of the six covenanted contributions.</p>
         <p>I motored with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> into Durham, and officiated at the funeral of Captain Rogerson in S. Oswald's &amp; Bow Cemetery. There was a considerable gathering of people. Rogerson's loss will be felt in many directions, for, though not a man of outstanding ability, he was companionable &amp; active.</p>
         <p>Then I went to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, and talked over some matters of diocesan business with him. I had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, and then went to the Town Hall, where a meeting of the newly formed 'Durham Society' had been convened. The Papist Mayor presided, a pleasant, up&#8211;standing illiterate man, and Major Tarporley from Newcastle made a halting speech. I spoke "off the surface of my mind" for a quarter of an hour, and said little that was worth saying, but, perhaps, nothing that ought not to be said<hi rend="bold">: </hi>&amp; then the meeting ended. Ella &amp; I returned to Auckland, where Gobat<persName xml:id="5408"></persName>, the Socialist Vicar of St James' Darlington, came to dinner. He had been lecturing on some modern authors in a dissenting chapel under the chairmanship of Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>