<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Suggestion points inevitably beyond itself towards faith as its ultimate goal. In like manner mental analysis and autognosis lead on to the problem of mental synthesis, in which a general philosophic and religious outlook on life is inevitably demanded of both patient and analyst. The patient must work out his own salvation, it is true, but he will turn to the analyst for help and is justified in looking for such help. Some training in ethical and religious philosophy on the part of the analyst is a well&#8211;nigh indispensable part of his intellectual equipment in dealing with certain types of psycho&#8211;neurosis. On the other hand, no form of spiritual healing can safely dispense with medical opinion, and in particular with the specialized knowledge in neurology and psychiatry, which every well&#8211;qualified psycho&#8211;therapist possesses.</p>
         <p>W. Brown. Suggestion &amp; Mental Analysis</p>
         <p>p. 125. (London 1923)</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[199]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent, perhaps wasted, the morning in reading on the tiresome but fascinating subject of psycho&#8211;therapeutics</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> It is clear to me that there is a section of ecclesiastically&#8211;minded doctors who are prepared to "go one better" than the ecclesiastics in the rush back to medieval superstitions: &amp; they join hands with the anthropologically&#8211;interested pundits of science who (like <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rivers</hi>) are amused to see the latest phase of "civilized" medicine reproduce the savage crudities of the earliest!</p>
         <p>After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, where I presided in the Common room of the Castle over a meeting of the Rural Deans, which I had convened in order to consider the financial situation of the diocese. They were all present together with the Archdeacons &amp; Canon Goldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>, Captain Carter, &amp; Clayton also attended. <hi rend="bold underline">We decided that the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> visit the Rural Deaneries, &amp; expound the purpose &amp; claim of the Diocesan Fund</hi>: that the Finance Board sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be requested to reduce its estimates: that the parochial quotas sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be raised, but that the Rural Deans sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be requested to raise a voluntary addition to meet the enlarged expenditure: &amp;, finally, that there should be such a re&#8211;casting of our financial system as w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> bring the rural deaneries into a more direct relation with the diocesan Board. After the meeting I interviewed an Ordination candidate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>