<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. I completed the letter to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, which I had begun in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and sent it off. Also, I prepared some notes for tonight, and wrote to Frank Berry &amp; Sir Charles Ballance. After lunch I walked in the Park for more than an hour, the mildness of the air &amp; the sunshine making the walk delightful. Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> accompanied me to Gateshead, where I had tea with the Westcotts<persName xml:id="5385"></persName> in the rather squalid house, which does duty for a vicarage before going to the rickety hut which serves for a church. The building was filled but mainly with girls, and the congregation was attentive. I am not sure whether there is really much advantage in making a parish here, or much prospect of doing so. But the decision has been taken, and must stand. After service we returned to Auckland, that is, I did, for Jimmie was dropped in Spennymoor.</p>
         <p>I finished the novel which I read in the train yesterday – "The Four Feathers" by A. E. W. Mason. It is quite a good story.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> wrote a civil letter in acknowledgement of the Primary Charge. He cordially agrees with what I say about the Enabling Act, but is less accordant with my observations on Copec.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>