<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[234]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I come now to the next wisest of their customs: having no use for physicians, they carry the sick into the market&#8211;place; then those who have been afflicted themselves by the same ill as the sick man's, or seen others in like case, come near &amp; advise him about his disease and comfort him, telling him by what means they have themselves recovered of it or seen others recover. None may pass by the sick man without speaking and asking what is his sickness.</p>
         <p>Herodotus. I. 197.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This account of the Babylonians may be based on a misunderstanding of the facts. Probably in ancient Babylon as in modern eastern cities the diseased were a prominent feature, begging alms of every passer&#8211;by, and this perhaps is what Herodotus saw. Anyway, we are assured that "the profession of medicine was well organized and systematic" among the Babylonians.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'The profession of a doctor carried with it grave responsibilities, even as far back as the time of Hammurabi. One has only to read the list of fines to which a surgeon was liable if he accidentally inflicted unnecessary damage on a patient in treating him'.</p>
         <p>(v. Hastings. Enc: of R. &amp; E. iv. 746)</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[235]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Davison came to see me about his schools. I took occasion to ask his opinion about spiritual healing. He had evidently read and thought much on the matter. He said that during his 14 years ministry at Deafhill he had been in close association with the local doctor, who w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> often "hand over" cases to him, especially when it was vital that they sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be calmed &amp; sent to sleep. He had been told that he possessed the healing gift, but he was not so sure himself, and did not care to accept responsibility for assuming that he had. He expressed some contempt for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson</hi>: and gave me the general impression of good sense.</p>
         <p>I motored to Stillington, and confirmed 98 persons, of whom the majority were males. After tea with the Vicar, I went on to Stockton, and confirmed two sick persons in their houses. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bott</hi>, <hi rend="underline">the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> John's</hi>, who had arranged these confirmations, showed me his church, &amp; called my attention to the Sacrament reserved in a side&#8211;chapel for the sick. He assured me that he made no other use of it. Then I went to Holy Trinity, &amp; there I confirmed about 170 persons, of whom the overwhelming majority were females. After the service I returned to Auckland, feeling more than commonly fatigued. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>