<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is true that the spectacular cases are for the most part hysteria, as my old friend Charcot well explained, but the influence of what I may call the psychic extends to the whole of disease. Time after time I have strained my conscience so far as to assure a patient of his recovery in a crisis as of pneumonia, or a fever, in the hope – not rarely successful – of fanning the spark of life to a flame ……</p>
         <p>A sporting doctor in the Yorkshire dales – an old friend of mine – once cured a young woman who had lain in bed for months "palsied" from the waist downwards, by taking a ferret out of his overcoat pocket, &amp; after 3 solemn warnings, putting the animal into the bed. Two painfully silent minutes followed; then with a scream the paralytic sprang out of bed – as she said, "when a cold nose touched my leg". Meanwhile she was rigid with terror!</p>
         <p>Sir Clifford Allbutt. Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925. </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wasted the morning in writing a short article on 'Patronage' for the 'Morning Post'.</hi></p>
         <p>After lunch we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; I) motored into Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the Church Building Society, and then went to the Castle to meet the Rural Dean, the Vicars of Christ Church, &amp; S. George's, Gateshead, &amp; Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName>, to consider the future of the <hi rend="underline">Durham School Mission</hi>. After two hours discussion, the subject remained as perplexing as before, and I reserved my verdict. We had tea in my rooms, and then M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Henson rejoined us, &amp; we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Then I wasted at least two hours in trying to draft an Address to the King for the ensuing Convocation. At last, I had to abandon the attempt for lack of material, and wrote to tell the Archbishop as much!</p>
         <p>Ella went to a Missionary meeting in the Edgar Hall, &amp; came back less edified than disgusted, for, of the two "deputations" who were the chosen orators, she described the one as 'dull', &amp; the other as 'vulgar'. This severe description coming from so charitable a judge was certainly well&#8211;merited. The audience numbered about 40 persons. And this in a parish of 18,000 souls, in which the Vicar is an enthusiastic advocate of foreign missions! The life seems to have perished from all ecclesiastical activities. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>