<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[250]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I wrote 1) to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, 2) to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, 3) to Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName>, 4) to Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName>, 5) to Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>. </p>
         <p>After lunch I walked in the Park with the dogs for an hour. Later I motored to Easington Colliery, and there preached at Evensong in the temporary church. There was a large congregation, in which were unusual numbers of young men. The service was well rendered, &amp; there were no illegalities, save the omission of the "State" Prayers. But two servers were "adorned" with lace, and there was an extinguishing of candles after the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> collect, which was an unnecessary &amp; (to me) novel proceeding. However in the main I was well pleased, &amp; indeed was foolish enough to promise that I would present a copy of the Revised Bible for use on the lectern. We returned to Auckland after the service. The mildness of the weather was, perhaps, the reason why the road was frequented by numbers of amatory couples! I got back to the Castle in time for dinner, &amp; found that Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had already returned from New Shildon where he had been officiating. There was a brief report of my address to the Conference in the 'Observer'. It reads rather savagely, &amp; is set out under an aggressive headline!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>