<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[289]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Thank God, no paradise stands barred</p>
         <p>To entry, and I find it hard</p>
         <p>To be a Christian, as I said!</p>
         <p>Still every now and then my head</p>
         <p>Raised glad, sinks mournful – all grows dread</p>
         <p>Spite of the sunshine, while I fear</p>
         <p>And think, "How dreadful to be grudged</p>
         <p>"No ease henceforth, as one that's judged.</p>
         <p>"Condemned to earth forever, shut</p>
         <p>"From heaven!"</p>
         <p>But Easter day breaks! But </p>
         <p>Christ rises! Mercy every way</p>
         <p>Is infinite, &#8211; and who can say?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Browning</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Christmas&#8211;Eve and Easter Day. </hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>A brilliant Easter morning. The sun shone through faint and warming mist upon a landscape on which Spring had thrown a hardly discernible tint of living green. The Chapel looked most beautiful. Cosin's plate stood on a fair linen cloth heavily adorned with lace, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dillon's gift. I celebrated the Holy Communion alone, as Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> had gone to assist at Bishopwearmouth, &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> was celebrating at Tudhoe Grange. We mustered in all 21 communicants, of whom seven were males. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[290]</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Bishop Middleham, where I preached the sermon and celebrated. The service was choral but not too elaborate. There was the charm of rural simplicity about the worship, and the attention of the people was exemplary. The communicants numbered about fifty. After service I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> came with me to Durham in order to attend Evensong in the Cathedral. The singing was very good. After service I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. Then I motored to Newcastle and preached in that Cathedral at Evensong. There was a large and attentive congregation, &amp; much rather noisy musick. After this service I went on to Jesmond Parish Church, and preached into a broad&#8211;casting box. There was a considerable congregation, and a large choir.</p>
         <p>In the vestry awaiting my arrival there was a letter from the "station director" of the Broadcasting Company, asking me to omit the section of my address which referred to the recent <hi rend="underline">cause celebre</hi>. I didn't open the letter until after the service, and therefore the request could not have been granted: but if I had opened it, no difference would have been made. For, indeed, it is intolerable that episcopal sermons should be "censored" by broadcasting clerks! After this performance I returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>