<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[211]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Church Assembly occupied itself all day with the Pensions Measure, which was defended with astonishing ability by Lord Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>, an octogenarian with the aspect &amp; manner of a young man. There was a vast parade of clerical opposition, but it crumbled away into nothing before a promise that there should be a further opportunity for revision in July. I sate through most part of the division, but limited myself to voting with the majority. I lunched with Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName>, and met his vicar, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McGowan, a rather self&#8211;confident and manysided [sic] divine. As I was walking away from the Assembly, I was accosted by a somewhat seedy&#8211;looking person, who announced himself as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ben Tillett</hi>. He said that he had been one of the Labour Deputation to Russia. I inquired whether he or any of his colleagues could speak Russian. He replied in the negative, but added that they had the services of three Government interpreters! He was very confident that all the accounts of Bolshevism current in this country were altogether false, and waxed eloquent on the corruptions of the Russian church. I asked whether the Report of the Labour Mission would be published, &amp; he said that it would appear immediately. I promised to buy a copy, &amp; so we parted. I wondered what induced him to speak to me, &amp;, indeed how he came to know who I was.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[212]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>As I walked to Westminster, I was hailed by two of Baldwin's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> secretaries, Fry<persName xml:id="5424"></persName> &amp; another. They spoke of the retirement of Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName> from the Deanery of Westminster, as about to take place, &amp; begged my opinion as to his successor. I replied that, if an appointment were made from the chapter, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> was the only possible man. But as a matter of policy I disliked appointing from the chapter. I added that I hoped a diocesan bishop would not be chosen, as there was a real danger of deaneries being reduced into retirement&#8211;posts for the episcopate. I mentioned the name of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName> as deserving consideration. Later I dined in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName>. He said that there was a desire that I should return to Westminster as Dean. This is probably a <hi rend="underline">canard</hi> hatched in Westminster. It has been mentioned to me by Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, Storr, and Westlake. But, of course, it is wholly out of the question, even if it were seriously proposed., How could I afford to live in that Deanery on its tenuous endowment? <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> is evidently making way in Birmingham; the younger clergy of his diocese are coming about him freely. I had some talk in the club with the Bishop of Winchester, a dull, well&#8211;meaning man who is in a place too big for his powers.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>