<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[236]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We are well persuaded that disorders of the mental health of a community cannot be easily excluded from the purview of the epidemiologist. Certainly the so&#8211;called epidemic manias and psychoses of the Middle Ages were, like many of the mental phases manifested during the late War, closely associated, temporally and geographically, with widespread disorders of physical health.</p>
         <p>F. S. Marvin. Science &amp; Civilization p. 264</p>
         <p>Science &amp; Health by F. G. Crookshank</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and confirmed 118 persons in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles's Church. Afterwards I had tea in the Vicarage. Aird said that the Papist Mayor was one of his parishioners: that the Dean's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> observations on his (the Mayor's) absence from the Cathedral on the customary occasion last November was generally disapproved: that he himself had called on the Mayor &amp; dissociated himself from the Dean's attitude: &amp; that some of his people had wanted him to do as much in the pulpit. Then I went on to Stockton, and confirmed 132 persons in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Church. Both these confirmations pleased me. The candidates were of the right age, and very attentive. But the atmosphere of the churches was asphyxiating. I returned to the Castle after service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>