<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[220]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The tenacity with which Protestant nations cling to the orthodox tenets of the Reformation can scarcely, I think, be said to bear any fixed proportion to the national morality, and Sweden, which of all Protestant countries has been most conspicuous for its prolonged legislation against heterodoxy, is said to be equally conspicuous for the scandalous amount of illegitimacy among the people.</p>
         <p>Lecky. Rationalism in Europe, p. 393.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi> report the first edition of Quo tendimus? is sold out, &amp; that they "are considering the question of issuing a new edition". I told them that, if they did so, I should like to write a preface.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Downing</hi> writes to say that "the Commissioners are prepared to appropriate so much of the consideration money as may be required for the discharge of the mortgage to Q. A. B. in respect of the provision of electric lighting at the Episcopal Residence".</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and was there from 11.30 a.m. to after 5 p.m. Institutions, Board of Finance, and talk with my Suffragan. When I got back about 5.30 p.m., I found a desolating letter from Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>