<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Once a man thinks that he can heal by prayer, and laying–on of hands, and anointing, nothing will stop him. Not only will women, more than men, practise the new–faith–healing, but all, Christian or not, who discover a gift that way. "The importance becomes almost irresistible," Mr Hickson<persName xml:id="5413"></persName> says, who is the chief of these healers. I am well aware that he has a beneficial influence, but his account of his work, and of his cases is too like <hi rend="underline">Science &amp; Health</hi> for me.</p>
         <p>Stephen Paget "The Faith &amp; Works of Ch Science"' p.209</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the morning in reading through Sir Clifford Allbutt's admirable Harveian Oration (Oct. 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1900) on 'Science and Medieval Thought'. Old Firth of Esh came to pour out his woes, and stayed to lunch. Then I motored to Gateshead, and, after talking over the matter with Stephenson, and visiting the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's Mission, decided that the original project of forming a new parish sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> stand. On returning to the Castle, I communicated my decision to the clergy concerned.</p>
         <p>Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName> sent me the draft of a public declaration on the situation in the C. of E., which he and his friends have it in contemplation to put forth. I sent it back to him with a letter.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>