<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[291]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>It is not at all uncommon to find people analysed </p>
         <p>until they have lost all initiative and self&#8211;respect</p>
         <p>until they have lost all initiative and self&#8211;respect [sic],</p>
         <p>and left to pull themselves together as best they can,</p>
         <p>because the analyst has himself no adequate synthesis </p>
         <p>of life, which he can pass on to the patient. I know </p>
         <p>many patients who have had this experience, </p>
         <p>and their condition is deplorable beyond all expression.</p>
         <p>Harold Anson<persName xml:id="4107"></persName>. "Spiritual Healing". p. 113.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went off for a short holiday i.e. to carry out another mad series of unnecessary engagements. </p>
         <p>I received from Herbert an ardently expressed letter of thanks for the Revised Bible that I presented to his mission church at Easington Colliery. My visit seems to have impressed the pitmen. "People were very astonished that you – a real Bishop  <hi>̶</hi>  should condescend to read the lessons, though they thoroughly enjoyed your reading. A criticism I have heard not once or twice has been "Eh! It was lovely: it was as good as two sermons". I have made a note of that: it is very illuminating". In point of fact my principal object in reading the lessons was indirectly to let Herbert know how much I dislike the careless and indifferent mode of reading which is now so general.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[292]</hi></p>
         <p>Rain fell in the forenoon, but then the weather became fine. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked in the Park with the dogs. It pleased me to see so many people enjoying themselves innocently. There can be no question as to the improvement in the manners of the people which education has effected: whether there has been an equal improvement in their morals is more doubtful.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Patrick Wild</hi><persName xml:id="5226"></persName><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Crawfurd Inge</hi><persName xml:id="4597"></persName><hi rend="italic">, both promising though very different lads who will start at Oxford this October, came to visit us.</hi></p>
         <p>Canon Bothamley<persName xml:id="3854"></persName> sent me a small book which he has just published. Its title has almost a 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century sound:&#8211; "The Heart of the Eternal or Strong Consolation for those that labour and are heavy laden. A cordial for Christ's brave Soldiers in the Battle of Suffering". I opened at p. 124 and found a confusion between Domitian and Diocletian. </p>
         <p>I paid &#x00A3;9:3:0. for the copy of the Revised Bible which I presented to the mission church at Easington Colliery. Also I paid &#x00A3;25:19:9 for the insurance of the two cars.</p>
         <p>It is sufficiently obvious that any small sums that may drop into my account from the tip of my pen will not long stay in it.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>