<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[248]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The Editor of the British Medical Journal sends me the issue of June 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910, which contains the articles on Faith healing, and says that it is the last surviving copy.</p>
         <p>Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> sends me a volume, "Christianity &amp; Auto&#8211;suggestion" by Brooks &amp; Charles. I read it through at once, &amp; found much that was illuminating &amp; to my purpose relevant.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park with the dogs. Beck managed to get a piece of stick fixed in her palate. With Bryden's aid I removed it.</p>
         <p>Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, Parry&#8211;Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName>, &amp; Hodgson<persName xml:id="5274"></persName> came here to talk over Escomb. We agreed that I should instruct Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> to get out estimates: that we would make no public appeal at present: but would privately solicit subscriptions.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> addressed the Congregational Union at Leeds yesterday, and quoted the Bishops of Durham &amp; Manchester as illustrating different types of thought within the churches. Of course he said that they were</hi> <hi rend="underline">both</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">right! His speeches are improving both in form and substance. In addressing the Sectaries he took his stand definitely as a professed Christian. This is, I must needs think, both significant and consoling. Also it argues a measure of courage, &amp; a genuine conviction</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>