<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[273]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>This, then, is the last thing I can say about Lourdes. It would be quite useless as evidence – indeed it would be almost impertinent to dare to offer further evidence at all – yet I may as well hand it in as my contribution. It is this, <hi rend="underline">that Lourdes is soaked, saturated and kindled by the all but sensible presence of the Mother of God</hi>. I am quite aware of all that can be said about subjectivity and auto&#8211;suggestion, and the rest; but there comes a point in all arguments when nothing is worth anything except an assertion of a personal conviction. Such, then, is mine.</p>
         <p>R. A. Benson. "Lourdes" p. 79.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This day was altogether wasted. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi> came to see me, and lunched here. He accepts the living of Lynesack, vacated by Marsh, who follows Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> at Tudhoe Grange. I went in to Durham with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and presided at a meeting of the Clergy Training &amp; Maintenance Board. After tea at the Castle, we motored to Sunderland, where I distributed prizes to the boys of the Bede Collegiate School. The Mayor presided, &amp; I was surprised to see the Victoria Hall almost completely filled. My speech was heavy &amp; not very suitable, but it was applauded. The triumphant Boy, Ord, rehearsed a very long Prologue composed in verse by the Head Master in which I was grotesquely complimented!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>