<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>And there still preserved among Christians traces of that Holy Spirit which appeared in the form of a dove. They expel evil spirits, and perform many cures, and foresee certain events, according to the will of the Logos. And …… many have been converted to Christianity as if against their will, some sort of spirit having suddenly transformed their minds from a hatred of the doctrine to a readiness to die in its defence, and having appeared to them either in a working vision or a dream of the night. Many such instances have been known.</p>
         <p>Origen against Celsus Bk. I c 46</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> writes to thank me for my "most interesting charge". I spent the morning in going carefully through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dearmer's</hi> book <hi rend="underline">'Body and Soul'</hi>. He is a confused and self&#8211;contradictory writer, with more knowledge than he can assimilate, and as much conceit as knowledge. I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> in the Park, and then read through <hi rend="underline">"Miracles which Happen, a Study in Suggestion &amp; Auto&#8211;suggestion"</hi> by a parson, the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Arthur P. Pannell</hi>, a careful piece of work. I ought to take at least a year over my pronouncement on Faith Healing, instead of a few weeks! And then there is the little book on the Reformation.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>