<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[233]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There is what appears a genuine story of a Chinaman who had paid an idol priest to cure his daughter, but she died; whereupon the swindled worshipper brought an action of law against the god who for his fraud was banished from the province.</p>
         <p>Tylor. Primitive Culture. ii. 171</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Winston, and officiated at the funeral of the late Rector, Hughes. There was a fair muster of local clergy, &amp; the church was filled with neighbours. I heard with regret that a pit was being opened on the river&#8211;bank below the Church, and already the glorious view of the Tees had been damaged by the felling of trees.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Canon Brown of Monkwearmouth, offering him the Rectory of Winston &amp; the Rural Deanery of Barnard Castle. Also to Bothamley<persName xml:id="3854"></persName> of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas, Durham, offering him the Canonry.</p>
         <p>I went to Bearpark, and there confirmed 47 candidates. Then I went on to Brandon, and confirmed 67 candidates. I found there among the clergy, Nevill Hudson, the young man who was not altogether happy at Knutsford. He seems to have settled in comfortably, &amp; hopes to be licensed in due course. The Irishman, Mack, whose wife died, has decided not to return to Brandon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>