<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[268]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">The infidels have hooted witchcraft out of the world;</hi> and the complaisant Christians have joined with them in the cry. I do not so much wonder at this, – that many of these should herein talk like infidels. But I have sometimes been inclined to wonder at the pert, saucy, indecent manner wherein some of those trample upon men far wiser than themselves; at their speaking so dogmatically against what not only the whole world, Heathen and Christian, believed in past ages, but thousands, learned as well as unlearned, firmly believe at this day. I instance in D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Smollett and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Guthrie, <hi rend="underline">whose manner of speaking concerning witchcraft must be extremely offensive to every sensible man who cannot give up his Bible</hi>.</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Journal. July 1770.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Yet the excellent Wesley was quite wrong, and the pert contemners of the Word were quite right. All the church now follows in the wake of "the infidels". Zeal does not seem often to go along with insight, and truth always makes its first appearance in disreputable company. It is, precisely, this circumstance that makes resistance to truth so easy to good men.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[269]</hi></p>
         <p>I expended the morning on Lourdes, to which I meditate devoting a chapter. I have before me 4 accounts from different points of view:</p>
         <p>α. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Huysmans'</hi> "<hi rend="underline">The Crowds of Lourdes</hi>", an aesthetic Papist whose faith is exstatic, &amp; whose repugnance is extreme.</p>
         <p>β. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Oxenham's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">The Wonder of Lourdes</hi>", a sentimental Dissenter, whose belief in the miracles is strengthened by a perception of the journalistic effectiveness of the believer's pose.</p>
         <p>γ. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thurston's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Lourdes</hi>". The article in Hastings' Encyclopaedia, a prevaricating Jesuit's affected candour &amp; constrained confession.</p>
         <p>δ. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Butlin's</hi> '<hi rend="underline">Remarks on Spiritual Healing</hi>'. A sympathetic doctor's examination of the miracles.</p>
         <p>None of these perceives the religious objection to the recognition of the cures as supernatural or miraculous exertions of Divine Power. </p>
         <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I walked round the Park after lunch. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Singapore called, and had tea. He had never before seen the Castle</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I had some talk with him. He said that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><persName xml:id="5413"></persName> had conducted a mission in Singapore: that many non–Christians attended: &amp; that it was difficult to estimate permanent results. He told me that the late Metropolitan, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lefroy</hi>, had been anointed in his last sickness. After he had departed, I motored to Haughton–le–Skerne, &amp; there confirmed 44 candidates. I was much pleased with the attention and apparent devotion. After the service, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>