<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[293]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mark's, Jarrow, writes to say that on Sunday evening he was 'listening in with a little group of shipyard workers' to my broad&#8211;casted sermon, &amp; that they were "much gratified" at my reference to the Dennistoun case. This sounds bad. However, he goes on to assure me "that from further remarks he had heard from many others who were listening to me, that in Jarrow at any rate, my words had touched some consciences, &amp; made a very deep impression'. This is better. </p>
         <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, Crawfurd<persName xml:id="4597"></persName>, &amp; Patrick<persName xml:id="5226"></persName> motored to High Force to see the water&#8211;fall. I stayed at home and tried, but vainly, to do some more of the book. After lunch, Patrick and I walked round the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p>A dentist in Scotland is moved by my broadcast address to write to me. He has been drinking, &amp; is alienated from his wife &amp; children, whom he loves. He thinks he would keep the pledge if he might sign it with me, &amp; begs me to write to his wife! I don't quite know what he means by "signing with me". But I wrote out a promise for him to sign, &amp; me to witness. Also, I wrote to his wife. It's rather "drawing a bow at a venture".</p>
         <p>The "Times" reports the death of old Miss Cockshott. I wrote to Miss Graham in condolence.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>