<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[230]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Whickham, stopping at Gateshead to have lunch with the Rector, and there I officiated at the funeral of Canon Little. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> read the Lesson, Stephenson read the prayers, &amp; I took the Commitment. The church was filled with parishioners, who were, I think, genuinely distressed by their parson's sudden death. After the funeral I had much talk with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> on diocesan business. On returning to Auckland I wrote to the Lord Chancellor, &amp; to the patronage secretary about the appointment of Canon Little's successor.</p>
         <p>The Thanet Templar Convention of the International Order of Good Templars at a Meeting of the East Kent District Lodge representing 44 lodges &amp; temples &amp; 2434 members held at Canterbury sends me a resolution "deeply regretting the utterances of the Lord Bishop of Durham on the Temperance question", &amp; calling upon that gentleman "to review his attitude for the future"!</p>
         <p>Violet Carruthers<persName xml:id="1261"></persName> wrote to ask me to recommend a good commentary on S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Epistle to the Romans for her Lenten reading. I sent her a list of books.</p>
         <p>Cecil Ferens<persName xml:id="4218"></persName> sent me an affectionate &amp; very grateful letter in reply to what I wrote to him in condolence for the death of his brother Lionel.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>