<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[282]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I believe Shakespeare was not a whit more intelligible in his own day than he is now to an educated man, except for a few local allusions of no consequence. As I said, he is of no age  <hi>̶</hi>  nor, I may add, of any religion, or party, or profession. The body and substance of his works came out of the unfathomable depths of his own oceanic mind: his observation and reading, which was considerable, supplied him with the drapery of his figures.</p>
         <p>S. J. Coleridge. Table Talk. P 312.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The weather today has been almost oppressively warm. By consequence, I have been abnormally stupid and idle. Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Haldane</hi> celebrated her 100<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year yesterday. Her picture appears in the newspapers with very flattering notices. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to tea, and gave me some account of his doings in London. He is in expectation of his father's death, &amp; then he will have to be the 'bread winner'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked round the Park with the dogs about 5.30 p.m. Rain fell with considerable vehemence, an ill promise for tomorrow.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> sent me a note acknowledging the proof of my preface to the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> edition of "Quo tendimus"?, and expressing his approval of it.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>