<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[247]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Whatever exorcises the demon of Fear and brings to the sick man's bed the Angel of Hope is a powerful aid to medical treatment. It is therefore as unscientific as it is inhuman to put aside faith healing as mere superstition.</p>
         <p>'Medicine &amp; Miracles'. B. M. J. June 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910. </p>
         </div>
         <p>I paid the balance due on account of Income Tax, viz &#x00A3;720:1:8 making a total for the year of &#x00A3;1220:1:8. Now there is the Super&#8211;tax to be dealt with.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Parks with the dogs, and fell in with five miners, all young men, with whom I had some conversation. All were unemployed. They spoke with much bitterness of their condition and, indeed, my heart bled for them. There seems to be no chance of improvement. Rather it is the case that the situation in the mining industry worsens daily.</p>
         <p>We motored in to Durham, &amp; there I confirmed 125 persons in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas's Church. <hi rend="bold underline">The atmosphere was asphyxiating, the congregation restless, the candidates confused, the Bishop himself listless and dull. I came away in an ill mood! When shall I persuade the clergy that the ventilation of their churches is a matter of grave spiritual importance. The Prince of the power of the air has an easy triumph over Christians who are poisoned &amp; somnolent by an ill&#8211;aired building</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>