<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[277]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The Passion and Death of Jesus Christ are solemnly upheld before the eyes of Christian people throughout this week: what do they really mean to us here and now? The thought of them will be hard&#8211;pressed by holiday plans in most minds: will they succeed in holding any place at all? And what ought to be the thoughts which the solemn &amp; sustained presentation of the Passion &amp; Death of Jesus Christ should suggest to Christian minds? </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> assisted. We were in all 8 communicants.</p>
         <p>At 3 p.m. I confirmed 146 candidates in South Church. Everything seemed to go wrong. The discrepancy between the sexes was abnormally bad – only 36 boys to 110 girls! The atmosphere was asphyxiating, and the coughing incessant! Add that the weather was detestable, &amp; the discomforts of the function are sufficiently indicated.</p>
         <p>We (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Ernest, &amp; I) motored to Staindrop, where I preached, and dedicated the bells. Ernest read the lessons, Before beginning my sermon, I read the Exhortation to Communion in the Prayer&#8211;book. After service we dined at Raby Castle. <hi rend="bold underline">Lady Barnard has not yet seen Durham Cathedral</hi><hi rend="bold">!!</hi> I pledged them both to put an end to this scandal, by lunching in Auckland, &amp; then going with me to Durham. After dinner we returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>