<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I succeeded in finding the passage in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lea's</hi> <hi rend="underline">History of Auricular Confession </hi>which describes the ecclesiastical rules under which physicians were required to act. Those rules do provide a remarkable example of that co&#8211;operation of priests &amp; doctors which is now generally advocated, but the cruelty &amp; degrading hypocrisy which any serious attempt to obey them must have involved were so terrible, that, in point of fact, they could not be held back from becoming rapidly obsolete. The casuists came to the rescue of the authorities, and "saved their face" by explaining away their demands. <hi rend="doubleunderline">S</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Pius V</hi> was only tolerable because he was followed in due time by Signore. An "infallible" Church must needs be in the hands of the Casuists, for it can hardly <hi rend="underline">cancel</hi> its rules however practically disastrous; it can only <hi rend="underline">explain</hi> them so that they are not obeyed!</p>
         <p>In the afternoon, I walked in the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and in the evening there was a dinner party in honour of the newly married <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strakers</hi>, followed by a reception of some neighbours. For this purpose, the electric light is invaluable. It shows up the large rooms to advantage. It was not a very interesting company, but, in its own rather heavy manner, it appeared to enjoy itself, and had dispersed soon after 11 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>