<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[226]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Shrove Tuesday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle about 8 a.m., and motored to York (66 miles). The weather was very misty when we started, but became brilliant before we had reached Northallerton, &amp; continued so until 2 p.m., when it became very rainy &amp; blustering. No less than 11 bishops attended the consecration of the new Bishop of Sodor and Man. Among them was Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> of Birmingham who assured me that the new bishop was one of the "Liberal Evangelicals", &amp; genuinely liberal. He is a big, rather heavy looking man, who doesn't suggest much mental activity. The service in the cathedral was admirably arranged, and the music exquisite. When the function was ended we lunched in the County Hotel, &amp; then motored back to Auckland through heavy rain. We were delayed by a puncture, but even so traversed the distance in 2 hours &amp; 15 minutes. The rain fell mercilessly all the time.</p>
         <p>I revised the new preface for the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> edition of "Quo tendimus?", and sent it to Hodder &amp; Stoughton. I received a letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> reporting the progress of the garage. The main difficulty seems to arise from the dishonesty of the people of Johannesburg, who will not pay for the work they order.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>