<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[225]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from Lord Balfour inquiring whether any Reformed Church in the XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and XVII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries had issued an official condemnation of the Copernican theory. I wasted the morning in trying to verify my belief that none such had been issued, and finally had to send my illustrious correspondent nothing better than my personal impression!</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Blackhall, where I dedicated a painted window erected by an old lady, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lee, to the memory of her son. The donor was not well enough to attend the service, so I visited her in her house, &amp; talked for a few minutes. Then we returned as far as Durham, where we had tea with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Leng came with a long face to report the back spring broken. So I hired a car &amp; set off with Wilson &amp; Clayton to South Shields, where I instituted the Rev. T. Anderson<persName xml:id="5433"></persName> to the Vicarage of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's. As we were returning a man simply walked into the car, and of course was knocked down. We carried him to the Infirmary, and where greatly relieved to learn from a very pleasant young doctor – who told me that he came from Durham &amp; was named Ingram – that no bones were broken. So I charged a by&#8211;stander to see the man returned to his house, &amp; we continued our journey. At Durham we dropped Wilson, &amp; were met by Leng with the Wolseley car. The weather was wretched.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>