<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[241]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday in Lent, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>What keeps a congregation fixed and absorbed is a preacher's feeling what he says, and being himself, as it were, in the words which come from him. Reality is the powerful and moving element on such occasions. Reality is of itself always striking, always effective. There is a sympathetic impulse always felt, as soon as ever the mind recognizes the fact that the person speaking is in earnest: he is immediately the centre of all minds around him, when this is seen: there is life and intentness in the whole scene of thought, just as when a wire vibrates, or a spring leaps and fastens the stray material that comes near it.</p>
         <p>J. B. Mozley. Essays. vol ii. p. 153.</p>
         </div>
         <p>There was a thin veil of snow on the frozen earth when morning broke in bright sunshine. These sudden changes of temperature perplex the birds and damage the trees.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. I motored to New Seaham (leaving <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> in Durham on the way), &amp; had tea with the Dillons<persName xml:id="3784"></persName>. Then I preached at Evensong in the church, &amp; after service returned to Auckland, stopping in Durham to hear 'Athalie' in the Cathedral, and to recover the ladies.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>