<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[262]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The practices of the modern Greeks show in many respects an instructive parallel to the ancient worship of the healing gods. Everyone has heard of the famous sanctuary of the Virgin at Tenos, but this is a quite modern foundation, and there are many local shrines less known but no less effective to that end. The most remarkable of all is perhaps the Church of the Virgin at Ayassos in Lesbos.</p>
         <p>v. Rouse. Greek Votive Offerings. p. 235</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I had a woeful letter from Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>. The dolorous liberty of the divorcee is evidently unpalatable</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Heighington, and there confirmed 15 persons. There were no candidates from Aycliffe and Denton. The church is interesting, &amp; contains a pre&#8211;Reformation pulpit, with an inscription <hi rend="underline">orate pro anim</hi><hi rend="underline">&#x00E2;</hi>.</p>
         <p>Later, I motored to Evenwood, &amp; confirmed 67 persons. There were but 19 males, which is a very bad proportion. In spite of this, however, I was pleased with the service. The candidates were very serious, &amp; the congregation very attentive.</p>
         <p>The weather has again become cold &amp; squally. In the afternoon there was a glorious rainbow.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>