<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Another utterly wasted day! The brief interval of fresh air has given way to a rise in temperature, &amp; the spring&#8211;like conditions, which have persisted through January have returned. Wall&#8211;flowers, snow&#8211;drops, crocuses, violets, and primroses are all blooming in the garden, and the pear&#8211;blossom is on the verge of bursting into view. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Phelps, the Vicar of Withington, lunched here. Incidentally he mentioned William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; it appeared that he knew his family well, and that they were excellent folks. So far, so good. Professor Bacon<persName xml:id="3057"></persName> of Yale arrived on a visit. I took him for a walk. Then the late Dean<persName xml:id="3471"></persName> arrived, &amp; then the present Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="5129"></persName>. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> joined us at dinner.</p>
            <p>Professor Bacon tells me that he voted for Prohibition, although he had previously been opposed to it. He thinks that the policy will succeed because (&#x3B1;) the constitutional procedure for reversing it is extremely difficult &amp; protracted. (&#x3B2;) there is a very general and determined organisation which is guarding its enforcement. (&#x3B3;) there has grown up in the 'dry' states a great population which has never known alcohol or the "saloon". (&#x3B5;) the civic feeling of the best citizens is really aroused against the continuance of a politically &amp; socially corrupting system within the Republic such as the liquor interests had certainly become. The resistance &amp; evasion have not so far exceeded what the supporters of the Prohibition Law had always expected. I am not convinced.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>