<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The weather continued wet and gloomy, so that I felt it reasonable to telegraph to Sellac cancelling my engagement to dedicate the War Memorial in the churchyard. Then I settled down to the Windsor Sermon, and finished it. Captain Hamilton called to report the resignation of the unfortunate Vicar of Breinton<persName xml:id="5107"></persName>.</p>
            <p>The "Hereford Times" reports a speech made by the egregious Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName> in acknowledgement of a testimonial<note xml:id="206" n="1"></note> on leaving Leominster. He refers to me without naming me, &amp; quotes from a private  letter which I wrote to him. His language is extraordinarily insulting, &amp; indicates how deeply his vanity has been wounded. He is also good enough to describe Moore<persName xml:id="4331"></persName> of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's as "the great spiritual power in the diocese". I have surmised that these two men have been drawing together for some time past, and no doubt they will find common ground in disliking their Bishop. It is, of course, a good thing "to see one's self as others see us", but even so, it does rather surprise one to see such an astonishing caricature offered to the public. It will be interesting to see how he gets on with the Bishop of Exeter &amp; his patrons, the Dean and Chapter. Cant and flattery carry far with some people, and they have served him well hitherto: &amp; yet, if there be any core of honesty in the world, there must be a limit to their influence. I am heartily glad that my diocese is rid of him.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>