<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I left Hereford in pouring rain by the 9.55 a.m. train, &amp; reached Paddington well to time at 2.45 p.m. I drove to Great College Street, &amp; deposited my bags. Then I walked to S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's &amp; officiated with Carnegie<persName xml:id="2955"></persName> at the memorial service for Charlie Parker<persName xml:id="290"></persName>. There was a considerable congregation, &amp; the singing was excellent. After service I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Younger</hi><persName xml:id="4464"></persName>, &amp; asked him what were the prospects of the Divorce Bill in the Commons.<note xml:id="519" n="1"></note> He said that the Bill would be vigorously opposed, &amp; that there was general disgust at the spectacle of <hi rend="doubleunderline">F. E. Smith</hi><persName xml:id="2508"></persName> as the champion of the "spiritual" character of marriage. He thought it probable, in view of the state of government business, that the Bill would fall through. Then I encountered <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName>, a squalid figure looking abjectly disreputable, &amp; smoking a huge cigar. He said that the House of Lords was waking up to the true character of its performance in passing the Enabling Act, &amp; <hi rend="underline">that its present insistence on the Divorce Bill in the teeth of the Bishops was a belated essay in self&#8211;assertion</hi>. He waxed merry over the spectacle of <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Curzon</hi><persName xml:id="1018"></persName> being ordered about by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><persName xml:id="234"></persName> with a total disregard of his dignity. Then I went to 45 Cadogan Place, and had tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dorothy Parker</hi><persName xml:id="950"></persName>. From her I went to the Athanaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; wrote letters. I dined in the Club with the new Archbishop of Wales<persName xml:id="1454"></persName>, who told me that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wickham Steed</hi><persName xml:id="5242"></persName>, <hi rend="underline">the Editor of the Times, is fully persuaded of the reality of the great Jewish conspiracy against Christendom</hi>. After dinner I sate with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Glazebrook</hi><persName xml:id="4234"></persName>, and talked of the position created by the Divorce Bill. He meditates a letter to the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>". Then I walked back to Great College Street.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>