<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> had an interview with Lawson Forster<persName xml:id="5172"></persName>, which appeared to be mutually satisfactory. Then I began work on the Windsor sermon. After lunch, Wynne Willson went with me to Kimbolton, where I had an interview with the War Memorial Committee about the Memorial Cross, &amp; essayed to pacify them. In the end I promised to dedicate the Cross myself on Saturday May 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Then in pouring rain we returned to Hereford, &amp; went through the correspondence.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>April 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920</p>
            <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rutherford,</p>
            <p>Charles Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName> is in my belief a young man of high personal character, of considerable intellectual ability, &amp; of genuine piety. The late headmaster of the Cathedral School gave him a very excellent testimonial, and emphasized his good influence over the boys. He is reported to be a preacher of more than common quality, and I think he has studious interests, which might go some way towards redressing the balance which his ecclesiastical <hi rend="underline">parti pris</hi> might endanger.</p>
            <p>He has no doubt the faults of a self&#8211;centred temperament, &amp; these have, I conceive, been strengthened by his situation as an only son, &amp;, possibly by association at Oxford with rather a narrow type of Anglo&#8211;Catholic. I am sure he is honourable, &amp; could be trusted to keep any pledge which he had taken. He certainly evokes affection from those with whom he is associated, &amp;, though he stands in great need of wise &amp; strong guidance if his clerical life is to develop wholesomely, I must needs think that he would respond to fair &amp; friendly dealing. He has not altogether "hit it off" with the present Vicar of All Saints, but his position as a part&#8211;time curate was rather difficult, &amp; I do not think the fault was wholly on his side. Of his disciplinary qualities I have had no direct means of forming an opinion.</p>
            <p>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            <p>The Rev. S. H. Rutherford</p>
            <p>S. Peter's Vicarage, Acton Green, W.4.</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>