<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I travelled to Oxford, and stayed there for the night with the Headlams<persName xml:id="552"><persName xml:id="553"></persName></persName> in Christ Church. In the afternoon I took part in one of the most tiresome meetings I have ever attended. It was held in the interest of the Ladies Settlement in Bethnal Green: and was attended by an exiguous number of senior ladies. Nobody under 40 seemed to be present, &amp; very few under 50! And this is a mighty movement into which the girls are to be carried! <hi rend="bold underline">The post&#8211;war fervours run to jazzing and profanity, to anything rather than "good works</hi><hi rend="bold">"!</hi></p>
            <p>I dined in college at the Gaudy. It was a pleasant meeting. After dinner <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>, Hardinge<persName xml:id="548"></persName>, Bain<persName xml:id="850"></persName>, Amery<persName xml:id="324"></persName>, &amp; I had a lively discussion over the eviction of the Turks from Constantinople. </p>
            <p>After the meeting I called on Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, &amp; had an interview with his wife<persName xml:id="649"></persName>. The poor old lady is evidently a subject of melancholia. Headlam &amp; I walked twice round the Christ Church Meadow. He has made a good start with his Bampton Lectures. It is not without significance that the "Church Times" absolutely ignores them. These ecclesiastical journals have two notes – insult and neglect. The first is employed to ruin the comparatively weak &amp; unknown: the last, to belittle &amp; hamper the strong. Both have been plentifully used in my own case. Now – beyond spiteful allusions to "the Hereford Scandal" – I m generally ignored. Headlam showed me a correspondence which has passed between himself and the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> on the subject of training candidates for the Anglican ministry. His Grace is evidently perturbed.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>