<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I returned to the Swedish lectures. I called on the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName>, whom I found in bed with a bad chill. After lunch I motored with Mary<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> to Kilpeck &amp; Abbey Dore. Then I dictated letters to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>. Before going to bed I dipped into Creighton's<persName xml:id="118"></persName> life. There are many good things in it. In 1899 there was a grave situation in the Church of England. <hi rend="italic">Creighton foretold that "self&#8211;government" would mean disruption.</hi></p>
            <p>"Englishmen always act very legally: they w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> make a broad system, with very little discretion beyond. The ritualists w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have to recognise that they must fall in, or go; this w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be much more apparent then than now. There w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be much stricter subordination required. Everything w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be much more definite. I am tolerably certain that this w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> rapidly end in disruption. If this were confined to England, it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be bad enough; but the Anglican communion in the empire w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> follow in some degree."</p>
            <p>The last 20 years have witnessed a steady worsening of the position. The ritualists have become more Roman &amp; incomparably more anarchic. </p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p><hi rend="italic">"The tolerance which the extreme people ask for is the right to do whatever they like, irrespective of the organisation to which they belong. They will not try to get what they want by persuading others of its harmlessness, by agitating, by explaining, by moving in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>. They take the right to do what they like, &amp; are aggrieved at the narrow&#8211;mindedness of those who distrust them."</hi></p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>