<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[186]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A wet disagreeable morning with a hypocritical interlude of sunshine soon followed by more rain. I left the Palace at 9.30 a.m.; &amp; motored to Munslow, where I confirmed 36 candidates. The Vicar – Powell<persName xml:id="4365"></persName> – is the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> incumbent of that name. His great&#8211;grandfather, a tanner of Bridgnorth, having made money, bought the advowson of Munslow, &amp; sold it to his son for 10/6. The son appointed himself as vicar of Munslow, &amp; was followed in the office by his son, whose son is the present incumbent. There is a young Powell already in orders who looks to succeed in his turn. <hi rend="bold underline">Divine vocation by hereditary right! `Tis a very odd spectacle.</hi></p>
            <p>The church has a very solid Norman Tower, too decayed to allow of the bells being rung: a number of medieval benches: &amp; 4 windows of beautiful medieval glass. After lunching with the incumbent, I motored to Cardington, &amp; there confirmed 29 candidates. This parish is about 750 feet above sea&#8211;level, and commands the most beautiful views. The parson, Buss<persName xml:id="4731"></persName>, has been a missionary. In the chancel of the parish church is an elaborate tomb of one Leighton, a Welsh judge, who died in 1607. There is a double piscina in good repair. Anning<persName xml:id="5201"></persName>, Vicar of Rushbury, &amp; Friederichs<persName xml:id="5202"></persName> Vicar of Eaton were at the service. I returned to Hereford by way of Church Stretton a few minutes before 8 p.m. These confirmations in Shropshire involve a heavy expenditure of time &amp; petrol. Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came in at 9 p.m. to go through the letters: &amp; then I read the newspapers.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>May 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920</p>
            <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Martin.</p>
            <p>I think you should rest content with the archaeological interest of the record about the pew. It would be a rather arbitrary proceeding to revive a long dormant claim on a title nearly two centuries old, especially as the whole sentiment of the Church has changed on the subject of private rights inside parish churches, &amp; you would set the conscience of the people against you. I have myself for many years been a member of the Free &amp; Open Church Society<orgName xml:id="327"></orgName>, which wages unceasing war on faculty pews &amp; pew rents, so I could hardly join in setting up or restoring a Faculty pew in Diddlebury. Charles I and the shipmoney is not a sound precedent to follow! </p>
            <p>I am writing from London where I came for a Bishop's meeting tomorrow &amp; Thursday.</p>
            <p>With kind regards.</p>
            <p>Yours sincerely</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>