<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[191]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The day was spent at Lambeth, where we had a keen &amp; illuminating discussion on the proposal to "continue" the clerical training experiment at K as a "test school" for aspirants to Holy Orders. <hi rend="bold underline">I spoke twice in opposition to what seemed to me nothing else than the "thin edge" of the Roman seminarist system</hi>. What, I asked, are the essentials of "Seminarism"? I answered that they were these three: (1) prematurity of vocation, (2) early immersion in a clerical atmosphere: (3) subsidising of clerical education. "The plan is educationally obsolete, &amp; religiously mischievous". Incidentally, I referred to the "side&#8211;light" on the working of seminarism provided by <hi rend="underline">Tyrrell's</hi><persName xml:id="1084"></persName> "Letters", and quoted his bitter phrase about "love&#8211;lorn nuns and emasculated priests". I spoke also against episcopal insistence on a year at a training college. <hi rend="underline">Headlam's</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> correspondence with the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> was read. It sounded very truculent, but in spite of this, the general feeling was favourable. <hi rend="bold underline">I had some talk with Nickson<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> about Durham. He professes to desire not to be offered the succession to Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, but probably, his "nolo episcopari" [I do not want to be a bishop] would have no more than the usual significance if the chance came to him.</hi> I gathered that he would rather like to come to Hereford if I left that see. Later, I fell in with <hi rend="underline">Oman</hi><persName xml:id="2141"></persName> in the Athanaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. He expressed his desire that I should be translated. There is, I think, a fair probability that my name will be considered, but something like a moral certainty that it will not be accepted.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[192]</hi></p>
            <p>I found the Archbishop reclining on the sofa in the club, &amp; he began to talk. <hi rend="bold underline">I told him that I had accepted Abp. S&#x00F6;derblom's<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> invitation to assist at the consecration of two Swedish bishops on Sept. 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. He at first expressed satisfaction, and then a measure of incertitude. I offered to send him S&#x00F6;derblom's letter, &amp; he accepted the offer with some eagerness. </hi>Then I told him about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lombard's</hi><persName xml:id="5103"></persName> alleged introduction of "girl servers" at the Holy Communion in Cound, &amp; asked what I had best do. "Forbid it, certainly", he replied: &amp; when I suggested that such a prohibition might be difficult to enforce, he agreed &amp; thought I had better request that the practice be discontinued! Walking away from the Club I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fisher</hi><persName xml:id="2107"></persName>, whom I urged to go on with his educational settlement. He did not speak very hopefully about his chances of success. Then I walked with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="636"></persName> as far as <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and <hi rend="bold underline">discussed Durham. He thinks that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi><persName xml:id="120"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> may very well be chosen, &amp; that I may be offered the see if he refused. The notion of my going back there is, he says, being generally talked about. He had been told by the Abp., as also had I, that a resolute effort would be made at the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> to get some declaration on doctrine accepted</hi>. This provides a special reason why my preferment to Durham might be thought desirable. I should come into the Conference with increased &#x00E9;clat, &amp; the fanaticks would be proportionately discouraged. I dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> &amp; his wife. The Bishop of Llandaff<persName xml:id="3489"></persName> was also there. We had some interesting talk on the subject of spiritualism, on which Barnes expressed himself with knowledge, acumen, &amp; good sense.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>