<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[155] </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The weather was woeful, chilly and wet all day long. I went to the dentist by the underground to Earl's Court, &amp; the tube to Piccadilly Circus: then a taxi took me to Queen Anne Street. <hi rend="bold underline">Proceedings in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName> were very dull</hi>. The new Bishop of S. Alban's (Furse<persName xml:id="1602"></persName>) read the Litany. He is a huge man with a fine voice, but he will be a steady supporter of the wrong side<hi rend="bold underline">. The Bishops of Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName> &amp; Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> assumed that the Church was unanimous on the subject of the Divorce Bill now before the House of Lords.<note xml:id="519" n="1"></note> I thought it needful to tell them that they were mistaken</hi>. The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> thinks that there is little chance of the Bill becoming law this year. His Grace read a letter from Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> on the method of making Crown appointments. It gave nothing away, &amp; was a judicious &amp; effective pronouncement. There was a desultory discussion of a resolution on emigration sent up from the Lower House. The Bishop of S. Alban's made a successful maiden speech, stigmatising the resolution as vague &amp; futile. The Bishop of Peterboro<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> &amp; I set out to walk to Fulham, but the rain was so persistent that we changed our minds &amp; shared a taxi (6/&#8211;). Then I wrote several letters<hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I found myself antagonized by Bishop Woods. He is so unblushingly conventional. The National Mission was for him a triumphant success: the Enabling Act is a spiritual victory and the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> (of which he is episcopal secretary) an epoch&#8211;making event. All this irritates while it amuses me</hi>.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>