<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Another pleasant bright day wasted in Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>. We spent the whole morning in discussing the proposal of the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> to add another question &amp; answer to the Catechism, and a motion to adopt a new translation of the <hi rend="underline">Quicunque vult</hi>. After lunch the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> explained his Criminal Law Amendment Bill, &amp; we unanimously blessed it. Then the Bishop of Norwich explained the new Union of Benefices Act. I announced my intention of opposing the resolution about the Crown patronage. </p>
            <p>I dined at the House of Commons with Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName>. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> M.<persName xml:id="666"></persName>, Buff<persName xml:id="836" display="no"></persName>, &amp; Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> made up the party. Buff looked enchanting: it is difficult to believe that she is 26. She ought to marry, but her father tells me that the youth who ought to have married her, &amp; whom she would have married, was killed in the war. I wonder what will be the final effect of their tremendous experiences upon all these splendid young women, who during the last five years have traversed centuries! Craik was very severe on the present Rector of St. Margaret's, who seems to give the impression of a "fashionable person". As I passed the church in the half&#8211;light, I was seized with a strange regret. Why did I leave Westminster, where I was (apparently) doing useful work, to launch myself in kinds of work for which I have no special aptitude? </p>
            </body></text></TEI>