<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A damp unpleasant day from start to finish. I felt most woefully unequal to my work, but I determined to go through with it. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Credenhill, where I confirmed 14 candidates; and then we lunched with Miss Eckroyd. This lady was good enough to express much sympathy with me in my initial difficulties, which, I suppose, appeared more formidable to her than to me. She seems to have been a friend of Bishop Percival<persName xml:id="475"></persName>. Then we motored to Wellington, where I confirmed 22 candidates. The church, dedicated to S. Margaret, is interesting: the parson (Rev. C. P. Lee<persName xml:id="5175"></persName>) is, I conjecture, a stiff High Churchman, and has a clerical manner, but he did not impress me badly on the whole. After having tea in the vicarage, we returned to Hereford, and found Ruth Spooner<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> there. Captain Hamilton came again to see me about the Vicar of Breinton<persName xml:id="5107"></persName>. The poor man seems to be unmanageable: &amp; certainly ought to be certified. But, if his resignation is to be secured, we must keep him in the category of the legally sane until he has signed it.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Sparrow Simpson</hi><persName xml:id="2447"></persName> writes on the Prospects of Union between the Eastern and Anglican Churches in the new Quarterly, "The Christian East":&#8211;</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"What would contribute enormously towards complete confidence on the part of the Greeks &amp; to their official acknowledgment of our ministerial succession, <hi rend="bold underline">would be a clear and definite statement by our own authorities that Anglicans believe ordination to confer an indelible character &amp; grace of the Holy Spirit</hi>. If the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> were to frame some resolution of this kind, it would satisfy what Eastern theologians desire to know".</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>