<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Even so sane &amp; moderate a churchman as the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName>, when he addresses his brethren in Wales, employs a manner of speech, which must be profoundly exasperating to the Nonconformists whom he seeks to conciliate.</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"So then the first truth to realize in regard to the Church in Wales at the present time is that <hi rend="underline">it is an integral part of the Holy Catholic Church of Christ</hi> which is a fundamental article of the Christian faith enshrined in the Apostles' Creed. <hi rend="underline">It is in its Catholicity, not in its recognition by the State, that its qualification for its national mission consists.</hi>"</p>
            </div>
            <p>He speaks of "the fundamental principles of Church Order, revealed in Holy Scripture, &amp; recognized for centuries by the whole undivided Church before the deplorable separation of East &amp; West", and, since the Reformed Church has preserved these principles in its constitution, "Welsh Churchmen may, <hi rend="doubleunderline">therefore</hi>, face the future with confidence that the Church in Wales may rely without any shadow of misgiving …… upon the Divine promises made to the whole Church of Christ." This language is only intelligible on the Anglo&#8211;Catholic theory that 'episcopacy' is of the essence of the Church. Does the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> David's really hold that theory? I think not, but he continues to use a manner of speech which implies it. Yet no 'reunion' is a possibility on such a basis. If it were effected, it could not possibly outlast the first collision between ecclesiastical authority and the individual conscience. Nor could it be effected save by the aid of enormous misapprehensions.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi></p>
            <p>Having sent Professor Bacon<persName xml:id="3057"></persName> to see the cathedral under Fearne's<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> guidance, I applied myself to the composition of a letter to the Diocese on the Welsh Church. After lunch I went to the Cathedral for the unveiling of the monumental tablet set up there in memory of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sinclair, the late Organist. The old Dean<persName xml:id="3471"></persName> performed the function, &amp; the new Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> read the lesson. I gave the Benediction. After a short walk by the river with Bacon, I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas, and gave an address to the Bell&#8211;ringers, of whom no less than 78 were present.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bateman</hi><persName xml:id="4471"></persName> asked for an increase of his wages, pleading with obvious reason the increased cost of clothing etc. But I pointed out to him that bishop's butlers like bishops were no longer reckoned among the necessaries of life, but rather among those objects which find their place in museums! A gardener and a chauffer [sic] must be had in a rural diocese, but not a butler, since the impoverishment of the bishops &amp; the change of social habits have made entertainment impossible. Besides, he escapes the greater part of the increased cost of living. Rates &amp; taxes don't affect him, while they sweep away a third of my income, &amp; the increased price of his food falls on me. Thus there is a case for making a distinction. In any case, I cannot increase my expenditures on anything or anybody which cannot be justified as necessary. A fresh addition to the income&#8211;tax &#8211; &amp; this is a contingency by no means improbable – might compel me to vacate, or partially to shut up, the Palace. My butler would obviously be the first person to be dismissed. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>