<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>The weather is again milder. On the whole the frost is to be regretted, for everything needs checking in the interest of the future. I went to the bank and invested Fearne's<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> legacy (&#x00A3; 100) in War Loan, i.e. I charged the Bank manager to effect the investment. I worked at the Lectures all morning, &amp; sawed wood with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> in the afternoon.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> asks me to preach in S. Paul's on Sunday evening July 11</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">. I consented of course. It cannot be said that I hide my candle under a bushhell, when on two succeeding Sundays I preach in London during the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>: &amp; at S. Paul's and the Abbey!</hi></p>
            <p>I had a brief note from the Vicar of Hatfield<persName xml:id="4923"></persName> saying that he would come here on Thursday at 4 p.m. That interview will be extremely difficult.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Streeter arrived in order to speak at a meeting of the Y.W.C.A.<orgName xml:id="237"></orgName> So <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne accompanied her to the Institute while I stayed at home &amp; wrote to Ralph, Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName>, &amp; Baker&#8211;Wilbraham<persName xml:id="1427"></persName>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The latter sent me a pamphlet, full of pious platitudes of the neo&#8211;evangelical type, and setting forth a project for propagating these throughout the country. I gently blessed the platitudes, and brutally stamped on the project! How pathetic is this inextinguishable belief in 'societies' ! I suppose the pious fussing which goes to framing &amp; starting them is as a pillar&#8211;bed for the uneasy conscience to repose on!</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>