<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>March 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920</p>
            <p>My dear Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName></p>
            <p>Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> was so deferential to the Abp. of C. that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have felt it very difficult to oppose a measure which his Grace was actively pressing; but he disliked the so&#8211;called <hi rend="underline">autonomy </hi>of the Church intensely, and had nothing but contempt for the "Representative Church Council"<orgName xml:id="57"></orgName>.</p>
            <p>One of my arguments against the Enabling Bill was the certainty that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not command the acceptance of the faction w<hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> in the name of "Catholick principles" has refused obedience to <hi rend="underline">every</hi> authority legally established in the National Church. Now that my reasoning is justified by experience, it is rather hard that I should be insultingly bracketed with these fanaticks!</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">You</hi> are the last of the Tractarians: and <hi rend="underline">I</hi> am the last of the National Churchmen. These "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" go beyond us, &amp; will bring about a disruption before many years have passed.</p>
            <p>Lacey's<persName xml:id="1936"></persName> subtlety seems to be too much even for <hi rend="underline">his</hi> friends!</p>
            <p>Yours aff<hi rend="superscript underline">ley</hi></p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            <p>The Very Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi></p>
            <p>Dean of Westminster</p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p><hi rend="italic">"I have often had the choice as to the disposition of troops on the field of battle, but when there has been a point that it was really important to hold, when there has been a tactical area of great importance which we could not afford to lose, it has always been the English troops that I have chosen."</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">General Sir Henry Rawlinson<persName xml:id="5164"></persName>, May 8</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1919</hi></p>
            </div>
            <p>This is an interesting testimony, and very welcome just now, when English self&#8211;respect is really imperilled by the subordination into which Englishmen have been brought on every plane of public life.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nint lunched here. He aspires to be ordained, but does not seem particularly well suited, either in body or in mind. I advised him to betake himself to an urban bishop.</p>
            <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" reports Lloyd&#8211;George's<persName xml:id="234"></persName> speech to the Liberals. He declares war against the "Labour" party which he describes as Socialist: but his reference to Lord Rob<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cecil<persName xml:id="131"></persName> was very hostile. The "Times" has a bitterly censorious leader, but L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Northcliffe's<persName xml:id="4024"></persName> vendetta is so naked, that his utterances are discounted.</p>
            <p>The English Church Union<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> has espoused the case of a rebellious parson, whom the Bishop of Bath &amp; Wells<persName xml:id="173"></persName> is prosecuting for a series of illegalities including Benediction. <hi rend="bold underline">The President, L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>, has announced his dissent from this decision.</hi></p>
            <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived. After a term abandoned to the theatre, he may possibly dedicate a vacation to his schools!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>