<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>The post brought two acceptable letters, the one from Swinnerton Dyer<persName xml:id="5120"></persName> at Westhope assuring me that the hatchet had been definitely buried there, &amp; the other from the Vicar<persName xml:id="5156"></persName> writing very pleasantly about what he calls "the great service" in Peterchurch on Sunday afternoon. He writes: </p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p><hi rend="italic">"I am sure it was a very auspicious beginning of your episcopal visit to this part of the Golden Valley, and the great congregation was a decided expression of confidence in your ministry in this portion of the Diocese. I have never witnessed such a gathering at a Confirmation service before, &amp; I believe it will the beginning of a much needed stimulated interest in the Church hereabouts. Two of the men said "and now it only remains for M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Holland<persName xml:id="5156"></persName> to keep in touch", but that is the difficulty. We are going to try very hard. I hear on the all sides today how much the service was appreciated, &amp; thought you might care to</hi> know."</p>
            </div>
            <p>This is pleasant reading, &amp; goes to show that I may not have been wholly mistaken when I allowed myself to think on Sunday that there was a friendlier feeling in the clergy. Holland, the Vicar of Peterchurch, has been no less than 21 years in the parish. He is well reported of by the Archdeacon, &amp; certainly made a good impression on me. There is no vicarage in his parish, but he occupies rather a tumble&#8211;down house belonging to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Powell, the patron. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>