<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> sends me a letter which he has received from T.A. Lacey<persName xml:id="1936"></persName> with reference to the proposal of the recent Conference at Oxford that ministers of different Churches sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> receive "authorisation" from one another, &amp; thus be qualified for exchanging pulpits. K. had asked for an explanation of the word "authorisation" as used by "an Anglo&#8211;Catholic". Lacey's letter is suggestive of some "slimness" on his part:&#8211; </p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knight</p>
            <p>The term "authorization" was used because it had to cover all forms of reciprocal action. Of course the only kind of authorization that w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> suffice in our case is imposition of the bishop's hands with suitable prayer. Legal difficulties w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> probably make the use of the complete rite of the Ordinal necessary, but I very much wish that a modified rite containing the bare essentials were available. I explained this to the drafting Committee, citing in illustration the procedure of Bramhall<persName xml:id="5136"></persName> in reconciling a Presbyterian in 1661. You will find it in vol. 1. P.xxxvii of his Works, ed. 1842. Some people w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> reckon this <hi rend="underline">ordination</hi>: others w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> reckon it, as Bramhall did, the "supply" of something canonically required. This difference of estimate is unavoidable. My judgement is that we ought not to "offer" anything. They must ask for it. They will do this when a real desire for full communion is developed, &amp; until then it is useless to attempt any action. They are moving in this direction. <hi rend="bold">[32] </hi>I very much wish that the bishops w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> adopt Bramhall's precedent in dealing with all dissenting ministers who in present circumstances wish to join us, instead of putting them through the mill with ordinary candidates for Ordination. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be an object&#8211;lesson, showing what w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be done in case of corporate reconciliation, &amp; my impression is that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> much reduce reluctance. I have urged this course on our own bishop, who is pretty certain to consult <hi rend="underline">yours</hi> about it.</p>
            <p>Yours v. truly</p>
            <p>T.A. Lacey.</p>
            </div>
            <p>K. himself shares my suspicion that there is no sincerity in these conferences with nonconformists in which Anglo&#8211;Catholics take a prominent part.: " I can't help feeling that the recent conference at Oxford has trapped the Nonconformists &amp; bambooled the Evangelicas". </p>
            <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kearley, Vicar of Prestaign, called to make arrangements about the consecration of a grave.yard in his parish. Then I went to the Cathedral &amp; licenced a curate to Little Birch. Also I instituted Preb: Machen<persName xml:id="4807"></persName> to Frodsley, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Elgar Jones to Montgomery, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Astbury to Llanveynoe. The new Vicar of Montgomery came to lunch. He will go out of my diocese in a few weeks, when the Welsh Act comes into force.</p>
            <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to Kingsland, &amp; had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Warde Jackson. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Boughton&#8211;Knight from Downton were there, &amp; expressed themselves very pleasantly.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>