<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A pleasant day, sunny but colder. I spent it in the Upper House of Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>, where we were decorously harmonious but mortally dull. Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName> met me in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and inquired about N. who had written to him in a very canting vein. <hi rend="bold underline">It seems that the poor man has found the Bp. of H. 'not spiritual enough'. Heaven knows he may be right there, however wrong elsewhere</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>But what is it to be "spiritual"? There is no adjective more often on the lips of ecclesiastics, and none more in need of precise definition.</p>
            <p>I dined with Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName> in Park Lane. The taxis having struck as a protest against the price of petrol, I put my shoes in my pockets, &amp; walked. The company was interesting – M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowther<persName xml:id="1731"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4490"></persName> &amp; the Hon: M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rochford Maguire, Lord<persName xml:id="759"></persName> &amp; Lady Lytton<persName xml:id="918"></persName>, Col: Repington, &amp; another lady, whose name escaped me. I had much talk with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowther at dinner, and with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Maguire afterwards, &amp; found both ladies intelligent, informing, &amp; interesting. Mine host and Lord Lytton seemed eager to hear my views about the ecclesiastical question, &amp; held me to the subject though I tried to get away from it. As I walked home, I was saddened by the spectacle of a drunken woman being <hi rend="underline">wheeled</hi> home by three policemen, &amp; making much clamour of futile protest on the way. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>