<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[153] </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>A most glorious morning. The birds sang divinely as I dressed, transforming the tiresome process into a high liturgy! Who would leave the country for the city on such a day as this? Yet such is the necessity under which I live. Against my will, with the clear knowledge that the object of my journey is for all good intents &amp; purposes quite fertile, I yield to the mechanical pressure of office, &amp; attend Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>!</p>
            <p>The All Souls tumbler, with its inscription, arrived, &amp; was duly presented to my Godson<persName xml:id="3886"></persName>. Then I wrote some necessary letters, and tidied up my study.</p>
            <p>I left Hereford by 12.50 p.m. and travelled to London. At Paddington I hired a taxi, &amp; drove to Fulham, dropping my robe&#8211;bag at the Church House on the way. The taxi&#8211;driver charged me 8/&#8211; ! </p>
            <p>The Bishop's<persName xml:id="4088"></persName> niece had married earlier in the day, &amp; I came in to the relics of the Feast! <hi rend="bold underline">After tea I walked across to Fulham Vicarage, and had a long talk with Gerald, who looks very ill. </hi>He seems to be getting on admirably in his parish.</p>
            <p>In the train I read through the Life of Bishop Bedell<persName xml:id="5187"></persName> by his son, edited by old John E. B. Mayor. It is a fascinating account of a genuinely good man. He was born in 1571 and died in 1641. He was so forward a pupil that he was sent to Cambridge in his 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year, but not to his advantage, for "the first four years (as himself was wont to say) he lost, only keeping pace with the rest of his years." </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[154] </hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>April 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920.</p>
            <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knapp<persName xml:id="5183"></persName>,</p>
            <p>Grave complaints have come to me with respect to the irregular conduct of the services in Pixley Church. It is alleged that on April 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> "the door&#8211;key was mislaid &amp; in consequence no service was held there"; &amp; that this is not a solitary instance of neglect. </p>
            <p>You will, I am sure, understand that these are grave matters, and raise large issues. </p>
            <p>I shall be glad to know what you have to say in explanation. </p>
            <p>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford </p>
            <p>The Rev. A. H. Knapp,</p>
            </div>
            <p>This person holds the two livings of Pixley and Aylton. Pixley has a population of 108 persons, and an income of &#x00A3; 154. Aylton has 95 parishioners, &amp; &#x00A3; 149 for endowment. Thus the united parishes have 203 parishioners, and &#x00A3; 303 income. He was ordained in Hereford in 1884, and become Rector of Pixley in 1894, have [sic] been previously curate there for 4 years. He has thus resided in that little parish for 30 years: &amp; must now be a man about 60 years old – too young for hope, too old for change. But what can I do? He is not likely to be influenced by admonitions, &amp; the machinery of the law, cumbrous &amp; costly, is hardly worth setting in motion.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>