<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A damp &amp; dropping day, which seemed disposed to brightness but failing in its purpose "through weak endeavour". Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> accompanied Eckett<persName xml:id="4551"></persName> &amp; me to Breinton, and after service, returned home on foot. There was a scanty congregation: I preached a brief sermon from notes. Then I saw the Churchwardens in Hamilton's house. I went on to James's<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> house, &amp; saw him there, before returning to the Palace.</p>
            <p>The case of an insane incumbent<persName xml:id="5107"></persName> who has nothing to live upon save the income of his benefice is extremely embarrassing. If, moreover, the benefice be too poorly&#8211;endowed to admit of providing funds for the payment of a substitute, the situation is still further complicated. To do justice to the parishioners, and to be merciful to the incumbent are obligations not easily reconciled. It is not easy to perceive a remedy: for insanity may overtake anyone, and it is always, when fairly regarded, the object rather of compassion than of resentment.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came to go through the communion service with me before making his first approach to the Altar on Easter Day. He is the first confirmation candidate whom I have prepared since I left Westminster, and will probably be the last I shall ever prepare. Our relation to one another has become the more close, since I also baptized him, and since we are so much together motoring about the diocese. He seems frank and sincere: so far as I can see, he is doing his chauffeur's duty well. May the chapter of religious profession which will begin on Easter for him be carried through to the end without failure or shame!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>