<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>I too have labored hard to settle religious controversies, but I soon discovered that reconciling doctrines was a vain work. Then I planned a kind of truce of God, &amp; I brought in the idea of toleration, which had already been suggested by the Peace of Westphalia.</p>
            <p>Leibnitz<persName xml:id="5193"></persName></p>
            </div>
            <p>From 10.30 a.m. to 6 p.m. I was at Lambeth. There was a vigorous discussion over the Bishop of Chichester's<persName xml:id="301"></persName> proposals, which <hi rend="bold underline">I opposed with all the energy in my power</hi>. There were 2 issues. 1. [symbol] the creation of a Central Candidates C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi> and 2. [symbol] the continuance of Knutsford as a sifting &amp; training centre for "young civilian candidates" i.e. lads between 16 and 19. I resisted both, the one as undercutting episcopal authority, the other as introducing the puerile vocations and seminarist training of Rome. However, I was defeated over the Central Candidates C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi> by 18 votes to 7, and, when a futile rider had been appended by 23 to 4, the Knutsford proposal was postponed. The Abp of York<persName xml:id="130"></persName> supported me in opposing the last. I think there was sufficient display of opposition to make the centralizing ring somewhat apprehensive.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> asked me to introduce, or rather to make one of the speeches by which should be introduced, the subject of Reunion in the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
            <p>He said that neither Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName> nor Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> in England, or Bernard<persName xml:id="225"></persName> in Ireland would be members of the Lambeth Conference. He had discussed the matter with them, and they had agreed that it was impossible. There are more than 60 bishops who have resigned sees at home or abroad, who will be outside the Conference, and it would be invidious to make exceptions in the case of individuals, who on personal grounds were desirable.</p>
            <p>I went to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. Then I walked back to Warwick Square, in good time to dress for dinner. The company included the vicar of the parish, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Batty<persName xml:id="5142"></persName> &amp; his wife. He said that he had got 700 names on his electoral roll, &amp; that his parishioners numbered 20,000! He was making efforts to increase his electors. <hi rend="bold underline">Miss Rose Bradley</hi>, looking younger than ever though she must be nearing 60, dined. It was pleasant to see her again. After everybody else had retired, mine host<persName xml:id="912"></persName> and I talked for awhile [sic] before going to bed. <hi rend="bold underline">He says that Carnegie<persName xml:id="2955"></persName> don't count for much in the City of Westminster</hi>. At the last dinner of the Past Overseers' Society<orgName xml:id="64"></orgName> he was not even asked to make a speech! It appears that Fedarb<persName xml:id="156"></persName> now reads the lessons in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. I cannot reconcile myself to this handing&#8211;over to the layman a duty which might seem peculiarly that of the clergyman. No doubt it gratifies the layman, whose vanity is pleased, &amp; this gratification is likely to be greatest in the case of an old National schoolmaster.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>