<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; read the paper: looked in at the bookseller: walked to Westminster &amp; called first on Charles, &amp; then on the Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName>: lunched at the Club: picked up my bags in Warwick Square: drove to Paddington, &amp; returned to Hereford by the 3 p.m. train.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Dean of Westminster has been entertaining the Bishop of Durham</hi><persName xml:id="276"></persName><hi rend="italic">, and probably using the opportunity thus incidentally provided in order to counsel him to get out of the 'scrape' into which Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> has led him in the matter of Jowett's<persName xml:id="1725"></persName> proposed sermon in Durham Cathedral. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It appears that Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName> is going to withdraw his promise to attend on the occasion, &amp; give the Blessing. Now surely this is greatly to increase the magnitude of the blunder</hi><hi rend="italic">. For, first, he executes a retreat before the pressure of news&#8211;paper agitation: and, next, he adds the prestige of success to the E.C.U: finally, he changes what was designed as an evidence of religious fellowship with the Dissenters into an ugly demonstration of religious estrangement. It will not diminish the sum&#8211;total of mischief that he will have enabled the Archdeacon of Durham<persName xml:id="590"></persName> to triumph over the Dean. It would appear to be the case that the feebleness of the Diocesan has transformed the indiscretion of his Dean into a serious set&#8211;back to the cause which both of them must be supposed to advocate. Welldon "spoils the pitch" for everybody else!</hi> I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName><note xml:id="526" n="1"></note>: &amp; paid my Supertax.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>