<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Who does not change his opinions between twenty and thirty? A young man enters life with his father's or tutor's views; he changes them for his own. The more modest &amp; diffident he is, the more faith he has, so much the longer does he speak the words of others: but the force of circumstances, or the vigour of his mind, infallibly obliges him at last to have a mind of his own: that is if he is good for anything.</p>
         <p>Newman<persName xml:id="337"></persName>. 'Loss &amp; gain'. P. 190</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Weston&#8211;under&#8211;Penyard &amp; called on Craigie<persName xml:id="4949"></persName>. Rather to my dismay he postpones his departure "until he can find a house to go into", that is, as matters now stand, until the Greek Kalends. I had tea with K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> who gave me an account of his visit to the Conference on Reunion at Oxford.<note xml:id="522" n="1"></note> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lacey</hi><persName xml:id="1936"></persName> seems to have 'queered the pitch' very characteristically, &amp; <persName xml:id="114"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName></persName> was, of course, clamorously futile. I don't think anything effectual is likely to come out of these meetings. Nobody is frank, &amp; few are quite sincere. K. is ruminating over an ecclesiastical policy for '<hi rend="underline">the Times</hi>', and inclines to disenowment, though (rather oddly) he would like to retain the Establishment. He thinks that, if the Anglo&#8211;Catholics were thrown on their own resources, they would soon discover how slight is their hold on the nation. While they can use the national endowments they can delude themselves, &amp; others.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>