<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> took her guests to Malvern, and left me in peace, but beyond writing a letter about Easter Offerings to the diocese, and arranging my table. I did little! The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName>, Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, Davies<persName xml:id="4189"></persName>, Money&#8211;Kyrle<persName xml:id="4330"></persName>, &amp; the new Diocesan Missioner lunched here, and afterwards we all attended the meeting of the Diocesan Mission Committee in the Dining Room. Beattie<persName xml:id="4506"></persName> fetched me in his car, &amp; took me to the iron room where a club for discharged ex&#8211;services men was making its start. I declared the club open in a short speech, &amp; then left the concert to take its course. There was but a small gathering of men, which may have been owing to the comparatively early hour at which the function took place, but suggested an indifference of the majority to the effort. Nor was I greatly impressed by the temper of the gathering. It seemed to me listless &amp; even unfriendly. Beattie assured me that this was not the case, and that it was the men's awe of the episcopate, but that I find difficult to credit. They did, indeed, give three cheers for "D<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Henson", but <hi rend="underline">that</hi> also did not sound very hearty. The truth is that there is a thoroughly nasty temper abroad in Hereford as elsewhere, and my known dislike of "Labour" methods may well make me an object of suspicion. I notice that the railway men in Leicester have presented cross &amp; candlesticks to the Socialist parson's church there as a thank&#8211;offering for their victory &amp; in memory of the great strike!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>