<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Addresses at Confirmations must needs be concerned with a few subjects, &amp; do not lend themselves to much variety. I incline to emphasise the human aspect of the rite as constituting religiously an assumption of the "toga virilis" [costume of manhood]: and I do not emphasise sufficiently perhaps the more strictly ecclesiastical aspect. It seems a futile performance to go over matters which must have been handled in the confirmation classes, and the most that can reasonably be expected is that one should succeed in interesting &amp; impressing the candidates so that their confirmation acquires in their minds a shade more of spiritual significance than it might otherwise have. Perhaps the new importance which has been bestowed on women ought to induce one to say something about feminine responsibilities, and those who regard the Enabling Act as a great Spiritual Event will emphasise the meaning of the new franchise which it confers on every baptised person above the age of 18. But I find it difficult to treat with religious solemnity that squalid essay in denominationalism. To hold my peace in view of the <hi rend="underline">fait accompli</hi> is the utmost to which my self&#8211;suppression attains! At most it can mean very little in the parishes. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
            <p>The weather was most delightful, and rendered my motoring extremely pleasant. I left the Palace a few minutes after 9 a.m., and motored to Cleobury Mortiner where I arrived in good time for the Confirmation at 11 a.m. There were only 15 candidates, (11 from Cleobury Mortimer and 4 from Neen Savage). I fear Malden<persName xml:id="4917"></persName>, the Vicar, is more "Catholick" than discrete. The patronage is in the hands of Keble College, Oxford. After service I motored to Tenbury; &amp; lunched at the Vicarage. At 3 p.m. there was a Confirmation in the parish church. The candidates numbered 88, of whom 34 were males. Several of the clergy from the Deanery were present: &amp; Fortescue<persName xml:id="4760"></persName> carried the staff. After tea in the vicarage, I returned to the Palace, arriving about 6 p.m. </p>
            <p>The Ecclesiastical Secretary writes to say that he "purposes asking the Lord Chancellor<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> to present the Rev. II. Basil Martin<persName xml:id="4322"></persName>, Vicar of Pudleston, to the benefice of Hatfield": and Lord Pembroke<persName xml:id="5306" display="no"></persName> writes to say that he has agreed to my request that he sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> offer the living of Abdon to the Vicar of Lee S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>. Margaret. If these arrangements are successfully through, there will be two tiny parishes merged in their contiguous parishes. I suppose that this policy of reducing the number of independent cures, desirable on many grounds as it is, will imply a certain loss of influence for the rural church. The parishioners will lament the absence of a resident parson, and there <hi rend="underline">will</hi> be a measure of justification for their lamentation. On the balance of mischiefs I think that amalgamation is the preferable policy. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>