<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[158] </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>Before getting up I read through the book which Ingram<persName xml:id="166"></persName> commended to me so earnestly ̶ "The Special Bases of the Anglican Claim by George J. Holden M.A. new &amp; revised edition, with notes of F.C.R. Hicks M.A. and S.L. Ollard M.A. with foreword by the L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Bishop of London A.R. Mowbray &amp; Co.</p>
            <p>I left the Palace in company with the Bps. of Peterboro<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> E.<persName xml:id="3668"></persName> &amp; I., and was dropped at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName><hi rend="italic">. There I was called to Lambeth by telephone. The Abp.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> wanted to talk about the course he had best take over the Divorce Bill.<note xml:id="519" n="1"></note></hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">He had just rec</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">my Dioc: Messenger and read my message to the clergy on Marriage &amp; Divorce. He said he agreed with it. </hi>The particular point on which he was in doubt was an amendment wh. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><persName xml:id="311"></persName> was prepared to move leaving those married under new law without remedy against the parson if he refused these communion. This, though in the interest of the clergy brought in Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> as the authority for determining who sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> &amp; who sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be admitted to the Holy Comn.; &amp; therefore, w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not only be a bad precedent but w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> raise the question of what is called "Erastianism" in an acute form. I agreed with his Grace that the amendment had best not be moved<hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Abp. was more flustered &amp; worried than I have yet seen him, except at the time of my Consecration. </hi>He certainly is horribly pressed. I lunched at the Athenaeum, &amp; then went back to Hereford. I arrived in a downpour of rain, &amp; was met by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. There was a considerable accumulation of letters on which I set to work after dinner.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>