<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A warm wet day, bad for body and mind. I breakfasted with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; then walked to Westminster, where I received the H.C. in Henry VII's Chapel. The attendance of bishops &amp; clergy was not great, indeed considering that it was the last occasion on which the Welsh representatives would attend as members of the Canterbury Convocation<orgName xml:id="68"></orgName>, it was disappointingly small. Nor was it satisfactory that out of the 70 clergy no more than half a dozen communicated. <hi rend="bold underline">The rule of fasting communion has cancelled the sense of fellowship. </hi>After service I went into the City, &amp; changed a cheque. Then I returned to Westminster, lunched at the Church House with the Bishops, and attended the Convocation. The Bishops went in procession to the Lower House, &amp; there the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> discoursed to us both on the severance of the Welsh dioceses, &amp; the Enabling Act. The Archbishop of York<persName xml:id="130"></persName> <hi rend="underline">in mufti</hi> sate beside the Primate. Then we returned to the Upper House, and spent the afternoon exchanging compliments with the Welsh bishops. I dined at the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Pancras Hotel with the <orgName xml:id="4">Seven</orgName>. Masterman<persName xml:id="431"></persName> was host. Swallow<persName xml:id="91"></persName>, Russell<persName xml:id="2057"></persName>, Bp. Stevens<persName xml:id="72"></persName>, White, Pelham, &amp; the Vicar of Chigwell<persName xml:id="5147"></persName> were there. It was the 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> meeting of the Club, which I founded with Marsden<persName xml:id="82"></persName> in 1899. We have all grown older, &amp; the world is greyer now. Some have passed away. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>