<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi>[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Wednesday, January 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>Many a modern minister in our so&#8211;called "free" churches has felt that he had no more sacred calling than to rid his church of the incubus of the creed. Pitching creeds overboard has become his most exhiliarating &amp; his most sacred task.</p>
            </div>
            <p>Raymond Calkins<persName xml:id="5135"></persName> in "Approaches towards Christian Unity". </p>
            <p>I wrote a few letters, &amp; then went off to London for the Bishops' Meeting. The weather was atrocious, &amp; it made journeying melancholy. I drove to <hi rend="bold underline">49 Warwick Square</hi>, &amp; deposited my bags. Then I went to the barber, &amp; had my locks shorn. To the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; read Clemenceau's<persName xml:id="4940"></persName> novel: it is full of effective satire on current life. I dined with mine host. Bridget<persName xml:id="1650"></persName> and her husband were there. He has but recently returned from Riga. He takes much the same view of the European situation as Keynes<persName xml:id="5100"></persName> &amp; thinks that we must make terms with the Soviet government in Russia.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> was in the Club. I could not avoid meeting him. He exhibited his usual courtesy, though he was evidently embarrassed. He said that the outlook was gloomy on every hand: &amp; indeed gave reason for hope nowhere. I agreed, but could not help reflecting that it was odd that he should feel like that on the morrow of his notable parliamentary triumph. His Grace's difficulties are, perhaps, only now beginning since the Enabling Act has been passed.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>