<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I wrote letters in the Athanaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and then went to the barber &amp; had my hair cut. Then I lunched in the Club at the same table with Pelham<persName xml:id="3580"></persName>, the Vicar of Barking. Archdeacon Gibbs<persName xml:id="2722"></persName>, &amp; the Bishop of Chester<persName xml:id="2409"></persName>.</p>
            <p>I walked to Lambeth, and attended <hi rend="bold underline">the meeting of Bishops</hi>. An opportunity presented itself, <hi rend="underline">I said what I thought about the Bishop of Salisbury's<persName xml:id="178"></persName> foolish letter to the "Times". He made a rather heated reply, but the general sense of the bishops was with me. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> expressed much approval of the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and so did Buckle<persName xml:id="322"></persName>, whom I saw in the Club. </hi>Then I visited the dentist, and, when I had finished with him, I returned to the Club, and wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>.</p>
            <p>Two items of news in the evening papers strike me as more than commonly grave. The dockers are refusing to load ships with ammunition for Poland: and the agricultural labourers are organizing marches to London in order to demand 50/&#8211; a week. The hearing of the Railwaymen's monstrous demand for an additional pound a week all round is evoking some suggestive evidence. They do not base the demand on the increased price of necessaries, but on the increased wages of other classes of workmen. The Railwaymen find themselves out&#8211;bought in the shops by the dockers and pitmen. <hi rend="underline">Hinc lacrymoe rerum</hi> [hence weep about affairs]<hi rend="underline">!</hi> We <hi rend="underline">must</hi> come to a catastrophe on these lines.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
            <p>"Truth" has a paragraph about the vacant see of Durham, and mentions the Bishops of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> and Hereford as likely to be offered Moule's<persName xml:id="276"></persName> succession. It adds that the latter would be welcomed &amp; useful in the North. I ran into Charles, &amp;, of course, he began to talk as if it were a settled thing that I must be Bishop of Durham! I told him that it was one of the unlikeliest events in the world. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName> mentioned Strong<persName xml:id="120"></persName> as both likely and a desirable successor to Moule. I must need think that, if Strong would accept the Bishoprick (and I think he would) his appointment would be excellent</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic underline">Wild</hi><hi rend="italic"> tells me that the old days of capitular strife have returned in Durham to the scandalous amusement of the people. I am glad my resident there is associated in the people's rememberance with capitular peace. Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> reports much bitterness and bickering. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He says that Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> is universally detested, and that Watkins<persName xml:id="590s"></persName> is openly his enemy. It is all very woeful &amp; scandalous</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi></p>
            <p>Why are these little societies of dignified &amp; learned clergymen so frequently distinguished by their internecine quarrels? I have often asked myself that question, and never yet succeeded in finding an answer which is satisfying. About the scandalous fact, however, there can be no shadow of a doubt.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>