<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A glorious day. An unhelpful breakfast of light talking, myself the chief offender: and then, after reading over my discourse, I walked to the parish church with the Vicar. There was a considerable, but not a crowded, congregation, which listened with close attention to my <hi rend="italic">sermon on "Religious isolation". I celebrated as well as preached. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Vicar was pleased to tell me what the clergy generally thought of me</hi><hi rend="italic">! He said that they thought my great power was that of a debater, and that I was "so clever" that I could advocate either side of a case with equal success! I suppose the suggestion is that I have no principles, &amp; merely contend for the love of contention! Well, well: it is good (though rarely flattering) to see ourselves as others see us!</hi> At Evensong there was a great crowd in the parish church. I preached from S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> John VI. 68,69 with special reference to marriage. The attention was close &amp; sustained, and, if I may judge from the observations made to me afterwards, an impression was made. I was favourably impressed by the good discipline in the choir&#8211;vestry. The choir – 24 boys &amp; 20 men – behaved reverently. As we walked home through the streets which were swarming with young lads and lassies, most of whom did not look as if they had been to church, there was a despondent thought in one's mind that our congregations even when they fill the churches to the full, yet leave the bulk of the people outside. Before going to bed I had a good deal of talk with the Vicar, who seems a good fellow.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>