<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I dictated a number of letters to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>. There arrived from the Oxford Press a number of copies for the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. <hi rend="bold underline">One copy I sent to Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName> for the King</hi>. <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName> &amp; Kitty his wife left us: and in the evening Mary Radford<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> arrived with my godson, John<persName xml:id="3886"></persName>. I received from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ralph M. Easley, Chairman of the Executive Council of the National Civic Federation<orgName xml:id="326"></orgName>, a request for permission to reprint the Article on "The Church &amp; Socialism" in the E.R. He also sent me some copies of the "National Civic Federation Review" from which I gathered that the situation in America is more like that in Great Britain than I had supposed. I wrote at once in reply as follows:&#8211;</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>April 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920</p>
            <p>My dear Sir,</p>
            <p>I have to acknowledge your very interesting communication of the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> inst., and the enclosed copies of "The National Civic Federation Review", which I have read with very great interest.</p>
            <p>So far as I am concerned you are heartily welcome to make any use you will of the Article in the "Edinburgh Review" (Jan. 1920) which I wrote on "The Church &amp; Socialism".</p>
            <p>The situation in America appears to present a closer resemblance to that in Great Britain than I had supposed. On both sides of the Atlantic the eager entrance of the Churches into economic conflicts has been attended by this considerable disadvantage of inoculating them with an eager restless spirit akin to, perhaps identical with, that fanaticism which has ever been the shadow of religious zeal.</p>
            <p>I cannot pretend to take an optimistic view of the outlook. The War has shaken everybody out of normal grooves, &amp; induced a temper, the remotest conceivable from caution, or equity, or balanced thinking.</p>
            <p>Believe me,</p>
            <p>Yours v. faithfully,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford.</p>
            <p>Ralph M. Easley Esq.</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>