<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">4th Sunday in Lent, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>A bright morning after a night's rain. I went to the Cathedral &amp; received the Holy communion at 8 a.m. As we returned through the garden after service, I was pleased and <hi rend="underline">surprised</hi> to see a thrush busy at his worm on the lawn. So few are the birds this year that we welcome a singing bird's appearance as a notable event. </p>
            <p>I motored to <hi rend="underline">Hope&#8211;under&#8211;Dinmore</hi>, &amp; there confirmed 24 candidates. The parson, Carlton, impressed me well, though perhaps too addicted to "Catholick" notions. After service I lunched with M. Burrell at Hampton Court. This is an old and interesting house, dating from the XIV century. The chapel contains some excellent medieval glass. After lunch, I motored to <hi rend="underline">Ludlow</hi>, and confirmed 85 candidates in the noble church. I had tea with "Archdeacon" Maude<persName xml:id="5163"></persName>, whom I licensed to officiate in the diocese. His brother&#8211;in&#8211;law is Stamar<persName xml:id="5154"></persName>, the new Rector of Berrington. By this time the weather had changed for the worse, &amp; I motored back to Hereford in a blizzard. </p>
            <p>The newspapers report a revolution in Berlin organised by the Monarchist factions. The Republican government has fled to Dresden, &amp; proclaimed a general strike. Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> is disposed to think that this episode is to be reckoned as a fortunate event, &amp; speculates on its effect on our Labour Party, who have been loudly philo&#8211;German. I am disposed to take a less sanguine views. If Germany goes into civil war, and then falls into anarchy, the consequences both in France &amp; in Britain must needs be calamitous. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>