<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote an article on "Marriage &amp; Divorce" for the next issue of the "Diocesan Messenger", in which I urge the clergy to read the Majority Report of the Divorce Commission as well as the Minority Report, and indicate some sympathy with the new Bill</hi>. In view of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> I feel it necessary to define my attitude. After lunch I walked for 2 hours on the beach with <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, &amp; then wrote to Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> and Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>.</p>
            <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> forwards a letter from M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Moore, the wife of the Harvard Professor<persName xml:id="1266"></persName>. It contains the expression of a sentiment which must be widely distributed in the United States: "<hi rend="underline">I should think you would hardly like to confess that you know an American after the shocking default of our country in the matter of international relations. We are humiliated beyond words. My husband is speaking as often as he can on affairs of the Near East, trying to build up a sentiment for better things. Much of it is ignorance on the part of our people. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">[</hi><hi rend="underline">We can hardly wait for the next presidential election to have done with Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName> &amp; his ilk</hi>."<hi rend="bold">] </hi>Certainly the moral reputation of the great Republic never stood so low as at the present time, &amp; the President whose sonorous platitudes were welcomed with such rapture, as if they constituted a new revelation from above is in the most abject situation conceivable, disowned at home &amp; discredited abroad, a convicted Pecksmiff. It is only considerations of business that hold us back from giving open expression to our disgust and contempt for the man &amp; all he stands for!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>