<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The weather cleared, &amp; my journey was made under sunshine. But my departure was saddened by the tidings that Charles Parker<persName xml:id="290"></persName> was dying.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">I left Hereford at 9.55 a.m., and reached Paddington at 2.45 p.m. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; afterwards proceeded to Windsor where I arrived in due course at the Castle. I found myself comfortably established in 448 449 West Front. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Dean<persName xml:id="4115"></persName> came to my room, &amp; was most friendly. At dinner I sate beside the Queen<persName xml:id="2728" display="no"></persName>, &amp; had much friendly conversation with her. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner the King<persName xml:id="2727" display="no"></persName> fastened on me, &amp; we had a great talk</hi><hi rend="italic">. In the course of conversation I mentioned, &#x00E0; propos of the P. of W.<persName xml:id="5186"></persName>, that I had just edited a memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> of Sir W. Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName>, &amp; w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be gratified if H.M. would accept a copy. The King was most gracious, &amp; said he w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be delighted. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">(</hi><hi rend="italic">We spoke about Prohibition, &amp;</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> the King said that Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> had hustled him into undertaking to abstain during the War, &amp; he had been miserable for 5 years!)</hi> <hi rend="italic">Our talk was protracted, but discursive, &amp; I don't find much to record. After their Majesties had withdrawn, I went to the smoking room for awhile before going to bed. So far my visit has been very pleasant. Their Majesties have been most kind &amp; welcoming: and Prince Henry<persName xml:id="5185"></persName> pleased me beyond my expectations.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <p>The King spoke of the Prince of Wales<persName xml:id="5186"></persName>. "He won't read anything: not even the newspapers: but he has a rare power of getting knowledge from conversation &amp; a curious ability of saying the right thing in any situation." I suggested that in these respects he "took after" his Royal Grandfather: &amp; the King agreed. The Queen told me at dinner that the Prince commits his speeches to memory. These speeches are composed for him by "Griggs<persName xml:id="5180"></persName>, the editor of the Round Table". So H.M., and he ought to know. I was impressed by the evident thought which both their Majesties had given to the Labour question. The King had talked with Adamson, &amp; been assured by him that the workmen had no grievance against the Crown.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>