<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>The seat of Truth is aloft, of Virtue in the midst; both places of honour: but neither truth nor virtue draws to an utter extremity.</p>
            <p>Sir Edwin Sandys<persName xml:id="1987"></persName></p>
            </div>
            <p>It was snowing hard at daybreak. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bickerstaff</hi><persName xml:id="4923"></persName>, bidding him come here to see me at 4 p.m. on Thursday next.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. S. J. Richards</hi> came to see me in obedience to my summons. He brought with him his churchwarden, a farmer named Hassall. He admitted that he had closed his churches on November 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, and one of them on Nov. 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. He explained the circumstances, and promised that the fault should not be repeated. The population of Walterstone &amp; another parish in the diocese of Llandaff, which he holds by dispensation, does not reach 200 souls, and of these 3/4 are Dissenters. M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi>Richards is unmarried, &amp; lives in lodgings in Pandy. I asked how he occupied his time. He said that he had hobbies of his own – liturgiology &amp; music &#8211; &amp; these helped him to endure the solitude. He was a round thick&#8211;lipped man of a familiar Welsh type, not unlike in aspect the Bishop of St. David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName>.</p>
            <p>I attended <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilley's</hi><persName xml:id="3618"></persName> lecture in the Lady Chapel. It was excellent. He started by quoting from an Oratorian, who wrote in the early part of the XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tabaraud</hi><persName xml:id="5191"></persName>: This excellent man appears to have reviewed the prospects of Christian Union in 1808, and arrived at a very depressing conclusion. Lilley's thesis that the real barriers are the conflicting "group temperaments", which have developed since the Reformation contains much, though not the whole, truth.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bossuet</hi><persName xml:id="5192"></persName> [sic] negotiations with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leibnitz</hi><persName xml:id="5193"></persName> for the reconciliation of the Lutherans and Roman Catholics "broke down on this point of variation".</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"Individual Catholic doctrines, such as purgatory or the Mass, Leibnitz thought that his countrymen might accept: but he refused to guarantee that they would believe to&#8211;morrow what they believed today. <hi rend="underline">"We prefer</hi>", he said, "<hi rend="underline">to belong to a Church eternally variable, &amp; for ever moving forwards"</hi>. [v. Cambridge. M.H. V. 87 ]</p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jurieu</hi><persName xml:id="5194"></persName>, the Calvanist opponent of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bossuet</hi>, anticipated <hi rend="doubleunderline">Newman's</hi><persName xml:id="337"></persName> theory of development, and he was largely in agreement with the famous Jesuit, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petavius</hi>. The modern Roman Catholick has accepted the argument of the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Calvanist. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Salmon</hi><persName xml:id="2993"></persName> points out that the whole value of the theory of Development depends for the Roman Catholic on the dogma of Papal Infallibility, by which true development can be surely and authoritatively declared:</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"There are Eastern developments and Western ones, Protestant and Romish, even infidel developments: which is the right one? The Romanist answers, The Church of Rome is infallible: she alone has been commissioned to develop doctrine the right way; all other developments are wrong. Let the Romanist prove that, &amp; he may use the doctrine of Development, if he then cares to do so: but it is quite plain that without the doctrine of Roman infallibility, the doctrine of Development is perfectly useless to a Romish advocate". [ v. "Infallibility of the Church" p.42.].</p>
            </div>
            <p>This seems to me sound as well as acute. The proving of Infallibility is, in the nature of the case, impossible.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>