<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The most glorious day imaginable! I walked with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in the garden for half an hour before going off to Bradford. <hi rend="bold underline">I left Hereford at 11.35 a.m., &amp; vi&#x00E2; Droitwich and Birmingham (where there was a wait of 1 hour 15 mins) travelled to Bradford, arriving 7.5 p.m. A churchwarden met me, &amp; I went straight to the Vicarage</hi><hi rend="bold">,</hi> where two aged ladies, the mother and mother&#8211;in&#8211;law of the Vicar received me. On the journey, I read "The Skilled Labourer 1760&#8211;1832", by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hammond.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Stanford Jones<persName xml:id="5165"></persName>, the Vicar of Bradford, is a slightly&#8211;built man, with an eager look and an alert manner</hi><hi rend="italic">. He has an intelligent face, and a manner which might be called conventional though in no offensive degree. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He certainly has a sense of humour, and a little appetite for good stories</hi><hi rend="italic">. In his study there was not the plenitude and variety of books that might indicate the student's tastes and habits, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">there were enough to suggest a measure of intellectual variety</hi><hi rend="italic">, and this character disclosed the purpose of a preacher who would be accounted "abreast of the times". I observed Inge's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> "Outspoken Essays"<ref xml:id="1083"></ref> on his table together with several volumes of recent sermons. He was one of the members of the Mansfield Conference on reunion, and shared the distrust of Lacey<persName xml:id="1936"></persName> which Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> expressed, and which has been so shockingly justified by Lacey's ignominious &amp; unsuccessful efforts to explain away his signature appended to the findings of the Conference. The Vicar of Bradford would appear to be one of the neo&#8211;Evangelicals, who is seeking escape from the bondage of the party.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>