<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">The paper announces the death of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Humphrey Ward</hi><persName xml:id="1224"></persName>. It is but a few weeks since we united in a final and futile protest against the Enabling Bill. </p>
            <p>I confirmed about 200 candidates from the Rural Deanery in S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas Church. The clergy, 14 of them, stood in a semi&#8211;circle behind me while the laying on of hands proceeded. The service occupied just under an hour and a half. The weather, which was threatening, held up until the service was over, and then developed into a hurricane of wind &amp; rain. Through this I motored to Madley, and there confirmed 21 persons in the glorious parish church. In spite of the weather there was a fair congregation. I got back to the Palace shortly before 8 p.m.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The confirmation addresses are woefully lacking in variety. I think the clergy generally like them. M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Turner with every appearance of sincerity thanked me for my address, &amp; added that "it was a model for addressing country people". I am not sure that his opinion is worth much, but he has been concerned with rural folk all his ministerial life, and he is said to be a good man. The candidates themselves are always very attentive, &amp; give the impression of being really interested. But the lack of variety is distressing, &amp;, if I took about a chaplain with me, would drive the poor wretch to distraction. Fortunately for human nature it includes an amazing faculty of sustained inattention, and chaplains, like regular church goers, develop this faculty to its greatest perfection. It is, moreover, the salvation of bishops.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>