<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[170]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Bishop Wordsworth's<persName xml:id="1554"></persName> manual may fairly serve me as a scholarly &amp; authoritative statement of Anglicanism from the original Tractarian point of view. It is, of course, utterly uncritical both in its handling of Scripture, &amp; in its references to the Fathers. Two antipathies hold the writer to his <hi rend="underline">via media</hi>, that against the Papacy, and that against the Dissenters. The equal &amp; sustained violence of these conflicting sentiments keep him steady in his difficult pose<hi rend="italic">. </hi>The hatred of Dissenters persists in the neo&#8211;Tractarians, though it has generally to be 'camouflaged' by a plentiful parade of fraternal verbiage, but the hatred of the Papacy has given place to a regretful admiration. This, perhaps, is the more surprising since the Papacy has become still more extravagant in its claim, &amp; still more hostile in its attitude. The weakening of one of the two balancing antipathies has given increased power to the other, with the result that the difficult central poise of Tractarian Anglicanism has become impossible, &amp; the drift towards Rome is becoming irresistible. Add that the collapse of the Establishment before the forces of denominational self&#8211;assertiveness, &amp; secularist Erastianism has withdrawn the great moderating principle from the English church, &amp; the irreparable character of the present failure is made sufficiently evident. Anglicanism can only survive as an interesting variety of Protestant Christianity with a polity framed on the ancient model. To claim a "Catholick" character is to be committed to a surrender to Rome.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
            <p>I confirmed nearly 50 persons in Condover Church: Fielden<persName xml:id="4560"></persName> came to the service. After lunch I motored to Harley, &amp; confirmed 25 candidates. Afterwards I returned to Hereford, arriving about 6.30 p.m.</p>
            <p>The rates for the half&#8211;year are &#x00A3;60 15. 6: an increase of &#x00A3;11. The amount levied is now 13/&#8211;.</p>
            <p>Among my letters was one from Alington<persName xml:id="541"></persName>. He expresses appreciation of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, which he thinks "very successful". I wish I could think the same. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>