<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[157] </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>I received the Holy Communion in the Palace Chapel, &amp; read the lessons at Mattins. After breakfast I walked in the garden with the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> E. and I. We encountered the gardener with an Aberdeen terrier. I asked whether he could obtain one for me, &amp; he said he thought he could. So I asked him to do so. Then I went in the Bishop's motor to Westminster, &amp; spent the day there, for the business, swollen by various new items from the Lower House, held us until 4 p.m. In the morning I successfully resisted a proposal to go back, at the instance of the Lower House, on our resolution fixing 2 as the minimum number of communicants. <hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon I spoke against the Bishop of Chelmsford's<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> motion urging the National Assembly to take the reform of the Courts in hand immediately. He was seconded by the Bishop of Truro</hi><persName xml:id="5047"></persName>. My point was that the conflict of first principles within the Church of England would be precipitated by the attempt to solve the problem of the final Court; that I didn't wish the disaster of disruption to be hastened: <hi rend="bold underline">that the National Assembly ought to earn the confidence of the Church &amp; Nation before it embarked on the thorny question of the Courts. </hi>The Abp. of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> made a lengthy statement on the whole question, &amp; came down on the side of the resolution: His Grace was followed by the Bp. of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> who "went for" me. I contented myself with getting the resolution verbally amended. </p>
            <p>The Bishop of Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName> is reported to be ill of pleurisy &amp; congestion of the lungs. He lies at Cambridge in his brother's house.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>