<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> changed the order of business with the result that the Crown Patronage debate did not come on before lunch. In a thin and jaded house I made a speech which deserved more success than it had. As I walked away I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName> gaiterless &amp; with no strings in his hat. He is getting white but remains as alert &amp; agile as ever. The way in which he threaded his way through the traffick in Oxford Street w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have done credit to a street Arab! I had tea in his rooms in Margaret Street &amp; talked for half an hour. He is just back from his Mission in Cambridge, which has evidently pleased him greatly. He found little trace of modernism among the men. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bethune&#8211;Baker</hi><persName xml:id="4131"></persName> had not affected them. He said that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Orchard</hi> had accepted Ordination from Hereford, &amp; he was not well impressed with him. <hi rend="bold underline">Gore said that he had been greatly surprised at the sudden downfall of the National Church idea, &amp; was, of course, immensely pleased.</hi></p>
            <p>Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> came to fetch me from the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and carried me to 9 Ralston Street, where I dined with him &amp; <persName xml:id="2056">Elsie</persName> very pleasantly. After dinner I went upstairs &amp; saw <persName xml:id="2764">Peggy</persName> and <persName xml:id="2799">Rex</persName> in their cots – a sweet spectacle. Then Harold drove me back to the Athenaeum, and we parted. </p>
            <p>In the club I found the Bishop of St. David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName> and St. Asaph<persName xml:id="1454"></persName>, and exchanged a few remarks with them before going to the club. I suspect that the Upper House of the little Province of Wales is hardly a happy family. </p>
            </body></text></TEI>