<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. and received the Holy Communion. My wife and my guests went with me. <hi rend="bold underline">I was particularly pleased to notice that Professor Bacon<persName xml:id="3057"></persName>, who is a Congregationalist, communicated</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After breakfast William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Lingen, where I preached to the congregation of villagers at a choral celebration. I had expected Mattins, and my sermon was determined by the first lesson. This ruffled me, and I was not well&#8211;pleased to notice the linen vestments &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">divers interpolations in the service</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>But who dares so much as whisper that Rubricks should be obeyed? The weather which had been most hostile when we travelled to Lingen improved wonderfully, &amp; we drove back to Hereford in sunshine.</p>
            <p>James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> brought the Judge, Lord Coleridge<persName xml:id="5145"></persName>, to tea. I had some interesting conversation with him. When he had gone, I had scant time to get myself in order for preaching at Evensong at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's Mission Church, Holmer. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Waterfield<persName xml:id="5129"></persName>, &amp; Prof. Bacon accompanied me. The little church was well&#8211;filled, and, as soon as I had suppressed the coughing, the congregation was very attentive.</p>
            <p>Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lilley<persName xml:id="4307"></persName> came in to supper: and we had much pleasant talk. The new Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> seems disposed to be friendly and loyal. His wife<persName xml:id="5129"></persName> will certainly be popular.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>