<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>I travelled to Oxford by the 10.40 a.m. train, and arrived in good time for lunch with the <persName xml:id="66">Pembers</persName><persName xml:id="937"></persName>. At 2 p.m. the Funeral took place. Johnson<persName xml:id="2407"></persName> and I officiated; Frank read the lesson from the Warden's stall. There was a good muster of Fellows and Luordams. The procession to Holywell Cemetery was very solemn. I recalled the same procession nearly 6 years ago when we were carrying Warden Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> to the grave. Now it is Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName>. The spring&#8211;like softness of the air and the bright sun made everything very gracious &amp; comforting<hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I read the prayer of Committal, and gave the Blessing</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi> Then I walked with Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>, and called on Fletcher<persName xml:id="355"></persName> who is ill with influenza. After tea in the Common Room, I went to the station, &amp; travelled to Hereford, arriving at 8.25. The Dean<persName xml:id="3471"></persName> was on the platform. I gave him a lift to the Cathedral gates.</p>
            <p>There was little interest among my letters.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">And so the story of my relations with Raleigh is ended. </hi>He was enormously difficult to converse with, for his moroseness of manner and economy of speech made conversation extremely difficult and very laborious. Hence those who only met him in society, and [sic] occasionally conceived an unfavourable notion of him as a man of a hard and cryptic nature, with whom friendly intercourse was all but impossible. <hi rend="bold underline">But his heart was golden. He loved his friends, and was most patient &amp; forgiving. He was a wise, true, generous man, &amp; the best of friends</hi>. I owed him much, consulted him often, &amp; loved him. I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>