<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[139]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>After breakfast I walked round to James's<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> office, and transacted some urgent business. Then I dictated some letters to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ward<persName xml:id="5181"></persName>, the Vicar of Croft, called about the schools in his parish. I counselled surrendering them to the local authority. It is too late now to spend money on the schools, which must in any case be handed over to the State shortly. He stayed to lunch. After lunch I received a deputation of parishioners from Coddington protesting against the union of that little parish with Wellington Heath. I was very polite, but gave no hope, that my mind could be changed. The total population of Coddington is only 120, and the value of the living about &#x00A3;230.</p>
            <p>I sent copies of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> and to Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>. Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> writes to say that he has received his copy from the Press:</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"I have just got from the Clarendon Press your life of the Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName> – most interesting of course to those who like us of 1883 saw practically the whole of his rule. I think it is a very good sketch – but could have stood more of the College &amp; less of the politics. But of course those who want to know about All Souls in detail are but a handful. You hit his wisdom off perfectly well, the more I think over him he more do I marvel at the fact with which he discharged a most difficult office. Fancy having to deal with Robarts<persName xml:id="537"></persName> for one hour, &amp; Holland<persName xml:id="776"></persName> for the next, each set on his particular grievance! And he was always a kindly being."</p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi></p>
            <div type="verse">
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Sin&#8211;hounds.</hi></p>
            <p>My sins, like stag&#8211;hounds, do my soul pursue,</p>
            <p>Wish eager haste they hunt from scent to view,</p>
            <p>And though I cross &amp; double as I go,</p>
            <p>And soil in Lethe's conscience dead'ning flow,</p>
            <p>I cannot baffle them by devious flight,</p>
            <p>Remorse, the Huntsman, always casts them right.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell, I do not know, alack!</p>
            <p>How many hounds there may be in the pack;</p>
            <p>I know that some are big, and black as night,</p>
            <p>And some, like whippets, slim and buff and white.</p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">The bigger hounds are mute as on they fly,</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="underline">The little sin&#8211;dogs make the loudest cry.</hi></p>
            <p>F. C. G.</p>
            </div>
            <p>I copied these lines from the Westminster Gazette. The initials are those of Carruthers Gould<persName xml:id="1000"></persName>, the cartoonist.</p>
            <p>I sent the inscription for John's christening mug as follows:</p>
            <p>John Edward Dicey Radford<persName xml:id="3886"></persName>.</p>
            <p>Baptised March 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1916.</p>
            <p>in the Cathedral, Allahabad.</p>
            <p>from his Godfather.</p>
            <p>Herbert, Bishop of Hereford.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>