<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">I motored to Onibury after an early lunch. William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> young brother sate beside him. It seemed natural to invite him to witness his brother's confirmation</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>There were 26 candidates, of whom 15 were males. The little church is very interesting, and has been carefully restored. It consists of a rather long chancel, and a nave. There is a squat Norman tower, &amp; the chancel arch is Norman. Above the arch, and on the north wall are fading frescoes. There is a gallery, and an old font. The congregation, mostly women, filled the church; children occupied the gallery. <hi rend="bold underline">William was confirmed last of the male candidates</hi>. After service, which just lasted an hour, we had tea in the Vicarage. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Swinnerton&#8211;Dyer<persName xml:id="5120"></persName> from Westhope came over from Diddlesbury, &amp; had some speech with me respecting the arrangements for my visit on Low Sunday. His foolish sister<persName xml:id="5104"></persName> persists in refusing all dealings with the Vicar, who, so far as I can discover, appears to be blameless. The sun shone brightly as we returned, &amp; the last stage of the journey was illustrated by a glorious sunset. On reaching the Palace, <hi rend="bold underline">I gave William a Bible together with the notes of the address which I had given at his Confirmation</hi>. Then I wrote the letters with Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>.</p>
            <p>Warde Fowler's<persName xml:id="5159"></persName> 'Roman Essays &amp; Interpretations' contains a lecture on 'Theodor Mommsen<persName xml:id="5188"></persName>: his Life &amp; Work', printed exactly as it was delivered in 1909. It is extremely interesting, &amp; makes one realize more fully the scale of the calamity which has perverted and submerged the intellectual life of Germany.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>