<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>The whole notion of fixing the Holy Ghost to times and seasons and forms of prayer is only defensible if these performances of ours be viewed simply as a sort of impetration, to be answered in God's own queer way, at the time and through the medium we least expect. </p>
            <p>Tyrrell<persName xml:id="1084"></persName> in 1901 ('Letters' p. 148).</p>
            </div>
            <p>A glorious spring day from start to finish. I left the Palace at 9.30 a.m., and motored to Wistanstow, where I confirmed 44 candidates. The Church, dedicated to the Holy Trinity, is interesting, but the high pews almost hid the candidates from my sight! I lunched with La Touche, and then motored to Diddlebury, where I confirmed 29 candidates. After service I had to tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Martin<persName xml:id="5104"></persName>, an odd clever woman with a mania for family history. Swinneston Dyer<persName xml:id="5120"></persName>, her brother, joined us. I got back to the Palace about 7.15 p.m. </p>
            <p>The "Clarendon Press" sent me reviews of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, which had appeared in the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="underline">Glasgow Herald</hi>. Neither was particularly favourable.</p>
            <p>Holland<persName xml:id="5156"></persName> of Peterchurch accepts Weston&#8211;under&#8211;Penyard. I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Powell, the patroness of Peterchurch, suggesting that she sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> offer that living to Prebendary Stallard<persName xml:id="4117"></persName>.</p>
            <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Hereford Times</hi>' has a long &amp; hostile leader on my little letters in the Diocesan Messenger on Divorce: It is always clear to me that the time must come when the politeness of that journal will give place to another &amp; doubtless more sincere disposition!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>