<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We know only modern characters thoroughly. Men must have been dead some time for the whole truth to be told, &amp; not long enough to fade into distance – say, about 500 years, from Dante or Petrarca to Carlyle. How many of these that belong to history will bear scrutiny? The better we get to know them from letters, diaries, table talk, etc., the worse, as a rule, they appear. It is very difficult for the most keen&#8211;sighted Diogenes to detect a really good man – for instance, in the Reformation, or Revolution. We have to conclude backwards, from experience in the known to the less known age: and so are not dazzled by the halo of Fabricius &amp; Decius.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Lord Acton's Correspondence. p. 215.</p>
         </div>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went off to lunch &amp; pay calls in the county. I worked at the Lectures, &amp; then lunched with Riddell<persName xml:id="4840"></persName> t&#x00EA;te&#8211;&#x00E0;&#8211;t&#x00EA;te. After lunch I walked with him to Bullinghope, &amp; then he walked back with me to the Palace. Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came to do the letters. He will probably refuse Weston&#8211;under&#8211;Penyard, and resign his Rural Deanery. Arnold Thomas<persName xml:id="5133"></persName>, the sectary at Bristol, sent me an 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century pamphlet, issued in connexion with the Trinitarian controversy among the dissenters, in which Bishop Croft<persName xml:id="4540"></persName> was mentioned with much respect. I sent him a copy of 'The Naked Truth'<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>