<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>Major Hamilton came to see me about this hapless Vicar of Breinton<persName xml:id="5107"></persName>. He seems to have behaved beautifully himself, spending time &amp; money freely in the poor man's service, &amp; putting himself to an infinity of discomfort and exertion. But the position is impossible. The expenditure of money cannot be less than &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">10</hi> weekly in the home where he is now placed: &amp; the net income of his benefice is &#x00A3;<hi rend="underline">204</hi>.</p>
            <p>I kept indoors all day being <hi rend="underline">hors de combat</hi> with a monstrous cold, contracted last Saturday at Bridstow, and worsened by the series of confirmations &amp; the strange weather.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bowen</hi><persName xml:id="4492"></persName> came to see me, &amp; suggested that I should invite D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jones<persName xml:id="5174"></persName> of Bournemouth to stay here when he comes to edify the sectaries next week! It might be worth doing.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came to inquire whether anything could be done to establish a branch of Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName> Social Reform society: &amp; I was wholly unsympathetic. What is the use of my pretending to agree with these socialists?</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alington</hi><persName xml:id="541"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> writes to ask that he may see me in the interest of a new vague, windy project for saving the world which Baker&#8211;Wilbraham<persName xml:id="1427"></persName> and the Evangelicals are floating. I could but tell him that I was asphyxiated with societies, and</hi> <hi rend="underline">blas&#x00E9;</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">with good works</hi>!</p>
            <p>Finally, Lady Croft's daughter, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Nicholson</hi>, writes to ask for an interview in order that she may stir me up for a fresh effort for the Y.W.C.A.<orgName xml:id="237"></orgName> It is too much: these endless societies are killing all sincerity among us, &amp; making life a squirrel's cage of futile and ceaseless activity.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>