<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>A field of Thistles seemed once a battle of Pikes unto some discoverers of the Duke of Burgundy. You can apply what I exemplify. I go no farther, but leave you to yourselves; &amp; if it be possible, unto more charitable conceits of those that deserve no others imputation but. They are no Puritans: which God in goodness keep out of this Church &amp; State, as dangerous as Popery, for any thing I am able to discern: the only difference being, <hi rend="bold underline">Popery is for Tyranny, Puritanism for anarchy: Popery is original of Superstition: Puritanism, the highway unto Profaneness; both alike enemies unto Piety</hi>.</p>
         <p>Montague<persName xml:id="5134"></persName>. A. D. 1625</p>
         </div>
         <p>Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> brought Gillenders<persName xml:id="5176"></persName> to lunch. I was relieved to hear that the latter will accept Leominster. He looks a sensible strong man. At least he is the antithesis to the outgoing vicar. Then I sawed wood with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Theobald, the Inspector of schools, brought to tea his father Canon Theobald<persName xml:id="5140"></persName>, a fine old clergyman, approaching 90 years of age, but very upright &amp; alert. We conversed on politics, secular &amp; ecclesiastical. Rather to my surprise I received a cheque for four guineas on account of my little article on Prohibition. I dictated some more of the Swedish Lecture to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, but I doubt more than ever whether it will serve.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>January 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hereford</p>
         <p>I am obliged to you for your letter. In these days it is more than ever important that we should be loyal to the professed principles of the Church of England, &amp;, as far as possible, should avoid anything which might imply disregard of the Law. On both considerations I am really glad that your memorial will take the form of the Cross, &amp; not of the Crucifix. Private patronage, honourably administered in the spirit which you express, is in my judgement very serviceable to the Church, &amp; I for one should be reluctant to assist in its abolition. Certainly, when it secures to a parish the residence &amp; pastorate of a man like M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Binstead<persName xml:id="4511"></persName>, it needs no other justification.</p>
         <p>I enjoyed my visit to Mordiford on Sunday morning.</p>
         <p>Believe me. Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
         <p>J. I. Hereford Esq</p>
         </div>
               </body></text></TEI>