<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I tried to put together notes for a fresh confirmation address from the text: <hi rend="underline">"Little children, guard yourselves from idols</hi>": but my mind is reluctant. Repetition is becoming too shameless! I left the Palace about 11 a.m., and motored to Ludlow where I lunched at the Angel. Then I went on to Much Wenlock and arrived about 2.30 p.m. At 3 p.m. I confirmed 48 candidates. After the service Bartleet<persName xml:id="5067"></persName> showed the glorious parish church to me and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Then I had tea with Lady Catherine Milnes Gaskell<persName xml:id="4996"></persName>. I motored to Coalbrookdale and there confirmed 63 candidates. The church was built in 1851, and looks it! But it has fair acoustics, and a peel of 8 bells. I mounted to the belfry &amp; spoke to the ringers. I stayed the night under Bartleet's roof. We had a great talk together, &amp; did not get to bed until 1 a.m.! He impresses me well, &amp; is certainly very keen about his work. His wife is a German though born &amp; brought up in England. In spite of the fact that 3 of her brothers fought in the British Army, &amp; that one of them was killed, the panic&#8211;born suspicions of the parishioners have made continued residence in Much Wenlock odious to her, &amp; she resides in Weston. Bartleet has resumed the liberty of the bachelor, &amp; finds a certain advantage in being able to get readier access to his people. He is very full of his own war experiences, &amp; in the mood to make all manner of adventurous experiments. I think, however, that he begins to see that the problem of recasting the Anglican system in the light of the Chaplains' new convictions is not so easy a matter as it seemed in France!</p>
            </body></text></TEI>