<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>This path of hypocrisy hath been so much trod and beaten by clergymen that wise men who discerned it long since gave notice of it in a fable of a monk who, being a poor fisherman's son, still spread a net over his table as a remembrance of his mean original, till having by those shows of humility reached the highest preferments, he laid away the net, because then the fish was caught. </p>
         <p>Samuel Torshell..p. 22. (1644)</p>
         </div>
         <p>I <hi rend="bold underline">received a slender volume from Sanday<persName xml:id="359"></persName> – "Divine Overruling"</hi> – which, he explains in the Preface, "contains my last public utterances as Lady Margaret Professor." It is curiously interesting, but less well&#8211;knit &amp; well&#8211;written than most of his work.</p>
         <p>Money&#8211;Kyrle<persName xml:id="4330"></persName> &amp; Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> lunched here: &amp; we went through the commissions of the lay&#8211;readers. Binstead<persName xml:id="4511"></persName> called about his memorial Cross in the Churchyard; &amp; Claude Lighton<persName xml:id="4612"></persName>, about the scandal at Hatfield. Then I walked for an hour with Wynne&#8211;Willson.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Cross v. Crucifix is the issue which the war&#8211;memorial raises not infrequently</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Especially when the restoration of one of the old churchyard crosses is projected, this issue is certain to arise. The medievalists, of course, are insistent for the crucifix, which they assert, probably with truth, was the original form. The Romanizers have other interests than the archaeological to determine them in the same view.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>