<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>The aggrieved parent returns to the charge with the reinforcement of Potter's resignation: I judged it well to send the whole correspondence to the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> as Chairman of the Governing Body. Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came in. He tells me that it is doubtful whether I continue to be Visitor of the School since it placed itself under the Fisher Act. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be a relief to learn that I was without any <hi rend="underline">locus standi</hi> in this melancholy business.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="3512"><persName xml:id="3813">Darwins</persName></persName> went off after lunch. </hi>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored them to the station, &amp; then took me to Condover Hall where I was the guest of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fielden</hi><persName xml:id="4560"></persName>. On arriving about 4.30 p.m. I found him waiting me: We had much interesting talk over the economic situation. He says that the demands of the railway men are altogether beyond the resources of the railways: that the present situation is so unfavourable that no capital can be raised for the improvement and development of the railways: that these objects are urgently important.</p>
            <p>He expressed much discontent with the Budget, which discloses no indication of any genuine effort to affect economies. He thought that the Labour leaders were in many cases definitely aiming at revolution, but that the mass of the rank&#8211;and&#8211;file were not consciously revolutionary. The cotton industry, he said, was extraordinarily prosperous for the moment, but it was so artificial that protracted strikes might wreck it altogether. Generally, he could see no way of escape from disaster on the road which the nation is now following. I agree. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[166] </hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>May 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920. </p>
            <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Crookes,</p>
            <p>I have to acknowledge your letter &amp; enclosure, and to assure you that I will consider both very carefully. </p>
            <p>The arrangement of an exchange is not so easily made as you seem to think, for the consents of two patrons, &amp; generally also of two Bishops must be secured before the wishes of the two incumbent(s) directly concerned can be carried into effect. And it needs no showing that neither Bishops nor Patrons are eager to welcome the arrival in a parish of a clergyman who is known to be unsatisfactory, or unpopular, or undisciplined. </p>
            <p>However, I will consider the matter very carefully with an earnest desire to help. </p>
            <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford </p>
            <p>George Crookes Esq</p>
            <p>Orcop Grange, Hereford.</p>
            </div>
            <p>The afternoon post brought me two archiepiscopal letters – one from Canterbury, the other from Upsala. Both were interesting. His Grace of C.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> expresses himself with unusual cordiality, &amp; thanks me "from my heart for a most helpful &amp; encouraging letter", and adds that "it is an immense support &amp; stimulus " to 'have my thoughtful &amp; patient aid". </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">Archbishop S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> writes at some length, &amp; acknowledges receipt of a copy of "The Naked Truth"</hi><ref xml:id="1026"></ref>, which I sent him:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"I congratulate you on the edition of the Tractate of the former Herbert in Hereford. It is remarkable to find at that date in England ideas that we are accustomed to associate with later epochs. And you understand how comfortable it must be for a Swedish heart to read page 95&#8211;97, about Deacons, exactly the ideas underlying our deaconate.</p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">I am looking forward with keen interest to your lectures in the second half of September. And I have the honour of inviting you to assist a rare event of our church, I mean the consecration of two diocesan Swedish Bishops at once on the 16 after Trinity, the 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> September this year in our cathedral of Upsala, the sees of V&#x00E4;steras &amp; Wisby being now vacant by the death of two prominent members of our Episcopacy. We should consider it as a token of Christian fellowship and mutual recognition if you will accept my invitation to assist this consecration in our cathedral</hi>."</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">This invitation may have considerable importance. When I recall the importance attached in some quarters to the assistance of the Abp. of Spalato at the consecration of Laud<persName xml:id="3468"></persName>, I can imagine that a time might come when some similar importance might be attached to the Bishop of Hereford's share in a Swedish consecration</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[168]</hi></p>
            <p>I dined alone with mine host, and had much conversation with him. We ranged over a large area, &amp; touched on many subjects. The parish of Condover contains about 850 souls. Great efforts have been made to secure that every person entitled to be on the electoral roll should at least have the chance of getting his or her name entered thereon. The number of the enrolled is 170. Last week the first meeting was held, and no more than 9 persons attended! <hi rend="bold underline">There is an almost complete indifference to the whole business. How any one can go on pretending that there was ny general desire for the Enabling Act baffles me</hi>.</p>
            <p>Fielden told me that the experience of his Firm was that women were definitely inferior to men in brain capacity. They could hold their own in positions of inferiority, but could rarely rise to those of responsibility. It mattered in his opinion but little that women should be declared the equals of men, &amp; as such empowered to receive equal payment, for they would not succeed in getting employment. We discussed the Divorce Bill,<note xml:id="519" n="1"></note> &amp; I was pleased to find that we were substantially in agreement. Fielden is a keen advocate of the union of benefices, and it was with difficulty that I could make him allow that there was loss as well as gain in an arrangement which, while securing adequate employment and adequate maintenance to the parish clergy, withdraws a resident ministry from the hamlets &amp; smaller villages. The old claim of the National Church can no longer be advanced.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>