<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p><hi rend="italic">"Neither Cranmer<persName xml:id="1838"></persName> nor Laud<persName xml:id="3468"></persName> were men (was a man) without great virtues or grave faults. </hi>But <hi rend="underline">whilst Cranmer's face had been turned steadily forward towards the future</hi><hi rend="italic">, Laud's gaze was fixed in contemplation of a bygone, and, to some extent, an imaginary past.</hi></p>
            <p>S. R. Gardiner<persName xml:id="4944"></persName>. History viii. 128.</p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gardiner's</hi> analysis of Laud's policy, and the reasons of its failure is more just &amp; illuminating v.ch.LXXVIII. 'The Metropolitical Visitation' (vol viii p. 106ff). </p>
            <p>I wasted my morning in miscellaneous reading: lunched early: attended a meeting of the Union&#8211;of&#8211;Benefices Committee: motored to Bridstow and had tea with K<persName xml:id="62"></persName>: did the letters with Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruikshank</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName> sends me an account or the proceedings in Durham Cathedral on Sunday. He does not seem very cheerful about it:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"I fear that things are not yet ripe for reunion even on these modest lines, until the great 'Purge' has been affected. Four Canons were there with Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName>, Poole<persName xml:id="2810"></persName> &amp; the boys. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName> stayed away: he had promised in November to support the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> loyally though he did not like the thing: about a fortnight ago he wrote a long letter to the Bishop protesting against it, &amp; asking leave to publish. But fortunately it has not appeared. It was full of the most greasy &amp; nauseous unction. He probably felt that he had scored sufficiently when the Bishop<persName xml:id="276"></persName> backed out of his voluntary offer to come and give the blessing."</p>
            </div>
            <p>Monk certainly acted in a very despicable fashion.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>