<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[134]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>I read through the Report of the Royal Commission on Divorce &amp; Matrimonial Causes (Nov: 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1912) with the view of writing something for the <hi rend="underline">Diocesan Messenger</hi>. It is extraordinary difficult to make up one's mind whether to "cross the Rubicon" by supporting the large proposals of the Majority Report, or to gather the cheers of the ecclesiastical gallery by standing stiffly on the traditional position. The Minority Report, signed by Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName>, Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName>, and Dibden<persName xml:id="909"></persName>, is very thin and quite evidently meant to please the multitude of churchfolks. Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> article, "Divorce: the question of principle", ("The Modern Churchman", Feb: 1918) is an excellent piece of work. I wish he were on the Bench for the discussions of marriage at the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. An article headed "The Mystical Union", in the "Nation" (April 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1920) is a very sophistical composition written from the text of L<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Birkenhead's<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> speech on L<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Buckmaster's Bill.<note xml:id="519" n="1"></note> It lays down that "whatever has hopelessly broken up all chance of that mystical union (call it love, or community of spirit, or the marriage of true minds, or what you will) should be at least as strong a ground for divorce as adultery is". But adultery admits of definition and proof. Can as much be said for "whatsoever has hopelessly broken up all chance of the mystical union"? In effect, this fine plea of giving primacy to the "spiritual" aspect of marriage, works out practically as a claim for divorce by mutual consent, nay, at the wish of one of the parties.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>