<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <p>The post brought me a penitent letter from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> W. promising amendment. May God help him to hold to his good purpose! Also a formal request from the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> that I <hi rend="italic">should introduce to the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> the subject of relations with and reunion with the Non&#8211;episcopal Churches.</hi></p>
            <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> failed to be on time with the car, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Streeter had to be hustled to the station. He made an ingenious acknowledgement of his fault, which on that account I the more readily condoned. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> stayed in bed, being afflicted with a heavy cold. Add that a heavy mist lay like a wet curtain over the world, and the ill start of the day is sufficiently apparent.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">I prepared notes for my speech at Cardiff in aid of the Starving children of central Europe. These kinds of public&#8211;speaking don't really suit me. If I can judge myself, I should be best in a set political oration, and, perhaps with practice, I should make a tolerable debater. But the sentimentalism which marks successful appeals, &amp; the jokes which make the fortune of popular orators are beyond, or below me. </hi></p>
            <p>I travelled to Cardiff, and was met by the Bishop's car: after an early dinner at the Palace we all went to the technical college for the meeting. There was a good attendance. The lord Mayor presided. He is a fluent speaker, &amp; was rather too long in his opening remarks. I spoke for about 20&#8211;25 minutes, &amp; then Miss Courtney for 35minutes. An excitable Jewish Rabbi proposed a vote of thanks, &amp; we had a collection.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>