<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A note from K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> tells me that the author of the communicated article in the Times of last Saturday on the use of the R.V. in church was the Editor of the Quarterly. <hi rend="bold underline">George Prothero<persName xml:id="319"></persName> ought to have more sense</hi><hi rend="bold">,</hi> but all these "literary" folk hang together, &amp; their opposition has the effect of making dislike of the R.V. fashionable. K. himself will write on the other side next Saturday.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Meyer &amp; Shakespeare<persName xml:id="393"></persName> for information about Nonconformity. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles Scott</hi><persName xml:id="4667"></persName> came to see me. He is in treaty for a curacy in Plymouth, where he will find himself in a nest of Anglo&#8211;Romans.</p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wright</hi><persName xml:id="4457"></persName><hi rend="italic"> spoke to me this afternoon about fresh scandals at that unhappy parish Hatfield, where the parson, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bickerstaff</hi><persName xml:id="4923"></persName><hi rend="italic">, continues to live most disreputably. This is another of the Lord Chancellor's<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> livings. It is only worth &#x00A3;168. yearly according to the calendar, and there are but 205 parishioners. I called on James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> in order to learn from him whether I can do anything: he seemed doubtful. The recent case of the Vicar of Rusper indicates the difficulty of proving accusations of loose living against a clergyman. Nor can it be doubted that an incriminated parson ought to be secured against any chance of oppression. Still the scandal is notorious &amp; extreme. Something ought to be attempted in aid of the Church's good name. These tiny country parishes are very unfavourable to discipline. Men "go to pieces" through idleness &amp; solitude.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>