<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> accompanied <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and me to Bridstow, where we lunched with Miss Armitage. Then I confirmed 21 candidates in the parish church, and dedicated a memorial Cross by the roadside. The weather was very threatening, but we did succeed in escaping the rain. A good number of the parishioners came together to tea in the vicarage, and I talked to a good many of them.</p>
            <p>We got back to the Palace about 6 p.m., when Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I went through the letters. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Goad</hi><persName xml:id="5170"></persName> arrived to stay the week&#8211;end. The Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> came to dinner. We had very interesting conversation. Captain Good gives a very bad account of the Greeks &amp; Armenians, though he allows the truth of the horrible massacres of the latter. He holds strongly that the Sultan must remain in Constantinople, &amp; that S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Sophia must continue to be a mosque. It appears that the famous Church is situated in a district entirely inhabited by Turks, that there could be no regular use of it for Christian worship, &amp; that even its occasional use would necessitate an elaborate organisation of military wardship. He thought that the Arabian state which we had set up had no promise of stability. I inquired what was the truth about the Vatican's alleged intriguing against Italy during the War. He admitted that the peace pronouncement of the Pope had had a very disintegrating effect on the Italian conscripts. He denied that the division in the Eastern side of the Adriatic was racial, &amp; asserted that it was rather political. The Italians are the progressives, &amp; the Yugo&#8211;Slavs the conservatives.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>