<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Kennedy and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Streeter left in the course of the morning. At noon James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> brought me a number of papers to sign. I went to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kimbolton</hi>, accompanied by <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, and there dedicated the Memorial Cross in the Churchyard. Tallents<persName xml:id="4860"></persName> the present Vicar, Edwards<persName xml:id="4552"></persName> the late Vicar, &amp; Wynne Willson the previous Vicar took part in the service. There seemed a goodly collection of the parishioners, &amp; I <hi rend="underline">hope</hi> there will be a restoration of harmony in the parish.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName>, when he brought in the bed&#8211;room candle, announced that there was a telegram at the Post Office stating that the Bishop of Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName> had died. Events come with such rapidity, &amp; situations develope so surprisingly, that one can hardly escape a tremor of anxiety. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Bishop Moule was a genuinely good man, whose intellectual powers had been early paralyzed by his Evangelical creed</hi><hi rend="italic">. Those powers were considerable. He was an excellent scholar, and a preacher of unusual force &amp; eloquence. But his mind was tied down to such futile interests as the interpretation of prophecy, Adventism, &amp; the like, so that intelligent men, who could not but respect his goodness, put him aside as for all practical purposes useless. He was a bad diocesan, partly because his interest lay in foreign missions, &amp; partly because he had no aptitude for administration. His personal timidity made him unable to speak openly &amp; directly when such manner of speaking was required. Thus he acquired a reputation for shyness, which was not wholly deserved. He was unworthily uxorious, and in manner &amp; aspect mean.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>