<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to London after breakfast; I cleared up my room, and wrote to Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> admonishing him to make an end of side&#8211;shows, &amp; devote himself to the proper business of his residence in Oxford.</p>
            <p>The Bible &amp; Prayer Book Examiners  ̶ Davis<persName xml:id="4543"></persName>, Lushington<persName xml:id="4312"></persName>, Carpenter<persName xml:id="5149"></persName>, Tallents<persName xml:id="4860"></persName> and another  ̶ lunched here, and afterwards had their annual meeting. Parker<persName xml:id="5005"></persName> of Burwarton came also to lunch.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">The papers give considerable space to Jowett's<persName xml:id="1725"></persName> sermon in Durham cathedral. A foolish incumbent, said to be an ex&#8211;Baptist, Rev</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. P. J. Casey<persName xml:id="5150"></persName>, Vicar of Wheatley Hill made, or tried to make, a protest, and was forcibly removed while the congregation sang. </hi><hi rend="underline">"When I survey the wondrous cross"!</hi> Otherwise everything seems to have passed well enough, and the popular sympathy was disclosed not only by the attendance of the Mayor &amp; Corporation in State, but also by the attitude of the crowds inside and outside the Cathedral. It will be interesting to note the next performance of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName></p>
            <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came to be prepared after dinner: we dealt with the Lord's Day.</p>
            <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Humphrey Ward<persName xml:id="1224"></persName> wrote to me. She has been having "a long &amp; amusing talk with Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> about the Church Assembly Act". I suspect that it is precisely that temper of "amusement" which has paralysed the whole opposition to "Life &amp; Liberty". You cannot fight the dervishes of fanaticism with jests and gibes. "Life &amp; Liberty" has been in deadly earnest all the time.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>