<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>The weather improved, and my motoring was under sunshine. I left the Palace at 11 a.m., and reached Barrow House Broseley at 1.30 p.m. Here I lunched very pleasantly with Lord<persName xml:id="5178"></persName> &amp; Lady Forester. Bartleet<persName xml:id="5067"></persName> was there, &amp; Lord Forester's heir, a young man of 20. After lunch we discussed the question of uniting the livings in Lord Forester's gift: &amp; I undertook to see the Ecclesiastical Commission on the subject. Then Lord F. shewed me the parish church, a curiously interesting building, of which the chancel is reputed to be pre&#8211;Norman. We had tea at the Feathers in Ludlow on our way home, &amp; were back in the Palace by 6.30 p.m.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">The composition of this little sermon for the King's benefit causes me much perplexity. It must be short: it ought to be edifying: it should also be interesting. These are qualities not easily or often combined. My mind runs on a discourse: about the folly &amp; danger of spiritualism, a subject which must be allowed at the present time to possess both interest &amp; urgency. In the fashionable world, which will certainly be represented in my congregation, spiritualism is reported to have become a phrase, &amp; some "great ladies" are among its most ardent apostles. And it is disclosing its mischievous character by the old unmistakeable tokens. Credulity waxes &amp; deepens until an atmosphere is created in which imposture flourishes. When the demand for communications from 'the other side' is so brisk, an active factory for its satisfaction is promptly established on this: and the business is developed by much advertising!</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>