<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A wet stormy day and very cold. Accompanied by old Alderman Farr from Leominster, I motored to Staunton on Wye, and presided at a meeting of the Jarvis Trustees<orgName xml:id="313"></orgName>. There was much petty business which I got through quickly, &amp; was back in the Palace by 1 p.m. At 2 p.m. I presided over a meeting of the Diocesan Mission C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi>. We drew up regulations for the Diocesan Missioner, who is still unable to find a house.</p>
            <p>I received two affectionate letters from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, the one from Kobe, Japan dated March 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, the other from Yokohama, dated March 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. He had received at once 3 letters from me, the latest bearing date January 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> seem that the letters I wrote on November 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and Dec. 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> have gone astray.</p>
            <p>Hutton<persName xml:id="2511"></persName> writes to acknowledge his copy of the "Memoir"<ref xml:id="996"></ref>:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"A thousand thanks for it. I have read it with great delight. It seems to me to be ^written^ with extraordinary discretion &amp; charm. It must have been extremely difficult to compile, but I think you have triumphed over all difficulties &amp; produced a true &amp; worthy memorial of a noble gentleman."</p>
            </div>
            <p>This is flatterous &amp; excessive, but I think it does not wholly miss the mark. The "Memoir" is ragged, ill&#8211;proportioned, &amp; ill&#8211;expressed, but it so far succeeds that it leaves a definite impression on the reader's mind, &amp; that impression is mainly just. One who had never known the Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName>, would form a worthy estimate of him from reading this sketch.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>April 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, 1920.</p>
            <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Randle,</p>
            <p>I don't like exchanges, which are difficult to reconcile with any coherent theory of Divine vocation, &amp; are almost invariably resented by the parishioners; but I shall not refuse to consent to your seeking an exchange, because it is clear to me that there are strong reasons why a change of parish is advisable in your case. It will not be easy for me to answer the inquiries about you, which in due course I may expect to receive. It is hardly possible for me to say with truth the favourable things which are commonly said about a parish clergyman when he leaved his parish, but I will say the truth as kindly as I can. Meanwhile I will hope that you may be brought into a situation which will develope your better qualities, &amp; enable you to fulfil the solemn task of a parish clergyman with acceptance.</p>
            <p>Believe me,</p>
            <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford.</p>
            <p>The Rev. C. W. Randle.</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>