<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[104]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>The morning was dark and damp: the day developed badly: and closed in wind &amp; rain. Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> accompanied me on my confirmation journey. Leaving the Palace at 9.30 a.m. we motored to Bucknell, where I confirmed 29 candidates. Then we went on to Lydham, where we lunched with M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Sykes, and afterwards I dedicated a "Victory Cross" set up by the Sykes family in the Churchyard. Then we motored to Clunbury, and here I confirmed 36 candidates. We had tea with the Vicar, Rev<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> A. D. Beavan<persName xml:id="5166"></persName>, and then returned to the Palace, which we reached about 7.15 p.m.</p>
            <p>I received an affectionate letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> addressed from Honolulu on February 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. I gather that the latest letter from me was dated Nov: 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and had been received at Balboa, which he left on January 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. There must [be] a considerable accumulation of my letters somewhere, for I have written regularly every fortnight.</p>
            <p>The Bishop of Bath and Wells<persName xml:id="173"></persName> has "deprived" M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Wynter<persName xml:id="5167"></persName> for persisting in the use of "Benediction" after having been forbidden by his diocesan. It will be interesting to see what will be the next step<hi rend="italic">. The English Church Union<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> has espoused the rebellious pardon's cause: but the President, Lord Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>, has made public his dissent from this course. It is difficult to see any possible arrangement, for the objection is taken to the consistory court as "Erastian". The entire legal system of the National Church is repudiated by these men in the name of "Catholick" principles. How can their demand be conceded? It is a claim to sheer anarchy.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>