<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>A Congregationalist Minister, Rev. W. Lawson Forster<persName xml:id="5172"></persName>, desires to be ordained in the Church of England. His uncle, an incumbent in the diocese of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Edmondsbury &amp; Ipswich, wrote to commend him to me, and now he writes himself. He appears to hold an important position in his denomination, viz: that of minister of Chelsea Congregational Church: and he has hereditary links with Congregationalism. His uncle tells me that both the man himself and his wife have private means. This will certainly facilitate a favourable decision on my part: but, of course, it does not affect the main question. I told him to come &amp; see me on Wednesday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April.</p>
            <p>I took Goad<persName xml:id="5170"></persName> for a walk by the river for an hour and 20 minutes. We talked hard, and were the better for it. He returned to town by the midday train. After lunch I motored to Shobdon, and there confirmed 41 candidates in the curious parish church, which resembles the Pavilion at Brighton. However its acoustics are excellent. On the whole the service pleased me. <hi rend="bold underline">On returning to the Palace, I wrote to Prebendary Machen<persName xml:id="4807"></persName> asking him to become Rural Dean of Condover in succession to Auden</hi><persName xml:id="4500"></persName>. Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>writes to suggest the organisation of a counter&#8211;blast to the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Conference in the shape of a public meeting of moderate and Liberal Churchmen. I replied at once in the hope of nipping such folly in the bud. Fawkes is a child in ecclesiastical politics, and takes the falsest measure of forces and tendencies of any man of my acquaintance. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>March 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920.</p>
            <p>My dear Fawkes,</p>
            <p>I am quite clearly of the opinion that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be a grave mistake to emulate the tactics of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks in organising meetings to impress the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. Let them proceed with a policy of arrogant sectionalism. The more vehement &amp; violent they are the better from the point of view of all who wish well to the Church of England, for the more apparent their disloyalty becomes, the more chance there is that they will be disowned by English Churchmen who are sincerely such.</p>
            <p>It is, to my thinking, certain that any counter&#8211;blast w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be relatively too insignificant to be effective: &amp; might be extremely mischievous as giving a wholly false impression. In any case I do not think a Bishop c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> fitly take part in the proceedings. His office, if nothing else, suggests a wider r&#x00F4;le than that of a partisan. He c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not decently tie his hands by declarations in advance of the discussions at Lambeth. <hi rend="bold underline">I am amazed at the folly of B</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">p</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of Salisbury<persName xml:id="178"></persName> in taking part as preacher in the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Conference, and I cannot understand how the B</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">p</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of London's<persName xml:id="166"></persName> "welcome" to that Conference can be sincere</hi>.</p>
            <p>The clergy here generally report that their parishioners sign the roll&#8211;papers very willingly. Everything turns on the parson. If he is at the pains of explaining the situation to the people, they see the importance of being registered as Churchpeople. The difficulty will be in the towns.</p>
            <p>Yours aff<hi rend="superscript underline">nly</hi></p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>