<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Brilliant sun after the rain. I went to the Cathedral &amp; received the Holy Communion. The opening words of the Epistle &#8211; "Be ye therefore followers of God, as dear children; &amp; walk in love, as Christ also hath loved us &amp; hath given himself for us" &#8211; struck me as well&#8211;suited for my use in addressing confirmation candidates; &amp; when I got back to the Palace I fitted them on to my notes for the day.</p>
            <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dilwyn</hi>, where I confirmed 35 candidates, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Old Radnor</hi> where I confirmed 7. In the interval we lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Beeby very pleasantly.</p>
            <p>Old Radnor Church is nobly placed at the top of a considerable hill nearly 900 feet above sea&#8211;level. It is a fine structure of the late XV<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and early XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries, &amp; contains some features of unusual interest. (1) The noble screen which runs right across the church carrying its rood loft intact. (2) the carved organ&#8211;case of the pre&#8211;Reformation time. (3) the fine open carved roofs. (4) the curious ancient font reputed to be a Druidic altar adapted to Christian uses. (5) the stone seat set in an alcove in the western, where, it is surmised, the official who had charge of the excommunicated had his place. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lloyd, the parson's wife, gave me a small tractate on the church which she had compiled. As we entered the church there was a sudden blizzard of wind &amp; snow: when we came out the sun was shining, and our journey home was pleasant enough. The evening lights showed the fair country very fairly.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"The sacraments are not to be compared to a legal conveyance where a technical error, of which we are not aware, will invalidate the deed. They are spiritual instruments &amp; <hi rend="underline">the conditions of their validity are not technical or material, but spiritual and moral.</hi>"</p>
            <p>"If S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Iranaeus' principle is sound that 'where the Spirit of God is, there is the Church of all grace', <hi rend="underline">we cannot deny the existence of 'all grace' in those churches in which we recognise the Spirit of God</hi>".</p>
            <p>"The verdict of experience leads us to the conclusion that at different periods of history God has used various forms of ministry and Church Government for the good of the Church, &amp; that all three chief types, episcopal, presbyterian, and congregational, have been valid for some purposes &amp; invalid for others. What we may learn from the experience of the past is that for the true welfare of the Church what is needed today is not to choose one type to the exclusion of others, but to combine what is good &amp; useful in them all."</p>
            </div>
            <p>These are extracts from 'a charge delivered by the R<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Rev. H. Whitehead<persName xml:id="5157"></persName> Bishop of Madras at his 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> visitation on January 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1920. They mark a great change of attitude on the part of a man bred in the "straitest sect" of High Churchmen. I remember him as the close friend of Henry Wakemen<persName xml:id="5158"></persName>, himself one of the narrowest High Churchmen I have fortuned to know.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>March 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. 1920</p>
            <p>My dear Bishop,</p>
            <p>I must thank you heartily for sending me your charge which I have read with deep interest &amp; large agreement. It is strong, courageous &amp; constructive.</p>
            <p>It is a very notable thing that in all directions experience is leading English clergymen into new &amp; more generous thoughts of non&#8211;episcopal Christianity.</p>
            <p>I recall as I write what was said to me by the late Bishop Dowden<persName xml:id="2154"></persName> of Edinburgh, and the late Bishop Doane<persName xml:id="2913"></persName> of Albany U.S.A., with both of whom I have the privilege of some conversation shortly before they died. They both started in the Episcopate with the unbending Tractarian attitude established in their minds, &amp; life had taught them to lay it aside as intolerably inconsistent with its teachings. Bishop Jayne<persName xml:id="1727"></persName>, lately of Chester, might be added to their number: &amp; I think I shall do you no injustice if I add also your name to the list. From Scotland, America, England &amp; India the witness is identical. </p>
            <p>I look forward to meeting you in the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> at Lambeth, &amp;, perhaps, we may find ourselves co&#8211;operating in an effort to move forward on the lines of humble acknowledgment of God's Providence in History.</p>
            <p>In England within the last year there have been many conferences of Anglicans &amp; non&#8211;Anglicans, &amp; many important resolutions <hi rend="bold">[81]</hi> have been adopted. There are, however, evidences of a vigourous movement of re&#8211;action to which the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic Conference" in London will give expression.</p>
            <p>I am sometimes inclined to think that a disruption of the English Church, in which the Romanizing section of the "High Church" party would secede to Rome, <hi rend="underline">may be</hi> an indispensable condition of effective action in the interest of re&#8211;union.</p>
            <p>Believe me, sincerely yours,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford.</p>
            <p>The Right Rev. the Lord Bishop of Madras.</p>
            </div>
            <p>I wrote to the Master of the Temple<persName xml:id="3587"></persName> promising to preach for him on the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July. My list of preaching pledges ought now to be complete:&#8211;</p>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">1.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">March 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="left">Bradford. Parish Church (2)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">2.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">" 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="left">Eignbrook Congregational Mission</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">3.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">April 4.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">Hereford. The Cathedral.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">4.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">June 6.</cell>
                  <cell rend="List_Paragraph">Cambridge. The University.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">5.</cell>
                  <cell rend="List_Paragraph">July 11.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">Westminster Abbey</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">6.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">" 18.</cell>
                  <cell rend="List_Paragraph">S. Paul's Cathedral</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell rend="left">7.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">" 25.</cell>
                  <cell rend="left">The Temple</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>How these discourses are to be prepared it is not quite easy to see, nor yet what I can preach about most wisely. But clearly the subject of Reunion must take a prominent place in them. In view of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> that is inevitable.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>