<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I caught the 9.45 a.m. from Paddington, &amp; reached Hereford at 2.17 p.m. Among the letters awaiting me was an interesting one form George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, with an account of the Chinese Wall. I wrote a number of letters including one to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Lawson Forster</hi><persName xml:id="5172"></persName>. The Congregationalist Minister, who has made up his mind to be Ordained next Advent. I hope it will turn out well. The "Guardian" has a friendly review of the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> <ref xml:id="996">"Memoir"</ref>. I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Graham</hi><persName xml:id="633"></persName> thanking me for his copy of the "Memoir", which (as he is now quite blind) had been read to him. He seems to be pleased with it.</p>
            <p>The "Modern Churchmen" has an article on Arthur Hugh Clough<persName xml:id="5203"></persName>, which contains this fine little poem:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="verse">
            <p>It fortifies my soul to know</p>
            <p>That, though I perish, Truth is so:</p>
            <p>That, howso'er I stray or range,</p>
            <p>What'er I do, Thou dost not change.</p>
            <p>I steadier step when I recall</p>
            <p>That, if I slip, Thou dost not fall</p>
            </div>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>"It is the approach of a 'new order' that wakes religion &amp; unites sects. Cataracts are normal &amp; necessary to the stream of progress. We feel things cannot possibly go on as now" – Tyrrell<persName xml:id="1084"></persName></p>
            </div>
            <p>But the 'religion' that is waked is a new religion, &amp; the sects of the old, if united at all, are only united against it. The History of Christianity is proof of this.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[194]</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>May 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, 1920</p>
            <p>My dear Lord Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>,</p>
            <p>I enclose Abp. S&#x00F6;derblom's<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> letter, &amp; a copy of my reply. The occasion appears to be interesting &amp; may possibly come to have an exceptional importance.</p>
            <p>I am sorry to hear that an effort is likely to be made to get a doctrinal pronouncement out of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. The policy of such pronouncements is utterly mistaken: &amp; their substance can hardly be worth anything. For they can only escape being offensive by being ambiguous: &amp; then their very ambiguity becomes a fresh offence. Nor do I feel personally free to acquiesce in any course which w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> impinge, or might fairly be thought to impinge, on my personal honour. I don't know what provision is made in the constitution of the Lambeth Conference for recording the protest of a minority: but I think it highly probable that I should desire to make full use of it.</p>
            <p>Believe me,</p>
            <p>Always your Grace's </p>
            <p>Sincere &amp; dutiful</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            <p>The Archbishop of Canterbury.</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>