<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p>I do not believe in any plans for Christian unity <hi rend="underline">without first being sure of the general consent of the practising members of each communion concerned</hi>. Were any such plan to be pressed before each Christian communion concerned is ready for it, the inevitable effect would be to injure seriously what unity exists in each communion in a premature attempt to promote unity between various Christian communions: <hi rend="underline">unity like charity begins at home.</hi></p>
            <p>Bishop of St. David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName>. A.D. 1919</p>
            </div>
            <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" publishes a correspondence between Lord Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName> as President of E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName>, and the Abp. of York<persName xml:id="130"></persName> in reference to Jowett's<persName xml:id="1725"></persName> preaching in Durham Cathedral. It provides an interesting commentary on the view that "the general consent of the practising members' of the C. of E. must be secured before "any plans for Christian unity " can wisely be projected. <hi rend="underline">The Anglo&#8211;Catholicks claim a permanent veto on all approaches to non&#8211;episcopalian Churches, and also complete liberty of approach to the unreformed Church of East &amp; West. Thus the plea for delay based on a charitable consideration for "weaker brethren" can but serve the cause of the bigotted opponents of the Reformation. In point of fact the plea is urged with a cynical insincerity by the latter, and acquiesced in with a fatuous weakness by their antagonists</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
            <p>The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came to lunch at 12.30 noon and then we motored to Michaelchurch in order to inspect the parish church, which had been reported as needing large expenditures. Edmund Parker<persName xml:id="5002"></persName> came with us. The weather was brilliantly fine, so that we were able to see the country to great advantage: and the country in that part of my diocese is eminently worth seeing. The car did its duty to admiration, surmounting the rather formidable hill with success. The church is interesting for two things – a fine timbered roof, and a large fresco on the north wall of the nave representing <hi rend="underline">either</hi> Christ in S. Joseph's carpenter's shop, <hi rend="underline">or</hi> Jubal Cain surrounded by musical instruments. We were met by Powell<persName xml:id="5143"></persName> the Rural Dean, and by Gray, the Vicar. The state of the church hardly justified the grave reports of its condition: &amp; certainly it is barely possible to carry out any work in the present state of the Labour market. We returned to Hereford by way of Abbey Dore, stopping to look at that incomparable church. We were back at the Palace in good time for tea. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Crees<persName xml:id="5144"></persName>, the new Headmaster of the Cathedral school, called on me with reference to the Confirmation at the school. He says that Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName> is not much use as a schoolmaster: his heart is elsewhere. Evidently the new Broom intends to sweep very clean indeed! Captain Christmas called, and undertook to send out my letters to the Churchwardens from the Finance Board's office.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>