<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Some courageous parson writes to me at length expounding his admirable fitness for preferment, &amp; begging me to persuade the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName> to prefer him without delay to an important London benefice which is vacant. I replied thus:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>Dear Sir,</p>
            <p>I am obliged to you for your letter of the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> inst. in which you are good enough to assume that I possess influence in Crown appointments, &amp; request me to exert that influence in your own behalf.</p>
            <p>I have no reason for thinking that your assumption is well&#8211;founded; and, even if it were, I make it a rule never to intrude my advice where it is not solicited.</p>
            <p>Believe me,</p>
            <p>Yours v. truly,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford.</p>
            </div>
            <p>I wrote to Warner<persName xml:id="4698"></persName>, offering him the Prebendal stall vacated by the death of Prebendary Ayscough<persName xml:id="5182"></persName>.</p>
            <p>Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> lunched here. His recalcitrant farmer, Yorath, who has just been made a J.P., seems to have become reconciled.</p>
            <p>I walked with Mary<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> along the river bank. The weather was bright &amp; warm, so that everything looked its best. Moved and encouraged by the sun, the birds, notably the thrushes, have been very tuneful today.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>