<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>I left Cardiff by the 9.28 a.m. train and reached Hereford at 11.19 a.m. On the way I read the jubilant account in the "Times" of Asquith's<persName xml:id="215"></persName> return for Paisley. It is certainly a heavy personal blow for the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName>.<note xml:id="520" n="1"></note></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">At 3 p.m. I instituted M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Stamer<persName xml:id="5154"></persName> to the parish of Berington. At 4 p.m. the wretched B.<persName xml:id="4923"></persName> from Hatfield came to see me. He repeated the grotesque nonsense which he wrote to the Abp.<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, but I w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not allow it, &amp; confronted him relentlessly with the alternative, either immediate resignation, or prosecution. He elected to resign. James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> had the document ready, with the requisite witnesses: and it was forthwith signed. I reserved to myself the fixing of the date when the resignation sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> take effect. This is all very distressing.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">I decided that the resignation should take effect on March 31</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic">, and that B. sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not be allowed to officiate again: &amp; I wrote to him stating my decision. Also, I wrote to the Abp. of Canterbury and to the Lord Chancellor<persName xml:id="2508"></persName>, reporting what had happened. It seemed to me advisable, in view of the scandal which had been caused, to send the announcement of B.'s resignation to the local newspapers.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">I had a letter from Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> which troubled me. His heart is evidently fixed on the stage. His little triumphs at Oxford have again shaken him off his balance. In view of such continuing proofs of instability, can I be right in encouraging him to think of taking Holy Orders? I begin to suspect that my duty lies in the opposite direction</hi>. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>February 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920</p>
            <p>Dear Sir<persName xml:id="5155"></persName>,</p>
            <p>You ask me two questions which admit of short answer.</p>
            <p>1. <hi rend="underline">What is the Church going to do about the Amritsar massacres</hi>?</p>
            <p>The Church, by which presumably you mean the clergy, will, I hope, reserve judgment on the lamentable occurrences at Amritsar until the facts have been duly certified. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be extremely wrong for men, who are in a special degree committed to the defence of morality, to set an example of injustice by condemning accused officials on partial information.</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="underline">Where were the so&#8211;called servants of Christ whilst the massacred men, women, &amp; children of Amritsar were lying hour after hour in agonising pain etc.</hi>?</p>
            <p>I have no direct knowledge of the situation, but I conjecture that the Missionaries &amp; their converts, whom presumably you refer to, were not likely to be taking part in an illegal assembly: &amp;, until I know what was the extent of their knowledge &amp; opportunity, I am obviously not in a position to pass judgment on their behaviour. Their known record prohibits the suggestion that they w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be lacking in humanity, or (so far as the English missionaries are concerned) in courage.</p>
            <p>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            <p>Roy Horniman Esq </p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>