<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>What can I say to these Methodists which shall be wise, sympathetic, and really serviceable to Religion? The sermon that I have prepared is dull, unflattering, &amp; innocuous, calculated rather to damp their ardour than to conciliate their vanity. It will disappoint them, but it will do no harm. The speech tonight is more difficult. I noted in Hammond's book this doggerel which was sung by the hunger&#8211;bitten artisans in Lancashire in the years following Waterloo:&#8211;</p>
            <div type="verse">
            <p>The Bishops, Vicars, Curates,</p>
            <p>Parliament and Kings</p>
            <p>Not only evils are</p>
            <p>But worthless things.</p>
            </div>
            <p>This will serve as a humourous illustration of the temper which War is apt to develop in the masses. I shall set out the reasons why I am glad publicly to associate myself with the work of the <hi rend="bold underline">Eastbrook</hi> Mission<placeName xml:id="98"></placeName> type. And, these I shall group as (1) civic, and (2) religious. This arrangement will give me sufficient "rope". Some reference to "reunion" will be expected from me, but I shall say little on that subject. My presence in such an assembly is sufficient disclosure of my views.</p>
            <p>I walked into the city, and had my hair cut at a little shop hard by the Cathedral. There was a Freemason among the customers, who claimed fellowship with me. There is certainly a large measure of reality in that Brotherhood. It seems to command from its members a larger degree of loyalty than the Christian Church secures from Christians.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <p>The floor of the Great Hall of the Eastbrook Mission was well&#8211;filled at noon when I preached to the Methodists. There were something more than 1000 persons present according to my counting: I was told that there were more than 1200. Afterwards I lunched with some of the ministers at the Midland Hotel. <hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Muir<persName xml:id="4997"></persName> gave some rather startling facts as to the spiritist or spiritualist cult in Bradford</hi>. Apparently Sir Oliver Lodge<persName xml:id="614"></persName> has a secretary in Bradford named Hill, with whom he communicates by spiritualistic means. This man read the proofs of "Raymond", and told Muir that in his judgement much of it should not have been published as being untrue. There was a returned Methodist Chaplain, just back from Germany, named James. He said that his relations with Anglican chaplains varied according to the ecclesiastical colour of the individuals. After an early dinner I went to Eastbrook again for the evening meeting. The great hall was filled to its utmost capacity, &amp; there was much fervour of the typical Methodist variety. I did not think the speaking was of a high order: my own speech was a dismal failure, but the coughing (which was incessant) disconcerted me. <hi rend="bold underline">The Vicar of Bradford<persName xml:id="5165"></persName> &amp; his wife, responding to my earnest advice, made their appearance, &amp; were welcomed with much enthusiasm</hi>. The minister announced that he had asked for &#x00A3;1700 to be collected at the Festival, &amp; had now received &#x00A3;2100. So <hi rend="bold underline">the one recognised test of spiritual success – financial support </hi>– was not witholden, and, on the announcement of the figures, the doxology was sung with remarkable fervour. I talked with the Vicar until midnight, &amp; so to bed.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>