<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[141]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>I left the Palace at 8.45 a.m., &amp; motored by way of Ludlow &amp; Craven Arms to Diddlebury. There was much land under water about Leominster: at two places the road was submerged, &amp; the car had to make its way through water rising to the axles. I read the lessons &amp; preached in the parish church, my pastoral staff being carried by a choirman. The Church of S. Peter is an ancient edifice of very great interest, villainously restored &amp; filled with intolerable glass. The north wall of the nave is apparently Anglo&#8211;Saxon work of the "herring&#8211;bone" type. After service I baptized the infant daughter of Captain Ludlow the churchwarden. Then I lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> L. Swinnerton Dyer<persName xml:id="5120"></persName>. At 3 p.m. I went to the Chapel, concerning which so much friction has been caused. Evensong was sung, and an Anthem sung very effectively. I preached again, and then had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dyer. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Martin<persName xml:id="5104"></persName> still remains hostile, but I think there is some chance of her coming to a better mind if she be left alone. I think Mason<persName xml:id="5106"></persName>, the Vicar, though probably more well&#8211;intentioned than tactful, has behaved fairly, in rather a trying situation. On the return journey we were delayed at Ludlow by "dirt in the petrol", as William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> diagnosis ran. I was back in the Palace before 7 p.m. The weather was dull with some transient intervals of sunshine in the middle of the day, and some slight essays at rain as the day drew to a close.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>