<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>At breakfast there was rather an interesting discussion about the decorations which have been so freely distributed. The number has now become embarrassingly great; &amp; the selection of individuals presents an almost insoluble problem. A ludicrous, probably apocryphal story was related of a lengthy list for the Military Medal which, when investigated, turned out to be a list of men ordered to be vaccinated!</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">I came away from the Castle pleased with the recollection of a very agreeable visit, &amp; withal overwhelmed with the pathetic sense of the insecurity of all that Windsor stands for. The King's<persName xml:id="2727" display="no"></persName> conception of his r&#x00F4;le as a constitutional Sovereign is so modest that it is difficult to imagine the situation in which he w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">"stand up" to a popular movement. </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">He was very emphatic in asserting his opinion that the King of Denmark had made a mistake in his recent action. He had just written as much to his brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, the King of Norway.</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi> <hi rend="italic">The mere financing of Windsor is becoming a grave difficulty. The Queen<persName xml:id="2728" display="no"></persName> spoke very frankly about the enormously increased expenditure on wages. "Of course, like everybody else, we can't keep things up: we have reduced the establishment in order to pay the higher rates." Will the monarchy in England just die of financial inanition?</hi></p>
            <p>The weather was so wet &amp; gloomy that I abandoned my projected visit to the photographer, &amp; went to the hairdresser instead. Then I caught the 4.20 p.m. train at Victoria, <hi rend="bold underline">and arrived at Birchington</hi> at 7 p.m. <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> was on the platform to meet me. I found Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> cheerful but very white and frail.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>