<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[125]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>[symbol]</p>
            <p>The weather was dull and threatening, but <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were not deterred from carrying out our engagement to visit Hartlebury. We left Hereford at 10.30 a.m., &amp; motored as far as Leominster, where a tyre burst. After procuring a new tyre we continued our journey, and arrived at the castle about 1.30 p.m. Ernest's<persName xml:id="636"></persName> brother, the Master<persName xml:id="4827"></persName> of Corpus, was there as well as his sister. The garden and grounds were looking very delightful. After tea, we returned to Hereford, where we arrived about 6.30 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">Almost at the same time there came the Rev. W. Lawson Forster<persName xml:id="5172"></persName>, the Congregational Minister, who seeks ordination in the Church of England.</hi></p>
            <p>He is in his 45<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year, a tall man, fairly stout &amp; stooping: he has the conciliating manner &amp; fluent speech of the Dissenting pastor, to whom the approbation of his people is as the breath of life: nevertheless he expressed himself in a reasonable way, &amp; did not "cant" in the customary manner. <hi rend="bold underline">It was evidently a blow to him that he could not be ordained straight away, and thereupon left free to live where he would. I explained to him that a bishop's jurisdiction was necessarily limited to his own diocese, and that he would have to reside here at least two years after Ordination. </hi>This dismayed but did not wholly daunt him. He disclaimed the suggestion that his Ordination in the Church of England implied the belief that his present Ordination was "invalid", though I fear that is the natural interpretation: &amp; professed to be influenced by a desire to fulfil his ministry in a system of greater "authority" than the Congregational.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi> [symbol]</p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>April 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920</p>
            <p>My dear Sir<persName xml:id="5179"></persName>,</p>
            <p>I beg to return your nephew's letter.</p>
            <p>He came here last night, and I had some talk with him. You will no doubt hear from him in due course that <hi rend="bold underline">I shall be prepared to accept him for Ordination next Advent on conditions which I explained &amp; which are indispensable.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold underline">Among these was included satisfactory proof of baptism. If such could not be forthcoming I should have to required conditional baptism, as no loophole of dubiety with respect to that matter could rightly be left.</hi></p>
            <p>Believe me,</p>
            <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford</p>
            <p>The Rev. W. D. Lawson</p>
            </div>
            </body></text></TEI>