<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>A most glorious morning. After breakfast <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked, (like Nebuchadnezzars in Babylon) exulting in the beauty of the garden. Hereford is seen to perfection on a bright spring day, before the trees are opaque with leaves, &amp; the air sultry with the heat. This is a day of beauty, very rememberable.</p>
            <p>I left the Palace at 9 a.m., &amp; motored to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stottesdon</hi>, 4 1/2 miles south of Burwarton. The whole route was a feast of natural beauty. I confirmed 29 persons at Mattins, and, after lunching at the Vicarage, dedicated a memorial window at a special service in the afternoon. The parish church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary is a fine building with several features of unusual interest – an elaborately carved late&#8211;Norman font, capitals curiously under&#8211;cut, and a west door with very curious carving obscured by the tower. Some medieval glass collected from the east window has been brought together &amp; placed in the small window near the font. There is a Jacobean pulpit, and rather fine sedilia, nearly buried by the raising of the chancel floor at a violent restoration. These are deeply scored, the result (as is alleged) of sharpening arrows on the stone. The Vicar of Stottesdon is the <hi rend="underline">Rev. W. Murcott</hi>, who has held office since 1894. He was ordained in 1884, and is a well&#8211;preserved man rather more than 60 years of age. The living must now be worth nearly &#x00A3;600. Lord Barnard<persName xml:id="5197"></persName> is the patron. After tea at the Vicarage I returned to Hereford arriving about 6.30 p.m. The evening lights were magnificent. Certainly a rural bishop has alleviations and compensations to be set in the scale against his obscure &amp; futile activity.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>