<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <p>Prof. Bacon<persName xml:id="3057"></persName> went off after breakfast, and the car which carried him to the station returned to take me. <hi rend="bold underline">Hardly had I settled myelf in the carriage &amp; opened the "Times", before my eye fell on the announcement of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Raleigh's</hi><persName xml:id="14"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> death. He has been moribund for many months past, so that his actual departure is what men call "a happy release". There is an appreciative notice in the "Times" but his real excellence was unsuspected. </hi>He was certainly one of the best Christians I have ever fortuned to meet. My friendship with him began with my election at All Souls in 1884, and lasted up to the end. I wrote to Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName> from the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> saying that I hoped to attend the funeral.</p>
            <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert Coleridge</hi><persName xml:id="5145"></persName> introduced himself to me in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. His wife appears to be some relation of mine. I dined with Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers<persName xml:id="2708"></persName>. They had got two other Scots to meet me – Lord Justice Clerk<persName xml:id="5146"></persName> (?) and Sir William McLaughlin (?). We had a brisk conversation on politics. I encountered Lord Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName> in the Club: he says that he thinks Lord Grey's letter is admirable, but that it is too favourable to the Republican leaders, who are actuated by a bitter personal hatred of Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName><note xml:id="525" n="1"></note>. But Wilson provokes fierce antipathy. He did so at Princeton, where the University was divided into implacable factions.</p>
            <p>Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> over the telephone pledged me to dine on Friday.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>