<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[159] </hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920. </hi></p>
            <div type="quote">
            <p><hi rend="italic">'Things are what they are, and the consequences of them will be what they will be: why, then, should we desire to be deceived?' To take in and to digest such a sentence as that, is an education in moral and intellectual veracity.'</hi></p>
            <p>Matthew Arnold.</p>
            </div>
            <p>I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; then cleared off a whole mass of tiresome letters. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burrell came to see me about Humber, &amp; then the Vicar of Dyndor called to ask counsel about some tiresome parishioners who have taken to writing libellous post&#8211;cards. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Waterfield<persName xml:id="5129"></persName> &amp; a party came in to lunch. Then I visited the Zenana Missionary Exhibition in the Shire Hall<hi rend="bold underline">. As I came out I saw a Trade Union orator addressing a crowd, &amp; stopped to listen. He was exalting the virtues of organisation. Really, Catholicism has not so much expired as changed its name. These perfervid Trade&#8211;Unionists display the spirit &amp; employ the arguments of Jesuits!</hi> Colonel<persName xml:id="3512"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin<persName xml:id="3813"></persName> arrived by the afternoon train. Both of them expressed great disgust at Jowett's<persName xml:id="1725"></persName> preaching in the Cathedral at Durham. The vulgarity of the whole incident ̶  the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> &amp; the preacher being photographed together - stirred them most. Deep in the hearts of the English gentry is the repugnance, half dislike, half contempt, with which they regard Dissenters, those crude &amp; violent enthusiasts, whose crazy notions &amp; fierce self&#8211;assertion wrecked the Church &amp; Monarchy in the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, and will repeat the infamy in modern fashion in the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>! The past enchains us all.</p>
            </body></text></TEI>