<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Clark,</p>
            <p>I have read your letter with much interest and sympathy. The present position is moving quickly (if I may use that phrase) to a complete break&#8211;down. The reason is sufficiently apparent. Our whole ecclesiastical system assumes a situation, social, economic, political, religious, which is vanishing, &amp; has largely vanished. What the way of escape will be is not yet apparent: but passi graviora.<note xml:id="509" n="1"></note> There will be a way out, probably in the unlikeliest direction. Meanwhile there is nothing for us but to be sternly loyal to personal duty, &amp;, for the rest, to "live from hand to mouth". </p>
            <p>The spiritual condition of Church Stretton has caused, &amp; does cause, me much anxiety. But at present I can do nothing. </p>
            <p>Yours sincerely, </p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford </p>
            <p>M. B. Clark Esq. </p>
            </div>
            <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
            <div type="letter">
            <p>May 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920.</p>
            <p>Dear M. Sandars<persName xml:id="5258"></persName>, </p>
            <p>I am greatly obliged to you for your letter, &amp; for the observations which you are good enough to make on the "memoir"<ref xml:id="996"></ref> which I edited. </p>
            <p>If an opportunity should come to me of correcting one or two matters, which are either obscure or misleading or both, I shall certainly introduce something to mitigate the error which you have pointed out. </p>
            <p>Sir Robert Morant<persName xml:id="2180"></persName>, for whom, though I had but a slight acquaintance with him, I had a very warm regard, sent me a memorandum on Anson's<persName xml:id="228"></persName> career as Parliamentary Secretary. It gave me the impression – perhaps a mistaken one – that there had been some lack of cordiality, &amp; I got the same impression from Anson's Journal, though the references to Morant were uniformly honourable. Accordingly, I said as little as I could, &amp; have perhaps given the impression that I did not realise the great work which Morant was doing.</p>
            <p>I was much handicapped by lack of material, for Anson was not a sufficiently considerable figure to merit a large biography, &amp; he left little behind him. The <hi rend="underline">Journal</hi> was private, &amp; it was hard to determine how much one could properly publish. You will understand my difficulty. Again thanking you.</p>
            <p>I am, v. faithfully yours.</p>
            <p>H. H. Hereford </p>
            <p>The R. Hon: J. S. Sandars C.V.O. </p>
            </div>
            <p>[Pp. 179 and 180 missing]</p>
            </body></text></TEI>