<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; instituted Poole to his honorary canonry in the face of the assembled school. Then I licensed three curates in the chapel at the Castle. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> joined me, &amp; we lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> at the Club. Next, I presided at a meeting of the Finance Board. When this was over, I motored to Houghton–le–Spring, accompanied by Clayton &amp; Wilson. We had tea with the Rector, and then continued our journey to Sunderland. We went to the Rectory, where I received a deputation – the two churchwardens &amp; a local surveyor(!) – on the subject of the parish church, which is affected by coal–workings. I advised a fresh survey by Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName>. From the Rectory, we went on to All Saints Church, where I "admitted" the new parson, Harry Saxton.<persName xml:id="5434"></persName> There was a considerable congregation, &amp; several clergy. We motored back to Auckland, dropping Wilson in Durham on our way. We reached the Castle at 9.15 p.m. Archdeacon &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Charles arrived during the afternoon. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Emmet's</hi> death in New York is reported in the papers. This is certainly a loss to the "liberal" section of the Church of England. I cannot say that I knew him well, nor that he greatly impressed me. But I thought him both honest and intelligent.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>