<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[59]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in Christ Church at 8 a.m. There were 90 communicants.</p>
         <p>At 10.30 a.m. there was a service in the Parish Church to which the Royal Institute of Public Health, which has been holding a Congress in Scarborough last week, came in state. There were many mayors &amp; medical pundits in their robes: &amp; the procession was witnessed by great throngs of the holiday&#8211;makers. The parish church, which is said to seat 2000 people on the floor, was crowded. <hi rend="bold underline">I preached the sermon which I had prepared, and afterwards gave the M.S. to Sir W. Smith.</hi></p>
         <p>In the afternoon the Vicar took me for a walk round the beach, &amp; later I preached in Christ Church to a considerable congregation almost wholly composed of women! <hi rend="italic">An interesting naval man came to supper. A propos my insistance on the importance of Housing in my sermon this morning, he told me the following. The 'Lusitania' on her trial trip developed a speed far in excess of that which she attained in crossing the Atlantic. Her owners complained, &amp; the builders commissioned their leading expert to accompany the vessel on her next trip, &amp; to investigate the cause of her failure to justify her promise. His report was summed up in the counsel, '</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Reconstruct the stokers' quarters.</hi> <hi rend="italic">' This was done, and the 'Lusitania' henceforth attained easily the speed which had been guaranteed.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>