<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> wrote to announce his safe arrival in Hereford. <hi rend="bold underline">The Editor of the Morning Post wrote to express his willingness to allow the Durham&#8211;Zanzibar correspondence to be republished, but stating that he had no means for undertaking their re&#8211;publication himself. Shall I make them the text of a pamphlet, or even a small book</hi> <hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p>Miles &amp; I visited the little parish church of S. Andrew, which the Vicar showed to us. It contains a very beautiful rood&#8211;screen of the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, and a remarkably fine monument to Sir Edward Coke, the son of the famous Lord Chief Justice, and his wife &amp; infant daughter. The lady is recumbent with the babe in her arms, the husband is standing in a recess above her. The figures are the work of the famous sculptor Nicholas Stone. An extremely quaint inscription recording the death of a lady by "an apoplectick dart" is on a tombstone in front of the Communion rail. Externally the Church has a modest, but not an undignified aspect. The chancel is roofed with that which, as a protection from nesting birds, is covered with wire. The detached round tower is built of flint, and carries the five bells. In the Vicarage I was shown the registers which date from 1539, &amp; have been printed, and the plate which includes a large flagon of 1704. There was a Vicar of Bramfield as early as 1189: and a parish church is mentioned in Domesday. The cure was served by the monks of Blythborough Monastery.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Lady Thomspon took us out in the afternoon. WE paid two calls, ad on both occasions my acquaintance was claimed. In the one a Miss (or M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi>) Perry reminded me that, when I was Vicar of Barking, I hd preached for Canon Perry in S. Matthew's City Road: in the other, Sir Ronald Lane reminded me of his brother, the Dean of Rochester. I remember meeting him when I stayed at the Deanery for a preaching visit. IN the grounds of the housewas a little 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century church. The parish has been joined to the adjoining ne after the fashion which is now beginning everywhere to prevail. We otored to another church ^?^ Haleston, which made a fine show in the landscape, but was disappointing when seen at close quarters. Two Norman doorwards showed that the present structure which is in the normal perpendicular style had replaced an earlier fabric.</p>
         <p>The Vicar was good enough to send me a verbatim copy from Suckling's Suffold of the curious Epitaph in the Chance of Bramfield Church. It runs thus:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Between the remains of her brother Edward,</p>
         <p>And of her husband Arthur,</p>
         <p>Here lies the body of Bridgett Applewhaite,</p>
         <p>Once Bridgett Nelson.</p>
         <p>After the fatigues of a married life,</p>
         <p>Borne by her with incredible patience</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>For four years and three quarters, bating three weeks,</p>
         <p>And after the enjoyment of the glorious freedom</p>
         <p>Of an early and unblemisht widowhood,</p>
         <p>For four years and upwards,</p>
         <p>She resolved to run the risk of a second marriage bed,</p>
         <p>But Death forbad the banns:</p>
         <p>And having with an apoplectic dart,</p>
         <p>(That same instrument with which he had formerly</p>
         <p>Dispatch'd her mother,)</p>
         <p>Touch'd the most vital part of her brain,</p>
         <p>She must have fallen directly to the ground,</p>
         <p>(As one thunderstrook,)</p>
         <p>If she had not been catch'd and supported</p>
         <p>by her intended husband.</p>
         <p>Of which the invisible bruize,</p>
         <p> After a struggle of above sixty hours</p>
         <p> With that grand enemy to life</p>
         <p>(But the certain and merciful friend to helpless old age)</p>
         <p>In terrible convulsions, plaintive groans, or stupyfyng sleep,</p>
         <p>Without recovery of her speech or senses.</p>
         <p>She died on the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> day of September, in the year of our Lord 1737.</p>
         <p>And of her own age 44.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>