<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather was uncertain, like that of a typical April day. There was a thunder&#8211;storm in the course of the morning, and a sharp deluge during the afternoon. In the intervals there was bright sunshine, &amp; the day ended quite civilly. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> arrived from Hereford with the car about midday. After lunch we left Stowe House, and motored by way of Kenilworth &amp; Banbury to Cuddesdon, where we arrived about 7.15 p.m. On the way we stopped to look at the remains of the great castle of Kenilworth. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, who had seen them before, remained in the car, while William and I went round the castle with the guide, a most loquacious &amp; dogmatic example of his class. We had tea at Leamington.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Burge received us with his usual courteous benignity, &amp; his wife with her frank yet embarrassed kindness.</hi> Staying in the Palace are M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Illingworth, the widow of the well&#8211;known divine, and a young lady whose name escapes me.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The last time that I slept under this roof</hi> was on May 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1887, the night before my Ordination to the Priesthood. For my diaconate the preceding year, I had been lodged in the Theological College. Bishop Mackarness was then nearing his end, &amp; his physical weakness was distressingly apparent.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>