<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">"I think that your suggestion of 'Byron' is excellent, so, please carry on.</hi>" Thus the Vice–Chancellor of Cambridge approves my suggestion that I should choose the subject for my 'Rede Lecture' from the circumstance that a 100 years will have passed since Byron died in Greece. I have always felt that the choice of a text is the hardest part of sermon preparation!</p>
         <p>At 11.30 a.m. I celebrated the marriage of the Hon. Robert James &amp; Lady Serena Lumley<persName xml:id="4311"></persName> in the Chapel. The function developed into something almost approaching a "fashionable marriage". There was much suppressed feeling, but no untoward expression of it. Half the choir of Durham Cathedral came over with the Precentor. Parry–Evans, the bridegroom's brother–in–law, assisted, and I gave a short address. On the whole the business went through quite satisfactorily. By 12.45 p.m. the company had departed, and peace reigned once more in the Castle! After lunch I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; was woefully beaten. Then I had an interview with Miss Coleman about the Rescue Work.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Gladstone, then 73 years old, judged that 71 was too advanced an age for any man to be made Archbishop of Canterbury. He informed Bishop Browne of Winchester that his advanced age alone prevented his nomination as successor to Archbishop Tait. I have always thought Temple<persName xml:id="171"></persName> was too old for the Primacy</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>