<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit Tuesday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>When we weigh the merits of the medieval church and have remembered all her good deeds, we have to put into the other scale as a weighty counterpoise the incalculable harm done by a marriage law which was a maze of flighty fancies and misapplied logic.</p>
         <p>Pollock &amp; Maitland, vol. ii, p. 389.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote letters, played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; read rather aimlessly. That is the whole history of the day.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The resignation of Bonar Law, which was announced yesterday, forms the leading topic of the newspapers</hi> <hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">His Majesty's choice of his successor seems to be limited to the alternative, L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> or M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Baldwin<persName xml:id="4118"></persName>. The former has the stronger claim, but the latter is the better placed, for the days of Peer&#8211;premiers are over. It would be absurd to have the Prime Minister unable to cross swords in debate with any member of the Official opposition. We have evidently embarked on a period of such political instability that the record of public service counts for nothing, &amp; the prize of leadership will fall to the man who at the moment happens to be "in the public eye"! I have a real desire to see the helm of the State pass into the hands of an Englishman: and I wish to see an end of the Scottish r&#x00E9;gime in the Church of England. But there is small chance of it!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>