<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[222]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A volume of poems comes from Hugh Lyon. It was but yesterday that we were wondering what had become of him. He has a 'pretty pen', and a poetic temperament, but the mantle of Wordsworth has not fallen on him!</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a sermon for use tomorrow, and in preparing notes for the afternoon's function.</p>
         <p>After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went to Holmside where I dedicated a war&#8211;memorial which took the form of a tower equipped with a clock and bells. The Ritsons<persName xml:id="3822"></persName> were in force. One Colonel unveiled the tabled: another set the clock going: the old man unlocked the door. I pronounced the short dedication formula, and gave an address in the open air. There was a considerable congregation, but the function was marred by the noisy cheers from an adjacent football match! In this parish there is a population of &#x00A3;2500, and a mean little church, which seats less than 200.</p>
         <p>Fletcher send me two of my own letters to W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>, which had been found among his papers. He asks me to send him any of Ker's letters to me which I possess. I turned out the drawers which hold my general letters, but I found no more than two of his. There must be more, but where they are, or whether they have been preserved, I know not. Now that my friends are passing away I regret ever more intensely my carelessness in preserving &amp; arranging their letters.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>