<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Latest Decalogue</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Thou shalt have one God only</hi>; who</p>
         <p>Would be at the expense of two?</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">No graven images may be</hi></p>
         <p>Worshipped, except the currency:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Swear not at all</hi>; for, for thy curse</p>
         <p>Thine enemy is none the worse:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">At Church on Sunday</hi> to attend</p>
         <p>Will serve to keep the world thy friend:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Honour thy parents</hi>: that is, all</p>
         <p>From whom advancement may befall;</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Thou shalt not kill</hi>: but need'st not strive</p>
         <p>Officiously to keep alive:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Do not adultery commit</hi>:</p>
         <p>Advantage rarely comes of it:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Thou shalt not steal</hi>: an empty feat,</p>
         <p>When it's so lucrative to cheat:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Bear not false witness</hi>: let the lie</p>
         <p>Have time on its own wings to fly:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Thou shalt not covet</hi>, but tradition</p>
         <p>Approves all forms of competition.		</p>
         <p>A. H. Clough. 	 	 </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p>Four out of the five men who are to be ordained on Trinity Sunday are "Knutsford Men". The normal supply is represented by one man! There is no sign anywhere of any improvement. What can be the end of such a state of things? The Church is just withering away.</p>
         <p>I worked at my 'charge' to the Ordination Candidates. In the afternoon I motored to Durham, and, after interviewing a candidate in the Chapter Office, went on to Pittington, where I confirmed 120 persons in the beautiful parish church. The service pleased me. After tea at the Vicarage, I went to Shadforth, and had a short interview with the Vicar, Perkins, who was in bed with a failure of nerves. Then, through falling rain, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The King has offered the Premiership to M</hi> <hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline"> Stanley Baldwin<persName xml:id="4118"></persName>, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, and the offer has been accepted. The appointment appears to be generally approved, &amp;, indeed, to have been almost inevitable, for L</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName>, whose services &amp; seniority might seem irresistible titles to the principal place, is held to be disqualified by his peerage! It is hard on him, but his peerage did him much service in the earlier stages of his career. M</hi> <hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline"> Baldwin is mainly a dark horse, but that is probably an advantage. Lloyd George has made no delay in announcing his opposition to the new Government. Bonar Law's retirement releases him, in his opinion, from any obligation to maintain a "benevolent neutrality" towards his successor.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>