<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Before going to the House of Bishops I called on D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Vernon to inquire about Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> plans. It is evident that she is apprehensive of a recurrence of the mischief from which last year's operation was thought to have set her free. The discussion on the motion for "general approval" continued, with an interval for luncheon, until 4 p.m., when the vote was taken. Three bishops – Norwich, Bristol, &amp; Worcester – voted in the negative , but why I cannot imagine. The most notable speech was that of Lang, who expressed his preference for the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> Prayer book of Edward VI, in which he was supported by the Bishop of Winchester, whose speech was painfully incoherent and <hi rend="underline">senile</hi>. He draws towards fourscore, &amp; ought to retire. The Bishop of Chelmsford ranted &amp; canted, &amp; so (with an added touch of buffoonery which was all his own) did the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's. The latter made a very bad impression on everybody. As one listens to him one is amazed that the episcopate of England should be represented by a rowdy undergraduate, for he is nothing more.</p>
         <p>I returned home by the 5.30p.m. express, and had Strong as my travelling companion as far as York. We had much talk together. He is certainly far more liberal on ecclesiastical matters ^than might be inferred from his ecclesiastical "colour"^ , but I cannot avoid the suspicion that he is not so liberal as he seems, or as probably he imagines himself to be. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met the train at Darlington.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>