<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[217]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Zanzibar's reprint of his letter to the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi> under the title "In defence of the English Catholic" reached me this morning. He has added a Preface and his 'Final Address at the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Congress'. I was sufficiently moved by perusing this pamphlet to write an Article for the "<hi rend="underline">Spectator</hi>" entitled "<hi rend="bold underline">A Go&#8211;as&#8211;you&#8211;please Church</hi>".</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Stoddart, who aspires to be the curate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Matthew's Darlington, came to see me, &amp; stayed to lunch. There lunched also a party of <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> friends, to whom I showed the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Ordination Candidates, six in number, arrived about 6 p.m. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> also arrived, &amp; gave the address in chapel at 7 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Knight</hi> <hi rend="italic"> had some talk with me about his parish. He describes the people, almost all miners, as well&#8211;paid, self&#8211;indulgent, &amp; intellectually undeveloped. "It is a parish without a book in it", he said, but one of the newsagents told him that on Saturday afternoons he usually sold 3000 copies of the "Football Edition" of the evening paper. The people are extremely well&#8211;fed, indeed, their interest in the butcher shops divides their minds with that in their sports. Whippet racing, rabbit coursing, betting on horse races &amp; on everything else, &amp; above all football absorb them. Over&#8211;crowding is terrible. He spoke of 13 persons being in a 4 roomed house: of two married couples with a child, and another about to be born occupying a single room. And the morality matches the housing.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>