<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to Victoria Street in time to catch the 10.40a.m. train to Birchington. <hi rend="bold underline">We were joined on the platform by Arthur Rawle<persName xml:id="813"></persName> and Miss Graham. Albert Henson also was in the train but we only discovered the fact when we reached Birchington. The funeral took place at 2.30p.m., the vicar officiated. Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, Ella, Arthur Rawle, Albert Henson and I were the mourners. Miss Graham &amp; Miss Curtis were in the church, &amp; a company of the neighbours including Major &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Powell Cotton. The grave was well chosen on the south side of the Churchyard near The Church. After the service we discussed what might be the best arrangement for Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, now that she has lost her companion. Ella was insistent that she s</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">hd </hi> <hi rend="bold underline">come to Auckland, and as she herself seemed to desire this, I readily acquiesced. Then we returned to London, &amp; dined quietly at the Deanery.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> sent a very nicely expressed letter of condolence from all the servants at the Castle. A good many wreathes were sent. Boyden, who used to wheel Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> about in the bath&#8211;chair, spoke with genuine affection of her. Indeed, I think no one could have come into personal contact with her without discovering her intrinsic excellence.</hi></p>
         <p>The great heat continues.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>