<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington, where I took train for London. <hi rend="bold underline">Lang was my compagnon de voyage, and we had some conversation. I doubt if he is "going straight" in the matter of Prayer Book Revision. His unexpected advocacy of the 1549 Prayer Book has too much the appearance of a 'bid' for the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" vote</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> I made him read the little tract on the said Book published by the Society of SS Peter &amp; Paul, and written by a very "cock&#8211;sure" fanatick named ^Archdale A. King^. He was, I suspect, rather startled by it, but he did not admit as much. On arriving at King's Cross I drove to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Then I visited the Barber: &amp; went to Adeney's where I tried on the clothes I ordered a fortnight ago. On returning to the Club I found a crowded meeting of the members proceeding. A proposal to build an additional story, with a view to providing bedrooms was under discussion, but I did not abide the result, as I found the asphyxiating atmosphere of the over&#8211;crowded room unendurable. The proposal, as I learned afterwards, had been "turned down": and this is well. The 'Athenaeum', like the Jesuit Society, should never be altered: 'Sint ut sunt aut non sint' is a sound rule for such institutions! After leaving my bags in Marsham Street, &amp; taking a constitutional in the Park, and then went again to the Club, where I dined with Strong. He professes willingness to make the handling of the Courts proceed synchronously with the Revision of the Prayer Book, but I doubt if he will stick even to that.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>