<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>What does the Bishop of Chelmsford desire to show by his votes on Prayer Book Revision in his synod of the clergy of his diocese? He can hardly think that the decision if the issues at stake can be determined in that way. Had the appeal been made to the votes of the parochial clergy, there would certainly have been no Reformation. It cannot be decently suggested that on any matter of truth or principle a valid decision, moral valid, and binding on the conscience, could be reached by counting heads! As indicating the extent of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic revolt in the diocese of Chelmsford the figures have a certain interest. But the mere putting to the vote questions on which the Church of England has spoken, implies a shock to discipline, and puts forward a quasi&#8211;pledge to make changes of system.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" contains a very long letter from the Bishop of Chelmsford headed "A divided Church". He writes in a very canting way, and his proposals are what might be expected</hi>. The two Abps are to appoint a magnified "Round Table Conference" which "sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be asked to consider questions relating to the Canon, Reservation, &amp; Eccles<hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi> Courts". <hi rend="bold underline">The Conference is to go into retreat in order to secure Divine guidance</hi>, &#8211; "If God vouchsafe to reveal to them His way to heal our divisions, let them come forth and tell it to His Church to be dealt with in Convocation &amp; in the National Assembly". This fatuous proposal will, of course, be welcomed by the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics".</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p>I dictated to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName> a letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Professor Heawood</hi> in answer to his request for guidance in the matter of P. B. Revision. Also I wrote to the Bishop of Ripon sending him a draft of a Resolution to be moved by me, &amp; seconded by him, in the House of Bishops. These letters had been dispatched before I had seen the Bishop of Chelmsford's fatuous letter in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>". It would not, however, have made any serious difference.</p>
         <p>After an early lunch I, accompanied by Canon Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, motored to Muggleswick in order to attend the funeral of Smith, the Vicar of that parish. The little church was filled with the parishioners. After the service we had tea with old M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Ritson<persName xml:id="3822"></persName>. We returned by way of Durham, where Sykes got down, &amp; we called on Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName>. We motored to South Hetton, where I confirmed 120 persons in the mean little parish church, which is within a few weeks of celebrating its "Diamond Jubilee"! We returned to Auckland where we arrived about 9.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>The weather continues to be wet and cold, most depressing. Some well&#8211;known public man proclaiming in characteristic "Protestant" phrase that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> never be priest&#8211;ridden, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Monsell</hi> replied:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"Ridden, you need not fear to be,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">By prophet or by priest,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Since Balaam's dead; &#8211; and none but he</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Would choose you for his beast</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>