<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>We loafed about the house and garden during the morning, reading and talking: and in the afternoon (publish it not in Gath!) I slumbered for the day was sultry, &amp; the heat was great. After tea <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Thompson</hi> motored us to see <hi rend="underline">Framlingham</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Dennington </hi>churches. The first is notable for its noble timber roof, for the fine series of tombs of the Howards, and for the helmet of the Earl of Surrey, who commanded the English army at the Battle of Flodden. This interesting relic is suspended from the chancel wall. While we were in the church, the parson entered in his canonicals, and read a curtailed version of Evensong. We attended the little service, and afterwards inspected the church. The parson was civil, but knew little about his church. Hard by are the ruins of <hi rend="underline">Framlingham Castle</hi>. We went on to <hi rend="underline">Dennington</hi> which is full of interest. The fine set of medieval pews with carved bench ends, the elaborate and beautiful screens, and the tomb of a 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Lord Bardolph were notable features. I noticed on the altar what was evidently a tabernacle, and as a lamp burned before it, I suppose the Blessed Sacrament was reserved therein. In the porch hung a notice of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Congress in London.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>