<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">One</hi> Canon reduced to writing by God Himself: <hi rend="underline">two</hi> Testaments, <hi rend="underline">three</hi> Creeds, <hi rend="underline">four</hi> General Councils, <hi rend="underline">five</hi> centuries, and the series of Fathers in that period – the three centuries, that is, before Constantine, &amp; two after, determine the boundary of our faith.</p>
         <p>Bp. Andrews. Opusc. Posthum: p. 91.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This simple arithmetic does not help us much now: but it seemed irresistible in the Court &amp; Church of James I: &amp; is still effective in the audiences which rise to the name of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pusey!</p>
         <p>I worked at the Scarborough Sermon until Duncan from Willington arrived, in order to explain the situation in his parish. I spoke to him with much candour, but with much kindness: and he expressed himself very properly. He stayed to lunch.</p>
         <p>I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>: &amp; then played the tame Bishop to <persName xml:id="112">my wife's</persName> tea party. Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName> had brought an old barrister whose name I have forgotten, &amp;, of course, I had to show him over the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Miss Maud Bull<persName xml:id="5737"></persName>  from Hereford arrived on a visit.</hi> She is making a tour of the North, &amp; expresses her mind with the freedom &amp; lucidity which all her acquaintance appreciate.</p>
         <p>The weather continues damp &amp; chilly: but John assures me that there will be change with the "day moon"!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>