<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The Vicar of Bramfield, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Boyce, &amp; his wife came to lunch. He has held the living for more than 23 years, and, though he has more than 500 parishioners, he does not appear to be dissatisfied with a communicants' roll of about 80! There are 2 chapels in the parish, and at least 200 of the people go nowhere. Our hostess motored us to see some more churches. In the course of the afternoon and evening we visited four viz: 1. Hasleworth. 2. Blyborough. 3. Reynton. 4. Southwold. Of these Blyborough is both the most dilapidated and the most interesting. Its stately dimensions, the curiously carved benches, and the Hopton tombs are all noteworthy. But it had a desolate and neglected appearance. The young woman in attendance said that the congregations varied in umber from 9 to 20 individuals, thought the parishioners numbered several hundreds.</p>
         <p>Southwold Church, dedicated to S. Edmund, is a noble building which has retained its medieval chancel screen. In the sanctuary there is a piscina with no less than three ledges above it. Mostly the churches stand open, but we had to fetch the key in order to gain entrance to Southwold.</p>
         <p>After dinner, the heat being great, we sate in the garden. Miles and I had some religious conversation, but in these great matters does good come ever from discussion?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>