<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God the King of glory, who hast exalted thine only Son Jesus Christ with great triumph unto thy kingdom in heaven; We beseech thee, leave us not comfortless; but send to us thine Holy Ghost to comfort us, and exalt us unto the same place whither our Saviour Christ is gone before, who liveth and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghost, one God, world without end.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a free translation from the Sarum, which runs thus:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O rex gloriae domine virtutum qui triumphator hodie super omnes celos ascendisti, ne derelinquas nos orphanos: sed mitte promissum patris in nos spiritum veritatis, alleluia.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. My guests communicated.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The General, Lady Kirkpatrick, and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Durham, where we attended morning service in the Cathedral, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; heard the Archbishop of York preach an excellent sermon, in which he expressed his agreement with my Cathedral scheme. I insisted on pronouncing the Benediction myself in order to maintain the rights of my See</hi> <hi rend="bold">!</hi> Amery was staying at the Deanery. There were 4 quondam Fellows of All Souls in the Cathedral together – Lang, Henson, Pemberton<persName xml:id="2837"></persName>, &amp; Amery. After lunch at the Deanery, I motored to Gateshead &amp; preached twice – to the Freemasons in Christ Church, &amp; to the general congregation at S. Edmund's.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>