<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The essential faiths of mankind show a surprising power of surviving the dogma on which they are supposed to rest.</p>
         <p>Pringle Pattison.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times prints the short letter which I wrote at Bishopthorpe in answer to the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t </hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Alban's. It will no doubt be ignored by the "Church Times", which none the less gives great prominence to the most offensive paragraph of the Bishop's letter</hi> <hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>Edgar Dobie wrote me a quaint affectionate letter in which he tells me that he has 'sometimes to champion my cause – often against very ordinary people, who do not wish to reason, but who oppose on principal, &amp; certainly will not be convinced.'</p>
         <p>'I have defended to the best of my ability, and have wished you could be there personally. I am always comforted when I say to myself. "They do not know him and I do; &amp; I love him because I know him". That is a touching expression of loyalty from an old Durham chorister. I do not mind much the misrepresentation &amp; insult of the 'Church Times' on my own account, but I do regret the distress &amp; disturbance of mind caused to so many persons, clergy &amp; laity, who do not know how far partisanship will carry men, &amp; are at the mercy of what they read. Probably the continuing denunciation of the Bishop in the newspaper which they read regularly with religious devotion does affect their minds, &amp; make episcopal government more difficult.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>