<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[237]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>All our guests left us except the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName>. I wrote at some length to <hi rend="doubleunderline">the Bishop of Ripon</hi> in answer to a distinctly unsatisfactory letter from him on the subject of Divorce. After lunch I took the Dean to Raby, where a son &amp; heir was born last week. We found Lord Barnard<persName xml:id="5197"></persName> at home, offered him our congratulations, and were shown the Castle. Then we went on to Staindrop, where we found the Vicar (Spurrier) busy in harvest decorating. He shewed us the church, and took the opportunity of my presence to express his desire to create a side chapel by transferring the present choir vestry to the opposite side of the church, and to ask me how to deal with his curate, who will not visit and cannot preach! He has recently married a wife and therefore ! </p>
         <p>For some reason or other I was indisposed, &amp;, though I sate at my table, I did no work! The recent mine accident in Scotland led me to talk to John, who at one stage in his career drove ponies in Brancepeth pit. It appears that Safety lamps are not generally used, and that where danger from gas is feared, canaries are used to test the atmosphere.</p>
         <p>I found myself compelled to make my apologies, and retire to bed. Probably my foolish presumption in walking about in the garden without an overcoat, &amp; playing bowls on very wet turf, gave me a chill, which could not be conjured away.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>