<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[147]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A magnificent summer day from start to finish. I wrote a welcoming letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Woollcombe</hi>, whose appointment to be bishop suffragan of Whitby is announced in the morning paper. He is a good fellow of the clerical type now fashionable – "life &amp; liberty", mildly socialistic, very "Catholic", &amp; vastly loving to the sectaries at damns!</p>
         <p>We left the Castle about 10.30 a.m., &amp; motored by way of Piercebridge &amp; Boroughbridge to Marston Moor, where we ate our lunch under a hedge. Then we continued through Selby, where we looked at the Abbey church, &amp; Doncaster to the "Old Bell Inn", about 3 miles from Retford, where we had tea. Then we resumed our journey, but when we were a few miles from Retford, a rod broke &amp; we limped to Carlton noisily. On the way William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> telegraphed to Bishop Auckland for a new rod. This is the first breakdown of its domestic economy which the "Nash" car has experienced, and as the register records nearly 3500 miles, I suppose we must not complain. Yet is may not be denied that such an experience on the first day of a motoring holiday is disconcerting!</p>
         <p>We were kindly received by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Skeffington Craig at Carlton Hall.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Lawrie &amp; her family are here. They – except the younger boy Sidney – are about to visit Canada, &amp; this circumstance provided a subject of conversation additional to the too&#8211;familiar topic of the family relationships. Haliburton, the eldest boy, is spoiled, &amp; therefore ill&#8211;mannered.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>