<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A revolution in Bulgaria is reported, and the death of Princess Christian. So the world goes. I cleared off a mass of correspondence, &amp; then motored with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to Gateshead where a garden party in aid of the Waifs &amp; Strays Society had been arranged. It was wretchedly attended.</p>
         <p>Elwood of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Chad's talked to me about the mission Church of S. Hilda, which he desires to close and sell, there being little real need for it, and the reduced state of his staff making it very difficult to maintain the services. I went to look at the building, &amp; satisfied myself that his contention was reasonable.</p>
         <p>A letter from Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> told me that he accepted my nomination of Appleton for the living of Seaham Harbour. Thus all 3 livings have been filled by my suggestions for the Crown has appointed my nominees to Middleton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees, and All Saints, Sunderland. Viz: Perrott to the first and Saxton to the last.</p>
         <p>I learned that old Canon Martin was actually dying: his death will vacate an important and valuable living. In September the resignations of Canon Hopkinson &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fellowes will mature – Whitburn, Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne, and Kelloe are all wealthy livings, &amp; all in my gift.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>