<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>As illustrating the temper and tendency of the new "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" movement, it is worth mentioning that the insistence of the Vicar of All Saints, Newcastle, on substituting a celebration of the Holy Eucharist for the accustomed service, had <hi rend="bold underline">the effect of so offending the Lord Mayor &amp; Corporation Newcastle that they refused to attend Divine Service in All Saints on Sunday thus breaking a tradition 'centuries old'</hi>. I wrote to Newsom<persName xml:id="923"></persName> inquiring whether the report in "<hi rend="underline">The Illustrated Chronicle</hi>" was true, and he replied that it was "<hi rend="underline">a substantially true account</hi>" but "<hi rend="underline">not a matter of great moment</hi>". The Vicar in his view was "<hi rend="doubleunderline">pedantic</hi>" in the matter! </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop ^of Melbourne^ had some conversation with me before taking his departure. He said that his son, the Sec: of S.P.C.K.<orgName xml:id="23"></orgName> assured him that the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> was gravely divided on the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" question, &amp; that he himself had been invited to join the Committee with a view to determining a new policy. I doubt the value of this</hi>. He told me that a woeful Eyton in Australia returned to the vices which had drawn him from England, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; died finally from poison which was self&#8211;administered. His suicide was "hushed up.</hi>" He expressed himself rather strongly about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Moule's</hi> weakness in dealing with cases of discipline, and his failure to stand by him (the Abp) in a very grave case. He held that in the case of these moral failures, it was not right to give another chance. T<hi rend="doubleunderline">ha</hi>t vice was both disqualifying &amp; incurable.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
         <p>The weather became warm &amp; sunny. It was possible to sit out in the garden without discomfort. These happy changes were particularly welcome in view of the <hi rend="underline">Church Lads Brigade<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> camp</hi>. The boys, about 500, arrived in the course of the afternoon. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Timothy Eden</hi>, &amp; an officer from Beamish named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingram</hi>, stayed in the Castle. The other officers were billeted in the town.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>