<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[194]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather was brilliant, and added enjoyment to the expedition which we made to Northwick Hall. Aleck, his two boys, and I left the house at 10.15 a.m., and motored about 60 miles to lunch with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Spencer Churchill</hi>, &amp; to see his magnificent collection of coins, bronzes, pictures etc. We found him seated in his study at a table covered with statuettes &amp; other antiques in a room of which the walls were hung with master&#8211;pieces of Sir Joshua Reynolds, Romney, &amp; other masters. The owner of these treasures is a good&#8211;looking man, apparently not much above 40 years of age, with a frank manner, &amp; a winning address. After entertaining us at lunch, he showed us his picture gallery. It has many admirable works by Italian, Dutch, &amp; Flemish masters. He showed us also his rich collection of Greek coins, &amp; his fine specimens of medieval illumination. Then he proposed that we should visit his stables &amp; gardens. We found that he unites the keenest interest in cattle, sheep, dogs, and poultry with an intelligent concern for the arts. We had tea, &amp; returned to Brockham End by way of Cheltenham. The milometer on the car registered 124 miles.</p>
         <p>It is a notable evidence of my ignorance that I had never so much as heard of the collections in Northwick Hall until I viewed them today. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>