<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Aleck Lawrence &amp; I breakfasted pleasantly with Vincent Baddeley &amp; a friend. Then I made my way to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> by an immense detour, the crowds which were gathering for the Duke of York's wedding making the direct approach impossible. I found a considerable parcel of letters awaiting me, &amp; spent the morning in answering them. At lunch, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Humphrey Ward introduced himself to me, &amp; we had some conversation.</p>
         <p>I transferred myself from Marsham Street to the Deanery of S. Paul's, and, after tea with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, <hi rend="underline">went to the Cathedral, and preached to the Royal Society of S. George</hi><orgName xml:id="329"></orgName>. There was a considerable congregation, and I think they could all hear, but there is always something unnatural to English folk about a week&#8211;day sermon! Old Canon Newbolt was the only member of the chapter present at the service. He expressed himself in a very melancholy manner as to the prospect of Prayer book Revision. He belongs to the older Tractarian school which views with considerable perturbation the lawlessness of the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics", and, to do it justice, had a sense of order and loyalty. Crauford Inge<persName xml:id="4597"></persName> has grown to be a thoughtful, well&#8211;mannered youth of seventeen. I was certainly pleased with the result of his three years at Shrewsbury: &amp; I shall make an effort to gain &amp; keep his friendship.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>