<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[238]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I did not get up for breakfast, so the Dean came to my room to say, Goodbye, before going off. He expressed himself very generously as to our hospitality to the Commission. Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> was carried down in her chair to see the chapel, and the flower&#8211;beds.</p>
         <p>S. came to see me. He disclosed the utmost astonishment and indignation. I could not but promise to write again to the Chaplain General which I did, there and then.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi> write to say that they sent me a letter on the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> inst. In that case, it must have gone astray, for I never received it. I sent to them the newspaper cuttings of the two letters to the 'Morning Post' together with the following:</p>
         <p>1. What does the Church of England stand for? Westminster Abbey 1922</p>
         <p>2. Appeal to sound learning &amp; Christian Unity: S. Paul's, Covent Garden, 1919</p>
         <p>3. The Church of England. Westminster Abbey. 1919.</p>
         <p>4. Charge to Ordination Candidates. 1923.</p>
         <p>5. Reunion of Christendom. West Hartlepool. 1923.</p>
         <p>6. Magna Carta &amp; Church Reform. 1915.</p>
         <p>Also I promised to send an "Introduction" in a few days.</p>
         <p>The loss of a whole week, when the shortness of time for printing &amp; publishing is so evident, is a grave inconvenience: for unless the booklet is placed in the hands of the lay members of the National Assembly before the meeting in November, its object will have been defeated.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>