<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>To allow sewer&#8211;gas to enter a house is now an indictable offence, &amp; the owner of premises who fails to take steps to prevent it soon finds himself before the magistrate. Legislative measures ought to be taken to prevent any public building, hall, church or house from being used, unless a sufficient quantity of pure fresh air is introduced with regularity. The importance of keeping houses clean, streets swept &amp; sewers flushed, is admitted – all with the object of maintaining the air in a pure condition; &amp; after millions have been spent with this aim in view, air is allowed to become absolutely foul and putrid for want of proper ventilation. Air which has passed through the human lungs has been well designated "air&#8211;sewage". It is highly poisonous, &amp; is charged with impure matters. It is then breathed, rebreathed, &amp; breathed again to the injury of all present, &amp; with the result of the serious illness &amp; the death of some.'</p>
         <p>"The Ventilation of Tunnels and Buildings" by Francis Fox, M.Inst.C.E. London. 1899</p>
         </div>
         <p>Sir Francis Fox id an authority to whom, perhaps, the clergy will listen more respectfully than to their own Bishop. His performance at Winchester is, of course, unforgettable.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">After lunch I took the Darlings and Yvonne to see High Force</hi>. The weather was fine, but rather cold and blustering. There was more water in the Fall than I had dared to hope, and, indeed, it was a very impressive spectacle. The beauty of the physical environment of this Fall could hardly be exceeded. After having tea at the Hotel, we motored to Barnard Castle, intending to see the Bowes Museum. But we found the Museum closed. We motored to Staindrop, where we stopped to visit the parish church. Then we returned to Auckland, lingering at the spot on the road where Raby Castle discloses its beauty. We arrived home about 6.20 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me Rowlandson's wonderful drawing of the late Archdeacon Watkins<persName xml:id="590"></persName>. It is hardly a caricature so much as a very striking likeness. The sketch presents him as he was at the end of his life, grey &amp; slightly bowed</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi> was very amusing at and after dinner. He has a large fund of good stories, and he tells them well. He is very good tempered, and easy to "fit in" to his environment. It is plain enough that he likes talking about himself, and that his estimate of his own achievements does not err on the side of inadequacy: but he has a fine sense of humour, &amp; he has done much, and seen much, in the course of his life. <hi rend="bold underline">His daughter is not beautiful, but she is bright &amp; amicable.</hi> She has a fine voice, &amp; knows how to use it. She sang ten songs after dinner to the general delight. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>