<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[164]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Miles went off to Yarmouth to join the Choir, which was spending there its annual festival. Lady Thompson and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> motored to Lowestoft to pay visits &amp; do shopping. I sate in the garden &amp; talked with the Vicar, whose "staying power" moved my admiration. When, 'at long last', (as the sectaries say) his reverence departed, I wrote a series of letters. We (i.e. Lady T, Ella, &amp; I) had tee [sic] with Lord &amp; Lady Huntingford, very pleasant people living in a large attractive XVIII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house, on which Wyatt had laid a heavy hand. I had some talk with Lady H., and was much pleased with her candour and intelligence. The day became very hot and sultry.</p>
         <p>The papers contain the text of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Curzon's</hi><persName xml:id="1018"></persName><hi rend="underline"> Note to France</hi>. It is more severely expressed than has been generally expected, &amp; discloses a strained situation, which may easily develope into actual discord. On the whole I incline to think that, though so late, it is a good thing that Great Britain should at last resume her liberty of action. France is both selfish &amp; cynical. In alliance with her there is no limit to the immoral sophistries to which this country might find itself committed. Both the Morning Post, and the Daily Mail condemn the Government, very unpatriotically as I must needs think. They might at least refrain from comment.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>