<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>But Easter Day breaks! But</p>
         <p>Christ rises! Mercy every way</p>
         <p>Is infinite, – and who can say?</p>
         </div>
         <p>Is this '<hi rend="underline">the victory that hath overcome the world, even our faith</hi>'? Is anything more possible now? </p>
         <p>A dull rainy morning, very depressing to heart and mind.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 12 communicants, including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; John. Ashton, the Park&#8211;keeper, with his wife and daughter came also.</p>
         <p>I motored to <hi rend="underline">S. Helen's, Auckland</hi>, where I preached &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion at 10.30 a.m. There were 152 communicants, almost all very young men &amp; women. In administering the Elements, after using the full formula at the start, we merely said the opening words:&#8211; 'The Body of our Lord Jesus Christ which was given for thee.' This arrangement was expeditious, and appeared to work without irreverence.</p>
         <p>We all motored to <hi rend="underline">Durham</hi> for Evensong in the Cathedral. I sate in the Throne, &amp; pronounced the Benediction. Immediately after the service we motored to <hi rend="underline">Kirk Merrington</hi>, where we had tea in the Vicarage before going to church for Evensong. I read the lessons and preached. The church was filled with a congregation remarkable for the large proportion of young men which it included: &amp; they were all very attentive. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>