<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I received a disconcerting letter from M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Powell Cotton about poor Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> again went to Birchington in consequence.</hi> I went to Westminster &amp; there seconded the Bishop of Chelmsford's motion:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>That, in view of the urgent need of restoring discipline in the Church of England, &amp; having regard to the recommendations contained in the Report of the Royal Commission on Ecclesiastical Discipline issued in 1906, it is desirable that a measure for reconstructing the Diocesan &amp; Provincial Courts &amp; the Court of Final Appeal to be introduced forthwith into the National Assembly &amp; carried into law with all possible despatch."</p>
         </div>
         <p>As soon as I sate down <hi rend="bold underline">Bell brought me 3 telephones from Birchington which Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> sent on from the Deanery. These were so alarming that I made my excuses to the Archbishop, and hastened to Birchington. I found my poor sister in a woeful state, talking incessantly &amp; incoherently. I don't think she knew me. I wrote to the doctor stating my desire for a second opinion: &amp; the Matron of the Hospital declared herself ready to be responsible for the night. Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> is to arrive tomorrow &amp; I hope to stay in Birchington.</hi> <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I returned to the Deanery, dining at the Savoy.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>