<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather is blustering, and bitterly cold. There were showers of sleet in the course of the morning. I completed the sermon for Westminster Abbey, and wrote many letters. Old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Milner, who has been taking the duty at Middleton&#8211;in&#8211;Teesdale came to lunch. He reported the circumstances in which the unhappy parson had died. The Rectory appears to be in a shocking state of dilapidation. Then came M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Perrott, the son of the old Vicar on the hill. He is mainly employed in teaching in a secondary school, retaining a link with Holy Orders by serving as a part&#8211;time curate in one of the Sunderland parishes. He had sought an interview with me because he feared that I disapproved this arrangement! I re&#8211;assured him, but pointed out that the Ordination Vows contemplated the career of pastorate. I asked him about his circumstances. He said that he could not manage with a less income than &#x00A3;450 per annum. But this exceeds by &#x00A3;100 the average income of the parishes in this diocese.</p>
         <p>I went round to Edgen Hall, where a number of deaf and dumb people were being entertained at tea, and through an interpreter, I made a short speech to them. A woeful spectacle! </p>
         <p>Then I returned to the Castle, and wrote letters until dinner. Summer time begins tonight. The clocks were all changed before we went to bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
