<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> April, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove me to Darlington to catch the London express. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went with me, and we were both nearly frozen by the bitter wind. Sir Hugh Bell joined the train at York, and was vivacious &amp; interesting as ever. <hi rend="bold underline">His daughter, the redoubtable Gertrude, is returning home immediately</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> She is opposed to an evacuation of Mesopotamia at this juncture, &amp; thinks that, in a few years time, the Arabs might form a stable state.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I called at 7 Victoria Street, and saw </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName><hi rend="italic">. She is evidently in a grave state, and the position is not improved by her evident depression. She even talked as if it were an agreed point that she was suffering from </hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">cancer</hi> <hi rend="italic">, an idea which, of course, I scouted, though perhaps with more eagerness than confidence. However we must see that the radium treatment will effect. The woeful thing is that, with the best will in the world, one </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">can but be an onlooker on the sorrows of those we love</hi> <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>I dined in the Guildhall with the Royal Society of S. George<orgName xml:id="329"></orgName>. The Prince of Wales presided, and spoke very well. I was placed beside the Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="bold underline">who began the conversation by reminding me that he had read the lessons in University College Chapel when I read the service as chaplain</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> That must be not less than 37 years ago. We had much interesting talk together, and parted with many professions of mutual regard. He is an odd&#8211;looking little round man, who doesn't give the impression of extraordinary ability. But he talks with knowledge and intelligence.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>