<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[209]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"Summer time" ended last night, and we all had an hour longer in bed to admire a brilliant morning, and to wonder what the reasons could have been which led Parliament to make the lapse into winter take place so early. I read the new 'Life' of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Shaftesbury</hi> which has been written by the Hammonds. It is melancholy reading both for the horrible picture of early XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th </hi>century England which it presents, and for the painful disclosure of personal religion which it makes. Probably I should have been one of the reluctant majority who voted against all economic experiments in the name of philanthropy, and thus I should, to the measure of my influence, have identified the cause of Christ with the harshest expressions of "the dismal science"! This is a consideration which must needs weigh with me when I determine my course in current politics. Is the "Christian Social Union" right after all? Ought I, indeed, "at long last" (as the sectaries say) to seek admission to the "Life and Liberty" Association? At least I may plead that, not only were the conditions of labour in the early XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century highly inimical to economic efficiency, &amp;, therefore, indefensible on any ground, but also, that the situation of Great Britain at that time gave it so great an advantage over all other countries that there was an almost limitless margin in which philanthropic essays in the economic sphere were possibly without disaster. Neither of these conditions exists now. Not too much, but too little labour threatens the workman's efficiency: &amp; Great Britain has lost its privileged position. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[210]</hi> [symbol] </p>
         <p>There is, moreover, a significant change in the general situation. <hi rend="underline">Then</hi>. the cause of the labourer was unpopular, &amp; could only be pleaded at great cost of social disfavour &amp; political disadvantage. <hi rend="underline">Now.</hi> the politicians are tumbling over one another in the race for popular support, and no quicker route to social distinction can be found than the profession of "Socialist" opinions. Power has shifted from the 'classes' to the 'masses': and it still draws the eager homage of the ambitious, the sycophantic, and the unthinking. There is no reason in the nature of things why the right cause should not also be the popular &amp; prevailing cause, but the union of characters is historical unusual, &amp; always implies a peril to the better factors of the alliance. </p>
         <p>The championship of the "oppressed" is a morally exhilarating occupation, and, if it entail sacrifice on the champion, is morally impressive, but there is nothing either morally exhilarating or morally impressive about the struggle for class "rights", and class dominance, even though the class be the least educated and the most numerous. If, moreover, the methods of the conflict be themselves immoral &amp; oppressive, it can hardly but be the case that the combatants are the more debased as they prevail. Something of this kind is actually happening in the sphere of modern politics. The dominance of economic issues lowers the continuing strife of factions into a squalid fight for material advantage. It is really impossible to regard the "Labour Leaders" and the "Society Socialists" as in the true line of succession from the Prophets &amp; Reformers. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[211]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Penelope<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> going with me, I motored to Edmundbyers, where I confirmed 11 candidates in the little Church, among them the daughters respectively of Dolphin<persName xml:id="2798"></persName> and M.P. who lives in the parish. The little church was filled, and everything seemed reverent &amp; sincere. After lunching at the Vicarage, we called on the Ritsons<persName xml:id="3822"></persName> at Muggleswick. We found a party from New Zealand had just arrived, &amp; everybody was very hilarious! Ella &amp; Penelope went to Muggleswick Vicarage to see the Poules, &amp; to attend Evensong with them. I motered to Castleside, and, after having tea with Elphick, preached in the little parish church. Then I returned to Muggleswick, took on board the ladies, &amp; returned to Auckland, arriving about 10 p.m. </p>
         <p>Edmundbyers with 215 parishioners, &amp; Muggleswick with 365, are two of the smallest parishes in my diocese so far as population is concerned, but the area of both is very large, and in Muggleswick Divine Service has to be conducted in two places. The endowment of the one parish is put down in the books as £475, and that of the other as £420. The residence houses are good &amp; not excessively large. Both are in the patronage of the Dean &amp; Chapter. In the event of Disendowment it is not probable that clergy could be maintained at these little places, nor, indeed, can it seriously maintained that they provide, singly or even in contribution, adequate employment for a clergyman during the week. On Sunday he has employment enough, but there are only 52 Sundays in the year. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>