<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A telegram from Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> brought me the news that the expected end had come. Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> died yesterday. It is hard to believe that I can never see her, &amp; talk with her.</hi></p>
         <p>The last months have been, I fear, darkly shadowed by bodily pain, and mental anxiety. She spoke to me several times about the probability of her own death preceding Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, and undoubtedly she was much distressed by the loneliness in which that untoward reversion of the natural order would bring the aged lady. <hi rend="bold underline">My last sight of her was last Wednesday, when she talked incessantly as if in delirium. Whether she knew me or not, I cannot say, but she clasped my hand, and talked incessantly about me. 'Brother – dearest Brother' she kept on saying. As I look back, I do not recall any unkindness that ever occurred between us. We were constantly writing to one another, and I think she knew how greatly I respected her steady self&#8211;surrender to duty.</hi></p>
         <p>Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> went off to Scotland by the early train. I walked to Westminster, lunched at the Club, attended the National Assembly in the afternoon &amp; dined alone with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at the Deanery.</p>
         <p>The great heat continues.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>