<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Lumley, and lunched with Lady Scarbrough. Lord S had to go off to the scene of the terrible colliery accident reported in the papers this morning. After lunch Lady S showed us over the castle, and then we returned to Auckland. A canadian Professor &amp; his wife were brought over to see the Castle by Min Shafto &amp; a Knutsford man came to visit Clayton. The stayed to tea. At 5 p.m. we motored to Durham, picked up Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName>, &amp; went on to Trimdon Grange, where I consecrated a portion of the new burial ground. <hi rend="bold underline">I took occasion in my address to the people to denounce the hideous glass globes which are everywhere being introduced into the burial grounds</hi>. We got back to Auckland in time for dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> having accepted appointment to Haughton–le–Skerne, I offered the Rectory of Bishopwearmouth to Wynne Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName>. If he were to accept it, and acquit himself as Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> has done at Houghton–le–Spring. I shall have done a good turn to the diocese. That, perhaps, is too much to expect, but I may fairly expect him to do the larger scene of Sunderland what has done on the relatively petty arena of Hereford: &amp; if so much might be gained, I should be fairly contented. Of course, he may flinch from so formidable a task, &amp; if he does, I could not blame him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>