<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Low Sunday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I attended the morning service in Newtonards parish church, where we occupied the great square pew of the Londonderry family, and I read the lessons. The Rector preached the sermon from 2. Timothy I.7. "<hi rend="underline">For God hath not given us a spirit of fear, but of power, and love, and discipline</hi>." He was evidently concerned with the 'burning' subject of education, but his utterance was not very distinct, &amp; perhaps the acoustics of the building were not all that could be desired. Anyway, I failed to hear much of the discourse. After lunch we were taken by our host to see a church–parade &amp; march past of the Ulster constabulary arranged for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Derby</hi>. The wind was bitterly cold, but the sun shone brightly, and an immense concourse of people came to witness the function. 5800 men were formed into a hollowsquare. The service was conducted by the Bishop of Down, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Montgomery</hi> the ex–Moderator of the Presbyterians, &amp; a little unctuous Baptist. (I am not sure whether I got the identities correctly when I was introduced to the two last.!). Not a word was audible to those on the 'grand–stand'. After the religious service, the men marched past <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Derby</hi>, &amp; made a fine show, many of them being ex–service men. We returned to Mount Stewart, &amp; attended Evensong in the private chapel, after which M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Filson Young</hi> and I walked for an hour before dinner. The evening was brilliant, &amp; the view of the Lough was wonderfully beautiful.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">General Godley</hi>, who now commands the British Army of occupation, is a tall thin man, with an aspect of great determination. His powerful jaw indicates an iron will, and his keen eyes glancing through narrow eye–lids suggest no common sagacity. He is an impressive soldierly figure, who could hardly be other than dominating. If his aspect does not belie his character, he is particularly well–fitted for the very difficult position which he now holds.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Derby</hi> is a heavy, rather common–looking man, with coarse features, and an appearance of bluff honesty, which might be useful if it were balanced by an adequate intelligence. He talks freely, and has a friendly manner, but probably deserves his reputation for stupidity. He brought with him a very agreeable assistant–secretary, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">E. Speed</hi>, with whom I had some pleasant conversation, &amp; whom I shall try to see again.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tweed</hi>, the sculptor, is apparently a friend of <hi rend="doubleunderline">W. P. Ker</hi><persName xml:id="22"></persName>, of whom he speaks with effusion. He told me that he modelled the medal for the All Souls' Centenary celebration. He is possessed of an ingratiating, almost a servile, manner, &amp; he has an unpleasant face, but he expresses very excellent sentiments, &amp;, if they reflect his mind, must be a good man.</p>
         <p>After dinner there were some very silly games, (though no cards,) in which, however, I took no part, but becoming of my abstinence rather absurd than morally impressive!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>