<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The "Times" yesterday reported that "the Presbyterian Church of America" passed a resolution "requiring every Presbyterian minister, church official, church members, &amp; the faculties students in denominational schools to sign a pledge of total abstinence from alcoholic liquors". I received a copy of an American newspaper "The Chronicle" which is published quarterly by the Protestant Episcopal Church. It contains a paragraph complaining of "the English attitude to intoxicating liquors". </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The question is approached in a common&#8211;sense way, entirely, regardless, it would seem, of the overwhelming abuse of the custom, &amp; without an atom of effort to carry out the Pauline principle of refraining because of the weakness of one's brother".</p>
         </div>
         <p>It concludes with a rather sinister statement: </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"It is not apostolic succession, or other offensive doctrines, that set the gulf so deep between the Church of England and other Protestants. It is rather the invincibility of certain English social habits". </p>
         </div>
         <p>There is certainly a wide and widening cleavage between the Churches on social questions as total abstinence, female ministry, divorce, and socialism: but it hardly follows the normal denominational lines. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8.15 a.m. The 7 candidates and 2 chaplains communicated. Then I tried to complete my "charge" but failed to do so. I wrote the names of the candidates in the Bibles and Greek Testaments. After lunch Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I walked in the Park, which is looking wonderful. Magpies abound, &amp; we saw &amp; heard the cuckoo. After tea I had interviews with the candidates, and attended Evensong at 7 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">The "Church Times" has a paragraph suggesting an inquiry into the administration of the Diocese of Exeter, where the Bishop has just announced the shelving of the projected division.</hi> This announcement is the more surprising since it follows so soon upon the rather excessive emphasis laid on the "enthronement" of the suffragan Bishop of Plymouth. "Fish" is certainly too precipitate, and too garrulous.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishops of Chelmsford and S</hi> <hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline"> Alban's are singing in unison on the subject of Prayer&#8211;Book Revision, and their performance is heartily applauded by the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics", for its message is always the old futile sentimentalism, and its suggestion that in no circumstances &amp; for no causes must charitable Christians enforce law, or go beyond brotherly exhortation! In the present mood of the public, however, this "blethering" accords well enough, &amp; it paralyzes any real effort to "restore discipline"</hi> <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>