<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I sent a draft for &#x00A3;200 to Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> from Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> and myself. Also I sent a cheque for &#x00A3;5:11:0 to James Foreman in payment of his tailor's bill! Talking with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi> after breakfast, he told me that the prolonged defence of sensational criminals by distinguished counsel was made possible by the newspapers who 'found the money' in order to get the 'copy'. Crippen was thus financed, &amp; probably many others.</p>
         <p>He told me that, when <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> retired from the Mastership of the Temple, there was a strong desire among many of the Benchers that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName> should succeed him, and that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi> himself would willingly have done so. This project was defeated, however, by the opposition (as was generally supposed) of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward Ridley</hi>, who at the time was Treasurer.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> took the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darlings</hi> to Escombe and South Church, which they looked at, &amp; then returned to the Castle in time to get away to London by the 12.50 p.m. train. We parted with expressions of regret. Indeed they were very agreeable visitors.</p>
         <p>After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Wingate, where I dedicated a porch and a vestry as additions to the mean little parish church, which provides for the public worship of 10,000 people, and, alas!, more than satisfies the demand! We returned to Auckland after tea at the Vicarage.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>