<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I walked with the Bishop of Down for an hour, and discussed the ecclesiastical situation. He expressed himself with much good sense and more liberality than I had expected. When he had gone away, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><persName xml:id="2818"></persName> claimed me for a walk, and we spent the rest of the time before lunch in strolling and talking very pleasantly. </p>
         <p>We travelled in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Derby's</hi> special train to Larne, and were thus made witnesses of the enthusiastic demonstrations at the railway station in Belfast. Lord Londonderry, accompanied me and joined with the Prime Minister and the rest of his colleagues in bidding farewell to the War–Minister. Our passage across the sea was less intolerable than we had feared, &amp; less pleasant than we had desired. We were not sick, but, perhaps, we were rather astonished at the fact. There was a 'through' carriage to Newcastle. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> got out at Carlisle and I went on to Newcastle, where a room in the Hotel had been reserved for me. A slumbrous but amiable hotel–porter brought me hot water, &amp; so I went to bed at 3.10 a.m., tired and dinnerless but less dilapidated than I had expected to be. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">So ended a visit which interested me much. I met several men whom I had desired to meet e.g. General Godley, Filson Young, Tweed, and above all mine host and hostess, whom I was really glad to see in their own house. On the whole, they pleased me well. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>