<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Thirty six years ago I was ordained by Bishop Mackarness in Cuddesdon Parish Church. It was magnificent weather, &amp; all the world was agog with excitement over the approaching celebration of Queen Victoria's "' Jubilee". "Lux Mundi" had not yet appeared (it was published in 1888). The 'Independent Labour Party' was formed. Lightfoot was living in this house, surrounded by an eager company of young graduates from Cambridge. Benson was reigning at Lambeth. Leo xiii held the Papacy.</p>
         <p>We motored to Durham for the Ordination at 10a.m. The congregation consisted in part of Canon Wykes's<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> parishioners who came to hear him preach, &amp; to witness his son's Ordination to the Priesthood. The sermon was excellent in substance, and excellently delivered. Nothing could have been more solemn &amp; impressive than the Ordination itself, and I trust God's Blessing was on it.</p>
         <p>After the service we (the Preacher, 2 chaplains, 5 candidates &amp; myself) lunched with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>. Then, after a walk in the Banks, I attended Evensong in the Cathedral. I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk, after which I returned with my ladies &amp; Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> to the Castle at Auckland. The weather which had been sultry and overcast through the day, had now degenerated, &amp; we drove home through heavy rain. May appears destined to maintain its ill character until the end.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>