<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hooker's</hi> good service was to break down the Genevan theory as to the nature of the authority of Scripture in all church matters. Much of what is said of the authority of the ancient Church seems to me to rest on a precisely analogous but still more untenable theory.</p>
         <p>Hort to Stanton, Nov: 29. 1891. (ii. 435)</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is excellently said. Unhappily we tend in the Church of England to magnify the 'ancient', or, still more, the 'undivided' Church.</p>
         <p>I worked unavailingly at a sermon for Scarborough, played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and wrote necessary letters.</p>
         <p>Among these I wrote to the Bishop of Chelmsford telling him what had passed at the Bishops' Meeting on the subject of the business to be undertaken next July in the House of Bishops, and stating that I had privately given notice to Cantuar of my intention to move a resolution to be seconded by the Bishop of Ripon. I expressed the hope that he would be able to support it.</p>
         <p>Many of the bishops are exhibiting unmistakeable signs of funk! I fully expect to see them flinch before any real policy of restoring discipline. They live in a little world, and are quite content with its approbation. It is so much pleasanter to have everybody smiling on you, and flattering. But there is a price to be paid for all this, &amp; it is heavier than they know.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>