<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'The Whigs of this time (1853) were men of intellectual refinement; they had a genuine regard for good government, &amp; a decent faith in reform: but when we chide the selfishness of machine politicians hunting office in modern democracy, let us console ourselves by recalling the rapacity of our oligarchies.'</p>
         <p>Morley's<persName xml:id="341"></persName> Life of Gladstone, vol. I. p. 446.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The papers this morning are filled with the report of a disgusting outbreak of disorder in the House of Commons, in the course of which four Labour members were suspended. Their coarseness and brutality are almost beyond belief. Is it no more than the inability of ignorant, ill–bred men to control their speech? Or is it a settled determination to insult &amp; degrade Parliament? The effect on the public mind must in either case be deplorable.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; I motored to Catterick Camp (27 miles), and there lunched pleasantly with Colonel Chapman<persName xml:id="5730"></persName> and his officers. After lunch we witnessed the sports. The weather was calm and warm: the situation of the camp was beautiful: the scene was animated &amp; cheerful. Shaddick and Connor were acting as padres, and apparently very popular. After tea we returned to Auckland where we arrived about 6 p.m.</p>
         <p>After dinner <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were tempted by the beauty of the evening to walk in the garden.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>