<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Style has three kinds of excellence, correctness, lucidity, and elegance (for many include the all&#8211;important quality of appropriateness under the heading of elegance). Its faults are likewise three, namely the opposites of these excellences.</p>
         <p>Quintlillian. I. v.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I thought it well to write to the Abp. of Canterbury asking him whether I was expected to second the Bishop of Chelmsford's motion</hi> which appears on the printed Agenda in the original form of my resolution, not in the conflated form which I had offered as a compromise. </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Lambton, where the County Nursing Ass<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> was being entertained by Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>. The dining room was well filled. Lady Gainford presided. The Countess of March was the chief speaker. I proposed a vote of thanks to her Ladyship &amp; our noble host. Then we had tea in a large marquee in the grounds, &amp; in due course came away, &amp; returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">A cheerful letter from Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> was quickly followed by a very disconcerting communication from Madge Graham. It is but too plain that doctor &amp; nurses were in a kindly conspiracy to put a cheerful aspect on a situation which is really extremely unpromising. But we can do nothing. The real tragedy of human life emerges in the utter helplessness of virtue &amp; affection before the inexorable fact of physical disease.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>