<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">We left Bramfield Hall at 10.40 a.m., and motored</hi> to Darsham, where we took the train for Paddington. We left at 11.8 a.m., and arrived without change at about 2.10 p.m. We drove at once to Charing Cross, where we deposited our impedimenta. Then I bought myself a pair of braces, for those I was wearing had come to grief: and had my hair washed. <hi rend="bold underline">We left Charing Cross at 4.30 p.m., and arrived at Sandling Junction at 6.3 p.m. Here Lady Cohen met us with the car, &amp; carried us to Sandy Hatch, an agreeable house set up on the cliff above Hythe, commanding</hi> noble views over the sea, &amp; over the Romney Marsh. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Herbert &amp; Lady Cohen</hi> have lately returned from a visit to Palestine, where they were the guests of the Governor (Store). <hi rend="bold underline">They do not share the political ideals of the Zionists</hi>, but they think that the country is making progress, &amp; that it might maintain a population of as many as 3,000,000 people, which is more than four times its present population. Lady Cohen is certainly a very accomplished painter. Her water–colour sketches adorn the house, &amp; are remarkably good. I was surprised to learn that she had never yet exhibited in the Academy, though she has arranged for private exhibitions of her paintings. We retired to our bedrooms at the reasonable hour – 11 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>