<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, who shewest to them that be in error the light of thy truth, to the intent that they may return into the way of righteousness; Grant unto all them that are admitted into the fellowship of Christ's Religion, that they may eschew those things that are contrary to their profession, and follow all such things as are agreeable to the same; through our Lord Jesus Christ. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>This beautiful collect is taken from the 'so&#8211;called Sacramentarium Leonianum' which 'regarded as a whole appears to be a private collection rather than an official service book.' It is found only in a single MS. written in the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century'. (Brightman)</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. Six of my servants, including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and John, communicated. After breakfast I went to my study, &amp; there continued reading and writing.</p>
         <p>William motored me to Evenwood, where I had tea with the Vicar &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ragg before going to the Church for Evensong. There was a crowded congregation, but the church only accommodates 350 persons. I preached, but the people were rather puzzled than edified! I consented to postpone the date of Ragg's resignation until the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> of August. The difficulty now is to find him a house to live in. We returned to the Castle immediately after service in broad daylight, thanks to Summer time.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>