<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m. All my guests communicated. After breakfast we had a conference until 12.30 p.m., when we lunched, and dispersed. I motored in to Durham and presided over the Committee of the Conference Committee. We determined the order of proceedings for the next Conference, on October 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">I refused to allow the election of 6 representatives to Temple's<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> Conference at Birmingham to be on the agenda.</hi> When this Committee was over, another immediately succeeded, the Board of Education. Here we discussed the Coundon School question, &amp; then I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Just a hundred years will have passed since Byron died in Greece, when I have to give my Rede Lecture at Cambridge. Why should I not take him as my subject</hi> <hi rend="bold">?</hi> There would be an obvious reason for my choice which would serve to propitiate the critics; and it might not be beyond my powers to acquire so much acquaintance with his life and words as to make it possible for me to produce a tolerable essay. Next year I must carry out a formal visitation of the diocese, and that will necessarily leave me small margin for such <hi rend="underline">parerga </hi>as the Rede lecture. It has always been my dream to deliver a charge which should be something more than a summary and analysis of the answers to my inquiries.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>