<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>When one in his (Bishop Cosin's) presence was pleased with some propositions, wherein the Pope condescended somewhat to the Protestants, he most discreetly returned (in my hearing), <hi rend="underline">'We thank him not at all for that which God hath always allowed us in his word', adding withal, 'He would allow it us so long as it stood with his policy, &amp; take it away so soon as it stood with his power'</hi>."</p>
         <p>Fuller, 'Worthies of England' pub<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> 1662</p>
         </div>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Stockton, where we lunched with the Mayor, who entertained the principal performers before the Function of Unveiling &amp; Dedicating the War&#8211;memorial<hi rend="italic bold underline">.</hi> After lunch we processed though densely crowded streets to the Parish church, by which, on a corner of the churchyard, the memorial was erected. A platform had been erected for the ceremonial. The spectacle of the crowd was most impressive. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> unveiled, and I dedicated the memorial: we both made short speeches. After tea in the Town Hall, we returned to Auckland. Later we went to Cornforth where I confirmed 150 persons.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">D. Lowther Clarke, late Abp. of Melbourne arrived</hi>, &amp; Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName>. Also Lady Renshaw &amp; Madge.</p>
         <p>The weather continues damp, cold, and clouded. I begin to fear for next Sunday's parade.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>