<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Visitation of the Rural Deanery of Lanchester</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 7.50 a.m., and in an hour's time arrived at Consett. At 9 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the parish church. Of the clergy 18 communicated. After breakfast in the Vicarage, I returned to the Church and, after the Litany had been read by the Rural Dean, gave a devotional address to the clergy, who were gathered in the chancel. Then followed the discussion on the Marriage Law, which was held in the Vicarage. We all lunched together in the parish hall. In the afternoon the Vicars of Consett and Leadgate accompanied me on little tour of inspection. They expounded to me the necessity of making fresh provision for the new population (about 3000) which has been brought into their parishes in order to man the new mine. I went into one of the new four&#8211;roomed cottages. It was occupied by 7 persons – a miner, his wife, 4 boys who all worked at the pit, and a daughter The 4 boys occupied 2 double&#8211;beds in one room: the daughter had a room to herself: &amp; the parents used another. The kitchen was the living room. The Vicar of Leadgate showed me the remains of his school, which was burned down. Local belief attributed to arson to Linn Feiners. After tea in the Vicarage, I attended the meeting of the Parochial Church councillors, of whom more than 200 were present. This finished my visitation of the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of the 13 Rural Deans. We returned to Auckland arriving at 10 p. m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>