<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[141]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A young man named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Heselton</hi> came to see me, being sent by Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName> on the chance that I might persuade him to be ordained. <hi rend="bold underline">He is 28 years old, &amp; has taken his degree in the University of Edinburgh. He is at present disposed to become a schoolmaster, but says that from early boyhood he has had the desire to become a clergyman. I pointed out that what we call Divine Vocation can hardly be more surely disclosed than by the combination of desire &amp; opportunity: that in his own case that combination appeared to exist: that the clergyman's career was fuller of spiritual opportunity than the schoolmaster's; finally, that there was a more urgent need for good clergy than fo good teachers. He went away professing his resolve to come to a decision, &amp; to let me know what it was. How far can I rightly urge men to be ordained when no one can say with any certainty whether the Church of England will be recognizable in a few years?</hi></p>
         <p>I "fooled away" the time in clearing up my study, &amp; trying to get my papers into some kind of order. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> was so busily engaged in over&#8211;hauling the car that I could not get him to play bowls. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName></hi> came to see me about a curiously puzzling case of clerical discipline which occurred in the interval between Bishop Moule's death &amp; my coming into residence: but he could throw no fresh light on the subject; &amp; I was left as puzzled as ever respecting my duty.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The object of Reunion is not a theological thing, but rather a practical &amp; devotional one. People in devotion are united together. Things which separate them are the theoretical ones. When we begin to speculate and define the different doctrines, then the disagreement comes. <hi rend="underline">And my fear is that, when the different divines come to agree on all their differences, &amp; bring about Reunion, there will be nobody to unite</hi>. It has been said that the people themselves will compel the different theologians to leave all these subtle speculations &amp; unite the Churches on a more practical &amp; simple basis. But to my disappointment, what I see is quite the opposite. <hi rend="underline">People get tired of all these religious controversies and, instead of being interested, they begin to leave the Church altogether</hi>, &amp; besides there is a strong tendency, especially among progressive people, against organized religion: &amp; the idea that a united Church will do more harm to the world than good is gaining ground, because it is true in many cases, that a strong organized Church very seldom can avoid mingling in politics.</p>
         <p>v. Church Quarterly Review: July, 1923. p. 286.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Article, from which the above is taken, is entitled, "<hi rend="underline">Christian Reunion from the point of view of the Eastern Orthodox Church</hi>". The author is described as 'a graduate of the University of Athens'. His article 'was awarded a B.Litt. degree at Oxford in 1922, &amp; is therefore earlier in date than the recent declaration of the Oecumenical Patriarchate on the subject of Anglican Orders.'</p>
         </body></text></TEI>