<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, whose never failing providence ordereth all things both in heaven and earth: We humbly beseech thee to put away from us all hurtful things, and to give us those things which be profitable for us; through Jesus Christ thy Son our Lord, who liveth &amp; reigneth with thee in the unity of the Holy Ghost, ever one God, world without end.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>I copied this collect from the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> Prayer Book, and only discovered when I read it in the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. that the conclusion had been varied. In the Prayer Book as it now stands, the collect ends without reference to the Persons of the Blessed Trinity. Is this change to be explained by mere carelessness, or by some cryptic design? William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and Charles<persName xml:id="1679"></persName> communicated. The first is in the fullest sense, my 'spiritual son', the last is my godson. The two young men are within a few months of the same age, and both are unusually promising in very different ways. It was a good sight to see them kneeling together at the Lord's Table.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Just a fortnight ago Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> passed away. I find it still difficult to realize that she has gone. And now Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> has gone too. My life is emptying rapidly, &amp; the shadows grow long on my road also.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast William motored me to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wolviston</hi>, where I read the lessons and preached in the poor little mean parish church, which replaced an interesting medieval building about fifty years ago. This is representative of this diocese. <hi rend="bold underline">When the great period of church building set in during the episcopates of Baring &amp; Lightfoot there was a preliminary process of vandalism by which the county was swept clean of its little old churches</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> The congregation was mainly feminine, and hardly filled the little building, which at most could not seat more than 150 people. The population is stated to be as many as 800, mostly engaged in agriculture, &amp; the benefice is worth no less than &#x00A3;869 net. The patrons are the Dean &amp; Chapter. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Martin Brack</hi> has been Rector since 1906. He was at one time Lecturer in Botany at Armstrong College. I lunched with the High Sheriff, <hi rend="doubleunderline">W. R. Webster</hi>, who lives with his parents at Wolviston Hall. Plainly a rich man. After tea, William and I set out again from the Castle. We motored 20 miles to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dinsdale, </hi>4 miles beyond Darlington. There I read the lessons &amp; preached in an interesting little medieval church. After service the Rector, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Greatorex</hi>, showed me the church, &amp; the Elizabethan cup &amp; cover bearing date 1571. The rectory is excessive in size for the petty endowment. We admired the garden, which is extensive &amp; well&#8211;kept, &amp; returned to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>