<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I finished <hi rend="doubleunderline">Morley's</hi><persName xml:id="341"></persName> '<hi rend="underline">Life of Gladstone</hi>'. Certainly my deep&#8211;seated dislike of the G.O.M. was seriously shaken. He was on such a grand scale, that by comparison, all my generation look like pygmies. The weather changed suddenly, becoming cold, blustering, and wet. As evening drew on the temperature rose, &amp; it blew a hurricane.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Winchester's resignation is announced at last.</hi> <hi rend="italic">It was high time. His recent performances both in the House of Bishops and in the National Assembly have been distressing, so obvious in speech &amp; manner were the ravages of senility</hi> ['old age' written above in red]. <hi rend="italic">He was born in Feb. 1844, so that he is far advanced in his 80</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">th</hi> <hi rend="italic"> year. He came on the scene with many advantages, &amp; he made full use of them. He was a resolute Tractarian to start with, &amp; he developed into a thorough&#8211;going "Anglo&#8211;Catholic". He used to the full the influence </hi>['strength' written above in red]<hi rend="italic"> of his family connexions &amp; official position to advance the fortunes of his party. [He possessed the art of dissembling his partisanship by a great appearance of wide&#8211;mindedness: so that though he was one of the narrowest High Churchmen of his time, he passed for one of the most liberal.] His personal influence was powerful, extended, and in some important respects unwholesome. The Archbishop of Canterbury fell under it, &amp; was led far afield from the course natural to a man of his type &amp; tradition. He cultivated youth, &amp; was venerated by the "Life &amp; Liberty" fanaticks </hi>['zealots' written above in red].</p>
         </body></text></TEI>