<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[191]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Aleck, John and I walked into Bath across the fields on high ground which commanded the most glorious view. The weather was brilliant, and the recent rains had given a richness of verdure to the country, more often seen in June than September. We talked incessantly and the subjects of our converse were numerous and varied. In Bath we went at once to the Roman Bath, where M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Taylor, who is in charge of the excavations met us, and conducted us to the scene of his labours. It appears that the Romans had, at some time subsequent to their original erection of the baths, made extensive changes in them, substituting hot air for hot water. Three levels of flooring have been uncovered. We returned to Brockham End for lunch, and afterwards our hostess &amp; the two boys with Miss Lawrence accompanied <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and me to Malmesbury, where we visited the wonderful fragment of the wonderful Abbey church, and had tea very comfortably in the Hotel adjoining the Churchyard We got back to Brockham End about 7p.m. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The paper reports that Italy, disregarding the Greek appeal to the League of Nations, has seized Corfu.</hi> Thus the situation is developing most untowardly. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi> is a bull in the diplomatic tea&#8211;shop. <hi rend="bold underline">The Latin nations are intolerable in victory, and abject in defeat.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>