<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The heat increases. A record 90<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi> in the shade if reported today. <hi rend="bold underline">Letters from Birchington gave the worst account of poor Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> condition. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to Camberwell to visit the Institution into which the poor girl is to be sent</hi>, and I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> to write my letters. I spent the morning in the Club: then lunched there pleasantly with Gamble and Bernard. I walked to Westminster, and attended Evensong in the Abbey Church. After service I had tea with Vernon Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName> &amp; his wife. I returned to the Club, and there had an interview with an Ordination Candidate. Then I walked back to the Deanery where a dinner party had been arranged. Lady Boyce, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Gaskell, Sir James Masterton Smith, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Macnaughten came to dine. Sir Frederick &amp; Lady Maurice had been invited, but failed to turn up. We had much interesting conversation. Sir J. M. Smith gave a circumstantial account of the circumstances in which Asquith left, or was driven out of office in 1916, and the deadly feud with Lloyd George began. <hi rend="bold underline">He defended Winston Churchill<persName xml:id="2441"></persName> energetically against the accusation of having effected his own escape at the cost of his friends during the Boer War. On the whole I think he made out his case.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Gaskell talked in a bright, intelligent way as became one who had been a "soul".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>