<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m. The candidates &amp; chaplains communicated. After breakfast I finished my "charge". In the afternoon I had a long talk with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. He is certainly making an impression on Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, which has been much neglected under the last 4 Rectors, all of whom were old men, past work when they were appointed.</p>
         <p>I received the news that Smith, the Vicar of Muggleswick, had died of pneumonia. This is sudden. He presented candidates for confirmation on</p>
         <p>I went into Durham, and presided over the legal business in the Chapter House, prefacing the action of the Ordinandi by a few words about the gravity &amp; significance of the pledges they were taking. Then I walked in the Banks with Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, and dined with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>.</p>
         <p>At 8.30 p.m. the candidates and chaplains gathered in the Deanery Chapel, and I delivered the "charge". It sounded very severe and melancholy; but try as I may to be anything else, I cannot escape these notes of sternness and foreboding. After this, Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I motored back to Auckland, and Cruickshank remained in Durham.</p>
         <p>We were back in the Castle by 10 p.m., and there played cards with the ladies before going to bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>