<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The heat last night was very exhausting. This morning the sky is overcast, &amp; there is a feeling of thunder. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; received the Holy Communion together. Canon Simpson as the Celebrant, &amp; the service was actually that provided in the Prayer Book, reverently but rather rapidly read. The Communicants were mostly of the female sex.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After breakfast a telegram from Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> arrived. It ran thus:</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">'Removal now impossible serious change during night Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> passing away, still unconscious.'</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>We tried to telegraph that, unless sent for, we would arrive tomorrow. But no telegram could be sent. It seemed difficult to justify cancelling public engagements, &amp; there was obviously nothing we could do if we did get to Birchington today.</p>
         <p>I preached in the Temple Church repeating the sermon which I preached in York Minster last Sunday. There was a large &amp; attentive congregation. The service was curiously congruous with my thoughts. One of the psalms was the funeral psalm, number 39: and the lesson was David's lament over Jonathon: the anthem was "Justorum Animoe in mann Dei sunt": &amp; after the service the "Dead March" in 'Saul' was played. This was with reference to the death of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maurice Hewlett</hi> who was a member of one of the Inns. We lunched at the Inner Temple. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Banks presided. Darling was there, &amp; very pleasant.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi></p>
         <p>I had some talk with Banks about the Church in Wales, expressing my surprise that so 'advanced' a Churchman as the Bishop of Monmouth should be appointed to a bishoprick. He said that if it had been known that he was as "advanced" as he had shown himself to be, he would certainly <hi rend="doubleunderline">not</hi> have been elected! There was an Anglo–Catholick lawyer, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hensoll</hi>, in the company. He is chancellor of several dioceses. He has the shifty evasive look so commonly noticeable in the eyes of men who practice confession. I didn't take to him. <hi rend="bold underline">Later, I preached in S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Pauls Cathedral</hi> to a very large congregation, though not so large as might normally have been expected. My subject was "Truthfulness"; I connected my argument with Prayer Book Revision. It was a serious effort to cleanse the Church of England from the taint of insincerity. There came to supper the Headmaster of Westminster &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Costley White.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">(It is, indeed, difficult to realize that Marion has gone. She was so quiet, so unselfish, she devoted that we "took her for granted", &amp; probably did not realize the extent to which she was over–straining her physical strength. I cannot recall any lives more entirely surrendered to the claims of others than those of my two sisters. Jennie's<persName xml:id="84"></persName> death in 1896 left an incurable wound on my heart: &amp; now poor Marion's death in 1923 renews the anguish in a more poignant form. The shadows are deepening: it cannot be long before the call comes to me also.)</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>