<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>There was a mighty Thunderstorm during the night. From 11.30p.m. to 5.30a.m. the thunder rattled, crashed &amp; roared incessantly while the rain fell in torrents. It is described in the newspapers as the most violent storm in living memory. No lives appear to have been lost, but several houses were struck. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Russell's house, near London, was struck &amp; burned to the ground. In some metropolitan districts the rainfall exceeded 2 inches.</p>
         <p>I spent the day in attending the National Assembly, where I certainly did myself no credit by speaking twice, first to resist a silly objection to paying the clerks no more than the market rate of wage: next, to explain why the diocese of Durham is not likely to pay its quota to the Central Finances Board. The Archbishop was moved to make a sharp reply! I lunched at the House of Lords. For the "Committee Stage" of the two considerable measures dealing with Union of Benefices and Dilapidations, the Archbishop very sensibly delegated his chairmanship to Lawrence Hardy and Ld. Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName>, to the great quickening of our pace! The attendance of members was no doubt affected by the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Conference which began today.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I dined quietly together at the Deanery. We were to have dined with Lady Struthers, but we thought it decent to cancel the engagement. The great heat continues.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>