<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the morning in writing a long letter to the 'Times' on Prayer Book Revision</hi>. In this I emphasized the fact that <hi rend="underline">only</hi> as the first step in the Restoration of Discipline was P. B. Revision worth attempting. I also took occasion to call attention to the smallness of electoral rolls in London, &amp; suggested that it seemed to indicate that "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" alienated rather than attracted the people.</p>
         <p>Wright from S. Francis came to see me. He was in a highly excited &amp; fanatical state, spoke of going to the tropics to save souls, and delivered seething like a denunciation of me &amp; my ways! I gather that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Warner</hi> is an ignorant &amp; tactless jack&#8211;ass, who tries to shelter himself by making free use of my name!</p>
         <p>The mason who was giving the finishing touches to the "dilapidations" of the containing wall round the bowling green, is a "comfortable prophet". He assures me that 'if I live another hundred years, the bulging wall will yet be standing". But <hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&#x00F6;e</hi><persName xml:id="648"></persName>, a more authoritative seer, said that it might fall any day now!</p>
         <p>I returned to old <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi> <hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"> Eade</hi> the very interesting account of Aycliffe Church, which he lent me on Sunday. Apparently the proper pronunciation of the name is Jackley i.e. <hi rend="underline">locus guercorum</hi>, the place of oaks. This explains the acorns and oakleaves [sic] which are carved on the remarkable priest's tomb&#8211;stone, now preserved in the church. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>