<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Visitation of the Darlington Rural Deanery</hi></p>
         <p>A bright deceiving morning led in a wet &amp; blustering day. <hi rend="bold underline">William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington in time for the Celebration in S. Cuthbert's at 8.30a.m.</hi> We breakfasted in a little cafe︠ not far from the Church. At 10.30 a.m. we returned to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's, where the Rural Dean read the Litany, and I addressed the clergy "devotionally". Then, through a deluge, we went to an Institute, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; I addressed them on the Reform of the Marriage Law. They were interested but, did not say much: the Evangelicals through sheer ignorance of the whole subject; the "Catholicks" through fear of committing themselves!</hi> Then I lunched with a retired engineer named, I think, Storr, who was pleasant enough. After lunch I went to the Training College, &amp; distributed prizes to the students. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Pease</hi><persName xml:id="5262"></persName> presided. After tea at the college I went to a house in S. Matthew's parish &amp; confirmed a young woman bedridden. <hi rend="bold underline">Finally, I addressed a large meeting of parish church councillors on the subject of Prayer Book Revision. They were attentive, and, I think, interested but they were not very eager to ask questions. The whole subject is new to them; they do not see why change I needed: nor have they any knowledge of the disorders which loom so large in the ecclesiastical life of the south. The mere notion of enforcing law on disobedient clergymen is alarming &amp; repugnant: They are easily swept away by any irrelevant maundering about "charity"etc , while all the time they are extremely hostile to the illegalities themselves.</hi> We returned to Auckland after the service, arriving about 9.30 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>