<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shebbeares</hi><persName xml:id="5363"></persName> and the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inges</hi><persName xml:id="427"><persName xml:id="1209"></persName></persName> went with <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi> to Stanhope, while <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I made our way to Durham for the Lay Readers' Festival. I gave commission to a number of laymen, among whom was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi>. Then I addressed them, dwelling most on the importance of keeping up the practice of reading. After tea with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Quirks</hi><persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, I presided at a Conference of the Lay Readers at which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Storach</hi> introduced the subject of "Work with Lads". We returned to Auckland by train. The Evening Paper reports <hi rend="underline">the death of the Bishop of Chelmsford</hi>. He had undergone an operation which was reported to have been successful, but evidently the strain was too severe.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watts Ditchfied</hi> was a man of considerable natural ability, unusual power of work, little education and great ambition. He thrust himself into matters which he did not understand, and deserted the partisan high road which he knew well. Like the Bishop of Peterborough he was much flattered by the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, whom he served well while professing to condemn their characteristic methods &amp; doctrines. He and I had some correspondence over the effort to reform the Courts, and we combined in the House of Bishops. He moved the resolution which I had drafted, &amp; which I seconded. It was carried with a slight modification.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>