<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a letter for the Diocesan Gazette in which among other things I dealt with the subject of <hi rend="bold underline">glass globes in churchyards, and the ventilation of churches</hi>. Brereton, the Headmaster of the North&#8211;Eastern Counties School, came to lunch. He expounded to me the grievance which he felt at having his son summarily rejected for the chemistry mastership! I pointed out that he was strategically at some disadvantage since nepotism was not unknown in the educational world! When he had departed, I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; was again beaten badly. In this sphere, Youth is irresistible. After tea, I wrote letters.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">M</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Connell, the daughter of Bishop Montagu Villiers, arrived on a visit – an intelligent &amp; indeed vivacious old lady of fourscore. She said that on one occasion, when her father was confirming, a female candidate was unable to leave the pew, being immobilized by her crinoline, which she herself had manufactured with the iron hoop of a beer&#8211;barrel!</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi> <hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">C. herself had assisted in extricating the candidate</hi> <hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">She said that the miners were a rough people who threw half&#8211;bricks at her as she rode through their villages. The late bishop's godson, </hi>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Handley Gear</hi> <hi rend="italic">, &amp; his wife arrived. He gained the V.C. during the War, &amp; impressed me as an attractive &amp; modest young fellow</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>