<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather became fine and warm. After breakfast, Cranford walked with me to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. There I dealt with such letters as had come for me, and then walked to Westminster, and called on Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>, with whom I had much talk, &amp; had luncheon. He confirms the story which Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> told me last night on excellent authority, that when M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bonar Law's government was established in power of the General Election, Lord Rothermere called on him, &amp; offered the support of his numerous newspapers. The Prime Minister made a civil acknowledgement, &amp; said that undoubtedly such support would be valuable. 'It is best not to beat about the bush', said his Lordship. 'In plain language, I want an Earldom &amp; a seat in the Cabinet.' M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bonar Law turned him out of the house, &amp; as he left, he shouted threats of mischief which his press would henceforth inflict on the new government! Now, as the admirable M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Tom Creevey would have observed, Did you ever? <hi rend="bold underline">I called on Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> in the Roedium Home, &amp; found her very cheerful, &amp; looking wonderfully well</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Then I returned to the Athenaeum, &amp; wrote more letters. Finally, I walked back to the Deanery, &amp; dined with my friends.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>