<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk took me on to the Lake for an hour before I took my departure. Nothing could be more restful than the placid lake fringed with autumnal woods. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I Ieft Lake End about 10.45 a.m., and <hi rend="bold underline">motored to Bishop Auckland where we arrived a few minutes after 4 p.m.</hi> The whole journey lay through very beautiful scenery: the weather was perfect: we were on the friendliest terms with one another. I cannot recall a more enjoyable day. We lunched comfortably at the George Inn, at Penrith. The distance was 103 miles. <hi rend="bold underline">In four days we have travelled no less than 541 miles</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Last Saturday the most destructive earthquake known to human history took place in Japan. Tokio [sic] and Yokohama, cities with populations respectively of 2,000,000 and 500,000 were destroyed, and vast numbers of the people perished. The estimates of the number killed vary from 600,000 to 250,000. It is impossible not to speculate on the political effects of this unprecedented catastrophe. Japan has for the time being fallen out of the number of "Great Powers". <hi rend="bold underline">Will it be still thought necessary for us to construct the naval base at Singapore? The fears of Australia will for awhile be laid to sleep: and the United States will be free from the nightmare of a Japanese invasion.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>