<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; thence to Westminster. The proceedings in the House of Bishops were uncommon dull. Mostly his Grace of Canterbury held forth at immense length on the dullest of subjects &#8211; the Colonial Clergy Ordination Act. I came away in time to meet Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> &amp; Ellie<persName xml:id="3192"></persName> at Paddington at 1.30p.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me on the platform. <hi rend="bold underline">She had seen D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Wakeford Pinch at the Radium Institute and had received a re&#8211;assuring report about Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>.</hi> We went together to Victoria Station, &amp; there lunched. I returned to Westminster only to find that the House had risen. I then went over to the House of Lords, and wrote my letters. Bristol, Oxford, and Norwich were there, &amp; I had some talk with them. I went to the Athenaeum, &amp; dined with Bernard, as my table&#8211;mate. He thinks that "it is yet too soon to say" whether the Free Hate will "make good". The most formidable rock is the financial deficit which the great destruction of property has made alarmingly great: but the farmers are prosperous.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Athelstan Riley</hi><persName xml:id="213"></persName> came up to us, rubbing his hands with delight at having "defeated the women" in the House of Laity by retaining "obey" in the Marriage Service<hi rend="bold underline">, and at having secured the insertion in the Calendar of the feasts of "S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Joseph" and the Assumption of B.V.M.!</hi> Bernard emitted an expression of contempt both at the childish exultation, and at its course!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>