<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>A party organ, suppressing some facts, misrepresenting others, is the worst of all guides, because it can by incessantly reiterating untruth produce a greater impression than any man or body of men, save only ecclesiastics clothed with a spiritual authority, could produce before printing was invented.</p>
         <p>Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName>. Mod. Dem. i. 82</p>
         </div>
         <p>Apply this to the case of young "Anglo&#8211;Catholics" who devour the '<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>', &amp; see the Bishop of Durham in the light of its venomous belittlement &amp; misrepresentation. I cannot doubt that the injury inflicted is both considerable and irreparable. Even if the victim attempt to correct the falsehood or remove the false impression, his correction can only appear after the mischief has been done, &amp; if it secure any attention at all, it will hardly gain credit from those who have accepted and circulated the falsehood. The only reasonable &amp; the only self&#8211;respecting course is to ignore these wretched journals in the hope that they will overreach themselves. "<hi rend="underline">Magna est veritas et proevalebit</hi>." That is probably true in the long run, but in the haste &amp; hustle of the modern world nobody has time or mind to wait for the slow reflections of experience!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>