<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[186]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather was detestable from early dawn until fall of night. Deluges of rain were punctuated by brief intervals of sunshine, and accompanied by a violent wind. We left Wonham Hall about 11am, and motored to Maidenhead, where we lunched with Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> and Ellie<persName xml:id="3192"></persName> In their new house, Hillbury. It is pleasantly placed, commodious and set in a fair garden of about an acre's extent. A little before 3p.m. we resumed our journey and motored by way of Bridgewater to Glastonbury, where we had tea in "The Pilgrims Inn", a medieval building, and looked at the relics of the famous monastery. We went on at 5.30.p.m. and arrived at Brockham End, by way of Wells and Bath, at 7p.m. A violent deluge marked our arrival, and a hurricane of wind. We were kindly received by Nan Lawrence (Aleck was absent) Miss Lawrence, an elderly lady, whom I have not identified, Miss Dickenson, and the two boys John and George.</p>
         <p>Motoring for pleasure is too dependent on fine weather to be altogether satisfactory. No measure of cheerful optimism could pretend that out drive from Wonham Hall to Brockham End was pleasurable. The limitations of small "touring car" are not to be concealed when the weather is hostile, for the hapless pleasure seeker is driven to an evil choice between being asphyxiated in a closed car, or saturated in an open one. We adopted a middle course and enjoyed a measure of both discomfort, being partly stifled, and partly soaked.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>