<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I travelled to Belfast by the Stranraer to Larne route, and were so fortunate as to have a calm passage. We arrived at Belfast at 9.30 a.m. and were met by a car, &amp; driven to Mountstewart. Rain fell persistently, so we sate indoors. Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Filson Young, and I talked politics hard until lunch–time. We discussed the Education Bill which, as Minister of Education, Lord L. has introduced into the Northern Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> It leaves religious teaching to the Churches. The problem is less complicated in Ulster than in England, but I doubt <hi rend="underline">this </hi>solution. There is a guard on this house, but its necessity is questioned.</p>
         <p>Lord Plunket &amp; his wife – pleasant young people, &amp; apparently fond of one another – are here, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Tweed, the sculptor. There are others, whom I am slowly making out.</p>
         <p>After tea, I wrote to Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, and – at some length – to the editor of the Guardian, on the subject of the failure in the supply of Ordination candidates.</p>
         <p>The conversation turns repeatedly on Prohibition, etc., of course. I must needs profess my detestation of it. But this places me, or seems to place me, in accord with the "Drink Interest", which is, on many grounds, not a creditable thing. Lord L. is himself somewhat inclined to "Pussy–foot" views, &amp; it is odd that he sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> find himself therein opposed to his bishop!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>