<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Ritualism is too strong to be 'put down'; a serious attempt to do so would simply shatter the church. On the other hand, it is odious to the majority of Churchmen, partly from habit, partly from dogmatic objection. The time is passed by when it was possible to conciliate these rival bodies of opinion. If a fatal collision is to be avoided, the only thing to be done is to get them into different buildings."</p>
         <p>L<hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi>Salisbury to Abp. Tait. Feb. 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1881. (ii. 449)</p>
         </div>
         <p>Forty&#8211;two years have passed since these words were written, &amp; they could hardly be improved upon. The Church of England is hopelessly divided, &amp; its distinctive witness in Christendom has ceased.</p>
         <p>I re&#8211;cast a sermon on "Truthfulness", and added a few pages of reference to Prayer Book Revision; and decided to make shift with this for S. Paul's on July 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>Davison came to talk over my proposal that he should go to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, West Auckland. He seems rather disinclined to move, &amp;, indeed, he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> hardly gain financially by doing so, as his present benefice is worth nearly &#x00A3;600 per annum: &amp;, though S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's is worth about &#x00A3;640, he ought to pay a curate out of his income.</p>
         <p>The weather today has been delightful. Laws started to water the flower&#8211;beds – a performance which was almost startling in its assumption of summer conditions!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>