<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather has changed for the worse, &amp; rain is falling. In the streets the decorations for the Royal Wedding have a bedraggled and almost silly appearance. I wrote letters in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> until lunch&#8211;time. After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi> <hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Buckmaster</hi><persName xml:id="3687"></persName> laid hold of me in the smoking room, &amp; talked in a friendly fashion for an hour. He is not intending to amend the Divorce Bill, equalizing the sexes, which will come up from the H. of Commons, but will reintroduce his own Bill.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colin Kennedy</hi><persName xml:id="2432"></persName> came at 5 p.m. He is growing, or rather has grown, into a solid&#8211;looking man with a weather&#8211;beaten aspect. He now contemplates starting as an architect 'on his own'. He is just 30, has no immediate intention of marrying, &amp; has the world before him. He walked with me to Victoria Street, where I visited <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName>. I dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers</hi> at 31 Sloane Street. They have just returned from India, and are full of their experiences. The dinner party consisted of Lord &amp; Lady Emmott, an American lady, a civil servant, Fleming, &amp; myself. We had much interesting talk, but nothing worth remembering was spoken, &amp; certainly nothing was remembered.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A short letter, which I wrote to the '</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi> <hi rend="italic">' yesterday, appeared in that journal this morning. It reads cogently, &amp;, I think, 'takes the wind out of the sails' of the Bishop of S</hi> <hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Alban's.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>