<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923. </hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I entertain the strongest dislike to the Permissive Bill ('Local Option'). I cannot perhaps, express it in a stronger form than by saying that, <hi rend="underline">if I must take my choice,</hi> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; &amp; such it seems to me is really the alternative offered by the Permissive Bill &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; whether England should be free of sober, <hi rend="bold underline">I declare, strange as such a declaration may sound coming from one of my profession, that I should say it would be better that England should be free than that England should be </hi> <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">compulsorily</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> sober. I would distinctly prefer freedom to sobriety, because with freedom we might in the end attain sobriety: but in the other alternative we should eventually lose both freedom &amp; sobriety.</hi> But, though I am strongly opposed to the Permissive Bill, I do wish that the ratepayers oh? [sic] have some voice &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; not an absolute &amp; sole voice, but some voice &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; in the regulation of the liquor traffic.</p>
         <p>Magea [sic] ( 'Life'. vol. II. p. 43) in 1872. </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103] </hi></p>
         <p>We left the Castle, &amp; motored to Darlington where we caught the early train to York. After having our bags at the Deanery, we proceeded to the school, where I distributed prizes &amp; made a speech. S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's School claims to be the oldest school in the country: the claim is not undisputed, but it is strongly supported by a history which can be plausibly carried back to the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. It is now a flourishing institution in which about 300 boys, of whom four&#8211;fifths are boarders, are successfully educated. After lunching with Coyne, the Headmaster, we returned to the Deanery. Later in the afternoon, the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> took me, and Judge Head into the Minster, and there explained to us in a most interesting manners, the method of dealing with the painted windows, which are being taken out, cleaned, restored, and reloaded. The process is most difficult &amp; delicate: but the result is wonderful. <hi rend="bold underline">There are now four altars in York Minster; and everyone has been appropriated to some specific use. I could not but express a certain uneasiness at this multiplication of altars, which really can only be justified on a view of the Holy Communion which is certainly not that expressed in the standards of the Church of England. These great medieval buildings are a continuing influence hostile to the Reformation, which defaced them, and has very little use for them. They are winning the battle in which they had seemed to perish</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>