<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury informs me that the Bishop of Chelmsford "will gladly propose the Resolution in the form you have suggested". I wrote to the Bishop of Ripon telling him how matters now stood</hi>.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Sunderland, and baptized the infant son of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Silva White in S. Peter's Church. Then I returned to Durham, &amp; had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. After this, I had an interview with J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, then returned home.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>: and to Albert Saxton<persName xml:id="222"></persName>. Also I wrote to Poole offering him the honorary canonry vacated by Canon Martin's death: to Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName>, explaining why I could not give preferment to Poole: and to S. Short of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, Auckland, offering him the vacant benefice of Kelloe.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">It appears to me advisable to make as little delay as possible in appointing to vacant livings: A lengthened vacancy gives opportunity for much greedy speculation &amp; not a little unworthy wire&#8211;pulling. Some clergy are embittered by disappointment: many are damaged by envy: some cherish a resentment, none the less injurious for being wholly unreasonable. All these mischiefs are reduced by rapidity in making appointments. On the other hand, of course, must be set the disadvantages which attach to all prompt action. One sometimes loses the best man by not thinking of him soon enough</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>