<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[235]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Lord God. Whose inscrutable wisdom hast ordained that Thy Hoy Purpose in the World should be served by sinful men, look with compassion on Thy servants, who bear the yoke of ministry in Thy church, and save them from their sins, giving them power and joy in Thy service, and grace to live as befitteth. Thy servant, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8.15 a.m. All the guests attended &amp; communicated except <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Wolmer</hi><persName xml:id="1028"></persName>. After breakfast the Commission sate in the small dining room from 10a.m to 1p.m.: In the afternoon, some of the party were motored into Durham to see the Cathedral, others were led by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to Escomb to see the Anglo&#8211;Saxon Church: the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> and I played bowls at home. We all met at tea: and then the Commission resumed its session from 5p.m. to 7.30p.m. At 8p.m. we dined.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Morley's</hi><persName xml:id="341"></persName> death, reported in yesterday's newspapers, misses the question, whether he could be fittingly interested in the Abbey, or elsewhere with Christian rites. He was confessedly an Agnostic, if not definitely an Atheist: he has exposed himself in severe criticism on those who, having abandoned the doctrines of Christianity, do yet allow themselves to be buried as Christians, &amp; even leave directions for such burial in their wills.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>