<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation in the Abbey Church at Mattins when I preached a sermon from the words:&#8211; "<hi rend="underline">Why is my liberty judged by another conscience</hi>? – I took occasion to speak frankly about Prayer Book Revision. Somebody must have carried a report of the <hi rend="bold underline">sermon to the Archbishop, for he rang me up on the telephone, and asked me to see him</hi> <hi rend="bold">.</hi> Accordingly I called at Lambeth at 4.30 p.m: and talked with his Grace for an hour &amp; a half in his bedroom, for he was supposed to have a touch of influenza, &amp; had gone to bed. He expressed agreement with my general attitude, &amp; pressed me on the necessity of a constructive attitude. He was constantly defending me against those who urged that I was merely destructive. He gave me the impression of being greatly perplexed. I attended Evensong in the Abbey Church, &amp; heard a conventional sermon from a Canadian clergyman. In the course of the afternoon, I called on Lady Craik<persName xml:id="793"></persName>, and had a brief interview with her. <hi rend="bold underline">She said that Sir Henry<persName xml:id="344"></persName> had been in the Abbey Church in the morning, &amp; had brought back a "glowing" account of my sermon. On the other hand, the Dean was certainly not ardent, and Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> said that he could not hear what I said</hi> <hi rend="bold">!!</hi></p>
         <p>I had much talk with Charles &amp; his wife. Relations with the Minor Canons are evidently very strained, &amp; the Dean is thought to be unduly influenced by them.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>