<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, Thursday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant, we beseech thee, Almighty God, that like as we do believe thy only –begotten Son, our Lord Jesus Christ to have ascended into the heavens; so we may also in heart and mind thither ascend, and with him continually dwell, who liveth and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghost, one God, world without end. </p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This Collect is from the Sacramentum Gregorianum.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We mustered as many as 10 communicants, &amp; among them William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and John.</p>
         <p>The whole morning was frittered away in writing letters. One to the Bishop of Chelmsford bore on the practical question of episcopal procedures when the National Assembly meets in July. Another, to Canon Glazebrook, stated my reasons for declining to associate myself with the 'Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName>' in the matter of the Courts. I coped these two letters into my Register. </p>
         <p>Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> came to lunch, but I had hardly any converse with him as I had to get away to Durham for Evensong in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and her Swiss friend accompanied me. After service we all tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, with whom was Miss Headlam. Then we returned to Auckland. The weather continued to be extremely cold. Last night there were hail&#8211;storms, and today the wind is bitter. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>