<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">Almighty and everlasting God, who art always more ready to hear than we to pray, and art wont to give more than either we desire, or deserve; Pour down upon us the abundance of thy mercy; forgiving us those things whereof our conscience is afraid, and giving us those good things which we are not worthy to ask, but through the merits and mediation of Jesus Christ, thy Son, our Lord.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Amen</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>We attended the morning service in S. Chad's Church – mattins to the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> collect, and Holy Communion with sermon. Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> read the lessons admirably, and the Vicar (Salisbury) preached. The sermon from the text "<hi rend="underline">I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life</hi>", was a thin extemporaneous performance, but, rather to my surprise, it seemed to please my host &amp; hostess. Certainly if the laity are satisfied with that kind of oration, the clergy will provide nothing better.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">I wrote to Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>. It was a difficult and painful task. Before sealing the letter, I showed it to Dorothea<persName xml:id="2768"></persName> &amp; Godfrey, and at their suggestion made an emendation</hi>. Also, I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. The evening passed into the unedifying type of conversation to which mixed society is commonly condemned, and in which a Bishop can only discredit himself. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>