<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>After the confirmation in Stanhope Church I stopped at a book&#8211;stall set near the door, on which placed a number of tracts. The first I noticed was on 'Confession' b A. V. Magee: the next, one on "Reunion" by the same author. "I should hardly have expected to find this literature in Butler's church" was my comment to the Rector, who was of course, serenely unconscious that the most pronounced "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" was being offered to his parishioners in the parish church! The incident was significant. These complaisant "Liberals" are the best, because the least deliberate, allies of obscurantism.</p>
         <p>There were but 20 candidates from the two parishes of Stanhope and Muggleswick: and of these only 4 were males. Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> is, I fear, more interested in his study of Hegal's philosophy than in the preparation of candidates for confirmation! </p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed 109 candidates in S. Paul's Church. Everything pleased me. After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> brought one of the Sedberge boys, named Noad, to see the Castle, and to stay the night. He seemed a pleasant lad, but he was handicapped by a waxing bilious attack, which sent him to bed.</p>
         <p>The weather became astonishingly cold. This morning a white frost lay on the ground, and at Stanhope about midday there was a smart hail&#8211;storm.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>