<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The post brought me several letters about the Articles in the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi>, from which I learned that the said articles had been reproduced in the <hi rend="underline">Newcastle Daily Journal</hi>. One letter from a Papist named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard Berlyn</hi> was interesting, as it disclosed the deep contempt with which the Anglo&#8211;Catholics are regarded by the Romans. </p>
         <p>I spent the whole morning in writing letters. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> took Charles &amp; his wife into Durham. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went with me to Middleton–on&#8211;Tees, where I instituted Perrott to the Rectory. There was a considerable congregation, &amp; I hope that a good start was made. The new Rector's father was present together with several other clergymen. Before the service I called on the old schoolmaster, who for fifty years played the organ in the church, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Oddie. He is now more than 90 years of age, &amp; visibly nears his end, but he is still intelligent &amp; interested in parochial affairs. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi>" announces that the Bishop of Zanzibar is to answer my articles in its columns. This, on the whole, is satisfactory as he certainly has much to explain. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Albert Saxton</hi><persName xml:id="222"></persName> sent me a cutting from the "<hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>". It was an article by 'Artifex' (= Canon Peter Green<persName xml:id="540"></persName>) entitled "The Bishop of Zanzibar &amp; the Telegram", and is expressed with much vigour &amp; even bitterness.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>