<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923. </hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">Where things have been instituted, which being convenient and good at the first, do afterwards in process of time wax otherwise; we make no doubt but they may be altered, yea, though councils or customs general have received them. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">… For there is not any positive law of men, whether it be general or particular; received by formal express consent, as in councils, or by secret approbation, as in customs it cometh to pass; but the same may be taken away if occasion serve. Even as we all know, that many things generally keep heretofore are now in like sort generally unkept &amp; abolished everywhere.</hi></p>
         <p> Hooker. Eccl. Pol: IV. xiv (.I. G14) </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hooker</hi> is justifying the Elizabethan settlement, &amp; assumes the right of the national authority to be the power by which such departures from established procedure are authorized &amp; carried out. The fact that the settlement had stood so long, some 40 years ago, showed, </p>
         <p>'that God would at leastwise by tract of time teach the world, that the thing which he blesseth, defendeth, keepeth so strongly, cannot choose but be of him?' </p>
         <p>This argument proved something like a boomerang in the disastrous period 1640 – 1660.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Right Hon: Thomas Ferens</hi> came to lunch. He has attained to wealth and prominence in Hull, but he retains a loyal attachment to Bishop Auckland where he was brought up. He told me that from the time when he was a clerk working in an office, he had followed the rule of devoting one tenth of his income to good work; that since he had become a wealthy man, he had devoted the whole of his profit: and now that he was drawing to his end, he was disposing of much of his capital in the same way. This is very excellent: of course he is not an Anglican, but some kind of Methodist! </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> arrived to shepherd the Ordination candidates, and then came the candidates themselves. There are but seven all told, 2 priests, and 5 deacons. Of the latter all but 4 hail from Knutsford. It would seem that the normal sources provide now hardly any candidates at all. </p>
         <p>After dinner I examined Laudreth, one of the deacons, in Hooker. He had evidently read the whole of the Ecclesiastical Polity, and done so intelligently. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi> had much talk with me before going to bed. He gives a woeful account of the clergy in his rural deanery. All of them are dispirited: most of them are ignorant &amp; idle: few of them are intelligent or capable of learning. Their influence on the population is almost negligible. Religion is at a very low ebb in the whole district, and the churches are empty.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>