<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Would you write reasoned article or even two articles of fifteen hundred words each on late Anglo&#8211;Catholic Congress? please wire reply.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gwynne.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Editor, Morning Post</hi>".</p>
         </div>
         <p>This telegram was brought to me as I sate at dinner with the Rural Deans, and I wired that I would write two articles!</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName> and Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> went off this morning to Lumley to spend the night with the Scarboroughs<persName xml:id="3465"><persName xml:id="3466"></persName></persName>, &amp; then get on to Cloan.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon the Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans arrived for the annual conference</hi>. After tea we gathered in the library, and Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> introduced the subject of Sunday Schools. He submitted the proof of a <hi rend="underline">quaestionnaire</hi> which should be sent to the clergy, &amp; this we adopted with some slight amendments. After dinner I took Cosgrave to my room, &amp; offered him the living of Whitburn, which, however, he declined on the ground that the house was too large and the climate too severe. This is the second refusal of that living. After Evensong I had some talk with Knight.</p>
         <p>I gave a signed photograph of myself to Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>. The weather continues to be fine, but the great heat is happily replaced by a fresh atmosphere, in which one can breathe &amp; move. Old Sir Henry Howarth is reported to have died yesterday. He was a powerful amateur in many fields, and an indefatigable raconteur.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>