<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Before going to breakfast I wrote to Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> briefly and sternly. He seems to think that he can impose on me without limit: but I am not willing that he should remain for an hour under the delusion that his present conduct can be condoned.</hi></p>
         <p>We left Cuddesdon a few minutes after 10 a.m. and motored to Bampton in Devonshire, a distance of 156 miles. We arrived at 7.30 p.m. having expended 2 1/2 hours in divers delays. We <hi rend="bold underline">lunched at Bulford with General &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline"> Oldfield. There was another officer, Holland, at lunch. I was interested to notice that both these able and experienced soldiers were quite vehemently opposed to the French.</hi> Our route lay through Salisbury Plain and the Wiltshire downs: the roads were excellent, and the country mostly pastured with sheep, but with much arable land intermixed with the grass. There must be a very small population. We passed lose to Stonehenge, and gained a good view of the enigmatick and world famous stones. <hi rend="bold underline">We were hospitably welcomed by M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline"> Buchanan at Wonham, Bampton. There were staying in the house Commander and M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline"> Paget, Miss Luttrell, and Sir Thomas Holderness. Here again I observed that the opinion of the company was unanimously opposed to France. There is significance in the change which has come over the public mind in this connexion.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>