<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, the protector of all that trust in thee, without whom nothing is strong, nothing is holy; Increase and multiply upon us thy mercy; that, thou being our ruler and guide, we may so pass through things temporal, that we finally lose not the things eternal: Grant this, O heavenly Father, for Jesus Christ's sake our Lord.	</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This collect is from the Sarum Use. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. At 9.15 a.m. I left the Castle, &amp; motored to Forest (31 miles) and at 10.45 a.m. preached at Mattins to a little congregation of about 60 rusticks. After lunching with the Vicar, Randle, I went on to Harwood, where I preached to a little company of about 30 people. This is a chapelry of Forest, &amp; is quite alone in the bosom of the hills. I motored over the ridge (c.2000 ft.) which separates Teesdale from Weardale – a difficult road which put William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; the car to a fairly severe test, which <hi rend="doubleunderline">both</hi> stood triumphantly – and after tea with Canon Croudace preached in Eastgate Church to a congregation which by no means filled the little church. After service we returned to Auckland arriving at 9.45 p.m. We had traversed exactly 68 1/2 miles in the course of the day. The weather was fairly fine, but there was a wet mist on the higher hills, &amp; much wind.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>