<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather continues bitterly cold. I spent the morning in preparing a speech for use later. Then I motored to Durham, &amp; lunched at the Castle with Pemberton<persName xml:id="2837"></persName> to meet Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>. After lunch, the formal 'placing of the commemoration stone' of the new Science building took place. There was a considerable gathering of the University. <hi rend="bold underline">Pemberton presided &amp; I made a speech before calling on the Chancellor to place the stone</hi>. When this ceremony had been performed by Lord D. &amp; a vote of thanks to him duly passed, the company went to the Castle where tea was provided in the Hall. I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, &amp; discussed with him several diocesan matters. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I dined at the Castle. Finally I attended a meeting of the D.J.C.C.H. and made a short speech introducing <hi rend="doubleunderline">D. Lowther Clarke</hi>, who addressed the students at some length. He said nothing that was noteworthy &amp; indeed gave the impression that he had fallen into his anecdotage. Then we returned to Auckland. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, to my distress, coughed continuously all the way home.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> wrote to say that she had visited a specialist; that he reported on the whole favourably, that she would probably have to renew the radium treatment in about four weeks, &amp; that she was relieved &amp; re&#8211;assured by his report. I trust she is not mistaken</hi> <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>