<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I celebrated the Holy Communion in Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> room. Everything was very devout &amp; comforting</hi>. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, where I licensed two curates, lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, and had a business conference with the two archdeacons<persName xml:id="2785"><persName xml:id="3688"></persName></persName>. We returned to Auckland for tea.</p>
         <p>The publisher sends me a short story by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hall Caine</hi>, "<hi rend="underline">The Woman of Knockaloe</hi>", which he affects to think is a heart&#8211;piercing pronouncement, which must startle the public, and may bring the courageous author into much tribulation. He need not fear, for his thesis is the most familiar &amp; the least disputed in the world – the hatefulness of War; &amp; the mood of disgust &amp; repugnance which he expresses is just now prevailing. <hi rend="bold underline">The book is more likely to bring him shekals </hi> <hi rend="underline">[sic]</hi> <hi rend="bold underline"> than abuse!</hi></p>
         <p>I tried to write the promised Article for the "Spectator", but had no success whatever. Has my right hand really "lost its cunning"? The difficulty is to find a topic that shall be (&#x3B1;) suitable for a secular journal, (&#x3B2;) connected with the present situation in the Church of England, (&#x3B3;) judicious for handling at this juncture, (&#x3B4;) sufficiently within my power &amp; province to be handled by me. The limits of space are too strait for any adequate handling of anything. Add, that the next fortnight is more than ever crowded with business, for the Ordination is immediately followed by the Patronage Commission.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>