<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Paterson</hi><persName xml:id="4893" display="no"></persName><hi> came for the last time, and, when he had gone his way, I got up to resume a more normal manner of living. I walked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><hi> in the garden. The wind last night snapped off a great part of the poplar tree by the river&#8211;bank.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read again </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burnet's</hi><persName xml:id="1435"></persName><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">Discourse of the Pastoral Care</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="1036"></ref>. How admirable it is, &amp; how informing &amp; characteristic! There is an impulsiveness about the bustling bishop, which goes far to make him almost loveable.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"In short, the being able to state rightly the grounds of our hope, &amp; the terms of salvation, and the having a clear &amp; ready view of the new covenant in Christ Jesus, is of such absolute necessity, that it is a profaning of orders, and a defiling of the sanctuary, to bring any into it, that do not rightly understand this matter in its whole extent".</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">His notion of a clergyman's recreation is sufficiently simple</hi><hi rend="bold">:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"His friends and his garden ought to be his chief diversions, as his study and his parish ought to be his chief employments. He must still carry on his study: making himself an absolute master of the few books he has, till his circumstances grow larger, that he can purchase more".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>K. gave a most excellent address in the chapel, not only eminently sound and suitable in itself, but very persuasive, and giving the impression of sincerity. I could wish such an address were given to all the Ordination Candidates throughout the country.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Burnet</hi><persName xml:id="1435"></persName><hi> comments on the fact that the question as to being "inwardly moved by the Holy Ghost" is asked only in the Office of deacons:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"This is put only in this office, &amp; not repeated afterwards; it being justly supposed, that where one has had this motion, all the other orders may be in time conferred, pursuant to it: but this is the first step by which a man dedicates himself to the service of God, &amp; therefore it ought not to be made by any that has not this Divine vocation. Certainly the answer that is made to this ought to be well considered: for if any says, "I trust so",</hi> <hi rend="underline">that yet knows nothing of any such motion, &amp; can give no account of it, he lies to the Holy Ghost, &amp; makes his first approach to the altar with a lie in his mouth, &amp; that not to men, but to God</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This is very terrible, and sets one on a train of self&#8211;questioning reminiscence, not very consolatory.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
