<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">O God, from Whom alone can come the power to minister, and Whose Will alone can give the right, have mercy on me, &amp; forgive all the faults and failures of my ministry through all these years. Thou alone knowest the greatness of my sin, Thou alone canst forgive it. I thank Thee for the opportunities of service renewed continually, and for the graces &amp; comforts which have cheered my life. I beseech Thee, of Thine infinite goodness to grant me will and power to devote the remainder of my days more sincerely to Thy service and the help of Thy people. Grant me the light of Thy good Spirit to guide me in the difficult way I must tread. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee"</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Thirty years ago on Advent Sunday, I was instituted publicly in Barking Parish Church as Vicar of the Parish. It was a rash adventure for a man of 25 without experience or influence to undertake, perhaps it was sinfully rash. I do not know. At the time I was torn with doubt, and now, when as Bishop I re&#8211;consider the facts, I am still full of doubt. But I had no advisor, and it was a difficult choice. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Lady Chapel. After breakfast I stayed in my room and prepared an address on the League of Nations for the afternoon. We had an early lunch, and then motored to Worcester, where we arrived in good time in spite of a puncture on the road. The Refectory was completely filled with an audience of men </hi><hi rend="underline">and women</hi><hi> – the destruction of the Sex barrier is now everywhere apparent – and I gave my address, which was listened to very attentively. There were some questions afterwards, which I answered, &amp; then we went to tea in the Deanery. The Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName>, the local member of Parliament<persName xml:id="4765"></persName> (</hi><hi rend="bold underline">who said he had been manager of the Jute works in Barking, and had known me there</hi><hi> ), and two labour men came also, and I had some talk with them. The Cathedral nave was filled for the Evening Service when I preached on "The Advent of Jesus". Acoustically Worcester is above the average of cathedrals, immensely superior to my little Hereford. We had supper with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon James</hi><persName xml:id="4784"></persName><hi>, a brother of the new Provost of Eton<persName xml:id="3416"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lacey</hi><persName xml:id="1936"></persName><hi> &amp; his wife were there. He is evidently bent on persuading everybody that he is a very liberal minded man, &amp; he appears to be 'taking in' some of his colleagues. We left Worcester shortly after 9 p.m. and were back in the Palace about 11 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
