<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I got up, &amp; came down to an early lunch. After lunch there was a meeting of the standing C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> of the Dioc: Conf</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ce</hi><hi>. It was decided on the motion of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Wheeler<persName xml:id="4906"></persName> to treat the existing Conference as valid for the purpose of the present election: and to issue the requisite notices for the purpose. This the secretaries, Col: Middleton<persName xml:id="4631"></persName> &amp; Canon <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName>, undertook to do forthwith. A meeting of the Book&#8211;Box C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> was attended by Bannister, and two laymen, of whom the only one whose name I could identify was Wiltshire, the clerk to the County Education C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>. This gentleman announced that the late Bishop had transferred the Fund to Trustees, &amp; thus taken it altogether out of the hands of his successor in the see. This announcement made everybody look very silly! It makes no real difference, &amp; relieves me of responsibility for the Fund. But it is an odd, furtive, inexplicable way of doing business.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName>, James <persName xml:id="88">Adderley</persName>, and a M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Molesworth, who sent me an interesting account of his dealings with the sectaries in a large Norfolk parish. Also I wrote to Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. The proof of my letter to the diocese arrived from the printers. It is cold, stilted, and limited in range, but it will have to serve. There </hi><hi rend="underline">are</hi><hi> disadvantages attaching to a chronic inability to "fall into line".</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
