<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "Times" was brought to me in bed; and there I read a column, summarizing </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the Report of the "Church &amp; State" Committee</hi><hi rend="italic"><ref xml:id="817"></ref>. It made me very angry to see that, in spite of the assurances given to me in the Committee by the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> </hi><hi rend="i bold strikethrough underline">in Committee</hi><hi> [sic]</hi><hi rend="italic">, and later by the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> privately, this Report has gone out to the world, without a minority Report, and without the commentary of what was called a "second reading debate". I was so moved that, after breakfast in the club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I wrote a letter to the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">", and gave it to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Geoffrey Dawson</hi><persName xml:id="2709"></persName><hi rend="italic">, when he came to the club to join me at lunch. The Bishop of</hi><hi rend="bold">[2] </hi><hi rend="italic">Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, happening to come into the Club, I shewed the letter to him, and he expressed cordial agreement in my plea for a Royal Commission. I had much talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Geoffrey</hi><hi rend="italic">, desiring to persuade him to take a line on the question of reconstructing the Establishment, and urging that he should adopt the line of following precedent, and insisting on a Royal Commission as the constitutional preliminary to legislation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Are two Scottish Primates in collusion with a Welsh Premier to destroy the most distinctively English of all English Institutions</hi><hi rend="i bold">? </hi><hi rend="italic">The ultramontanism of the first and the sectarianism of the other, blend easily in an attack on a national Establishment of religion. </hi><hi> I shewed</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey</hi><hi> also some portion of this hapless memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and he expressed approval. We walked together into the City, and parted at Printing House Square. I called at the Deanery of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's but found both Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> and Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> were out. Then I went to 15 Bridge Street, and had tea with Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, who has clearly been "pulled down" by the influenza. Finally, I returned to the Club, wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, dined with Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName>, and ended by a rather futile attempt to prepare my Worcester speech. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
