<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the Rector of Ludlow<persName xml:id="4602"></persName> offering him the prebend's stall vacated by Prebendary Lambert's<persName xml:id="4794"></persName> resignation. He is reported to have refused a similar offer from my predecessor, but I hope he will accept</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I travelled to Manchester after an early lunch. The last stage of my journey was relieved by the conversation of my travelling companions, an employer from Birmingham &amp; a young officer of the R.F.C. When I got out at Manchester the latter asked, "Are you the </hi><hi rend="underline">famous</hi><hi> D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Henson?" which amused me not a little. Canon Scott<persName xml:id="3746"></persName> met me on the platform. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic">Knox<persName xml:id="3173"></persName> came to dinner: also one of the University professors, Maxwell Garnett<persName xml:id="4763"></persName>, who is married to a daughter of Professor Poulton<persName xml:id="4833"></persName>. We conversed of many things, &amp; of course the ecclesiastical situation. Bishop Knox expresses himself strongly against the attitude taken up by the two Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName>, and says that he is prepared to make a fight at the Representative Church Council. But I have my doubts as to his performances being equal to his professions. The Bishops of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, &amp; Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> have declared privately their agreement with me, but they also are apt to be silent when speech is golden!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
