<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[20]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Croft<persName xml:id="4540"></persName> was a country gentleman, of ancient lineage and large property. He had the prejudices as well as the virtues of his class, and both are considerable. He was neither a student nor a thinker: but he had an active mind, and a considerable fund of information. He evidently "fancied himself" as a preacher, and did possess a vigorous flowing style, which lent itself to popular uses. He was probably a good diocesan, active, masterful, and genuinely concerned for the religious welfare of the people. In these days, he would have been a prominent advocate of what is called "reform". I suspect the new Bishop of Coventry is the nearest modern parallel. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Yeatman&#8211;Biggs</hi><persName xml:id="2047"></persName><hi rend="italic"> also is a local magnate, with the double advantage of pedigree &amp; property: &amp; he shares with Croft a fussy zeal for well&#8211;intentioned innovation. My predecessor was, I think, the greater of the two, but he lived in an age less favourable to make&#8211;belief than our own: &amp; his proposals, unlike those of the modern bishop, were not mere echoes of the clamour of the crowd. His most considerable, &amp; most creditable, composition is "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Naked Truth</hi><hi rend="italic">"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>, which, though published anonymously, seems almost at once to have been identified as his work.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
