<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We attended Mattins at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Giles's, and heard an inoffensive sermon from Ralph's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> brother, the Vicar<persName xml:id="4781"></persName>. We all stood up while the names of those parishioners &amp; members of the congregation who had fallen in the War were rehearsed from the pulpit, and the "Dead March" was played. After service I called on poor Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName>, and said Goodbye. It was a distressing experience. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> took me for a walk after lunch. He is pressing for a Royal Commission on the Central Board of Finance, but will surely be defeated. He spoke highly of the Bishop of Ely's<persName xml:id="532"></persName> new book against Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName><ref xml:id="1037"></ref>, but I do not think either he or the bishop perceives the real point to be met. We parted at the corner of Broad Street. I went to Frewen Hall<placeName xml:id="49"></placeName>, &amp; had tea with the Omans<persName xml:id="2141"><persName xml:id="2142"></persName></persName>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">with whom was my godson, Charles<persName xml:id="1679"></persName>, a tallish lad of 17, rather shy and pale</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> Next I went to Magdalen, and had an interview with the President<persName xml:id="2521"></persName>. He had read through so much as I had yet written of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and expressed approval of it. He seems seriously minded to be helpful. Finally I returned to All Souls, and dined pleasantly in the Common Room. Oman, Headlam, Johnson<persName xml:id="2407"></persName>, Richards<persName xml:id="4839"></persName>, and Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName>, with 2 guests.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
