<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious sun&#8211;rise, the whole eastern sky aflame – an awful rose of dawn. I celebrated in the little squalid chapel of the Palace. <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName>, Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, Ernest, the two candidates Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> and myself. One of my two candidates, Custance<persName xml:id="4748"></persName>, displayed an astonishing ignorance. Too rashly I accepted him on the strength of his having passed the Cambridge Preliminary Exam</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">n</hi><hi>, but really he expresses himself no better than an average Sunday School teacher. I had interviews with both the young men, and was not wholly satisfied with either. The one is deeply infected with the Romanizing poison, which is so widely distributed among Anglican youth just now, and the other is quite below the level of knowledge &amp; intelligence which Ordination ought to imply. However, such as they are, I have undertaken to ordain them, &amp; now I must leave them to God. Whether the change of weather affected me, or the medicines prescribed by the leech, or the exertion of getting up, I cannot say, but a giddiness overtook me, and, though I made a start at dinner, I could not continue, but betook myself to bed. K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> took my place in chapel, and gave the "charge" to the candidates. This indisposition is very unfortunate and very disconcerting. Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> arrived alone; his wife having a chill. He looks well, and seems cheerful. Bredwardine is fortunate in its Vicar. </hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
