<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached twice in the Cathedral – at Mattins &amp; at the Evening Service. There were very large congregations on both occasions. The Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> was present at Mattins, an unusual proceeding. He received the Holy Sacrament afterwards, though he had already celebrated in his own chapel. But he preferred to repeat his communion rather than set, or seem to set, an example of non&#8211;communicating attendance – a nice point of casuistry. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The abominable malady from which I suffered in the summer has now returned, &amp; in abominably inconvenient form. I was in discomfort yesterday: in pain this morning: in agony tonight. A seat in the chancel, supplied with cushions, was arranged for me in the evening, but the preaching was difficult, &amp; I was very glad when it was over</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> The new Dean, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Swayne</hi><persName xml:id="4856"></persName><hi>, was present. He is a tall, good&#8211;looking man, who may do well. He is said to smoke a pipe in the streets, and to attend meetings in a short coat! These are, perhaps, the natural marks of a dignitary who espouses "Life &amp; Liberty", as Swayne is supposed to do. As soon as possible after my return to the house, I went to bed in much physical misery!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
