<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Last night I had an hour's talk with Mead&#8211;Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, before leaving the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. He appears to be thinking seriously of renting the large prebendal house, which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Simey is vacating at Durham, but is staggered by the dilapidated state of the house, and the reluctance of his wife. He assured me that the War had not brought vast profits to Armstrongs, but rather embarrassments: but I never know what precise value to attach to statements of that kind. The weekly wages paid in that firm now exceed &#x00A3;250,000 weekly! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He expressed continuing regret at my departure from Durham, and spoke absurdly about my returning as Bishop</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> But I replied that, apart from other difficulties, no Prime Minister would be fool enough to bring such another hornet's nest about his ears as was caused by my appointment to Hereford. Characteristically enough, he was hugging </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Taylor's</hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Medieval mind</hi><hi rend="italic">". </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I breakfasted in the Hotel with the single object of getting some butter. At the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, we are rigorously limited to margarine, which my soul loathes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to Lambeth, and there spent the day at a meeting of Bishops. The subject of discussion was </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the conditions under which non&#8211;Anglicans might be allowed to preach and pray in consecrated churches</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> There </hi><hi rend="bold">[4] </hi><hi> was a lively discussion, the character of which was determined by speeches from Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> (who is back from America in great form) and myself. Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName> made a good speech on my side of the question: and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">all things were going well, when Gore cut in with a vehement protest against a vote being taken, and their Graces "fell flat" as Jericho's walls. So we ended rather lamely with a general understanding that the subject sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be brought before the Convocation</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> The Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> was eager to be in charge of the business.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">My letter appeared in the "Times"</hi><ref xml:id="1055"></ref><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">It evidently made the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> very angry, for he made reference to it in his opening speech.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked away with the Bishop of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, who is justly excited over the question of educating the ordinands who are coming in from the Army. They are being adroitly monopolised by the Theological Colleges: and will no doubt prove a tower of strength to the "catholic" cause in due time! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">He is prepared to join with me in opposing this "Autonomy" project, when it comes up for discussion in the Representative Church Council in February.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined at the Club.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
