<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Instead of going to Ledbury, as I had hoped and intended, I must continue in bed ignobly and discomfortably. The post brought me "with the Author's compliments[^"^] a small volume – "</hi><hi rend="underline">Letters to a Missionary</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="1034"></ref> by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">R. F. Johnston</hi><persName xml:id="4790"></persName><hi> – which interested me so much that I read it through in bed, while <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Ernest went to the Cathedral. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It appears that the China inland Mission is divided on the dogma of everlasting damnation, which the majority of its missionaries are teaching in the crudest &amp; most revolting form. The letters pretend to be addressed to a missionary who refuses to teach the dogma. They branch out into a vigourous &amp; effective criticism of Christianity as it is now presented</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The author professes to stand outside the Christian churches, &amp; repudiates for himself the Christian name. He thinks the modernist or 'liberal' position properly untenable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Observer</hi><hi rend="italic">" reports that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName><hi rend="italic">, Master of the Temple, is to go to the Abbey in succession to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Boyd Carpenter</hi><persName xml:id="280"></persName><hi rend="italic"> – a good appointment, which at least saves the Abbey from falling to the enemy. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Carnegie</hi><persName xml:id="2955"></persName><hi rend="italic"> is now the only High Churchman on the Chapter, and he is the only Oxford man. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName><hi rend="italic"> is from Dublin: all the rest are from Cambridge.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
