<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning was passed in interviews. First, young Bateman came to say goodbye. I gave him a letter of introduction to Archdeacon Cody<persName xml:id="2907"></persName> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Mark's Toronto. Next came Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> whom I told definitely that he had best terminate his chaplainship at Christmas. Then came Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>, with whom I had a long &amp; earnest conference respecting his Ordination. To lunch came </hi><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Harrison, a daughter of Bishop Atlay<persName xml:id="4713"></persName>. She said that the old gardener remembered planting the cedars in the garden. This was when Bishop Hampden<persName xml:id="4768"></persName> came to Hereford in 1848, so the trees must have been just 70 years in the garden. She accused M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Percival of mutilating several trees in the garden by having their branches lopped off</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I walked for an hour after lunch. D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Morris called to see me in the interest of Norcock, but he added little to my information. Then <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> came, and undertook to act as Secretary after Christmas until I should make a final arrangement. I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, who has been seriously ill with pneumonia following that odious influenza. Lawrence Holt<persName xml:id="3655"></persName> was good enough to write to me about him. The weather continues to be mild, damp, and very unwholesome.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
