<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A languidly warm day. I started to work at a letter to the diocese on the subject of Church Reforms, but I made little headway. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Castle Frome, where the Rector (Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> W. P. P. Matthews<persName xml:id="4811"></persName>) met me with the plans &amp;c of a new painted window which some parishioners propose to set up as a war&#8211;memorial to a young officer who has fallen in the War.</hi><hi rend="italic">The little church contains a wonderful early Norman Font, and some recumbent effigies in marble: also an Elizabethan cup &amp; chalice, the latter dated 1571. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Matthews is a relation of the <persName xml:id="560"><persName xml:id="1275">Rolfes</persName></persName>, &amp; had seen my photograph in their possession. We returned to Hereford by way of Ledbury. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">A telegram from L. Percival<persName xml:id="4358"></persName> informed me that the old bishop, my predecessor, had passed away</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">He had been a prominent man in his day, a strong partisan, but it may perhaps be the case, though I have hitherto ever refused to admit it, that only in the grooves of party can any real effect be secured. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Percival</hi><persName xml:id="475"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was a Radical partisan, &amp; made no attempt to conceal the fact. His position as a member of the House of Lords gave him opportunities of influence which I do not possess, &amp; he was a comparatively rich man, whereas I am an extremely poor one.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
