<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Let Thy blessing be upon my action this day. O God, and have regard. I beseech Thee, to the needs of Thy People, and not to the sins of Thy Servant. Give Thy grace to these young men, whom I shall ordain to be Thy ministers, and own the deed of Thy Servant for Christ's sake.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dull damp morning infinitely depressing. I breakfasted in bed, and got up but in time for the service, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">deliberately garnering my strength for the function</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> The service went through without hitch and was impressive &amp;, I trust, also edifying. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> preached an excellent sermon from 1.Cor: III. 11&#8211;15. <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> presented the candidates. Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName> read the Gospel</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The singing was good and congruous. After the service the declarations &amp;c were made in the Palace under the direction of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName>. Scott brought to lunch a friend, Roger Wodehouse<persName xml:id="4883"></persName>, a curate of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Thomas's, Oxford, who is a relation (grand&#8211;son or grand&#8211;nephew) of Mathew Arnold. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the S. Martin's Preventative &amp; Rescue Home<orgName xml:id="304"></orgName>, and there I confirmed 7 girls. The sisters had arranged everything very nicely. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">K. had some talk with me about his own plans</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I think he inclines more to come into the country. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> is strongly of opinion that I should write a memorandum on the ecclesiastical situation, and send it to the P.M. This was the advice of Geoffrey D.<persName xml:id="2709"></persName> when I discussed the subject with him. I am rather shy of approaching the P.M. directly especially after the tempest which arose about my nomination to Hereford. Then there is the further suggestion that I should write three "communicated" articles to the "Times", setting forth the objections to "autonomy". and indicating an alternative procedure. Major<persName xml:id="3660"></persName> writes to suggest that I should write something for the "Modern Churchman". I have undertaken to preach at the Temple on February 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> with a view to the meeting of the Representative Church Council in the week following.</hi><hi rend="bold underline">All these undertakings form a heavy mortgage on my leisure, which is already bound with that hopeless "Memoir"<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and with "The Naked Truth"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>, which has more labour in it than might be supposed. The repeated indispositions which have befallen me since I came to Hereford are not only an ugly warning in themselves, but also an additional reason for my activity in the diocese. Yet the meeting of the R.C.C. in the first week of February gives a measure of urgency to that business, which I cannot ignore since "Time &amp; Tide wait for no man". And the doctor talks of my reducing the amount of my work &amp; worry</hi><hi rend="bold">!!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
