<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the day at Lambeth. Two subjects provoked most of the discussion viz: the National Mission Committee Reports, and the question of Women's place in the Church. Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName> made a careful speech on the first, in which he </hi><hi rend="italic underline">on the whole</hi><hi rend="italic"> endorsed my position, &amp; I made a conciliatory speech, in which, however, I repeated my objection to the Reports of the Abps' Committees. I wanted to know what they were designed to effect, &amp; what limits there were to the policy they expressed. "Did the bishops intend to take over the functions of the Universities?" There was a considerable debate over the women. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> proposed a resolution asserting that there was no objection in principle against lay women exercising every function now open to lay men</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The natural &amp; perpetual subordination of woman to man was expressed in the reservation of the priesthood &amp; the episcopate to man.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I challenged this "principle", which, I said was no more than a strong precedent</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">"When the higher ministry of prophecy was open to women, &amp; they were admitted within the ministerial order as deacons, how could it be matter of principle to exclude them from the priest&#8211;hood &amp; the episcopate?". But, on the ground of expediency, I saw many grave objections to going forward with concessions to women. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> called on M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Davidson<persName xml:id="404"></persName>, &amp; we walked away together, calling successively on Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> &amp; the Gows<persName xml:id="216"><persName xml:id="542"></persName></persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
