<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins in the Cathedral, and stayed to the Holy Communion. There was an immense congregation. The sermon – an exhortation to unselfishness – was preached by a Minor Canon named Besley<persName xml:id="4722"></persName>. Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> was there. After lunch I walked with Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>. On Lambeth Bridge we saw a boy fall from the iron&#8211;work. He lay so still that we feared the worst. I hastened to S. Thomas's Hospital but they referred me to the Police. Having found a constable I sent him on to the scene of the disaster in a taxi, but aid had already arrived from the West</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi> side, &amp; the boy had been removed to that Hospital. I went to the Cathedral at 7 p.m. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> preached an excellent sermon, well&#8211;planned, well&#8211;phrased, and well&#8211;delivered. He has a considerable voice which, as I judge, carried well over the building. There was a great congregation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He came in to supper. He had detected my hand in the articles on the Church in the "Times".</hi><hi rend="italic">Rather to my surprise he had not seen before the well&#8211;known quotation from Burke which I set at the head of the second article. Unfortunately he is not a member of the Representative Church Council. Influenza will certainly keep away a good many of my supporters, but nothing but sheer necessity will hold back my opponents. It is the Jesuits v. the Medieval Church!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
