<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright but cold day. I worked at the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> all the morning, &amp; produced 3 sheets by lunch time! A deaf lady from Much Dewchurch lunched, &amp; then we had a visit from old Canon Palmer<persName xml:id="4349"></persName>. He said that he possessed some pieces of plate which had once belonged to Bishop Van Mildert<persName xml:id="4869"></persName>. I wrote to Professor Adam of Hartford, Conn. U.S.A., from whom I received a letter inquiring whether there would be a sphere for him as a lay&#8211;preacher in the Church of England, he having been bred a Presbyterian &amp; being nowise discontented with Presbyterianism, yet averse from Nonconformity. On James's<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> advice I wrote to the Norwich Union Insurance Office reporting the motor collision in which poor Croft was knocked down. He thinks that, as there appears to have been no negligence on either side, there would probably be no legal case for compensation, but there can be no doubt as to the equitable grounds for such compensation, for the poor man was without fault in the matter, &amp; has received considerable injury.</hi><hi rend="italic">My brother<persName xml:id="636"></persName> of Worcester is being early initiated into the trials of a bishop, for already he has to decide upon a difficult &amp; displeasing case of discipline. Can a man who has married his niece at a registry office be admitted to Holy Communion? In these cases the difficulty is to find a remedy. The offence once committed, there seems no choice open but to condone it!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
