<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the morning on the memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, which hangs fire woefully. In the afternoon I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and did my letters. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> called, and I talked with him in the garden for an hour. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He is deep in psycho&#8211;therapeutics, and has started experimentalizing on his own account. He says that he has been successful in cases of shell&#8211;shock. I have a vague fear that much mental &amp; moral confusion is bound up in the Faith&#8211;healing movement. But, for good or ill, it appears to have "come to stay". It is a lamentable thing to be wholly outcast from the characteristic tides of one's own time: but that is a situation into which I feel myself drifting</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Elizabeth Smith</hi><persName xml:id="4472" display="no"></persName><hi rend="italic"> arrived during the afternoon, and the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Campbell Dodgsons</hi><persName xml:id="4753"><persName xml:id="4754"></persName></persName><hi rend="italic"> in the evening. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">They tell me that M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Romanes<persName xml:id="102"></persName> has become a Roman Catholick.</hi><hi rend="italic">This is the fitting d&#x00E9;nouement of her career as a militant neo&#8211;Tractarian. But Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> must needs feel distressed at the defection of another disciple. Streeter thinks that he intends to devote his leisure to a polemic against Anglican Modernism, but I doubt whether his heart lies in that controversy. His interest, perhaps, lies in the Roman controversy, in which he first made his name as a controversialist. In later years men turn most willingly to the concerns of their youth, and tend to grow weary of the conflicts which filled their manhood.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
