<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a slight frost this morning enough to warn us against our hopes. I wrote two pages of the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and for the rest spent the morning in talking with divers interlopers. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came to lunch. In the afternoon I walked for an hour with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and then wrote a short sermon for tomorrow. My chauffeur, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, is reported to be in bed with flu: however the Hereford Motor C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi><hi> undertakes to send me an efficient substitute. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Tallents<persName xml:id="4860"></persName>, the Rector of Upper Sapey, offering him the living of Kimbolton</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">Bishop Stubbs<persName xml:id="2924"></persName> was a wise &amp; learned man, and he found himself able publicly to make this declaration:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"I speak from experience when I say that a man who becomes a Bishop gives up everything else to enable himself to give himself to the work that God sets him: &amp; very sadly inefficient he finds himself."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">He was very resentful of the smart criticisms of so&#8211;called Church Reformers, and he was a whole&#8211;hearted opponent of Disestablishment. In his time the evil was but in its bud, which now in its full &amp; insolent fruitage threatens to ruin everything. His charges are pathetically remote from the situation which now confronts us.</hi>	
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
