<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It rained all night, and kept on raining all day. I motored to Tarrington, and there confirmed 37 candidates. It was a pleasant service, &amp;, I trust, also edifying. I lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Green Price</hi><persName xml:id="4237"></persName><hi>, who kept to luncheon </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Randle</hi><persName xml:id="4658"></persName><hi> the Vicar of Stretton Grandison, and Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M. R. S. Onslow</hi><persName xml:id="4643"></persName><hi>, Rector of Stoke Edyth, who had brought candidates from their respective parishes. We had some rather interesting conversation on the conditions of ministry in rural parishes. Then I went on to Fownhope where I confirmed 32 candidates, &amp; afterwards had tea with the Vicar, Rev. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">F. G. Nott</hi><persName xml:id="4824"></persName><hi>, a weak listless creature. The parish church has an unusually lengthy chancel. On my return, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bulmer</hi><persName xml:id="4521"></persName><hi> came to see me about tomorrow's meeting. It appears that the result at the County Council election was indecisive, so that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Corner</hi><persName xml:id="4745"></persName><hi> will secure re–election as chairman. Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne–Willson</persName></hi><hi> came to do my letters; and young </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi><persName xml:id="4667"></persName><hi> came to ask me for help at All Saints. I took occasion to tell him not to make a jack–ass of himself by wearing his cassock in the streets. The Archdeacon of Hereford<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came to stay the night. We had some interesting talk after dinner while Blair Ripley<persName xml:id="2882"></persName> smoked his pipe. So ended another day. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
