<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A white frost, and a glorious day. I administered Confirmation to 19 candidates in the parish church &#8211; a hideous structure. After lunching with the Lushingtons<persName xml:id="4312"></persName> I motored to Leighton. The views were as noble as the road was execrable! Here I confirmed 21 candidates in a modern church beautifully placed in the hills. The parson, Drew<persName xml:id="4755"></persName>, has a pleasant wife &amp; two nice little girls. He tells me that his squire, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Naylor, is a young man of ability very well disposed to the church. The old parish church is a wattled building of great antiquity said to be highly interesting. </hi><hi rend="italic">From Leighton </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I motored through very beautiful country to Alberbury, and was entertained by Lady Leighton<persName xml:id="4800"></persName>, &amp; her son Sir Richard<persName xml:id="4799"></persName>, at Loton Park</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The house is Jacobean with a large modern extension. There are the ruins of a castle nearby and the parish church which is an interesting medieval building with a very curious tower. The parson, Roberts<persName xml:id="4899"></persName>, seems a poor creature. He c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> tell me </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nothing</hi><hi rend="italic"> about the history of his church, and knew </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nothing</hi><hi rend="italic"> of its architecture. He has recently lost his wife, and now dabbles in spiritualism! He came to this parish 6 years ago by an exchange. Out of more than 600 parishioners he has about 40 or 50 communicants at Easter, and would now like to get a parish nearer London!!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lady Leighton seems to be well&#8211;disposed towards the church. Her son, Sir Richard, has been recently released from Germany, and is now rather perplexed as to his own career. He seems an ingenious young man, &amp; gave an interesting account of his experiences in Berlin. His father, Sir Brian<persName xml:id="4798"></persName>, was a queer adventurous creature, who had a passion for fighting, but he seems to have had an affection for children, and was wont to have East End children to stay in his property. Lady L. meditates perpetuating his memory by bounding a house here for the entertainment of poor children. This gives a pleasing impression of the late baronet, whose reputation in these parts is not of the highest. His son, Sir Richard, now 26 years old is rather at sea as to his plan of life. The war cut short his training as an engineer, and then the death of his brother made him heir to the baronetcy. There is a property of about 4000 acres, and double estate duties to be paid. This will compel the selling of perhaps a fourth of the estate. Certainly these are difficult times for landholders. If their troubles meant a great increase in small holders, they might be borne with equanimity by the rest of us: but do they?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
