<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I did not sleep well, but relieved the tedium of the night by reading "Catherine<persName xml:id="4858"></persName> &amp; Craufurd Tait<persName xml:id="4857"></persName>"<ref xml:id="1042"></ref> which was in the bookcase beside my bed. The impression the book leaves on my mind is that of </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">a small intensive society, very good in a conventional way and very conscious of their goodness, much given to praising one another in private letters, &amp;, I should suspect, not indisposed to candid criticism of one another in private conversation</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">When Craufurd Tait wanted a living his father refrained from appointing him to a valuable benefice in his gift, and arranged that the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> should appoint Craufurd to a London benefice, from which he removed the vicar to the said benefice. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This nepotistic device is evidently regarded as rather notably virtuous</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The smallness of the reigning coterie which allotted the higher preferments of the National Church as if they were parts of a family property is very significant. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lambeth and Latitudinarianism of a very mild type have been replaced by Winchester &amp; Neo&#8211;Tractarianism, but the domestic point of view remains, though the monopoly is being seriously invaded</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, Hereford, and now Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> can hardly be fitted into the family scheme, though the method of "adoption" has been found capable of extensive application!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Aldenham Hall and motored to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Evancoid</hi><hi> vi&#x00E2; Ludlow, Leintwardine, and Presteign. I arrived about 1 p.m. and lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline">Lewis</hi><hi>, a retired parson, who owns a beautiful property in the parish. His only child, </hi><hi rend="underline">Jack</hi><hi>, was to be confirmed. There were altogether 21 candidates, of whom 10 were boys &amp; men. The little church was completely filled with an attentive congregation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Roland Pryce<persName xml:id="4834"></persName>, my old curate, who is beneficed in the adjoining diocese, came to lunch, and stayed to the service</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> After tea, I returned to Hereford vi&#x00E2; Kington, arriving about 6.15 p.m. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName></hi><hi> did the letters with me. </hi><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Blair</hi><persName xml:id="4725"></persName><hi>, the late Bishop of the Falkland Islands, dined here – a large man, chastened by failure and demurely conventional.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The evening paper announces that the Government have lost the bye&#8211;election at Hull by over 900 votes. This is another significant warning against misunderstanding the meaning of Lloyd&#8211;George's<persName xml:id="234"></persName> sweeping victory at the polls. The rapidity with which the flood&#8211;tide of political feeling is ebbing can hardly be paralleled.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Life &amp; Liberty" people are gambling on the accident which has brought into the House of Commons a great majority of Tories.<note xml:id="453" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
