<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[154] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName> &amp; her sister came to my study, and went over with me all that had been prepared of the memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">They professed themselves satisfied</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> If the president of Magdalen<persName xml:id="2521"></persName> will send his promised contribution, I can perhaps, bring the matter to some kind of a conclusion. After lunch, we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, Mary<persName xml:id="4867"></persName>, &amp; I) motored to Hartlebury Castle, vi&#x00E2; Bromyard &amp; Worcester, &amp; called on the new Bishop<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. We were shown the castle, which is very interesting, and the grounds, which are extensive &amp; beautiful: and then we returned to Hereford vi&#x00E2; Kidderminster, Bewley, Tenbury, Brimfield, &amp; Leominster, arriving shortly after 8 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Ernest is evidently pleased with his new greatness, and resolved to essay residing in the Castle. He retains his Directorship of the Insurance Office, which is worth &#x00A3;500 per annum, &amp;, I suppose, must have perhaps, as much again from investment of his savings during the last 25 years. The income of the see is &#x00A3;3.900. He has no chaplain, and pays nothing to his legal secretary. The household is reduced to the smallest dimensions: and the garden, which employs 3 gardeners, is intended to cover its own expenses by the produce which is sold. I shall be interested to observe the fortunes of this bold effort to house economy in a feudal palace!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
