<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Surely the most inspiring and enigmatic of Festivals – more so, perhaps, than Easter, for the alleged historic fact holds more loosely to the spiritual witness, &amp; the spiritual witness itself comes nearer to our own problem. Not the death of the body is the worst part of our burden, but that death in life of the spirit which S. Paul has described in Romans VII. The collect for the Festival is entirely satisfactory. Even the reference to the alleged historic fact is phrased symbolically. "The heavens" is less </hi><hi rend="italic underline">physical</hi><hi rend="italic"> than "heaven": and the phrase "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">so we may also in heart &amp; mind thither ascend, &amp; with him continually dwell</hi><hi rend="italic">" leaves nothing to be desired. It is Pauline and it is thoroughly congruous with the modern spirit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. &amp; celebrated the Holy Comm</hi><hi rend="i sup u">n</hi><hi rend="italic">. Rather to my surprise there were more than a score of the Cathedral school boys there, &amp; they all communicated. This must surely be the survival of some old rule, little harmonious with the mind of the present day. However, they carried themselves very reverently, and there is always something moving in the communion of boys. So much lies before them, &amp; they know so little of it. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">A new boat and old rocks</hi><hi rend="italic">" says the grim Highland proverb. The glorious beauty of the world in this brilliant early summer accords perfectly with worship, &amp; communion, &amp; the unquenchable ardour of youth.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[222]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent some time in revising my Confirmation notes: then I wrote to Llewelyn Davies returning the addresses of his father<persName xml:id="644"></persName>, which, though excellent in their way, seemed to me too remote from the actual situation which now confronts us to be worth printing.</hi><hi rend="italic">Then the "Times" arrived with a long letter from the Bishop of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> in support of the Enabling Bill. I wrote a brief reply, &amp; sent it off.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I confirmed over 170 persons in the Cathedral. It was a moving &amp; dignified service. Among the candidates was the daughter of General Lawson<persName xml:id="3923"></persName>, who had command of the Northern district, when we were living at Durham. He, his wife, &amp; his daughter came in to tea after service. We motored to Bodenham, where I confirmed 22 persons in the parish church. I was rather tired, but the service seemed to be reverent. We got back to the Palace about 8.15 p.m. Among those whom I confirmed in the Cathedral were Melbourne<persName xml:id="4892" display="no"></persName>, the page&#8211;boy, &amp; Randall Bateman<persName xml:id="4891"></persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Thomas<persName xml:id="4804"></persName>, the Secretary of the Free Catholic Movement, replies to my letter in a long &amp; interesting letter.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is evident that Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName> "Oxford Petition" has come as a sharp and unpleasant surprize to the section of Nonconformists with whom he has been "carrying on" for some considerable time past</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
