<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Many a day the only entry in the diary is, '</hi><hi rend="underline">My daily task, thanks be to God.'</hi><hi> The amount of labour, mental and mechanical, which is intimated by this short phrase, must be estimated by reference to his printed books, &amp; to the still extant Adversaria, from which his books proceeded".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Pattison's<persName xml:id="494"></persName> "Isaac Casaubon<persName xml:id="4733"></persName>"<ref xml:id="19"></ref> p. 230.</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I was indisposed all day, and went to bed early: so that my record may equal Casaubon's in brevity though not in quality. Beyond a few letters, &amp; the newspapers, I solaced myself with Casaubon. Mark Pattison is an admirable biographer, and he found a thoroughly congruous subject. There is a ring of personal bitterness in the contemptuous language which he employs to describe the much&#8211;vaunted learning of the Jacobean divines, but he is probably not far from the truth when he lays emphasis on the theological and controversial interest which dominated English learning. James I comes out creditably in his dealings with Casaubon, &amp; the latter's uniformly respectful references to his royal patron in his private correspondence are creditable both to himself &amp; to the King. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is hardly true to say that the Anglican controversialists represented the appeal to sound learning</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> This appeal on all essentials was to the Bible, and on non&#8211;essentials to Christian antiquity. Their opponents really stood on the Authority of the Church, &amp; </hi><hi rend="underline">their</hi><hi> appeal to antiquity was merely polemical. Hence the facile &amp; frequent forgeries.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
