<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The reaction after the War carries far, and the deep disappointment which has followed the shouting over the Armistice weighs heavily on men's spirits. Already the confident hopes so freely proclaimed in November have become too plainly chimerical for intelligent repetition. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We have done with the kindly nonsense about "making war to end war", and are quite naturally discussing the probabilities of the next War</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">From every point of the compass there come to us tidings of violence and discontent. Egypt and India are as nearly in revolt as the circumstances make possible. Ireland is evidently preparing for some fresh madness of rebellion. Roumania, Poland, Bohemia, Belgium, Serbia – all the new nations, whom we are pledged to establish, are </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">trembling on the verge of this mysterious Russian malady which, without (as we are assured) a single recommendation, succeeds in winning ever fresh recruits</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">France and Italy are angry and disillusioned, forced to face their internal problems with every disadvantage, and Great Britain is heading for bankruptcy on a tide of economic madness, which might well move the laughter of school children. The United States, after an orgy of altruistic cant, is backing out of Europe with the "swag" of the ruined continent in her pockets!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Preaching, in the circumstances of a rural bishop, presents a very different problem than that which an urban preacher must solve. It is no longer possible to prepare the sermon with anxious care, to make sure that its phrases are as finished as they can be made, &amp; that lucidity has been as nearly achieved as the subject permits. The congregation will no more be known, &amp; sympathetic, able to place the right construction on characteristic expressions, familiar with the preacher's points of view &amp; modes of reasoning. The very pulpit will be unfamiliar, &amp; often disconcertingly inconvenient. He will have to discover the acoustics of the church, and the idiosyncrasy of the congregation. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Bishop is in the category of curiosities, something between a first class funeral and a cinematograph show</hi><hi rend="italic">. Accordingly there is sure to be an element in the congregation when he preaches which has exhausted its interest in the service as soon as it has gazed its fill at the oddly&#8211;garbed novelty, &amp; is frankly bored by the sermon. The school&#8211;children are brought to the Church specially for this occasion, &amp; they may be trusted to punctuate his Lordship's preaching with their coughing. Thus the situation is unhelpful. Add that the rustic people have an extreme dislike of written sermons, &amp; a dismaying stupidity. The Bishop knows that the local paper will probably report the words which he improvises for their benefit, &amp; thus their dullness determines his reputation!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> accompanied me in the car to Bettws. We left the Palace about 11.40 a.m. and reached our destination about 2.40 p.m., stopping for about 15 minutes to eat the luncheon we had taken with us. We travelled by Kingsland, Aymestrey, Wigmore, Brampton Brian [sic], and Knighton. There was a long hill at the end for Bettws is 1400 feet about sea level. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Vicarage is said to be highest in England</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> I confirmed 24 persons in the little parish church. The Vicar of Bettws&#8211;y&#8211;Crwyn, Rev. E. Irving Watson<persName xml:id="4875"></persName>, has been there for 6 years. He is also Vicar of the adjoining parish of Newcastle. The combined incomes only amount to &#x00A3;332, and there is a curate. The acreage of the two parishes is no less than 15,266 acres. In spite of the loneliness which must belong to his life, this parson &amp; his wife appeared to be cheerful. There is no village: the people – about 300 – live in detached farms &amp; cottages scattered over the great area of the parish. He expected about 60&#8211;70 communicants at Easter. The sun shone brightly as we returned to Hereford, &amp; shewed up the scenery to great advantage. We noticed that the swallows had returned.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My letter appeared in the "Times"<ref xml:id="1063"></ref>, it reads somewhat more savagely than is perhaps advisable at this juncture.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
