<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to Westminster. The crowds were already collecting for Princess Patricia's<persName xml:id="844"></persName> marriage. The Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> &amp; the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> were absent for the same reason. Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName> presided, &amp; we spent the morning in divers futile discussions. In the afternoon, the question of the franchise was debated. Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> led off, &amp; was followed by Sir Fred</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">k </hi><hi> Holiday<persName xml:id="4587"></persName> &amp; the Bishop of Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> made an excellent speech. I spoke but not very effectively</hi><ref xml:id="1060"></ref><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> The debate was adjourned after a characteristic oration from Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> which was loudly cheered. I dined at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went to the play. The "Times" contains a letter from Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> analysing the "Life &amp; Liberty" movement<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note>, &amp; supporting the proposal of a Royal Commission. I met Lord Beauchamp<persName xml:id="4806"></persName> &amp; had a short talk with him on the parliamentary prospects of the Enabling Bill. He didn't think they were bright. A Royal Commission would not interfere with the Government's programme, &amp; might therefore be conceded. But, if this Council adopts the Selborne Scheme, as it probably will, there will be little disposition to accept a Royal Commission, even though the Scheme have no chance in Parliament. Ella went to two plays, and returned shortly after 11 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
