<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a shockingly indecent book, purporting to disclose the infamies of German immorality. No doubt matters are amazingly bad in Germany, &amp; there is much to alarm as well as to astonish in the morals of Britain. But I doubt the quality of the enthusiasm for purity which takes the form of concentrating attention on the worst forms of impurity. The old Christian reticence was safer &amp; sounder. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Before starting on my Confirmations I burned the book</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We started at 9.30 a.m. and motored to Brimfield where I first confirmed 14 candidates at Mattins, and then, after lunch, consecrated an addition to the churchyard. The Vicar, Waterfield<persName xml:id="4874"></persName>, is an "old Westminster", &amp; once won the pancake there! We had tea with Lord Cawley<persName xml:id="4736"></persName>, who lives in a large and well&#8211;situated Georgian house, once inhabited by Lord Rodney, not far from Leominster. We found both his Lordship &amp; Lady Cawley<persName xml:id="4737"></persName> very friendly. I went to Eye and confirmed 32 candidates, of whom only 8 were boys. The parish church is unusually interesting, &amp; there are some fine recumbent monuments of the Cornwall family. The parson, Buckle<persName xml:id="4730"></persName>, is a cousin of the former Editor of the Times<persName xml:id="322"></persName>, &amp; has been Vicar of Eye for no less than 28 years. He had once inhabited the large house hard by the church, and therein had carried on a girls' school: but now he has vacated the first, and given up the last.</hi>    
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
