<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> suggesting that the resolution to be moved in Convocation might run thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"That this House, persuaded that an effective measure of ecclesiastical reform must form part of any adequate process of national "re&#8211;construction", would welcome the appointment of a Royal Commission to inquire into the State of the Church of England, &amp; to suggest a plan of reform ".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> and I motored to Stretton Grandison in order to view the trees on the glebe which the Vicar wished to cut down, &amp; to inspect Ashperton Church. We got dreadfully bemired in walking across the fields. Randle<persName xml:id="4658"></persName> was very pleased with himself for what he had done at Ashperton. I was pleased to see that the roof appeared to be sound, &amp; that the building had been "swept &amp; garnished": but I fear there's little to be done with an incumbent who sees no religious fitness in a decently&#8211;kept church. Then we went to Frome Bishop, and viewed the church. The vicar, Hopton<persName xml:id="4778"></persName>, is an eccentric Ritualist, who has been 38 years in the family living. He lives absolutely alone, doing everything for himself. His study was not</hi><hi rend="bold"> [49] </hi><hi> ill&#8211;kept, or unattractive, and the refreshment he offered was simple and good. He said that many of his parishioners were 'tramps', whose parochial character was fictional. On Easter Day, out of his 500 parishioners, he had but 35 communicants, and seemed to think the fact satisfactory! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>When we returned to the Palace, we found Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> in my study. He had come from a meeting at the Deanery, to discuss the revival of the Musical Festival, which the War had suspended.<note xml:id="450" n="1"></note> Fearne Booker<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> arrived in time for dinner. After dinner I attended a meeting of woman&#8211;patrols in the Town Hall. Miss Peto<persName xml:id="4830"></persName> from the Bristol Training College gave an address, &amp; I said "a few words".</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
