<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> "let himself go" with a vengeance last night when he 'turned and rent" Lord Northcliffe</hi><persName xml:id="4024"></persName><hi rend="i bold">.<note xml:id="454" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic">The attack was no doubt well&#8211;merited, and it was certainly courageous: but whether it was also judicious remains to be seen. It will be a definite gain to public morality if this "syndicated journalism" is proved to be too weak to destroy a Statesman who openly denounces it. The verdict of the newspapers appears to be decisively favourable on the Prime Minister's speech as a Parliamentary effort. Of course there is an element of 'Schadenfreude' in this, for the rivals of the Northcliffe Press can hardly avoid satisfaction at its public humiliation. The moralist will have cause to rejoice if Lord N. has to "take it lying down", for he has been appealing to the lower passions of the people, and the P.M. is representing the general conscience. I must needs confess to a feeling of regret at the degradation of the "Times", for I have often used its columns, and found advantage in doing so for causes which I care for. Probably the resignation of the editorship by Geoffrey Dawson<persName xml:id="2709"></persName> has its explanation in his refusal to join in the attack on the Prime Minister. What a complicated mechanism of involuted treacheries political life really is! When the veil is lifted, &amp; one can see the play of forces which determine its course, who would not thank God that he has not been a politician?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> James' Church after lunch, and there confirmed about 120 candidates from some 14 parishes. It is a new church &amp; rather cheerless. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The patronage belongs to the Simeon Trustees<orgName xml:id="302"></orgName>, &amp; that is rather a paralyzing circumstance</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> At present the Vicar is the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. F. J. Lansdell</hi><persName xml:id="4795"></persName><hi>, who has been about 9 years in the parish, &amp; in that time has succeeded in depressing everybody! Then I motored to King's Capel, being accompanied by <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; the two girls. We had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wyndham Smith</hi><persName xml:id="4803"></persName><hi>, whose daughter, </hi><hi rend="underline">Barbara</hi><hi>, was confirmed by me at Bridstow. The family has resided in the house since 1573, but the succession has generally passed thro' females, so that the names have varied. A surgeon named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bonney</hi><persName xml:id="4727"></persName><hi> was there, a relation of the old Professor<persName xml:id="1862"></persName> at Cambridge. I confirmed 12 candidates in the parish church, an interesting building with a Jacobean pulpit &amp; pre&#8211;Reformation pews. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We motored home by way of Fownhope and Mordiford, the way being illustrated by a glorious sunset. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I have now made an end of my Lenten Confirmations. Since Ash Wednesday I have confirmed on no less than 37 occasions, and have laid hands on about 1500 persons. The address has been largely the same from one church to another, &amp; I am glad to hear the last of it</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
