<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a heavy snow&#8211;fall proceeding briskly at day&#8211;break. And already the snow lay on the ground to the depth of several inches. The aspect of the world was fantastically beautiful. I read in bed Bishop Robertson's<persName xml:id="358"></persName> Charge to the Exeter Diocese<ref xml:id="1041"></ref>, delivered in 1910. He says things worth noting:&#8211;</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"If no other good thing were claimed for Protestantism, the creation of modern Biblical scholarship is its lasting glory. And this the more, that it has worked not for itself merely, but for the common course of knowledge &amp; truth. At the present day the field of Biblical work is becoming more &amp; more a common ground upon which all workers meet, giving &amp; receiving help &amp; light to the advancement of learning which is authoritative for all. Here, as elsewhere, there is growing up a commonwealth of learning with the promise, or at least the possibility, of contributing some day to a breaking down of party walls in other regions also.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>We motored with some difficulty on account of the snow to Pulverbatch, where we arrived half an hour late. Here I confirmed 20 candidates, &amp; afterwards lunched with the Vicar, Rev. M. J. Ransome<persName xml:id="4835"></persName>. After lunch we motored through the snow to Church Stretton, where I confirmed 30 candidates. Then we returned to Condover Hall<placeName xml:id="93"></placeName>. Snowing hard all the time.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There came to dinner M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Corbett<persName xml:id="4744"></persName>, from Longnor, a little parish which is united with Leebotwood. The parson is the Rev. H. H. Meakin<persName xml:id="4812"></persName>, whose income is under &#x00A3;200, &amp; who has no vicarage house. The population of the combined parishes is under 400 souls.</hi> <hi rend="italic">After the ladies had retired, we had some conversation on land&#8211;owning: &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Fielden<persName xml:id="4560"></persName> appeared to prove that the profits of the landlord did not now exceed 2 per cent. I was surprised to learn that a farm of 250 acres would require the investment of about &#x00A3;5000 capital.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
