<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After getting rid of my letters with <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson's</persName> help, I motored with <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> to Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Teme, and lunched with the Rector, Prebendary Stallard&#8211;Penoyre<persName xml:id="4117"></persName>. After lunch we went on to Rock, &amp; had tea with the Rector (Jenkins<persName xml:id="4598"></persName>), against whom a complaint had reached me. He is a shifty plausible Irishman! Then we went to Abberley, where the churchwarden received me. Finally we went to Far Forest, &amp; called on the Vicar (Paulley), a candid but fanatical "Catholick" who is setting his parishioners by the ears over some ritual innovations. His wife seemed even more absurd than himself! The day was beautiful, so that we saw the beautiful country to the best advantage.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On returning home, I wrote to Stallard&#8211;Penoyre, offering him the vacant living of Weobley. The notion of doing this was a sudden one, &amp; I acted on it without hesitation. I said to him, "Prebendary, if I offer you the living of Weobley, will you consider it?" "My lord, I should be bound to consider it", he rejoined, &amp; added, "But I am too old to undertake new work". "Nonsense", I said, "when you can ride in an open car without an overcoat". So we parted very amicably, but whether, on reflection, he will accept the living remains to be seen. He is a High Churchman, and voted against my election as Bishop!</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
