<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lord Wenlock<persName xml:id="973"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="3264"></persName> called shortly after 10 a.m. At 11 a.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Much Dewchurch, where I confirmed 37 candidates. We lunched with the Vicar – Rev. E Brooke Bradley<persName xml:id="4518"></persName>. Several clergy were present. I remember the name of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> W. L. Groves<persName xml:id="4240"></persName>, the Parson of Much Birch. After lunch we motored to Kingstone, and there I confirmed 15 more candidates. They were presented by the curate. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Timmis<persName xml:id="4864"></persName>, to whom I have offered the living of Thruxton&#8211;with&#8211;Kingstone made his appearance in khaki. He told me that he would accept the living. On the whole I was pleased with these confirmations. There were more males presented than females: and the candidates were of the suitable age, mostly about 16. They were attentive, &amp; had an appearance of sincerity which may have been misleading but was assuredly welcome. Knight<persName xml:id="4299"></persName> of Holmer called to ask advice about his parish, &amp; then <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> did the letters.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The proofs of the "Naked Truth"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref> arrived: they crossed my preface in the post. The printers have reproduced with great exactness the spellings &amp; even the letter&#8211;forms of the original. It makes 122 small pages. My introduction will add from 30 to 40 pages: so that the whole will amount to a small volume.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
