<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi>It was snowing smartly at day&#8211;break, and the river was in flood. The snow changed to sleet, and then to rain, while the river continued to rise. It overflowed its banks: and submerged much of the garden. At the bridge about 4.30 p.m. it registered 15 feet. Hearing that the water was out round Kingsland so that I could not approach the place by road, &amp; finding the trains extremely inconvenient, I telegraphed to the Vicar cancelling the Confirmation which had been arranged for tomorrow. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Blair Ripley</hi><persName xml:id="2882"></persName><hi> went off about midday. At 2.30 p.m. the Reconstruction Committee assembled in my dining room. There as a significant absence of any wish to turn out old Corner<persName xml:id="4745"></persName>, the Chairman: but they agreed to support the nomination of a Labour Alderman. Sir Richard Harrington's<persName xml:id="4771"></persName> name as a possible chairman commanded no support. Then that quaint old creature, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. E Mogridge</hi><persName xml:id="4816"></persName><hi>, Vicar of Weston Beggard, called with his wife to announce his impending resignation. After dinner the moon shining on the waste of floodwaters made a very beautiful scene. Most part of the "Bishop's meadow" appeared to be submerged at 10 p.m., but about that time the flood had reached its height, for after that it began to wane. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> reported a fall of several inches in the level of the waters.</hi>
         </p></body></text></TEI>
