<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought a letter from the officer, Jones<persName xml:id="4791"></persName>, who wrote from Italy some while ago offering to prepare a bibliography of "The Naked Truth"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>. He has returned, &amp; desires to carry out his purpose. Some portions of the bibliography were enclosed: he thought a day in the British Museum would enable him to complete it. After breakfast I walked to 99 S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Martin's Lane, and agreed with Chatto and Windus to include this addition. Then after assisting <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in packing our property for removal to the Deanery at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi> Paul's, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and, finding </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><persName xml:id="249"></persName><hi> there, took him straightway for a walk. I pressed on him the importance of speaking in the Lower House tomorrow, but he seems rather timorous.</hi><hi rend="italic">Then I went on to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and called on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gow</hi><persName xml:id="216"></persName><hi rend="italic">. I found him on the sofa with a sprained ankle. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He goes into a nursing home for an operation for cataract</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">This sounds as if he might possibly regain his sight.</hi><hi> I walked back to the Hotel, and, after lunching, paid the reckoning (&#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">18.16.8</hi><hi> for one week!)[^.^] We drove to Westminster, &amp; deposited my robes at the Convocation House. Then Ella went off with the luggage, and I to the Club. We met again at tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Gow<persName xml:id="542"></persName>: and then I attended the Joint Committee on the Reform of Convocation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Brotherhood dined at the Deanery. It was a pleasant party – Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, de Candole<persName xml:id="4544"></persName>, Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>, Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, and myself. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We discussed the question of a Royal Commission</hi><hi rend="italic">, and various names were suggested as possible commissioners. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Asquith</hi><persName xml:id="215"></persName><hi rend="italic">, as Chairman, was generally approved. The 2 archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName>, &amp; perhaps Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> &amp; another Bishop to balance him: Prof. E. W. Watson<persName xml:id="250"></persName> (Oxford), Prof. Bethune Baker<persName xml:id="4131"></persName> (Cambridge): Sir Henry Hadow<persName xml:id="3178"></persName>, Sir Edward Clarke<persName xml:id="4002"></persName>, the Provost of Eton<persName xml:id="3416"></persName>, Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> – this would be eleven commissioners, 5 laymen and 6 ecclesiastics. Other names suggested were Lord </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Justice Bankes</hi><persName xml:id="4715"></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Justice Atkins<persName xml:id="4690" display="no"></persName>: and to these might be added Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName>, though he is at present too decrepit for anything. Such a Commission would represent Law, Church, &amp; History. Probably there ought to be some representative of the House of Commons, and some Labour man. Clynes<persName xml:id="4739"></persName> might serve for the latter, and for the former anybody would serve provided he were neither a Cecil, nor a Talbot, nor a Lyttleton, nor a Palmer. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But I doubt whether Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> will have sufficient care for the Establishment to take a step which would be friendly to it</hi><hi rend="i bold">:</hi><hi rend="italic"> his antecedents point rather to some action in the other direction.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
