<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A white frost leading in a fine day, though cold. We left the Palace at 9.15 a.m., and motored to Knowbury, a parish in the Clee Hills. There was much snow in and about the Church. Here I confirmed 27 candidates. The Vicar, Rev: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">J. H. Parry</hi><persName xml:id="4914"></persName><hi>, was appointed by the Crown in 1914. He gave me the impression of a futile, shiftless person, but he assured me that under his ministry the congregation had tripled. We had lunch at Bitterley Court with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wheeler</hi><persName xml:id="4906"></persName><hi>. The house dates from 1600 A.D., and is finely placed about 600 feet above the sea&#8211;level. Bitterley = Butterlea, i.e. fat pasture, the fertility of the soil being extraordinary. In the afternoon I confirmed about 90 candidates in Ludlow. The glorious parish church lends itself well to such a function. I was pleased to see that a considerable congregation came together to witness the Confirmation. After having tea at the Rectory, we motored back to Hereford, arriving in the Palace shortly after 7 p.m. The weather was fine all day so that we motored with the car open, &amp; were able to enjoy the scenery. On our return journey a large white owl flew slowly across the road as we passed. Sheep with attendant lambs are difficult to negociate with a motor, when their shepherding is entrusted to small children.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
