<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At last a genuine spring day, bright sun and gentle air. I walked in the garden with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Reichel</hi><persName xml:id="413"></persName><hi rend="italic"> after breakfast, &amp; counted the rooks' nests. There are now 21 distributed over 3 trees in the proportions 15, 4, 2. I shewed R. the entries in my journal relating to the controversies of January 1918, and also </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam's</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName><hi rend="italic"> article in the CQ<ref xml:id="1002"></ref>. He had been among those who understood "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">ex animo</hi><hi rend="italic">" as = literally, and not, as I must needs maintain as = sincerely: but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he declared himself satisfied on the point</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I confirmed 16 boys from the Cathedral school and 2 men from Kimbolton, and, after lunch, motored with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> to Stoke Bliss, and there consecrated an addition to the Churchyard. The little church is beautifully situated. It contains a carved pulpit and reading desk of 1635. The parson, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi><persName xml:id="4876"></persName><hi>, has come from Brixton. Before leaving the church I gave a short address which seemed to please the clergy, of whom four had come to the function. The drive back to Hereford was illustrated with very noble prospects. <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> came to do the letters. He said that he had received news of his mother's death. <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> came to see me. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Webb</hi><persName xml:id="4867"></persName><hi>, Penelope's<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> sister, arrived for a short visit. I wrote a number of letters before going to bed, and thus ended another busy &amp; futile day. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There is clearly no prospect of any other work then this gipsy business of confirmations until Easter has come &amp; gone</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
