<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Pearce's<persName xml:id="636"></persName> Consecration</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The collect for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Matthias's Day will always have a curious interest for me, for it was used</hi><hi rend="underline"> against</hi><hi> me as a suitable prayer for the use of those who would hinder my consecration.<note xml:id="365" n="1"></note> By obvious implication I was comparable with "the traitor Judas" from whose like the Church was to be 'always preserved'. Now, after bearing the yoke of the episcopate for a whole year, I go to take a share in laying the same yoke on Ernest Pearce. The reminiscences of the Bishops who refused to take part in my consecration must needs be mingled when they find themselves associated with me in the consecration of another. They will hardly have been reconciled to my presence on the Bench by their experience of me during the past year, for I have been mostly in conflict with them all the time, and am on the verge of another open collision this week.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The service in the Abbey was very solemn &amp; impressive. There was no waiting fear of some explosion of fanaticism as last year when I was consecrated. There were, I think, 12 bishops assisting the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> in the laying on of hands. The sermon was preached by Edmund Pearce<persName xml:id="4827"></persName>, &amp; was suitable. We lunched with the Gows<persName xml:id="216"><persName xml:id="542"></persName></persName>. Later I went to the Nursing Home, and had tea with Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, who looked very frail &amp; pretty. I did not stay long, as I feared to do her injury by over–fatigue in talking.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
