<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a change in the weather, which became warm and wet. I was incapacitated by headache for any useful work. In the course of the morning I tried to "work off" my incapacity by sawing, but with little success. It is sad to think how much time is lost by the physical consequences of changes in the weather. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came to lunch, as also Money&#8211;Kyrle<persName xml:id="4330"></persName> &amp; his wife.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My first article<ref xml:id="1056"></ref> made its appearance in the "Times" this morning, where it has been clipped into the compass of a single column</hi><ref xml:id="1056"><ref xml:id="1057"></ref></ref><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">It will, perhaps, set some people thinking on the course to which the Church is being committed. Knight<persName xml:id="4299"></persName> of Holmer came to see me. He is very insistent that his curate, Stanley<persName xml:id="4853"></persName>, merits preferment, in spite of the fact that he has no degree, and is of brief standing in the diocese. Then Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came to do the letters: &amp; I made such preparations for departure tomorrow as were possible.</hi><hi> In response to a request from Ellershaw<persName xml:id="3459"></persName> and How<persName xml:id="3685"></persName>, I wrote to Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> suggesting that he should nominate Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> for the degree of D. Litt: when he is inaugurated as Chancellor next term. </hi><hi rend="underline">A </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Baptist minister, the Rev</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Herbert Gratton<persName xml:id="4766"></persName>, writes to me on the subject of his ordination in the Church of England. He seems to be a man of unusual ability</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
