<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The frost continues with more than a suspicion of fog. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the day in the Convocation house</hi><hi>, where the debate was uncommonly dull. I forgot my engagement to lunch with Bevan, &amp; lunched in the Church House.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">During the afternoon we had a discussion on the proposed permission to women to do in the churches all that laymen may do. Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> proposed a "principle" which I ridiculed as nothing of the kind! We came to no vote, but were to refer the matter to a Joint C</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">tee</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">There was a breeze at the last minute, when most of the bishops had left, over an amendment to the address which the Lower House proposed. It made a truculent reference to the demand for self&#8211;government. I protested against the intrusion of contentious matter into a formal document, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Gore vigourously defended it</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Finally, two bishops were entrusted with the task of drafting something which should satisfy the Lower House without being actually offensive.</hi><hi> I called on Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> and had tea with her. Then I returned to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and after writing some letters, dined with the Bishop of Southampton<persName xml:id="1123"></persName>. Athelstan Riley<persName xml:id="213"></persName>, in a high state of excitement, told me that he was standing for Oxford University!! Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> seemed to think that there might be some difficulty in finding anyone to oppose him. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But I will not believe that the University could sink to Riley</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
