<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Elizabeth<persName xml:id="4472" display="no"></persName> accompanied me in the car. We started at 10 a.m., and arrived in </hi><hi rend="underline">Bredwardine</hi><hi> in good time for the Confirmation at 11 a.m. There were 21 candidates, of whom but 4 were from the parish itself. After lunching at the Vicarage we motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Presteigne</hi><hi>, going out of our way at Kington &amp; travelling about 10 miles superfluously, but arriving in time for the Confirmation at 3.30 p.m. I confirmed 55 candidates in the parish church, which is large and interesting. The persistent coughing of the congregation &amp; some of the candidates disturbed me grievously. There has been much influenza in the parish.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Rector of Presteigne is the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. H. L. Kewley</hi><persName xml:id="4793"></persName><hi>, who was appointed as long ago as 1898, after serving as curate in the parish for four years. Thus for a whole quarter of a century he has worked in the place, and from his 1705 parishioners he expects between 200 and 300 to communicate at Easter! This seems rather disappointing. </hi><hi rend="italic">He told me there was much dissent in Presteigne, and that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the War had greatly injured his work</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The returned soldiers had altogether lost the habit of church&#8211;going. He spoke in a disheartened way, which rather distressed me, but the endowment is no less than &#x00A3;923 and he could hardly be moved.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
