<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[214]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the cathedral at 8 a.m., and celebrated the Holy Communion. The two archdeacons<persName xml:id="4450"><persName xml:id="3618"></persName></persName> assisted.</hi><hi rend="italic">Instead of going to Mattins I remained in my study, and read a very interesting &amp; suggestive volume just published by the Cambridge Press called "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Christ, S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Francis &amp; Today</hi><hi rend="italic">"<ref xml:id="1049"></ref> by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">G. G. Coulton</hi><persName xml:id="4746"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It is full of good and acute </hi><hi rend="italic underline">dicta</hi><hi rend="italic">, but disfigured by a good deal of what I must needs call bombast. The parallel between Franciscanism and Christianity is curiously close. S. Francis more or less consciously modelled his career on that of Jesus: and the tradition in both cases exemplifies the play of the same forces. The XIX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century produces another parallel, also illuminating in the history of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Babism</hi><hi rend="italic">. The book consists of lectures delivered during the War, &amp; they reflect the excitements of the time. There was a great deal of exaggerated sentiment, and not a little sheer nonsense, evoked by the experiences of an unprecedented crisis. Looking back on it all, one is divided between amusement &amp; humiliation. Men are very little changed by what they have gone through: and, after having been represented as heroes, are being discovered to be only the ordinary British folk they always were – goodnatured in the main, but lazy &amp; unimaginative, very easily gulled by agitators &amp; astonishingly suspicious.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
