<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Major Thelwell<persName xml:id="4861"></persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="1812"></persName> took their departure after breakfast having first photographed me in the garden. Then I finished the sermon on "Sound learning". M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Rushton<persName xml:id="4842"></persName> the new Vicar of All Saints and his wife came to lunch: &amp; later in the afternoon M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Baldwin, friends of <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived. Then <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> did the letters, and for all useful purposes the day was over.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My letter "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Scotticising the English Church</hi><hi rend="italic">"<ref xml:id="1061"></ref> appeared in the "Times".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">An official of S.C.V.D.<orgName xml:id="316" display="no"></orgName> called upon me. I could not imagine what the initials might mean. They stood for the sufficiently sinister label. "Society for controlling Venereal Disease". He wanted me to approve a meeting, &amp; the starting of a branch in Hereford. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But I was not sympathetic, for I doubt the prudence and practical value of this new fashion of parading "Pudenda" from the housetops</hi><hi rend="i bold">;</hi><hi rend="italic"> and I think this little city has been overmuch filled with this kind of doctrine for some months past. The feminist agitation is almost wholly concerned with it. Literature of the purity&#8211;pornic type has been poured upon us &amp; the female population is now mainly divided between the Suspected and Imperilled and the Suspicious &amp; Secure! However, I sent the man on to the Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
