<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the day at Lambeth in the meeting of Bishops. The matters discussed were of more than ordinary interest. In the forenoon </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> brought forward the scheme of re–union which he has been elaborating with the Wesleyans, or rather with a section of them</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">Watts Ditchfield<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, speaking as an ex. Methodist, gave an illuminating account of the situation, and shewed that the 'rank &amp; file' were very far from approving the scheme. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I criticized it severely, and challenged the Evangelical Bishops to say whether they were really prepared to stand on the necessity of Episcopacy. The Bishops of Durham<persName xml:id="276"></persName> and Manchester responded to my challenge by repudiating the dogma. Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> made a strange speech, in which he said that matters had almost reached breaking–point with the "Catholic" party in the C. of England</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Ultimately we passed a vague resolution rather to save Ingram's face than from any other motive. In the afternoon Russell Wakefield<persName xml:id="421"></persName> brought forward the delicate and difficult question of Control of the Birth–rate. There was a considerable discussion which, however, disclosed a very divided state of episcopal opinion. The subject is new to many of the bishops, and repulsive to all; but the necessity of reckoning with it is becoming apparent, &amp; I thought there was a sound of concession in the atmosphere.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> raised the question of the Church's attitude toward the Peace, &amp; spoke rather strongly of our failure to recognize responsibility as a Church. Ingram repudiated the suggestion so far as the diocese of London is concerned, &amp; referred with some complacency to the nine days of continuous prayer which he had ordered on two occasions. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I rose &amp; expressed the hope that we should have no more archiepiscopal summonses to prayer. I said that I could not accept the doctrine of prayer which was involved in the Bishop of London's procedures: that the Gospel insisted on forgiveness as the condition of acceptable prayer, &amp; that this condition was absent from the prayers of congregations, who assumed the truth of their own view of the Germans. I said that these repeated "war–prayers" provoked something like moral nausea in many thoughtful &amp; devout minds. Gore spoke in the same sense. It is odd how often he and I come together in our conclusions, while opposed in our reasonings</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi> We dined with the Johnson–Fergusons<persName xml:id="995"><persName xml:id="996"></persName></persName>. Lord Southwark (erstwhile Causton<persName xml:id="4734"></persName>) was there, &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="4735"></persName>. Also Sir E (?) [sic]<persName xml:id="3345"></persName> and Lady Moon. With the latter I had much pleasant conversation: &amp; generally it was quite a pleasant dinner–party. We returned by the underground railway, &amp; were home a little before midnight.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
