<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read the "Times" &#8211; a very Baruch&#8211;roll of trouble &#8211; in bed before getting up: breakfasted very badly (still neither butter nor marmalade, though the slum&#8211;dwellers can get both!) in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>: had my hair cut &amp;c: and then walked to 11 Queen Anne's Street, off Cavendish Square, where I had a brief interval with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Colyer<persName xml:id="4740"></persName>, the dentist. He gave an ill report but insisted on my being radiographed before he could decide on a policy for my teeth!! He named M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> C. A. Clarke, 42 Welbeck S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> : W. as competent for the business, &amp; I arranged over the telephone to see him on Saturday at 10.30 a.m. Then I returned to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> and lunched. This meal ended, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I walked to Lambeth, &amp; spent the time up to 6 p.m. in the Meeting of Bishops</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Archbishop of C.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> gave some account of his recent visit to France, with which he seemed well&#8211;pleased. He also announced that the next Lambeth Conference would probably be held in July, 1920. The Bishop of Lichfield<persName xml:id="3831"></persName> having brought forward the subject of the "National Mission" Reports. I made a short speech on the same, more crudely phrased than I c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have wished. But, nevertheless, I said some true things. Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, as Bishop&#8211;elect of Worcester, was present. I dined at the Athenaeum, &amp; afterwards had some talk with Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
