<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> tells me that his motion &#x00E0; propos the Enabling Bill will be seconded by Lord Crewe<persName xml:id="1056"></persName>. This may, perhaps, give a more definitely party colour to it than is pleasant. It might mean that the Asquithian Liberals will add English Disestablishment to their platform. Then I shall be reviled as the villain of the piece! Yet it will but be the fulfilment of my prophecy that the attempt to secure "self&#8211;government" can only precipitate disestablishment</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">As I understand the project, any material alteration in the scheme, which the Bill is to 'enable', effected by Parl</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic">, will taint it with Erastianism, and disqualify it for "Catholick" acceptance! Yet it is surely impossible that any self&#8211;respecting imperial legislature can permit itself to be hustled by this "take&#8211;it&#8211;or&#8211;leave&#8211;it" attitude.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I walked to the dentist after breakfast. On the way </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I overtook M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Justice Darling<persName xml:id="4032"></persName>, &amp; had some talk with him. He told me that the general opinion of the lawyers was adverse to the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">After finishing with the dentist, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> &amp; wrote letters. Then I walked to 28 Queen Anne's Gate and lunched with Lord Haldane. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We discussed the method of opposing the Enabling Bill. He says that Lord Crewe<persName xml:id="1056"></persName> will second his resolution</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">Then I walked to</hi><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi><hi rend="italic">Lambeth, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">spent the afternoon in the Bishops' meeting, where we discussed the situation of the Welsh Church. I said that it w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be intolerable to have the disestablished bishops in the Canterbury Convocation, &amp; that alike in the interest of the Church in Wales and in that of the Church of England, there sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be a separate province of Wales created. This was on the whole the prevailing opinion. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> wrote on a slip of paper, and passed across the table to me, a question. Whether in my heart of hearts I believed that the Establishment c</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">last 50 years. I wrote in reply, "No; I don't think it will last 10", and returned the slip to him</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">At tea&#8211;time</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> observed to me, "I think you'll win". Indeed I myself think that any serious opposition in Parliament will defeat the Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There was a pleasant dinner&#8211;party. George Prothero<persName xml:id="319"></persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="664"></persName>, J. G. Butcher<persName xml:id="2092"></persName>, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ware<persName xml:id="3786"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Napier<persName xml:id="4822"></persName> were there. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I had some talk with Butcher about the Enabling Bill which he has rashly promised to support. He agreed that, if it got into Committee, it must be amended. Earlier in the day, I met Marriott<persName xml:id="4624"></persName>, who also was one of the pledged, but who said that my letters in the Times had shown him that he had been mistaken</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
