<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in writing letters<note xml:id="461" n="1"></note>, and then the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came to lunch. After this, I presided for an hour and a half over the inspectors of religious instruction in the elementary schools. Then I discussed the Diocesan Messenger with Parker<persName xml:id="4647"></persName>, whom I have asked to be Editor. Then I sawed wood for an hour, &amp; did my letters with Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I read through the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> criticism of the Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> Scheme.<note xml:id="316" n="2"></note> It is carefully composed with much expert knowledge and not a little adroitness</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> But it is vitiated by one fatal and pervading fallacy. The Reformation is ignored throughout. It is everywhere assumed that the old names carried the old senses. There was </hi><hi rend="italic underline">no</hi><hi rend="italic"> spiritual revolution in the XVI</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century, altering religious values and giving a new direction to religious development. This shallow &amp; fictionary manner of treating ecclesiastical history is characteristic of all these so–called "Catholicks". They live in a complete 'fool's paradise" of make–believe. They are isolated from the general conscience, and all but unintelligible to the general mind. But from their own perverse standpoint their position appears to be unassailable. Their reasoning is close and accurate: their definitions are precise: their knowledge of detail is astonishing: their conclusions are equally inevitable and absurd.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
