<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The river was half frozen. It is reported that there were 20 degrees of frost in London last night. Though bitterly cold, the day was bright &amp; pleasant. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off with her guests to Ludlow by the 9.15 a.m. train: and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I went to London by the 9.55 a.m. vi&#x00E2; Gloucester</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The Dean of G. &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> came into the train there, &amp; beguiled the journey with conversation. At Paddington I had the good fortune to get a taxi at once, &amp; was thus brought to Garland's without difficulty. I had tea in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; there had some talk with the Archbishop of C.<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, Sir Lewis Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName>, &amp; Justice M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">c</hi><hi rend="italic">Cardie<persName xml:id="4325"></persName>. The latter was very interesting on the topic of prohibition: he said that his experience as a Judge did not bear out the view that "drink" was the principal cause of crime. I mentioned Lord Gorell's<persName xml:id="663"></persName> opinion that "drink" occasioned most divorce&#8211;suits: &amp; he said that his experience in that court was to the opposite effect. The Bishop of Southampton<persName xml:id="1123"></persName> was in the Club. We sate together at dinner, &amp; talked. He said that the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> had explicitly given him to understand the he (the Bp. of W.) did not object to his taking part in my consecration last February. I told him how deeply I resented the behaviour of the Bishops, and how essentially unjust that behaviour appeared to me, the more I considered it.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
