<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Lady Chapel at 8 a.m. It was a solemn service</hi><hi rend="i bold">, </hi><hi rend="italic">very devotional. The glorious epistle at once abashes and consoles me. The first, surely, for if 'Charity'</hi><hi rend="italic underline">be</hi><hi rend="italic"> the root of the matter, what place have I – torn with a thousand feuds – in the Christian ranks? But, the last, as surely, for if 'Charity' be thus supreme, then this vehement insistence on creeds &amp; politics is – as from my soul I believe indeed – wholly beside the mark. There is, as I can see things, not the least chance of my going back on such beliefs as I have grown to with respect to churches &amp; creeds, &amp; so far I am already sentenced for weal or woe: but there might conceivably be some advance towards this indispensable grace of "charity", since there, not my poor puzzled intellect is concerned, but my conscience &amp; will, answering to the approaches of the Divine Spirit. And of these blessed approaches I am not, thank God!, wholly unconscious, though, alas! my response to them has been hitherto woefully small. So from my heart I repeat the Collect for today, &amp; make my prayer for "that most excellent gift of charity".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought a letter from the Archbishop of Upsala<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> accepting my suggestion of dates for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Olaus Petri</hi><hi> lectures viz:&#8211; Sept. 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st </hi><hi> &#8211; Oct 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. That arrangement must presumably be regarded as settled, though how the lectures are to be prepared, I cannot imagine.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I stayed in my study until lunch, writing letters and preparing notes for the afternoon. The South African, Banfield<persName xml:id="4714"></persName>, came to lunch. We found him intelligent, well&#8211;mannered, and communicative. He went with us to Lugwardine, where I dedicated a cross in the open air to the memory of the men from the village who had fallen in the War. There was a short service in the parish church (S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's) at which I preached from Galatians VI.14. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Far be it from me to glory save in the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi><hi>". There was a considerable congregation which listened with attention. Then there was a procession to the Cross, some more prayers, a hymn, &amp; the Benediction. It all seemed very devotional. The churchwarden said to me "I liked your sermon, Sir: I never thought of all that before". There seem to have been some misgivings in the parish about the Cross, so that my discourse may have a tranquillising effect. We had tea with Lady Croft<persName xml:id="4541"></persName>. There was a company of her family &amp; neighbours. Banfield seemed to be interested. He is, perhaps, a little dismayed at finding ordination a more inaccessible thing than he had supposed. I do not see that I could have said anything different. The weather all day long was mild and bright so that the out&#8211;of&#8211;doors function had every advantage.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lady Croft told me that Bishop Atlay<persName xml:id="4713"></persName> told her of an Ordination Candidate to whom he had said, "Now, don't forget the Butler", alluding to the illustrious author of the "Analogy". The young man replied that he already given the butler half&#8211;a&#8211;crown, and begged to know what the proper amount of the tip should be!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
