<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; celebrated the Holy Comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi>.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Then I set to writing the article on the Church of England which I promised. It resolved itself into a rather savage attack on the Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> Scheme, which I sum up as a proposal for Disestablishment without Disendowment. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">This is to be followed up by a second Article on the lines of what I have written in the "Modern Churchman". This will indicate the alternative policy</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi> I attended a meeting in the Kemble Theatre, and looked at a series of films designed to illustrate the methods of combating Tuberculosis. Miss M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi> Gaw explained the films in advance. Then I made a short speech, and D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Gold, the Medical Officer of Health, a long one, during which the audience was slipping away. The night was very wet, and, notwithstanding, there was a considerable audience. I hope these meetings do good. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is rather curious that I should be slipping into a kind of Christian Socialist position, in spite of my life–long refusal to be mixed up in politics. But the public mind no longer concerns itself with the interests which used to be called spiritual, and the next world is quite unable any longer to hold its own in competition with the world present: so that the miserable "sky–pilot" is really much at a loss to find any intelligible rôle in modern society. He casts about to make himself useful in any direction, however humble</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
