<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fine but very cold day with some threatenings of fog. After breakfasting in the hotel, and getting shaved. I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended the opening of Convocation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName>, Dean of Westminster, was admitted Prolocutor in the place of Stocks</hi><persName xml:id="1219"></persName><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> I visited the dentist, &amp; then returned to the Church House, &amp; spent the afternoon in the Convocation. Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> fetched me away at 5 p.m. to the House of Lords, where I sate on the steps of the Throne for a few minutes, watching the debate on the address. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is sad to think that I shall probably never get any farther into the House before the Bishops are clean swept out of it</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi><hi> Then I walked to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. I wound up the day by dining with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> &amp; his sister<persName xml:id="2109" display="no"></persName>. Nickson<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> was there, and we had a good deal of talk. He told me that during the 4 years since he has been Bishop of Bristol he has spent about &#x00A3;4000 of private income, so that, if there had been no pension to his predecessor, he would have just managed to live on the official income. Of course these four years have not been normal; hospitality has almost ceased: &amp; a Bishop has moved about as little as possible.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
