<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[84]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to Westminster, &amp; spent the day in the Representative Church Council. It had been anticipated that there w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be difficulty in seating the members, for no room was available except for the Hoare Memorial Hall, which could not accommodate much more than half the number of the Council. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">However not more than half the members attended</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Partly, the influenza, partly the fear of it, partly the difficulty of getting lodgings kept many away. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">As I entered the Hall two letters were handed to me. They were from the Bishops of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> and Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, stating that illness prevented their attendance. As these were my principal allies, their absence was disastrous</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> introduced the report of the "Grand Committee", </hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; then I spoke at some length against the whole scheme. On the whole my speech was well received, and even cheered at the close</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> followed, &amp; was very polite to me. Then the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> interposed with a very adroit &amp; telling speech, which was entirely to the taste of the Council, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; gave the 'coup de gr&#x00E2;ce' to opposition</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> After the Council had risen I walked to 5 Carlton House Terrace, &amp; had tea with Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName>. Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> was there, &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined us. Then we drove back to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's Deanery, &amp; dined quietly with our host.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
