<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather continues to be bitterly cold: and the sodden state of the ground hinders all work on the land. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">As demobilization proceeds, the number of the unemployed men &amp; women, &amp; adolescents of both sexes increases rapidly. Foreign trade is at a standstill, and the greater industries are thoroughly disaffected</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The foreign news could not be worse. While the Paris Conference appears to be paralyzed by inner conflicts, the Bolshevist menace becomes daily more formidable. Hungary has now gone over to the enemy, &amp; the position of Poland and Roumania has been rendered almost hopeless. Egypt is in hardly&#8211;suppressed revolt: and the situation in the Balkans worsens daily. The pressure of hunger grows daily more severe, and hunger is the Forerunner of Bolshevism. There is no confidence in the Government; Parliament threatens to break up into a congeries of groups, whose support must be purchased by bargaining. Ireland is completely out of hand, and may break out into open rebellion at any moment. The financial condition of the country is deplorable. Already a Budget of no less than &#x00A3;1500,000,000</hi><hi> [sic] </hi><hi rend="italic">is announced: probably the amount needed will be much larger. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a letter of condolence to the Vicar of Montgomery, who has lost his wife: also, I wrote an appreciation of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Forrest<persName xml:id="936"></persName>, &amp; sent it to his biographer, Leckie<placeName xml:id="4796"></placeName>: also I sent a reply to an application for advice from a Swedenborgian Minister. Then I worked at the sermon for Jimmie<persName xml:id="88"></persName>, &amp; then I was visited by two of my clergy in succession. After lunch I sawed wood, went to Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; wrote more letters till dinner time. Was there ever such a squirrel's cage of a life! D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Patterson<persName xml:id="4893" display="no"></persName> came in after dinner, &amp; renewed his injections of my arm with some anti&#8211;boil virus.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It occurs to me that it might be a reasonable pretext for postponing my Swedish visit till next year, that the Lambeth Conference is to meet next summer. I should certainly be better able to understand Anglicanism after attending that assembly. Besides, the "Life &amp; Liberty" agitation<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note> will have arrived at some </hi><hi rend="underline">d&#x00E9;nouement</hi><hi>. If the lectures could be postponed, I might have a more reasonable chance of preparing them. As it is, I hardly see how I can produce anything adequate. This unhappy Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> hangs round my neck like the avenging albatross about the Ancient Mariner's: &amp; the prospect of being under the dentist for Heaven knows what violences does not facilitate any form of literary effort. So I think I shall try for a postponement.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
