<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> writes to ask my opinion of the following "reasoned amendment" to the 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Reading motion</hi><hi rend="italic"> on June 3</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rd</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"To leave out all words after "that" in order to insert the words This House is unwilling to assent, without full preliminary &amp; independent inquiry, to legislation which will exclude from participation in the affairs of an Established Church a large portion of the nation, &amp; which will enable that Church without adequate control by Parliament, to make laws that may completely alter its constitution".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote to express my approval of this amendment, and added some observations on the personnel &amp; method of the Archbishops' Committee in order to show that it did not provide anything which could fairly be called "full preliminary and independent inquiry".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> A. Boyd Carpenter<persName xml:id="4729"></persName> M.P. wrote to say that he was opposed to the Bill as it stands, and asking for advice as to the best course of action, when it reaches the H. of Commons. "Other parties are fairly well organised in support of the Bill, and unless we can do something, no concerted action against the Bill will be possible!"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Measure for Measure</hi><hi>". It contains some very noble passages. The interview between Angels and Isabella is full of good things.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Ang</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your brother is a forfeit of the law,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And you but waste your words.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Isab</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Alas, Alas!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Why, all the souls that were, were forfeit once:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And He that might the vantage best have took.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Found out the remedy. How would you be,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>If He, which is the top of judgment, should</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But judge you as you are? O! Think on that:</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And mercy then will breathe within your lips,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Like man new made.</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Again, Isabella uses the well&#8211;known lines:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>O! it is excellent</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To have a giant's strength: but it is tyrannous</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To use it like a giant.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Again, in the same dialogue:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>but man, proud man!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Drest in a little brief authority, – </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Most ignorant of what he's most assur'd,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>His glassy essence, – like an angry ape,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Plays such fantastic tricks before high heaven,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As make the angels weep.</hi>
         </p>
</div></body></text></TEI>
