<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We travelled to London vi&#x00E2; Gloucester, leaving Hereford at 9.50 a.m., and arriving in Paddington about 3.45 p.m. After some delay, we secured a</hi>   
<hi rend="underline">taxi</hi><hi>, &amp; drove to 35 Eaton Square, where I left <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>: and then went on to Garlant's Hotel where I had secured rooms. I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> where I found the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, and Sir H. Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>. Lord Parmoor<persName xml:id="1736"></persName> laid hold of me with some talk of a letter to the "Times" on the matter of feeding the starving population in mid&#8211;Europe. He wanted me to sign it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Fisher<persName xml:id="2107"></persName> was in the reading room, &amp; I had an interesting talk with him. He said that Wilson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> impressed him as genuine, &amp; that he was an admirable speaker. We spoke of Oxford, &amp; I expressed the opinion that he ought to succeed Prothero<persName xml:id="1394"></persName>. He replied that he would have desired nothing better had he not been already committed to his present seat. He was rather anxious about Oxford lest it should provoke public interference by appealing for public funds. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Riley<persName xml:id="213"></persName> &amp; I dined together, &amp; had much talk. He &amp; his friends want to wreck the Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> Scheme,<note xml:id="316" n="1"></note> &amp; so do I. Beyond that community of object we have nothing in common</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He was very communicative on his relations with the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> who uses him as his intermediary in his dealings with the Eastern Churches. He said that he (Riley) wrote the prayer which their <persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130">Graces</persName></persName> recommended for use in behalf of the Russian Church. This is an odd situation. The Archbishop is not well&#8211;placed for standing up to these "Catholick" law&#8211;breakers, when privately he is under obligations to them. Hicks<persName xml:id="2261"></persName>, who has charge of the aspirants to Ordination who, to the number of about 2000, have come from the Army [sic]. He speaks well of them, but thinks there are too many of the "server", &amp; "Sunday School Teacher" class.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
