<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Confirmation addresses must needs have a common character, since all must have reference to the same limited subjects, and be addressed to the same types of persons. This year I have dwelt mainly on the interest and importance of adolescence, taking as my theme the Prayer&#8211;Book phrase, "years of discretion", and treating it as a description of the critical years from 14 to 20 which intervene between childhood and adult life. Then I have spoken of the difficulties and resources of the Christian life, to which in a manner Confirmation introduces us. I have commonly added something about the critical situation in the world, in which the need for Christian men &amp; women is paramount, if the bright dreams of "reconstruction" are not to vanish into smoke. Beyond a few words about the Holy Communion, and some concluding words about the solemnity &amp; significance of the answer which candidates must return to the Bishop's question, I say scarcely anything which could be called "technical" or specifically Anglican. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Very often the Dissenting ministers and other Nonconformists attend the services, and sometimes they are introduced to me. They volunteer expressions of admiration of the service, which several assured me they had never before witnessed</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">It is still the case, as Baxter<persName xml:id="5"></persName> said, that Confirmation might become an instrument of a wide reconciliation between English Christians.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[134]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the morning in my room composing a letter on Confirmation for the next issue of the "Diocesan Messenger". Meanwhile I sent the chauffer with the car to Bridgnorth to get some equipment for tomorrow's travelling.</hi><hi> After lunch I motored into Bridgnorth and confirmed 180 candidates in S. Mary Magdalene's Church. Then I motored to Highley, and there confirmed 12 candidates, of whom 10 were boys. The Church was well&#8211;filled mostly with young men from the adjacent colliery. So, though the number of candidates was so petty, I was glad that I had made the effort to get to this very awkwardly placed parish. The roads are dreadful. I did not get back to Aldenham Park before 8.40 p.m. </hi><hi rend="bold">The </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Barber&#8211;Starkeys</hi><persName xml:id="4120"><persName xml:id="4716"></persName></persName><hi> have rented this house from Lord Acton<persName xml:id="4183"></persName> for more than 30 years. They are now leaving as the present peer intends to reside here: but they have taken a house in the neighbourhood, not so ample in scale or so delightfully situated, but adequate for their needs. They are kind and hospitable people, very well disposed towards the Church, &amp; towards the Bishop. I promised to bring <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> here in June, when I confirm at Much Wenlock.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
