<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> John's at 8 a.m. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">No clergyman appeared, and none seemed to be expected! There were more than 30 persons in the chapel, including some of the school boys whom I confirmed on Friday. I celebrated, and when the service was half over, Eckett<persName xml:id="4551"></persName> the minor canon came hurriedly in to assist me. He was not on duty, but had been fetched from his house</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">This indecent incident moved my indignation which was not moderated by the information that it was nothing unusual for the congregation either to disperse without any service at all or to wait for 20 minutes or more while a clergyman was obtained. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There are certainly disadvantages about an octogenarian Dean</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> is reported to be ill with an attack of influenza. However, another man was sent from the Garage, who drove me to Cradley, where I confirmed 23 persons. The parson, Prebendary Janvrin<persName xml:id="4785"></persName>, was formerly Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's in Hereford. The church is modern, but the tower is ancient &amp; very interesting – a Norman shell encasing a Saxon wattle &amp; daub building. From Cradley I went on to Ledbury where I lunched with the Vicar<persName xml:id="4525"></persName>, &amp; then confirmed 96 persons in the glorious parish church. On returning to Hereford I went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Martin's, and instituted <persName xml:id="4506">Beattie</persName> to that Vicarage. <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName>, as Rural Dean, inducted him. There was a crowded congregation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
