<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> congratulating him on his election to succeed Prothero<persName xml:id="1394"></persName> in the representation of the University. I offered S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Devereux&#8211;with&#8211;Wormbridge to the Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> R. Pelly<persName xml:id="4654"></persName></hi>.<hi> Then I spent the whole morning in writing to the Archbishop of Upsala<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>, and drafting a scheme of the Olaus Petri lectures. Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> came to lunch, and, when the meal was ended, poured out his tale of woe from Bredwardine. The most serious factor is the power these petty factions &amp; frictions have on his rather sensitive temperament. Then <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> walked with me for two hours: the bright sun and absence of wind made walking delightful. The Dean came to see me about various matters including the proposal made by some bereaved mother to set up a memorial crucifix to her son's memory. I dissuaded him from accepting the gift on grounds of expediency. Then I did the letters, &amp; cleared up my table which had become an Augean litter of letters, papers, &amp; books. </hi><hi rend="italic">After dinner I read the Swedish History from the "Cambridge Modern History" aloud to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. The easy transition of the Danish and Swedish monarchies from the constitutional or limited to the absolute or autocratic character is very remarkable. In both cases it was effected by the combination of King and People against the nobility. If James ii </hi><hi> [sic]</hi><hi rend="italic"> had not been a Papist and a fool, it w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have happened also in England.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
