<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Feast of Epiphany, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent what I had written to Major<persName xml:id="3660"></persName>, perhaps foolishly, but, having promised him a contribution, I did not care to refuse it. I went to the dentist, but he did nothing. Then I sawed up wood for an hour. Lillie walked with me after lunch. He is an interesting &amp; stimulating companion.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I read through Bethune–Baker's<persName xml:id="4131"></persName> "The Faith of the Apostles' Creed"<ref xml:id="1039"></ref>, with great approbation, which I expressed in a letter to the Author</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He sets out with much force the position which I have maintained for years past. It is a happy coincidence that his little book should appear together with the Bishop of Ely's<persName xml:id="532"></persName> "Belief and Creed" to which it provides the effectual antidote. There is something significant &amp; suggestive in the spectacle of two Cambridge scholars of recognised eminence, dealing with the same material &amp; coming to diametrically opposed conclusions. That spectacle alone is enough to disprove the rigid position of the orthodox. It is a curious circumstance that the two academic bishops, Oxford &amp; Ely, should be the protagonists of obscurantism! </hi><hi> The Congregational Minister, <persName xml:id="4492">Bowen</persName>, called on me. He had seen Wilson<persName xml:id="4881"></persName> in Manchester &amp; was greatly impressed by his leonine head &amp; irresistible smile. Eckett<persName xml:id="4551"></persName> came to arrange about the "Emergency" work, which Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> resigns: and <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne–Willson</persName> came to do the letters. Thus was frittered away another day. </hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
