<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The line to be taken in Convocation is not easy to determine. I shall plead the fact that I have no seat in the House of Lords as an excuse for "taking up my parable" in the Convocation. I shall add that certain circumstances indicated that the crucial decision of the R.C.C. on the baptismal franchise was not very secure, e.g. Lord Hugh Cecil's<persName xml:id="314"></persName> language at the time, Bp. Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName> resignation. Then I shall develope such points as the following:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>&#x3B1; The methods by which the Scheme has been advocated are unprecedented and misleading. A delusive unanimity is being manufactured. The action of the Abps.<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> has made the expression of dissent very difficult.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>&#x3B2; Emphatic disclaimer of any desire for Disestablishment. If the Bill goes to Parl</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> securities must be taken that the essential points of Establishment are preserved, e.g. The baptismal Franchise, the appellate jurisdiction of the Privy Council, the Crown Patronage of the Bpks &amp;c. These sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be "reserved" i.e. placed outside the action of the new "National Assembly".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I must say something about the anti&#8211;National temper wh. marks the agitation, &amp; examine the case of the German Church. The worst outrages on the Christian </hi><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi><hi> conscience have been the work of Churches, not of Nations. The Establishment cannot be maintained if the ideas which it presupposes are banished from the minds of Churchmen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We are witnessing the consequence of the Tractarian dominance within the Church (i.e. the clergy) Keble<persName xml:id="4601"></persName> favoured the separation of Church and State on the ground that the State was no longer Christian" [sic].</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I shall emphasize the spiritual value of the Establishment, and its large possibilities</hi><hi rend="bold">:</hi><hi> the evident risk, even the probability, of provoking Disestablishment by this attempt to secure the plausible but delusive advantage of "self&#8211;government": and I shall insist that only a clear prospect of securing an escape from our present evils could justify taken [sic] a course which imperils our present position. Is there any such prospect?</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Knight (erstwhile Kirschbaum<persName xml:id="62"></persName>) came to see me. He has decided to accept Bridstow, and I arranged provisionally to institute him on Sunday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He will be a great acquisition to the diocese if he can settle down to the life of a country parson, and his wife will be more serviceable in the country, which she likes, than in the town, which she has never liked. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> expresses himself as pleased with the prospect of having him as a successor, and Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> will be glad to have him within reach. He hopes to write books.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
