<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left the Palace at 9.45 a.m. and motored to Culmington where I confirmed 32 persons in the quaint little 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century church (All Saints). The fabric has been much abused, but it contains a fine double piscina, an Easter sepulchre, an unusually low arch leading from the tower into the church, and an odd steeple (or arrested steeple). The Rector, Rev. D .E. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Holland</hi><persName xml:id="4777"></persName><hi>, is a brother of Sir T. Erskine Holland<persName xml:id="776"></persName>, quondam Chichele professor of International Law. He is a delightful old parson, well&#8211;liked by his parishioners, of a type now, alas!, not often met with. We lunched at Culmington Manor but M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4897"></persName><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Shaw</hi><persName xml:id="4898"></persName><hi> had been called away by the illness of their infant child. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mason</hi><persName xml:id="4809"></persName><hi> the Vicar of Diddlebury with Westhope, a cheerful man with a very puzzling parish, lunched also, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jeffrey</hi><persName xml:id="4787"></persName><hi>, the Rector of Tugford and Vicar of Shipton (the population of both parishes is only 272). After lunch we motored to Halford where I administered Confirmation to 28 candidates in a tiny church. The parson, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">de Castro</hi><persName xml:id="4568"></persName><hi>, holds Halford with Sibdon Carwood, both parishes having less than 300 people.</hi><hi rend="italic">These tiny parishes constitute a grave problem. The clergy have not enough to do, and generally also they receive less than they can reasonably be expected to live upon &#8211; a double disablement for effective ministry, indolence and poverty.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
