<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I revised &amp; partly re&#8211;wrote a sermon for use in Shrewsbury on Thursday, and instituted two parsons – Astbury<persName xml:id="4575" display="no"></persName> to Llanveyno, and Talbot<persName xml:id="4859"></persName> to Neenton. The former came to lunch. In the afternoon, the Rev. W. H. F. Meredith<persName xml:id="4813"></persName>, Vicar of Neen Savage, called to see me. He had some notion of celebrating the completion of 20 years of ministry in his parish by some kind of special service. Then came Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName>, the V. of Leominster, &amp; wasted an hour &amp; a half of my working time by futile maundering over his parish troubles. He seems to have given up his project of seeking another exchange. Then <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> did the letters with me for an hour: &amp; he was followed by <persName xml:id="4492">Bowen</persName> &amp; Chubb, the sectaries, who came to arrange the "League of Nations" Committee. This is a grievous wastage of time, but seems too normal in episcopal experience.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Roosevelt's<persName xml:id="2340"></persName> death is reported. It was sudden and peaceful, as he was sleeping. He had grown into a very ardent friend of Great Britain, and was in the midst of a vehement attack on President Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName> when death overtook him. He had done much, and was only in his 61</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> year.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
