<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[227]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A short note from Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>: "I am getting my tackle ready for Tuesday, &amp; am in communication with the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>", acknowledges my "very full letter", and says that the references have proved valuable.</hi><hi> Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName> tells me that the Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName> is sending to every member of Parliament a copy of the memorandum drawn up some while since by Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName>, Emmet<persName xml:id="4214"></persName>, &amp; himself. This suggests some important &amp; useful amendments. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, who is in a good position for appraising opinion in London, writes:&#8211;</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The Enabling Bill is meeting with an increasing volume of opposition. Men who were in favour of it now declare their opposition, &amp; if only the case against it were stated effectively in the Lords next week we should hear no more about it…. It is said that several members in the Commons who formerly expressed their sympathy with the Bill are now contemplating opposition. Wolmer's<persName xml:id="1028"></persName> list of supporters must be revised".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName> writes, "P. J. Forsyth<persName xml:id="1520"></persName> has given our friends a nasty knock". The 'Times' has today a long letter from Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> replying to Forsyth, but with more embarrassment than conviction. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My letter appears</hi><ref xml:id="1065"></ref><hi rend="underline">,</hi><hi> and also a letter from Massie<persName xml:id="4810"></persName>, dealing with some effect with the Bishop of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName>. The plot thickens!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Potter</hi><hi>, now a master at the Cathedral school came to see me. He wants to get some kind of spiritual </hi><hi rend="underline">locus standi</hi><hi> in the diocese. I promised to grant him a preacher's license. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Davis</hi><persName xml:id="4543"></persName><hi>, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Weonard's, came to lunch. After lunch I had a grave talk with him about the situation in his parish. Hardly had he left my room, before </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Capper<persName xml:id="4911" display="no"></persName></hi><hi> appeared. So I had a grave talk with her about the same. They both made peaceful declarations, but I think it is a case of incompatible temperaments, and a discord of women! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored into the country, and paid some calls. We saw "the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> H. A. Wadman</hi><persName xml:id="4871"></persName><hi>, Vicar of Byford, and his wife. They have a large house, and a petty income. Then we had tea with Judge </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingham</hi><persName xml:id="4782"></persName><hi> and his wife, pleasant people living in a pleasant place. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On returning to the Palace, I did the correspondence with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName></hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">Hardly had I settled to my work before I was interrupted by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fred Tisdall</hi><persName xml:id="4865"></persName><hi rend="italic">, an 'old boy' of the Westminster period, who is stationed in Hereford for some special work. He is married and has 3 children. At the age of 32 he retains the frank good&#8211;humoured expression which distinguished the lad of 13, which was his age when first I made his acquaintance. He said that I was just the same to look at, but greyer!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I gave a Bible to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Melbourne</hi><persName xml:id="4892" display="no"></persName><hi>, and a Prayer book to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Randle</hi><persName xml:id="4891"></persName><hi>, as a reminder of their confirmation yesterday. It is, perhaps, worthwhile, for the memories of this time in their lives cannot be too well secured.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather continues bright and warm. There are signs of actual drought, &amp; the farmers begin to look anxious. It is more than commonly difficult to keep one's self to any work within doors, &amp; out of doors the very notion of work is repulsive!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Muir Mackenzie</hi><persName xml:id="601"></persName><hi rend="italic"> writes to propose a visit next week. He mentions the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic">reading debate of [^the^] Enabling Bill, and adds "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">if there are not too many other speakers I shall have a say</hi><hi rend="italic">". Here is yet another Scotchman interesting himself in the fate of the Church of England! Can it be the case that the Church has fallen so completely out of touch with the English people that, in this hour of fate, none is to be found who cares what way befall it? "Democracy", the cant of the hour, accords ill with the hierarchical principle, which must needs govern the arrangements of an episcopal church: and, though there are many Socialists among the inferior clergy, the discord between the root&#8211;ideas of Socialism and Christianity is too profound to be easily bridged, if bridged at all. The "Via media" is unpalatable, and indeed almost unintelligible to our zealots of the sacristies.</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>

