<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A perfect summer's day. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me again to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Colyer<persName xml:id="4740"></persName>, and there I "tried on" my new dental outfit – a painful performance as my jaw had not recovered from yesterday's violence. Then we returned to the Deanery, and I lay </hi><hi rend="italic underline">perdu</hi><hi rend="italic"> again, reading the "Times" and writing letters.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">At 6.30 p.m. I went again to M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Colyer, and came away with a whole catacomb of dead bones within my jaws</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi><hi rend="italic">As I returned to the Deanery, when I was crossing the space in front of the Cathedral, I fell in with Archdeacon Holmes<persName xml:id="3420"></persName> who forthwith began to speak with some vehemence against the Archbishops'<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Five&#8211;million pounds Fund</hi><hi rend="italic">". He had just ordered the removal of the large poster which the zeal of a minor canon had reared in front of Queen Anne's statue. He says that "the City", which he professes to know well, will have nothing to do with it. He told me that the general feeling in the Lower House of Convocation with regard to my proposal for a Royal Commission was one of alarm. Might it not report in favour of Disestablishment? I think it very probably could do so, but then we should have a clear issue proposed to the country, on which and informed &amp; deliberate decision could be invited. Now we shall drift into Disestablishment without realizing our course.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
