<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended a meeting of the "Joint Committee" on the Reform of the Lower House of the Convocation. Then followed the Council. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I intervened on the clause about the "inherent" authority of the Episcopate<ref xml:id="1058"></ref>, &amp; there was some brisk debating</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Many members congratulated me on my speech yesterday<ref xml:id="1059"></ref>, Sir Edward Clarke<persName xml:id="4002"></persName> was especially effusive</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">This morning I could not refrain from having a dig at the Abp<persName xml:id="128"></persName>. "It w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> appear that his Grace and I agree in the region of fact, but differ in the sphere of prophecy. Prophets, the most respected not less than the least regarded, must acquiesce in the necessity of referring to the Future the vindication of their prophetic character. Time will show whether the Archbishop's comparatively optimistic forecast is better grounded than my more sombre vaticinations". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Thetford<persName xml:id="4728"></persName> showed me a telegram announcing the death of the Dean of Norwich</hi><persName xml:id="208"></persName><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Beeching and I were very intimate friends at Westminster while we were both canons, &amp; we have always been on affectionate terms. His death makes life poorer. In the afternoon we discussed the question whether women should be members of the Assembly, &amp;, of course, we decided that they should. Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; I dined with the Campbell Dodgsons<persName xml:id="4753"><persName xml:id="4754"></persName></persName> very pleasantly. There was a young engineer&#8211;capitalist there, who spoke with much intelligence on labour questions.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
