<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the forenoon in writing a letter to the "Times" in answer to one by Canon Field<persName xml:id="4758"></persName> which appeared in today's issue. He appealed to the authority of the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, as sufficient guarantee of the wisdom of the Enabling Bill. I replied by pointing out that the true author of the Bill &amp; its policy was the Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, and that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">his</hi><hi rend="italic"> genuine opinions were probably disclosed in the petition which he presented to the Upper House of Convocation from 14 clergymen including one of his own examining chaplains.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName> writes to ask for assistance in offering opposition to the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Serres<persName xml:id="4066"></persName> &amp; his wife called in the afternoon. He drew me aside in order to ask advice as to a dispute between himself &amp; his churchwardens as to the custody of the keys of the safe containing the registers. The position is not very easy, for access to the registers is often required by papists &amp; sectaries, who bury their dead in their own fashion, &amp; record the burials in the parish register. If, as the churchwardens appear to demand, the Vicar is never to let the keys go out of his own hands, the poor man will be for ever dancing attendance on his ecclesiastical rivals – a tiresome &amp; invidious experience! However I counselled peaceful procedures.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
