<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I tried in the morning to write the concluding chapters of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, but with no success. Was there ever such a dead albatross about a literary "ancient mariner's" neck?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I took the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Ansons</hi><persName xml:id="302"></persName><hi> &amp; Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> to see some churches. We went first to </hi><hi rend="underline">Kilpeck</hi><hi>, then on to </hi><hi rend="underline">Abbey Dore</hi><hi>, then to </hi><hi rend="underline">Bacton</hi><hi>, and finally made a detour through </hi><hi rend="underline">Dorstone</hi><hi>, where we had tea very comfortably in the village inn, and returned through</hi> <hi rend="underline">Weobley</hi><hi>. These were 4 churches of unusual interest and beauty. Add that the road, almost the whole way, lay though a romantically beautiful country, and the description of a perfect tour is complete. We left the Palace at 2.30 p.m., and were back there again at 7.45 p.m. Deduct 1 1/4 hours for seeing the churches, and having tea, &amp; there are left 4 hours of steady motoring. The road lay through a hilly district, and was in some places in a very bad condition: accordingly, we did not exceed an average of 15 miles. But 60 miles in an afternoon is something far beyond the possibilities of prae&#8211;motoring days. The weather was at first dull &amp; threatening, but it steadily improved, &amp; we wound up in sunshine.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Only one circumstance was steadily adverse, and that seems to be incurable. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I mean, the dust</hi><hi rend="i bold">,</hi><hi rend="italic"> which on the country roads is thrown up by the motors in great volumes, extremely disconcerting to travellers. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
