<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A sharp frost introduced a bright sky. I left the Baldwins in <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> charge, and went off in the motor to Churchstoke. I left the Palace at 10.45 a.m., and arrived at Churchstoke Vicarage about 1.30 p.m. In the car I read through the volume</hi> <hi rend="italic">"The Church of England, its nature &amp; future", in which the lecture I delivered in King's College is included.</hi><hi> After lunch, Lushington<persName xml:id="4312"></persName> &amp; I motored to Chisbury, where was meeting of the clergy of the Rural Deanery. We discussed the Baptismal Franchise. With one exception everybody approved it. Then I visited the parish church, a fine open structure with the piers of the nave inclining outwards very notably. In the Vicarage I was shown the chained library of one Lewis, 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century Vicar, which is said to include some of George Herbert's<persName xml:id="915"></persName> books. I was interested to see that it included many foreign divines, notably Calvin<persName xml:id="930"></persName>: This is the country of Lord Herbert<persName xml:id="4269"></persName> of Chirbury &amp; his saintly brother.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The clergy of this deanery appeared to be respectable and well&#8211;intentional men, but dull, very dull, save for Dunn<persName xml:id="4209"></persName> of Montgomery &amp; Lushington<persName xml:id="4312"></persName> of Churchstoke, both of whom are in charge of fairly large parishes. This confirms me in my belief that the very small &amp; isolated cures react badly on the incumbents who have charge of them.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
