<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There was a thunderstorm last night with some rain, but this day is again warm &amp; summer like. After breakfast I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> was there. He seems more pleased with himself than his performance with the crowd altogether justified. Old M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hoare<persName xml:id="2252"></persName> was there, &amp; insisted on my reading a small book on "Establishment" which he wrote some years since. I ran through it, &amp; found it a very sensible production. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After lunch Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and I went to Kew Gardens</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The train was fearfully overcrowded, so that the atmosphere became asphyxiating. Nothing could exceed the beauty of the Gardens. We lay on the grass, &amp; talked together. Then we made our way back to the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This being <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> Birthday, I went to the bookseller, and bought Sir Frederick Bridge's<persName xml:id="241"></persName> "A Westminster Pilgrim"<ref xml:id="1048"></ref> as a birthday present for her. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The gossiping old egotist</hi><hi rend="italic"> has brought together a good deal of material, much of which hardly seems worth printing. But the personal note is very acceptable to a large public. There is always the suggestion of lifting the veil, and allowing a sight of what is normally hidden. And this carries the promise of something "spicey", showing an unsuspected side of well&#8211;known individuals; in short, providing scandal. Then one likes to read of men &amp; events which one has known &amp; witnessed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
