<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>				
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Ten years ago I was inhibited by Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> from preaching in the Digbeth Institute at Birmingham. The document, which now hangs in my bedroom framed, bears the date March 26</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, 1909. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Now I sit on a Bishop's chair, and he "throws the cards on the table, and refuses to play". Which of us has won in the duel? Which of us can contemplate with the least measure of shame &amp; disquietude the ten years past? Both of us have led strenuous &amp; prominent lives. He has been more &amp; more taking the lead in the Church, and I have become even more solitary. Which of us had best employed his talents? Which has the most impractical and unpromising aspect – Gore's Catholicism or my Protestantism? The Church of England, as a whole seems unlikely to endorse his view of its rôle in the world, and is quite plainly determined to repudiate mine. What place of retreat lies open to him, and to me? Both of us, in our own different ways, are evidently chafing against the pinched frontiers of ecclesiastical life, and casting eyes of desire on that ample territory of general interest which has no place in it for the conflicts &amp; aspirations of Churches. He is ten years my senior, and to that extent has a larger cargo of hopes &amp; efforts to cast overboard in order to escape total shipwreck</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[139]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral, and celebrated the Holy Communion. The long Passion&#8211;tide Gospel is extraordinarily impressive. All my guests except Mary Webbe<persName xml:id="4867"></persName> were among the Communicants. Both <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> and <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName> were assistant[s] at the service.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I remained in my study during the morning: after lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> accompanied me to Cleobury Mortimer. The road between Tenbury &amp; Cleobury Mortimer was in a shocking condition, and so steep at places that the motor had great difficulty in getting over the ground. I confirmed 48 persons in Cleobury Mortimer Church, which is a fine building. It was well&#8211;filled. After the service I had tea with the Vicar, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Malden</hi><persName xml:id="4917"></persName><hi>, a rather conventional High Churchman. He told me that from his parish, with a population of over 1500 souls, he expected no more than 120 communicants at Easter. I motored to Hopton Wafers, and there confirmed 32 candidates. The little parish church was densely crowded. I hope the people were edified: they were certainly very attentive. Then we motored back to Hereford by way of the Clee Hill, Ludlow, and Leominster, reaching the Palace about 9.50 p.m. The view from the road over Clee Hill is magnificent, and on a fine day would be hard to beat. The road is excellently graded, and considering the altitude must be pronounced to be fairly easy&#8211;going.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
