<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Before getting up I read through Warre&#8211;Cornish's<persName xml:id="778"></persName> account of the Oxford Movement<ref xml:id="1047"></ref>, and much of it would serve with hardly an alteration as an account of the Movement for "Self&#8211;government", of which "Life &amp; Liberty" is the most forcible expression.<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note> The general summary holds:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The matter (of Tract 1) was a deliberate assault upon all that was conventional in the Church, an appeal to ages of superstition, asceticism, and intolerance, in full agreement with its author's conviction that it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be a gain to this country, were it vastly more superstitious, more bigoted, more gloomy, more fierce in its religion, than at present it shows itself to be".</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>These words are quoted from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Keble's</hi><persName xml:id="4601"></persName><hi> sermon, "The Religion of the Day", and "words could not have been better chosen to express the principle put forward by the writers of the Tracts, which was to set up against the religion of the day the religion of other days as they conceived it". The great difference is that the Tractarians were political </hi><hi rend="underline">Tories</hi><hi> : &amp; their successors are "</hi><hi rend="underline">democrats</hi><hi>". </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName><hi> is a member of the Labour Party: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="105"></persName><hi> are "Christian Socialists": the main body of the rank &amp; file are sentimental Socialists, who prate of S. Francis, &amp; think they can butter parsnips with pretty speeches.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We walked to Westminster, and attended service in Christ Church. There was a crowded congregation, in which (though it is little more than 6 years since we left Westminster) we could recognize nobody. The service was an abbreviated Mattins with some short form of strange prayer introduced oddly into the collects. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">R. J. Campbell</hi><persName xml:id="392"></persName><hi rend="italic"> preached from the Words: "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">As free, &amp; not using your freedom for a cloak of wickedness, but as bondservants of God". </hi><hi rend="italic">I heard the sermon with some difficulty as the acoustics of the building are bad. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The preacher has little action, &amp; a quiet manner, though, with rather a "stagey" effect. His sermon, so far as I could hear it, was an affirmation of the paradox, that human liberty &amp; human bondage are both true. There was a large surpliced choir, but the singing was congregational. Before two altars hung burning lamps, but whether there was the Sacrament reserved in either I know not</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; wrote to the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Newcastle</hi><persName xml:id="1980"></persName><hi rend="italic">, giving him, as he requested, some suggestions for a speech in Convocation.</hi><hi> After lunching in the hotel, we walked to Westminster, and attended service in the Abbey. The new canon, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">de Candole</hi><persName xml:id="4544"></persName><hi> was the preacher. He is a small, rather mean&#8211;looking man with a clear voice, &amp; a melancholy manner. The sermon was nowise remarkable. We had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray Smith</hi><persName xml:id="543"></persName><hi>, with whom were M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="2720"></persName><hi>&amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Yates Thompson</hi><persName xml:id="2721"></persName><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We drove to the Deanery of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul's. Sir Francis<persName xml:id="4886"></persName> &amp; Lady Younghusband<persName xml:id="4887"></persName> were there. She asked me whether I had written a "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">beautiful little book on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Robertson<persName xml:id="3776"></persName> of Brighton</hi><hi rend="italic">". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It appears that her mother had known the famous preacher well</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Warrington<persName xml:id="4851"></persName>, a son of the late Dean of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> David's<persName xml:id="4850"></persName>, was there. He is a suffragan of Liverpool, &amp;, of course, advocates "Life &amp; Liberty"<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note>, but he professes to be somewhat less positive in his advocacy than he was. We dined with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName><hi rend="italic"> at 28 Queen Anne's Gate. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="1386"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had provided for my toothless condition most carefully. It was a pleasant party. The conversation turned much on the ecclesiastical situation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord H. asked me to send him the papers relating to the "Enabling Bill", and professed himself ready to move for a Royal Commission. Now here emerges a difficulty, for Lord H. is extremely unpopular, and any proposal of his can hardly be uncompromised by the fact. He suggested Asquith<persName xml:id="215"></persName> as a suitable Chairman for the Royal Commission, and I welcomed the suggestion, for Asquith has many of the requisite qualities. The choice of the other members would be sufficiently difficult. The Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> would have to be included, but the laymen are hard to find</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
