<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to S. Nicholas, at 8 a.m. and celebrated the Holy Communion. There were more than 100 communicants. After breakfast Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> accompanied me to Much Dewchurch, where I preached, and celebrated for the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> time. The latter had not been included in my intention, but the Vicar<persName xml:id="4518"></persName> was almost voiceless with a cold, so that it was an obvious act of charity to take the Celebration. There were 39 communicants.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> came to see me in the afternoon, &amp; we had some talk. He seems to have much belief in the "Students' Movement", which having begun in conventional Evangelicalism, is now stretching out towards a more reasonable kind of Christianity. The "Anglican Fellowship" is developed from it. High Churchmen of the more spiritual type, having been impressed &amp; attracted by the evident devotion of the "Students' Movement", drew together to consider &amp; think out the religious situation. Men of candid spirits and muddled intellects like </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Neville Talbot</hi><persName xml:id="2023"></persName><hi rend="italic"> did this, &amp;, perhaps, something may grow from it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">W. Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> seems to have drawn back to the ecclesiastical camp, from which he seemed to be escaping. In his case, perhaps, something must be allowed for personal ambition</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Well&#8211;endowed by nature with brains, physically strong, extremely well&#8211;educated, &amp; (last but not least) born in the (ecclesiastical) purple, he is a "young man with great possessions", and the world is at his feet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[150]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I amused myself by turning over Selden's<persName xml:id="967"></persName> 'Table Talk'<ref xml:id="1043"></ref>. There is much caustic wisdom in it and some </hi><hi rend="italic underline">obiter dicta</hi><hi rend="italic"> of great value, e.g. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The main thing is to know where to search: for talk they what they will of vast memories, no man will presume upon his own memory for anything he means to write or speak in public</hi><hi rend="italic">". The two essentials are a good knowledge of languages, and a thorough mastery of intellectual method. Both must be gained in adolescence. It was my supreme misfortune that I came away from Oxford with neither.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in the Cathedral at Evensong to an immense congregation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The service was stately, but the amount of music made it rather lengthy. I hope everybody heard the sermon</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> The congregation was certainly very attentive. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName></hi><hi> carried the pastoral staff.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName> is wonderful, though his deafness is very trying. But his interest is as keen as ever</hi><hi rend="i bold">, </hi><hi rend="italic">&amp; his memory, though not so trustworthy as heretofore, is amazing. He talks incessantly, pouring forth a ceaseless stream of anecdote, criticism, aphorism, &amp; reminiscence. He is physically feeble, but mentally as alert as ever &#8211; a very wonderful &amp; admirable old man. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
