<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Writers are apt to flatter themselves that they are not, like the men of action, the slaves of circumstance. They think they can write what and when they choose. But it is not so. Whatever we may think and scheme, as soon as we seek to produce our thoughts or schemes to our fellow&#8211;men, we are involved in the same necessities of compromise, the same grooves of motion, the same liabilities to failure or half&#8211;measures as we are in life and action. Compared with the vast designs we frame in youth, all production seems a petty and abortive effort.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Mark Pattison<persName xml:id="494"></persName>. "Casaubon<persName xml:id="4733"></persName>"<ref xml:id="19"></ref> p. 383.</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in my study working mostly on the sermon for Jimmie <persName xml:id="88">Adderley</persName>. In the afternoon I sawed wood, prepared notes for an address tonight &amp; did my letters with <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName>. After an early dinner I went to All Saints, and there instituted Treherne's<persName xml:id="4426"></persName> successor, Rushton<persName xml:id="4842"></persName>. There was a fair congregation, and a good muster of the clergy. After the Institution, the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> performed the Induction. The latter function has been developed into a far more elaborate ceremonial than the former! Wynne&#8211;Willson carried the pastoral staff. It was a fairly satisfactory service.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
