<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Daily Graphic" reporter came to me at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and "interviewed" me on the subject of the miners, having taken occasion from the few observations which I made in the Convocation. For a quarter of an hour I improvised flatterous platitudes for his benefit.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Then I walked to S. Andrew's, Wells Street, and had some talk with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. He told me that he had had speech with Lord Wolmer<persName xml:id="1028"></persName>, &amp; found him extremely confident as to the prospects of the "Enabling Bill". He was shown a list of 300 members of parliament, who had promised to support it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The plan is to get the Bill hustled into law this year</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">I cannot believe that this is possible, &amp; yet the situation is so extraordinary that I cannot feel very sure about anything. I undertook to write something for the "Times" forthwith. After lunching at the Athenaeum, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I went off to Paddington. Just as I was leaving, Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> drove up, &amp; I exchanged a few words with him. "How are things really going?" I asked: "Oh, well enough", he said, "if we c</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> get rid of Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName>. He's well enough, of course: but also a terrible nuisance!" I can understand</hi><hi rend="italic">that the presence of a doctrinaire, equally impracticable and powerful, must be enormously disconcerting to the diplomatists. The League of Nations scheme is drafted &amp; published.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
