<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 10 a.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I started in the motor on another round of confirmations. We went to Goodrich, where I confirmed 33 candidates. After lunching with Prebendary </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Seaton</hi><persName xml:id="4672"></persName><hi> and his wife, we motored to Linton, stopping on our way to call on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Moffatt</hi><persName xml:id="4815"></persName><hi>, whose house is gloriously situated. At Linton I confirmed 15 candidates. After service we had tea in the Vicarage. The parson, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bennett</hi><persName xml:id="4129"></persName><hi>, is a delicately moulded man with a gentle expression and manner. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton</hi><persName xml:id="2511"></persName><hi> says that he is a saint. We motored back to Hereford, and arrived shortly before six o'clock. </hi><hi rend="italic">A telegram announced the immediate arrival of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Blair Ripley</hi><persName xml:id="2882"></persName><hi rend="italic">. He was on his way from Ripon to Rhyl. He is an intelligent rather silent man, whose services at the Front have been very considerable. He shewed me letters from several high officials expressing the warmest appreciation of the work which his engineering corps had accomplished.</hi> <persName xml:id="4448"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi></persName><hi> came, &amp; worked through the correspondence. I wrote the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. H. G. Morgan</hi><persName xml:id="4819"></persName><hi> offering him the Prebend in the cathedral vacated by the death of old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hanbury</hi><persName xml:id="4718"></persName><hi>. The weather all day long has been damp and blustering, a circumstance the more regrettable since we were passing through one of the loveliest parts of my diocese. Had the day been fine our drive from Goodrich to Linton would have been a succession of gorgeous pictures. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
