<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a letter from my godson, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert Nicholson</hi><persName xml:id="2285"></persName><hi>, who has now returned home, and will shortly resume his place in the ranks of civilians. I wrote to another godson, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Gilbert Simpson<persName xml:id="554"></persName>, sending him &#x00A3;10 to purchase a wedding present</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> After breakfast I resumed work on the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, and had made but little progress, when I was interrupted by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName><hi>, who had spent the previous day with the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> in order to inspect Bridstow. He seemed much disposed to accept the living, but postponed his decision until the end of the month. He seemed to think that I ought to be present in the Convocation, but how to do so in view of the dentist's action is hard to see. After lunch I took </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicey</hi><persName xml:id="403"></persName><hi> and the Anson ladies<persName xml:id="302"></persName> to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ledbury</hi><hi>, where we visited the parish church, and then had tea at the Hospital with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName>s</hi><hi>. We returned to Hereford by way of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ross</hi><hi>. The weather was clouded and chill. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Dicey is so frail and so deaf that he becomes rather an anxious problem to his host. His interest in everything is curiously keen, and he wants to know far more than one can tell him. I am lost in astonishment at his mental alertness, at his amazing memory, and at his inexhaustible powers of conversation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
