<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[104]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The paper reports the death of the dowager Lady Londonderry</hi><persName xml:id="2817"></persName><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">She was a very kind friend to me, and I had a genuine affection for her. Our last meeting was on February 25</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, when I had tea in Carlton House Terrace. My life is emptying fast. Beeching<persName xml:id="208"></persName> went out of it on February 26</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, and now Lady Londonderry has gone. They are both "taken away from the evil to come". This ill news shadowed my mind all day long, and made work on the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> more than ever distasteful. For his journal was full of Lord Londonderry's<persName xml:id="2816"></persName> name; and, though he was fully conscious of the absurdity of the arrangement which made that amicable nobleman his superior in the Educational Department, he had an evident affection for him, and recognized the loyalty of his co&#8211;operation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Beyond working on the Anson Memoir, and writing a number of letters, I did nothing. Perhaps my labours of yesterday predisposed me to idleness.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was interested by a letter from an ex&#8211;Nonconformist who had been ordained by the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName>. He finds himself woefully disillusioned by his experience of that diocese, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">where he is expected to carry himself as a Catholick priest instead of an English clergyman</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> He would like a benefice in the diocese of Hereford!!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
