<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I had a pleasant visit to Brogyntyn. The house contains a good many objects of interest. Lord Harlech<persName xml:id="4825"></persName> motored us (Lady H.<persName xml:id="3701"></persName>, Lady Kenyon<persName xml:id="4792"></persName>, &amp; me) into Shrewsbury, where we went to the Infirmary, and thence to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Chad's Church. Here a special service was held, and I preached a sermon. The offertory amounted to &#x00A3;658, which was said to be above the average. We lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Corrie, the owner of the Elizabethan house which was recently burned down. He is evidently a collector of china, glass, &amp; other artistic objects. His house is full of fine things, moving the admirer to covetousness.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I had a tiresome long wait for my train. Leaving my bags at the station, I walked into the town, and visited S. Mary's Church, a fine spacious building. Then I travelled back to Hereford, &amp; arrived nearly an hour late, &amp; half&#8211;asphyxiated with tobacco smoke. Among my letters I found a demand for more than &#x00A3;15. on account of Convocation &amp;c! This seems an excessive charge, &amp;, considering the mean estimate which I have formed of the practical value of those silly talking&#8211;shops, it is a horrible oppression that I should be thus pillaged for their support.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
