<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[105]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather changed for the worse, and our expedition to the extreme north of the diocese was made under pouring rain. We left the Palace shortly before 11 a.m., and motored to Kingsland, where I confirmed 23 candidates in the parish church. This is a very noble structure, containing two features of unusual interest – a fine 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century stained&#8211;glass window at the east end, and beside the porch a little building either a small chantry, or an anchorite's cell. In this place was a stone bed or coffin, in which (if that theory be sound) the holy man slept. We lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jobling<persName xml:id="4789"></persName> the Rector. His son<persName xml:id="4788"></persName>, who is beneficed in the Liverpool diocese, carried my staff, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Johnson<persName xml:id="4913"></persName>, the Vicar of Aymestree [sic], presented the candidates. The registers of Kingsland go back to 1538: but the old plate (prae&#8211;Reformation) was stolen within the last half&#8211;century. There is a population of about 900 in this parish, &amp; the value of the benefice exceeds &#x00A3;800. After lunch we left in in the motor for Condover Hall<placeName xml:id="93"></placeName>, and motored through Ludlow &amp; Church Stretton, arriving about 5 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="italic">After tea I read in the "Times"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> an obituary notice of George Russell<persName xml:id="1211"></persName>, who died yesterday</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was not a friend of mine, but I have seen much of him. His death makes another void in my life.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
