<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[220]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent some time in preparing notes for an address to the Confirmation candidates at Knighton, taking for my text the words of Psalm. XXIV, "</hi><hi rend="underline">The earth is the Lord's, &amp; the fulness thereof</hi><hi>". After an early lunch I started in the motor for Knighton. All went well until we were within half a mile of the church, when one of the back tyres burst with a loud report. We put on the "stepney" wheel, &amp; arrived in good time. There were 37 candidates. This parish is in Wales, &amp; will be cut off from the diocese as soon as the Disestablishment Act comes into operation. This was my first and last episcopal visit to Knighton. On the return journey the "stepney" wheel went to pieces with a bang about Canon Pyron, 7 miles from Hereford. We sent in a message for another tyre, and after a delay of 1 1/2 hours, we were able to continue our journey, &amp; got back to the Palace about 8.15 p.m. The two archdeacons<persName xml:id="4450"><persName xml:id="3618"></persName></persName> came to discuss the question of appointing a new Diocesan Messenger.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Forsyth<persName xml:id="1520"></persName> has a long &amp; cogent letter in the "Times" on the Enabling Bill</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">He writes as a Nonconformist, &amp;, from that point of view, makes out a strong case against the Bill. I really think there is a chance of defeating the Bill, but what then?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
