<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[36]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Day, January 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather was as bad as could be – heavy rain from morning till nightfall. Nevertheless our kind hosts carried through the programme they had arranged for us. We motored to Colne S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Aldwyn and had tea with Lady S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Aldwyn<persName xml:id="1001"></persName> &amp; her daughter Lady Victoria Hicks&#8211;Beach<persName xml:id="4776"></persName>. On the way we stopped at Cirencester, and had lunch very comfortably in the King's Head, a hostelry opposite the great parish church. The last we visited after lunch. It is mainly of the late perpendicular style, very lofty &amp; spacious. At Colne S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Aldwyn we were kindly received. Lady S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> A. insisted on showing Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> and me the little church, which, however, had </hi><hi rend="underline">nothing</hi><hi> in it worth seeing. The parson<persName xml:id="4905"></persName> came in to tea. I asked him whether there were any traditions of Keble<persName xml:id="4601"></persName> lingering in the parish, and he replied that there were hardly any, none certain or important.<note xml:id="449" n="1"></note> It is a sign of the times that the younger ladies are proud of their skill as dairy&#8211;maids, &amp; are about to adventure taking a farm on their own account. The butter was admirable, &amp; only the sternness of the Food Controller hindered Lady Victoria from presenting me with a pound of her own manufacture. We returned to Gloucester through a violent down&#8211;pour of rain, and arrived in the Hotel in comfortable time for dinner. It could not be described as a cheerful start for the New Year.</hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
