<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a heavy fall of snow during the night, &amp; when we looked out on the world from our bedroom window, we found that we had rushed back into the winter. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The newspapers</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">report that Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> has resigned. In the letter to the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, announcing his purpose, he gives his reasons, and includes the vote on the baptismal franchise at the recent meeting of the R.C.C. This action would be more impressive if it had not been so often threatened. He threatened to resign in the last Lambeth Conference, and last year when I was consecrated. The truth is that Gore, though a good &amp; able man, is a bad loser. If he is thwarted, he throws the cards on the table, &amp; refuses to go on playing. The appointment of his successor will be interesting</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Probably Strong<persName xml:id="120"></persName> will be offered the see. He </hi><hi rend="italic underline">may</hi><hi rend="italic"> refuse it, as his eyesight is giving trouble. Then there is always W. Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="4506">Beattie</persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="4507"></persName> came to lunch: also M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Polly, Angel<persName xml:id="1812"></persName> and her husband Major Thelwell<persName xml:id="4861"></persName> arrived for the week&#8211;end. He has recently arrived from Cologne, where he returns in a week's time. His account of the situation there was rather disconcerting. The Germans are by no means convinced that they have been beaten, &amp; they are still strong enough to be formidable.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
