<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[106]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather remained unpityingly hostile all day, nothing but rain. Confirmation candidates came to church in the most uncomfortable circumstances. We motored to Dorrington where, in a squalid 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century church, I confirmed 24 candidates. The Vicar, Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> E. F. Wayne<persName xml:id="4877"></persName>, was appointed 28 years ago. After lunch we motored to Cound, where I confirmed 26 candidates. The parson, Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> F. H. Bolingbroke<persName xml:id="4726"></persName>, carried my pastoral staff. The Church (S. Peter's) has a modern chancel, &amp; northern aisle. Its distinction is a fine set of 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century pews. There is also a Jacobean pulpit, &amp; some medieval tiles. The font is ancient &amp; there is an old alms&#8211;chest, probably 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century.</hi><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Fielden<persName xml:id="4560"></persName> went off to London to confer over the Labour difficulties, which have a very threatening aspect. It seems probable that the first consequence of the War will be to precipitate a conflict of interests within the country, which may easily attain the dimension &amp; acquire the character of civil war. There are forces behind the Labour demands which no reasons can satisfy, &amp; no patriotism can condone. The only question is whether they are dominant.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
