<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The post brought me a reply from the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>. It is not encouraging. "My own opinion is that any useful modifications must now be introduced in Parliament and, if in the House of Lords, preferably by lay peers". As if any lay peers have thought or concern for ecclesiastical matters at this juncture. Even where there is the interest, there is not the requisite knowledge. The matter will be left to what Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> called the "extra&#8211;ecclesiastical laymen", and they are impossible. Lords Halifax<persName xml:id="1748"></persName> and Kinnaird<persName xml:id="345"></persName> are equally absurd. Besides, there is a traditional propriety in the House of Lords which makes men reluctant to conflict with the two Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> when questions of the Church are raised. Their Graces are committed beyond repentance to the policy of the Enabling Bill.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote again to the Bishop of Southwark<persName xml:id="4762"></persName>, expressing my regret that he should be absent from Convocation, and accepting contingently his invitation for the Bishops' Meeting. If those secret conclaves at Lambeth were abolished: if the time spent in them were added to the Sessions of Convocation: if the Upper House met in a place large enough to admit the general public: and if the meetings were frankly open to the public, I incline to think that the influence of the Episcopate would be greatly increased.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to the barber, and had my hair cut. The weather has become warm &amp; spring like. I purchased this year's issue of "Who's who" – the volume waxes yearly, &amp; now threatens to rival Crockford: and its price has risen to 30/&#8211; net.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Major Thelwell<persName xml:id="4861"></persName> and Angel<persName xml:id="1812"></persName> his wife came to see me, and had tea. He has just been appointed to some post in Berlin. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He tells me that the drunkenness of the British officers in Cologne is causing much perplexity to our authorities, and inflicting considerable discredit on the British name. The behaviour of the 'Tommies' was far superior to that of their officers – a fact which can hardly assist the discipline. Energetic measures had been taken ageist prostitution</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The income tax remains unaltered. There is an increase of the Death Duties which now on fortunes of &#x00A3;2,000,000 reach no less than 40 per cent. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Austen Chamberlain</hi><persName xml:id="343"></persName><hi> claimed with some reason that this was a levy on capital of the most effective and least invidious form. Imperial preference on colonial wines &amp;c. is introduced. The Budget seems to have been well&#8211;received, though the Labour men affected to be angry. The by&#8211;election in Aberdeenshire has gone against the Government. This is the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> seat lost by the Coalition since the General Election. There has certainly been a considerable revulsion of feeling in the constituencies.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
