<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Inequality of property, in the degree in which it exists in most countries of Europe, abstractedly considered is an evil: but it is an evil which flows from those rules concerning the acquisition &amp; disposal of property, by which men are incited to industry, &amp; by which the object of their industry is rendered secure &amp; valuable. If there be any great inequality unconnected with this origin, it ought to be corrected.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Paley<persName xml:id="3691"></persName>. Moral Philosophy<ref xml:id="1082"></ref>. Bk. III. e. ii.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I worked away again at the Article, wading thro' a vast lot of poisonous rubbish – the publications of the Church Socialist League<orgName xml:id="324"></orgName>. Some quotations from these will lead to the Archbishops Committee's Report, which differ only in degree</hi><hi>. Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> came to ask me to head a deputation to the magistrates on the subject of retaining the limitation of the hours of sale in the public&#8211;houses of Hereford. I promised to do so if the deputation were genuinely representative. Rushton<persName xml:id="4842"></persName> sends me a note about young Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>, which is rather disconcerting. I hardly know what will be best to do with him. He ought to have a normal curacy.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>