<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The frost continues. This morning the cold is bitter. What an infinity of suffering does this mean in this country among the poor who can get no fuel! What miseries of privation &amp; lingering death among the starved millions of central Europe, Russia, and the Balkans! The Hand of the Almighty is heavy on His World. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8a.m. &amp; celebrated the Holy Comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi>. My post included a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Draper</hi><persName xml:id="3587"></persName><hi> with the very welcome news of his having been appointed to the Mastership of the Temple. He was ordained as long ago as 1880, so that he must be at least 7 years my senior. To start a preacher's ministry in London at 63 is rather a formidable venture. I wrote to congratulate him. </hi><hi rend="italic">I also wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Forge</hi><persName xml:id="5085"></persName><hi rend="italic"> of Walmley Vicarage thanking her for the memoir of her son Noel<persName xml:id="5086"></persName> who was killed in the War. The following is pathetically interesting: "Noel was one of six boys (at Bedford School) who in 1913 pledged themselves to take Holy Orders &amp; to do all possible good in the world. He was the fifth of these to fall, &amp; the 6</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">. was Noel's friend &amp; ideal Cap</hi><hi rend="i sup u">tn</hi><hi rend="italic">. Tristram Yarde<persName xml:id="5131"></persName> M.C. who fell in some of the last fighting in Palestine, after trying most heroically to save his men". Verily "the economy of Heaven is dark".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><persName xml:id="3619"></persName><hi> accompanied me to Holme Lacy, where we lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Lucas Tooth</hi><hi> before going to the Church for the dedication of the Churchyard Cross. Her brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Warrand</hi><persName xml:id="5127"></persName><hi> acted as host. After Evensong I preached from the chancel step, and then preceded the congregation to the Cross, and read some prayers. After Evensong I preached in the Cathedral. Whether it was that I myself was tired, or that the congregation was tired out by a very long Bach anthem, I know not – perhaps both causes acted together – but the fact could not be doubtful. My sermon did but puzzle and bore the people.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Macaulay's</hi><persName xml:id="2977"></persName><hi> description of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sydney Smith</hi><persName xml:id="3896"></persName><hi> when he made his acquaintance in 1826 is rather suggestive of the case of more recent divines:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"His notions of law, government &amp; trade are surprisingly clear &amp; just. His misfortune is to have chosen a profession at once above him &amp; below him. Zeal would have made him a prodigy; formality &amp; bigotry would have made him a bishop: but he could neither rise to the duties of his order, nor stoop to its degradations". [v. Life I.168]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It would not need to exclude the Episcopate from providing the true subjects of that paradox now!</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>