<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">38]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is an odd paradox that these "Church Socialists" who revile the Protestant Reformers as the chief agents in the triumph of the middle class are themselves protagonists in another revolution which confessedly aims at the triumph of another class, the 'proletariat'. The 16</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century was a theological age, therefore the "class–war" expressed itself in a religious Reformation: the XX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century is an age of secularism: therefore the class war expresses itself in economic Revolution. In both, the ecclesiastical factor is secondary to the economic. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But Religion interposes in Politics at its peril</hi><hi rend="italic">. The process of social development is inflamed and degraded by fanaticism. In the age of the Reformation the darkest chapters disclose the closest association of religious and economic motives. The peasants' Revolt in Germany and the Religious Wars in France may serve as sufficient examples. Religious fanaticism is not ordinarily connected with knowledge or moderation: it carries the audacity of ignorance &amp; the fervour of passion into a sphere where beyond all things sound knowledge &amp; a calm judgement are required.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">39]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The real meaning of the present turmoil is that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">we are witnessing the birth–pangs of a new order</hi><hi rend="italic">. There is no reason why it should not come into the world quite smoothly, if people understand what is happening &amp; do not offer an unreasoning opposition (The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'Times'</hi><hi rend="italic">. Nov: 19. 1919). But "birth–pangs" are hard to combine with this optimism. The metaphor is born of the reiterated experience w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">h</hi> <hi rend="italic">unites social change with dislocation, distress &amp; disorder.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The parallel bet. the XVI</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> and XX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> centuries is close. Thus in both an age of revolution succeeds an age of discovery: in both an economic change is associated with a religious movement: in both there is a monstrous campaign of exaggeration against existing institutions: in both there is gross injustice to individuals: in both, the loftiest professions cover the lowest aims, and veil the coarsest characters. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In the retrospect the Reformation is less respectable than it seemed to its advocates. Will not the same be the case with the economic Revolution which is now proceeding?</hi> <hi rend="italic">There are Socialists who are swayed by altruistic dreams, but who can doubt that the mass of modern Socialists are inflamed by the sordid passion of envy?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Swinnerton Dyer<persName xml:id="5120"></persName> came to lunch. I had read James's<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> summary of his documents, &amp; was quite prepared to admit his ownership of Westhope Chapel. But its status as a consecrated building seemed to me to be a necessary presumption both from his documents, &amp; from the facts of the case. The Chancellor, James, &amp; Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> also came to lunch. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> S. D. was himself very reasonable, but wished to consult his family before finally accepting the compromise which I proposed. His sister, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Martin, seems to be the ruling power, &amp; I promised to see her.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lilley and I walked together for an hour and a half. The I had a long interview with C.S.<persName xml:id="4845"></persName> The lad is right </hi><hi rend="underline">au fond</hi><hi>, but with his head woefully full of absurdities, &amp; overwhelmingly conceited. I gave him a fortnight to consider my decision. Then I wrote the letters. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived from Carlisle about 10.30 p.m. I wrote to Lennie<persName xml:id="4987"></persName> telling him that, in spite of the badness of his papers, I would ordain him on the understanding that his diaconate extended to not less than two years, and that he pursued a course of reading prescribed by the Examining Chaplains. Even so I doubt whether I ought to tolerate such ignorance as his.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>