<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> thanking him for his generous help during the year, &amp; sent him a copy of the Naked Truth<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>: I also sent a copy to the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName>. I wrote to Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, sending him a copy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The morning was employed by paying bills, &amp; preparing a balance sheet for the year &#8211; a disconcerting performance. After lunch I walked round Belmont with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. The wind was very keen, &amp; the sky looked ominous of snow. On returning home I wrote my own letters as Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> was absent. Then, after an early dinner, we all went to the Shire Hall for the choristers' concert, which was very entertaining. There was a very numerous company &amp; very appreciative. The fiddling of a lad named Harding whom nobody seemed to know, &amp; who turned out to be a pupil of the Cathedral organist<persName xml:id="4595"></persName> hailing from Wales was greatly applauded.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I read poetry to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and Ernest until midnight, when we exchanged good wishes, and went to bed. Thus ended the year. The weather which had been warm &amp; wet changed during the afternoon &amp; we walked from the Shire Hall to the Palace under a clear moon on ground hard as iron with a stiff frost.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>