<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Chapman<persName xml:id="5071"></persName> at the University Press respecting his suggestion that Gwyer<persName xml:id="306"></persName> sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be asked to supplement Dicey's<persName xml:id="403"></persName> estimate of Anson's<persName xml:id="228"></persName> law books, and also to Gwyer asking him to undertake it.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Then I wrote &amp; despatched the article which I undertook to write for "Nash's Weekly"</hi><hi>! After lunch, Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> came to see me bringing with him a deaf Australian with a voice of thunder, who wanted to buy the Vicarage at Ballingham. I promised to go to the parish tomorrow, &amp; inspect the houses. After an hour's work, I sate down &amp; wrote letters.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I offered the prebendal stall vacated by old Jellicorse<persName xml:id="5098"></persName> to Bartleet<persName xml:id="5067"></persName> of Much Wenlock: and the office of diocesan Missioner to Wall<persName xml:id="5124"></persName> of Emmanuel Church, Preston. Then I wrote to Baker<persName xml:id="5065"></persName> of Yockleton, and his aggrieved parishioner, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Mosson.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Also, to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Britton, the blind widow, who insists on living at the Rectory of Frodesley. This lady is patroness of the living of which her husband was Rector, &amp; she appears to think that her rights in that capacity exempt her from the common fate of clerical widows. It may be no easy task, however, to remove her from the Rectory, &amp; her blindness adds an aspect of brutality to any exercise of coercion.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>