<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>:<note xml:id="495" n="1"></note> and then went at the head of a deputation to the Police Court in order to oppose an extension of hours to the market pot&#8211;houses. Nothing could exceed the squalour of the police court. The result was disappointing. The hours were </hi><hi rend="underline">only</hi><hi> increased from 2.30 to 4 pm. However, I suppose what I said may do some good.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jenner<persName xml:id="5099"></persName> from Vennwood came to lunch. He is a clergyman from the diocese of Bath &amp; Wells. His health is unsatisfactory, so he has resigned parochial work &amp; come to live on a small property which belongs to him in this county. He is also the heir to an estate in Glamorgan, &amp; desires to learn something about estate&#8211;mangagement before entering on his inheritance. He seemed both agreeable, and religious. After lunch, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Lillie motored into the country to pay calls, and I walked for 1 1/2 hours. Then I wrote letters &amp;c until dinner. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There seems little time for reading: my days are consumed in the puerilities of diocesan administration, a hand to mouth existence hostile to any form of intellectual effort. </hi><hi>When I read Ralph's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> Essays, I get vision of the abyss which is parting me from the power of achievement. It is a melancholy reflection!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>November 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Lord Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName>, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am greatly obliged to you for your note on the late Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName>. Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName> &amp; Gwyer<persName xml:id="306"></persName> have gone at some length into the merits of the law books: &amp; the Speaker<persName xml:id="784"></persName> has contributed a full account of his parliamentary career. If you will allow me to add a note or two at the right places quoting your authority, I think that w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be the best method of incorporating the substance of what you have written. The MS. is now in the printer's hands so that any considerable addition or change of plan is scarcely possible: but what you have written is far too good to be lost, and your name w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>be more than acceptable. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours sincerely,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>November 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Prebendary,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I fear that my shield will not add to the interest or the beauty of your collection, for it will be blank. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My forbears were Devonshire farmers &amp; small landowners for generations beyond counting, &amp; they carried no arms. I cannot depart from their practice now.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>As to the seal, I </hi><hi rend="underline">could</hi><hi> not get one cut during the War, &amp; now, when the artists are again available, I can't afford the money (&#x00A3;40) which it would cost. So I continue for the present to use the temporary seal – a mitre over my initial with the usual inscription. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours sincerely, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>