<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> before breakfast. Afterwards I motored to Staunton&#8211;on&#8211;Wye, and presided at a meeting of the Jarvis Trustees<orgName xml:id="313"></orgName>. It was reported that there was an outbreak of diphtheria at the school, though of a very slight character. After lunch Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> brought an Ordination candidate to see me. He seems to have small chance of passing his examination.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The municipal elections throughout the country have been marked by two features – </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the smallness of the polls, and the victories of "Labour". In many London boroughs the "Labour" party is supreme, and can begin to show the public a specimen of its capacity</hi><hi rend="italic">. One result at least is sufficiently certain – a further rise in the local rates. I paid my half&#8211;year's rates &#8211; &#x00A3;49.17.4 as against &#x00A3;37.8.0 in May. This represents an increase of &#x00A3;25 in rates alone. It is not surprising that there is audible from the country clergy "an exceeding bitter cry", for they are assessed, not merely on their houses, but also on half the tithe rent&#8211;charge. Blank ruin must now be staring many of them in the face. They are not considerable enough in numbers or influence to make it worth any politician's while to espouse their cause, &amp; seek to remove their grievance.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>