<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">All Souls Day, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I preached my sermon to a chapel full of fellows and quondams; and afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion. I recalled the day when first I worshipped in that place. There has been much failure in my life, but here I am by God's mercy, &amp; I am still minded to fight on. After service I shewed William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> over the college. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">In the Library I spoke to him about his baptism. It makes no great matter in my eyes whether he is a Baptist or an Anglican; but it matters much whether he escapes being anything definite</hi><hi>. After lunch we walked to the Orchard, &amp; called on Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> D.<persName xml:id="649"></persName> desired me to see her, &amp; I found the poor old lady in rather a depressed state. Then we had tea with Ernest in Wadham. There came to meet me a student named Morgan, who has just produced a novel designed to expose the brutalities of the gun&#8211;room. I asked him whether he meant his picture to be understood as a transcript from life, &amp; he assured me that this was the case. He had gone through it all himself. I dined in Hall with a numerous company of fellows &amp; quondams. Brand<persName xml:id="2046"></persName> is sub warden, &amp; made his speeches with much success. But we are all getting too old for gaudies!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>