<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Holy Innocents Day, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I went to the cathedral, and celebrated at 8 a.m. My budget of letters included one from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nelson</hi><persName xml:id="4341"></persName><hi>, conceived in a less hysterical vein. Also, a very characteristic letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fletcher</hi><persName xml:id="355"></persName><hi> explaining how he came to see the proofs of the Warden's<persName xml:id="228"></persName> 'Life'<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. It appears that he is a delegate of the Press, and sees all proofs in that connexion. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robertson</hi><persName xml:id="251"></persName> <hi rend="bold underline">writes to say that, although not yet official, the announcement that he is going to succeed Sir O. Lodge<persName xml:id="614"></persName> at Birmingham is true</hi><hi>. After breakfast I motored to Eardisland, &amp; preached at Mattins in the parish church. My sermon was an extemporaneous discourse from notes on the subject of the Festival. After service </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Col: Clowes</hi><persName xml:id="4942"></persName><hi> &amp; his wife showed me the sketch of the memorial which they wish to set up on the church wall beside the pew where they sit. These poor people looked so ravaged with grief that I was really distressed for them. Christmas is a hard time for those who have lost only sons.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to the Bishop of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>: and then finished reading Keynes's<persName xml:id="5100"></persName> painfully interesting book, "The economic consequences of the Peace"<ref xml:id="1088"></ref>. It is difficult to avoid the conclusion that a great crime was committed at the Paris Conference.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">"Never in the lifetime of men now living has the universal element in the soul of man burnt so dimly"</hi> <hi>&#8211; this is the terrible sentence in which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Keynes sums up the opinion he has formed of his contemporaries during the months of negotiation in Paris. If that opinion be even approximately true how great has been the moral disaster of the War! What a consequence of the willing sacrifice of lives in a passion of exalted chivalry!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Rain started falling in the course of the afternoon, and as church&#8211;time drew on there was a steady downpour, not friendly to church&#8211;going. I was not much surprised, therefore to find All Saints very scantily attended when I preached at Evensong. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There was much ceremonial which fidgetted me, &amp; I submitted to be clothed in a cape, &amp; led round the church like a sacrificial bull, preceded by light &amp; incense! I dislike all this posturing more than I can say: nor do I think that it really pleases more than a handful of people. The behaviour of the "servers" in the inner vestry where they are admitted on an equality with the clergy displeased me much. The boys did not so much as rise when the Bishop entered. Religion seemed more like a rehearsal for a play than anything spiritual.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>