<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi>			
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 3rd, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName> told me that there was a general desire that yesterday's sermon should be printed, &amp; suggested that I should leave the MS. with the Domestic Bursar<persName xml:id="251"></persName> for that purpose. I did this, &amp; at the same time returned to him his Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> letters. Then I walked round to the Clarendon Press, &amp; had an interview with one of the officials with respect to the Anson Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. After this, I went back to the Warden's Lodgings. We left at noon, and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">motored to the Dillons</hi><hi>, where we lunched very pleasantly. Then we continued our journey as far as Charlton Kings, where we had tea with the Smiths. We went on again at 5.30 p.m., and got back to Hereford through Gloucester and Ross by 7.50 p.m. The weather was lamentable, rain falling ceaselessly all day.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" today contains the Bishop of Norwich's<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> letter to the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, &amp; his Grace's reply. In all 10 bishops had signed the Norwich letter, which is a poor thing in itself, but important as being a stoke on the right side. Its appearance may be taken to indicate that the unquestioned dominance of the "Catholicks" has ended</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Old Prebendary Jellicorse<persName xml:id="5098"></persName>, aged 89, sends me his resignation of the prebend in the Cathedral which he has held since 1892.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>