<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in revising the proofs, &amp; sent the whole lot back to the Clarendon Press. Then I wrote to the Secretary, to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sanday</hi><persName xml:id="359"></persName><hi>, &amp; to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Anson</hi><persName xml:id="302"></persName><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Boden</hi><persName xml:id="2936"></persName><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne Booker</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName><hi> went off after an early lunch, and I betook myself to the Cathedral Library where the Diocesan Finance Board met to distribute the sum of &#x00A3;3000, voted for this diocese by the central Board. There were 138 applications from the clergy, and of these 92 were allowed, the grants ranging in amount from &#x00A3;10. to &#x00A3;50. </hi><hi rend="underline">We are forging our own chains in thus accepting money from the Central board, but the appetite of the necessitous clergy is insatiate and irresistible</hi><hi>. The Committee sate until 5.30 p.m., &amp; was concluded in the Palace, whither I carried the members for the benefit of tea. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName> <hi>and his wife<persName xml:id="2663"></persName> arrived during the afternoon. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ramsay</hi><persName xml:id="5114"></persName><hi>, one of the ordination candidates, arrived a day before his time! After dinner I instructed </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi> for an hour. He can find his way about the Bible, and this is by no means always the case with our candidates for confirmation. Cruickshank and I had much conversation before going to bed. He confirms my impression that my successor<persName xml:id="114"></persName> at the Deanery gives the people no very high notion of independence!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>