<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8. a.m. After breakfast I wrote to Ernest, sending belated thanks for the books on Byron, which he sent me a week ago. I went to the Cathedral for Mattins, &amp; heard a very fine sermon from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Simpson</hi><hi rend="italic">. The text was 2. Cor. IV.5. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">For we preach not ourselves but Christ Jesus as Lord, &amp; ourselves as your servants for Jesus' sake</hi><hi rend="italic">". He used very vehement language in repudiating "professionalism" &amp;c., </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; incidentally declared that he had voted for the Labour Party, &amp; w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> do so again</hi><hi rend="italic">. Probably this is the only part of the sermon (which was admirable in form &amp; substance) which will be remembered. After service I walked along the river with him, &amp; had much talk. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He is quiet rigid in his attitude towards the Virgin Birth, therein surprising me for he had suggested other possibilities</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D. Maples</hi><persName xml:id="4993"></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his wife came to tea. He has been hearing bad accounts of the financial outlook. It is fairly evident that a considerable increase of the income tax is in contemplation. S. Peter's was densely crowded at 6.30 p.m. when I preached on "Marriage". The service is heartily congregational, but why the Vicar "makes hay" of the Prayers in the Prayer&#8211;book I cannot imagine. There seems a temper of lawlessness for its own sake abroad in the Church.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>