<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I communicated in the Palace Chapel at 8 a.m. This is a suitable &amp; devotionally successful building. It made me more than ever discontented with the squalid room at Hereford. At 11 a.m. I attended Mattins at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Alban's, and preached to a great congregation. This is a very fine new church, &amp; appears to be well&#8211;worked. The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vining</hi><persName xml:id="5123"></persName><hi>, was formerly in Sunderland, where I remember preaching for him. In the evening I preached in the cathedral to a considerable assembly. The service is an unconventional arrangement. There is no choir, and everything, except the lesson, is taken from the pulpit. After service we had supper in the Deanery. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Wills</hi><persName xml:id="5058"></persName><hi>, the Dean's<persName xml:id="4449"></persName> father&#8211;in&#8211;law, who is a tobacco&#8211;millionaire, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Peel</hi><hi>, a Fellow of Magdalene College, Cambridge, were also there. There is no doubt about the intimacy of the alliance between the Church and 'Capitalism' in the City of Bristol. The Bishop<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> evidently commends himself with great success to the commercial magnates of the City, and they are contributing to the diocesan funds with considerable liberality. But a suspicion grows on my mind that there must be a quid pro quo for this lucrative patronage, &amp; that it may be something which a Christian Church ought not to be willing to yield.</hi>     
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>