<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Immediately after breakfast I motored with Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> to Stoke S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Milburgh, and there confirmed 39 candidates. The church is a simple but dignified building with a fine timber roof erected in 1707, and an unusually commodious early English font which the present Vicar found in his garden, &amp; restored to the church. After lunch with the Vicar (Rev. H. J. C. Burton<persName xml:id="4523"></persName>) we motored to Clee S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret, where I was shown by the Vicar (Rev. A. J. Knapton<persName xml:id="5101"></persName>) another most interesting church. We then visited the Heath Chapel, a fascinating little Norman church, with a large font of a primitive fashion, square pews, faded frescoes, Laudian Table and rails, &amp; Norman iron&#8211;work on the door. We had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Knapton, whose two sons were presented to me, one an undergraduate of Trinity, Cambridge, the other a student at an agricultural college. On our return journey, we had a puncture at Ludlow, &amp; did not reach the Palace before 6.30 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Enabling Bill passed last night. The Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> referred to me as 'the most rigorous, persistent, &amp; eloquent of the critics', and spoke of my 'characteristic public spirit'. Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> said 'he agreed with the Bishop of Hereford'!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>