<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53] </hi><hi>[sic, duplicated pages 52 &amp; 53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Gow<persName xml:id="216"></persName> who is now recuperating in Madeira: also to Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, &amp; Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>. I paid several bills which were due: &amp; then cleared my table for a meeting of the Clerical Charities Committee. Hopton<persName xml:id="4280"></persName>, Edwards<persName xml:id="4552"></persName>, Simpson<persName xml:id="4640"></persName>, Wright<persName xml:id="4457"></persName>, and Lee<persName xml:id="4610"></persName> lunched here, and then we all went to the meeting of the Diocesan Fund Committee, and spent the afternoon in arranging the annual grants to the poor livings.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Then I had an interview with Roberts, the Curate of All Saints: with whom I discussed the situation of S.<persName xml:id="4845"></persName> at that church. Later I wrote to Canon Procter<persName xml:id="5113"></persName> [Proctor] at Gloucester, who is S.'s Godfather, describing the situation, and suggesting that he should give his Godson some counsel at this very important juncture. I take blame to myself for ever consenting to the arrangement by which S. continued in the school, and only had Sunday work in the parish. It might have worked had matters been normal there, and he himself a less unusual type of man: but the change of incumbents has worked mischief, and S. has disclosed a temperament which stands in special need of the normal discipline of parochial life. It is a lesson to me to be less complaisant in future.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>