<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A heavy snow storm started shortly before 7 a.m. Alfred Spelling<persName xml:id="7"></persName> sends me a copy of "The Southend Standard" for Nov: 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>: 1919, containing a report of a "clerical sensation". Some foolish parson has been declaiming rather more extravagantly than is usual even in "High" Churches against the Reformation, &amp; the Incumbent<persName xml:id="5126"></persName> (the orator was "deputationing" for the Additional Curate Society) found it necessary to protest, &amp; announce his intention of answering the sermon on the following Sunday! He seems to be the recently appointed Vicar of All Saints, Southend, of which Keble College is patron. "Church of England religion won't do. It is a compound of ignorance, of indiscipline, and laissez faire that w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> spell failure in any walk of live etc. etc." It is an odd spectacle. The man hails from Durham where he took a 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> class in Classical honours.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I travelled to Manchester by the 1.12 am. Express. Fog delayed the train between Crewe &amp; Manchester, so that we arrived 45 minutes after time. Canon Scott<persName xml:id="3746"></persName> was waiting on the platform to receive me. There was a pleasant dinner&#8211;party, but I cannot recall the names of the guests. Captain Francis Scott<persName xml:id="5117"></persName>, mine host's son, is at home, but under orders to proceed to Mesopotamia with a draft of recruits.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>