<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received another amazing letter from N. which I replied to with care, first consulting the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> as to my answer. I shall be interested to see whereto this curious episode is tending. Reviewing my relations with N., I cannot honestly say that I think he has any grievance. It was not possible for me, as Bishop, to refuse to hear complaints, nor could I do other than refuse to take any action except in a legal way, giving him every opportunity for self&#8211;defence. In sending for the churchwarden, in the first instance, and inquiring whether there was any foundations to the allegations which, if they were true, could hardly have escaped his knowledge, I took a step which seemed to me obviously right. When I ascertained from the churchwarden that there was no likelihood that evidence w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>be forthcoming to support the allegations, what could I justly do but regard them as baseless. My opinion of N.'s incompetence for his present position was honestly formed partly on my own observations, partly on the state of the parish, and partly on the reports of those who had known him longer than I, and of his neighbours, both clerical and lay. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Dear Mr Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I think you are under some misapprehension. There is no question of any charge against your character so far as I am concerned. Before you were offered the living which you have just accepted, reference was made to me, and my letter determined the action of the Dean &amp; Chapter of Exeter. That circumstance is surely sufficient answer to anyone who wishes to know my view of your character. After an interval of months, I cannot undertake to remember what passed at a private interview, but I recall that it was quite friendly, &amp; that you expressed yourself very properly, &amp; left me with the belief that you agreed that Leominster was not well suited to you, &amp; that a change was desirable. I came to distribute prizes on October 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> on the invitation of the School authorities, who were, of course, solely responsible for the persons invited to be present on the occasion. I return the letter of the Bishop of Sodor &amp; Man<persName xml:id="3229"></persName>, and remain,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours faithfully</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>