<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, (S. Thomas), December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>Grant Thy Blessing upon Thy Church in this place, &amp; own the act of Thy Servant in ordaining these men to the ministry of Thy Church. Give unto them, O Lord, a clear &amp; comforting sense of Thy Presence, and let not my sins bring weakness to their obedience. Deepen in me the love of Thy Name, &amp; make Thy strength perfect in my weakness. Amen.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The names of the Ordinands are the following:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Priests: </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Charles Henry Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>, B.A. Queen's, Oxford.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Martin Custance<persName xml:id="5077"></persName>, B.A. Durham.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Deacons: </hi>	
         </p>
         <p><hi>Harold Arthur Ramsay<persName xml:id="5114"></persName>, B.A Wadham Oxon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Norman Stanley Kidson<persName xml:id="4983"></persName>, B.A. Cambridge, Queen's.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Selby Lennie<persName xml:id="4987"></persName>, B.A. Durham.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>On the whole I think they are rather better than the average of Ordination candidates, though Custance &amp; Lennie know woefully little. They seem to be all actuated by the best of motives, &amp; none of them confessed to any scruple or embarrassment in subscription. This last circumstance is in a way rather disconcerting.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The post brought me a remarkable letter from the Vicar of Leominster</hi><hi>. He writes:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"As the vast majority of the people have asked me to remain here, I propose, on the Sunday after Christmas to explain to them my reasons for leaving. Subject to your permission, I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to read from the pulpit your letter dated July 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1919, which was marked 'private'."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This was the letter in which I told him that I thought it desirable that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> leave Leominster on the first convenient opportunity (July 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919). This egregious parson proceeds:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"The reading of your letter will let those who think that I am running away from difficulties see that the door is closed as far as work in Hereford Diocese is concerned. On the other hand, the generous letter of the honoured Bishop of Exeter will let them see that the door is opened (Rev. III.8) for work in my old diocese".</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Incidentally, the letter will show that he was seeking an exchange before it was written, so that it will hardly serve as an explanation of his departure. But what an amazing jackass the man must be thus to publish my low opinion of him, &amp; to invite public attention to his "rolling&#8211;stone" proclivity. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Ordination was very solemn, and would have been quite satisfactory, if I had not, by some unaccountable stupidity, omitted the Prayer for the Church Militant. I was quite unaware of the circumstance until it was disclosed to me in the Vestry. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> preached an admirable sermon. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to the Rescue Home, where I confirmed seven girls; on my return to the Palace, Charles<persName xml:id="4529"></persName>, my Chancellor, called, &amp; had an hour's talk with me. </hi><hi rend="italic">He says that his Father<persName xml:id="247"></persName>, when offered by Abp. Temple<persName xml:id="171"></persName> the post of Principal of the Court of Arches pointed out that he was the son of a Wesleyan, and unconfirmed. "What has that to do with it?" growled Temple, &amp; insisted on the appointment. The old man strongly approved of my letter in the</hi> <hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>". I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; heard the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> preach his first sermon. He has a good voice, a deliberate utterance, &amp; a good arrangement of his material:</hi> <hi rend="underline">but there is an absence of fire, &amp; emotion which is not compensated for by any indications of special knowledge</hi><hi>. After service, I went to the Town Hall, and presided at a meeting in aid of the Starving Children Fund. The Mayor made an excellent appeal.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>