<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> writes to inquire about the Rev. C. C. Randle, who is seeking an exchange. I wrote to him a candid and discriminating account of the Vicar of Stratton Grandison with Ashperton. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Then I gave <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> the money for Christmas Boxes to the Household. Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came in to discuss various matters in his archdeaconry. He undertook to write to the Lord Chancellor's<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> Secretary<persName xml:id="4397"></persName> with reference to the appointment of a successor to the egregious Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName> in the vicarage of Leominster. I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hamilton, the Patron of Silvington asking him to offer that tiny parish to the Vicar of the adjacent parish of Cleeford S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Mary. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked for about an hour, &amp; then attended Evensong in the cathedral &amp; listened to the carol singing. The 'Hereford Times' contains a full report of my chancellor's decision on the Tenbury faculty. He decides that the Crucifix is illegal. He depends largely on the judgements of Lord Penzance<persName xml:id="5130"></persName>, a circumstance which will not commend his verdict to the acceptance of High Churchmen who regard Lord Penzance as the very embodiment of the State's illegitimate authority over the Church. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>