<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I worked at a sermon on marriage, and was interrupted by Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName>. D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Harris<persName xml:id="4581"></persName> from Colwall lunched with me. He wants to get near one of the great libraries in order to complete his work on N.T. criticism. I called on James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName>, &amp; said that I hoped he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> train one of his sons to the ecclesiastical business, so that the clergy might have someone to deal with in his absence. Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> called to see me. Then I went through a considerable pile of correspondence with Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> returned rather to my surprise.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Hereford Times" contains more hostile letters</hi><hi>. One writer reminds me that "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Hereford has not yet quite become reconciled to D. Henson's appointment</hi><hi>". Others, harp on the string that as M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> nominated me to the bishoprick, I must have preached at his instigation and in his interest! As proof positive, it is pointed out that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I actually made use of the word "anarchy", which the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName> also used in his letter on the strike</hi><hi>! These are difficult times for bishops; &amp; the new Socialism is even less tolerant of independence in preachers than the old democracy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>October 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Harrison,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It gave me real pleasure to receive your letter, and to know that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">you approved my sermon</hi><hi>. I have to thank you for a bundle of copies of your admirable "Appeal". I have taken measures to secure their distribution in the right quarters. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The War has not helped the cause of theological liberty</hi><hi>. Indeed the recrudescence of very crude superstitions, and some bigotries which five years ago seemed moribund, are very depressing. But I do my best, and with the better heart when I know that veterans like yourself can understand &amp; sympathize with my efforts.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me. Yours sincerely</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frederic Harrison Esq</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>To the Editor<persName xml:id="4952"></persName> of Nash's Weekly.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>October 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear Sir,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>You shall have the Article in about 3 weeks' time, and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I shall be glad enough to accept the honorarium you are good enough to name</hi><hi>. The very heavy taxes are immersing Bishops in an Apostolical poverty more wholesome for their souls than for their banking accounts!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. faithfully</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Eveleigh Nash Esq</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I worked at the Marriage Sermon all the morning, and finished it. In the afternoon I walked with Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName>. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> brought me the regrettable news that Green&#8211;Price<persName xml:id="4237"></persName>, the Rector of Pembridge had died. I wrote to his widow<persName xml:id="4965"></persName>. Canon Simpson<persName xml:id="423"></persName> arrived for the week&#8211;end. He has come to preach for the Bible Society<orgName xml:id="198"></orgName>, and to address a meeting.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>