<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, 1919</hi><hi>. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The weather continues to be unseasonably mild. I went to the cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. There were more than 80 com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">I preached at Mattins to a considerable congregation from Hebrews I. 1, 2: and afterwards assisted at the Holy Communion. The sermon was originally preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, Westminster, on Christmas Day 1912: and I chose it now because I wished to have a final proof that the doctrine I teach in Hereford is identical with that which I taught in Westminster. Besides, on the first Christmas spent here, I held it right to handle that very subject – the Divinity of Christ – with respect to which I had been most abused. Mainly, I judge, the sermon "went over the heads of" the congregation!</hi> <hi>Bannister<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="4119"></persName> came to tea, &amp; then we all went to Evensong in the Cathedral. The anthems and carols were excellently sung. There was a large congregation at the service, including, so far as I could see from the choir, an unusually large proportion of men. After dinner, after a custom which I have followed for many years on Christmas Day, I read aloud to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> Milton's 'Ode to the Nativity'. Its powers and beauty never impressed me more. And he was only 21 when he wrote it. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Ellwood</hi><persName xml:id="5081"></persName><hi> writing verses in the Old Bridewell (A.D. 1662) notes the fashion of women to ape the dress &amp; behaviour of men: </hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi>Nor are they within their baubles satisfy'd,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">But sex distinctions too are laid aside</hi><hi>; </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The women wear the trowsies and the vest</hi><hi>. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>While men in muffs, fans, petticoats are drest, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Some women, oh, the shame, like ramping rigs,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Ride flaunting in their powder'd periwigs;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Astride they sit, and not ashamed neither</hi><hi>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Drest up like men in jacket, cap and feather</hi><hi>. </hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>It would appear that we are reverting to the habits of our ancestors at the Restoration. Ellwood's estimate of the manners he denounces is not likely to have been shared by average English folk, but his testimony as to the facts may be trusted. Probably these feminine fashions disappeared before the efforts of the societies for reforming society which played so considerable a part during the reigns of William III and Queen Anne. It may be the case that history in this respect also will repeat itself, and the present license of female manners will be followed by a reaction, which will restore the barriers between the sexes. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>