<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I worked at the Article but to little purpose</hi><hi> for I was interrupted, first, by the Doctor who gave me another inoculation, and, next, by the Vicar of S. Peter's who is very full of his absurd grievance. He went off in a huff, having disclosed himself more than enough. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Town Hall, and attended the new Mayor's<persName xml:id="5080"></persName> reception. There was a great crowd.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The 'Hereford Times' announces two clerical appointments of interest. Archdeacon </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Waterfield<persName xml:id="5128"></persName>, lately Headmaster of Cheltenham, is to be the new Dean of Hereford, and Bishop Michael Furse<persName xml:id="1602"></persName> is to be the new Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Albans</hi><hi rend="italic">. Both men would, I suppose, be described as High Churchman. Furse is still under 50. He is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">persona grata</hi><hi rend="italic"> to the Farnham Ring, and his appointment probably indicates, what the course of the Enabling Bill seems to imply, that the "old gang" are restored to power in Downing Street. Indeed, it is difficult to see how such a Prime Minister as L.G.<persName xml:id="234"></persName> – ignorant of persons, parties, &amp; policies within the Church – could be expected to escape the influences of faction which is supreme in the Hierachy, in Society, and among his own Colleagues.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>