<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning over the proofs of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. There is some risk of the broth being spoiled by the multiplicity of cooks! Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName>, W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>, and Fletcher<persName xml:id="355"></persName> are reading the proofs, and every several contributor corrects his piece. All the matter is in type except Gwyer's<persName xml:id="306"></persName> note on the law&#8211;books, &amp; that may hang everything up again.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The 'Times' has a short letter from Chancellor 'Perverse' Smith<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> answering my letter, but not very effectively. He is an odd angular person who is more laboriously &amp; consistently in error than any other ecclesiastical lawyer of my acquaintance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch I motored to Eastnor, &amp; confirmed 55 candidates in the parish church. After service I had tea in the Vicarage. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi>Somers Cox<persName xml:id="5119"></persName>, the Vicar's wife, is an American. The road was unpleasantly favourable to skidding.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Several letters from parsons asking me to explain the working of the Enabling Act disclose a considerable &amp; widely&#8211;extended anxiety as to the effect of the measure on the harmony of the parishes. Over most of the ground the Act will probably not be brought into effective operation.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>