<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Turner came to consult me on the point whether he should accept the living of Walford&#8211;on&#8211;Wye, which the Lord Chancellor<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> has offered him. I advised him to accept it. After lunch I motored to Neen Sollars, accompanied by Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName> and young James<persName xml:id="5096"></persName> as acting&#8211;Registrar. We mistakenly adopted the more hilly route, and arrived 15 minutes late. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I instituted M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> John Henson<persName xml:id="4264"></persName>, lately Headmaster of the Cathedral School, to the Rectory</hi><hi>. After service we had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Gurney, the Vicar's Churchwarden. We returned by way of Tenbury, &amp; found it easier going. After dinner I attended a meeting in the Town Hall, and heard an excellent speech from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Francis Champneys</hi><persName xml:id="5070"></persName><hi>, on the subject of Venereal Disease. I moved a resolution for the forming of a local branch of the National Council for combating Venereal Disease. The audience consisted of about 80 persons, of whom half were females, mostly middle&#8211;aged. It cannot be described as an influential or an enthusiastic assemblage, but there are too many meetings in Hereford, &amp; the same people come to them all. It is a high time that another method of "raising the wind" was discovered!</hi></p>
         <p></p>
         </body></text></TEI>