<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rashdall</hi><persName xml:id="117"></persName> sends me his <hi rend="underline">Bampton Lectures</hi><ref xml:id="1085"></ref><hi>: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName><hi> send his volume on the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Spirit</hi><ref xml:id="1086"></ref><hi>" which has been written by a series of authors under his editorship. Both these volumes represent considerable knowledge, and intellectual vitality. Add </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge's</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName><hi> very notable volumes on </hi><hi rend="underline">Plotinus</hi><ref xml:id="1010"></ref><hi>, &amp; his "</hi><hi rend="underline">Outspoken Essays</hi><ref xml:id="1083"></ref><hi>", which are, perhaps, even more indicative of mental &amp; moral power. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">All these authors are strongly opposed to the "Enabling Bill", and the type of religion which it expresses. And herein, I apprehend that they are really representative of the abler English clergy</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">The desire for practical reforms, &amp; the circumstance that many of the liberal thinkers are also political Liberals, with whom a merely denominational view of the Church is habitual, have led many of our abler men to acquiesce in the Bill, and even to support it;</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">but there can be no doubt that it represents the triumph of the lower elements in the hierarchy organized &amp; led by the 'Tractarians'</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I travelled to Bristol in order to spend the week&#8211;end with the Bishop<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, and to preach twice in his city. He met me with his little car, and carried me through the rain to his palace, where we had much talk. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>