<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I devoted the day to writing a New Year's Letter to the diocese. It took a gloomier tone in the process of composition than I had intended. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nelson</hi><persName xml:id="4341"></persName><hi> of Leominster sent me a rudely expressed letter. The man is so stuffed full of self&#8211;conceit that he is incapable of profiting by his own failures. His facility of writing is an additional snare, for he depicts himself in the colours of an oppressed saint; and is seduced into crediting his own description! Pecksniff is a very common type. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Before M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Scott took her departure, I had some talk with her about her son<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>. She expressed herself very properly. I sent the Harley Charity (&#x00A3;10) to the two clerical widows, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Ireland and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Cook. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fedarb</hi><persName xml:id="156"></persName><hi> sends me as a Christmas gift</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Westlake's</hi><persName xml:id="800"></persName><hi> little book on 'Westminster'<ref xml:id="1087"></ref> in 'The Story of the English Towns'. It is creditable in Westlake that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have stuck to antiquarian work until he has become quite an established authority on everything in Westminster, and he is wise also for popular interest in antiquarian studies is likely to survive the religious interest which interests Westminster. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>