<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A bad post. The squire<persName xml:id="5120"></persName> of Westhope writes violently against his vicar, &amp; protests that the feud is never to be healed! I suspect that the root of the whole trouble is "spretoe injuria formoe"<note xml:id="496" n="1"></note> of the squire's sister – a strong&#8211;willed female addicted to Ritualism, &amp; parson baiting. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>At 11 a.m. I left the Palace in the car, and motored to Oldbury, stopping on the way at Ludlow to lunch at the Feathers. The weather was unkindly: nevertheless the little church was fairly filled. I dedicated a memorial window &amp; tablet. Prebendary Wright sought permission to demolish the garden wall, which will need to be rebuilt. He has been Vicar for 40 years, &amp; has never obtained a dilapidations&#8211;certificate. Now he begins to apprehend the cost of the accumulated dilapidations. An architectural friend has roughly estimated it at &#x00A3;2000! The annual value of the living is &#x00A3;205. I was back in the Palace at 7 p.m., &amp; found a telegram from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Humphrey Ward<persName xml:id="1224"></persName> about the anti&#8211;Enabling Bill meeting. It was too late to telegraph to her, so I wrote. Then I had an interview with Charles Scott<persName xml:id="4667"></persName>, &amp; definitely settled to ordain him to the Priesthood on the 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> Dec:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Swinnerton Dyer,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your letter distresses me. There is not the smallest intention of suggesting any doubt of your ownership of the churchyard, or of re&#8211;opening it for use. Reference to it was made solely by way of identifying &amp; describing the chapel. If you will suggest a better phraseology, I will consider it with the desire to meet with your wishes. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The situation with respect to the Vicar's position is more serious. He cannot divest himself, &amp; I could not permit him to divest himself, of his pastoral responsibility for the parishioners at Westhope. It w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> offed deeply against every recognized principle of good order, if neighbouring incumbents were to accept an invitation to invade the sphere of the Vicar of your parish. I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be compelled by my obvious duty to forbid them to undertake the services in your chapel.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Surely there is a better way. The unhappy friction between you &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Mason<persName xml:id="5106"></persName> has grown out of a misunderstanding, for which he was certainly not responsible, &amp; with respect to which you were mainly right. The misunderstanding is removed. Ought the friction to be perpetuated? It is only what might be expected that much 'bad blood' had been caused, &amp; that a good many </hi><hi rend="bold">[56] </hi><hi>ill&#8211;advised things have been said in the course of the controversy. Is there no place for the temper of reconciliation and goodwill?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Sir, you have a very special responsibility to be placable, just because you have exceptional influence, &amp; because your personal rights have been the subject matter of dispute. May I not ask you to help me as your Bishop to re&#8211;create harmony, &amp; restore good feeling bet: the parishioners &amp; their Vicar.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>To help in that good work, I shall be delighted to come to Westhope, &amp; preach as I said: but I c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not come in such wise as to consecrate division &amp; discord in the parish.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>With very kind regards</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Most sincerely yours,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Vicar<persName xml:id="4842"></persName></hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have made my decision about Scott, &amp; think it well to inform you what I have resolved to do. On a careful review of all the circumstances, I think equity requires that he should be ordained. It c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not be right to prejudice his future by postponing his Ordination at the last minute – a course wh. w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> normally be taken only for very grave reason. I have insisted, however, that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> give you formal notice (three months) to terminate his curacy at All Saints, &amp; that that he shall leave the school on the earliest opportunity, that is, as soon as he can obtain a suitable curacy in another diocese. Also, I have put him on his honour, that, so long as he remains in my diocese after being ordained to the Priesthood, he shall not hear private confessions without my permission.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have good hope that his behaviour during the remainder of his time at All Saints will tend to remove the somewhat unfortunate impression he appears to have made on you.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Hoping you are getting better,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am, yours v. sincerely,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> A. Rushton.</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>