<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName>, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have no objection to your reading to your people my letter of July 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, provided, of course, that you read the whole of it, and state that it was marked 'private'. You will not connect it with your decision to leave this diocese, for you will remember that you had been seeking opportunities of departure for many months before, and that it was written in answer to a request that I should sanction a project exchange. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I think, however, that you are well&#8211;advised to seek a smaller sphere of work, better adapted than Leominster to your temperament and power. I am glad to hear that the Bishop of Exeter is prepared to welcome you to his diocese, and I hope you will be happy in your new parish.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. faithfully, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.<note xml:id="498" n="1"></note> The newly ordained clergy took their departure. The Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> followed a little later.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Waterfield<persName xml:id="5129"></persName> lunched here, and were shown over the Palace. They strike me as kind and sensible folk who are likely to be both useful and popular in the city. Jones finishing planting the fruit trees. I wonder whether we shall enjoy any fruit from them. In any case, I have done my duty by the garden. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived in the course of the afternoon. He is very full of theatricals, clubs, societies etc. – of everything save his work! I had some grave talk with him before going to bed, but good advice slips off him like water off a duck's back! He certainly has considerable ability of rather a perilous sort, &amp; a curious lack of perspective. He makes friends easily, and seems to provoke few, if any, enmities. This proves the amiability of his disposition, but perhaps indicates a certain lack of tenacity. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">He tells me that the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> has published a correspondence between himself and the archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> with respect to myself! The "Church Times" appears to have been delivering itself with respect to the same gentleman. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Cecil<persName xml:id="4760"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am glad to read your "Christmass" letter, though I am old fashioned enough to prefer the customary spelling: &amp; I hope you will not be over hasty to </hi><hi rend="underline">"restore the Eucharist to its proper place on Sundays"</hi><hi> &amp; to introduce vestments, which are not only illegal, but also unfamiliar &amp; possibly also unedifying. You have a celebration of the H.C. every week – I am very glad to see it, &amp; wonder what you mean by the "</hi><hi rend="underline">proper place</hi><hi>" of the Eucharist, unless you mean to join those who w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> encourage non&#8211;communicating attendance, &amp; bring back a manner of treating the Holy Sacrament which the C. of E. has definitely dis&#8211;allowed. I should be sorry to think that this was in your mind.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I will look again into the question of Middleton, &amp; see whether we can hasten matters. Meanwhile don't talk about resigning. As Charles II said of his humourous barber's suggestion: "There is reason in the thought". I will gladly propose you for membership in a Masonic Lodge, or get you proposed: but I must first satisfy myself as to the best Lodge for you to join.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>May God bless you, &amp; give you joy in this holy season &amp; guidance in the New Year.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours affect</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev Cecil Fortescue.</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>