<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in attending educational conferences, at which both D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Maples<persName xml:id="4993"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Holland<persName xml:id="4976"></persName> attended. We did not effect much. It is more than ever clear to me that nothing can, or ought to be done to prolong the "dual" system. Holland lunched at the Palace, &amp; told me the situation as it now stands with the Government. It appears that Fisher<persName xml:id="2107"></persName> has actually outlined a scheme for unifying national education, &amp; that the "National Society" is not hostile. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Brockhampton, where I had an interview with the poverty stricken curate<persName xml:id="5084"></persName>, &amp; then had tea with the Fosters<persName xml:id="5087"></persName>, to whom I opened his case. They are evidently by no means devoted to their priest, who seems a poor creature. Still they undertook to add &#x00A3;25 to his income, and I promised to ask for as much from the Diocesan Fund for the present distress i.e. during the current year. Also, by way of sweetening the financial bargain, I undertook to preach &amp; lunch in the little church at 11 a.m. on January 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>! The obstinate squire<persName xml:id="5120"></persName> of Westhope refuses positively to have any dealings with his Vicar<persName xml:id="5106"></persName>, &amp; will close his chapel! So much for episcopal essays at peace&#8211;making.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>