<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We left the Palace at 12 noon, &amp; motored to Gloucester taking Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> with us, as he wished to visit his friends in Oxford. We lunched with the Dean<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Gee<persName xml:id="3484"></persName> at the Bell Inn, where they are still living while the Deanery is being prepared for them. We left Gloucester about 2.30 p.m. and motored as far as </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Burford</hi><hi>, where we stopped in order to have tea in the Bull Inn, and see the magnificent and interesting parish church. The Vicar<persName xml:id="5082"></persName> happened to be in the Church, and recognized me. He shewed us the features of the Church very obligingly. I was particularly interested to see the new work of Meade Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>. About 5.25 p.m. we left Burford, &amp; reached Oxford about 6.15 p.m. Here we found a pleasant party collected under the Warden's hospitable roof – Geoffrey Dawson<persName xml:id="2709"></persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="5078"></persName>, Wilfred Green<persName xml:id="5091"></persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="5092"></persName>, and the <persName xml:id="66">Pembers</persName><persName xml:id="937"></persName> themselves. A very agreeable dinner with much conversation afterwards rounded off a day, full of pleasing experiences. The colouring of the woods was really most beautiful, and lingered in the memory. Autumn, "the soul of all regret" never wore a more alluring aspect. It is no less than 35 years since Frank Pember and I were elected together at All Souls.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>