<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote a sermon on "The modern Problem of Drunkenness" for use next Sunday in Holy Trinity, when I am pledged to preach for the C.E.T.S.<orgName xml:id="188"></orgName> After lunch I motored with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to Ballingham, &amp; there inspected the Rectory and the house w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi><hi> it is proposed to substitute for it. I decided against the transaction. On returning to the Palace I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Tickle announcing my decision. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" gives a considerable extract from my letter in the 'Diocesan Messenger' under the heading "Illegal use of Incense: the Bishop of Hereford's acquiescence". Will this lead to any controversy? If the days were normal, assuredly Yes: but, as things stand with us now, I think </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">nothing</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> ecclesiastical could interest the English people</hi><hi>. This is the reason why it is quite possible that the </hi><hi rend="underline">Enabling</hi><hi> Bill may pass into law. Since the public is wholly indifferent, the fanaticks have their way. The Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> has a letter in today's "Times" supporting the Bill. As an ex&#8211;sectary he is of course quite unable to understand the meaning or force of the main objection to the Bill.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Prebendary,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The direction in the Diocesan Messenger about the Lectionary is not intended to be retrospective. I can well understand that the clergy, who, in conformity with my predecessor's permission, introduced the new Lectionary, might find it difficult to go back on their traces. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>On the other matters, my feeling is adverse to any deliberate departure from the prescribed forms. There is a distinction in my mind between a special occasion, and a regular procedure: and again, between adding new services congruous with the old and desired by the people for good reasons, and cutting about &amp; altering at will the old service. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The congregations are different at the several celebrations, &amp; the relief, if relief it be, is really claimed, not for the people, but for the priest.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have been much perturbed by the very general abandonment of the Prayer book after the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> collect: &amp; I have seen no reason for thinking that, as forms for regular use, the new are superior to the old.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The "National Mission", as you know, did not commend itself to me, and I am very sceptical indeed as to its value. But on these points which you mention I have not yet made up my mind whether it is desirable that I should address the diocese, of what, if I did, it is really expedient to say. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have every confidence in your loyalty and wisdom with respect to these matters: &amp; until I do speak, please hold yourself free to go on as you have been going. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours ever,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev. Prebendary Ragg. </hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Not a few clergy in the diocese appear to be using the new unlegalised Lectionary, having been encouraged to do so by my predecessor who – when clearly in his old age &amp; within a few months of his resignation – gave them his permission. Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> himself, Lushington<persName xml:id="4312"></persName>, Riddell<persName xml:id="4840"></persName>, Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, and the Cathedral clergy have all taken this course. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Bishop<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your letter of Nov: 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> has been unanswered, partly, because I have been away from home: &amp; partly, because I have been much pressed with work. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>The grave matter about consenting to a reference of the subject (Fellowship with Non&#8211;Anglicans) to the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> is the implied understanding that its verdict will be accepted. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Now that is precisely what I, and I suppose, every other man whose conscience is engaged in this matter, are not really prepared to do:</hi><hi> and I think it is very desirable that in some formal and public way you make an explicit statement that your acquiescence in any postponement of a decision is conditioned by </hi><hi rend="bold underline">your determination to retain your liberty of action. </hi><hi>The L. C. will certainly do nothing but cant: &amp; quite possibly it may even </hi><hi rend="underline">recant</hi><hi> such frail essays as it has ventured in the past. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Matters might well come to an issue of conscience &amp; will, in w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi><hi>, if we stand firm &amp; stand together, we must win, because </hi><hi rend="underline">au fond</hi> <hi>[at bottom] this exclusive Catholicism of our opponents involves a Reformed Church in self&#8211;stultification. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>I don't think his Grace has acted very candidly, &amp; I feel very sure that, if we depend on him, he will 'let us down'. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours ever,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Bishop of Norwich</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>