<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I sent off the article to Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName>, and then fell to the proofs of the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir</hi><ref xml:id="996"></ref><hi>. I sent the two first slips to the Press with letter to the secretary calling attention to some points. Also I wrote to Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName>, saying that her paragraph about her father sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be inserted: &amp; to Buckle<persName xml:id="322"></persName>, apologising for the stupid attribution of my work to him! Fearne Booker<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> arrived from Durham. Somebody sent me a copy of the "Manchester Guardian" of Nov. 26. It contains a trenchant article by Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> commenting on some recent utterances by Peter Green<persName xml:id="540"></persName>, which have attracted some public notice. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The following is rather "strong meat" for the religious public:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I think Canon Green may be rather too pessimistic about the present state of religion in the country. Why sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> we make church&#8211;going the test? Public worship bores a great many religious people, because they prefer to say their own prayers, &amp; because we are now a nation of readers, not of listeners. The whole system is becoming an anachronism: but this does not mean that people are less religious than they were. The change in our habits is very unfavourable to organized religion: but what attempt did the founder of X</hi><hi rend="i sup u">ity</hi><hi rend="italic"> make to organise religion?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>