<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A beautiful bright morning. The sun shining through crimson &amp; golden leaves makes a gorgeous scene. This autumn emulates the glories of an American Fall. I wrote to F. B. Meyer declining the invitation to go to Newcastle in January for a meeting about Reunion; I said:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"My own hopes &amp; beliefs in this matter of Reunion are, perhaps, sufficiently well&#8211;known. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is also becoming evident that the obstacles within the C. of E. are traceable to a conflict of principles w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">h</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> will have to be fought out</hi><hi rend="italic">. The position is not without suggestive parallels in the ecclesiastical history of this country, &amp; it may perhaps be the case that it is again on the eve of some important &amp; dramatic developments. I do not know but in any case you may be sure that I </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">shall do what I can to draw together into an effective fellowship all in this country who share the same Evangelical convictions &amp; ideals</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in showing Simpson about Hereford, &amp; after lunch I presided at a meeting of the Bible Society<orgName xml:id="198"></orgName>. It consisted of parsons &amp; old spinsters. Simpson made rather a disappointing speech. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Babstock,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have read with great interest the letter w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi><hi> you have been good enough to send me. You are, I think, under some misapprehension as to the facts; &amp; do not, perhaps, quite understand the drift &amp; intention of my words.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">It is entirely evident to me that the Railwaymen were led into an indefensible position, &amp; that they were defeated because the national conscience was against them</hi><hi>. Trade Unions have done much good in the past; but their history has some black chapters; &amp; I do not think the recent strike will add to their credit. It is, I believe, true that most Englishmen are averse from methods of violence; but there is a wave of unreason &amp; unrest sweeping over the world, &amp; it is apparent in England as elsewhere. I think much is said &amp; written about the failure of the Church in the past which is exaggerated and untrue. Be this as it may, power is now quickly passing into the hands of working man, &amp; with it the temptation to abuse it. My duty, as Bishop of Hereford, is to promote good &amp; resist evil. I should fail grossly, if I came forward at a public crisis to excuse what I knew to be wrong, &amp; to </hi><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi><hi> approve what I believed to be unsound.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have no doubt whatever that in the long run the working men of my diocese will approve a course of absolute sincerity even when it seems to tell against action which they have taken.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours sincerely,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H. Hereford</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This letter was written in reply to a very long &amp; confused composition addressed </hi><hi rend="bold underline">to me by a railway man, who has been studying my strike&#8211;sermon, &amp; finds it very unpalatable. He professes to be "concerned about the position of the Church of Christ", and is apparently a deacon in the Congregational Church</hi><hi>. He reminds me of the admirable conduct of my brother of Peterboro<persName xml:id="3933"></persName>, &amp; refers to his letter in the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>". I infer that there is much disturbance of conscience among the strikers, &amp; that they clutch eagerly at any shreds of condonation the servile folly of our time&#8211;servers can give them. The most brutal selfishness now to be found in the public life of England actually succeeds in posing as the most authentic version of the Mind of Christ in the region of economic life!!!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>