<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; then turned to the proofs of the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. I wrote to Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName>, &amp; returned his letters; also to Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> sending him proofs to read; and to Sanday<persName xml:id="359"></persName>, making suggestions. I wrote to the Secretary of the Press, assenting to his proposal that Madan sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be asked to add some notes of references to Oxford phenomena.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> sends me a pamphlet which he has written on "The Church of England". It contains some very good things, and a quotation from one of my sermons.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rashdall's</hi><persName xml:id="117"></persName> '<hi rend="underline">Bampton Lectures'</hi><ref xml:id="1085"></ref> <hi rend="italic">have come at last. Preached in 1915, they only appear in 1919. A learned volume of 500 pages. He is able to say in the Preface that</hi> <hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">except in the case of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Augustine he has read through all the writings of the Fathers, whom he has dealt with at any length in the lectures', and that 'in his case he has read, he believes, all that was relevant to his subject'</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">This statement implies a very noble view of the teacher's duty, and rebukes the facile quotation at 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> hand, which, I fear, is the habit of most 'preachers &amp; teachers' at the present time. May God forgive us the shallowness &amp; insincerity of our work!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>