<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A woefully wet day. After an early lunch, we i.e. Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I motored to Clodock, and there I formally re&#8211;opened the parish church after restoration, and preached a sermon. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName>, and 8 clergy were present, and there was a large congregation. My sermon was embarrassed &amp; its effect largely destroyed by a puling infant, whose wailings were incessant. The weather was so inclement that I could not decently request the brat to be removed, but its presence wrecked my discourse. After service I inspected the church which has many interesting features, &amp; then had tea in the vicarage. We got back to the Palace about 5.30 p.m. </hi><hi rend="italic">Then I corrected and returned the proof of my "Edinburgh" Article on "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Church and Socialism</hi><hi rend="italic">". I am not satisfied with it, but it will serve to disclose to some unsuspecting sentimentalist the direction in which they are now moving, and the catastrophe which surely is awaiting them. The wind blows constantly and with growing strength in that direction, and nothing will much longer be able to stand against it. Whosoever now runs before the wind has an easy course, &amp; makes quick progress!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>