<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919. </hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>'I look upon the task of socialization, not only as an economic, but also as a moral postulate. I do not believe it is a matter of mere materialism; at any rate, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I can put up with the materialism of the hungry more easily than with that of the overfed'</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>President Masaryk<persName xml:id="5105"></persName> Oct 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919. (v. Times, Nov 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919).</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The bitter weather continues, &amp; the omens are favourable to its continuance. It is said that the warmth of the mines attracts the pitmen to their work, &amp; so far the cold tends to provide its own remedy. The "Times" prints a letter, for the authenticity of which it vouches describing the horrors perpetrated by the Bolshevists. It purports to be addressed by a British officer serving with Denickin<persName xml:id="5079"></persName> to his wife. But the incredulity of our "Labour" men is insurmountable. They discount everything that appears against Bolshevism as only another Capitalistic 'stunt'. And Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> is evidently meditating one more </hi><hi rend="underline">volte–face</hi><hi>. The anti–Bolshevists are plainly handicapped by their eager insistence on economy. They cannot suppose that intervention in Russia is compatible with cutting down expenditure.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">30]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>November 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Moore<persName xml:id="4331"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am glad you did not send your 'statement' to the papers for it must needs have </hi><hi rend="underline">some</hi><hi> effect in defeating my efforts to maintain harmony: but as I have the smallest conception of the grievance which you seem to feel, I cannot understand what your reasons for writing can be.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Of course I am at all times ready to see you, or any other of my clergy, but I cannot undertake to discuss my decisions as to the policy which seems to me right in the administration of my diocese. Nor can I draw a distinction between illegalities with which I may personally sympathize and illegalities which I personally regret. If an incumbent desires me, as his Bishop, to know &amp; acquiesce in illegal actions, I think it important that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> know within what limits I am ready to meet his wishes. So much is made clear in my letter to the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Diocesan Messenger'</hi><hi>. So much, &amp; no more. The only alternative to this considered acquiescence in </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold">31]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi> <hi rend="underline">some</hi><hi> illegalities is an enforcement of the law against </hi><hi rend="underline">all</hi><hi>. That is a policy which, although logical, does not seem to me expedient or even practicable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. faithfully,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>H. H.Hereford.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I marked this letter 'private', for my correspondent is quite capable of publishing it without first seeking my permission. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">His vanity is evidently offended at finding himself linked with his Ritualistic neighbour<persName xml:id="4667"></persName> in a common description as a law–breaker: but of course the combination of the contrasted types was essential to the effectiveness of my statement of policy, and also to a disclosure of its real character</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It is true the Evangelical law–breaking is merely anarchic, being inspired by no principle and directed to no definite end: while the "Catholic" law–breaking is of a more deliberate and dangerous kind. It expresses a policy, the complete expression of which would involve the Romanizing of the Established Church: but this distinction, though real &amp; important, must needs be ignored in episcopal administration.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>