<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spent the morning, or misspent it, in writing a letter to the "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" headed, "The Passing of a Bill and the Passing away of an Ideal</hi><hi>". It was only a mourning wreath laid on the coffin of the National church! I want to set people thinking though the time has gone by for action; but something will have been gained if the new "National Assembly" is forced to take a humbler note. The "Literary Supplement" has a friendly notice of "The Naked Truth"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref> headed "Two Bishops of Hereford".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Kington, and there I confirmed about 30 candidates. Later I attended a performance of "Eager Heart" by the G. F. S. girls in the Town Hall. </hi><hi rend="italic">It was prettily arranged but the bad enunciation of the performers made it quite impossible to understand anything that they said. Seven new volumes of the Loeb classics arrived. Thucydides, Homer, &amp; Livy have now come into the series. When (if I live) I have to retire into a cottage or even into lodgings I shall possess in the Loeb classics a portable library of excellent range &amp; quality wherewith to relieve the toedium of senility!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>