<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52] </hi><hi>[sic, duplicated pages 52 &amp; 53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1919.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The morning post brought a letter from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Humphrey Ward<persName xml:id="1224"></persName>, enclosing a cutting from the Manchester G</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> with her letter on the Revival of Tests. She asks me to take the chair if a meeting of protest against the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> Reading is arranged. I replied that, if a possible date were fixed upon, I would do so. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Her</hi><hi> opposition is not likely to attract much support from the rank &amp; file of churchmen who, however divided among themselves, agree in fearing &amp; disliking "Latitudinarians". Nor is it likely to strengthen my position in the diocese or in the country to appear publicly in association with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Humphrey Ward: but </hi><hi rend="bold underline">noblese oblige</hi><hi>: I cannot refuse an appeal from those who are standing for a large tolerance of theological variation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName>, my Godson Herbert Nicholson<persName xml:id="2285"></persName>, &amp; Aleck Beechey<persName xml:id="1708"></persName>. Then there was a meeting of school inspectors, which began at 12.30 p.m. and, with a brief interval for lunch, went on till 3p.m. I walked for an hour: then ran through Leckie's<persName xml:id="4796"></persName> Memoir of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Forrest<persName xml:id="936"></persName>, &amp; wrote to thank his sister for sending me a copy. After dinner I presided at a meeting of the Y.W.C.A.<orgName xml:id="237"></orgName>, and listened to an oration from Miss Picton Turberville<persName xml:id="5112"></persName>.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>