<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>Reading: Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> Atonement.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I worked at the Swedish Lectures, until lunch when Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> arrived from Bridstow, bringing with him </hi><hi rend="bold underline">one of the tutors at Knutsford Training College, named Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName><hi>. He thought that about one third of the students were really fitted for the ministry, and that as large a proportion were quite unfitted. The remainder were difficult to classify. One difficulty arises from the circumstance that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">many of them are either married or engaged to marry, and that the ladies are not well&#8211;fitted socially or educationally, for the r&#x00F4;le of a clergyman's wife</hi><hi>. He said that the average age of the candidates was about 25. On the whole, what M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Clayton said tended to confirm in my mind the impression which I had already received from other accounts viz. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that it is in the main unfortunate that this attempt to gain recruits for the Christian ministry from the Army was made. It was one of the many blunders which are traceable to the so&#8211;called "National Mission", a venture hastily conceived &amp; ill conducted in the emotion and excitement of the War</hi><hi>. I motored K. and his friend back to Bridstow.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>