<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The warm weather continues, and in view of the coal shortage we must be thankful for it. I went to the cathedral and celebrated at 8 a.m. After breakfast I revised my notes for an extemporaneous sermon at Canon Pyon from Rom: XII.I "</hi><hi rend="underline">I beseech you, therefore, brethren, by the mercies of God, to present your bodies a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God, which is your reasonable service</hi><hi>." In a hurricane of wind and rain I motored to the parish, &amp; preached to about two score people. Afterwards I had some talk with the churchwardens in the vicarage, and was assured that the parish was admirably worked, &amp; would resent nothing so much as the eviction of their beloved vicar!! I also had some talk with the vicar's wife, on whom I urged the duty of her husband's resignation. She said that he had decided to resign, but had not fixed the date.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I preached at Evensong in S. Nicholas's Church – a structure of which the hideousness is almost incapacitating for worship. It has no redeeming utilities, for its acoustics are bad, and its arrangement by no means convenient. Wynne&#8211;Willson's<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> boys, Jack &amp; Sandy, escorted me home.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>