<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I finished reading Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> Bampton Lectures<ref xml:id="1085"></ref>. They are stimulating, learned, &amp; transparently honest. I do not know any other living divine who thinks so clearly, works so conscientiously, and writes frankly. The book 'holds the field' as a courageous effort to 'restate' the traditional doctrines of Atonement in a form tolerable to the modern Christian.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> and I motored to Burwarton, and lunched with Parker<persName xml:id="5005"></persName>, who after lunch, accompanied us to Silvington. Here we were met by Griffiths<persName xml:id="4910"></persName> [Griffith], Vicar of Cleeton S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Mary, who has just been appointed to the Vicarage of Silvington which he will hold together with Cleeton S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Mary. I called on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi>Farquhar the widow of the late incumbent, and talked with the Churchwarden.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Then we returned to Burwarton, and had tea. Then we motored to Hereford, and I was back in my study by 6.45p.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>, and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went to a little dance at D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Patterson's, leaving me to myself. Inter alia I tried to understand the new Union of Benefices Act, which seems a very petty measure, but its legal language is so abominably obscure that I cannot be sure that I understand it.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>