<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>Reading: Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> Atonement.]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The day was frittered away in work on the Swedish Lectures, sermon preparation, letter&#8211;writing &amp;c. Wright<persName xml:id="4457"></persName> and the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> lunched here, and discussed the business for the meeting of the new Diocesan Finance Board next week. The clergy are obsessed with the notion that they are grievously oppressed in the matter of the tithe&#8211;assessment &amp; rating. They do not distinguish between hardship and injustice, nor do they realize how indifferent the public is to the fortunes of the clergy, a body of men too few to count at the polls, too scattered to be able easily to combine, and too politically inexperienced to understand the methods of successful agitation. I spent an hour preparing William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> for Baptism. He seems to be interested and sincere. After prayers, I wrote the cheques for the monthly accounts.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName> writes to say that he thinks the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> should be dedicated in the fuller formula, "To the Warden &amp; Fellows of the Souls of All Faithful People deceased, of Oxford". There is an archaic interest about the description which, is, perhaps, worth preserving. How thankful I shall be when this tiresome little volume is off my hands.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>