<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>Reading: "The Spirit" ed. Streeter<persName xml:id="3230"></persName>.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I muddled away the morning over the Lectures. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">General Clive<persName xml:id="5075"></persName> &amp; his wife, and M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Clive<persName xml:id="4941"></persName> lunched here before the service in the Cathedral at which the memorial to Col. Percy Clive<persName xml:id="4270"></persName> was unveiled by the Lord Lieutenant. </hi><hi>There was a considerable gathering of people among whom were the tenantry. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Clive<persName xml:id="5223"></persName> &amp; her two boys made a pathetic appearance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>An illuminating case is before the courts. The plaintiff, Hodges, is a foreman, and claims that the defendant, Webb, compelled him to be dismissed by his employers, by threatening to call out the members of the Electrical Trade Union unless he were dismissed. The defendant admitted that "he told Hodges that if he was not prepared to join the E.T.U. he (Webb) w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have to call his men off the job". This is an interesting illustration of the working of the Trades Disputes Act, and the verdict cannot fail to have far&#8211;reaching consequences. If (as is quite likely) the verdict is for the defendant, it will be curious to mark the attitude of our Christian Socialists, who profess themselves so zealous for "Life and Liberty" in the Church of England.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>