<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi><hi>, the Ordination candidate from Bott's parish, who is now at Keble, wrote to me. He is 'busy with Elizabethan literature'. He thinks that 'Hooker's style is fairly close to yours allowing for some differences of sentence structure'. That is an odd opinion, for my "style", if I have anything that can be called a 'style', is rather after the model of Swift than after that of Hooker.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Nigel Cornwall writes to tell me that he has accepted an appointment as chaplain to the Bishop of Colombo, and will leave the diocese at the end of this year.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] I wrote a letter of condolence to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Davidson</hi><hi>.  I finished and despatched to S.P.C. K. the little article on Education, which I had promised.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gow</hi><hi> detailed to me a long rigmarole about the ecclesiastical situation in Maderia, which is in the Diocese of Sierra Leone.  I promised to speak to the Bishop of that see at the Conference.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The glorious weather continues, and everything is rushing into bloom.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Linnell </hi><hi>with his wife and child left the Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
