<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, London.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Before leaving the Castle I sent a cheque for &#x00A3;25 to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marr</hi><hi> in order that he might get to the sea for convalescence after his operation.  This reduces the balance of the Barrington Fund to a perilous small sum.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> accompanied me to Darlington.  The train was unusually empty, perhaps because people were preferring to see the Prince of Wales who visits Teeside today.  I had a carriage to myself, &amp;, save for the heat, travelled comfortably.  I drove at once to 12 Neville Terrace, Onslow Gardens., where I found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><hi>. The house is very small, &amp;, perhaps, rather inconveniently distant from Lambeth, but it will suffice.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined at Grillions in its new place of meeting, the Grosvenor House Hotel in Park Lane.  It was a small, but very pleasant party of: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Murray</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hartington</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Buckmaster</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey Dawson</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Owen Seaman</hi><hi>, and myself. We had a brisk conversation which never flagged, &amp; we parted in the utmost amiability.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Geoffrey</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke about India with evident anxiety.  He said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Irwin</hi><hi rend="italic">, the best of men, could believe no ill of anybody, &amp; was therefore, but too likely to be deceived by the plausible humbugs in India.  He himself wrote the articles on India in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; he had today had an interview with the Prime Minister, who expressed himself well enough, but pleaded both the exigencies of his position as the head of the Labour Government, and the yielding counsels of the Government of India.  </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Geoffrey</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> expressed no estimate of Ramsay Macdonald.  He was, he thought, both vain and false.  I said that I hoped Baldwin w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be contented with his triumph over Beaverbrook &amp; Rothermere; &amp; would not continue the contest.  He replied that Baldwin himself had told him that he had done with the matter</hi><hi rend="italic">.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Buckmaster</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke with enthusiasm about </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Joan of Arc</hi><hi rend="italic">, whose history he had evidently studied with care: but he had not seen the articles in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic"> which affirmed that she was alive five years after she was said to have been burned at Rouen.</hi>
         </p>
        
           </body></text></TEI>
