<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[165]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[struck through] I wrote to the Bishop of Sierra Leone, sending him the letters which M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gow sent me with reference to the untoward state of affairs in the English Church at Madeira.  I disclaimed any personal knowledge of the matter. [end]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We are mostly engaged in going over the proof of the Report, and this gives considerable opportunity to the "Die–hard" Anglo–Catholicks to renew the fight: but </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Temple</hi><hi rend="italic"> is an excellent chairman, good–tempered, resourceful, &amp; very industrious: so we made fair progress.  We sat until 3:30 p.m., &amp; then went to Buckingham Palace for the Royal Garden Party.  There was an immense concourse: the refreshment tent was besieged, but many could not get 'bite or sup'.  After two fruitless efforts, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi rend="italic"> (very reluctantly) consented to come away.  I am never so near becoming a Republican as on these occasions when I am graciously permitted to approach His Majesty!!  But the ladies love these shows: &amp; so long as that continues to be the case, we shall have to put up with them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We dined with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><hi>.  Lord and Lady Hanworth were there: and an eminent sculptor and his wife.  It was a very pleasant party.  After the ladies had withdrawn, we had an unusually interesting discussion on politics: and I found myself in marked agreement with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hanworth</hi><hi>.  He gave me the impression of being anxious to "bury the hatchet" of the Prayer Book controversy: and I was myself in the mood to be reconciled.  Accordingly, we became quite cordial as the conversation progressed, &amp;, when the party broke up, he volunteered to drive us home in his motor, and did so very civilly.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Di</hi><hi> was very kind, and, indeed, so far as the situation admitted, affectionate.  But we had no singing which was a disappointment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hanworth</hi><hi> said that the new master of the Temple, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carpenter</hi><hi>, was well–liked: but that he was ill heard, a fact he more regretted since he was certainly a good preacher.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><hi> asked when I was preaching again, to which I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> but reply, "at the Greek Kalends".</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
