<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received from S.P.C.K. a cheque for £5.13.1. on account of my commission of 10% on sales of the pamphlet. '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church &amp; State in England</hi><hi rend="italic">'.  It appears that 2262 copies have been sold, surely a very disappointing number, but the subject is abhorrent to most Anglicans, who shrink from the suggestion of Disestablishment all the more vehemently since they cannot dispute its reasonableness.  </hi><hi>[symbol] </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Another "Open Letter" on the subject of the British lazzaroni has appeared this time from Alderman J. Chuter Ede<persName xml:id="5467"></persName> J.P., M.P. for South Shields. It is illustrated with a picture of Auckland Castle, and a photograph of the Bishop, I wrote to him a gentle letter of protest. That is all the notice that I can fittingly take of his attack.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The thin–skinned resentment of "Labour", which is evoked by the merest suggestion that it is not perfect is a very embarrassing and very menacing phenomenon.  With an electorate swollen by the most ignorant &amp; unserviceable of the population, the flattery of the mob is the shortest &amp; safest road to popularity: &amp; for most men, popularity is the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">unum necessarium</hi><hi rend="italic"> of life.  It is difficult to discover any effective remedy for this ill state of the world, as it stands now.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Reichel</hi><hi> thanking him for his Address on the Resurrection, which was really good, though somewhat belated in the mental attitude which it discloses.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Warren</hi><hi>'s charming poem, "The Death of Virgil", and returned it to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Richards</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bidgood</hi><hi> of S. Luke's came to lunch.  He wanted to consult me about the education of his boy, aged 12, who appears to be a dullard.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A Church Army Captain, named Clark, now working in S. Stephen's parish, South Shields, came to see me.  An aunt has left him money enough to pay for 2 years training at a Theological College, &amp; he aspires to be ordained.  I said that if he went to Salisbury Theological College for 2 years, &amp; passed the Deacon's examination I would ordain him.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He gives a horrifying account of the over–crowding in South Shields. The buildings are officially condemned, but as there are no houses in which to place the people who w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be dispossessed by their demolition, they are suffered to continue in use</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> went with me to Hamsterley, where I collated </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Linnell</hi><hi> to the Vicarage.  Save the Rural Dean none of the local clergy was present.  The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Linnells</hi><hi> dined with us before going home.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
           </body></text></TEI>
