<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A misty day until the afternoon, &amp; then sunshine until nightfall. I prepared notes for my sermon, and, after an early lunch, motored with my chaplain to Blackhall for the "stone&#8211;laying" of the new church. There was Evensong in the temporary church when I preached on 1. Cor:III.II. "</hi><hi rend="underline">For other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid which is Jesus Christ</hi><hi>".  Then "processed" to the new church which is half&#8211;builded.  There Alderman </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Whitwell</hi><hi>, a local mine&#8211;owner, "laid" a "foundation stone" in the wall, high &amp; lifted up with his name on it.  I improvised a "dedicating prayer", and gave a Benediction.  Then we returned to Auckland, &amp; found the motor&#8211;cycling race in the Park proceeding.  There was a serious accident, the unfortunate youth was carried to hospital.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamilton</hi><hi> came to see me.  He is dubious about his future, as the Vicar has advised him to look out for another sphere in view of his own impending retirement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The newspapers give prominence to another outburst against the Bishops from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bircham</hi><hi> of Barnard Castle.  He takes up his parable against their incomes and palaces: &amp; denounces their partiality in appointments! Well, well!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
