<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Can I maintain the thesis that universities attain their greatest influence when society is most disordered and corrupt? In the 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century the conciliar movement marked the high&#8211;water mark of academic power: and certainly there are few more degraded epochs.  In the 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century, the universities slumbered as did the rest of the exhausted world: and their new prominence coincides with a new period of corruption &amp; social disintegration.  Intellectual activity makes political discontent and social discomfort vocal, &amp; thereby precipitates revolution.  War must needs tell hardly on universities, both by killing off many admirable students, actual and potential, and by destroying the wealth of the community.  The diversion of intelligence from academic to military activities has an ill effect on intellectual life.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The quiet epochs lack stimulus: the disturbed want leisure – which deficiency is the greater law to culture? Outlook of books, especially of real books may, perhaps, provide a test of academic quality. Here there is an apparent conflict between the two characters of a university, as both a home of research, and a great teaching centre.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Birthday Honours list contains many points of personal and local interest.  There are three new O.M.s – </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi><hi> the philosopher, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Monty James</hi><hi> the medievalist, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Trevelyan</hi><hi>, the historian – a most excellent selection.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We motored to Catterick, &amp; witnessed the King's Birthday Review. The spectacle was very impressive but could not but suggest many melancholy thoughts. As these ranks of well&#8211;drilled, vigorous young men marched past, I could not but remember that the whole of them, dead or mangled, would have expressed the loss of a second&#8211;rate battle in the Great War. There was considerable delay in getting away, for the cars were numberless. However we got back to the Castle shortly after 1.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><hi> a very appreciative account of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi>'s visit.  His sermon seems to have pleased Their Majesties: and he has evidently made a conquest of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stamfordham</hi><hi> himself. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I motored to South Hylton, where I collated </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hitchcock</hi><hi> to the vicarage.  There was a good attendance of his clerical friends, and a large congregation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received from M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hodgson another letter about Kenneth.  She has visited him in Oxford, and interviewed the Warden of Wadham.  She says that her son is 'having panicky attacks' such as he is wont to have 'at examination times': and that the Warden said that it would be a good thing if she could go to Oxford and remain there during his finals!  This seems absurd enough and offers faint promise of the degree!  On the whole my mind settles to the conclusion that, in his own interest, I had best not give Kenneth any fresh chance.  He had best for now face life and its inexorables without anything to screen from him their character.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lady Trevelyan &amp; Miss Monkhouse arrived to stay the night: as did also Prof. Hamilton Thompson &amp; his daughter. Lady T. tells me that the amazing old man, her father, Sir Hugh Bell, is wonderfully well, and still full of interest in secular affairs. He is reported as making a long speech, and apparently accepting public invitations as freely as possible. Plainly he means to "die game".</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
