<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in sermon&#8211;preparation.  There came to lunch the Rev. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">H.R. Flower</hi><hi>, who, for 4 years past, has been one of the staff of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Chad's, Gateshead.  He was ordained in U.S.A., and desires to transfer himself permanently to England.  Accordingly, he is requesting the Archbishop of York to grant him a licence under the Colonial Clergy Act, and needs an approving letter from me.  Before granting this, I desired to satisfy myself that he no longer cherished the homeward aspirations which recently filled his mind, &amp; nearly led to his secession.  I had a long conversation with him, and finally decided to give him the letter for which he asked.  </hi><hi rend="italic">On the whole, he impressed me well.  He hails from Chicago, and his account of that city accords with the worst reports that are current in England.  He says that the "co&#8211;ed" universities of U.S.A are sinks of immorality, &amp; that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Judge Lindsay</hi><hi rend="italic">'s books give a true account of the facts.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Quo tendimus</hi><hi>?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie Lillingston</hi><hi>, whose very moving, because plainly sincere, appreciation of his murdered tutor, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wollaston</hi><hi>, appeared in yesterday's </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>. The Coroner's inquest on the murderer and his two victims is an uncomfortable side&#8211;light on undergraduate life at Cambridge. Neurotic youths, obsessed with a morbid egotism, and armed with repeating revolvers, are apparently able, without the knowledge of the academic authorities, to pursue courses of incredible folly, and even murderous crime. This miserable youth was evidently the leader of a set. Meanwhile, the University mourns a very distinguished teacher, &amp; the country is the poorer for the loss of a very valuable citizen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Miss </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maxwell</hi><hi> arrived on a visit.  I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Linnell </hi><hi>thanking him for the little old coloured print of S. Margaret's and the Abbey, which he sent me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Also, I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Leslie Wilson</hi><hi>, thanking him for his photograph. My mantle&#8211;piece is becoming congested with photographs!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
