<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[255]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The violent thunderstorm of yesterday was renewed during the night, the deluge of rain was too much for the drains, the water pouring into the basement. Havock and loss of life arereported from many places.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Nikolaus Pevsner</hi><hi>, carrying a type&#8211;written recommendation from the Board of Works, called here desiring to see the Chapel.  He was gentle youth with a pleasing manner, and a disarming smile, rather reminding me of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie Lillingston</hi><hi>. He was preparing lectures for delivery in his university, G&amp;#x00F6;ttingen. He expressed himself with proper enthusiasm about Durham Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi><hi> with his wife and sister went off after breakfast.  He is on holiday, and pleads the fact as an excuse for appearing in lay garments.  I told him that he ought at least to have retained the collar so that his clerical character might be perceptible.  I suspect that the influence of his father has not been exalting – a slack, worldly man, who has long lost ideals &amp; enthusiasms, if, indeed, he ever had any.  And </hi><hi rend="underline">he</hi><hi> was the son and the biographer of Bishop Westcott!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[256]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Kay</hi><hi> lunched here, and then walked round the Park with me.  He has just returned from Lahore, where he has completed the term of 3 years service which he agreed upon.  Now he seriously inclines to return for a ministry in England.  I was interested in his account of his experiences in India.  He ascribes much of the present troubles to the education system which, with the best intentions and the worst judgement in the world, as have established in that country.  A numerous proletariat of graduates has come into existence, which with enormously exaggerated self&#8211;estimate &amp; boundless social ambition, finds itself unwanted save for the meanest menial employments.  From 500 to 800 applications would be made for a clerkship in a mercantile firm.  These men disillusioned and embittered, ascribe all their woes to the British Governm</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">t</hi><hi>. He did not seem very confident that Christianity was making advance in Lahore, and would not advance beyond the cautious statement that 'he thought the church was holding its own'. I was surprized to hear that the Afghans were riddled with venereal disease. For I had ever supposed that they were unusually clean &amp; physically sound.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[257]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">I am, I confess, naturally inclined to that which misguided zeal terms superstition</hi><hi>" – so Sir Thomas Browne acknowledges his pious affection for the time&#8211;sanctioned methods &amp; instruments of Catholick devotion. He proceeds to explain himself:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"At the sight of a Cross or Crucifix I can dispense with my hat, but scarce with the thought or memory of my Saviour…</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I could never hear the Ave&#8211;Mary Bell without and elevation…</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At solemn Procession I have wept abundantly while my consorts, blind with opposition &amp; prejudice have fallen into and excess of scorn &amp; laughter."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then he professes his devotion to the Ch. of England.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"there is no church whose every part so squares unto my conscience, whose Articles, Constitutions, and Customs seem so consonant unto reason, &amp; as it were framed to my particular Devotion, as this whereof I hold my belief, the Church of England: to whose faith I am a sworn subject, &amp; therefore in a double obligation subscribe unto her Articles, &amp; endeavour to observe her Constitutions".</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
