<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><!080830>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received 'With M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> W. P. Richardson's compl</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">mts</hi><hi> – he is an official of the Durham Miners' Association – the 'Monthly Bulletin of Statistics' affecting the Coal Mining Industry of Great Britain, issued by the Mining Federation.  It is a most elaborate statement and needs a competent exegete!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning was frittered away. I cannot determine the question on what subject to address the medical students in Newcastle in October, when I give the formal address at the opening of the autumn session.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon, I went into Durham in order to see Lazenby, but he was in Newcastle. However, I got at him on the telephone, &amp; arranged that he should lunch at Auckland tomorrow.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to the Castle, and then went to tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi><hi>, who was entertaining the Land Agents' Association.  His nephew, a King's Scholar of Durham School, was there, a tall stripling with an intelligent face who said he desired to be a Civil Servant.  He said also that he was a friend of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi><hi>'s, &amp; that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi><hi> spoke often of me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Fawkes &amp; Noel Lamidy.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
