<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1930, Auckland Castle</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most glorious morning. The recent rains have made the country fresh and verdant. In the brilliant sunshine everything looked at its best. Who would be such a fool as to live in the City when he could live in the Country? The mere cessation of the unceasing movement and clamour of London is infinitely comforting.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It cannot but be the case that to live in that ceaseless rush and roar must damage brain and heart. The energy of high fever becomes the normal habit of city folk. Sanity implies quiet, and gradualness of movement and the long pauses for thought which the Country alone can provide.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in dictating and writing letters. In the afternoon I walked round the Park with Charles. When I returned a telegram came to me in these terms:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Committee 3 resolution 24 on intercommunion being re&#8211;opened by president's permission tomorrow probably 5.30 in view of </hi><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi><hi> [symbol] minority agitation please return if possible for vital debate.  Several Bishops."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I think that Lang has shown great weakness in consenting to reopen this question: nor can his conduct be easily reconciled with fair&#8211;play.  But the entire extent of the mischief which the bigoted minority can effect, would be the removal from the Resolution of a permission so jealously conditioned as to convey a minimum of courteous intention.  The question of intercommunion would remain where it has been left by the South Indian Scheme.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Moreover, it is by no means certain that my presence and speaking would assist the cause which I should advocate. For I personally go far beyond the carefully&#8211;guarded action which is all that most of the "liberal" bishops are prepared to accept. "Several Bishops" may, and probably does, mean very little. Had some of them appended their names to this telegram, it might have gained persuasiveness. I should look rather an ass if I hastened back to Lambeth in order to swell a secure majority. On the whole, therefore, I shall not yield to this S.O.S.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
