<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We disposed of the Report of the Committee on the Ministry, and made a beginning on that on Moral Witness.  The morning was filled by the debate on Deaconesses, in the course of which </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I made a speech which was loudly applauded, &amp; seemed to impress the Conference.</hi><hi rend="italic">  A number of the Bishops thanked me for it, and expressed admiration.  In this, I think they were mistaken, for the speech was really a flimsy, poor, impromptu affair, which owed all its effectiveness to the speaker's sincerity, and the essential soundness of his argument.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The vote, of course, went against me</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">But there was a substantial minority, and I asked that the numbers might be recorded: but the Archbishop was reluctant, &amp; I yielded to his wishes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch we were all photographed in our seats – a silly performance.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Lichfield introduced the resolutions dealing with Peace and War.  I took exception to the first as being vague and general.  Also I criticized the references to </hi><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi><hi rend="italic"> the Teaching and Example of Christ.  The resolution ran thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">'We affirm that war, as a method of settling international disputes, is incompatible with the teaching and example of Our Lord Jesus Christ.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Rather to my surprize there was a considerable discussion, which stood over for the morrow.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The garden party given by the Archbishops and Bishops of England took place in the Palace grounds. Save for the occasional showers, everything seemed to go off happily. We are collecting visitors for August: viz. Archbishop and M</hi><hi rend="i superscript">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cantes, the Bishop of Rhode Island &amp; his wife, and the Bishop of Blackburn and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Herbert.  I found it uncommonly difficult to identify the overseas Bishops.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We returned to Neville Terrace by bus and underground, an unexpectedly easy journey. Ella went out to dine with her friend, the vegetarian crank&#8211;lady, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Webb, the cricketer's wife.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
