<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension Day, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, G.D.A.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Those who reject the record of miracles in the New Testament do so solely on the ground of improbability; but there are many things which everyone accepts that are improbable.  Of those the greatest is life itself . . . .  Nothing again on the mechanistic theory could be more unreal than memory . . . . </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The grounds on which Christians believe that the miracles recorded in the New Testament were real or possible are not those of science, but they are based on a probability which to them is as high as that of many scientific tests. It is not the probability of the act, for that is improbability itself, but the probability of the truth of the record of it that concerns most . . . Modern scholarship &amp; biblical research have only strengthened the essential credibility of that record, &amp; it is on intuitive perception of its credibility that Christian faith depend.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Prof: W. M. Thornton 'Riddell Memorial Lecture, Second Series, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Is this sound? or satisfying?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m.  We numbered 20 communicants including </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John</hi><hi>, and the 4 </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brydens</hi><hi>.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi><hi> served. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spend the morning in my study, preparing my sermon, and writing letters. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi><hi> and I walked around the Park, and had much talk together.  His 'Anglo&#8211;Catholicism' is certainly compatible with a very frank acceptance of Criticism.  He represents a type which is curiously interesting.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I motored to Kelloe, where I consecrated a Holy Table, and preached at Evensong.  There was a large and attentive congregation.  The choir – 20 girls, 14 boys, 10 men – had surplices, but no cassocks.  The singing was very hearty. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In this church, dedicated to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Helen, there is an ancient cross, now set up against the north wall of the sanctuary, on which is carved what seems to be the history of the Invention of the Cross.  This benefice is in my gift, and is stated to be of the net value of &#x00A3;1130.  The population is rather more than 2000.  I appointed the present Vicar, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Short, in 1923.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
