<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, Eton.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the chapel at 8 a.m.: &amp; received the Holy Communion. Alington celebrated: &amp; about 50 boys communicated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>John Wrightson with 4 other boys came in to breakfast: but, as all the talk was about divers athletic happenings, of which I knew and cared nothing, I found the meal tiresome.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The service in chapel was rather wonderful especially the singing of the boys. My sermon took about 20 minutes to deliver, &amp; was, I think, listened to attentively, but it was probably rather dull &amp; heavy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Alington, Fletcher, the headmaster of Charterhouse, and I walked until lunchtime. We saw the Lower Chapel, &amp; various class&#8211;rooms. At lunch we went to the College Hall: afterwards the Provost took me to his house, &amp; showed me the fine collection of "leaving portraits". We visited the Library which is full of treasures. The Provost</hi><hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi><hi>'s</hi><hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi><hi> wealth of curious learning was equal to explaining everything.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong in chapel at 5 p.m. The Headmaster ascended the pulpit, and, in place of a sermon, read out sacral poems. Of these one was Faber's 'Old Labourer'. It is the first time that I have heard that poem quoted. After service John Wrightson seized hold of me, and carried me to his room, where was his younger brother, Peter. The two boys took me for a walk in the playing field, and manifested much affection.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Several boys came in to dinner, among whom was one, Guest, whose vivacity and intelligence impressed me greatly.  We had a vigorous talk on many 'burning' subjects, including nationalism &amp; establishment.  I was astonished at their eagerness, &amp; at the opinions which they expressed.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is sufficiently evident that Youth is bubbling over with ideas and ideals, which are by no means to be easily brought within conventional limits. What a stimulus to intellectual growth must life in a great public school contribute! Over and above the teaching and the tradition this free interchange of though must be extremely valuable, perhaps the most valuable element in the entire experience.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
