<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[218]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We had much interesting conversation at breakfast, and parted in high good humour.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Peers</hi><hi> and I left Rock Hall about 9:30 a.m. and motored to Warkworth Castle, which I had never yet seen.  This is a north pile of the 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> and 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> centuries, &amp; makes a grand feature of the landscape.  We went on to Chesters where we inspected the Roman Camp, and the museum.  Then we lunched at Hexham, and visited the Priory Church.  We satisfied ourselves that the rib arrangement of the Anglo&#8211;Saxon Crypt, which we had observed in Ripon was to be found also in Hexham.  The verger, a young &amp; self&#8211;confident man, gifted with the omniscience that belongs to his class, showed us the many interesting features of this magnificent church.  The apse of Wilfrid's church, and a tomb which, without any obvious reason, was alleged to be Acca's, was especially noteworthy.  We agreed that the Bishop's Chair may be reasonably regarded as Wilfrid's own.  We motored back to Auckland, &amp; arrived to find Ella "cumbered with much serving".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[219]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The newspapers give great prominence to the Encyclical &amp; Resolutions of the Lambeth Conference, most of them print these documents almost in </hi><hi rend="italic underline">extenso</hi><hi rend="italic">.  There seems to have been little harm done during my absence, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the numbers voting for and against the Birth&#8211;Control Resolution are recorded</hi><hi rend="italic">. One Bishop, Walter Carey, of Bloemfontein, "clears his conscience" by making public his vehement dissent from that Resolution. Probably, we shall have some other disclaimers.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi><hi> writes to inform me that there is trouble brewing in Pelton.  A numerously&#8211;signed petition of the parishioners has been addressed to the Chancellor asking for a faculty to order the removal of a series of illegal ornaments which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi><hi> has illegally introduced into the parish church.  The Chancellor suggests that I might possibly induce M. to remove items of his own accord.  I might as well invite the treat Tower of Durham to afternoon tea.  The man is an ignorant bigot, and, I do verily suspect, not quite sound in his head.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
