<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, Military Service in York Minster.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A thick mist and a drizzling rain was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander's</hi><hi> report on the weather, when he called me at 6 a.m.; but there was a feeling of fineness in the air, and I refused to allow myself to be dismayed by his pessimism.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> and I breakfasted comfortably at 7 a.m. and left the castle at 7.30 a.m.  We arrived in York in two hours, &amp; went to the Deanery.  The minister minster was thronged, and nothing could have been more impressive than the service.  The singing of the hymns &amp; the National Anthem was unforgettable.  The loud speakers were in good form, and the wireless appears to have acted well.  I was assured by many persons that my sermon was well heard: and the warm expressions of General Shute, Sir Hugh Bell, &amp; others allowed me to believe that it was appreciated.  After the service there was a march past of the troops, I stood in my robes beside the General, &amp; saw the men pass.  We were frequently photographed by a batch of indefatigable photographers.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We motored home, lunching on sandwiches by the way, and arrived at 2.20 p.m. I had just time to put a few finishing touches to the notes of my sermon to the Freemasons when that service in the chapel became due. There was a smaller attendance of Brethren than on previous occasions. I prefaced my sermon by a statement about the new practice of admitting women to Freemasons' Services. I said that in my view, it was undesirable &amp; unsustainable, and that I would not permit it in the chapel. Then I preached from Proverbs xxvii.17 "</hi><hi rend="underline">Iron sharpeneth iron: so man sharpeneth the countenance of his friend</hi><hi>". The men listened attentively and were I hope impressed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I learned with distress that the unhappy youth who lost control of his machine and collided with a tree while racing in the Park yesterday has died. He is said to be but 19 years old. This untoward incident adds to the fear and loathing with which motor&#8211;cycles have ever filled me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Observer</hi><hi>" gives some prominence to the quotations from my article "Reflections" in the May issue of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Leslie Wilson</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Simpson</hi><hi> the two ex&#8211;butler's boys.  It is a question whether the time is well bestowed: but both the lads write to me, and I fear that, if I left their letters unanswered, I might do them a spiritual injury.  I confirmed them both, and, while they were in my service, both were regular communicants in the Chapel.  I cannot "wash my hands" of a pastoral responsibility for them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I began reading "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Vatican Council the story told from inside in Bishop Ullathorne's Letters"</hi><hi> by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dom. Cuthbert Butler</hi><hi>, Monk of Downside Abbey. The writer is an orthodox Papist, and he makes no attempt to conceal the fact, but he does not give the impression of being deliberately unfair, &amp; he always expresses himself with urbanity. I think it must be allowed that the Anglican estimate of the Vatican Council was distorted by the vehement resentments of the defeated minority, &amp; that the methods of the majority were more defensible that has been generally admitted.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
