<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[239]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious morning, blue sky and brilliant sun. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 10 communicants. After service I walked round the bowling green with my guests, who expressed great admiration of Castle, Garden, &amp; Park. That indeed is the hour at which are to be seen at their very best.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a letter of condolence to the Duchess of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Northumberland</hi><hi>: and my fortnightly letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Herberts</hi><hi> walked in the Park for an hour before lunch with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> and me.  Everything looked quite delightful.  After lunch the Bishop carried the three ladies into Durham to see the Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Hebburn, and preached at Evensong in the parish church – a dingy, depressing building which is acoustically infamous.  I prefaced my sermon with a reference to the late Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marr</hi><hi>, of whom I allowed myself to speak in terms of eulogy. But I hate passing judgement on anybody in that way. The church was nearly full, but it would not accommodate more than 300 persons, and the population of the parish is little short of 7000!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
