<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[66]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Tuesday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Maxwell</hi><hi> left after breakfast.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">W. Ralph Rumney</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to see me, &amp; I promised to ordain him in September if &#x3B1;) he gave me satisfying evidence of baptism &amp; confirmation, &#x3B2;) his references were satisfactory, &#x3B3;) he passed an examination on the Bible, the Prayer Book, &amp; Doctrine, &#x3B4;) he offered a suitable title.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He is certainly an unusual, &amp;, I am disposed to think, an unusually strong, type of man. The son of a miner at Dipton, he has succeeded in getting education enough to make him able to preach and teach with more than average success. He gave me a little penny booklet, "How shall we pray?", which he had written for the 'South Africa General Mission', and I was impressed by its substance and form. He served through the War, &amp; then went for 3 years to an Interdenominational College at Glasgow for training as a missionary. But he yearns for the Sacramental System, and has been attending the services, &amp; even receiving the Holy Communion, in the Church of England.</hi>
            <seg>  </seg>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dick</hi><hi rend="italic"> sent him to me with warm commendation</hi><hi rend="i bold">.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">So I determined to run the risk of dispensing with my own rules, &amp; ordaining him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[67]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Louis Rudolf Pearson</hi><hi>, an Ordination candidate from South Shields, aged 19, came to be interviewed with a view to his receiving a Diocesan grant.  A slim youth, rather amiable than vigorous, but the captain of his school, &amp; very well commended, he desires to enter Keble in October.  I took him to the chapel, and said prayers with him.  On the whole, he pleased me.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It would be difficult to imagine two more divergent types of Ordination Candidate than Rumney and Pearson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon I walked round the Park with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Graham White</hi><hi>, and heard much talk from him.  He assures me that his friend </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hiram Craven</hi><hi> has not actually joined the Church of Rome, though he has resigned office in the Church of England.  He showed me a tract entitled "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Hour of our Proving: the Reasons for a Resignation</hi><hi>" which H.C. has published.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">In this the Bishop of Durham is largely quoted!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I made a start with the Individualist Club speech, and wrote about one third of the necessary amount. But I cannot be sure that this may not all have to be torn up: for I am not yet quite clear on the point of what I desire to say!!</hi>
            
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
