<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I changed a cheque at the Bank in Victoria Street, and then went to Lambeth.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Neville Talbot is becoming a problem. He led off with a rambling speech which lasted a full half hour</hi><hi rend="italic">, in the course of which he recommended again his own little book!  I spoke shortly, and, perhaps more successfully than before.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Palmer</hi><hi rend="italic"> was long and obscure, both defects being aggravated by his unfortunate stutter.  The Bishop of Algoma, &amp; one of the Scotch Bishops disclosed hostility to the South Indian scheme, &amp; so did the quaint old Archbishop of the West Indies </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">(Hutson)</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">. After lunch we had a deputation of </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough">Sectaries</hi> 
<hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">Nonconformists</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">, 11 in number. They included Carnegie Simpson, who spoke brusquely &amp; effectively. Again, Neville Talbot inflicted a long &amp; mostly irrelevant speech. Headlam also spoke. I found it hard to imagine what good could come from such a deputation received in such wise. I came away, &amp; went to the House of Lords where I voted with the Government on the "Spreadover" Amendment on the Coal Bill; 168 to 36.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lord Hailsham<persName xml:id="5563"></persName> spoke against the Government with astonishing vigour &amp; force.  He gesticulates a good deal, and has a prize–fighting manner.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Buckmaster was very eloquent on the other side. On the whole, I include to regard him as the best speaker in the House of Lords</hi><hi rend="italic">. The Lord Chancellor, Sankey, has a solemn impressive manner. He speaks slowly, and frames his sentences well. All these men are lawyers, &amp; their excellent speaking suggests that legal training &amp; habit may be very advantageous to an orator, perhaps as advantageous as the training &amp; habit of a preacher are the reverse.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined at the Atheaeum with Athelstan Riley. He had got together his collection of Patriarchs &amp; other Orthodox folk, the Archbishop of Utrecht, &amp; the Abp. of Roumania. Lords Brentford ("Jix") and Beauchamp were there, and of the English hierarchy, Temple, Durham, &amp; Chichester. The Abp. of Dublin represented the Church of Ireland. There were speeches. I made a short, foolish, impromptu speech!!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
