<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"In the Middle Ages the ascetic contempt for the body – partly Stoic, chiefly oriental – the barren alliance of medicine with philosophy, and the low esteem of mechanical callings hid from the physician the very gates of the city into which he would enter."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>v. Clifford Allbutt. Science &amp; Medieval Thoughts</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>(Harveian Oration 1900). p. 61</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Even in the xvi</hi><hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi> century medicine and anatomy were taught wholly from books; &amp; teachers were forbidden to use other than prescribed books."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ibid. p. 69</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Galileo may be venerated as the first modern naturalist to set the experimental method conceptually, whereby, and thoroughly before himself, including the deductive side of it."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ibid. p. 98</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The night was stormy and wet.  Rain continued to fall till the middle of the day.  It was cold enough to make a fire in my study acceptable.  After dealing with the correspondence, I returned to the Newcastle Address, &amp; read through again the brilliant and suggestive Harveian Oration which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Clifford Allbutt</hi><hi> delivered in 1900 on '</hi><hi rend="underline">Science and Medieval Thought</hi><hi>'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Eddon</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Craghead, brought a party of Toc H. members, who had been 'running' the camp at Seaton Carew, to see the Castle and have tea.  The arrived at 3 p.m. and departed at 5.45 p.m.: and I hope the enjoyed themselves.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Boutflower</hi><hi> and his brother, the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Southampton</hi><hi>, arrived and had tea with us. They made themselves pleasant to the men.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Rev. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Maclaren</hi><hi> &amp; his sister – Australians who had been commended to us by the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inges</hi><hi> – arrived about 6 p.m. and were shown over the House.  He is the chaplain of a large school in Adelaide, of which the Headmaster is </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bickersteth</hi><hi>, the son of the Canon of Canterbury. They are motoring to Scotland &amp; seeing all they can on the way.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
