<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The morning was occupied with the debate on the Report of the Moral Witness Committee.  The Bishop of Exeter led off with a passionate diatribe against contraceptives, which he clearly placed in the same moral category as abortion and infanticide.  He was loudly cheered.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I followed with a speech which I had prepared rather carefully</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was designed as a reply to the speech of the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Alban's.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"The Bishop w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have us affirm the inexorable attitude of Rome, but he cannot – he would not if he could, for hi is an honest man – clothe us with the casuistic elasticity of which Rome reconciles as unyielding theory to an all&#8211;accommodating practice."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I insisted on simplifying the question thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Can this new fact – the existence of healthful &amp; easy methods of preventing conception – be brought within the practical system of Christian morality?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I took occasion to comment on the hackneyed diction, "Hard cases make bad law" </hi><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">which had been used several times by the opposition bishops.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Do 'hard cases' make 'bad law'?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yes: if the hard cases are few, and incapable of being brought under the general laws.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">No: if they are so numerous that the law becomes generally in operative.  This is roughly the present situation.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Are we going to take up a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">non&#8211;possumus</hi><hi rend="italic"> attitude, and leave the problem to find solution in the unauthorized and unguided action of individuals?  Or are we going to shoulder our own teaching responsibility, &amp; indicate the conditions of rightful use?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Personally, I cannot doubt in which direction the way of our duty must be found, &amp;, therefore, I propose (always reserving my right to seek amendments in detail) to support the Resolutions before us.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My speech certainly made a great impression, </hi><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi><hi rend="italic"> and many bishops thanked me for it.  I was followed by another dervish, Walter Carey, Bishop of Bloemfontein, who made another impassioned appeal, which plainly moved the Conference.  The applause was very laud, but I was assured that it expressed rather admiration for the orator than agreement with his contention, and that, if a vote had been take, the Report w</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have been accepted.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> asked that the Report might be referred back for re&#8211;casting: and this was agreed to.  We then completed the section dealing with Race problems.  After lunch, the Report on Unity was introduced by speeches from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Temple</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic">, of which the first was admirable &amp; the last characteristic. After tea the members of the Unity Committee were photographed. The Bishop of Ripon (Burroughs) dined with us, &amp; went with us to the reception by the American Bishops. We got home about 11 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
