<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant day from morning till nightfall.  I worked at the Edinburgh Sermon.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi><hi> from South Shields came to lunch, and I offered him the charge of the conventional district in Sunderland which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wykes</hi><hi> is relinquishing.  He accepted my proposal with commendable alacrity.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Poole</hi><hi> came to tea, and reported on the situation at S. Oswald's, West Hartlepool.  If only </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilburn</hi><hi> were less "nervy" things would go better, but, as it is, anything is possible.  On </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Poole</hi><hi>'s suggestion I wrote to Lilburn.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattison</hi><hi> and I motored to Stockton, where I instituted the Rev </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Champion</hi><hi> to S. Paul's in succession to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vincent Harlow</hi><hi>. There was a considerable gathering of the local clergy, and a large congregation. The service was both hearty and reverent. A number of people arrived from Harrogate by char&#8211;a&#8211;banc, and car, determined to see their parson into his new job. I based my address on S. John xvi. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Howbeit, when He, the spirit of truth, is come, He shall guide you into all the truth</hi><hi>."  I carried </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Champion</hi><hi> with me to Auckland Castle, where he stayed the night.  We got back about 9.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
