<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Rain fell heavily during the night, and when the morning came, the outlook for the Bank Holiday was dismal enough: but beyond occasional rain&#8211;showers in the early part of the day, the weather steadily improved, and the afternoon &amp; evening were fine.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At Lambeth we resumed our discussion of the Anglican Organization Report.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I made a speech, and moved an alternative form of the printed Resolution.</hi><hi rend="italic">  This was approved by an overwhelming majority. In speaking, I took occasion to explain the position of the English Bishops:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"At least one fifth of the Bishops now gathered at Lambeth are Bps. of the C. of E., an Established Church, to which the statements of the Report do not rightly apply.  The C. of E. does not possess the freedom stated.  In truth, the Establishment in England is at present in a state of partial paralysis.  The Church has agreed on a formal protest or declaration of </hi><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi><hi rend="italic"> fundamental principle, and has charged the Archbishops to appoint a Committee to review the relations of the Church &amp; State.  Broadly we may say that a process of change has been started, which must "mend or end" the Establishment as it now exists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Establishment implied national Christianity. It is precisely because the development of modern democracy has created the secularized State, so that the great majority of citizens are no longer, in any effective sense, Christians, that the historic Establishments are quickly disappearing.  It is certain that the C. of E., the last survivor of the type, will soon be disestablished.  I think that the English Bishops must proceed on the fictional assumption that they also are free: &amp; that they can do this without sacrifice of self&#8211;respect, because they are honestly determined to vindicate the spiritual liberty of the C. of E. at </hi><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi><hi rend="italic"> all costs, and thus to make the assumption, on which alone they can take part in these debates, as true as it is indispensable."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was cheered when I rose to speak, and when I resumed my seat the applause was emphatic &amp; continued.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Scott Thompson</hi><hi> dined with us.  She talked with characteristic vigour on the subjects which interest here.  The Duke of Bedford, whose family archives she has the task of arranging, appears to be an estimable nobleman of an old&#8211;fashioned, almost archaic, type.  Her investigations into the history of the House of Russell, have led her to some rather interesting conclusions as to the allocation of the monastic properties in the XVI</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th </hi><hi>century. No layman was granted the entire property of a dissolved foundation: but the land was granted with a definite purpose of creating local influence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Mall was lined by thousands of holiday folk waiting to see Amy Johnson drive past.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
