<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I slept badly, and got up feeling very giddy &amp; weak.  The necessity to attempt what one feels unable to accomplish is a sore burden.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I left the Castle at 8.15 a.m. and motored to Gateshead, where I dedicated a side&#8211;chapel and a "children's corner" in S. James's Church, celebrated the Holy Communion, and preached the sermon.  In spite of the wretched weather (it rained steadily until about 1 p.m.) there were about 200 communicants.  I felt so ill that my enjoyment of the service was destroyed, but I could not but be impressed by the spectacle of so many very poor people worshipping so devoutly.  Most of them were young men &amp; women.  Old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Reed</hi><hi> was among the communicants.  After the service we proceeded to the Rectory, where I rested.  At 3.15 p.m. there was the annual service of the Gateshead Freemasons in the parish church. The floor of the church was fairly filled with the Brethren.  I preached on 1. Cor. L xv.58.  In my sermon I drew a parallel between the history of the Roman Wall and that of Freemasonry.  After tea at the Rectory, we returned to Auckland.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest Henson</hi><hi> arrived in his car which he drives with characteristic recklessness.  The afternoon &amp; evening were comparatively fine.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
