<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It was raining briskly when Ella and I went to the Church at 8 a.m. for the Holy Communion, and when we returned. [struck through] The Bishop of Lincoln was the Celebrant, and there were but few communicants, no doubt because of the holiday exodus from the West End which marks August.</hi> [end]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast, I prepared notes for a speech in the Conference tomorrow, and then fell to writing letters. [struck through] I wrote to Joyce Jobling, Charlie Lillingston, and Ernest.</hi> [end] 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The re–arrangement of business announced by the Archbishop yesterday will postpone the decision of the Moral Witness C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> to the later part of this week: and my purpose is to return to Auckland on Tuesday.  I am sorry for this, but I hardly see how to change my plans.  I have spoken on the question, which is the only really divisive question, of contraception, and there is no advantage in speaking again.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[struck through] <hi>Ella and I lunched with General &amp; Lady Kirkpatrick.  He told me in the course of the conversation that he and Lord Haig had entered the Staff College together, &amp; that Lord H. was colour–[195] [symbol] blind, and had for that reason nearly been refused admission to the Staff College.  He did not rate Lord H.'s intellect very high, but could not say too much for his character.  He had served in India under </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Irwin</hi><hi>, &amp; had the greatest admiration for him as a man: but his very goodness led him to trust unwisely persons, e.g. Patel, who were thorough–paced knaves.</hi> [end] 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch Ella and I visited the Exhibition of English Ecclesiastical Art. It contains many extraordinarily interesting and beautiful things. We noticed with special satisfaction the objects sent from All Souls, Durham, Hereford, and Westminster. Then we parted, Ella going to tea with Lady Strathmore, and I going to the United Service Club, where I read the Sunday papers. I attended the Evening Service in Westminster Abbey, and heard with difficultly a sermon from the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Peter's, Eaton Square.  I heard enough to assure me that the preacher had given little labour &amp; thought to his discourse.  The service was over within the hour, so that I was home before 8 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
