<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[220]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Peers</hi><hi> left after breakfast.  His departure was regretted, for he is an agreeable guest as well as a well&#8211;informed &amp; intelligent man.  He is certainly an admirable comrade for an archaeological expedition.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read through the Lambeth Encyclical.  It is dignified, sonorous, and impressive: but, of course, it 'rings hollow' to anybody who knows that the actual state of mental &amp; moral confusion in which its authors are immersed.  It is not likely to escape hostile criticism, and, indeed, it lies exposed to obvious objections: for its actual concessions, while destructive of logical coherence, are too petty to have much reconciling value.  The references, report, &amp; resolutions dealing with "youth" are windy and futile.  Their absence would have improved as well as shortlived the Evangelical. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Scott Lidgett</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to ask me to write an article for the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Contemporary'</hi><hi rend="italic"> on the Lambeth decisions, but I declined.  There is nothing useful that I can say, &amp; much that is foolish that I might be led to say.  On the whole, I think it wisest for the present to say nothing.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Scarbroughs</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to lunch.  Also, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dennis</hi><hi rend="italic">, the Baptist Minister, who desires to be ordained and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arthur Watts</hi><hi rend="italic">, who was to have walked with me in the Park.  After lunch I had some talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dennis</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; was favourably impressed by him.  I said that provisionally I would accept him for Ordination at Trinity 1931.  But he must resign his present pastorate at the end of this year: &amp; devote himself wholly to preparation for the Ordination.  I bade him think over what I said, &amp; let me know his decision. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">George</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Beatrice Dennistoun</hi><hi rend="italic"> with their children, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Patrick</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Joanna</hi><hi rend="italic">, came to tea: &amp; hardly had they departed, before </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wall</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his wife brought to us the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Uganda</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Willis</hi><hi rend="italic">.  I was glad to find that Bishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Willis</hi><hi rend="italic"> was pleased with the result of the Lambeth Conference.  He agreed with me that the American bishops were curiously undistinguished &amp; ineffective.  I showed the Bishop and his wife over the house, which (rather to my surprize) they were eager to see.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Charles</hi><hi rend="italic"> went off for his month's holiday, leaving me in a perilous helplessness.  The weather all day has been glorious.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[222]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishop of Ballarat writes a pleasant letter to answer to mine. He seems to have some desire to cultivate an acquaintance, which is amiable, if unwise:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"I know that you will acquit me of any desire to flatter when I tell you that I was hoping that I might have the opportunity of meeting you at Lambeth. I had heard so much of you, of course, and you are better known &amp; appreciated even so far away as Australia than I expect you allow yourself to realize."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This is handsome enough.  If the over&#8211;seas bishops expected much from the Bishop of Durham, they must have been woefully disappointed, for </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that Prelate really played a very small part in the Conference, &amp; actually absented himself from the hectic days which concluded it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Marie Stopes</hi><hi> is reported in the evening paper to have claimed the Resolutions of the Conference a considerable victory for her agitation.  She may be right in this.  If so, the resentment within the Church will be the sharper.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
