<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote at some length to old D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">James Wilson</hi><hi>, erstwhile Canon of Worcester, who now at the age of 94 is still alert in mind &amp; as optimistic as ever. He addressed a long letter to me, sending it through the Bishop of Liverpool in order to give it a chance of escaping the w.p.b.! I sent him, as the most effective way of disillusioning him about myself, a copy of '</hi><hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi><hi>'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert Horne</hi><hi>, an Ordination candidate, came to lunch. I had some conversation with him, &amp; decided to approve him as the recipient of a diocesan grant.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Jimmie Dobbie and Joyce Jopling came to see me, and walked with me in the Park. They hope to be married in August, &amp;, of course, prayed that I would officiate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> McCullagh</hi><hi> brought an officer named Davenport to see the castle.  I showed them round.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Pattinson and I motored to Shiney Row, where I confirmed 49 persons in the mean little new church, which I consecrated a few months past. Since the candidates were so few in number, I took them singly. The church was crowded, &amp; everybody was attentive. After the service we returned to Auckland. The weather became distinctly colder.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
