<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another beautiful day.  I cleared off a large mass of correspondence, &amp; then finished a poor little sermon for the troops at York.  After lunch we motored to Durham, where we dropped </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi><hi> at the School. I think he has enjoyed himself, and certainly I think well of him.  If only </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> would join hands with me in carrying him through these five years before he can be ordained, &amp; would make him feel that we both are glad to have him here, we might do a really kind thing, &amp;, perhaps, garner some comfort in our own declining years!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Anyway, he has another year at the school, &amp; we shall see how he shapes. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I went on to Gateshead, where I confirmed a sick man in S. Aidan's parish. Then, we went to the Newcastle station, &amp; met </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><hi>. We arrived home shortly after 5 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> and I walked for an hour in the garden before dinner.  The evening was ideal, &amp;, save for the bite in the air, one might easily have imagined that we were in the south.  Birds sang divinely, &amp; the castle with its setting of trees &amp; lawns, had an aspect of ravishing beauty.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
