<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, Hunstanworth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another glorious morning, &amp; the country, though needing rain, is still wonderfully verdant. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 17 communicants including our guest M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A blackbird has built its nest in the ivy a few feet of a window of the State room, from which it is possible to watch the nestlings at close range. Blackbirds seem fewer than thrushes now.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The union of Hunstanworth in the diocese of Durham with Blanchland in that of Newcastle has now been completed, and Hunstanworth will henceforth be in the diocese of Newcastle. This is matter of regret to the Vicar, (Rev W. Nairne Clark), and, at his request, I undertook to visit the parish on Whitsunday to preach &amp; celebrate there as a kind of farewell.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Maxwell</hi><hi> accompanied me to Hunstanworth.  We motored thither by way of Stanhope and arrived within the hour.  The gorse is full flower and brilliant, &amp; the country looked its brightest.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[63]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The congregation consisted of about 100 persons, and included a contingent from Blanchland.  Ancient feuds between the villages obstruct the easy working of the new union of the parishes: but </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nairne Clarke</hi><hi> is a sensible man, &amp; there is no reason why the arrangements should not succeed.  I preached and celebrated Holy Communion.  In the course of my sermon I made reference to the final severance of the parish from my diocese.  After service we lunched pleasantly with the Vicar, &amp; then returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Observer" has a comment on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge's</hi><hi> 70</hi><hi rend="superscript">th</hi><hi> birthday:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Such tale of years is suggested neither by the sustained technique of his pen nor by the poise and penetration of his criticism. As an intellectual influence – corrective of the current vice of facile assumptions – Dean Inge's service to his times cannot be overvalued."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent copies of the Spital Sermon to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carr</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><hi>, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Pattinson and I motored to West Pelton, where the "Jubilee" of the church was observed. I preached to a large and attentive congregation.</hi>
            
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
