<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"In the present financial situation of the Diocese the Bishop cannot sanction any additions to the objects for which the Diocese, as such, is financially responsible: and he would, therefore, deprecate any appeals for money for any new object made through the normal diocesan machinery (i.e. rural deanery &amp; parish). The use of that machinery could not but be interpreted as implying Diocesan (i.e. episcopal) sanction."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H.D.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The above is a memorandum which I drafted, and gave to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax</hi><hi> who has evidently gone far in a project for raising funds to defray the cost (&#x00A3;10,000) of building, and the deficit on the working expenses (&#x00A3;400) on his precious 'Retreat House'.  He wasted more than two hours of good working time, and lunched here.  He is evidently seeking to plant his un&#8211;remunerative project on the diocese: but I won't take it on.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most glorious day. The lilacs are in bloom, &amp; the laburnums about to follow. Tulips and rhododendrons are breaking into flower: and wall&#8211;flowers are in almost gross opulence of scent &amp; colour. The copper&#8211;beech is wonderfully beautiful: &amp; the freshness of vernal green has not yet coarsened into the plentiful leafage of summer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started on the Article for S.P.C.K. and had written about half, when I was interrupted by that intolerable </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked round the Park after lunch.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson </hi><hi>and I motored to Gateshead Fell, where I confirmed over 100 persons in the parish church.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi> told me that the announcement of his being commanded to preach before the King had greatly moved the people.  His own congregation has presented him with a set of robes in which to perform his duty!  I suspect that the actual experience for the quaint little function in the Chapel of Buckingham Palace will be rather an anti&#8211;climax to all this preliminary excitement!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
