<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">What our Modernists lack is a sense of proportion in their "sincerity".  While they are hyper–scrupulous on the lesser matters, they are pachydermatous on the greater.  Here is </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Major</hi><hi rend="italic"> informing the world that the opening clauses of the Consecration Prayer are so repugnant to him that he can hardly bring himself to repeat them: &amp; so morally thick–skinned that he can stand at the Altar and say what he does not believe.  His scrupulosity boggles at phrases and details, while it tolerates the grater apostasies of unbelief.  Here is </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> belabouring his Anglo–Catholicks because they explain away the language of the oath of canonical obedience &amp; the declaration of assent and at the same time informing them with much parade of infallible assurance that he himself explains way the affirmations of Creed and Liturgy.  Was there ever such a case of 'straining out the gnat &amp; swallowing the camel'?  The position is plainly too paradoxical to continue.  It most provoke reprisals in the one quarter: and breed a general scepticism in the other.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left the Deanery at 11 a.m., and motored to Marston, where we lunched with the Rector and his wife, after visiting the church and the battlefield.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Griffith Jones</hi><hi> has the aspect of an 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century incumbent: he farms his glebe, keeps bullocks, shoots, and umpires at cricket matches.  We returned to York, picked up the Dean, &amp; motored to Rounton, where we attended the funeral of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Bell</hi><hi>. The Archbishop of York read the prayer of committal, &amp; (to my surprise &amp; regret) gave a short eulogy of the deceased before pronouncing the Benediction. It will be woeful, indeed, if we go back to the days of funeral discourses. We continued our journey to Auckland, where we arrived shortly after 5 p.m. The Ordination Candidate, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas McLeod </hi><hi>, had already arrived.  He impressed me favourably, and, as his references were unusually good, I decided to facilitate his Ordination.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I motored to Coxhoe, where I confirmed 83 persons.  The church was crowded, and there was close attention.  The vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Evans</hi><hi>, informed me that he had to go to Newcastle for medical inspection, &amp; that there was no small likelihood that he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have to undergo an operation.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
