<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The most interesting episode in the proceedings at Lambeth were vehement speeches against the South Indian Scheme from the Bishops of Indiana and Kootenay: but the first was effectively answered by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic">, and the last was not very impressive.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam's</hi><hi rend="italic"> performances in the Conference are very interesting.  He has certainly made a considerable figure both as a theologian and as a negotiator with the Easterns.  He has also 'cut in' on behalf of the S. Indian Scheme very effectively.  His attitude on Episcopacy has been greatly modified since the days when he used to "correct" my use of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lightfoot's</hi> 
<hi rend="italic underline">Dissertation</hi><hi rend="italic">.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He is apt to intervene too often: &amp;, perhaps, with too pontifical a manner. There is always a bludgeon up his sleeve; &amp; he is a hesitating speaker, but it must be admitted that he has done well.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[struck through] I attended the House of Lords and joined Ella at tea with the Duchess of Atholl. It had been supposed that the Pluralities Measure w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be opposed, &amp; there was a rally of Bishops to see it through: but at the last moment "Jix" &amp; Lord Atkins abstained from a division.[end]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Ella and I dined with Lady Struthers.  There was a young–looking married lady, whose name I have forgotten, but whose conversation interested me.  She said that she had four children, to whom she was devoted, &amp; thought that childless women were much to be pitied.  Then she rapidly advanced to the question, now everywhere debated, of "birth–control", and emitted opinions which rather startled me.  She did not see why unmarried women should shrivel into old maids.  Why should they not have lovers, &amp; by the help of contraceptives have no children?  Who would be injured by their doing so?  And if, nobody was injured, why was it wrong?  And so forth, as 'the plausible casuistry of the passions' – to use </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jeremy Taylor's</hi><hi rend="italic"> luminous phrase – suggests.  I told her that the Bishops at Lambeth were engaged in considering the questions connected with birth control, &amp; that I was greatly obliged to her for her frankness.  She assured me that the use of contraceptives was universal among her contemporaries, &amp; that objections seemed to her altogether unreasonable.  But </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Marie Stopes</hi><hi rend="italic"> was, she said, her dear friend!!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
