<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella and I went to S. Peter's, and received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. [struck through]The Bishop of Lincoln (Swayne) a former vicar of the parish was the celebrant, and among the communicants was Philip Baker–Wilbraham who lives near the church.[end]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in writing letters, while Ella and Fearne went to church for mattins.  Among others I wrote to </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Richard Crawshay</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi><hi> who had written to me from an address in Herefordshire.  He reminded me that some twenty years ago he sent me a little book, "The Sayings of Muhammad", being moved to do so by a sermon which he had heard me preach in S. Margaret's.  He was moved to write by reading, in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Daily Mail</hi><hi>, a report of my speech on '</hi><hi rend="underline">the British Lazzaroni'</hi><hi>, which he highly approved.  He sent me a cutting from 'The Ross </hi><hi rend="underline">Gazette</hi><hi>', containing a report of the trial of Welsh miners for stealing apples. The men were on the dole, but they could afford to travel many miles in order to rob orchards. The villagers had suffered so much from these robberies that they no longer dared leave their cottages on Sunday evenings, but stayed at home to keep guard over their gardens!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[struck through] We lunched with the Baker–Wilbrahams. Two of the girls were there, and a certain Miss Murray. I had a short talk with Phil. He has a rather difficult issue to determine in Truro, where the Protestant faction are challenging the legality of the pyx, which Athelstan Riley has presented to the Dean &amp; Chapter (i.e. the Bishop and canons). He cannot deny jurisdiction for Truro Cathedral is also a parish church: but a decision either way might have untoward consequences. Everything points to Disestablishment, as the indispensable preliminary to any effective action.[end]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to Barking, and preached at Evensong in the parish church. Thirty five years have passed since I left, and the place has changed almost beyond recognition. I missed my way in going from the station to the Vicarage, which is now hidden from the road by many mean buildings. All the ground about the house, which gave it dignity and quiet, has been sold, &amp; mostly covered with homes of one sort or another. The Vicarage itself had a poor &amp; neglected appearance, the garden being a little better than a wilderness.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The town has been horribly debased by new buildings, municipal and sectarian: and the quaint Elizabethan Town Hall has been demolished. Modern democracy has done its perfect work. S. Margaret's church has been partially restored, &amp; many interesting features have been disclosed in the course of the restoration. There was a considerable congregation, but not one that suggested that the church had any firm hold on the great population – about 45000 – of the parish. Young women were suggestively numerous: and young men as suggestively few. Of course, I had grown to be no more than a fading legend. A few middle–aged men, who had been choir–boys or members of the lads' institute spoke to me, and some old women who had known me in the past: but mostly I am forgotten, and as if I had not been. The present vicar, the Rev Leslie Hunter, is the son of the well–known Glasgow Congregationalist. He is a rather frail looking man, &amp; is reported to be painfully shy. In spite of the fact that the population has trebled since my time, the staff remains the same viz. vicar and four curates. I got home about 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
