<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Several more abusive letters on the 'British Lazzaroni' theme. It almost makes one despair of one's fellow creatures. Why they should think it worth while to write such witless balderdash passes my comprehension.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I began the address on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church &amp; State</hi><hi rend="italic">' for the E.C.U., and made very little progress.  There is so much that I could say, but so little that I can say </hi><hi rend="italic underline">wisely</hi><hi rend="italic">.  Then the audience will be so alien in sympathy that I shall be "a fish out of water".  What do they expect from </hi><hi rend="italic underline">me</hi><hi rend="italic">?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went in to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Finance Board. After having tea with the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; talking with him until 6.30 pm I motored to Sunderland, and administered Confirmation in S. John's Church. There were about 60 candidates and a small congregation. But these are genuine slummites, and I could not but love them. When I thought of the woeful conditions under which they live, &amp; reflected on the blankness of the future which they have to face, I could not but rejoice that Religion had reached them, and poured into their drab and dolorous lives some divine element of hope and faith. Jackson is certainly one of the Saints.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
