<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant spring day; and quite warm.  I went in to Durham, and licensed clergy, including </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi>. Both had preacher's licenses.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke in Newcastle yesterday on Reunion, and he does not appear to have spoken very wisely.  He referred to the Lambeth Conference with small respect, and seemed to urge his hearers to lawless courses.  "I can see nothing for it but what the Labour Party call direct action.  After all this is the way in which the dominant party came into power.  For my own part I think I would purchase reunion with the Presbyterian &amp; Free Churchmen even at the price of the secession of a few of our extremists."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We motored to Wheatley Hill, and there I confirmed 95 persons. The parish church is exceptionally mean even as judged by the standard of this diocese of mean churches. It only seats about 300 people, &amp; it has to serve a population of over 6000. The parson, Casey, is a crude Anglo&#8211;Catholick, but I was pleased with the service, &amp; with the aspect &amp; behaviour of the candidates.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
