<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">10 Cheyne Walk</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Chelsea</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">June 13</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1930</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear Bishop</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I do so thank you. Words like yours do help me. He had a real affection for you as you know – and he always felt your help as so real in the difficult Prayer book time, when you stayed with us at Lambeth. I am glad you were in Edinburgh at the time of his call home, and tell me of the love felt therefore him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">He was a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">real</hi><hi rend="italic"> Scotchman &amp; he turned in his weakness to re&#8211;reading some of the Scott's novels &#8211; &amp; enjoyed the new life of Sir Walter.  He almost always had a Scott in his box when we went away for a holiday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This is the worst time. I pray I may be worthy of him – please pray this for me, &amp; for his virtual daughter, Mary Mills.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours affect</hi><hi rend="i sup u">ly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Edith M. Davidson</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Please give my love to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8.15 a.m. The four candidates, Bishop Wood &amp; Moore from Sedgefield communicated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi> came to lunch, &amp; to give me an account of his experiences with their majesties. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Malden</hi><hi> &amp; his wife, having visited Sedgefield on the way, came to lunch.  He stated that he was unable to support me on Disestablishment, and seemed to think that the circumstance might make his acceptance of preferment from me impossible.  I bade him dismiss so absurd a notion from his mind.  He is rather a grim person, but his wife seems more cheerful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Wood</hi><hi> went with me to the Diocesan Conference, which was well attended, a fact which seemed to indicate much goodwill to the Bishop of Jarrow, who introduced the subject, "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Way of Renewal</hi><hi>". He took a solemn, devotional line, so that I judged a discussion superfluous, and bade the Conference stand for silent prayer.  Then I pronounced the Benediction, &amp; so we dispersed.  The attention to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><hi>'s paper was close, &amp; it seemed to make an impression.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Priestman</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Hart, had tea with me in the Castle.  We had much interesting conversation.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Priestman</hi><hi> was bred as a 'hereditary Quaker', whose membership of the Quaker sect ended when he married an Anglican.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked in the Banks, and observed to my surprise two biggish boys stark naked bathing just below the weir, in full view of the women &amp; girls. This would not have been allowed when I was Dean: but that was before the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I administered the Oaths etc. to the candidates in the Chapter Office: and then gave my charge in the Deanery Chapel. I repeated, with some additions, the charge on Clerical Impurity which I compose[d] six years ago. In 1924 as in 1930, I was led to deal with that repulsive subject by a hideous case in the diocese.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Wood</hi><hi> and I returned to Auckland where I found that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Rait</hi><hi> ("Domitiana") had arrived.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The day was brilliantly fine, and very warm. Rain still holds off.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
