<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[245]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The night was stifling, and, when morning broke a thick haze lay on the country like a pall. About 6:30 a.m. there was a considerable thunder storm, which failed to freshen or cool the atmosphere.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishop of Calcutta left by the early train. I breakfasted with him at 7:30 a.m.  In our talk, he told me that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hort</hi><hi> was an ardent photographer: that his father (</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Westcott</hi><hi>) was originally destined to be an architect. The many sidedness of the culture which the greater men of that generation exhibited ever surprises me. I do not think the standard has been maintained. "My</hi><hi rend="underline"> father used to say, I cannot think that in the long run, the finite will of man can defeat the infinite Will of God</hi><hi>." Whereto does that tend?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Newcastle, and attended the service in the Cathedral arranged in connexion with the Funeral of the Duke of Northumberland.<persName xml:id="5473"></persName> There was a large congregation. Rather to my surprize the Bishop of Newcastle was not present, [struck through] but probably he was conducting the interment at Alnwick, where (if I mistake not) the Duke is to be buried. – [end]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[246]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Archbishop and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Carter arrived in their car.  I had much conversation with him in the garden, where the warmth of the weather made it pleasant to sit.  The heat grew more intense as the night drew on.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Körsteiner arrived on a visit.  "Artifex" sc. Canon Peter Green<persName xml:id="540"></persName> of Manchester Cathedral contributes to their day's issue of the M. G. a very useful article headed "The Church and Moral Leadership".  He comments on the contradictory character of the criticisms which have been urged against the Lambeth pronouncements, and concludes that "when the first dust of conflict has had time to settle, the general judgement will be that the bishops have handled a great many difficult subjects with conspicuous wisdom and power".  He denies that 'such a gathering as the Lambeth Conference' can fairly or reasonably be required to make new departures.  Its function is 'to sift, estimate, &amp; judge the conclusion already arrived at by the whole body of the faithful'.  This appears to me both true and timely.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
         
           </body></text></TEI>
