<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
         <hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I came away from Eton after breakfast, and on arriving at Paddington, drove at once to King's Cross, and took the Pulman Car Express, which brought me to Darlington at 4.5 p.m. There I was met by Ella and the car. I beguiled my journey by reading Merejkowski's romance, 'The Death of the Gods'. It was an early ambition of mine to write an historical novel, of which the hero should be Julian the Apostate. This Russian writer has done very effectively.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Among my letters were several suggested by my speech on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The British Lazzaroni</hi><hi rend="italic">".  It appears that there was a fairly ample report in the Times of Friday last, a report which, though obviously careful, is disfigured by some curious errors.  My god&#8211;daughter </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Audrey Hall</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to say that she and her mother had seen my portrait in the Academy, and 'liked it immensely'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"I noticed the sword which is so interesting, but your beautiful purple robe attracted me most. Best of all I liked your attitude: it is exactly as I have seen you in Church."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This is well enough.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
