<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><!020630>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930, Reunion of Clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I showed Rawlinson the letter, entered into my Diary at the time, March 14</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, 1890, in which I replied to a request from Henry Reeve, the Editor of the Edinburgh Review, that I should tell him what I thought about the volume "Lux Mundi". He was much interested, and spoke strongly on the value of my Diary, and the wrongness of my present purpose to order its destruction. But I do not think he alters my view. If I had been a man of eminence, achieving something of permanent worth, whether in literature or in life, the case would be otherwise: but being essentially insignificant, there is no reason why my thoughts, or the petty happenings of my petty career, should interest anybody. They might conceivably have had a certain value for my descendants if I had had any: but since I am childless, I have nobody who would naturally be concerned with me. Moreover, my experience of men and things has been too limited for anything of general importance to have come into the record: my personal reflections have no more value than that of any other "failure"!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The eight young women who are members of the G.D.A. left the Castle after breakfast.  They professed that they had "enjoyed" their visit: I trust that they were edified.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi><hi> and his wife exerted themselves to interest and instruct them.  None of them appeared to be really representative of "the modern girl", at least if the common descriptions of her may be accepted.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi><hi> a well&#8211;expressed account of the Tristram Society's visit to Richmond.  He really seems to be interested in medieval churches.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The clergy whom I have myself ordained came together for their annual reunion to the number of about 50.  I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 11.30 a.m.: about 22 of the men communicated.  The creed, sanctus, gloria were sung, &amp; 2 hymns.  It was all very solemn, and, I trust, edifying.  In the interval before lunch we stood about or strolled in the garden.  The weather was minatory, but happily not prohibitive and improved as the day advanced.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi><hi> was rather "fluttered" at lunch by the appearance of 5 or 6 more persons than were expected.  However </hi><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi><hi> I think all succeeded in getting something to eat.  During the afternoon I got speech with a good many.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aubrey Pike</hi><hi> is in a very difficult frame of mind.  He is clearly getting no good from his present situation: yet it is hard to find a more suitable sphere within the diocese.  However, I suggested </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bott</hi><hi>, &amp; he undertook to get into communication with him.  I had some talk with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Carr</hi><hi>.  He will go to Africa to work under Bishop </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lasbrey</hi><hi> next year.  At Evensong I gave a short address.  After this they took their departure.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Cyril Clarke came to say Goodbye, before going to Canada to work under the Bishop of Algoma. I gave him a copy of '</hi><hi rend="underline">Church and Parson in England</hi><hi>': and he undertook to write to me. I am included to blame myself for not accepting this young man for my own diocese, but I could not surmount my dislike of the 'S. Paul's Brotherhood' where he had been trained for the ministry.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening turned out quite brilliantly: so that the Castle only then was looking its best when the clergy were leaving it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella &amp; Fearne went to Newcastle, returning thence with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Smith from Row.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
           </body></text></TEI>
