<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Another stifling and nearly sleepless night, and by consequence, I felt very limp and loose! I shared the taxi with the Bishop of Chester from the Athenaeum to the Church House.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After some indispensable business had been completed, the debate on Colonel Martin's motion was resumed.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I led off with a 20 minutes speech which was much applauded</hi><hi rend="italic">.  The speaking was mainly on the same side, and, finally the motion was carried with few dissentients.  Then I called on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Caröe</hi><hi rend="italic">, only to find him absent.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Alban</hi><hi rend="italic"> was there.  I lunched at </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi><hi rend="italic"> the Athenaeum with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Eden</hi><hi rend="italic">, the late Bishop of Wakefield.  He had been in the gallery of the Church House, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">heard my speech of which he expressed warm approval</hi><hi rend="italic">.  After lunch I walked to Sackville Street and had my clothes tried on.  Then I paid another visit to the Royal Academy: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">my portrait pleased me less than on the former occasion</hi><hi rend="italic">, but why I cannot imagine.  Then I visited the National Portrait Gallery in order to see </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Goya's</hi><hi rend="italic"> portrait of Wellington </hi><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi><hi rend="italic"> painted just after the Battle of Salamanca when the duke was a young man.  He has a curiously startled look.  This is the most interesting collection in London for the student of history.  I went back to the Athenaeum, and had tea, after which I wrote my daily letter to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Athelstan Riley</hi><hi rend="italic"> was in the Club, and fastened himself upon me.  He has become strangely affectionate to me lately, but, if he imagines that I abate anything of my dislike for his absurd ecclesiasticism, he is woefully mistaken.  He extracted a promise from me that I would dine with him on July 15</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> to meet some of his precious Patriarchs: and he pressed me so hard to promise to visit him in Jersey next year that I found it difficult to refuse.  The truth is that I shrink from sea&#8211;passage.  Even to enjoy the difficult hospitality of an ardent Anglo&#8211;Catholick.  I am not to be brought twice over to the woeful experience of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">mal de mer</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
