<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious day, mild and sunny, the country just moving into new life before one's eyes.  I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in Lambeth Palace Chapel, and, after breakfast, returned to Auckland. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi><hi> met me at Darlington.  We all motored to Chester–le–Street for the Confirmation. 180 candidates were presented. Before the service I dedicated a tablet presented by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Reid</hi><hi>. It recorded the names of the Bishops, Deans, &amp; Rectors who have served the Church in the parish for 1000 years past. This confirmation pleased me. The candidates were very attentive, &amp; the large congregation seemed to enter in the service. The Rector thanked me for my address which seemed to give him real satisfaction. It is but rarely that the clergy indicate any approbation of episcopal performances, so that this exception may, perhaps, merit record. Our female candidate was too shy to come up, &amp; would have gone home unconfirmed had I not gone back to the church and confirmed her. The poor maiden was white as a sheet!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I paid my quarterly account for books to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Rees</hi><hi>. It amounted to £19.6.3. which is rather above the average amount.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
