<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><!190730>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Committee sat until 12.30 p.m., and began half an hour earlier.  We were engaged on the draft report, and I succeeded in carrying some connections mitigating the over&#8211;rigid episcopalianism of the draft.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Neville Talbot was in a chastened mood</hi><hi>.  I lunched at the Athenaeum with Abp D'Arcy, who seemed well&#8211;pleased with the progress of his report.  He spoke in high praise of Strong and Barnes. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>He thought little of the American members of that C</hi><hi rend="superscript">tee</hi><hi>. So far certainly the Transatlanticks here made a very poor impression. They are not even 'elequent' or 'foreceful'!</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella and I went to Bexley in order to see Lady Limerick, and the wonderful old house, Hall Place, which her American son&#8211;in&#8211;law Ryan, lately deceased, bought for hear. She has furnished it in admirable taste. It is mainly a 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century house, &amp; is very charming indeed.  We stayed on to dinner and then were motored back to Neville Terrace, where we arrived about 11.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
	 <hi rend="bold">[154]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A local conservative member named, I think, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Smithers</hi><hi> came to dine.  He was in the House on Thursday last, &amp; witnessed the Rape of the Mace by a Communist member Beckett.  He spoke strongly of the manners or no&#8211;manners of the Labour party.  We got to an interesting discussion of Parliamentary personalities.  His admiration for </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi><hi> was unbounded, but he plainly showed considerable doubt as to his ability to lead the party to victory.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Winston Churchill</hi><hi> was, he thought, the cleverest main in the House, but universally distrusted.  He thought that his continuing invective against </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Snowdon</hi><hi> was overdone.  He though well of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inskip</hi><hi> but held "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jix</hi><hi>" in slight esteem.  I was impressed by his evident dread of a General Election.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Beaverbrook's</hi><hi> movement would endanger many seats, and certainly cause the loss of some.  He said that he was in the House, when the P. B. Measure was defeated, &amp; himself carried the figures of the division to the two Archbishops.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
