<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another brilliant morning, but the day became sultry as the afternoon drew to evening.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Linnell</hi><hi><persName xml:id="5468"></persName> offering him the nomination to Hamsterley.  After the shock of the baby's death, he and his wife might be glad of a change.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Wykes</hi><hi> has accepted Evenwood.  He will carry on the tradition, except the Evening Communion.  On the whole I am not troubled at this, for these evening celebrations are often irreverent and almost always superfluous.  Their introduction tends to become a reprisal–policy of the Protestants, and represents no genuinely religious motive.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Sunderland, and addressed a meeting of clergy &amp; nonconformists in the drawing room of Bishopwearmouth Rectory on "the relations of Church &amp; State". The discussion did not contribute anything of value but the affectionate sentiments emitted by some of the Dissenters were most edifying, &amp; if their sincerity equalled their affectionateness would be most welcome. But I have learned to discount the loving talk of separatists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[19]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Bell</hi><hi>'s sudden death in London is reported in the evening papers.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Hugh</hi><hi> was with her.  This is very sad.  I last saw her in York Minster when I preached at the Military Service.  I have met few women, more able and more charming.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a request from the Secretary of "The Individualist Luncheon" asking for the subject of my address on June 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>!! For my guidance a list of the subjects which have been handled this year was sent, and it rather alarms than assists me. At last, after many abortive essays, I settled on the following:–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'</hi><hi rend="underline">The British Lazzaroni: a post–war phenomenon</hi><hi>.' That will give me the opportunity of saying some true &amp; salutary things, which, since the Luncheon prides itself on its publicity, will get about, and possibly (though very improbably) do some good.  I shall invite the expression of their opinions from some of my saner clergy, who have been most conspicuously connected with the unemployed.  Even so, however, I am not very hopeful about it.  I don't possess </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi>'s art of saying familiar things in such wise that they sound original.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
