<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant morning.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><hi> had breakfast early and went off on his homeward journey.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I worked at the speech on Church &amp; State for the E.C.U.  It is not very easy to speak wisely.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> is again conspicuous in the newspapers.  He attended a meeting of Wesleyan Methodists in Birmingham, &amp; took up his parable against the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks to the extreme delight of the sectaries. He repeated his much&#8211;resented phrase about 'attaching spiritual properties to inanimate matter', and added that 'no one could discover a spiritual presence in a consecrated wafer'.  All this is as unfortunate as it is offensive.  My fear is that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> is exasperating his opponents so deeply that they will be hustled into some fatuous reprisals.  With </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic"> calling for 'direct action' in Newcastle and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> making play on the Sacrament at Birmingham, one can hardly wonder that modernism does not commend itself to some Anglicans.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi><hi> and I motored to Shadforth, where I confirmed 96 persons – 48 boys &amp; 48 girls.  The service pleased me for the candidates were attentive &amp; reverent.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
