<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The proceedings were dull and even tiresome.  It would in any case have been difficult to clothe the subject of organizing the Anglican Communion with interest, but the speakers did not improve matters.  The Bishop of Colorado </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">(Johnson)</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic"> made a speech which caused much laughter, for he is a born comedian </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">of a low type</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; he said many funny things: but most of his hearers were startled by such buffoonery indulged before such an audience.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My first impression of the American bishops is certainly very unfavourable</hi><hi rend="italic">. They are, by comparison with the bishops in 1920, markedly inferior company. Lawrence, Brent and Rheinlander have no successors.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Bishop Palmer, lately of Bombay, who now acts as an assistant in the diocese of Gloucester, spoke at some length. His stutter handicaps him rather badly. Old Carter, the Abp. of Capetown, raised the rather difficult question of the name by which the Anglican Communion should be described. Anglican we had ceased to be, but what substitute for that word could be agreed upon is hard to imagine.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He suggested copying the Scottish method, &amp; moving the word 'episcopal' as the defining adjective. Thus the Anglican Communion is w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be a federation of episcopal churches, Scotch, Irish</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi> American, Indian &amp;c &amp;c.  This suggestion was, however, received with coldness.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After the close of the afternoon session, we went in our robes to the ground outside the main entrance, &amp; were there photographed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My draft of an address to the King was adopted with slight alteration.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As I left the Castle, the coffin containing the body of the Bishop of Newcastle, N.S.W. was being carried into Lambeth Church. The Australian bishops will watch it during the night. In the morning there will be a celebration of the Holy Communion, and then will follow the funeral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The result of the election in Norfolk is reported in the evening paper. It shows that the tide is running against Free Trade, for though Labour candidate has been returned, the majority is a narrow one.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
         
           </body></text></TEI>
