<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Devotional Day, Friday, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I made my way quite easily by motor–bus to Fulham Parish Church, where the services and addresses were arranged.  The Bishop of London celebrated the Holy Communion at 8.30 a.m.  There were, I suppose, about 150 bishops present.  We had breakfast in a parish room hard by the church.  The readings were from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Church</hi><hi rend="italic">'s '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Pascal</hi><hi rend="italic">', the sermon on Bishop Andrews, but the acoustics of the room were so bad that many of the feeding bishops heard little. Old Bishop Talbot, now in his 87</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> year, was the conductor, but he was more impressive than coherent, and was heard with difficulty.  In the intervals between the addresses we sat about in the Palace Grounds, which are very beautiful.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The spectacle of the ancient moat, which has been filled in to save the expense of keeping it clean filled me with a resentful melancholy</hi><hi rend="italic">.  The great heat made attention very difficult </hi><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">and in point of fact I more resembled Eutychus than Apollo.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i bold">When the last address had been given, I got away, and went to the Athenaeum, where I had tea, and read the morning papers.  The </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Times</hi><hi rend="i bold"> has a short report of my speech in the Albert Hall: the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Daily Telegraph</hi><hi rend="i bold"> has a longer report and a short leader: the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Morning Post</hi><hi rend="i bold"> gives prominence to a lengthy article by that pragmatic jackass, </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Douglas</hi><hi rend="i bold">, expressed with some rudeness towards me.  The best report is in the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Birmingham Daily Post</hi><hi rend="i bold">, where no doubt the local situation furnished a reason for emphasizing what I said.  The </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="i bold"> has a fair report: &amp; the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi rend="i bold"> a brief one.  The Church Papers had necessity to postpone their reports until next week.  On the whole, I think it must be admitted that the Press have dealt fairly with the speech &amp; recognized its important.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
	 <hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>July 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Sir,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have to acknowledge your letter of the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> July, and to say that, which I fully recognize and appreciate the importance and potential value of such a symposium as the Central Council for Broadcast Adult Education has projected, I do not feel able myself to take any part in it.  Apart from the question of personal qualification for that particular work – a point, however, on which I am very doubtful – I am so much pressed with other duties, which cannot be avoided, that I dare not undertake any fresh responsibilities.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours faithfully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Herbert Dunelm.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Director</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Talks Department</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The British Boradcasting Corporation</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Savoy Hill</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>London</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>W.C.2.</hi>
         </p>
         
           </body></text></TEI>
