<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48] </hi>[sic] </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Canon Bowlby came to see me. He is staying with Hugh Stobart, an old pupil of his: and he had come over to Escombe where he possesses a farm. I did not realize that he had resigned the Headmastership of Lancing, and is now a residentiary canon of Chichester. I showed him the Chapel &amp; Stateroom.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Francis brought two lads, Ronald &amp; Gordon, aged 18 and 17 respectively, to be confirmed. After the service they had tea, and then returned to Middleton. </p>
         <p>Caröe looked in on me. He is on one of his lightning tours in these parts, and had a few minute between trains. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I picked up the old miner, who frequents the Park, &amp; took him round the bowling green. He disclosed an appreciation of the trees &amp; flowers, which surprised &amp; impressed me. Incidentally, he said that he had never been inside the Chapel. I suggested that we should have a walk around the Castle. So I spent most part of an hour in showing the old fellow over the place. He was greatly impressed, &amp; I think, appreciated my concern for him. But what can he make of it all? On the one hand, the idle and embittered miners full of Cook's rhetoric: on the other, the bizarre &amp; unintelligible splendours of the Bishop of Durham's house! I would give much to know the old fellow's real mind on the contrast!</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
