<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The two Ordination Candidates, my two Chaplains Lionel and Tony Chute, Ella and myself were the Communicants.</p>
         <p>Ella and Fearne accompanied me to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, where I officiated at the marriage of Rowland Burdon Webster and Mary Story. Archdeacon Derry, Brack, and the Rector assisted. I gave a short address. Then we attended the reception at South Hill, where a numerous company had come together. I was told that as many as 300 motor cars were "parked" there: but both the parties were well&#8211;known.</p>
         <p>At 5 p.m. I interviewed the two condidates – John Simner George Llewelyn, and Hugh Jameson Holme – neither of whom is notable. Then, after writing their names in the Greek Testaments, I made notes for a "charge"; which I delivered at Evensong to an assembly of six persons, viz. Chute, Moulsdale, Romans, Trotman, &amp; the 2 candidates. </p>
         <p>After dinner, I took Tony to my room, &amp; talked with him until Compline. We discussed again the situation in Oxford. He thought that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chavasse</hi> at S. Aldate's was probably the greatest personal power in the University. The evening services for undergraduates were ill&#8211;attended, &amp;, unless there was an eminent &amp; attractive preacher, nobody went to the regular University sermon. He wished that the possession of motors were prohibited to undergraduates. Discipline was not helped by them. There was not, he thought, much definite anti&#8211;Christian profession in Oxford, but there was little interest in religion. New College was said to contain an anti&#8211;Christian set. He owned to finding the musical services in Magdalen Chapel rather tiresome: &amp; the undergraduates hardly ever attended.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
