<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A Newcastle doctor writes to me about the crisis. <hi rend="bold underline">He offers reasons for thinking that the redoubtable M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook is actually suffering from mental disease, of which the megalomania which colours his speeches is an unerring symptom.</hi> If this view be sound, then the agitator's course may be cut short by death before long. But he may yet do much mischief before he goes to his own place. Who is the Frenchman who maintained that in Revolutions madmen rise to the top, &amp; seize the reins of power? He supported his thesis from the history of the French Revolution: he could strengthen it by the case of the Russian. In both the rôle of homicidal maniac has been prominent in both [sic]. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My article on "The deadlock in the Mines" in the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> has evidently attracted some notice. Correspondents refer to quotations from it in the "</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Sunday Times</hi><hi rend="bold underline">", "</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">the Scotsman</hi><hi rend="bold underline">", the "</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Newcastle Evening Journal</hi><hi rend="bold underline">", and the "</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Morning Post</hi><hi rend="bold underline">". I received letters both of approval, and of disapproval. The first come from Tories: the last from Socialists! Nothing in this party&#8211;cursed country can ever be considered on its merits</hi>.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Selwyn, the Editor of "Theology" is a prominent Anglo&#8211;Catholick, and the editor of the notable volume, "<hi rend="underline">Essays Catholick &amp; Critical</hi>", which may be called the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Apology. He sends me his grateful appreciation for my "outspoken words on the Coal dispute quoted in today's <hi rend="underline">Sunday Times["]</hi>, and suggests the making of "some kind of just protest" to be made by those who hold with me "against the truly disastrous activities of the Industrial Christian Fellowship". He thinks that the disgust produced in the educated classes will have an ill effect on recruiting for the Anglican Ministry among "those who send their sons to Public Schools &amp; Universities". He suggets that a [sic] "the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be asked to publish a letter <hi rend="bold">[97]</hi> signed by a dozen or fifteen persons whose names for one reason or another would carry weight". I am never much attracted by proposals of this kind. They invite counter&#8211;proposals which cannot but lessen, if they do not destroy, their impressiveness. Then, in this case, <hi rend="bold underline">the "Copec" nonsense has made such headway among the clergy that I doubt whether it would be possible to get any considerable number even of those who regret the action of the Bishops to sign any kind of condemnation of it</hi>. Besides, the Archbishop of Canterbury can hardly be thought to stand wholly uncommitted by the action of these goose&#8211;bishops, for they were his collaborators in his foolish pronouncement during the General Strike, and, though he did not actually take part in the conferences with Cook &amp; C<hi rend="superscript underline">o.</hi>, it was stated that he was cognizant of, and friendly towards, them. Few bishops or leading clergy will sign anything which can be interpreted as a censure on the Primate.</p>
         <p>Ella and I motored to Bealings, a hamlet not far from Woodbridge, and lunched with Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith, who have settled themselves in a house called "The Gables".  After lunch we went on to Ipswich &amp; called on the Bishop, but finding that he was absent in Brittany, we had tea in the "Great White Horse Hotel", and then returned to Bramfield. I learned from Colonel Smith that his nephew Herbert is already an ardent Anglo&#8211;Catholick, and is to be sent to Mirfield in due course. Both his mother &amp; his aunts are devout Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, so the poor child hasn't a dog's chance!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Bishop of Lichfield writes to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> disclaiming the episcopal authorship of the "memorandum", which the miners' representatives "accepted", but he does not say to whom the authorship is to be attributed. He declares that he and his colleagues "are resolved to persevere in the Christian task of reconciliation, &amp; shall lose no opportunity of promoting a just settlement of this disastrous &amp; protracted dispute". His obstinacy is equal to his muddle&#8211;headedness, and both are exceeded by his vanity.</p>
         <p>We (i.e. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Thompson, Ella, and I) dined out with Lord &amp; Lady Huntingfield. They showed us the house after dinner in order that we might see the new electric light installation. Wyatt had much to do in the building of the house, &amp;, where he was "on his own", &amp; not engaged in spoiling other buildings, he could do well. The proportions &amp; decorations of the rooms are admirable, as fine specimens of the time 1758–1770 as I have ever seen. Mine hostess reminds me of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Chapin: the latter lady is a caricature of the former. Both are illustrations of that type of earnest, pushing, enormously virtuous female, of which America is prolific. Lord H. is a cheerful, little, up&#8211;to&#8211;date pagan, who talks much and laughs more, but has both intelligence and good sense. After the ladies had withdrawn we had some political talk. He says that the present Parliament will probably extend the franchise to girls of 21! He is on the large committee of members who have been considering the possibility of legislating about the Trade Unions, &amp; did not seem very optimistic as to the probability of anything effective being done. He agreed with me that the Prime Minister's prestige was being perilously weakened by the continuance of the Coal Stoppage.</p>
         
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
