<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Bell of Tudhoe delates Watts of Shildon for holding me up to ridicule at Ferryhill before a large meeting of miners &amp; their wives! He took my article in the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> point by point, and criticised it. Well, there is no remedy for bad taste, &amp; lack of humour. If a clergyman chooses to insult his bishop, he can do so, not only with complete impunity, but, as things now stand with us, even with considerable applause. That large area of social conduct which is regulated not by positive rules, but by the unformulated assumption that "it isn't done" grows – as Sir James Paget said, ever smaller: and society is the worse for the fact</hi>.</p>
         <p>The "Manchester Guardian" has a leading article headed "Religion &amp; Economics". It describes me as "a keen adherent of the old economics", and credits me with a hankering for the old industrial horrors! I wrote a brief corrective note.</p>
         <p>I read through a very valuable little book by Sir Josiah Stamp, which bears directly on my Edinburgh article – "<hi rend="underline">The Christian Ethic as an Economic Factor</hi>". He certainly brings out the forgotten severities of the actual economic situation, and gives our "Christian" enthusiasts food for thought.</p>
         <p>Canon Storr, his wife &amp; daughter arrived. Ella took them into Durham to see the Cathedral. </p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson came over, and brought various papers [for] signature. He arranged about the train for the expedition on Friday, and had tea.</p>
         <p>Adamson, the Vicar of Grangetown, came to dine &amp; sleep. He wants me to accept from him a title for the Ordination of Neil, but I am not at all clear either that he is well–suited to train a deacon, or that his parish ought, in the present penury of clergy, to have a second clergyman. He is mildly Anglo–Catholick himself, and would hardly "hold in" Neil's Anglo–Catholick tendencies. However I can hardly find sufficient ground for refusing a title. </p>
         <p>Herbert Smith came for a visit – a silent awkward youth.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">"A soul like a walnut and a mind like a rag bag are the two enemies of all millenia</hi>." p. 20</p>
         <p>"The world accepts the pulpit valuation of the church wherever it is derogatory." p. 21</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Josiah Stamp</hi>, "<hi rend="underline">The Christian Ethic as an Economic Factor</hi>"</p>
         <p>Wilson tells me that there is an evil rumour afloat in Durham which credits the University with the intention of erecting lecture rooms on the eastern side of Palace Green, &amp; in order to do so, pulling down the fascinating xvii<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century buildings which now exist. The County Council is reported to have offered a grant in order to enable this outrage to be enacted. With the Castle threatening to fall down, and the restoration Fund definitely failing, the University might be expected to refrain from adding shame to poverty! Any appeal for money in the present state of the county is bound to fail.</p>
         <p>After dinner Mary Storr sang in the State Room very beautifully. She has a good voice, which has been carefully trained. Storr and I had some conversation before turning in. He seems to cherish the hope that Parliament may take an interest in Prayer Book Revision, and might even throw out the measure if it included Reservation. I extinguished the hope. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
