<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]In general a man ought not to do other people's duty for them; for their duty was appointed them for their exercise; and besides, who will do it in case of his death? Nor has a man any right to raise in others such a dependence upon him as that they must be miserable in case of his death, though while he lives he answers that dependence.["]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A comment on Butler's dictum, and, perhaps, a justification of it is provided <hi rend="bold underline">by a description of a patriarchically administered property which I came upon</hi> in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maclean</hi>'s "<hi rend="underline">Life of J. Cameron Lees</hi>" p. 405. It is not difficult to imagine that the permanent effect of such all&#8211;embracing benevolence as <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Ellice</hi> exhibited towards her tenants in Glengarry would be morally debilitating, and her death must have left many of them in a difficult situation. The fact that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maclean "<hi rend="underline">never heard a word of appeal on behalf of personal liberty – or of a Scotsman's house being his castle" indicates that an effect on character was apparent</hi>. It was probably a permanent effect, and could hardly be described as good. <hi rend="bold underline">Benevolence, conscientious and thorough&#8211;going, was, perhaps, on a broad view of consequences, doing more harm than good</hi>. Of course, one's judgment will be finally determined by the values which one attaches to specific moral qualities. Are courtesy, gratitude, loyalty, contentment to be placed above virility, independence, self&#8211;respect, &amp; the like? That the former are more agreeable, gracious and attractive may be conceded; but are they intrinsically superior? It is on the answer to that question that the final verdict turms. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I paid a first instalment of &#x00A3;100 to Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">ers</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cornish &amp; Gaymer</hi> on the Escomb Repairs Account. </p>
         <p>Also I paid &#x00A3;32.19.6 for furniture for the Diocesan Chaplain's Rooms. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamilton Thompson</hi>, President of the Northumberland &amp; Durham Archeological Association invoking his interest in the defence of Cosin's Building on Palace Green.</p>
         <p>I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Clelland, the heretick minister in Glasgow, saying that I would preach for him on April 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1927. How vain these promises so long beforehand must needs be.</p>
         <p>I picked up a lad named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Banks</hi>, who hails from Spennymoor. He is 19 years old, &amp; has been working in the pits earning 25/&#8211; to 30/&#8211; weekly. <hi rend="bold underline">He says that the Bishop of Durham confirmed him 3 years ago, &amp; that he is a regular communicant in the parish church</hi>. He seemed intelligent, and said he was fond of reading: so I gave him a copy of "<hi rend="underline">William Tyndale</hi>". His father, a joiner, is in work.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Blakiston</hi><hi rend="italic">, the President of Trinity, came for the week end.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">About 45 students from Cambridge, who are embarking on an undergraduates mission in Darlington came to have tea, and see the Castle. They were led by Canon </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Woods</hi><hi rend="italic">, the brother of the Bishop of Winchester. Before going off, I said a few prayers, &amp; spoke a few words in the Chapel. Also, I gave each of them a copy of my lecture on "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">William Tyndale</hi><hi rend="italic">". They were a pleasant crowd, not at all bumptious and canting. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But I am by no means convinced of the soundness of such missions, which yet I dare neither to criticize nor to refuse. Undergraduates should devote themselves to their studies, &amp; not stand to preach. However, as the world goes now, we must take the youth on their own terms, or we shall not get them at all!</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
