<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Rain fell most of the morning. I spent most of the time in the Library writing letters. Among others, I wrote to Spooner, Cruickshank, and William.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon we visited the parish church, a large pretentious galleried structure built about 100 years ago to replace an older structure, which the masterful &amp; wealthy rector pulled down in the teeth of parochial protests. The present bishop has just caused a vast pretentious episcopal throne erected in the nave to be removed, &amp; has replaced it by a demure conventional wooden cathedra in the chancel. Then we walked up the hill, and had tea with Miss Brown, who was so frequent a visitor to the Gows in Dean's Yard that we used often to meet her when she lived in Westminster. She has adopted a small boy – 2<hi rend="superscript">1/2 </hi>years old – and plainly doats on him. Intelligent conversation is rendered almost impossible by the affectionate exchanges between the two! On the whole, I prefer the ancient custom of relegating such children to the nursery.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Bailey</hi> has a well&#8211;expressed letter in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> on the mining situation. He describes as "important" and "untrue" the claim of Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kirk and Carter to represent themselves as the mouthpieces of "the Churches". To some extent this letter relieves me of the necessity of writing myself, as I should have done if Welldon had not again "butted in" and "spoiled the pitch".</p>
         <p>The weather, though cooler, was curiously "heavy" and exhausting.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
