<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Almighty and everlasting God, who art always more ready to hear than we to pray, and art wont to give more than we desire, or deserve; Pour down upon us the abundance of thy mercy, forgiving us those things whereof our conscience is afraid, and giving us those good things which we are not worthy to ask, but through the merits and mediation of Jesus Christ, thy Son, our Lord. Amen.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. We numbered 8 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, including two clergy. </p>
         <p>Parsons, the Rector of Birch, sends me the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> volume of a considerable work by many authors, entitled "<hi rend="underline">An Outline of Christianity: the Story of Our Civilisation</hi>", which he editors [sic] in company with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Peake. He sends also a letter asking me to "honour us with a brief expression of your judgment on the work". The editors "sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> regard it as a great favour, more especially if you w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> allow a sentence or two to be quoted under your name for the guidance of the readers among the general public for whom the 'Outline' has been prepared".  I dipped into the volume, &amp; formed a very favourable opinion, which I expressed in a letter. </p>
         <p>Also, I sent the "young practical pitman" a copy of <hi rend="underline">Quo tendimus</hi>? on the off chance that he would read, and could understand it.</p>
         <p>Also, I sent a copy of the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> to Lord Danesford, and another to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bovill, who had written to me about Bishop Westcott. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
