<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]The reading of histories may dispose a man towards satire; but the science of history, history studied in the light of philosophy, as the great drama of an ever unfolding Providence, has a very different effect. It infuses hope and reverential thoughts of man and his destination.["]</p>
         <p>v. S. T. Coleridge, "Church &amp; State". p. 38</p>
         <p>I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. Gennadius</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Envoyé Extraordinaire et Ministre Plenipotentiaire Honoraire de Grece</hi> who offers some comments on "the learned &amp; illuminating article on Pilgrimages" which he had read in the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>. Also I received a civil letter from the Bishop of Lichfield who sends me copies of his Diocesan Magazine containing his pronouncements on the Coal Stoppage. I spent the morning, after disposing of the business letters, in working at the <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Article</hi>, but very helplessly. My right hand has lost its cunning. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch I walked in the Park, where I talked for some time with a very decent and reasonable miner. He, like all the rest with whom I have spoken, is longing to get back to work. I inquired what truth there was in the rumour that the ponies were ill treated in the pits. He said that they were often over worked, a patient, good tempered beast being preferred to a more troublesome animal, &amp; put to work two shifts in succession. But generally he said that the ponies were not ill used</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Struthers</hi> arrived on a short visit.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
