<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]Of the six countries, the United States has been that in which money has been most generally powerful during the last sixty years, France that in which it is probably most powerful now, while Canada comes next, Australia, New Zealand, and Switzerland being practically exempt, though of course a party or a group of men with ample funds for elections and able to run newspapers in its interest enjoys everywhere an advantage.["]</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bryce</hi>, "<hi rend="underline">Modern Democracies</hi>". ii. 499</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received the proof of my Edinburgh article, which forthwith I corrected and returned</hi>. Then Spencer Wade came to see me about various parochial problems, and stayed to lunch. He is steadily moving away from the sentimental Socialism which he once professed. He says that the small pits in his parish are mostly working, though shorthanded. A number of people came to play lawn&#8211;tennis and look on. Among them were General &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dudgeon from Catterick, and Pemberton. Charlie Lillingston goes up to King's, Cambridge, in October, &amp; is looking forward to it with eagerness. He seems to be really keen on history. I found and sent him a copy of my paper on "<hi rend="underline">The gift of historical thinking</hi>".  A deputation from the local branch of the "British Legion" came to see about blessing a banner. I sent them to the Vicar.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
