<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A hot close night. I started the day in a jaded disaffected mood, not favourable for exertion or for society! The news of the Strike is all bad, save that the violences of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cook's oratory, which daily grow more extreme, <hi rend="underline">may</hi>, perhaps, indicate a consciousness of defeat, &amp; must provoke a reaction in all minds that retain any sense of decency. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Herbert Smith's comparatively reasonable speech may possibly disclose a purpose on his part to part company with Cook. Meanwhile time passes, and the loss to the Country caused by the Strike is reckoned to be not less than &#x00A3;8,000,000 daily. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Birkenhead in a speech reported this morning speaks ominously of increases of taxation, next year &amp; possibly this year also, as probably unavoidable. And so far the deadlock seems to be complete.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow came to see me during the afternoon. I showed him the copy of the letter which I sent to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> yesterday. <hi rend="bold underline">His comment was that it ought not to have been sent until the Strike was over. He thought the Castle windows might be in danger!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received two letters which gave varying accounts of the course of the discussions at Lambeth, the one from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baker&#8211;Wilbraham</hi>, which said that all was going well, the other from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest of Worcester</hi>, which indicated the possibility of a secession of the minority bishops.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Also, a letter came from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mary Radford</hi><hi rend="italic">, asking my advice on the point whether she should take charge of a Birth Control Clinic which, it is proposed to start in Oxford. I wrote to her on the subject, on the whole dissuading her. But the whole subject is as hateful as it is obscure and unavoidable. </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
