<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to Lionel in reply to his letter informing me that his project for going to India had fallen through. It would not be good for him to hold the Chaplain's Office for a long period, but two years would rather advantage than hinder his ministry.</p>
         <p>Also I wrote to J. G. Wilson on the subject of exchanging benefices asking him to consider the matter, &amp; to be ready to advise me about putting out some instruction to the clergy with respect to it. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi> has another letter in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, on the Coal Crisis. It is really hardly possible for me to do other than leave him in sole possession of the field!</p>
         <p>We left the Castle about 10 a.m., and motored to Woodchester, in order to lunch with Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Soltau&#8211;Simmons, and to view the Roman pavement in the Churchyard, which has recently been again uncovered. Our route lay through Worcester, Tewkesbury, &amp; Cheltenham. We stopped to look at the glorious Abbey Church at Tewkesbury. At Cheltenham, Ella stopped to call on her cousin, with whom was a pleasant&#8211;looking lad her nephew, Herbert Smith. The views from Birdlip hill were magnificent. We reached Woodchester in good time for lunch: and visited the Roman pavement, which in beauty &amp; freshness of colour exceeded my expectation. We reached home by way of Gloucester, where we had tea in the Bell Hotel, and went into the Cathedral. Ella stopped to visit some ancient nurse, &amp; then we resumed our journey, arriving back in Hartlebury at 7.15 p.m. after a very enjoyable and successful expedition, carried through in glorious weather. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
