<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have wasted most of the day in reading Houtin's "Un prê&amp;circ;re symboliste Marcel H&amp;#x00E9;bert (1851–1916)". It conveys a surprising view of the Roman Church, as honey&#8211;combed with scepticism of one kind or another. The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Abb&amp;#x00E9; Duchesne</hi><hi rend="italic"> does not make an edifying appearance in this book. He is credited with having destroyed H&amp;#x00E9;bert's belief in Christ's Resurrection (p. 89) and, certainly, letters of his are printed which indicate that he expressed himself as heartily in agreement with H&amp;#x00E9;bert's general position, though more cautious in confessing it. When the crisis came, and H&amp;#x00E9;bert was dismissed from his position as "le Directeur de l'&amp;#x00C9;cole F&amp;#x00E9;nelon" because he would not withdraw what he had written in Souvenirs d'Assise. Duchesne tried to persuade him to a recantation, and when his advice was rejected took it in ill part. H&amp;#x00E9;bert reminded him that he was himself mainly responsible for the loss of faith which now he professed to disapprove. Duchesne wrote him a letter (July 27</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1901) which is a demure &amp; canting composition. H&amp;#x00E9;bert did not reply, and their friendly relations ceased abruptly. His expulsion from the priesthood seems to have been inevitable. I cannot honestly censure Cardinal Richard for deciding that "un prêtre symboliste" was out of place in the ranks of the clergy. If I were myself as Bishop required to pass judgment on such doctrine as that of Souvenirs d'Assise, I would not but have condemned it, though I should have insisted on a punctiliously fair trial before an independent tribunal. It is less the actual condemnation of the modernists that is reprehensible than the manner in which it is arranged, and the cruel harshness with which the condemned are treated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Frau K&amp;#x00F6;rsteiner, Ella's Swiss friend, arrived, and played the piano pleasantly after dinner. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
