<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>During the night there was a considerable thunderstorm, and this morning the air continues to be very heavy &amp; oppressive. It is a strange season. Yesterday's papers were filled with accounts of earthquake shocks. As in the famous case of 1750 the most violent shock appears to have been felt in Hereford: but the shocks were distributed over a very large area.</p>
         <p>The old Scottish missionary to whom I wrote (v. p. 103) returns to the charge in another lengthy epistle with which he encloses the cutting from the <hi rend="underline">Scotsman</hi>, on which he based his original letter, and a copy of "The Miner" containing an article by A. J. Cook. He is evidently an advanced Socialist, and represents what is becoming a numerous class in all the Christian churches. <hi rend="bold underline">Their finest flower is the reckless &amp; canting incendiary, Lansbury. They draw from their religion nothing but the consecration of their hatreds</hi>. In the xx<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century they represent the same psychological type and the same moral and religious perversion as the Munzers [= Müntzers?], Knipperdolings, &amp;c. represented in the xvi<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. <hi rend="underline">In their hands economics becomes a fanaticism: and Socialism finds in them the murderous zeal of a Clement or a Ravaillac</hi>. Probably many of them are literally "unbalanced" mentally: &amp; in quieter times would be either harmless or confined: but in these distempered epochs of Revolution the general madness releases them into prominence and activity. They march to the front, &amp; fill the world with their violence. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I am obliged to you for your further communication. The quotation from the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> in the <hi rend="underline">Scotsman</hi> is fair enough: none the less, I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> prefer that you had the whole article in front of you, &amp; I have directed my chaplain to send you the copy of the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> which contains it. </p>
         <p>I fear that our views, both economic &amp; social, w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be too discrepant to make it worth while for me to discuss the large propositions, explicit and implicit, of your letter. I live among miners, &amp; I have access to excellent information as to their condition, and I know that it is absolutely untrue to describe them as suffering much acute hardship during this "stoppage". I speak of my own district, Durham, but I am informed that the situation is not different in the other mining areas. </p>
         <p>Believe me, </p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Warwick</p>
         <p>10 West Mayfield</p>
         <p>Edinburgh</p>
         <p>N. B.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We left Bramfield Hall at 10.15 a.m. and  motored to Walsingham Abbey via Bungay and Norwich, arriving at 1.15 p.m. We wasted about 45 minutes in getting out of Norwich. <hi rend="bold underline">We lunched with Sir Eustace &amp; Lady Gurney, who showed us their very interesting house, and the ruins of the Augustinian convent</hi>. We visited the very fine parish church, &amp; admired the font, adorned with bas&#8211;reliefs of the Seven Sacraments. The church has the aspect of a Roman Catholic place of worship. There is a confessional box: the air is heavy with incense: images with tapers burning before them arrest the eye: the Stations of the Cross adorn the walls: &amp; the Sacrament is reserved. The Vicar happened to be in the church: so Lady Gurney introduced me: he dropped on his knee and kissed my hand! <hi rend="bold underline">Walsingham has again become a place of pilgrimage</hi>, and I gathered that this annual event was to take place tomorrow. Mine host tells me that the church is well&#8211;attended, &amp; that the villagers seem to like the services, which he himself detested. The Bishop of Norwich had visited the church, &amp; left the impression that he was pleased with what he saw! We returned by the way we had come, stopping in Norwich to have tea, &amp; to visit the Cathedral. I had forgotten, or had never before realized, what a very noble church it is. It was crawling with tourists. We got back to Bramfield at 7.15 p.m.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
