<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The whole series of questions relating to the extent and obligation of the obedience which citizens must render to the Law might well supply a suitable subject for the Newcastle Lecture. "The limits of civic obedience" or, "of obedience to the Law", "of legal obligation". There are 3 examples of <hi rend="underline">disobedience</hi> ready to my hand viz. the disobedience of the Prohibition Law in the U. S. A.; the disobedience of ecclesiastical Law by the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics"; and the breaking of legal contracts by the Trades Unions. These might be so far considered as to lend interest to the discussions.</p>
         <p>We left Carlton Hall at 10.45 a.m., and motored to Hereford by way of Leicester, Warwick, and Evesham, a distance of 143 miles. We burst a tyre early in the course of our journey, and were delayed by putting it right. We burst another tyre just at the end, &amp; arrived with a flat hinder tyre. Save for a little rain at the end, we had good weather and enjoyed the spectacle of the country opulent with autumnal crops, &amp; yet verdant as the early summer. We arrived at the Deanery about 7.45 p.m., having taken exactly 9 hours on the journey.</p>
         <p>The Dean &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Waterfield had gathered a dinner party of old friends which was well enough. Archdeacon &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lilley, Archdeacon and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Money&#8211;Kyrle, Prebendary &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Clark Maxwell, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Parker, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bullock Webster, Miss Smithson, &amp; the daughter of the house. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
