<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>For the first time since my operation I have had a bath!! The "catlap" method of clinical ablution is a very mockery of physical Puritanism! The Bath carries more than physical absolution.</p>
         <p>I dictated a letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi>, endeavouring to mitigate his feeling against the Vicar of Dawdon, and wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi> about his accident. Such an experience might well be the making of him. At lunch&#8211;time there was a thunder&#8211;storm, which did something to relieve the oppressiveness of the atmosphere. Captain Johnson and his wife called. He is our new adjutant of D. L. I., a pleasant young officer with a pleasant young wife.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My mind begins to concern itself with another article for the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Evening Standard</hi><hi rend="italic">. But the question of a suitable subject is not easy to answer. I think, perhaps, I might develop the argument that recent happenings, political and economic, have brought liberty into real danger: that, as </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Acton</hi><hi rend="italic"> used to maintain, the test of civilization is the amount of personal liberty which is secured to the citizen; that, so tested, modern civilization must take a very low place in spite of its mechanical resources. I might point out the circumstances which expose the wage&#8211;earner to the privation of personal liberty. Insecurity of employment the pressure of class opinion, the strength of class organization, the inconvenience of individuality, the conditions of artisan education, work, &amp; social life – all make it extraordinarily difficult for a modern wage&#8211;earner not to "toe the line" of common agreement. And there are still operative all the ancient factors of enslavement – ignorance, sacerdotalism, etc.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
