<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliantly fine day, warm, but not sultry, and free from wind which made <hi rend="bold underline">our visit to the Ullswater Sports</hi> entirely successful. The motor&#8211;drive through Kendal and over Shap Fell to Pooley Bridge on Ullswater was itself very enjoyable for it carried us through beautiful and varied scenery, rich in the verdure &amp; colour of summer though active with the business of autumn. The sports were held in a fine natural arena. The wrestling matches interested me extremely. A succession of splendid human animals displayed their strength, skill, and endurance to great advantage. Physically the English race is surely not deteriorating. Bicycle races, boys' races &amp; pole leaping, &amp; boys' fell race were all very interesting, <hi rend="bold underline">but the Hound Trail was the most curious and attractive item in the varied programme</hi>. Lord Lonsdale, a gross big man, was starter and judge. The end of the race was very exciting, for as soon as the hounds came in sight their owners started a vigorous whistling, &amp; welcomed their beasts with remarkable enthusiasm. To my surprise, for I had not realized that the races were being held in Oliver Stanley's constituency, <hi rend="bold underline">Lady Maureen &amp; her brother Lord Castlereagh were in the company, &amp; gave me an affectionate welcome</hi>. Robin looked pale &amp; had some scars on his face, but he professed to have recovered his health after his tragic accident. We drove home for tea. The whole expedition was most enjoyable. The cloudless sky and gay throngs gathered to applaud athletic youth in friendly contests, made it hard to realize that the country is in the danger &amp; confusion of a prolonged Labour conflict. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The economic situations with which we have to reckon are of three kinds.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">1. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Those in which the economic factor is unaffected by the human agent</hi><hi rend="italic">, as in the case of a total failure of the crops, or a complete destruction of markets. A new trade route, or the discovery of gold mines, or the invention of a productive instrument may create such situations. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">2. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Those in which the moral factor is supreme in the economic process</hi><hi rend="italic">, as in the willingness to work, to use a new invention, to trade with a foreign power.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">3. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Those in which the moral factor assists or hinders the economic process</hi><hi rend="italic">. The quality of work is largely determined by the temper of the worker. Authority may be exercised justly and considerately or it may be exercised harshly &amp; even intolerably. The inevitable hardships of life may be borne with patience, or resented.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">It is obvious that Christianity can have no influence whatever in the first: but slight influence in the second: &amp; a supreme influence in the third. Where the reconstruction of [an] economic system is concerned the Gospel is silent: where the moral character of the individual is concerned, it ought to be potent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Christ teaches a high indifference to circumstances, not a refusal to accept hostile circumstances. To despise circumstances is to overcome them, &amp; to ensure for the individual character a franchise and a development which they might seem to preclude. Life is gained by being voluntarily lost. We must "lose ourselves to gain ourselves. As Galahad".</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
