<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi> contains an interesting account of Chopwell from "a special correspondent". In answer to the question why that place should be so "advanced" in its politics, "an official of the local miners' lodge" replied: "If you want to fix the blame you can put your finger <hi rend="bold underline">on the Central Labour College, followed by intensive propaganda on the part of men who have been there</hi>. In season &amp; out of season we have preached Left Wing politics. We have held classes and study circles and meetings, and we have met with extraordinary success". <hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi>, the Vicar of St. Helen's, West Auckland, came to see me, and had a long talk. He is an intelligent &amp; experienced man who knows the miners well. He was very depressing, &amp; could suggest no way out of the <hi rend="underline">impasse</hi> into which we have been brought. He says that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cook</hi>'s popularity with the men is quickly growing: that they are inaccessible to argument: that they are by no means ill provided: &amp; that the strike will continue for a long time yet. He is very sure that the management of the mines is ill&#8211;organized and extravagant, &amp; expressed an unfavourable opinion of the Coal Commission's Report. He commented on the fact, which is certainly very surprising, that the miners are apparently well&#8211;provided with funds, so that they expend much in their amusements &amp; holiday&#8211;making. I asked him to say what steps he himself would suggest at this juncture in order to bring this ruinous conflict to an end; and he could suggest <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi>. That is the situation in a nutshell. From the Prime Minister downwards we are completely baffled.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The forces of organized Religion seem to be quite powerless to restrain the drift towards Communism. No doubt there is something nearly approaching a reign of terror in the industrial districts. "<hi rend="underline">You are a Churchman</hi>", said <hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi> to a Railway worker, "<hi rend="underline">how can you reconcile your conscience to breaking the contract under which you are employed, and joining in action which you know to be illegal, &amp; believe to be calamitous?"</hi>  
<hi rend="underline">"You see this house", replied the man, "it is my own, and represents the savings of years. It would be wrecked, if I were to stand out of the Strike"</hi>. The Trade Unions have degenerated in system and spirit. They are the mocking caricature of anything that could be called democratic; &amp; indeed, have been deliberately manipulated with the object of making them helpless in the hand of the ruling clique. "<hi rend="underline">Class&#8211;consciousness</hi>" has been developed so successfully that the working&#8211;masses are becoming completely inaccessible to argument by those, however distinguished &amp; trustworthy, who are not manual workers. Great numbers of the younger workmen belong to the generation, of which the boyhood was spent during the War, when discipline both at home &amp; in school, was disastrously relaxed. Many of them have been unemployed since the War, receiving the dole, &amp; losing all desire for work. These lawless youths are the Janizzaries [sic] of revolutionary Trade Unionism.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
