<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[181]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There is a nip of approaching winter in the air, and this woeful coal stoppage shows no trustworthy sign of ending. I worked at the Lock lecture until 12 noon when together with Ella and Fearne I motored to Muggleswick, where we lunched with old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ritson. He is growing disconcertingly deaf, but otherwise is in good health. We returned by way of Stanhope, in order to get a view of the moors, and got back to Auckland about 4.15 p.m. I sent the proof of my Edinburgh Review Article to old Sir Hugh Bell, inviting his opinion. [<hi rend="italic">space</hi>] Is there one of these absurd "storms in a parochial tea&#8211;pot["] brewing in the parish of S. Peter's Jarrow? I strongly suspect it. The new Vicar, Chapman, is evidently a precipitate &amp; self&#8211;willed person, eminently capable of making a mountain out of a mole&#8211;hill: and he has in one H. H. Spencer, a local solicitor, just the kind of man to improve for the worst any situation he may find to his hand.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Chichester having written to inquire whether there were any points in the Revision which I should desire to have re&#8211;considered by the Bishops, I wrote in reply to say that I desired to have the question of Anointing the Sick threshed out again. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I read Ralph's "Lay Thoughts of a Dean", which is just a collection of newspaper articles, but crammed full of wit, learning, wisdom, &amp; observation all set forth with the unvarying felicity of style which distinguishes everything he writes. Most of it is new to me for I rarely read the newspapers in which they appeared. I cannot doubt that Ralph's writings are telling on the public mind, and affecting public opinion: but whether for good or for evil I cannot make up my mind to determine. </hi>
         </p>
         
            
        
</body></text></TEI>
