<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]Proper words in proper places make the true definition of a Style . . . . .</p>
         <p>When a man's thoughts are clear, the properest words will generally offer themselves first; and his own judgment will direct him in what order to place them, so far as they may be best understood. Where men err against this method, it is usually on purpose, &amp; to show their learning, their oratory, their politeness, or their knowledge of the world. In short, that simplicity, without which no human performance can arrive to any great perfection, is nowhere more eminently useful than in this.["]</p>
         <p>Swift. A Letter to a Young Gentleman lately entered into Holy Orders. 1720.</p>
         <p>I caused myself to be robed, and attended service in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Lionel celebrated, and I pronounced the Absolution and Benediction as the Rubrick orders. We numbered 9 communicants, including Clarence Stock. After breakfast I wrote to William.</p>
         <p>The annual Confirmation in the Chapel took place at 3 p.m. The Bishop of Jarrow confirmed 83 candidates. After the service he talked with me for an hour. He did not seem disposed to approve my notion of writing on the Sunday question in the next issue of the Bishoprick. One grave difficulty about a quarterly publication is the probable absoluteness of its leader! I must write at least a month in advance of the issue; and in these precipitate days what may not have happened in a month?</p>
         <p>Clarence Stock returned to Oundle by the midnight train.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
