<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[78]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A perfect summer day – cloudless sky, no wind, brilliant sun lighting up a country opulent with harvests being gathered in, &amp; still verdant through the recent abundance of rain. What madness is it that makes men desert the country for the town. The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> has a letter from Sir J. Frazer eulogising Albert Houtin, who has just died.</p>
         <p>I spent most part of the morning in writing an Article for the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> on "The Strength of Churches". </p>
         <p>Ernest left after lunch in order to rush abroad for a brief holiday. <hi rend="italic">Miss Pearce took us to have tea with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henry Howard at Stone House, Kidderminster. There we found a stout old lady, Miss Macdonald, the Prime Minister's aunt, who spoke freely about her nephew, and was much gratified by my disapproval of the Bishops' intervention in the coal strike.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Howard is a wonderfully well&#8211;preserved octogenarian, of winning manners, who has made his house a treasury of art. He himself is an artist by many titles, particularly the painter's. He told me that he was 30 years old before he discovered that he could paint. He is particularly attracted by tapestries, &amp; has secured some noble pieces of the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries. The ceilings in the house were modelled on those of notable houses. He must be a very rich man for he has brought together a really remarkable collection of artistic treasures. But he has never seen Durham, though the fame of the tapestries in the Castle had reached him. The garden, though small, was worthy of the house. We returned to Hartlebury about 6 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>August 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1926</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Rust,</p>
         <p>Exchanging parishes is at all times a very dubious proceeding, and, therefore, the law provides that "before an exchange of benefices can be made, it is necessary to procure a licence from the Ordinary to treat of an exchange". You appear to have omitted this rather important preliminary, and to have begun &amp; concluded arrangements for an exchange without first applying for my permission. I regret, therefore, that my decision <hi rend="underline">not</hi> to sanction the exchange which you propose, must needs cause disappointment both to you and to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Reed. </p>
         <p>When I was in Hereford last week, Mr Reed wrote to me, &amp; had some conversation with me. I had the opportunity of making some inquiries about him, &amp; I decided that he would not be well&#8211;suited for appointment to Hamsteels.</p>
         <p>I do not know whether you have secured the consent of the Crown as Patron to this proposed exchange, but in view of my refusal to sanction it, you will take no further steps. </p>
         <p>Parishioners <hi rend="underline">never</hi> like exchanges, which they very naturally regard as ignoring their spiritual claim. </p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours very faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> E. Rust.</p>
         <p>Vicar of Hamsteels.</p>
         <p>I sent in to my Bankers &#x00A3;31.11.3. i.e. &#x00A3;20 the Evening Standard, &#x00A3;1.11.3. [sic] from Hodder &amp; Stoughton</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
