<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received a type&#8211;written letter from a correspondent living at South Hetton, who describes himself as "a young practical pitman, a member and local preacher of the Primitive Methodist Church", who has been sent a cutting from the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> with my letter, and proposes "to give me the answer he thinks fitting". It is an interesting composition, and illustrates the mental processes of the religiously minded artisans. I think I shall send him a "soft answer", but the fact that his letter is typed suggests that he is circulating it. </p>
         <p>We left Bramfield Hall shortly after 10.30 a.m., and motored to Riccall, where we arrived about 8.20 pm, having motored 214 miles by way of Diss, Thetford, King's Lynn, Spalding, Grantham, Retford, Doncaster, and Selby. We lost time &amp; added to the mileage in getting out of Suffolk. We lunched at the Globe Hotel in King's Lynn, and had tea in the George at Grantham.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Times</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">reports a prompt break&#8211;down of the negotiations between the miners and the mine&#8211;owners. Indeed, it is difficult to resist the impression that there was no sincerity in the action of the miners' leaders, only a tactical move to put themselves right with the public</hi>. The Prime Minister has gone off to drink water on the Continent, and the deadlock in the mines is again complete. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
