<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Conservative f&#x00EA;te in the Park was favoured with brilliant weather, &amp; seemed to attract a considerable number of young men and maidens. Sir Alfred Mond was the principal speaker announced on the bills. I wrote some observations on the "stoppage" for the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>, but as there will probably be an end of the business before the paper appears, my labours will probably have been fruitless.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Robert William Bruce Richards</hi>, an aspirant for Ordination, came to see me, and stayed to lunch. I accepted him as candidate for next Advent, &amp; promised to provide him with a title. I received from Adamson of Grangetown, a request that I would accept from him a title for <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Neill</hi>, who is also a candidate for Ordination at Advent. But I doubt whether he is not too much of an Anglo&#8211;Catholick for the purpose, especially as Neill himself, who has come under Wright's influence, is that way inclined. However, I will see him, and talk it over.</p>
         <p>The Conservative demonstration in the Park was mainly attended by shop&#8211;assistants enjoying their weekly holiday, many of the ladies being clearly non&#8211;voters.</p>
         <p>Trotman informed me that he had received an official communication about the Indian chaplaincy for which some while ago he had made an application. He is to be interviewed, and will, no doubt, be in due course appointed. This means his leaving me, probably this autumn. So, just as I was hoping to make a start with my two chaplains, I am set to the unpleasant task of finding one of them!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
