<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A slender post included a letter from Kitson Clark, the manufacturer of locomotives in Leeds, with whom I stayed when visiting that city to preach and lecture. He represents the most benevolent and socialistically&#8211;minded type of employer. He writes thus: –</p>
         <p>My dear Bishop</p>
         <p>In industrial matters it may indeed be well to fear the employers and the praise they bring. But I hope and think that you will accept the thanks of one here, who has been deeply and sympathetically interested in these subjects for 33 years. I am not going to add to the arguments. I have felt bitterly sorry with very many churchmen for the addition to the time of trouble which has come from the quarter to which you refer, and even more for the evidence of absence of real sober thinking. <hi rend="bold underline">I believe that Mr Baldwin will read your letter, and it will let him know that there are those who really care for both material and other than material things who desire to stand by him</hi>.</p>
         <p>I am, with kind wishes from my wife,</p>
         <p>Yours very faithfully</p>
         <p>E. Kitson Clark</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I conjecture that this letter expresses the mind of the majority of thoughtful lay Anglicans outside the Socialistic section, which is, save for the academicks and sentimentalists, mainly composed of half educated women and lower middle class folk, the section from which the Anglo&#8211;Catholic congregations are drawn, and which regards the publications of "Copec" as a new version of the original Gospel. The "Church Times" and the "Guardian" are their organs in the press</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Begg</p>
         <p>Your letter has been sent on to me from Auckland Castle, and I have read it with much attention. It hardly needs saying that, when I address my diocese on any subject, I neither claim nor expect universal agreement in the opinions which I may express. But I both claim and expect a careful and respectful consideration, and so much, I do not doubt, the views of the Bishop will never fail to secure from his clergy. </p>
         <p>If I may adventure one criticism on your memorandum, it would be this – that you do not sufficiently keep in view the actual situation, when you seek to explain, or extenuate, the course adopted by the miners' leaders. It is <hi rend="underline">nihil ad rem</hi> to point out former blunders, and other people's faults, when the grimly practical issue is <hi rend="underline">how to maintain on a remunerative basis the great industry by which miners live</hi>. Even if the Socialistic or Communistic reconstruction of society (in which, if I mistake not, you believe) be <hi rend="underline">ultimately</hi> practicable – a point on which human experience throws no favourable light, and which the latest reports from Russia seem to condemn – it hardly appears disputable that much time would pass before the new regime could be established, and <hi rend="underline">in the meanwhile</hi> the nation – 43,000,000 souls in Great Britain – must live. The problem of industry is ultimately the problem of feeding the people.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Also, I think that we, who are charged with special and solemn responsibilities must be always asking ourselves with respect to the opinions we utter, and the tendencies we assist, Quo tendimus? Frankly, I must confess that, when I consider the probable effect of the indiscriminating approbation which is given to ALL the proceedings of organized "Labour" by those who claim to be the friends (in some special sense) of "the underdog", I cannot think that the result is likely to be morally sound or economically possible. The temper of universal suspicion, and the poison of class&#8211;consciousness are widely&#8211;spread, and they are the conditions of violent Revolution. </p>
         <p>I shall always be glad to receive from my colleagues information as to the facts of popular life as they see it in their parishes at close range.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> A. Begg,</p>
         <p>Usworth Rectory,</p>
         <p>[Near?] Washington</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[126]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The situation seems to be improving. At least the miners have taken what seems to be the right step. They have opened negotiations with the mineowners. The Government awaits the opportunity of intervening</hi>. If we may fairly infer from recent events that the miners' leaders perceive that their game is up, it is difficult to avoid the conclusion that they mean to effect a settlement. But on what terms? <hi rend="underline">Frank Hodges</hi> is reported to have spoken very frankly on the loss which this foolish "stoppage" has inflicted on the miners. <hi rend="bold underline">It is in my judgment most desirable that the miners should be compelled to realize that they have been miserably led. If they would transfer their allegiance from Cook to Frank Hodges, they might even, in the long run, be gainers by a ruinous struggle</hi>. </p>
         <p>After lunch, Ella and I motored to Dunwich, and then went on to Aldburgh, where we had tea on the golf course with the Carmichaels. Denis Webster &amp; his wife were there, as well as Colonel Bill Smith with his wife and niece.</p>
         <p>A vigourous lad, M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gregor, arrived on a visit. He is an Etonian, and no more than 15 years old, but almost manlike in his proportions. He had motored from a Rectory near Bedford. His prattle amused me not a little. I enquired whether he was going to Oxford or Cambridge after leaving Eton, and he replied that he was going out to the Malay States to grow rubber – become an Empire builder – or wrecker!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
