<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Two subjects suggested themselves to my mind as suitable for treatment in the <hi rend="underline">Evening Gazette</hi> – <hi rend="underline">Royalties</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Walsingham Abbey</hi>. The first, perhaps, would be the more relevant to the actual situation: the last would be the more prudent. A third subject came to my hand as I searched for the account of Erasmus's visit to "Our Lady of Walsingham" viz. <hi rend="underline">A Puritan Humourist</hi>. Samuel Torshell, whose treatise "<hi rend="underline">The Hypocrite Discovered &amp; Cured</hi>" 1644 is full of good things.</p>
         <p>After lunch I walked round the Park with Herbert Smith and incidentally talked to several young miners. They are sick to death of idleness.</p>
         <p>["]William of Newburgh tells us that not a fourth part of the crusaders returned home – the rest died of want, exposure, or battle – &amp; in this he sees a striking exhibition of the mercy of God, for those who came back relapsed into their evil ways, while those who died went to heaven, so that the crusades were a success in peopling the heavenly Jerusalem if they failed to secure the earthly one …..["]</p>
         <p>["]In the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Father Gobat says that those who perform many pilgrimages are rarely sanctified, for to most people they are merely a matter of carnal gratification, &amp;, if we may judge from Binterim's defence of pilgrimages, objections to their demoralizing influence are urged against them at the present day ["] </p>
         <p>(v. H. C. Lea, Auricular Confession &amp;c., vol. ii. p. 129)</p>
         <p>Pilgrimages, like Methodist "camp&#8211;meetings", create an atmosphere of semi&#8211;hysterical excitement &amp; bring crowds together with results on [sic] sexual morality which are as shocking as they are, in the circumstances, inevitable.</p>
         
            
        
</body></text></TEI>
