<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Storr with his wife and daughter went off about noon, and Ella &amp; I then motored to Lumley Castle, where we lunched with Lord &amp; Lady Scarbrough. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Sir Ronald Storrs</hi><hi rend="italic"> was there, and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Marsh, Winston Churchill's secretary. I was interested in Storrs's conversation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He spoke amusingly of the Anglo&#8211;Catholick pilgrims, who are disposed to regard with almost abject reverence Oriental ecclesiastics, whose reputation was as black as their robes</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">He said that the birth&#8211;rate among the Arabs had been conditioned by a heavy rate of infant&#8211;mortality, but that we were so quickly improving their hygiene conditions that the babies were tending to survive, so that there was reason to think that the Jewish immigration w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be more than counter&#8211;balanced by the natural increase of the Arab population. He said that the extreme unpopularity of the French in Syria made our rule in Palestine popular, &amp; that the abandonment of their Protectorate by the French w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be a grave misfortune to us as it w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> mean the return of the Turks, with whom we had no military strength to contend. He gave me a cordial invitation to visit him in Cyprus, whither he is about to proceed as governor</hi>.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Spooner arrived for a short visit. He is four score: &amp; she is purblind, but both appear to be cheerful.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The news from the coal&#8211;fields today is discouraging. Cook has succeeded in stemming the tide of reaction, which threatened to restore activity to the Midland collieries. "Peaceful picketing" of a very violent kind went along with his eloquence with the result that most of the men who had "signed on" refrained from actually starting work. Meanwhile the winter is approaching: &amp; when it arrives, the situation will become almost unendurable</hi>.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
