<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is precisely nine weeks since the operation. I started to walk up and down stairs in normal fashion. I read Bright's Early English Church History with a view to the Hereford sermon, but gained woefully little. The papers announce the death of that very brave, briilliant, and patriotic lady, Miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gertrude Bell</hi>. She died at Baghdad in sleep [sic], worne out beyond all question by her indefatigable labours. Her life shames my conventionality, sloth, and cowardice.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi> lunched here. He brought me the <hi rend="underline">Funeral Sermon for Bishop Morton preached by John Barwick on Michaelmas&#8211;day 1659 in the parish church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Peter at Easton Mauduit in Northampton&#8211;shire</hi>. It has a clean&#8211;cut portrait of the valorous old bishop. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi> came to report that he had passed his matriculation. He now aspires to honours! Ambition is a week that grows quickly in young minds! He would be better&#8211;placed, perhaps, under a more energetic and masterful vicar than the amiable but somewhat lethargic Marsh.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Korsteiner</hi>, and I motored to Sedgefield, &amp; had tea at the great Rectory. What is to be the future of such a house? The present endowment (&#x00A3;1600) is all required to live in it suitably: but our reformers will not contemplate a parochial income that exceeds &#x00A3;700. Who would buy the Rectory? It is too large for the only kind of purchaser that is likely to present himself. Durham is not a district in which schools or institutions naturally establish themselves, for its amenities are few, and its climate is severe. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sykes</hi> told me that he had had some correspondence with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Iremonger</hi> about the Archbishop of Canterbury's unfortunate action during the Strike, and had sent him a cutting of my letter to the Newcastle Journal: but Iremonger would not publish anything in the Guardian. It is not the least grave indication of the sorry pass into which ecclesiastical affairs have come that a man of the type and temperament of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Iremonger</hi> should wield so relatively considerable influence at the centre.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
