<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The General Strike has led to a series of law&#8211;suits, which throw a curious light on the working of our society and the confusion of men's minds. Two such law&#8211;suits were decided yesterday. In the one, a firm of manufacturers in Walthamstow sued the Urban District Council for damages on account of losses inflicted by the cutting off of electrical power in deference to the demand of strikers. In the other, a Tramway manager brought an action for libel against the Sheffield Federated Trades and Labour Council. In both cases the plaintiff secured a verdict. The latter is particularly important for it raises the question of the manner in which ballots of workmen are now conducted. It was alleged that the Sheffield Tramways Committee had falsely pretended that the ballot of their workmen was secret. This zeal for genuine secrecy displayed by a Labour Organisation will not be forgotten when Parliament deals with Trade Union Ballots. The "Yorkshire Post" has an excellent leader on the subject.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">A deputation from the Council of Durham Colleges, consisting of Pemberton, Ritson, and Burchnall came to see me about the Castle.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The failure of Lord Durham's Appeal leaves the penniless University face to face with a financial demand which it cannot satisfy. What can be done? They had a suggestion about getting the Castle handed over to Trustees who would relieve the University of responsibility for its maintenance. I rejected this as impracticable. Finally, we agreed that non&#8211;committal approaches should be made to the Board of Works in order to discover whether, and if so, on what terms, it would take over the Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A number of lawn&#8211;tennis players &amp; their seniors came during the afternoon. The Bishop of Jarrow came &amp; discussed diocesan business. He tells me that Kirkup, the manager of the Houghton mine, says that the Joicey mines are losing &#x00A3;500,000 per annum while the pits remain idle. </p>
</body></text></TEI>
