<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wasted the morning in sending a letter to "the Times", on the lines of yesterday's reflections. Whether the Editor will publish it remains to be seen. Meanwhile the deadlock remains as hopeless a ever. <hi rend="bold underline">The miners have rejected "the Bishops' terms" by a small majority: &amp; nobody seems to know what to attempt next. Cook raves against the Prime Minister.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was a considerble thunderstorm in the course of the afternoon with deluges of rain mingled with hail.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Boyce, the Vicar of Bramfield, has resigned, and is living in a small house not far distant, which he and his wife have purchased. The parish has been united with another, to the great chagrin of the parishioners, who have petitioned against the arrangement but without effect. So there is no  longer an incumbent residing in Bramfield. The new Vicar is not disliked, but his wife is abhorred. All the choir have resigned, &amp; the parish is generally sulking. Yet there is little to be said against the union of two neighbouring parishes, of which the one has 100 and the other 550 inhabitants. None the less, the people are alienated, and the influence of Christianity greatly weakened. This situation is being created all over the country, &amp; must imply a great reduction of the Church's power &amp; prestige.</p>
         <p>I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rainbow sending her a cheque for Gerald's school fees: and to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kearney suggesting dates for the dedication of his organ.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
