<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After breakfast M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bovey and her daughter went away. I worked at the Edinburgh Article, and finally sent it to Harold Cox, with an explanatory letter, in which I owned my own discontent with the poor thing, but said that I thought that its publication would make people think. Also, I revised and despatched to the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> the article that I wrote yesterday. That is enough journalism for some while to come.</p>
         <p>We motored to Whorlton Hall, and lunched with the Bishop and Miss Headlam. A clergyman named Wigram, who said that his father was the old Canon Wigram Vicar of Hertford when I was myself Vicar of Barking, was staying there. He has lived much in the East in various capacities, &amp; knows much of Eastern questions. He said that the competence of the Turks to administer a state under modern conditions without Christian assistance was yet to be proved. They were themselves resolved to make the attempt, and confident of their sufficiency for the task. But this confidence was limited to themselves.</p>
         <p>George Dennistoun and his wife arrived on a short visit. He has left the navy, as his eyesight began to give trouble, and he now farms in New Zealand. Lady Limerick arrived while we were at dinner: she is as Irish, alike in charm and incoherence as ever. These visitors are, of course, very welcome, but there is no blinking the fact that they do not make the performance of duty easy! Ella does her best to "take them off my hands", but even so, I cannot altogether ignore them. The longer I live, the more I think that the method of the monastery is admirable.</p>
        
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
