<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On the whole, I think "The Fallacy of Class&#8211;consciousness" will be a better subject for an article than "Personal Liberty". My point will be that "class" is neither a permanent nor an exhaustive description of any man. He may pass from one class to another, or he may belong to several classes at the same time. Moreover, in this modern world, in which labour is increasingly divorced from individual choice, and made mechanical &amp; monotonous, the salvation of the individual is being sought in the direction of larger leisure, and a better equipment for the intelligent use thereof. It follows, therefore, that to determine a man's class by his economic position, is to make his social description turn on that factor in his life, over which he has least control, and which least reflects his individuality. Could anything be more unreasonable, more misleading, and more dishonouring to the man himself? <hi rend="bold underline">In what class should the educated working&#8211;man be placed? Where does the religious artisan come in? Which links are the stronger – those which tie him to his daily occupation, or those which unite him with his fellow&#8211;students, or with his fellow believers? Multitudes of working folk are Liberals and Conservatives: by what necessity of reason or justice are they required to belong to the Labour party?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[11]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Vicar called to see me, and talked for some while. He says that the miners, whom he encounters in his parish, are quite willing to accept an eight&#8211;hour day, but <hi rend="underline">dare</hi> not say so publicly. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spedding</hi>, the dentist, bears the same witness: and so does Leng, who is something of a gossip with the man in the street. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi> said as much for his parish. <hi rend="bold underline">The working&#8211;class Englishman is at present a bond&#8211;slave to his Trade&#8211;Union, that is, to the violent fraction which control it</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> told me that, as a result of the idleness of the pits and the consequent arrest of river&#8211;pollution, he had seen trout in the Gaunless. He says that two of the local mines have definitely closed down, and that two more are likely to do so. The tradesmen of Bishop Auckland are in much despondency. They find it difficult to pay the ever&#8211;waxing rates, and they see with fatal clearness the approaching collapse of the mining industry on which the prosperity of the town wholly depends. The finances of the Church of England cannot but be affected most injuriously by that untoward event, for no less than &#x00A3;400,000 per annum in Royalties alone goes, mainly from this county, into the account of the Ecclesiastical Commissioners.</p>
         <p>The Vicar sent me a brace of trout.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
