<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The dedication of the School Chapel</hi> was a simple but dignified function. Under a bright sun the whole scene was one of remarkable beauty. From the plateau on which the chapel stands a most noble prospect of the Cathedral is gained. The building was far too small to contain the congregation which desired to enter it. I think my little oration was congruous and adequate. After the dedication I went to my rooms in the Castle, and there received a deputation from the Council of the Durham Colleges, with respect to the appeal to the Board of Works on the matter of the maintenance of the Castle. When they had gone their way, the Bishop of Jarrow came, and talked diocesan business with me for an hour. Then I dressed for dinner, and walked to the School, where the annual dinner of <hi rend="underline">Old Du[n]elmians</hi> was to take place. We started at 8 p.m., and went on until about 11 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">General Poole</hi> was in the Chair, and I sate between him and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Judge Greenwell</hi>, both of whom are interesting. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Budworth</hi> proposed by <hi rend="bold">[sic]</hi> health in a lengthy &amp; portentously flatterous oration, into which he evidently put his heart, but which was none the less extravagant. However, I made a civil reply: and then <hi rend="doubleunderline">MacKenzie</hi>, once Headmaster of Durham, and then Headmaster of Uppingham, proposed the Chairman's health. He raved and roared for no less than 20 minutes, after which we got away: &amp; I was back in the Castle about 20 minutes before midnight.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Budworth</hi> affirmed with every appearance of sincerity that I was the principal cause of the prosperity of Durham School having secured the building of Langley House, and the adoption of the plan for a War Memorial which was carried out in the School Chapel. This seems to me nonsense!</p>
</body></text></TEI>
