<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote a short letter to the <hi rend="underline">Spectator</hi> pointing out the inapplicability to the present situation of the parallel suggested between the "Truce of God" and the action of the Ten Bishops.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received a letter from M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Thomas A. Stallard, a cotton spinner in Lancashire, asking leave to reprint &amp; circulate among his work&#8211;people the Article "The Deadlock in the Mines" which I wrote for the Bishoprick. I gave him the permission he asked for</hi>.</p>
         <p>Parry Evans came to see me. He says that Hudson Barker was asked as long ago as May to lend his school&#8211;room for feeding the miners' children during the Strike, and when he inquired for how long the room w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be required, he was told that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be wanted up to Sept<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, as they would "go in" on October 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>. The same experience was his during the Strike of 1921, when the miners took the room for 13 weeks, announcing quite accurately when the Strike would end. What does this mean?</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park in the afternoon, &amp; talked with some young miners, who protest that they long to get back to work.</p>
         <p>The British Legion asks me to arrange a service in the Castle Chapel for the dedication of a Branch Standard on some Sunday afternoon. I am not quite easy in mind about the British Legion, though it has the Prince of Wales for its patron &amp; is incorporated by Royal Charter, but I don't care to alienate any body of men just now. I wrote to the Secretary M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pigg J<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> to come &amp; see me. If the Legion is a sufficiently stable thing, I shall probably grant them the service. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[164]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>["]When faith is lost in the natural force and the self&#8211;supporting and recuperative powers of the people living according to the laws of social life, there seems no alternative but relief and ever more relief. That the voluntary aid is called "alms" and the public relief poor or poor law relief makes no difference.["]</p>
         <p>(v. C. S. Loch. "Charity &amp; Social Life" p. 219)</p>
         <p>(Macmillan &amp; Co. 1910)</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Albert Mitchell</hi> returns to the charge on the matter of raising the question of Lord's Day Observance in the forthcoming session of the C. A. He thinks that I ought to move the resolution myself in order that the secular press might notice it, and offers himself to second it. He thinks he will be able to secure considerable support for it. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dibdin</hi> asking for precise information as to the decision of the Ecclesiastical Commission. I suppose I must do this, though I always feel restive when associated with Evangelicals. They may accept my leading, but they know that I am a man of another spirit than theirs, &amp; they feel as uncomfortable in the partnership as I do! At bottom, of course, they are all "Fundamentalists", and would turn me out of the Church if they knew what I really think.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The mine&#8211;owners have returned a decided negative to M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Churchill's proposals. They will not accept a national settlement on any terms. So the end of the conflict is again postponed</hi>.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
