<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I walked round to the Vicarage, and offered to preach in South Church next Sunday morning, an offer which was promptly accepted.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Lady Eden brought her son Captain Anthony Eden &amp; his wife to lunch. We had political conversation</hi>.</p>
         <p>A numerous company came to play lawn tennis. I counted more than 30 at one time on the Bowling Green. Cruickshank came with his wife. I took him to my room, and had talk with him. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nairne Clark, the Vicar of Hunstanworth, came to dine &amp; sleep. After dinner Lady Limerick played charmingly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Trade Union Congress had a very uproarious meeting yesterday, the miners making noisy protests against Browley, the Railwayman, who had aroused their resentment by outspoken criticism of their leaders. Tomsky sent a lengthy &amp; insolent message to the Congress. This was the subject of much indignant protest</hi>.</p>
         <p>Ah, God, for a man with heart, head, hand</p>
         <p>Like one of the simple great ones, gone,</p>
         <p>For ever and ever by.</p>
         <p>One still, strong man in a blatant land,</p>
         <p>Whatever they call him, what care I?</p>
         <p>Aristocrat, democrat, autocrat – one</p>
         <p>Who can rule, and dare not lie.</p>
         <p>Tennyson.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
