<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>With much reluctance I kept my bed instead of going to the Holy Communion for yet another Sunday. But prudence prohibits any running of risks, though, Heaven knows, I am weary of these secularised festivals! The weather was bright &amp; hot, though uncomfortable by reason of a warm wind, which came from all quarters at once, mainly from the west.</p>
         <p>After breakfast I wrote in bed a letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, headed '<hi rend="underline">Perverted Trade&#8211;Unionism – a Plea for Legal Reform</hi>'. If the Editor publishes it, my popularity in the diocese will not be increased! This is said to be "Civic Sunday", and accordingly there has been much noise of band&#8211;playing in the streets. Democracy &amp; Band&#8211;playing appear to be inseparable. I loathe both!</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I sate in the Garden, &amp; read Trevelyan's <hi rend="underline">History</hi>. On returning to my study, I wrote to my brother, Gilbert.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">One result of the many&#8211;sided activity of the modern church, (which multiplies its organisations as it loses hold of the people,) is the existence of many companies, more or less disciplined, of children &amp; adolescents, who "parade" at the Church on every occasion of importance, with the result that the preacher, who is generally selected &amp; as considerable a personage as possible, has for his congregation a gathering largely composed of fidgetting youngsters, excited by their exertions &amp; bored stark by their compulsory inactivity. In such circumstances, serious preaching is out of the question, &amp;, indeed, is now rarely attempted. All things tend to the degradation of the modern pulpit.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
