<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A brilliant morning, promising a return of the "heat&#8211;wave". I wrote a few pages of the Hereford sermon, but I have no sufficiently clear notion of what I want, or at least, of what I ought, to say, to be able to say it. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Barwick</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">Funeral Sermon for Bishop Morton</hi> fills 53 closely printed pages, &amp; could hardly have contained less than 17,000 words. This would amount to as much as seven of my sermons, &amp; would at my pace of delivery have occupied about 3 hours to deliver.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Miller</hi><hi rend="italic">, the energetic editor of the local paper, called to ask me some expression of my opinion on the situation in the coal industry. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Instigante diabolo</hi><hi rend="italic"> I dictated some observations which were lacking neither in frankness nor in lucidity, however much they may have lacked discretion! Also, I wrote about 50 words in reply to a prepaid telegram from the Sunday Express asking my views. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>A numerous party of young men and maidens came to play lawn&#8211;tennis. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lillingston</hi> brought his new wife to be introduced. The lady must have attractions of character for she has none of person. However, she is said to understand motors. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Toland related at dinner some truly amazing stories of the corruption prevalent among the police in America, and, as she spoke of personal experiences, her stories might command more credit than most Transatlantick statements. She says that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">it has become a point of honour with all respectable citizens to demonstrate the failure of the Prohibition law by breaking it</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read an excellent summary of the Reformation by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hamilton Thompson</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the volume of Anglo&#8211;Catholic Essays, but it seems to me that (as is so often the case with men of his party) he is unable to perceive the religious significance of the facts which he quite fairly narrates, nor does he realize the implications of the concessions which, as an honest historian, he is compelled to make. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The retention of episcopacy is, of course, made the crucial matter in the record, and nothing seems to be allowed to the breach with the whole traditional conception of Christianity, both doctrinal &amp; ecclesiastical</hi>. </p>
</body></text></TEI>
