<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> went off to London by the early train in order to attend the Royal Garden Party, and visit the shops. I spent most of the morning &amp; some of the afternoon in finishing the Hereford Sermon.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hunter Blair</hi> and his daughter lunched here. They came in order that he might photograph such post&#8211;Reformation episcopal seals as are preserved in Auckland Castle. He is a recognized antiquarian, and has a considerable acquaintance with the Middle Ages. He expressed admiration for Coulton's books.</p>
         <p>Archdeacon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derry</hi> and Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson Walker</hi> came to tea, and stayed talking for some while. I lent the former 3 books viz. Houtin's <hi rend="underline">Une grande mystique</hi>, Allard's <hi rend="underline">La R&amp;#x00E9;volution et Religion</hi>, and the <hi rend="underline">Report of the Farnham Conference on Reservation</hi>. </p>
         <p>I sent a cheque for &#x00A3;15 to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gobat</hi>, the "Red" Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's Darlington, who has been ill, and is impecunious. This money comes from the Offertories in the Chapel, i.e. mostly from me.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Prime Minister's interview with the Bishops with respect to the settlement of the Mining Conflict seems to have left the situation unchanged. There were no less than 10 bishops there, including two suffragans</hi><hi rend="italic"> (Kensington &amp; Woolwich). The diocesans were the following – Lichfield, Winchester, Hereford, Birmingham, Manchester, Liverpool, Southwark, and Ripon. These are all "Socialists" except Hereford &amp; Ripon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The City Churches Measure was passed by 71 to 54 in the House of Lords.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
