<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[36]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the article for the Bishoprick, and sent it to the Bishop of Jarrow. It did not work out as well as I had hoped, but my capacity for work is yet small. The afternoon was fine, and a tennis&#8211;party came &amp; was busy. I sate and talked with them. The two pious ladies – the Misses <hi rend="doubleunderline">Foster</hi>, who "maternally devour the pastor", Canon Cosgrave, have now moved from his parish into Hurworth, of which the patronage has just been purchased by the Church Association. They were very indignant over this, being good "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks", but whether they would have felt so keenly for the rights of the parishioners if the new patron had been the E. C. U., I have my doubts. They are bent on having a chapel in their new house, and would know if I would licence it for celebrations of Holy Communion: but <hi rend="bold underline">I replied that only Peers had the right to possess the luxury of private chaplains, &amp; that I would nowise sanction any invasion of the incumbent's rights</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The aspect of public affairs grows ever darker. Last night the disorder which is now habitual in the House of Commons was carried to the House of Lords, where that shameless mountebank, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Parmoor</hi><hi rend="italic">, affected a vast indignation at the passing of the Eight Hours Bill, and the silly little peer, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">De la Warre</hi><hi rend="italic">, talked nonsense for nearly an hour. This childish display of obstruction was assisted by insolent interruption from the Labour Members who had gathered at the bar of the House. This indecent scene was brought to an end by the closure – an unprecedented procedure!</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
