<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]		</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Viscount Churchill</hi><hi rend="underline"> the chairman of the Great Western Railway wrote to me with reference to my letter in the Times</hi>, enclosing some documents which disclosed the working out of the General Strike on that important line. One thing was particularly interesting viz. the case of a man who said that he had been advised by the "<hi rend="underline">Deputy Bishop of Birmingham" (i.e. Bishop Hamilton Baynes) "that in such a matter (&amp;c. obeying the Trade Union's summons to strike) he could not act as an individual</hi>". The Bishop, to whom this statement was submitted, said that he had only expressed his sympathy with the man at his being confronted with a conflict of duties viz. that due to his class, and that due to his employer. <hi rend="underline">But he had evidently left another impression on the man's mind. And indeed, his own version of the counsel he gave is doubtful enough</hi>. Could it, indeed, be legitimate for a moral teacher to belittle the requirement of the Moral Law, for surely the keeping of contracts must come under that description, into a mere alternative to the order of the Trade Union? What martyrdom would then be requisite if that casuistry were admissable? What moral authority attaches to the claims of "Class"? It is evident enough that in Labour circles "Class" has re&#8211;placed the Moral Law. To be "Class&#8211;conscious" is the Alpha &amp; Omega of the new morality. That there are <hi rend="underline">some</hi> obligations attaching to Class may be admitted, but surely these are as by&#8211;laws in the kingdom of morals, and cannot be pleaded against its capital statutes. <hi rend="underline">Breaking contracts</hi> is prohibited by these capital statutes. The class&#8211;obligation only operates subject to this law.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I think my leader in the next <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> might take the form of a letter of advice to a young clergyman dealing with the question of the parson's attitude to current politics, which in the actual circumstances means his behaviour during Strikes. Under the form of such a letter I might say a great many things that need saying, and that are hard to say.</p>
         <p>Lady Londonderry writes to say that she had read my letter to Robin, who is not yet allowed to have any correspondence. I am not altogether sorry that she should see the tone and direction of my dealings with her son, but I cannot doubt that any beneficial effect that my counsels might conceivably have had on him is almost certainly destroyed by his knowledge that his parents have knowledge of them!</p>
         <p>Baily from S. Ignatius, Sunderland, came here bringing some relations from Assam to see the Castle. While they were being shown round by Alexander, he sate in my study and talked with me. He said that he found the people eager to welcome his visits, &amp; that particularly they valued his Blessing. He is a devout, and rather old&#8211;fashioned type of parson. I should doubt if there [are] many parish clergymen who accompany their visits with benedictions. I am, however, convinced that the least respected and the least respect&#8211;worthy clergymen in my diocese are those who thrust themselves into politics, generally as protagonists of "Labour". I gave the party tea. The Assam tea&#8211;planter said that he had been in Calcutta during the recent riots, and that they were far graver than had been reported in England.</p>
         <p>Lloyd George "let himself go" in a Baptist Chapel yesterday. He described Christ as likely to have approved his own attitude during the General Strike! &amp;, indeed, canted abominably, &amp; in the worst possible taste.  </p>
</body></text></TEI>
