<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[154]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent most part of the day on the Edinburgh Article, and finished it: but it does not content me. Indeed I had thought I could have done better, but it is far easier to perceive and parade the defects in the reasonings of others than to construct an argument of one's own! Yet, if I had time &amp; space enough I think I could set out a thesis which would hold water. As it is, I can but put out a fragment which only half&#8211;discloses my meaning.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon I walked in the Park, &amp; talked with two sets of miners. All expressed their earnest desire to get back to work</hi>. The suspicion crossed my mind that they might be speaking as they thought I would like them to speak, but, save in the case of one man who, I thought "protested too much", &amp; <hi rend="underline">might</hi> have been connected with some anti&#8211;Communist association subsidised by the owners, I could not doubt that they were speaking sincerely.</p>
         <p>An anonymous letter, indited from the Oxford Union, &amp; written in an educated hand, called my attention to the number of idle parsons who might be seen in Oxford.</p>
         <p>"Wherever you go they are in evidence, at the Hotels, at the Restaurants &amp; Caf&amp;#x00E9;s, in the Gardens &amp; Parks, &amp; in these Rooms. There is no evidence of poverty for they are fat &amp; cheery &amp; in some cases accompanied by their wives (?) in the latest state of semi&#8211;nudity."</p>
         <p>I judge my correspondent to be an evil&#8211;surmising Papist.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
