<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi> came to see me this afternoon. He seems to be entering on his clergyman's work with keenness. But unquestionably, there is a lack of regular discipline in the life of the English curate. Unless he has himself a strong will and a clear conception of duty, he is but too likely to degenerate into a slack and disordered habit. The loss of the church schools is a serious misfortune for the clergy whatever it may be for the school children. In order to be in his place for the religious lesson the clergyman had to be at the school by 9 a.m., and his normal day's work was thus timed to begin. However, this tiny fragment of an ordered scheme has generally disappeared. </p>
         <p>I read through the greater part of an excellent little book by A. Aulard: – "Le Christianisme et la r&amp;#x00E9;volution francaise". The author dwells much on the surprising fact <hi rend="bold underline">that the French peasants displayed no general resentment at the sudden and violent dechristianizing of the country</hi>. In some districts where the clergy had been individually popular there were signs of hostility, but not generally. In the towns the horrible parodies of Christian faith &amp; worship were eagerly welcomed, and the upper classes were for the most part Voltairians. In fact, the Church of France, without realizing the fact, had become an empty shell. When the blow fell there was no resisting power within it. The fall of the Russian Church has repeated the strange &amp; terrifying spectacle. Appearances in both cases were utterly misleading. On the eve of irreparable disaster both Churches seemed secure alike in the political system &amp; in the public esteem. Will the Church of England provide yet another example?</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
