<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We left Sawley Hall about 10.30 a.m., &amp; motored to Carlton Hall, near Newark, a distance of 82 miles. We arrived at 3.15 p.m., having delayed for an hour in Doncaster for lunch at the Danum Hotel. The sun shone, the air was fresh &amp; pleasant, the country beautiful in summer luxuriance. I expended on the way: 11/3 for lunch (4 persons), and 10/7 for petrol, a total of 21/10. We found M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lawrie here with her three children. Haliburton, now a Corporal, has been improved by Sandhurst: Sidney, now a tall lad of 16, makes progress with his music; and Blanche marches towards womanhood dowered with grace and promise. Lady Ross is here. Her husband, Sir John Ross, died a few weeks ago. Our hostess, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Skeffington–Craig, is unaltered &amp;, perhaps, unalterable. </p>
         <p>I wrote to Clayton suggesting that he should act as my Chaplain at Hereford on Friday.</p>
         <p>I found in our bedroom a novel by Stephen McKenna, "Tomorrow and Tomorrow", and I started to read it. The emotions &amp; excitements of the hectic period that followed immediately the ending of the War are already almost unintelligible and unmeaning to those, who, like ourselves, have become <hi rend="underline">blasé</hi> with altruistic fervours, and wholly sceptical of all putters–to–rights–of–the–world, within the space of eight years! Lloyd George, reverting to the guttersnipe of genius after having companied with Chatham, is a representative figure. We are all like that.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
