<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[165]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There had been a time of plenty and extravagance, of which in high quarters the famous "field of the cloth of gold" was typical; and probably, <hi rend="underline">in accordance with the frequently observed law of social economics</hi>, as the advance in wages and their purchasing power in the earlier part of the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century had not been accompanied by a simultaneous advance in self&#8211;discipline and intelligent expenditure, <hi rend="underline">it resulted in part in lessened competence and industrial ability on the part of the work&#8211;men, and thus in the end produced pauperism</hi>.</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">C. S. Loch</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">Charity &amp; Social Life</hi>" p. 295</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">For whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have abundance: but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that which he hath</hi>." (S. Matthew xiii. 12) "The frequently observed law of social economics" is thus shortly stated by the Founder of Christianity. Certainly what was observable in the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>–16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century has been quite as apparent in the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> –20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Abounding prosperity, unconditioned by moral improvement has worked out to a definite diminution of economic capacity. Is the working of this "law" the secret of the decay which, sooner or later, overtakes every civilised society? Did not Agur the son of Jakeh suggest the condition of soundness for nations as well as for individuals when he prayed "<hi rend="underline">Give me neither poverty nor riches</hi>"?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Radfords</hi> left the Castle about 11 a.m. Miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi> had already gone off by the early train. So we are again for the nonce free from visitors. I motored to Durham and licensed four curates in the Chapel of the Castle. Then I lunched with Wilson very pleasantly. After lunch I walked to the School, and was shown the new Chapel by the Headmaster. It is magnificently situated, &amp; commands a noble view of the Cathedral. I promised to supply a copy of the Revised Bible for use on the lectern. Then I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, where a considerable congregation was present. After this I went to the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed business with him for an hour. Then I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The extravagances of "Labour" clergy are almost incredible. <hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, the Vicar of New Shildon, reports that, during the General Strike, his neighbour </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Watts</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, led his parishioners at a public meeting to swear with uplifted hand that they would read no other newspaper than the "Daily Herald"! After this, I cannot wonder that he denounces his Bishop by name!! Yet he is by way of being an "Anglo&#8211;Catholick"! It is difficult to know what to do with a man like that. His own people are distressed and perplexed beyond measure</hi>. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi rend="italic"> returned from Scotland to break his journey southwards</hi>.</p>
         <p>I finally decided <hi rend="underline">not</hi> to move the Sabbatarian resolution in the Assembly, and so informed <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Albert Mitchell</hi>. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
