<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the article, "<hi rend="underline">Is this the moment?</hi>" and sent it in to the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>. It is just a reply to the <hi rend="underline">Spectator</hi>'s article under the same heading.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Wykes</hi>, whom I ordained four years ago, came to see me, and I proposed to him that he should become curate&#8211;in&#8211;charge of the new "conventional district" which has just been formed out of Bishopwearmouth. I told him to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi>, and then, after considering the matter thoroughly, to tell me what his decision was.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi> came to see me, and took me for a walk in the Park. He expounded to me his difficulties about attending evening classes, because only in the evenings could he get into touch with the men &amp;c. I yielded to his arguments &amp; approved his proceeding on the plan originally contemplated viz: that he should take his degree in the regular course, &amp; do his best to prepare for his Priest's Ordination at the same time.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Several letters arrived in consequence of my observations on the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Industrial Christian Fellowship</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; showed that there is much distrust of that society. I wrote several letters in reply.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi> was taken by Ella to Stanhope, where they found Shebbeare entertaining the Ruri&#8211;decanal Chapter, which had been discussing the hackneyed but formidable subject of "Miracles".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank</hi> wrote to ask me to preach in College on All Souls Day, but I had to telegraph a refusal. On November 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> I have undertaken to address the Ripon Diocesan Conference on Religious Education. But I could hardly have brought myself to preach in College, if I had been free of engagements. For I feel myself an exile from Oxford, &amp; almost an outcast.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
