<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant but very cold day. The shortage of coal is being severely felt by the poor people, who cannot pay the exorbitant price. In Sunderland 5/&#8211; per cwt. was being charged last week. Meanwhile <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cook</hi> is carrying a fiery cross through the country in order to perpetuate this idiotic stoppage. We shall learn this week the extent of his influence.</p>
         <p>I went in to Newcastle, and had my hair cut. As we returned, I noticed a considerable number of birds flying high up. At first I thought that they were rooks, but, when the sun caught them, I saw the white plumage, &amp; knew them to be plovers. I have not seen so many at once for a long time. The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> has a short paragraph headed "<hi rend="underline">Birds at height of 6000 feet</hi>". It runs thus: –</p>
         <p>"It is stated by Imperial Airways in their monthly bulletin that machines flying between Paris &amp; Zurich have recently encountered large flocks of birds migrating to warmer countries. They have been heading directly south, flying in spearhead formation, sometimes several hundred yards in width, &amp; when crossing the Alps have been met with at a height of 6000 feet. So intent are they on getting to their destination that they take little or no notice of the big air liners approaching them, &amp; the pilots have sometimes found it advisable to alter their course to avoid them."</p>
         <p>I spent some time in revising the <hi rend="underline">Lock Memorial Lecture</hi>, which displeases me more on every re&#8211;reading! However it is too late for me to write anything else, &amp; I have pledged myself to print it!! I wrote to Gerald Rainbow, who is now traversing his first term at Leatherhead. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Hugh Bell</hi> sent me a copy of the <hi rend="underline">Contemporary Review</hi> containing a[n] article which he had written on "<hi rend="underline">The Dispute in the Coal Trade</hi>". </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
