<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[239]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent most part of the day in writing a long letter to old Sir Edward Clarke on Prayer Book Revision. It will probably alarm &amp; displease him: but I want to free myself as far as possible from the entanglement of misunderstandings. <hi rend="bold underline">The Church Times gives prominence to my observations on Revision at the Diocesan Conference, &amp; finds in them only the threat of prosecution!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> came in to see me about Escombe, &amp; I told him what I had already told <hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi>, that I would not extend the work beyond the necessary repairs of the fabric. Furniture can be introduced at any time, &amp; so long as the present Incumbent holds the benefice, the less the better.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> and I walked round the Park after lunch. The weather was fine &amp; still. The autumnal colouring of the trees was seen at its best. </p>
         <p>I sent &#x00A3;20 to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi> for the Mission Building in the new district. That disposes of my earnings from the last <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> article.</p>
         <p>I received three books: "<hi rend="underline">The Legacy of the Middle Ages</hi>" presented by <hi rend="doubleunderline">E. F. Jacob</hi>: "<hi rend="underline">The Life of Sir Samuel Romilly</hi>" by the author, <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Edwin Mitchell</hi>: and "Birth Control" presented by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Douglas Sladen</hi>. The last is a translation of a book by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Johann Ferch</hi>, <hi rend="underline">President of the Austrian Birth Control League</hi>, &amp; is edited with an introduction by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maude Royden</hi>. There is something extremely repulsive about such a subject being handled by an unmarried woman. I wrote shortly to Mr Sladen, since he requested my opinion of the book, saying that I could not approve it. The effect of all this propaganda on unmarried girls cannot but be very evil.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
