<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most glorious morning, which, as the ending of summer time gave us an additional hour in bed, disclosed a riper splendour to our up&#8211;rising. Then I completed some notes for my address on the Eucharist, taking as a text the "comfortable words" of S. John xvi, 33. "<hi rend="underline">These things have I spoken unto you, that in ME ye may have peace. In the world ye have tribulation, but be of good cheer, I have overcome the world.</hi>"</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to South Hetton for the service at 10.30 a.m. The church was crowded. I preached from the Chancel step, &amp; was listened to with close attention. Probably the people expected me to speak about the "Stoppage", but I preferred to speak of the Holy Communion, as the "gifts" which I dedicated included an altar rail. There were about 130 communicants, which took the Vicar by surprise, so that I had to re&#8211;consecrate twice. On the whole I was pleased with the service which was, however, rather long – 2 1/4. We returned to Auckland immediately after.</p>
         <p>Tony and I walked round the Park. There were a good many lads &amp; others walking &amp; lying about on the grass. We had some talk with a group of half a dozen miners, among whom was my friend Francis. They are clearly depressed, and feel humiliated, but they find it difficult to admit that they are defeated. </p>
         <p>The temperature in Ella's room registered 68<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> Fahrenheit. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
