<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[219]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This unfortunate "Literary Committee" of which I am chairman is asked to provide a response "which choirs can sing" to the familiar &amp; unobjectionable, "Because there is none other that fighteth for us: but only thou, O God". We originally suggested what the American Book includes, "For it is thou, Lord, only, that makest us dwell in safety": and this was accepted by the Bishops: but on reflection the musicians prevailed, &amp; that excellent &amp; beautiful response was rejected. How would this do: – </p>
         <p>("For underneath)</p>
         <p>"Because beneath (under) the shadow of thy Wing alone:</p>
         <p>We are in peace, O God."</p>
         <p>or,</p>
         <p>Because thou wilt keep them in perfect peace:</p>
         <p>Whose minds are stayed on thee, O God.</p>
         <p>On the whole, the latter seems preferable, as being wholly Biblical: but will it satisfy the despots of the organ? Neither was approved by the bishops, but a formula accepted by Frere, &amp; accepted by me. We worked steadily all day, and had no hectic moments.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">At 5.30 p.m. I delivered the Lock Memorial Lecture in Denison House. There was a large, but rather dowdy&#8211;looking audience. The Archbishop presided, &amp; spoke for 15 minutes, &amp; I lectured for an hour. There was no sign of weariness, &amp; applause at the end, so I suppose the poor thing was a success.</hi> Among my hearers I noticed Fleming, Kitty, Lady Limerick, Lady Struthers, Cecil Chapman &amp; his wife. A lean &amp; hard&#8211;featured young woman introduced herself to me as Lock's daughter, &amp; thanked me for doing honour to her father.</p>
         <p>My article on "Fair Play for the Nation" (so it has been headed) appeared in the "<hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>" tonight. It reads well enough, and less savagely than I had feared.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
