<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[237]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Armistice Day, Thursday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Bishops of Lichfield and Manchester have been offering their <hi rend="underline">apologia</hi> for their interference in the Coal&#8211;Stoppage to the Manchester Diocesan Conference, and, according to a very full account of the discussion in the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>, were received with great applause. I am not surprized. The sentimental socialism which inspired that interference carries all before it in the religious world. It is a very ill&#8211;educated, a very prejudiced, and a very emotional world: and it has been soaking itself in "Copec" literature for more than a year past. The same combination of radicalism and mediaevalism as carried the <hi rend="underline">Enabling Act</hi> is operative in the economic sphere. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Zanzibar</hi> was both an "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" and a kind of Communist: &amp; he is for the moment the "reigning saint"! These Diocesan Conferences are not representative of such intelligence as still lingers in the religious world: &amp; their habitual orators are not the ablest of their members.</p>
         <p>I robed &amp; adorned myself with a vast Flanders Poppy, and, then, accompanied by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi>, similarly adorned, &amp; the pastoral staff, motored to the War Memorial, where I was met by the Vicar. Here a short service was conducted. I gave an address, dedicated the British Legion's standard, &amp; (after 2 minutes silence) gave the Benediction. The weather was damp, cold, &amp; squally. Then I returned to the Castle, &amp; set to work on an Article for the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> on the Sunday observance question, which is making a small flutter. The tide of self&#8211;indulgent fashion which is carrying the nation to a complete secularising of the Lord's Day is far too strong to be held up, and reversed, by the jeremiads of all the preachers in Britain.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[238]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella and I motored to Durham, and there in S. Cuthbert's Church I baptized Hugh Ernest Straker, the first&#8211;born child of Hugh &amp; Jean Straker. There was a considerable gathering of Ritsons and Strakers. After the ceremony we went to the Grandfather's, Colonel Ritson's, house for tea: and then returned to Auckland, where I at once returned to work on the Article, which I finished, and despatched by the Evening post. I headed it, "<hi rend="underline">The Problem of Sunday</hi>". It is a very poor piece of work.</p>
         <p>Caröe arrived from Barnard Castle about 10.45 p.m. Lionel met him with the car, and brought him here. He shewed me his plan for building lecture&#8211;halls on Palace Green and preserving Cosin's Alms&#8211;houses. Plans are always deceiving, but these seemed tolerable.</p>
         <p>Chancellor Dowdall sent me a very flatterous letter, together with Sir Walter Raleigh's books on Shakespeare and Wordsworth.</p>
         <p>Major Ropner wrote to inform me that the marriage which I had promised to celebrate in S. Margaret's on December 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> had been cancelled. "I couldn't find the great big heart in my lady for which I sought. Perhaps I wanted too much, and looked for something that never happens." He is a fortunate man not to have made the discovery <hi rend="underline">after</hi> marriage. This change is so far agreeable that it will save me a journey to Babylon &amp; back in one day!</p>
         <p>Pemberton writes to report progress on the negotiations with the Board of Works in respect of Durham Castle. "We gathered that very probably some arrangement could be made, much on the lines which I think we put before you."Apparently, the University has reached the point of making a definite offer of the Castle to the department. It is all rather humiliating.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
