<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[286]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Arthur writes to say that this silly rumour about my becoming Archbishop of C. is current in Minehead, and that he is being questioned about it. He actually seems disposed himself to regard it as serious. It is really exasperating, for even the repudiating of it seems to give it a kind of authority, &amp; attaches it to me personally, which is equally invidious &amp; offensive. I wrote at once to bid him sweep the thing aside with contempt as an impudent &amp; offensive stunt of our latter&#8211;day journalism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Two pleasant young fellows came to lunch. They were Sedbergh boys now at Cambridge who had come to see Ernest. One of them, Macpherson, told me that he had made up his mind to take Orders. Also, Canon Crudace &amp; his sister with the lady from Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear lunched.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; took up my quarters in the Castle for the Ordination. Newsom gave the address at Evensong, &amp; was so rambling &amp; verbose that we were late for dinner. I had interviews with the men. They are the following: –</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>Deacons:</cell>
               <cell>Oswald Noel Gwilliam</cell>
               <cell>23.</cell>
               <cell>licensed to S. Mary's, Gateshead</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Robert William Bruce Richards.</cell>
               <cell>26.</cell>
               <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Gerald Munro Neill.</cell>
               <cell>24.</cell>
               <cell>"	    "     	Grangetown</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Priests:</cell>
               <cell>Norman Copland</cell>
               <cell>26.</cell>
               <cell>
                  <p>"	    "	Beamish</p>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Kenneth Kay	</cell>
               <cell>24.</cell>
               <cell>"	    "	Herrington</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>John Savage</cell>
               <cell>32.</cell>
               <cell>"	    "	Shotton</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Reginald Christopher Unwin</cell>
               <cell>24.</cell>
               <cell>"	    "	S. Gabriel's, Sunderland</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Fred Crosby</cell>
               <cell>45.</cell>
               <cell>"	    "	</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>John James Moore</cell>
               <cell>46.</cell>
               <cell>    "	    "	Lyons.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>On the whole, they are a satisfactory set, though no one of them seems to be distinguished by any unusual ability. And all except the 3 working men, Savage, Crosby, &amp; Moore, are of the right age. </p>
         <p>The total number of men ordained in the C. of E. last year is stated to be no more than 373, which represents a slight reduction from the year before. The annual "wastage" exceeds 600 men!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
