<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[243]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Dean told me last night that in Lancing School no less than 81 per cent of the boys were "only sons", and in Harrow, no less than 77 per cent. In both cases the fact was stated by the Headmasters: Bowlby and Ford</hi>. This is certainly the explanation of much that is profoundly disconcerting in Church &amp; State. The public&#8211;school class is steadily dying out of the community, &amp; its place is being taken by a heterogeneous crowd, which has a poor physique &amp; a poorer intellectual &amp; moral endowment, no tradition of public service, &amp; poverty&#8211;stricken standards of personal success. It is from this public&#8211;school class mainly that the bishops and deans of the National Church have hitherto been drawn. What will be the kind of ecclesiastic represented on the Bench in the near future? Already, in the parishes we are embarrassed by the low&#8211;toned professionalism of the parochial clergy. What will be [the] level of church life when the most pushing &amp; popular of these are in the seats of government? Professionalism in a Trade&#8211;Union atmosphere, mitigated by "retreats" and "quiet days" will be a poor substitute for the old honourable service, rendered freely &amp; without calculation of recompence. Scholarship and sacrifice are vanishing together, &amp; leaving us to a mixed multitude of socialists &amp; sacerdotalists, for the so&#8211;called "Evangelicals" have no future than that of "hot&#8211;gospellers" and quietistic fanaticks, &amp; the Modernists may be trusted to "go to their own place" in due course.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[244]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pearce</hi> made an ass of himself yesterday by calling attention to the fewness of Cambridge men in the selected members of the new Commission on religious education. The point was at best worthy of a post&#8211;prandial speech, where that kind of fooling is natural enough, but to take up the time of the Church Assembly with it was wholly absurd. I cannot understand this element of unreason in a man notably sagacious in other respects.</p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum after breakfast. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Graves</hi> told me that he was at Marlboro with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mead Falkner</hi>: that at the age of 13½ when he (M. F.) stood for a scholarship, he was 6 foot high, &amp; wore a tailed coat: that the school pundits, appalled by this imposing person, would not believe him to be so young: &amp; that he had to telegraph for his birth certificate. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Graves</hi> expressed his belief that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mead Falkner</hi> was really, though secretly, a Papist.</p>
         <p>As I walked to Westminster, I was hailed by a vigourous man, who introduced hmself to me as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Ropner</hi>, whose engagement to be married has been so suddenly cancelled. We had a little talk, &amp; parted affectionately.</p>
         <p>Nothing could have been more tiresome and futile than the discussions in the Church Assembly, and very small progress was made with the agenda. There is evidently a conspiracy on the part of a section of the clergy to assert themselves, &amp; oppose everything. They are unpleasant looking men for the most part, &amp; do not make a good impression, but no doubt they have a following of their own, which approves their obstructive tactics; and they seek no other approbation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[245]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Daily Express</hi> has an offensive paragraph on its front page headed "Archbishop to resign soon. Probable successor of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Davidson". The "probable successor" is the Bishop of Durham! Was there ever such folly?</p>
         <p>I dined with "The Club". The members present were: – 1. The Prime Minister 2. Lord Haldane 3. Lord Grey 4. Sir Henry Newbolt 5. Rudyard Kipling 6. The Bishop of Oxford 7. Lord Sumner 8. Oman 9. Geo. Trevelyan 10. The Bishop of Durham. <hi rend="bold underline">I sate beside the P. M., having Trevelyan on my other side</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi> looked vigourous, and seemed in the highest spirits. He spoke to me about ecclesiastical appointments which are pending, and we discussed several names. I said to him in parting, Would you like me to write to you on these matters? And he replied that he would be grateful if I did, provided always that I was not offended if he did not follow my advice. He certainly was very intimate &amp; cordial, but the Psalmist's counsel holds – <hi rend="underline">Put not your trust in princes, etc</hi>. I got back to the Deanery by 10.45 p.m. The weather today has been wet and warm: my heavy overcoat has been altogether excessive, &amp; I have brought no other.</p>
         <p>I visited <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Rees</hi>'s bookshop this afternoon, and purchased several books.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
