<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[283]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked all morning at the "Charge" for the Ordination candidates, and, in the afternoon, walked in the Park. On returning to the Castle I wrote a letter of condolence to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Emmott</hi>, whose husband died suddenly yesterday. He was a silent man, as became one who was Quaker bred, but his character commanded respect, and his sound judgment was recognized in the political world. He was a fairly regular attendant in S. Margaret's, Westminster, when I held that Rectory. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi> made it very clear yesterday that, so far as Lloyd George is concerned, nothing is forgiven or forgotten. The Liberal Party is to continue leader&#8211;less and unprincipled!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lionel and I motored to Southwick, where I confirmed 78 persons, mostly women &amp; girls. We were encountered by something like a blizzard going, and returning the roads were snow&#8211;covered &amp; freezing. Everywhere the boys were sliding. Why is it that some parsons present a reasonable number of males, &amp; others can show hardly any but females? It is certainly the case that in "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" parishes, not only are the candidates markedly younger than elsewhere, being, indeed, as young as the diocesan regulation will permit, &amp; sometimes (deceivingly) younger, but also the proportion of males is much smaller. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The insistence on confession is, perhaps, the reason</hi><hi rend="italic">. Boys who have reached the age of puberty are extremely reluctant to go to confession, unless, indeed, they have fallen into some habit of impurity, &amp; then they are even too ready to do so.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
