<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Presidential Address, and wrote cheques for the Household accounts. Then, accompanied by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi>, I motored to the house near Brancepeth which is occupied by Colonel and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Headlam</hi>, with whom we lunched very pleasantly. I promised to write to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi>, &amp; discuss how far he is well&#8211;disposed towards making an attempt to organize emigration in this county. </p>
         <p>We returned to Auckland after lunch; and then I set out again for Hedworth near Boldon, where I confirmed 103 persons. My address was a pitiful failure. The people coughed relentlessly, and reduced me to total imbecillity! <hi rend="bold underline">I noticed particularly how well&#8211;fed was the aspect of the candidates in spite of the fact that the whole district has been given up to unemployment for 16 months, a local strike having long ante&#8211;dated the present "stoppage"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> We returned to the Castle after the sermon, driving through heavy rain all the way.</p>
         <p>Canon Maynard Smith sent me his Life of<hi rend="doubleunderline"> Frank Zanzibar</hi>. The allusions to me are the reverse of complimentary.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
