<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[262]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">City Churches Measure</hi> was defeated in the House of Commons by 126 to 27. This is the second instance of Parliamentary rejection of the Assembly's Measures. The one – the Shropshire Bishoprick Measure – was defeated in the Lords: the other is defeated in the Commons. The combined forces of the City of London, the Artistic Folk, &amp; the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> were too much for the Ecclesiastical partisans. <hi rend="bold underline">This final assertion of the power of Parliament to override the Church Assembly will certainly facilitate the rejection of Prayer Book Revision, which will probably be attempted in both Houses</hi>. Bishops Pollock &amp; Barnes, possibly joined by Bishops Pearce &amp; Nickson in the House of Lords, will work to that end: and in the House of Commons there will be the party led by the Home Secretary and the Solicitor General, assisted probably by Labour Members &amp; Liberals. The prospect is gloomy.</p>
         <p>Ernest and I walked round the Park: and then I wasted my time by reading the book on the Kaiser by Ludwig, which Lord Balfour was recommending so strongly at Grillions. It is written in a dramatic style, and treats the Life as a tragedy, which indeed it was from its unhappy beginning to its humiliating close. </p>
         <p>James and Maimie Parker Smith arrived for the week end: they are moving from Bath to their house in North Berwick. </p>
         <p>Seven new volumes of the Loeb Classical Library arrived. They include a volume of <hi rend="underline">Eusebius</hi>.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
