<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[285]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>As I dressed, I reflected on my address to the Durham Boys whom I am to confirm this morning: and my mind settled on the Friendship of Christ. "Ye are my friends". The Lord appeals to us variously at different times of our lives. In boyhood He is the Friend: in young manhood, the Redeemer: in middle life, the Teacher: in old age, the God. At the end, he is the Friend again, not now in the fresh enthusiasm of a first love, but in the deliberate trust of proved conflict.</p>
         <p>Ernest &amp; I motored to Durham, and there in the Cathedral I confirmed 35 boys of the Grammar School, and 6 choristers of the Cathedral. The Dean &amp; Cruickshank were present. Immediately after the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The painter Ogilvy lunched here. He brought 3 paintings of me, on which he wanted to invite our opinion. I was struck by the change for the worst which the dentist has made in my countenance!</p>
         <p>Peter Richardson, Miss Headley, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dawson dined here before going with Ella &amp; Fearne to a dance in Howden&#8211;le&#8211;Wear. My inbred Puritanism always shudders at these frivolities, but my reason refuses assistance to my conscience in restraining them! Peter tells me that the  men in his colliery (Ferryhill) speak freely against Cook, whom they denounce as having led them badly, but they are very discontented with the additional half hour on the day, &amp; he does not think it altogether improbable that there might be another strike next year!</p>
         <p>Lloyd George's "unconditional" offer of his Fund to the Liberal Party was only accepted by 19 to 14, and it was pointed out that the offer only extended to the income, leaving the capital in his hands. Evidently there is no restoration of peace in that camp.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
