<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[288]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>You shall mark</p>
         <p>Many a duteous &amp; knee&#8211;crooking knave,</p>
         <p>That, doting on his own obsequious bondage,</p>
         <p>Wears out his time, much like his master's ass,</p>
         <p>For nought but provender, &amp; when he's old, cashier'd;</p>
         <p>Whip me such honest knaves. <hi rend="underline">Others there are</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Who, trimm'd in forms and visages of duty,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Keep yet their hearts attending on themselves,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">And, thowing but shows of service on their lords,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Do well thrive by them, &amp; when they have lin'd their coats</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Do themselves homage: these fellows have some soul</hi>;</p>
         <p>And such a one do I profess myself.</p>
         <p>(Iago's speech in Othello. Act I. scene i)</p>
         <p>Here is the fashionable clergyman painted to the life. Heaven help us all! We are scarcely equal to our vocations. Yesterday, I was told that the late Bishop of Chelmsford left &#x00A3;46,000: and the point was actively discussed. By what means had so large a sum been gathered by a clergyman who was professedly absorbed in spiritual work, &amp; believed to be less influenced than most men by normal secular considerations! Assuming the facts to be as alleged, there is certainly a desolating suggestion of the serpent's wisdom about this child of light!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[289]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful calm day, mild and bright. The Dean's sermon at the Ordination struck a controversial note, or rather several controversial notes, which rather jarred on me, but otherwise the service was moving and dignified. I think these young men must have gained all the help that can be gained from a friendly environment. After service, I "took up my carriages", and returned to Auckland with Ella and Fearne. Wilson had a cough, and absented himself, but his deputy, Cecil, did his duty very well.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Cockfield, where I unveiled a tablet to the memory of a deceased churchwarden, &amp; preached a sermon. There was a considerable congregation, but smaller than I had expected. Spurrier read the prayers, &amp; Lionel the lessons. I was pleased with the reverend demeanour of the men &amp; boys in the Choir, &amp; with the attention of the people. The Curate, Simmons, has had a varied experience, mostly in the Mission field, and he is said to be lacking in initiative. The Cockfield people, who are almost all miners, are said to be "very difficult". The full moon was shining brilliantly as we returned, and the Castle looked glorious. We walked round the Bowling Green to enjoy the spectacle: as we went through "Butler's Walk", the large owl, which has been observed during the last few days, flw out of the bushes.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
