<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[234]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My god&#8211;children wrote to me affectionately – Audrey Hall, Alfred Spelling and Gilbert Simpson.</p>
         <p>I motored in to Durham, and attended the function in the Town Hall, when the new Mayor (Goodyear) was formally sworn in, &amp; installed. There was the usual deluge of eulogy. I walked beside the Mayor to the Freemasons' Hall, where the company was regaled with champagne &amp; sandwiches, &amp; many speeches were made. I made a very bad one, &amp; the Wesleyan Minister made a worse! I came away as soon as I could, &amp; returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Then I acknowledged the Birthday letters which I had received. Dashwood writes to me: –</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"As regards the Prayer Book your Lordship's speech reported in today's "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times"</hi><hi rend="italic"> is by far the most significant contribution I have read on that subject. As I read it we have your Lordship's assurance that up to the present time, the Bishops have agreed to no alteration in the present Book which alters the doctrine of the Church. I assume the Articles may be taken as in some measure defining that doctrine.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There is one point which I don't think has been made clear as regards the alternative book. Will those who prefer to stick to the old book be precluded from using the new prayers or other quite harmless parts of the new book? i.e., is it to be the Prayer Book </hi><hi rend="italic underline">or</hi><hi rend="italic"> the alternate book."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I suppose as far as entire services go, it must be one or the other: but there is no reason why the prayers on special occasions provided in the new book should not be used by those who use the old services.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
