<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I left the Castle (Lionel going with me) at 8 a.m. and was in Darlington Station at 8. 35 a.m. The small booking&#8211;stall boy, William Baxter, was on the platform. He was confirmed by the Bishop of Jarrow, and assures me that he is "sticking to it". At York the Archbishop got in, &amp; we travelled together without other company, holding much converse on the way. We shared a taxi as far as the Athenaeum, &amp; there parted, I going into the Club, &amp; his Grace going on to Lambeth with the bags. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">At 2.30 p.m. the session began</hi><hi rend="italic">, and continued until 5 p.m. We dealt with the Burial Services. All the bishops were present except the Bishop of Bristol, who is prostrated with the influenza. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I walked to the Athenaeum, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">where I received a note from Buckle expressing warm approval of my Edinburgh Article</hi><hi rend="italic">. Lord Muir Mackenzie was there, &amp; had speech with me. He grows to be aged. I dined in Lambeth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Rather to my consternation there was a fire in my room, an attention which argues a kind solicitude on my hostess's part, but is really more than, in the difficult circumstances of a coal&#8211;strike, ought to be given to an invalidish guest. I did say as much to Miss Mills, but to no purpose. Ellis's pretty daughter was at dinner. She is contracted in marriage to an archdeacon old enough to be her father! How absurd people are! </hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
