<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My bank&#8211;book arrived, and as it showed a balance in my favour of over &#x00A3;3400, I walked over to the Bank, and directed the manager to invest &#x00A3;2000 in War&#8211;Loan.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote a letter of protest to the Bishop of Liverpool, who, though warned by Principal Wallis of the man’s unsatisfactory character, and advised to refer to me, ordained M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gibson without consulting me. This is certainly a very strange proceeding, and adds yet another item to the accumulating evidence of precipitancy in that Bishop.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Knowlden offering him the honorary canonry vacated by the death of Canon Urmson.</p>
         <p>During the afternoon I walked round the Park with Charles Shirran, a lad of 22 (on Nov: 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1926) whom I picked up. He was, of course, unemployed, &amp; had been so for 18 months. He lived with his parents, &amp; drew the dole of 18/&#8211; weekly. He worked at Newton Cap Colliery on the surface. I gave him the illustrated pamphlet on Durham Castle, and my lecture on 'Tyndale'.</p>
         <p>Ernest arrived in order to enter on his duties as Diocesan Chaplain. It is an experiment , of which the success cannot be taken for granted. The Sundays will probably be filled up easily enough, but the week&#8211;days are not so obviously provided for. Much turns on his ability to commend himself to the clergy, and something on their ability to attract him!</p>
</body></text></TEI>
