<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[267]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There are now vacant, or about to become vacant, the following benefices viz: –</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <p>1. Pelton</p>
                  <p>(Wellesley Wilkinson)</p>
               </cell>
               <cell>&#x00A3; 400</cell>
               <cell>9005 pop<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>patron. Rector of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <p>2. S. Hylton</p>
                  <p>(Fuller)</p>
               </cell>
               <cell>
                  <p>&#x00A3;365</p>
                  <p>(= &#x00A3;300)</p>
               </cell>
               <cell>3000 "	</cell>
               <cell>patron. Bishop</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>3. Billingham</cell>
               <cell>
                  <p>&#x00A3;410</p>
                  <p>(= c. &#x00A3;300)</p>
               </cell>
               <cell>4200 "</cell>
               <cell>"	D. &amp; Chapter</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>4. Aycliffe</cell>
               <cell>&#x00A3;391</cell>
               <cell>1245 "</cell>
               <cell>"	   "</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
                  <p>5. Shiney Row</p>
                  <p>(Renwick)</p>
               </cell>
               <cell>Poundsign350</cell>
               <cell>4400 "</cell>
               <cell>"	The Crown</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>I wrote to offer South Hylton to young Fuller, who is curate to his father in Norton.</p>
         <p>Wellesley Wilkinson, the Rector of Castle Eden, came to see me, and stayed to lunch. It is the old story, which he is the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Rector of that parish to repeat to me. <hi rend="bold underline">The squire's lady treats the parson with arrogance, and his wife with rudeness!! He would give anything to get away, and, indeed, I think he had better. But how?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Aycliffe, and took part in the <hi rend="bold underline">funeral of the old Rector, Eade</hi>. There was a considerable gathering of the county folk. <hi rend="italic">The old man represented a type of clergyman which is almost extinct. He and his father together held Aycliffe for 91 years. The church was nearly empty, and there was little done in the parish: but the parishioners held him in respect, and probably were more influenced by him than they knew or suspected</hi>.</p>
         <p>I motored to Hawthorn with Lionel, picking up Wilson, Cecil, and Boutflower in Durham on the way. There I instituted the Reverend Cornelius Widdas to the Rectory. The patron, Pemberton, was present. Old fumbling Boutflower read out my commission to the Archdeacon, and the Archdeacon's to him before actually inducting the poor parson!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
