<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi>'s address, "<hi rend="underline">The glory of the Latin language</hi>", with interest, appreciation, &amp; admiration. It is an admirable piece of work, &amp; makes one wonder why so excellent a scholar should have failed to make a greater impression on his contemporaries.</p>
         <p>I prepared notes for a short speech on <hi rend="underline">Foreign Missions</hi> – a subject which (may Heaven forgive me!) I care little about, partly, perhaps, because the zealots for it are so unattractive. However, I do not dispute its importance, nor yet its right to a place in the scheme of a Bishop's professional concerns. </p>
         <p>Ella, Fearne, &amp; Fawkes accompanied me to Newcastle, where I was pledged to "open" a Missionary Exhibition. My chairman was the local congregationalist minister, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lee</hi>, who "gushed" rather maddeningly. However, I ignored him, &amp; delivered the sapless stuff which I had prepared, and than spent half an hour in walking round the show. We returned to Auckland. The wind was so boisterous that I had little pleasure in the motoring. On returning I read through an exceedingly amusing sketch, "<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Belloc<persName xml:id="1915"></persName></hi> 
<hi rend="underline">objects to 'The outline of history'</hi>", by H. G. Wells. It is <hi rend="underline">very</hi> amusing, &amp;, on that account, the more potent as a solvent of such faith in traditional Christianity as still lingers among us!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Alfred Mond</hi> has returned from Canada, where, as he alleges, Ralph's criticisms of this country in his recent book, are doing much harm, and creating an "atmosphere of defeatism". I cannot conceal from myself that he has said many things which cannot be justified, many things that are wounding &amp; doubtful, &amp; some things which are unfair. But, taken as a whole, the book is considerable and "tonic".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi>'s son &amp; heir, <hi rend="doubleunderline">John</hi> is in the Courts as defendant in a libel or slander action. He takes after his mother so notably, that none can be altogether surprised. But Godfrey must be greatly annoyed.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
