<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[218]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to William for his Birthday. He is just as old as the century: and is, therefore, well into the best decade of a man's life. It is now more than two years since he went to Johannesburg, and our fortnightly letters have been steadily maintained. He was well&#8211;advised to leave this country, where neither employment nor liberty can any longer be counted upon by a working&#8211;man. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Sumner</hi> spoke almost despairingly about the situation last night. "I am thankful", he said, "that I am 67. If I were 47, I would not remain in England. I should seek another country, where a man could be free, and possess his own property." He thinks that the deficit next year will be so great that no additional taxation can bridge it. The Super&#8211;tax will, he said, be raised because those tax&#8211;payers have no friends: but he doubts whether, in the present state of industry, the Government will venture to add another shilling to the income tax.</p>
         <p>We worked all morning at "re&#8211;revision", and then were free in the afternoon, resuming at 5 p.m. I went to the hair&#8211;dresser, and then to Hugh Rees, where I ordered some books, including a sea[?]&#8211;story for James, which I directed to be sent to him direct. [I went to the hatter in S. James's Street, &amp; ordered a hat. Then I returned to the Club, &amp; read Asquith's book. At 5 p.m. we resumed our work at Lambeth, and continued at it until 7 p.m. There came to dinner M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bentinck. He is our minister in Abyssinia, &amp; she was a Miss Buxton. I sate beside her at dinner, &amp; found her very pleasant.]</p>
         <p>The Bishops have another foolish letter in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, supporting the miners.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
