<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[226]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A bitterly cold day with sunshine. We enter the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> month of the coal&#8211;stoppage with no clear indications of a settlement. Meanwhile hardship extends, &amp; tempers grow more inflamed. Another, &amp; very nearly successful, attempt on Mussolini's life is reported. The would&#8211;be assassin was lynched by the crowd.</p>
         <p>Wykes came to tell me the result of his consideration of my proposal that he should accept the charge of the new parish, which is being formed on the outskirts of Sunderland, out of Bishopwearmouth parish. He seems to have examined into the (not very encouraging) circumstances with much thoroughness, &amp; decided to undertake the venture. So far, so good, but, as he designs to combine his new work with getting married, I am left wondering at the complexity of human motive!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> William Wheeler</hi><hi rend="italic">, a railway clerk from Bolton, aged 26, who aspires to be ordained came to see me, and after some talk with him, I so far yielded as to promise that if he passed the Matriculation Examination at Durham, &amp; satisfied my examiners, I would ordain him on the understanding that he went on (after Ordination) to take a degree. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">On the whole, the young man impressed me as sincere and intelligent</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Bede College Committee. Then I went to the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed many diocesan matters with him. After which, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Hugh Bell</hi> writes to ask me to deliver an address at one of the Individualist Bookshop luncheons, adding that I have drawn this upon myself by my "admirable speech" i.e. the Lock Memorial Lecture. He adds that <hi rend="underline">Harold Cox</hi> will be the Chairman at the next meeting. Now I am really reluctant to offend the old gentleman, for whom I have a genuine regard, but that kind of public speaking is quite abhorrent to me, &amp; I do it woefully.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
