<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I pass "the grand climacterick" today, and enter on the last lap of my life's journey – old age. It is a terrifying thought. This year has been marked beyond all its predecessors by illness, worry, and failure: and I emerge from a very battered and desponding creature. My post brought me some messages of affection from Arthur, Cecil Fortescue, Linetta, Angel, Kathleen, and Jack Clayton. My family and guests offered me their congratulations. </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Craiks</hi> and the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chancellor</hi> went away shortly after noon: and then I had an interview with young Samuel Moore, the assistant curate of Barnard Castle. I bade him give three months' notice to his Rector in time to terminate his appointment by the end of June, &amp; received from him a promise that he would go where I send him.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" and the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" contain reports of my address to the Diocesan Conference. It is wonderful how insignificant &amp; commonplace statements look as abreviated in newspapers, though, when uttered, they had an "epoch&#8211;making" impressiveness!!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi> arrived after lunch, &amp; walked round the Park with me. He continues to be very enthusiastic about his work, though he begins to perceive that it has its disappointments.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fosca</hi> came from Gateshead to dine &amp; sleep. They presented me with a Birthday present – Rudyard Kipling's "<hi rend="underline">Debits and Credits</hi>". </p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson sent me an affectionate message: and the two old Graham ladies sent me a card. They are very loyal friends, but aging fast. </p>
         <p>I paid <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi>'s academic fees, &#x00A3;11.0.0.</p>
         <p>The weather throughout the day has been damp and depressing: and the news about the coal strike is doubtful and conflicting. But in spite of Cook's vapourings, the end cannot be far off.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
