<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[266]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful day, cold and bright. After breakfast, I took <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shadwell</hi> for a walk in the Park, and had much talk with him. The Chief Constable and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Morley came to lunch in order that the former might have some conversation with him. He told me that he would not publish his conclusions before January. He went away by the omnibus to Darlington, in the course of the afternoon: and I then betook myself to the inspection of a parcel of books on the British Empire, which may possibly give me some material for my lecture. At least they illustrate the temper of mind which the moralist is moved to criticize, and to that extent assist my purpose. A little book – "<hi rend="underline">The British Empire</hi>" – by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Lucas</hi> does more, for he asks the rather disconcerting question, "What business had the English to intrude into other people's lands, to take &amp; occupy them?" and his answer does not amount to more than the plea that, whether right or wrong, it has turned out well for the world. He admits that "there is no answer to these questions". "The safest test is perhaps that of what is called 'beneficial occupation'. The world has a right to demand beneficial occupation of all parts of its surface that can be put to good use, &amp; that is one main defence – if defence is needed – of colonisation." How "the world" can demand anything of anybody is not easy to see. The phrase can only mean "It is universally admitted by reasonable men that colonisation is justifiable when it results in the beneficial occupation of the land colonised["?]: &amp; then the difficult question remains. Who is the judge, &amp; what is the measure of beneficial occupation?</p>
</body></text></TEI>
