<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The night was very boisterous, and rain fell in great quantity, but the rise in temperature is marked and welcome. <hi rend="bold underline">I made a copy of so much of my Presidential Address as concerns Prayer Book Revision, and sent it to the Editor of the Times</hi>. Then I wrote to Lord Durham inviting him to lead an attempt to organize emigration in this county: and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi> thanking him for his gift of "<hi rend="underline">A Pensioner's Garden</hi>". Also, I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Maynard Smith</hi> thanking him for the Life of the Bishop of Zanzibar. </p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Durham, and presided over a meeting of the Board of Religious Education. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Thomlinson</hi> mitigated his motion in favour of an Appeal for the Schools into one for the Committee to consider the advisability of such an appeal. In this form I suffered it to pass, taking occasion to make a speech on the subject of the Schools, which indicated quite clearly that I would not sanction any general appeal. Then I interviewed a pleasant&#8211;looking lad, <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Suthren</hi>, the son of a motor&#8211;driver, who is at S. Chad's, and desires in due course to be ordained. After this, I returned to Auckland Castle. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chancellor Dowdall</hi> arrived about 6 p.m.: and I had some discussion with him before dinner about his recent judgment allowing an aumbry for the Reservation of the Sacrament to be used by the Sick only. He is a heavy, positive, thick&#8211;witted man with an oracular manner. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
