<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright frosty morning, very cold but all things beautiful. I think it might be a good thing for me to write to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Suthren</hi>, whom I have accepted as a candidate for Ordination, and who will receive a grant from the diocesan funds. He is but 18, and the five years which must intervene before his Ordination will make or mar his ministry. I wish he were elsewhere than in S. Chad's, where the men become more "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" than Christian!</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel (which was a very ice&#8211;house) at 8 a.m. We numbered but six, of which George Craik was one. At breakfast I received a telegram from George Nimmins. "<hi rend="underline">Best wishes. George</hi>." It is pleasant to know that in Java he yet remembers my Birthday. </p>
         <p>I spent most of the morning in preparing a sermon for Lyons: and much of the afternoon in walking round the Park with my guests. We talked much, and interestingly. It was more like one of the old Oxford walks than anything I have enjoyed for some while past.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">George Craik</hi> accompanied me to Lyons, where I preached to a crowded congregation of miners and their families. I was pleased with the reverence of the choir, and the heartiness of the service. This benefice is in the gift of the Crown, and has an annual net value of &#x00A3;427. The Rector, Rev. W. L. Law, has held office for 17 years, having spent his previous years since his Ordination by the Bishop of Lichfield in 1900 in Italian chaplaincies. He is a small, cheerful&#8211;looking man, with an efficient manner &amp; a tuneless voice. The curate, Moore, is one of my experimental artisan parsons, &amp; is in deacon's order, a dull&#8211;looking fellow enough. The people seemed interested &amp; friendly. We returned to the Castle immediately after the service. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi> outdid himself in paradoxical contrariness in conversation, but there was no breach of the peace before we parted for the night!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
