<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[220]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I drafted the following Rubrick which I shall propose for addition to the new prayer&#8211;book, where it would stand at the beginning of the book among the general rubrics there set forth: –</p>
         <p>"Although it hath been the wisdom of the Church of England in all ages since its foundation to make use of particular forms in the public worship of Almighty God, yet it is not intended thereby wholly to prohibit in the churches all other manner of devotion: and, therefore, the Minister may on suitable occasions at his discretion offer prayers in his own words immediately before or after the sermon, provided always that the appointed order of public worship be not interrupted, nor any part thereof omitted."</p>
         <p>If this were approved, it would certainly be interpreted as an olive&#8211;branch to the Evangelicals, who are rather dismayed by the general aspect of the Revision, and it would assist our approaches to Nonconformists, whose objections to "read" prayers is an <hi rend="underline">id&amp;#x00E9;e fixe</hi>. The great extension of various kinds of mission among "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" might even incline some of them to look favourably upon it: and it accords well enough with the generally anarchic tendencies of "Life &amp; Liberty" zealots. Frere, Donaldson &amp; Burroughs have professed themselves well&#8211;disposed towards something of the kind: but, of course, it is easy to formulate very plausible objections.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The discussion of my motion was, on the whole, satisfactory, though it led to no more than the reference of the subject to a special Committee. This consisted of the Archbishop of York, &amp; the Bishops of Durham, Winchester, Truro, Southwark, and Ripon. I am not quite sure that this list is correct. The rest of the day was utterly wasted.</p>
         <p>I had tea at the Athenaeum, &amp; later <hi rend="bold underline">dined with Lord Muir Mackenzie</hi>, at 27 Cumberland Terrace. The company consisted of mine host's daughter &amp; son&#8211;in&#8211;law (the swinish&#8211;looking pianist), Miss Vaughan, Lady Sheffield, &amp; Miss Haldane. With the last I had a good deal of talk. She speaks of Ralph rather severely, but more in sorrow than in anger. Of course he has given great provocation. But, though they bear themselves boldly enough<hi rend="bold underline">, I take the impression that both Muir Mackenzie and Miss Haldane are uncomfortable in the Labour party</hi>. I returned to Lambeth abour 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>One of the evening papers this week has a sensational account of the impending resignation of the Archbishop, &amp; indulges in some speculations as to his probable successor. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> is the favourite: next to him comes <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi>, &amp; then, <hi rend="underline">longo intervallo</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Henson</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi>. Of course there is no kind of authority for all this, but it has a certain effect in creating a sense of uncertainty. Certainly, the position of Primate of All England has few attractions in these ill days. It would be pleasing to have the opportunity of refusing it, but to hold the position has no kind of attractiveness. I told the Archbishop that I regarded him with mingled sentiments of admiration &amp; compassion. Envy surely has no place in my mind.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
