<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[287]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. All the candidates, the Bishop of Jarrow, Newsom, Lionel, and I communicated – thirteen in all, as at the First Lord's Supper.</p>
         <p>Breakfast in silence save for the reading of Fosdick's book, which is certainly interesting &amp; provocative.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote to William. It is now 2 years &amp; 5 months since he went to South Africa, &amp; our fortnightly letters have been hardly once intermitted. The record is nearly as good with George Nimmins in Java. These fidelities of friendship take up much time, but could I bestow it better?</p>
         <p>At Mattins, Newsom gave his second address to the candidates. It was so far superior to last night's performance that it was shorter and less disconnected, but on the most favourable estimate I cannot think that he did as well as I had a right to expect that a man of his age, experience, and position would have done. It is amazing what a friendly manner &amp; a kindly disposition will achieve in this world, for I believe it to be the case that Newsom is both popular &amp; influential in Newcastle.</p>
         <p>After the service, I took him for an hour's walk, showing him some glorious views of the Cathedral. Then followed lunch.</p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, when Purcell's delightful anthem, "<hi rend="underline">Rejoice in the Lord always</hi>", was exquisitely sung. It brought Westminster Abbey back to my mind. After the service, the candidates came to the Chapter House, and transacted the legal business under Wilson's guidance. Then we all had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight. I went back to the Castle, and had interviews with Crosby and Moore, the two working men candidates.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow, Cruickshank, Mousdale, &amp; Jimmie came to dinner, and stayed for Compline, when I delivered my Charge. The men seemed to be listening closely, and were, I hope, impressed.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
