<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[290]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received from old Lady Wimborne a queer letter, invoking my assistance in order to restrain her nephew, the Duke of Marlborough from becoming a Papist. She said that his Grace knew me, &amp; would be glad to see me. The first statement was, to the best of my knowledge, a falsehood: the last was certainly a hypocrisy. I returned a civil but guarded answer which was calculated to rid me of my ducal client! </p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, where I presided over a meeting of the Barrington trustees, &amp; visited Andrews's book shop. After purchasing a number of Christmas gifts I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Mrs Boutflower came to consult me about the Mothers' Union. <hi rend="bold underline">That society is evidently falling into the hand of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, who are re&#8211;casting its constitution with great skill, so as to make it the instrument of the Centre, which they can count on controlling</hi>. We must make an effort to save the rights of the Bishops to be supreme within their own dioceses.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Bellasis, where I dedicated a new organ in the Mission church. The parson, the Rev. J. A. Vigor, has been a "rolling stone" since his Ordination by a Scottish bishop in 1902. He did not impress me favourably, nor did the new organ which was, in spite of its dedication, noisy &amp; raucous. There was by no means a large congregation, &amp; the general effect of the service was distinctly depressing. However I preached from the words "<hi rend="underline">Rejoice in the Lord alway: &amp; again I will say, Rejoice</hi>". After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
