<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[251]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I was much interested in the attitude of the laity in yesterday's discussion. There was among them an "old guard" of Sabbatarians, of whom several came to the platform, &amp; imperilled the resolution by their fanatical fervour. There was also a section which would gladly have followed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi>'s lead, and "turned down" the Resolution by voting "the previous question". These were, I think, mostly "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks". It is not insignificant that Gamble's seconder was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Phillimore</hi>. Thus these opposed factions, with different intentions, were united in this respect, that both were irreconcilable by reasoned &amp; reasonable piety. The majority of the laity were (I judge) golfers, who themselves played on Sunday occasionally, &amp; were fathers of sons &amp; daughters who did so habitually. They had troubled consciences, which were comforted by the procedure of the Commissioners, which seemed to authorize their practice, but they were moved by my speech, &amp; rather glad to get rid of the subject in platitudes. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> in a few concluding words before the division did his best to belittle the significance of a discussion, of which it was surely his duty to emphasize the gravity. <hi rend="bold underline">But his Grace does not easily lend the assistance of his patronizing pomposity to anything which does not emanate from himself</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[252]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" has a brief account of yesterday's discussion, and a characteristic leader on "Sunday observance" in which it refers to my article in "The Bishoprick". As I was entering the Church House, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Middleton</hi> thanked me for my speech, &amp; spoke of the difficulty of maintaining any regard for Sunday in a country house. I soon had enough of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harris's prosing in the Assembly, and came away to see Storr, with whom I spent most of the morning. I lunched at the Deanery. Among the guests was M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Keble, a grand nephew of the Author of "The Christian Year". </p>
         <p>We returned to Auckland by the 5.30 p.m. from King's Cross, &amp; were met at Darlington by Lionel &amp; Leng. The train was very full. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Gainford</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Pease</hi> were on the train. The latter is still very feeble after his recent operation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">So ends another of these visits to London, which grow ever more tiresome and unpalatable. I wonder whether it has prepared trouble for the future. My two speeches in the Assembly can hardly do much harm, and certainly can do little good. Possibly my talk with the Prime Minister at the Club may facilitate communications with him in the future, when occasions may arise which make such communications desirable, but I doubt it. There is so much talking &amp; promising in the myriad momentary contacts of London life that it were rash indeed to attach importance to anything that is said or promised. Probably the brief meeting of the Episcopal Committee which agreed on the form &amp; place of a Rubrick authorizing extemporaneous prayer under certain conditions in the parish churches may be ultimately found to be the sole lasting achievement of the week.</hi>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
