<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Instigante diabolo. I wrote a short letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> headed "The Industrial Christian Fellowship", directing attention to <hi rend="bold underline">the impudent paper calling on its members to thank God for the interference of the Ten Bishops in the Mining Dispute</hi>. </p>
         <p>Then I revised and completed the Article for the Bishoprick. </p>
         <p>Old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Collier and his son came to lunch. He was very subdued. I gave him a copy of the Tyndale lecture by way of consolation!</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and there presided over a meeting of the Board of Maintenance. When this ended, I returned to Auckland where the annual meeting of Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans, postponed from the summer on account of my illness, was to take place. There were no absentees. After tea in the State&#8211;room, we had a conference from 5.00 p.m. to 7.15 p.m. We numbered 18 at dinner including Ella and Fearne.</p>
         <p>Canons Cosgrave, Wykes, and Knowlden were appointed a Committee to draw up a scheme of preparation for Confirmation. It is notable that all three are High Churchmen, though, perhaps, (with the doubtful exception of the first&#8211;named[)] none is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick. Evangelicals are for all practical purposes quite useless.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Rural Deans are naturally senior men. None is under sixty, several are above seventy: one (Crudace) must be nearly eighty. Only two out of the 14 – Douglas and Lillingston – could be described as Low Churchmen: only one, Cosgrave, might be called an Anglo&#8211;Catholick. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The remainder are "moderate High Churchmen", who, I should suppose, have never worne "vestments" in their lives, and would hardly know what to do if a parishioner desired to make confession, or prayed to be anointed with oil</hi><hi rend="italic">. They have an uncomfortable sense that things are going badly, &amp; a vague fear of "what is coming on the earth".</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
