<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A chilly wet day tending to become boisterous. In spite of it, however, Ella and I motored to Mount Grace, Northallerton, &amp; lunched with Sir Hugh &amp; Lady Bell, in the most interesting house which has been constructed in the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries out of the guest&#8211;house of the Carthusian Priory. After lunch, Sir Hugh showed us the ruins, which are more extensive than I remembered from <hi rend="bold underline">my visit in 1888, when, on August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, I drove over from Northallerton with Jennie. I was just ordained to the Priesthood, and was taking a holiday as "locum tenens" in the little parish of Ainderby, not far from Northallerton</hi>. On August 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> I received a letter from Bishop Blomfield urging me to accept the college&#8211;living of Barking. My journal, as I read it now after 38 years, reads oddly enough. I little thought then that when I visited Mount Grace again it would be as the Bishop of Durham, and the guest of the proprietor. Is one's life just a lucky&#8211;bag full of chances? or, may we dare to think that it is the scene of a particular Providence? Certainly, the latter view appeals most to one's insatiable vanity.</p>
         <p>Fawkes arrived by the afternoon train. He had lost his baggage, which, however, arrived by a later train.</p>
         <p>That strange boy, Herbert Smith, writes to me from his new school in Devonshire. He gives me an exact account of hours &amp; meals, which almost reads like a prospectus. Yet he is getting [on] for 17 years old!</p>
         <p>The weather has been distinctly colder. Fires are now starting everywhere. We burn wood, but even of that the supply is small: and the coal&#8211;cellar is practically empty. Yet the men still maintain a resolutely obstinate attitude.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
