<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[292]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The result of the Smethwick By–election is certainly disconcerting, for the Labour poll has been largely increased, and the Conservative poll largely reduced. The Liberal of course was nowhere.</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>Oswald Mosley (Labour)<persName xml:id="5634"></persName></cell>
               <cell>16,077 (14,491)</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Marshall J. Pike (Conservative)  </cell>
               <cell>9,495 (13,238)</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Edwin Bayliss (Liberal)</cell>
               <cell>2,600 –</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>It is obvious that neither the tergiversations of the Labour Party, nor the gross excesses of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cook, have in the smallest degree alienated support from "Labour".</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with Lionel. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tom Hay</hi> arrived with his dog at tea–time.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Stockton, where I consecrated the new S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Church. There was a good muster  of the local clergy, a considerable congregation, and an impressive service. I preached from the Chancel step, and was well listened to. After the service we dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Frank Brown</hi>. He seemed well and cheerful, but his intonation is defective, &amp; I found it difficult to understand what he said. He evidently has a very mean opinion of the Durham mine–owners, but his dislike of them must probably be discounted on the ground of his political prejudices. For they are Conservatives, &amp; he is a Liberal. We got back to the Castle shortly after 10.30 p.m.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
