<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[276]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The newspapers announce that the "<hi rend="underline">Life &amp; Liberty Association</hi>" has dissolved itself. The welcome intelligence is announced with some flourishes of self&#8211;admiration. Certainly that Association has done irreparable injury to the Church of England: &amp; it is not without significance that it disappears precisely when there are many signs that the nation is beginning to discover the fact.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> and I motored into Durham. There I licensed five curates in the Chapel of Durham Castle, and then lunched with Wilson. After this we returned to Auckland, &amp; walked for an hour in the Park, enjoying another most wonderful sunset.</p>
         <p>A letter forwarded to me by the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> informed me that my Article on "Religious Intolerance" had already appeared in that journal: and a grateful letter from the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi> may be taken to indicate that he has published the foolish epistle I sent him on Tuesday.</p>
         <p>The Principal of King's College was evidently pleased with my complimentary reference to his article in "The Legacy of Rome", for he thanks me for it effusively, and adds a polite comment on my allusion to my age: –</p>
         <p>"When I read your words about yourself ('a career which I suppose is now drawing to an end'), I turned up Porritt's "Unreformed House of Commons" to find a passage about the elder Pitt which I dimly remembered. '<hi rend="underline">I consider my political life as some way or other drawing to a conclusion, or rather as arrived at a period</hi>.' But Pitt went on gloriously. I need say no more."</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
