<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I slept badly last night, and read for some time before I was called. Lack of sleep breeds a fretfulness of temper which is an ill equipment for a day of conference about matters contentious! <hi rend="bold underline">We spent the day mainly in undoing what we had done yesterday! In the afternoon the discussion was so dull, and the atmosphere so asphyxiating that I all but fell fast asleep. Intelligent attention was quite beyond my power</hi>. After tea I walked to the Athenaeum, and had some conversation with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Hadow</hi>. He thought that the strike would peter out in another fortnight. I sent a note to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Buckle</hi> thanking him: &amp; wrote to Major Ropner, promising to marry him in S. Margaret's on December 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. It will mean coming up from Auckland, and returning in one day – an excessively fatiguing performance for any man: but there is no choice unless I refuse his request, which, for divers reasons, I am reluctant to do.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Gibraltar and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Greig, came to dinner. Also a layman, who held office in S. Martin's–in–the–fields. He spoke of the anxieties of the congregation as to the appointment of a successor to Dick Sheppard. The hiring is in the gift of the Bishop of London, who is now in America.</p>
         <p>The weather has become much warmer.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
