<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[249]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This warm wet weather continues, &amp; takes all the energy out of me. However I made two speeches in the Assembly, in the morning on education, and in the afternoon on the observance of the Lord's Day. In the first, I was out to "prick bubbles": in the last, I was trying to save religion from fanatical zeal. I lunched with old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Harry Craik</hi> &amp; his son – a gloomy meal, after which I walked into the Abbey, &amp; Chapter House. The famous tiles in the latter, are now seen to perfection, &amp; a functionary fits you with rubber shoes to walk on them. </p>
         <p>Ella and I dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Struthers</hi>. The company consisted of Miss Haldane, Sir Philip Gibbs,<persName xml:id="5709"></persName> Sir Richard &amp; Lady Butler, the Swedish ambassador &amp; his wife, and ourselves. Also Sir Reginald &amp; Lady Wingate. I had interesting talk with Sir Philip Gibbs about Italy &amp; Russia. <hi rend="bold underline">His description of the derelict Russian children, stark naked, filthy beyond description &amp; nearly starving, was dreadful indeed. He said that the Communist system had hardly been seriously enforced outside Petrograd &amp; Moscow, with the immediate neighbourhoods: that the system even within the limited area of its application had broken down: that it was now being revived, but could not possibly succeed. He had had interviews with Radek, and [Tchickterin (?)] who both talked with the utmost frankness, &amp; admitted their probable inability to restrain the Communist propaganda of the military zealots</hi>. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[250]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Committee of Bishops, appointed to draft a rubrick about extemporaneous prayer in the churches, met in the Council Room at the Church House at 5.30 p.m. There were 5 members present: – the Archbishop of York, &amp; the Bishops of Durham, Winchester, Liverpool, &amp; Truro. After discussion it was agreed to report to the Bishops two forms of a rubrick, with preference for the first: – </p>
         <p>(1) Note that after the conclusion of Morning or Evening Prayer, or of any service appointed in this book, the Minister may at his discretion offer prayer in his own words</p>
         <p>(2) …. the Minister may at his discretion lead the prayers of the people in his own words.</p>
         <p>It was also agreed that the aforesaid Rubrick should be inserted in the General Rubricks of the Book.</p>
         <p>This Rubrick, if finally adopted, will have little effect on the practice of anybody, but it will validate a good deal of lawless practice, and will please the Evangelicals, who will find so much to complain of in the rest of the Book. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> told me that he desires Revision to fail: and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pollock</hi> is determined to carry his opposition to change even into Parliament.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
