<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[299]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>That admirable but (I think) not very intelligent man, <hi rend="doubleunderline">S</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Clair Sarum</hi>, writes to invite me to attend a meeting in the Jerusalem Chamber in <hi rend="underline">order to discuss a "definite plan" for providing the Church with "leadership in Prayer"</hi>.  He is convinced "that the time is fully ripe for some definite lead to be given by the Bishops". What can he really mean? All Christian prayer is summed up in the petition, "<hi rend="underline">Thy Will be done</hi>", and, if we face our duty in the spirit of that petition, we are justified in believing that we shall not be unhelped by the Author of all Duty. What place is there here for any other leadership than that of example? <hi rend="underline">This fashion of organizing prayer, which now carries all before it in the religious world, at once perplexes and offends me. It all comes back at last to the sublimely simple expedient of the Buddhist Prayer&#8211;Wheel</hi>. And in most cases men go to their organized prayers, not to seek guidance, but to confirm their own decisions, and create support for their own projects. For who will lightly criticize or oppose any policy which he has been led to ask God to bless and prosper? <hi rend="underline">He mentions Prayer Book Revision and Reunion as matters which call urgently for the exercise of the leadership in prayer which he desiderates. But who does not see that with respect to both men have made up their minds, &amp; chosen their objectives? They will only be praying for the triumph of their own party, and drugging their consciences into accepting sectarianism as Christian zeal. On the whole, I incline to think that, in the present state of the Church, the less organized prayer the better</hi>!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[300]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I expended the whole morning in writing an article for the Evening Standard on "How the miner sees himself". I took M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wright's little volume of verse, "<hi rend="underline">Down under, &amp; other poems</hi>", as the basis of the article. In the afternoon I walked with Ernest in the Park: and later had an interview with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Edgar H. Iley, the irate son of the old lady, whom that silly Watts has summarily dismissed from all her numerous "Church works", alleging as his reason her failure to "co&#8211;operate" with him, which means that she abhors his politics, &amp; from time to time secedes to South Church! The position in Shildon is certainly very difficult.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi> and his wife came to spend a few days. Can I write a New Year's sermon for the Cathedral next Sunday, which would be suitable for publication in the Bishoprick? To do so would be some saving of labour. I think, perhaps, a careful review of the great issues that have emerged into clear &amp; menacing prominence during the year might not be unsuitable. Of such issues, possibly, these may be distinguished:</p>
         <p>1. The Church's (i.e. the clergy's) attitude towards the Labour movement.</p>
         <p>2. The protection of majorities in Church &amp; State from the tyranny of organized minorities.</p>
         <p>3. The question of the Christian ministry – recruitment, equipment, organization.</p>
         <p>4. The reduction of the power of the Centre to "force the pace" in the life of the Church.</p>
         <p>5. Prayer&#8211;book Revision.</p>
         <p>6. Broadcasting, motoring, cinemas, &amp; Sunday observance.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
