<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I began the day by yielding to a request from the Editor of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Morning Post</hi>, and sending him a brief letter on the Archbishop of Canterbury's speech to his Diocesan Conference. His Grace characteristically proclaims the authority of economic law, &amp; blesses the blundering interference of the Bishops in the Coal&#8211;conflict!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My little foolish letter on the "Industrial Christian Fellowship" appears on the front page of the Times</hi>.</p>
         <p>I wrote a short sermon for use tomorrow when I am to dedicate the Memorial Window in S. Hilda's, Hartlepool. Jimmie sends me a prayer which he has composed "for use when I visit": –</p>
         <p>O Father in Heaven, Who loveth each one of us, &amp; suffereth not a sparrow to fall to the ground except Thou knowest, care for us, &amp; be with us always.</p>
         <p>Help us when we need strength: comfort us when we need comfort; &amp; dwell in our hearts as we go about our daily work. </p>
         <p>Remember those near to us, who are far from us, &amp; keep them safe under Thy protection, &amp; love them.</p>
         <p>And, at this time of distress, when we are tempted to doubt Thy goodness, strengthen our trust in Thee, &amp; bring us through the darkness into the light of a stronger faith &amp; love of Thee.</p>
         <p>Bless all who live in this house, &amp; of Thy goodness lead them to the happiness that comes from Thy service, for Christ's sake – Amen.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
