<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[291]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I sent <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi>'s paper on "<hi rend="underline">The glory of the Latin Language</hi>" to the Prime Minister with a covering letter. Also, I sent the copy of the "Epistolae Obscurorum Virorum" which I bought from Bishop Ryle's Library to Ernest, from whom I received a copy of his new book, "Hartlebury Castle". His industry is admirable: &amp; his achievement is really notable in a working bishop.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with Ernest, and then had my hair cut and shampooed in the Bathroom by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Walter Cotterill.</p>
         <p>Fresh trouble has occurred at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shildon</hi>, where the Vicar's fanatical "Labour" politics is alienating the churchpeople, &amp; causing his workers to resign. I sent for the Rural Dean, &amp; he undertook to call on the Vicar, &amp; find out something more about the situation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank</hi>, my former butler's boy, came to see me. The poor lad is again out of work, through the departure of his employers, who speak highly of him. I gave him 10/&#8211; as a Christmas box.</p>
         <p>I sent from my private fund cheques to the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. E. Perry (&#x00A3;20) and Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> F. D. Jarvis (&#x00A3;25).</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Angel</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">writes from Berlin to say that the silly and mischievous canard about my being probably the next Archbishop of Canterbury has appeared in the German newspapers. She is, of course, quite excited about it, and expresses herself as if the appointment had already been gazetted!!!!! And I can do nothing, for to correct the silly thing would only have the effect of adding to its circulation. It is really too exasperating for words</hi>.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
