<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["] That Protestantism has trusted too largely to the quantity of its preaching is plain. It has commonly deluged its devotees with sermons, played spendthrift with formal religious discourses to the great detriment of their quality &amp; the great boredom of many of their hearers. We need not be surprised, therefore, at the present revulsion against preaching. We have richly deserved it. We have preached too much and not well enough. We need less quantity and more quality. The homiletical currency has been badly overinflated and we need a return to the gold standard. <anchor xml:xml:id="Hlk90461349"/>["]</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fosdick. ‘Introduction to McComb's Preaching in Theory &amp; Practice'</p>
         <p>I received an English version of the "Evangelical Letters of our Most Holy Lord Pius XI etc. on instituting a Feast of the Kingship of our Lord Jesus Christ" which is "Given at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter’s on the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> day of Dec: 1925". The salient passage runs thus:&#8211;</p>
         <p>"Therefore by our Apostolic Authority, we institute the Feast of the Kingship of Our Lord Jesus Christ to be observed yearly throughout the whole world on the last Sunday of the month of October – the Sunday, that is, which immediately precedes the Feast of All Saints. We further ordain that the dedication of mankind to the Sacred Heart of Jesus, which our predecessor of saintly memory Pope Pius X. commanded to be renewed yearly, be made annually on that day."</p>
         <p>This comparatively reasonable pronouncement of the Infallible Pontiff may, perhaps, command attention outside the ranks of his spiritual subjects.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received some copies of the re&#8211;print of my article in the Bishoprick, headed, "The deadlock in the mines" which is being issued to his work&#8211;people by a Manchester manufacturer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked at the Lock "Lecture", and then transported some books from my dressing room to the smoking room. </p>
         <p>After lunch I watched a Football Match, &amp; talked in the intervals of the game with a pleasant lad who kept goal for the visiting team. He told me that he was a driver in a pit, 18 years old, earned before the Strike 27/&#8211; per week, was unconfirmed, but not indisposed to remedy that disadvantage. His name was Arthur Graham. I was pleased to hear him speak of Duncan with respectful affection. </p>
         <p>I tried to order my thoughts for a sermon, or rather an informal address, on the Eucharist when I dedicate some accessories of communion (e.g. an altar rail) at South Hetton tomorrow morning; but I am so out of practice in this kind of preaching, that I made but small progress. I composed a dedication prayer as follows: –</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Almighty God, we pray Thee to receive at our hands these gifts which we here present, for the better ordering of our service when we draw nigh to Thee in the Blessed Sacrament: which our Saviour Christ Himself instituted and commanded us to continue. Look not on our faults, but accept us in Him, and for His sake grant us Thy Protection and the Comfort of Thy Presence all the days of our life here on earth, through the same Thy Son, Jesus Christ Our Lord. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The "stoppage" seems to be unable to stop. The miners are returning to work in some districts in considerable numbers, so that there is a chance of the end being reached by the failure of the Federation to retain authority over its members. But this is a slow process, &amp; winter is near at hand.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
