<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[277]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The papists in Seaham Harbour have organized a series of "Sermons on the Catholic Faith", and the parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Appleton</hi>, is much exercised thereupon. He writes to me suggesting that he should organize a "Teaching Mission" in the autumn of 1928, &amp; asks me to "suggest some really able Teacher". I don't know anybody who is not either an "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" or a "Christian Socialist", or both! Why can't he leave well alone. The one effective argument which the Papists possess – the bright eyes of the Irish girls – is inaccessible to his teaching!</p>
         <p>I did actually make a start in <hi rend="underline">writing</hi> the Earl Grey lecture: but not very successfully. The fact is that I am still uncertain as to my own intentions!! However it is something to have started.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hedley and her daughter lunched here, &amp; then went off with Ella to another of these incessant bazaars. I walked round the Park, &amp; was rewarded by another amazing sunset.</p>
         <p>N. B. I paid &#x00A3;131.13.0 to <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Peed &amp; Son</hi> for the rhododendrons, and some trees. If they grow, it is well enough: but if not?</p>
         <p>If the gardeners' wages, the cost of coke, manure, &amp; cartage, &amp; the bills for seeds etc be added together <hi rend="underline">the expenditure on the garden can hardly amount to less than &#x00A3;500 per annum</hi>. The repairs of the Castle, the quinquennial dilapidates, &amp; the rates &amp; taxes cannot be placed at less than &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">800</hi>. The cost of the car, and salaries of chaplains &amp; secretaries together with "office expenses" amount to at least &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">1100</hi>. So that before the House&#8211;hold expenses, &amp; the personal charges are faced, I must expend &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">2400</hi>. The rates &amp; taxes (apart from the Castle) amount to about &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">1600</hi>. Thus some &#x00A3;4000 per annum has to be expended in manners which I cannot control, and the maintenance of my household, my personal expenditure including subscriptions etc, have to be provided out of less than half my income.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
