<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[274]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>.</p>
         <p>A beautiful, still, mild winter's day. The post brought me a pleasant letter from William enclosing a number of newspaper cuttings on the native question, which he had collected from the Johannesburg papers.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi> sent me a cutting of a letter from Lord Astor on the "Oxford" Liquor Bill, and requested a commentary. I sent forthwith a letter, which will do no good, &amp; may do <hi rend="underline">me</hi> much harm.  </p>
         <p>James Parker&#8211;Smith sent me a cutting from the <hi rend="underline">Sunday Times</hi> containing an article by Charnwood on "The Church's Excursion into Politics". It was a severe censure on the Ten Bishops who intervened in the Coal Stoppage.</p>
         <p>The Editor of "<hi rend="underline">The Nineteenth Century &amp; After</hi>" writes to ask me to write the first of a series of Articles on "The Necessity for Religion": but I do not think that I will. I have too many irons in the fire. It is not easy to determine how wisely to treat such a theme. The old arguments are not so much disproved, as deprived of importance. <hi rend="bold underline">Christianity is rather crowded out than rejected</hi><hi rend="bold">. For all the questions which Religion professes to answer are as insistent as ever, &amp; in the answering of them lies the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">raison d'être</hi><hi rend="bold"> of Religion. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Lionel reported that 8 herons flew over the Park this afternoon. I suggested that more probably they were wild geese, but he said that old D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Cullagh, whose [sic] has some knowledge of birds, decided that they were herons</hi>. Ernest and I walked round the Park, Laws was busy with the cutting up of a large ash tree, which was dead. The trunk was hollow, &amp; contained copious &amp; fantastic growths of fungoids.</p>
         <p>I spent most of the day in reading the Life of Bishop Gibson. His relations with the Wesleys and Whitfield were very interesting. He began by <hi rend="bold underline">thinking the best, and ended by saying the worst of them</hi>: but he had left the scene before this movement had outgrown its early extravagances.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
