<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Another brilliant and very warm day. I worked at the Lock Lecture, and brought it to some kind of a conclusion. But it is extraordinarily shallow &amp; confused, &amp; I am half&#8211;inclined to tear it up, &amp; begin all over again. If I had the time, I would, but now I cannot. Ernest and I walked round the Park together in the afternoon.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi> writes to me from S. Helen's, West Auckland: – "Has your Lordship heard of one of the witty sayings as solution of the problem? One man on being asked what his solution was, answered 'that Cook should shoot Evan Williams, &amp; be hanged for it'! Our men here admit now that they are beaten. I know they would return at once to work, if a <hi rend="underline">real</hi> ballot could be taken. I hope they be wiser, if sadder." Certainly, the men whom I talk to in the Park are without exception eager to return to work.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ellershaw</hi> also sends me a mot which he esteems highly: – "A gem came my way the other day: it was said to me: – 'I think that when a man's got what he wants, he ought to be honest'. A man in trade gave it as his opinion."</p>
         <p>Lazenby sends a present of game. We have received lately gifts of game from the following: –</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>Lord Barnard.</cell>
               <cell>grouse</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Sir Frank Brown.</cell>
               <cell>grouse</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Alister Straker.</cell>
               <cell>grouse</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Sir John Noble</cell>
               <cell>Haunch of venison</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>J. G. Wilson</cell>
               <cell>partridges</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wood</cell>
               <cell>partridges</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>Ella read to me my lecture, and it took 47 minutes to read. This would mean at least an hour in delivery.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
