<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[275]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Fuller</hi> came to lunch, and discussed the question of his going to South Hylton. Of course, the only obstacle is the inadequacy of the income. However, I undertook that it should be raised to &#x00A3;350, so long as the pension is payable to the former incumbent. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi> asking him to see how far the Parochial Church Council will "play up". </p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with Ernest, and enjoyed the spectacle of a truly wonderful sunset. Also, we fell in with some miners, and had some interesting talk with them.</p>
         <p>Lionel &amp; I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, &amp; there I confirmed 85 persons, mostly from the parish. After the service I dined in the Rectory. On arriving at the Castle, I learned that Ernest had received a telegram announcing his mother's death.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received from James &amp; Maimie Parker&#8211;Smith as a Christmas present the charming volume called "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Fallodon Papers</hi><hi rend="italic">" which has recently been published by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is the revelation of a rare spirit – strong, calm, sympathetic, lofty. I was not prepared to find so many evidences of wide reading and large reflected wisdom. On the whole I am inclined to think that he represents the very best type of human kind, but (&amp; this is the pathos of it) </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the most extravagantly privileged</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ernest learned by a late telegram that his mother had died suddenly. He hurried off by the midnight train. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
