<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Headlam</hi> came to see me with respect to the project of organizing the emigration of Durham miners, who will be permanently unemployed as a result of the "stoppage". I promised that I would try to interest <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi>. It is nowise easy to be optimistic as to anything effective being done, but we must certainly try. The [Y.?] P. has an estimate that 20,000 miners will be idle in Durham county.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park during the afternoon. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spurrier</hi> and his mother came to see me, and I gave them tea. He asked me to officiate at his marriage on Thursday, the 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> April, and I promised to do so. Ella, Fearne, and Lionel went in to Durham to attend a lecture by Canon Hannay ("George Birmingham")<persName xml:id="5609"></persName> in the Chapter House. The subject was "Ireland and Hungary". </p>
         <p>A parcel of books arrived from Hugh Rees: –</p>
         <p>1. British Slavery &amp; its Abolition 1823–1838, by William Law Mathieson. 16/–</p>
         <p>2. Short History of Marriage by Edward Westermarck. 10/6</p>
         <p>3. Modernism in the English Church by Percy Gardner. 5/–</p>
         <p>4. The Anglo–Catholic Faith by T. A. Lacey. 5/–</p>
         <p>5. The Faith of an English Catholic by Darwell Stone. 3/6 (?)</p>
         <p>My reading grows ever more multifarious &amp; intermittent. It is difficult to know what to choose out of the varied stream of publications, &amp; one's choice is determined by the most various motives. The result must be to make one's mind a "rag–bag" filled with odds &amp; ends of unrelated information. And this is the negation of knowledge for it prohibits that concentration of interest which is the condition of gaining any degree of knowledge. <hi rend="underline">As I review my life I can see quite clearly that the root of its failure has been the lack of concentration</hi>. Partly this has grown from the circumstances of my life, but partly from a radical instability of character, itself the evidence of a deep–rooted defect. And now at 63 it is too late to attempt amendment. </p>
         <p>Miss Fox came for the week–end.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
