<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop expressed himself rather gloomily last night on the prospects of our essay in Prayer Book Revision</hi><hi rend="italic">. He thought that, if there were any considerable opposition to the measure in the Church Assembly, there was considerable probability that Parliament would reject the measure. He did not consider himself bound to present to Parliament every measure which the Assembly might adopt irrespective of the amount of opposition which it had evoked. </hi>[<hi rend="italic">He shared the grave apprehension which I feel as to the possibility, even the probability, of a Labour Prime Minister having control of the Crown Patronage. He spoke kindly of Ramsay Macdonald, who was, in his view, weak rather than wicked. Lloyd George was, he thought, wholly untrustworthy, but he was the only Prime Minister out of the ten whom he had personally known, who had succeeded in making Downing Street habitable!</hi>]<hi rend="italic"> So inveterate is the caution of his Grace, that, even when conversing freely with him in private, one cannot escape the suspicion that he is still on his guard, and saying no more than he judges it prudent for him to say to you! This circumstance detracts greatly from the interest of his conversation. I make desperate efforts to provoke him to indiscretions, but am almost always baffled by his wariness! I wonder whether he really speaks with the reckless frankness of friendship to anybody. </hi>[<hi rend="italic">He agreed with me when I expressed disgust with the "woolly optimism" that now marks Haldane's language on social, and economic questions: and he said that Haldane had made a bad mistake in joining the Labour Party, but I doubt whether he has said as much to Haldane himself, with whom he was staying recently at Cloan.</hi>]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Smoking Room is adorned by a large photograph of Cardinal Mercier, "presented by Lord Halifax". Time was, when such a picture could not have been set up within Lambeth Palace without endangering the Primate's neck! But we live in changed times, &amp; shall all be kissing the Pope's toe before we are much older.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The discussions ranged over a good deal of ground, and were not very effective. We agreed to "enrich" the service for Ordaining deacons, and we decided not to include in the Ordinal a service for "ordaining" deaconesses. This decision did not please the Archbishop of [C.?] who is far gone in feminism. I found myself voting against my friends, the Bishops of Worcester, Birmingham, &amp; Norwich; who oppose everything that comes from the other side. My view is that we must keep steadily in mind the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">purpose</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">for which the work of Revision was entered upon viz: the restoration of law, by legalizing everything which does not conflict with the fundamental principles of the Church of England.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Pearce and I came away together, &amp; drove to Paddington in time to catch the 4.45 p.m. express. On arriving at Oxford, I was met at the station, and driven to All Souls. </p>
         <p>I dined in College very pleasantly. Wilkinson, Pollard, Harris, Rouse, Beckett, [Zulnita?], and a number of guests were present. Among the last was Streeter, with whom I had some conversation. </p>
         <p>I am interested to observe that there is apparently no shortage of coal in the College. There is a fire in my bedroom, &amp; hall, common room, and coffee room were all equipped with fires. The discomforts of the "Stoppage" are unequally distributed. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
