<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[279]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The dissolution of the "Life &amp; Liberty" association ought not to go unchronicled. I half incline to make it the theme of an Article in the "Bishoprick". An obituary notice might, not unfitly, take its place in a review of the year. And therein might also be brought a criticism of Lacey's Apology for the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, and an estimate of the prospects of Prayer Book Revision</hi>. Add the formidable statistics of Ordination for the year, and a reference to the ecclesiastical effects of the great "Stoppage", and we have materials for a substantial contribution. Some notice must be made of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sykes</hi>' <hi rend="underline">Life of Bishop Gibson</hi>.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Maynard Smith</hi>, who is about to edit the Church Quarterly Review, wrote to ask me to write on Prayer Book Revision in the July issue of that journal. I replied civilly, but declining his request.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I started to read </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Lawrence</hi><hi rend="italic">'s "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Memoirs of a happy life</hi><hi rend="italic">", which he sent me a short while ago, and became so interested that I finished it. A good man, well&#8211;endowed by nature, financially "well&#8211;off", fortunate in all the circumstances of life – Lawrence took a cheerful view of the world.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, had tea with Wynne&#8211;Willson, &amp; preached in the Venerable Bede's church. The return journey was hindered by fog, but we got home safely about 9.30 p.m.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
