<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[303]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1926.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from the Prime Minister a very pleasantly expressed acknowledgment of Cruickshank's pamphlet on "The Glory of the Latin Language" which I had sent him</hi>: also a friendly letter from the Dean of Westminster saying that he would be glad to accept the studies on the Abbey, which I had offered to send him. So I caused these (5 vols) to be despatched forthwith. A telegram from Robin asked if he might bring a Princess of sorts to see the house. He brought her in the afternoon, and I acted showman. After Her Highness had departed, <hi rend="bold underline">Cecil arrived, with my Will, which I signed. Brooke &amp; Lionel witnessed the document</hi>.</p>
         <p>I worked at this precious Article, but to little purpose. Some malignant necessity compels me to write in such wise about the Strike that I give the impression of being altogether without sympathy for the miners, which is far indeed from being the case. But, <hi rend="bold underline">while my heart is with the men, my head is with the masters: and the last alone can express itself</hi>. I want to insist on the special obligation now resting on the mine&#8211;owners to make things more comfortable for the men, &amp; to remove all causes of discontent which are removable: but I can't do this, since I am quite unable to say what it is precisely that the mine&#8211;owners ought to do, and mere vague exhortation which cannot be crystallized into specific counsels is not worth much. There is much wisdom in saying nothing at all, and something to be said for echoing some party's shibboleth, but <hi rend="bold underline">this "mugwump's balancing" of saying what one thinks, is plainly absurd</hi>.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
