<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[364]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]In short, the Church of England is free, is orthodox: she has a plenary authority within herself, and has no need to recur to any other church to direct her what to retain or what to do. Nor will we, otherwise than in a brotherly way, and in a full equality of right and power, ever consent to have any treaty with that of France. And, therefore, if they mean to deal with us, they must lay down this for the foundation, that we are to deal with one another upon equal terms.["]</p>
         <p>Abp. Wake to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Beauvois, Aug. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1718</p>
         <p>v. Mosheim's Ecclesiasatical History, vol. iii. p. 643</p>
         <p>I went in to Durham, and licensed two clergymen – Bailey to be Chaplain to the Seamen's Mission in South Shields: &amp; Fletcher, to an assistant curacy at S. John's, Sunderland.</p>
         <p>After lunch, I motored to Staindrop, and, in the parish church, baptized Gerald Raby, the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> child of Lord &amp; Lady Barnard. He screeched lustily, and was therein encouraged by the example of his elder brother, who accompanied the service with a running commentary of his own! </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Times publishes my letter under the heading "Soviet Russia"</hi>. </p>
         <p>I motored to South Hylton picking up Cecil in Durham &amp; Wynne Willson in Sunderland. Ernest and Lionel went with me. I instituted Eric Fuller to the Vicarage, and afterwards dined with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Headley, &amp; her many daughters. Squance, a son&#8211;in&#8211;law [w]as there. He was Captain of Durham School, while I was Dean, &amp; then went to Magdalen. He now seeks to become an accountant, but finds difficulty in passing his Examinations! The congregation was not unsatisfactory in terms of numbers, but in the matter of sex, it was lamentably out of proportion, being mainly composed of young women and girls! Why is it that manhood and the Church are parted by so wide a chasm? We got back to the Castle a little before 11 p.m.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
