<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[366]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There is a column of my Lecture on the front page of the <hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>, and a leading article snifflingly favourable. Both the <hi rend="underline">Newcastle Papers</hi> give a column of report, &amp; decorate it with a photograph, but abstain from commentary. The <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi> has neither report nor comment. I suppose as the lecture was a domestic affair of Armstrong College, the general press takes no account of it, save in so far as it is given access to the M.S. The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> has nearly a column of report. On the whole, I think, the poor thing reads connectedly. It will not please anybody! <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Theodore Morison</hi> sends me a kindly expressed letter in which he says that my lecture "was exactly what I have thought the Earl Grey Lecture should be, a great handling of a great subject". And <hi rend="doubleunderline">Turner</hi> sends me a pleasant note of "congratulation". Nevertheless, I cannot pretend to be satisfied with it.</p>
         <p>I wasted the day (save for the formal business) in reading a romance sent me by the publisher "<hi rend="underline">Jew Süss, a Historical Romance, by Lion Feuchtwanger</hi>", which is most highly praised by the Review, &amp; certainly is a powerful composition. It is disfigured by passages of incredible &amp; gratuitous grossness, but its broad impression is not salacious. The description of a Jew hunt is wonderful, and the grossness of German life shot through by Jesuit intriguing is vividly portrayed. The central figure is boldly drawn, &amp; his moral evolution holds the reader's interest to the end.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi> kept his room, pleading a sore throat. He seems to have influenza. This compelled the usual bothersome revising of arrangements.</p>
         <p>The "Spectator" prints an article headed "<hi rend="underline">A Free Churchman on Prayer Book Revision</hi>", which is signed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold E. Brierley</hi>.  It is in the main very favourable, and contrasts with the fanatical denunciation of our own Evangelicals. The truth is that the latter are in a false positions [sic] as members of the Church of England. One result of the Toleration Act was to draw away from the National Establishment its most virile Protestants, for whom it provided another &amp; a less circumscribed sphere. The Protestants who remained in the Church of England were inferior in type, and have never been really at home there.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
