<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[369]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I tried to write on Prayer Book Revision for the <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh</hi>, but made no headway. The subject bores me unendurably! </p>
         <p>There came to lunch the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> R. Bidwell, Vicar of Gainford, who wore a grey suit and a white tie, and, as these phenomena suggested, expressed himself as hostile to the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks and favourable to the new Prayer Book: Archdeacon and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mangin from Alnwick, a hearty &amp; rather Philistine couple who might have lived in Barsetshire &amp; made a figure in its Chronicles: with them came also a dolourous female, the Archdeacon's sister&#8211;in&#8211;law, who might have been the original of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gummidge. There lunched also old D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullagh, who brought back "Palmerston" and borrowed "Bolshevist Russia". I had to get away to Durham immediately after lunch in order to preside at a meeting of the Board of Finance. It was amicable, but hardly exhilarating, for the year's income shows a deficit of about &#x00A3;600. After the meeting I went to my rooms in the Castle, and had tea. Then I received a deputation from the Council of the Durham Colleges on the subject of the Castle Restoration. Pemberton, the Vice&#8211;Chancellor, [Howe?], Masson, the Dean, Guillaume, Robinson, and one other formed the deputation. After an hour's talk they agreed to seek further advice on the Castle with a view to issuing a great appeal in the autumn. I disapproved the notion of a private bill to transfer the Castle to the State, as undesirable in itself and little likely to secure the acceptance of Parliament. Then, I picked up Ella &amp; Fearne, and returned to Auckland. The weather continues mild and almost close. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
