<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[312]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> called to see me with respect to a proposal which he had received from the Bishop of Llandaff, viz: that he should become the Diocesan Missioner. He was in doubt as to his duty. On the whole I inclined to think that he should accept the proposal. In any case he would not leave Bishop Auckland until Easter was over.</p>
         <p>Hardly had <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> retired before <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hall</hi> from S. Gabriel's, Bishopwearmouth, appeared. He was in doubt about accepting a chaplaincy in Bristol, which was not unlikely to be offered him. I went as far to dissuade him as I thought fitting.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi> &amp; I walked round the Park in the course of the afternoon, and then I finished the Article for the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>: after which I fell to clearing up my table, &amp; writing some overdue letters. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">An old gentleman, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Colonel Sir Ainslie Lunham K. C. B</hi><hi rend="italic">. wrote a letter filled with classical tags, &amp; facts about Bishop Butler. He had been moved to write by his approval of my sermon in the Cathedral. He signed himself, "Your Lordship's son &amp; servant", which has rather an antique sound. I wrote to him civilly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi> reported that the tortoise had died, and that he had heard the owl hooting on the Terrace. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
