<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[321]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A calm mild morning. I motored to Darlington and caught the early train to King's Cross. I had a carriage to myself, and beguiled the way with the newspapers, and with a book which Boutflower gave me: "<hi rend="underline">After many years, a Tale of Experiences &amp; impressions gathered in the course of an obscure life, by W. E. Heitland</hi>." It is published by the Cambridge Press.  Boutflower describes the Author as his "oldest &amp; most affectionate friend". On arriving in London, I first had my hair cut, and then proceeded to <hi rend="italic bold underline">Lambeth, where the Bishops were in session</hi><hi rend="italic">. Their meeting is largely commented on in the newspapers, but the comments are more interesting than accurate. For instance, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Morning Post credits me with the authorship of a 'draft' which the Bishops are to discuss</hi><hi rend="italic">! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Archbishops proposed various arrangements, which would have the effect of giving a premature publicity to the Revised book, and enabling all the mischief&#8211;mongers to organize opposition in advance of the critical meeting of the Assembly. We got on to the proposed rubrick about the annointing of the sick, and I expressed strong opposition. Barnes, Headlam, Pearce, Nickson, &amp; Lisle Carr joined me: on the other side were Garbett, Furse, Woods, &amp; Frere. The discussion was adjourned.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
