<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[354]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]In his (Paley's) lectures upon divinity, he took the view, maintained also in his "Moral Philosophy", that the Thirty&#8211;nine Articles were merely "articles of peace", inasmuch as they contained "about 240 distinct propositions, many of them inconsistent with each other". It was impossible to suppose that the imposers could expect any man to believe all . . . . . Paley was intimate with Jebb, but declined to join in the "Feather's" petition of 1772 for a relaxation of the terms of subscription, on the ground that "he could not afford to keep a conscience". He afterwards, however, wrote anonymously in defence of a pamphlet written in 1774 by bishop Law in favour of relaxation.["]</p>
         <p>L. S. in Dict. of N. B. "Paley"</p>
         <p>My cold being very heavy, I remained indoors, &amp; mainly read – an excellent life of John Wyclif by Principal Workman, published by the Clarendon Press. </p>
         <p>Jimmie, who has been down with influenza, came to see me during the afternoon. He bears the marks of illness on his face, but, as he has resumed playing football, I assume that he has effectively recovered.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Loft came to see me about a project for selling the vicarage house in S. Mark's parish, South Shields, where that queer creature [Hassell?] holds office.</p>
         <p>Then Heaver came to report the result of his visit to Crook, where I desire that [he] should take his title for Ordination at Trinity. He expressed himself very favourably, and seems ready to "take on" in a manly spirit.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
