<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[313]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have been active all day, and have done nothing. Letters absorbed much time, and some were important. In the afternoon I went in to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Board of Training and Maintenance. After this I transacted business with the Bishop of Jarrow, had tea with him, and then returned to Auckland, where I wrote more letters. And that is the whole of the day.</p>
         <p>That preposterous creature, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax</hi>, writes to inquire whether it would be agreeable to me that a retired South African Bishop should be appointed Warden of his House of Rest. I replied that there were cogent reasons why a Warden in Episcopal Orders was undesirable. <hi rend="bold underline">The whole business is just the spear&#8211;head of an Anglo&#8211;Catholick invasion of the diocese</hi>. A bishop would suit the fanaticks admirably. He would show how a Catholick bishop ought to dress and pontificate, and give distinction to all the little clerical shows in the Anglo&#8211;Catholick parishes! There are troubles enough in the diocese already, why should we add one of these squalid ceremonial conflicts?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Jarrow has been talking to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kirkup</hi><hi rend="italic">, the manager of the Joicey mines at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, about the situation in the coal&#8211;field. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kirkup</hi><hi rend="italic"> says that L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Joicey's Company has lost &#x00A3;400,000 "but it was worth it". The men were "at mercy". There was to be a 10 per cent reduction in the number of men: all sorts of labour&#8211;obstructing customs would be abolished: &amp; machinery introduced on a considerable scale. All this sounds rather alarming. The mine&#8211;owners are obsessed with the object of re&#8211;imbursing themselves for their losses during the "stoppage", and they do not look far ahead. The prospect of industrial peace is as remote as it ever was.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
