<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[348]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very cold but (for the most part) fine day. Ella and I left the Castle about 10 a.m., and motored to Bamburgh (75 miles) where we lunched with Lord and Lady Armstrong, and were shown over the Castle. At lunch were a nice&#8211;looking Canadian named Planta and his wife; who were making their first visit to England. The Castle is largely modern, but the keep is old. Nothing could exceed the majesty of the position, and much history gathers about it. Quite near the shore are the Farne Islands where sea&#8211;birds nest, &amp; the name of S. Cuthbert is remembered. On our homeward journey we stopped at the Vicarage in Alnwick, &amp; had tea with Archdeacon and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mangin. They spoke of the Bishop of Newcastle, whose resignation they thought necessary and imminent. The leading laity of the diocese were becoming restive, &amp; had made representations to the Archbishop.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> reports the death of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Johnson</hi> at the age of 81, and publishes a well&#8211;written &amp; very appreciative account of him. I suspect that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fletcher</hi> is the author.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow sent me the proof of the leading article on Prayer&#8211;Book Revision, which he has written for the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>. I thought it excellent, and told him so. There is a characteristically canting letter in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> signed by several prominent "Catholicks" exhorting "Catholicks" to abstain from demonstrations of hostility until the "Catholick" organizations have considered and reported!!!
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
