<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[307]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Day, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 11 communicants altogether.</p>
         <p>After breakfast I prepared my sermons for tomorrow.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Newcastle &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wild, with their sons, Cyril &amp; David and Miss Dalrymple came to lunch, &amp; I showed them over the Castle. The two lads impressed me as ingenuous, intelligent, and modest. After they had departed, I walked in the Park, &amp; enjoyed a lovely sunset. On returning to the Castle I went through the correspondence with Lionel, &amp; wrote letters.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Why is it that the artisan&#8211;bred clergy are so inferior in vigour, mental and physical, to others? About the fact I think there can be no doubt. Responsibility seems to be too much for them</hi>. This morning I received a letter from some doctor in Butterknowle describing in almost tragic terms the state of Spencer Wade and his wife. He must without delay be transferred to a more favourable sphere, or there will be a hopeless breakdown! It is little more than a year since he was suddenly sent from his parish in Manchester on the same plea. Durham was then the Mecca of his hopes, for there he could breathe his "native air", now it is urgent that he should leave it!!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[308]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The New Year begins with a series of "break&#8211;downs" &amp; departures among the clergy. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cook</hi> of Spennymoor and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petitjean</hi> his curate are both <hi rend="underline">hors de combat</hi>; I and my chaplain take the whole duty tomorrow. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Neville Hudson</hi>, the curate of Brandon, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Royle</hi>, the curate of S. Oswald's, West Hartlepool, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bailey</hi>, the Curate of Stockton, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Surtees</hi>, the Curate of S. Aidan's, West Hartlepool, are all leaving the diocese, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hall</hi>, the Curate of S. Gabriel's, Sunderland is probably doing so. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi>, the Vicar of Lynesack, is reported to be on the verge of a nervous breakdown, &amp; must have "a new &amp; more congenial sphere". Two parishes – Aycliffe &amp; Billington – are vacant. They are in the gift of the Dean &amp; Chapter, and must, therefore, be filled from within the diocese. South Westoe is to be vacant shortly: and Castle Eden will be vacant in January. <hi rend="underline">Here is a requirement of at least 9 more clergy to fill up vacancies, and there is nobody in view</hi>. What can be the end of this wasting process? <hi rend="bold underline">The Church of  England is just crumbling away. Meanwhile our ceremonial ever grows more elaborate: our "functions" more numerous &amp; pompous: and our machinery for self&#8211;advertisement more extensive. There are clergy to be found for organizing these incessant shows, &amp; meetings of every kind multiply daily, but the parishes are unworked, &amp; soon the vicarages will be untenanted.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
