<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[347]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from Gore a well&#8211;written and effective tract on the nauseous, and insistent subject of "Birth Control". Having read it through, I sent him a brief letter expressing my substantial agreement with him on that subject.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then I worked at the Lecture all the morning, but I am even yet not quite clear as to my intentions therein! After lunch I spent more than an hour with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Spedding the dentist. Then I walked in the Park, &amp;, returning to the house, resumed work on the Lecture.</p>
         <p>Miss Donaldson writes to me a long letter of self&#8211;exculpation, from which I received the impression that she regrets her resignation. But it is too late to go on that now: &amp; my civil reply assumed that to be the case. There has clearly been some muddling, and a certain amount of feminine friction. If ever women come to bear rule in Church and State, the wheels of government will not run smoothly.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Norman Sykes</hi> sends me a type&#8211;written letter in red ink in [sic] acknowledging a copy of "The Bishoprick", with the observations on his <hi rend="underline">Life of Bishop Gibson</hi>. He says that the pressure of his work at King's College leaves him no leisure to pursue his historical studies. This is really a public misfortune, for he has proved his quality, and a really good ecclesiastical history for the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century is greatly needed.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
