<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[342]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We all went in to Durham in order to lunch at the Deanery, and attend <hi rend="bold underline">the Commemoration of Founders and Benefactors</hi>. There was a goodly number of Honorary Canons at lunch together with some neighbours. <hi rend="italic">I sate between M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ford &amp; Lady Eden, &amp; found them interesting. The service was impressive, the singing exquisite: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the sermon inadequate and dull. Certainly the Dean of York is not a great preacher. His manner is at once melancholy and pompous;, but his substance deserved no better</hi><hi rend="italic">! After service we had tea in the Deanery, &amp; chatted with many old acquaintances. We returned to Auckland, where </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Norwood</hi><hi rend="italic"> arrived about 6 p.m., in order to address a meeting in the Town Hall at 7 p.m., over which I presided. There was a large attendance, mainly of men. I spoke shortly, &amp; then </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Norwood</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke for an hour. He is fluent, forcible, &amp; rather flamboyant, but he did not say anything worth remembering. We went back to the Castle, &amp; there he was very entertaining. He is a rather square&#8211;built man, Australian by birth, with a hearty manner, a frank smile, &amp; a sense of humour. He told some amusing stories about </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Joseph Parker</hi><hi rend="italic">, his predecessor in the charge of the City Temple. His account of Australia was not very favourable.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
