<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[322]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. <hi rend="italic">The discussions were not very exciting. One amusing incident relieved the tedium of the morning session. The Bishop of Carlisle was speaking on incense, and said that it had warrant in Scripture. He was interrupted by the clear, sarcastic voice of the Bishop of Birmingham – "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Incense is an abomination unto me</hi><hi rend="italic">". The House dissolved with laughter at a quotation so apt, so destructive, and so unexpected! A rather sentimental alternative for the Commination service, proposed by the Bishop of Winchester, was rejected by the Archbishop's casting vote. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>The proof of the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> arrived. I carried it to the Athenaeum, where I corrected it, and sent it to Carter. In the Club were Newbolt and Justice McCardie, with whom I had some talk. The Archbishop spoke at dinner about the notable softening of controversial methods, and gave some examples from his own knowledge. <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Talbot</hi> had talked of arming the rustics with pitchforks to resist the intrusion of Dissenting Ministers into the churchyards in the exercise of the liberty granted by the Burials Act. I reminded his Grace that many years later the same <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Talbot</hi> had refused to attend service in S. Margaret's because I had preached in favour of religious fellowship with Non&#8211;episcopalians! I think the improvement in controversial methods is more apparent than real. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
