<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[349]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Today I complete nine years of episcopate. It began in much distress: it has continued in much difficulty: it exists in a deepening discontent. And yet there is much, very much, in it for which, not the morbid melancholy of complaint would be fitting, but a humble thankfulness to the Divine Author of all Good. "<hi rend="underline">Why are thou so vexed, O my soul: and why art thou so disquieted within me? O put thy trust in God: for I will yet thank him, which is the help of my countenance, &amp; my God</hi>."</p>
         <p>I worked at the Lecture most of the morning, &amp; then M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jones the architect expounded to me the perilous state into which the Castle at Durham has come. He says that not less than &#x00A3;80,000 will be required. This is a bad business, and with the 1300<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centenary of York Minster monopolizing the public mind this year, there could not be a worse time for raising money. Jones stayed to lunch, and then departed. I walked round the Park with Lionel, &amp; then went through the correspondence.</p>
         <p>We motored to Pelton, picking up Wilson and Cecil in Durham on the way, and I instituted the new Vicar, Wellesley Wilkinson, in the squalid church. The wall&#8211;eyed curate, Brazier, read the service, &amp; the Rural Dean, who is also the patron of the living, Jackson, inducted the Vicar. I was displeased at the squalour of the Vestry &amp; the chattering of the choir boys. Two youths in much be&#8211;laced cotton gave me an ill impression.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
