<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[375]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I think, perhaps, a Prayer for the Empire ought to make mention of the great variety of races, languages, and stages of culture included in the British Empire, &amp; make petition for mutual forbearance &amp; unity in allegiance. Also, perhaps, we ought to pray for the security of the Empire from external attack. </p>
         <p>I wasted the morning in an unsuccessful attempt to draft a Preface which shall be adequate without being either too long or in any improper sense controversial. </p>
         <p>In the afternoon I walked in the Park, and picked up three young men who had not seen the inside of the Castle. So I took them there, and spent half an hour. They seem both intelligent and appreciative.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote to the Archbishop, and sent him the draft collect. It doesn't satisfy me, but I can't do anything better.</p>
         <p>I wrote to my Godson, Gilbert Simpson: to Bailey answering his very interesting letter from Avignon: and to Caröe who is lying ill in a Hotel in Mallorca. </p>
         <p>There seems a probability that the Bishops will have in front of them a large number of proposals and protests. How ought these to be treated? Probably it would be advisable to select a few very important points, &amp; with respect to them to concede the request of the Convention. Having thus "saved their face" by appearing thus to defer to their wishes, the Bishops should make a clean sweep of all the rest, and present their own proposals essentially unaltered for the acceptance or the rejection of the Convocations. Anything like a re&#8211;opening of the whole complicated issue of Revision would be quite disastrous. "<hi rend="underline">Sint ut sunt, aut non sint</hi>" must be the Episcopal Motto.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
