<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[309]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Ella and Fearne went with me into Durham, where I preached in the Cathedral to a congregation which, though not very great, was much greater than my experience of former years had allowed me to expect: and, afterwards, I celebrated the Holy Communion. The young Reporter, who haunts me, came into the Chapter House, and carried off my M.S. under a solemn pledge to return it. <hi rend="doubleunderline">If</hi> he breaks faith, I am truly undone, for the sermon forms the bulk of my article for the Bishoprick! We lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ellwood</hi>, <hi rend="bold underline">the Vicar of S. Chad's, Gateshead, came to see me, and was rather excessively persistent in urging me to sanction his use of his Church for the Miracle Play which he has been arranging. But I was obdurate, &amp; would not yield, being indeed, rather annoyed at his persistence</hi>. We returned to Auckland as the Cathedral bells were ringing for Evensong. Lionel and I went to Spennymoor, where both vicar &amp; curate were in bed, and conducted service in the parish church. He read the prayers, and I read the lessons and preached. Then we returned to Auckland in the teeth of a gale. The weather continues to be unseasonably warm.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
