<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[353]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A beautiful morning. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m., though I had a heavy cold, and felt miserable enough. We mustered 7 communicants including James. I wrote to William, and sent him the "<hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>". Then, as Lionel was going into Durham, I was craven enough to send a note to Jimmie "crying off" my engagement to preach in his Mission. So, after an hour's exercise in the garden, I stayed in my room reading promiscuously. I seized the opportunity of clearing up my table, and writing some private letters.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Church Papers give me an ill impression. The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Record</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">, from opposite points of view, hold a menacing language, none the less menacing for being in form punctiliously respectful to the Bishops. If the one side will make no terms with any re&#8211;arrangement of the Communion Service, and the other intends to follow the lead of the late </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Zanzibar</hi><hi rend="italic"> in "fighting for its tabernacles", I do not see how any acceptance of the Bishops' proposals can be looked for.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I counted the names of the clergy actually working in the diocese of Durham, and they amounted to no more than 374. There are 272 benefices, so that there are but 102 assistant curates.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
