<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[315]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The morning post brought a letter from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hird of Hodder &amp; Stoughton requiring "a complete manuscript" of the volume of Ordination addresses, which I design publishing and presenting to the clergy in Lent, if it can be got out so soon. I spent the morning in preparing the stuff, which was sent off by the afternoon post. Whether I have done wisely in this, I feel very doubtful, for it is impossible to touch on any matter connected with the Church of England without being "controversial", i.e. offending one or another set of cranks! However, I thought it not unfitting to mark the completion of 40 years since my Ordination by sending something to the clergy, &amp; I wanted to let my episcopal brethren know how I dealt with my Ordination candidates.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> announces the death of old Sir Francis Fox, who was in charge of the work on Durham Castle.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park in the rain. Everybody had gone to a Football Match on the Town ground, &amp; my progress was effected to the clamour of this cheering.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Hereford Times</hi> and the <hi rend="underline">Irish Times</hi> have published extracts of my Cathedral sermon. It is evident that the poor thing has drawn itself much public notice.</p>
         <p>I cast up my accounts for 1926, &amp; found that there was received &#x00A3;7,896.17.0, and paid out &#x00A3;8518.12.3: but of this &#x00A3;2000 was investment in war&#8211;loan, so that the net expenditure may be rather said to be &#x00A3;6,518.12.3, but there is half a year's income&#8211;tax yet to be paid. On the whole this is better than I had expected. The dilapidations next year, &amp; the new car this year, will require at least &#x00A3;2200, so I must still be as close&#8211;fisted as possible!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[316]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Newcastle, and formally presented to the Victoria Infirmary the Wireless Installation which had been provided by the students of Armstrong &amp; the Medical Colleges mainly by means of a notable "rag" in the streets of the City last June. The Lord Mayor presided, &amp; Lord Armstrong accepted the gift on behalf of the Hospital. I dined with Sir Thomas Oliver, to whom came also Lord &amp; Lady Armstrong, &amp; the sheriff of the City. I returned to Auckland after dinner, arriving home about 11.20 p.m. in the teeth of a considerable gale. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Turner</hi><hi rend="italic">, my admirable surgeon, was there, &amp; had some speech with me. He said I was looking well, but warned me against assuming that I was yet equal to my full work. I would </hi><hi rend="italic underline">like</hi><hi rend="italic"> to be able to interpret the mental imbecillity, under which I labour, to some extra&#8211;ordinary reason, but, as usual, my conscience hamstrings my desire! I enquired whether many men would be permanently unemployed in Newcastle, and I was assured that there must needs be many. It is thought that generally the men are returning to work in a good spirit. There seems to be much suspicion of the Government. The Prime Minister is suspected of an excessive sentimentalism where Labour is concerned, &amp; to be disinclined to any effective handling of the Trade Union question. Many of his followers are said to fear for their seats if the Trade Unions are touched. And broadly the notion is widely disseminated in "Society" that the devil of Revolution may be exorcised by kindness &amp; flattery. It is the greatest folly imaginable.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
