<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[337]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The cold snap continues, and the sinful earth is still draped in maiden white.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants including Lionel and James.</p>
         <p>Then I set to work on an article for the "Evening Standard", taking <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maycock</hi>'s book as a text. I headed it "<hi rend="underline">Whitewashing the Inquisition</hi>". It will make the Papists angry, but it is both just &amp; kindly expressed.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Observer</hi><hi rend="italic">" reports the death of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cornelia, Lady Wimborne</hi><hi rend="italic">. Her letters to me about her nephew, the Duke of Marlborough, express, perhaps, her last concern in religious matters. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I finished reading </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Samuel Butler</hi><hi rend="italic">'s "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Way of All Flesh</hi><hi rend="italic">". It contains much bitter wisdom, and not a little excellent humour: but its moral is unwholesome, &amp; it leaves a bad taste in the mouth. Then, being thoroughly idle, I read through again </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bradby</hi><hi rend="italic">'s admirable satire, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Chronicles of Dawnhope</hi><hi rend="italic">". The author, of course disowns any personal references, but it is none the less impossible to miss the origin of D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Tregarras, the headmaster. Bishop David of Liverpool is the obvious anti&#8211;type. His tall stature, his impulsiveness, his fondness for elaborate public functions in which he himself is the central figure, his fondness for novelties, his meddling with psycho&#8211;analysis, his lack of humour, &amp; facility of oracular speech – all mark him out as the true original of the description.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
