<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[374]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A thoroughly unsatisfactory day, in which little was done, and nothing done well. I revised the Edinburgh Article yet again.</p>
         <p>Wright and his Churchwarden came to lunch. They brought the plans of the projected new Church. I had some straight talk with Wright. He is a very sincere and unselfish fellow, but desperately narrow &amp; fanatical. After lunch I walked round the Park.</p>
         <p>The Archbishop of Canterbury writes to ask me to draft a prayer for the <hi rend="underline">Empire</hi>, for which Convocation has asked, and which the Bishops may possibly decide to insert. He mentions also the Preface. I drafted the following collect: –</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Almighty God, who rulest in the kingdom of men, and givest it to whomsoever Thou wilt, we thank Thee and praise Thy glorious name for that it hath pleased Thee to bring under the sceptre of Thy servant, our Sovereign Lord King George, a great dominion in all parts of the world, keep far from us all pride and selfish misuse of power, that, abiding in loyalty &amp; brotherly union, we may use aright Thy good gifts of freedom &amp; order to Thy glory and the welfare of mankind. Pour Thy blessing, we pray Thee, on all the nations of the British Empire. Grant wisdom to those who are called to exercise government therein, and to all the people thereof readiness to obey their godly commands. Hasten the day, we beseech Thee, when the work of righteousness shall be peace, and the effect of righteousness quietness and confidence for ever, through Jesus Christ our Lord, to Whom with Thee &amp; the Holy Ghost be glory &amp; dominion world without end. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
