<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[352]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked at the Lecture, and brought it to completion. It is woefully inadequate, but I have never quite succeeded in making up my mind as to what I really want to say! Thus the poor thing lacks unity and lucidity, the two things which are essential to a properly constructed lecture. However, it will have to serve my turn.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Watson&#8211;Armstrong, Lord Armstrong's son, with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Planta of British Columbia, came to lunch, and were shown over the Castle. Like most colonials, they expressed themselves vastly interested, and strangely ignorant.</p>
         <p>Then the Vicar of Escombe came to see me by appointment, and I had an interview which was by no means satisfactory. However, it was less annoying than I expected.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Watson&#8211;Armstrong has travelled in the Far East. He gave me an interesting account of Siam, which convicted me of much ignorance about that country, which I had supposed to be very backward. He assured me that it was almost the equal of Japan; that no less than 6000 miles of railway were open; that the Siamese were particularly adroit as air&#8211;men; &amp; that the foreign capitulations had been cancelled, so that Europeans were subject to Siamese law and law&#8211;courts. China now remains the only independent Oriental power, which has to endure the humiliation of having Europeans exempt from the native tribunals. Siamese Buddhism he described as a very latitudinarian religion.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
