<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[311]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received the copies of the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> for December 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1926, in which my article appeared. Rather to my annoyance, it was headed "Preaching Enmity by Poetry", instead of "The Miner as he sees himself", which was my own heading. Thus a hostile suggestion was made in the heading which was quite absent from the Article. I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wright, the author of "Down Under", &amp; pointed this out.</p>
         <p>I worked at an Article for "The Bishoprick" on "The Church of England, under George II and George V".</p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson came to tea. The sudden death of his partner, Cadle is a sharp blow for him. They had been friends since they were boys together at Durham School. It is the shadow on old age which grows ever deeper until the end.</p>
         <p>The "Times" has a short Report of my sermon. This is unusual, as that eminent organ does not often humble itself to publish what has already appeared in the provincial press. <hi rend="bold underline">From divers letters I gather that reports have appeared in other papers. It will hardly improve my relations with "Labour", but I cannot but think that it is a clear duty to be quite explicit on the subject of "peaceful picketing"</hi>. The sophistry by which that procedure is defended is as offensive to morality as it is intellectually contemptible. But the clergy, who have joined the Labour Party are in an ill case, being in a sense officially pledged to support their proceedings.  </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
