<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[335]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]When he (Wolsey) exchanged Durham for Winchester, he asked that the see which he vacated should be transferred to his son, a youth then studying in Paris.["]</p>
         <p>v. Acton. Historical Essays. p. 62</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Acton</hi> was a severe critick of his own church, so severe that his continuance in his own church puzzled his contemporaries, and constitutes a problem of which the solution is not easy to find. His review of Lea's "<hi rend="underline">History of the Inquisition of the Middle Ages</hi>" contributed to the <hi rend="underline">English Historical Review</hi> in 1888 and re&#8211;published in the volume "<hi rend="underline">History of Freedom &amp; Other Essays</hi>", is a notable illustration of his historical method. He draws a sharp distinction between the medieval institution, &amp; that which came into being at the Reformation. "<hi rend="italic underline">The later Inquisition, starting with the Spanish and developing into the Roman, is not so much a prolongation or a revival as a new creation</hi><hi rend="italic">. The medieval Inquisition strove to control States, and was an engine of government. The modern strove to coerce the Protestants, &amp; was an engine of war. One was subordinate, local, having a kind of headquarters in the house of Saint Dominic at Toulouse. The other was sovereign, universal, centred in the Pope, &amp; exercising its domination, not against obscure men without a literature, but against bishop and archbishop, nuncio and legate, primate and professor, against the general of the Capuchins &amp; the imperial preacher; against the first candidate in the conclave, and the president of the oecumenical council. Under altered conditions, the rules varied &amp; even principles were modified</hi>."</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
