<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[350]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"Mendacity and insincerity – in these I found the effects – the sure and only sure effects of an English university education." – Jeremy Bentham</p>
         <p>Bentham was at Oxford from 1760 to 1763. He boggled over signing the 39 Articles, &amp; evidently hated the place.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Lecture all the morning. Dick came to lunch, and shewed me the plans for the new church at Annefield Plain. This is his birthday: he is 32 years old today.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with old D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullagh. Two lads, aspirants for Ordination, came to see me, Needham and Kent. The first was a bricklayer's son, &amp; the last a clerk's. And yet people continue to speak of the Anglican clergy as forming a "class ministry". Both these lads pleased me: they seemed very manly fellows. </p>
         <p>Kenneth Hodgson came to see me. He finds difficulty in getting into Oxford. I don't think he realizes at all the probable cost of residence there. Nevertheless, I wrote to the Warden of Wadham, commending his application.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullagh, the Bishop of Gloucester, Miss Headlam, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Hedley &amp; her daughter came to dinner. Headlam looks very fit. He is evidently happy in the Bishop's life.</p>
         <p>The weather was mainly fine all day, but at eventide the wind began to rise, &amp; at nightfall it was blowing a gale. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
