<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[368]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A mild calm morning stirring dreams of domesticity in the rooks. But I had a restless night, and carried into the following day a great weight of more or less formulated worry. "<hi rend="underline">Why art thou so heavy, O my soul? and, why art thou so disquieted within me? I will put my trust in God, for he is the help of my countenance, and my God</hi>." </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but six communicants including James. After breakfast I wrote to William. Beyond that I did nothing useful, and then walked in the Park with Ella for an hour after she had returned from church. Our conversation was more animated than amicable! I became morally dishevelled, a state in which to preach acceptably is not in the power of man. However, "time and tide wait for no man", and preach I must, though my Christian profession hang upon me in tatters!</p>
         <p>For my sermon I chose one which, perhaps, more than any other, was fitted to provide the materials for melancholy self&#8211;criticism. Its subject was the light cast on the true meaning of Christianity by the names which the followers of Christ came to bear in the world: and the text was formed from the two passages: S. John xv.15 and Acts xi.26. The first records that the Lord called the Twelve his "<hi rend="underline">friends</hi>": &amp; the last tells us that the "<hi rend="underline">disciples</hi>" were first called "<hi rend="underline">Christians</hi>" at Antioch. The sermon seemed to be fitting as an introduction to the Season of Lent, when the practical aspects of the Christian profession are emphasized. </p>
         <p>I motored to Evenwood for Evensong at 6 p.m. The church was not much more than half filled, but it was explained to me that the parish was enduring a very severe visitation of influenza. The parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Richardson</hi>, had but recently been vaccinated, &amp; was feeling the effects. This circumstance added to an attack of influenza reduced him to an unhappy condition. However he read the prayers, and I read the lesson, and preached. He told me that he was going through the Composite book with his people, and liked it much. I think the main body of the parish clergy will be well contented, but the conflicting extremes are in revolt. The question is, how far do they have a following in the country. In the Assembly they are vocal enough.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
