<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[367]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[']I remember, when a boy, sitting on the shore of the Lake of Geneva with Prince Gortschakoff, the Russian Chancellor, his sons and young nieces. We had been discussing Mommsen and Gibbon. One of us had remarked that, at any rate, our civilization was secure from barbarian invasion. The old Chancellor, who had listened in silence, suddenly said: "<hi rend="underline">Do not believe it. The invaders of our civilization will be the proletariat: our fall will be greater than that of Rome or Babylon</hi>". We were not far from the home of Voltaire, and a volume of Tourgenieff was lying on the grass at our feet.[']</p>
         <p>Lord Esher in Manchester Guardian, Feb. 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1927</p>
         <p>I read through the chapter headed "Continuation of the History of the Church in the Nineteenth Century", which Stubbs added to his edition of Mosheim's History. It is written in a spirit of bigoted Tractarianism, and reads oddly enough now after the lapse of over 60 years. His disgust of Dissent, and horror of "Liberalism" are almost comical.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with Lionel. A football match between a Ferryhill team and S. Anne's, Bishop Auckland was proceeding in the Outer Park, while the Inner Park was enlivened by a Hockey Match between a team of soldiers from Catterick and the Bishop Auckland team. A good many golfers were busy on the links. So the Park presented a scene of much athletic activity. The weather was mild and still.</p>
         <p>I received back from the Reporters the M.S. of my Lecture, and sent it forthwith to the Registrar of Armstrong College for printing.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
