<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[327]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A brilliant morning with a white frost. I received the Holy Communion in the private chapel at 8.15 a.m. The Bishop celebrated. He adopted the "evangelical summary" of the Ten Commandments, and read <hi rend="underline">both</hi> the prayers after the administration. Also, after reading the formula of administration once aloud, he used the first half of it severally as he ministered the sacrament. All these innovations on the prescribed Order are, of course, quite illegal. <hi rend="underline">Quis custodiet</hi>?</p>
         <p>We had much talk at breakfast about Confirmation. <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Temple</hi> 
<hi rend="italic bold underline">said that he was ever thankful that his father had confirmed him when he was 12 years old</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">While everybody went to church, I remained in the house, and wrote to Ella and Arthur. Then I spent an hour in going through the Collects, Epistles, and Gospels for Black&#8211;Letter Saints, which have been referred to the Literary Committee. I don't see why we should provide "Commons" for Bishops, Abbots, Virgins, and martyrs which are all normal types. Why not limit ourselves to the types of extraordinary service – Martyrs, Missionaries, Doctors, and Saints. The last description is, of course, properly general: but the Church has so long recognized a class of super&#8211;saints, whom it designates "Saints" in the Calendar, that we must regard the word as technical. In point of fact all the names in the Calendar can be gathered under these descriptions of extraordinary service. If "bishops", why not "priests", and even "deacons"? Why not "kings" &amp; other laymen?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[328]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Several people came to lunch, including M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ryle. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Anderson of Waverley Abbey, and an officer named Capper. The last was governor of Guernsey, when the King visited the island, and he gave an entertaining account of the visit. He appears to be an authority on flying. He said that Great Britain and the Empire were at a great disadvantage by reason of their geographical situation. After the luncheon party had dispersed, the Bishop, Temple, and I went for a walk. The fine weather made this most enjoyable. Our conversation was frank and friendly, so much so that one had difficulty in realizing the width of our divergence on almost all questions of policy in Church and State. "<hi rend="underline">Let love be without hypocrisy</hi>" says S. Paul, and, perhaps, a rigid application of his words to social intercourse would desolate society. It must suffice that we make no secret from one another of our divergences, and maintain the standard of honour in our treatment of one another. For the rest, we may enjoy as fully as we can whatsoever in one another is enjoyable. The Bishop of Winchester and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Woods are admirable hosts: the castle is excellently appointed: &amp; the hospitality is generous without being either excessive or ostentatious. It is indeed lamentable that Farnham is so soon to be deserted, &amp; left to desolation. </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
