<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The glorious weather continues. After breakfast I went into Southampton, &amp; had my hair cut etc. Then I fell in with <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>, &amp; walked along the sea&#8211;front with him for half an hour. His mighty aspect, rollicking gait, &amp; explosions of hilarious laughter arrest much public attention as he parades the streets! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me at the railway station, where we fell in with <persName xml:id="3427">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> De Horsey</persName> &amp; her family. She was Cicely Lang when last I saw her!
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We travelled to Winchester, in </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">order to put up with <persName xml:id="691">Archdeacon Fearon</persName></hi>. Here we found the <persName xml:id="2047">Bishop of Worcester</persName> &amp; Miss Yeatman Biggs: also <persName xml:id="3428" display="no">Richmond</persName>. These are all suffragists! We attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; afterwards walked round the great Church under the guidance of the Archdeacon. A young lady recognized me &amp; pointed me out to her father who forthwith introduced himself as the Church&#8211;warden of the English Church at the Hague! A rather dilapidated parson came up, &amp; claimed acquaintance as 'having known me at Oxford': but him I could nowise recall!<persName xml:id="3426"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic">Causton</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Master of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cross, asked me if I could tell him what the letters H.S.E. meant on a tombstone! And he has lived among monuments for years!!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
