<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I attended Holy Communion in the Lady Chapel of the Cathedral, &amp; received the Sacrament from the hands of my <persName xml:id="691">excellent host</persName>. Nothing could exceed the beauty of the place, or the comforting solemnity of the service.
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3429">Canon Vaughan</persName> showed me the Chapter Library. There are not many treasures, but some objects of great interest. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3430">Bishop Morton's</persName> [Morley] books are there preserved in their own original bookshelves</hi>.
         </p>
         <p>
We all went into Southampton in order to hear the President's address. <hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="105">Bishop Talbot</persName> was in good voice. The occasion lent itself to his distinctive style of speaking – slow, sonorous, oracular. He was assisted by the sympathetic appreciation of his hearers: &amp; sate down after discoursing for an hour amid loud applause.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
We dined with the Bishop &amp; <persName xml:id="106">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Talbot</persName> at the Deanery. I sate next <persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName> at the table.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I took the chair at a distinctly rowdy meeting of the </hi><orgName xml:id="263"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Anti–Female Suffrage Society</hi></orgName><hi rend="italic">. <persName xml:id="3431">Arnold Ward</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3432">Miss Gladys Pott</persName> were the speakers. The suffragists attended in force, &amp; interrupted freely. However the meeting was judged a success.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
