<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I went into Southampton &amp; attended the Congress, while <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> with our combined baggage went to London from Winchester. As I was designing to catch the noonday train, the <persName xml:id="1123">Bishop</persName> asked me to speak before <persName xml:id="3434"><hi rend="bold underline">Morel</hi></persName>. <hi rend="italic bold underline">I spoke for about 8 minutes on the question of securing fair treatment for aborigines. My speech was very well received. </hi>Then I hastened off to the station, &amp; journed [sic] to Waterloo. I spent the afternoon in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> writing letters. There I saw &amp; conversed with <persName xml:id="3435">Birkbeck</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName>. The last was flushed with victory in a successful chapter&#8211;meeting. Then I went to King's Cross, &amp; joined Ella. While waiting for her, I fell in with <persName xml:id="3436">Stewart</persName> of Cambridge. He had just arrived from abroad, where he had seen <persName xml:id="1083">Loisy</persName>. We travelled comfortably enough to Durham, and were welcomed at the Deanery pleasantly by the maids, clamourously by the dog.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The 'Westminster Gazette' has a leader on the text of last night's discussion. The "Times" &amp; "Morning Post" give rather special prominence to <ref xml:id="735">my speech</ref>. The "Newcastle Daily Journal" does the same.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
