<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName> walked with me to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles's, and there we were shown the new Chapel of the <orgName xml:id="269">Thistle</orgName>. It is very small, &amp; contains 19 stalls viz: one (raised) for the King, and on either side 16 for the Knights. Facing the King's stall is the Chair of Admission, a Lectern, &amp; a seat for the <persName xml:id="1139">Dean of the Thistle</persName>. The carving is very elaborate &amp; beautiful: and the stained glass of the window is pleasing.</p>
         <p>
Then we returned to the house, &amp; lunched together, after which we bade one another farewell, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">I went off to Newcastle, where I arrived about 5 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p>
I presided in St James's Congregational Church over a meeting designed to commemorate the centenary of the local branch of the <orgName xml:id="115">London Missionary Society</orgName>. The two speakers were <persName xml:id="3480">Principal Ritchie</persName>, a former minister of the church, and <persName xml:id="3481">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Piggott</persName>, the co–adjutor of <persName xml:id="323">Sylvester Horne</persName>. It was curious to notice how the latter had picked up Horne's tricks of speech and action. In the course of the proceedings three deputations from other missionary societies were introduced. Of these one was from the <orgName xml:id="124">Church Missionary Society</orgName> – <persName xml:id="3483">Canon Hamer</persName>. After the meeting I went back to Durham, arriving about 10.30 p.m. I found <persName xml:id="542">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gow</persName> at the Deanery.</p>
 
            </body></text></TEI>
