<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>The end crowns all,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And that old common arbitrator, Time,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Will one day end it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Troilus &amp; Cressida. Act iv. Sc. V</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <div type="quote">
         
<hi>'So teach us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.'</hi>
         
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>Twenty five years ago on Advent Sunday I was instituted Vicar of Barking. How well I remember the events of that day! I recall the sentiments with which I received the spiritual charge of a great parish, and perforce I ask myself whether &amp; how far those sentiments have held their place in my mind through the changes of a quarter of a century. Assuredly, &amp; for good reason, I have lost much of the courage which then took small account of any difficulties. I have learned the truth of Shakespeare's words.</hi></p>
         
<div type="verse">
         
         <p>
<hi>But something may be done that we will not:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And sometimes we are devils to ourselves.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>When we will tempt the frailty of our powers,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Presuming on their changeful potency.</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>I have lost much of my self&#8211;confidence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I attended Mattins, &amp; afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion. The <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> preached a long rambling discourse, apparently extemporaneous. He has a vast accumulation of miscellaneous information in his mind, and it is always excitingly uncertain what particular fragments will be disclosed. One idea suggests another, &amp;, as he has no plan or scheme, he moves ever farther from his original starting point until the wretched hearer is asphyxiated by irrelevancy. As the text determines the start, so the clock compels the finish of this kaleidoscope of disconnected notions. But even this seemed tolerable beside the childish inanities of the afternoon preacher, whose discourse was barely adequate to a Mothers' meeting. Yet the preacher, <persName xml:id="3507">Bishop Taylor Smith</persName>, is reckoned one of the Leaders of the Evangelical party. Need one enquire farther for the reason why that party is prostrate and powerless?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An undergraduate of University College, Salter, who is chairman of the local branch of the <orgName xml:id="275" display="no">Students Volunteer Movement</orgName> came to tea, &amp; then expounded the meaning &amp; method of his organization. I made a considerable effort to appear sympathetic, but truly I was impressed neither by the man, nor by the movement.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
