<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. At 10 a.m. the Ordination was held. There were many priests ordained. <hi rend="bold underline">The sermon was preached by the Rev</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3495">A.C. Fraser</persName>, Vicar of St. Bede's, Sunderland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The preacher &amp; one of the newly ordained priests, Denham, a nephew of an old Oxford friend of mine, came to lunch. I attended Evensong in the cathedral. <persName xml:id="3494">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harriss</persName>, the Vicar of S. Andrew's, Oxford, preached.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After Service the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> came into the Deanery: &amp; I asked him to compose some stanzas to be asserted in Milton's paraphrase of Psalm 136, to match the occasion of our Commemoration on Jan</hi><hi rend="i sup u">ry</hi> <hi rend="italic">27</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">. This he readily undertook.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In conversation the Bishop expressed his great regret that he had never enjoyed the opportunity of receiving the Holy Sacrament in the Scottish Church. This interested me greatly, for too commonly it is the case that Evangelicals, who would readily admit Presbyterians to communion, do themselves shrink from receiving the Communion from Presbyterians.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
