<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Luke's Day, Saturday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A beautiful bright day. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m.
         </p>
         <p>
At 11 a.m. there was a Chapter Meeting – all present and in an amicable mood.
         </p>
         <p>
After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to Sherburn, &amp; attending the first part of the function of opening the new Aged Miners' Homes. <persName xml:id="3464">Lord Joicey</persName> officiated. We went to Lumley, and left cards on <persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarbrough</persName>. Then we returned in time to receive <persName xml:id="1907">Sir Aleck</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1908">Lady Lawrence</persName>, who came to spend the week end.
         </p>
         <p>
At 6 p.m. I motored out again to Sherburn, &amp; made a speech to a very crowded schoolroom full of mining folk. <persName xml:id="3137">John Wilson</persName> was in the Chair. I spoke more gravely than perhaps, the occasion suggested, taking for my theme the present unrest among working people, &amp; pressing some lessons of history as indispensable if the progress of society was to continue. The people listened very attentively: &amp; applauded with much appearance of sincerity. They seemed to understand that I was speaking in a serious spirit, on an urgent matter. <hi rend="underline">John Wilson</hi> was, I think, genuinely pleased.
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
