<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Eleven years ago &#8211; Oct. 20</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1902 &#8211; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were married in Westminster Abbey. We are today what those years have made us. It is a well&#8211;nigh impossible thing to travel back, and recall, the vague hopes &amp; expectations which filled my mind as I knelt beside my wife before the Altar, which had witnessed my vows &amp; hers. We know now that our home is to be empty of the best things that make home. That black day in January casts a chill over my heart still. It is not yet clear to me how best to handle so great a catastrophe. We have been much together at home, &amp; abroad: &amp; I suppose there are no discoveries to be made by either of us into the other's character. This transition from Westminster to Durham has opened a new chapter, and the nature of that chapter's contents are yet hidden. Death has been busy among those who were together in the Abbey at our marriage. <persName xml:id="296">Duckworth</persName> is dead. Ella's <persName xml:id="584">parents</persName><persName xml:id="828"></persName> are both dead. <persName xml:id="290">Charles Parker</persName>, from whose house we were married, is dead, <persName xml:id="570">Edith Bruce</persName> is dead: &amp; <persName xml:id="287">Colonel Gore&#8211;Booth</persName>: also his brother <persName xml:id="3471">Henry</persName>. Ella is almost destitute of relations now, as I always was. We are curiously alone in the world, with a widening circle of acquaintances, and only a collection of epitaphs for friends!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[29]</hi> 
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1907">Aleck Lawrence</persName> went off by the early train. He is a strange bundle of radical shibboleths &amp; shallow altruisms. If only there were some sense of the gravity of things in these young fools!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I travelled to Edinburgh</hi> by the afternoon express, arriving about 6 p.m., and drove at once to 39 Palmerston Place, where <persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName> received me with his accustomed kindness. He had arranged a dinner party in my honour. There were <persName xml:id="3472">Henderson</persName>, ex&#8211;Moderator of the U.F. Church, <persName xml:id="1140">Patterson</persName>; <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName>; <persName xml:id="3473" display="no">Mackintosh</persName>; <persName xml:id="1141" display="no">Weir</persName>; <persName xml:id="2497">Rankin</persName>; and one other. We 'reason'd high' of many things, &amp; passed an agreeable evening.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">How strange to me is this passion for ecclesiastical independence, which these Presbyterians profess, &amp; quite evidently feel! Here is their tiny sect, set in a corner of Christendom, &amp; conspicuously marked by local features which a sympathetic student of Scottish history must needs regard with indulgence &amp; even respect, but which an intelligent &amp; educated man cannot help seeing to be practical defects; &amp; here are its members using the lofty language about it which was extravagant on the lips of the Medieval Pope, who was held by an united Christendom to be </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Vice&#8211;Deus</hi><hi rend="italic">! The men are quite serious; &amp; cannot perceive the grotesque impression which they make on an observer's mind.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
