<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>It is only when feeling has ceased to accompany a creed that it becomes fixed, &amp; verbal departures from it are counted heresy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3491">'Mark Rutherford'</persName></hi>
         </p>   
</div>
         
         <p>
I received a letter from the Mayor thanking me for yesterday's service. A short extract from the sermon appeared in the <ref xml:id="769">'Times'</ref>.
         </p>
         <p>
I presided at a special meeting of the Chapter convened to consider the <persName xml:id="648">Architects'</persName> reports on the Fabric. We came to the decision to request them to take counsel together, and present us with their united recommendations. Thus we followed the example of the Chapter of S. Paul's, postponing &amp; perhaps evading the difficulty which we shrank from facing. 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The Durham Cathedral Statutes provide short prayers to be used daily by the <orgName xml:id="234">Grammar School</orgName> boys. One prayer is the following:
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Sancta Maria, Virgo et Mater Jesu Christi, age cum Filio Tuo ut haec schola quotidie proficiat in Ipso, ut omnes pueri in eadem discant Ipsum, ut erudiantur in Ipso, tandem ut perfecfi filii Dei fiant per Ipsum, et Tu quoque Jesu benignissime age cum Patre Tuo et Patre nostro, ut gratia Sui Spiritus nos suos Filiolos faciat sic Te Jesu discere et imitari in hoc seculo ut una tecum feliciter regnemus in futuro. Amen.</hi><note xml:id="168" n="1"></note>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2820">Bishop Cosin</persName> in 1665 issued injunctions to the Dean &amp; Chapter. Among these is the following:&#8211;
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'That country Curats be no longer suffered to preach the Prebendaries' courses'.</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
This injunction was not effectual for in 1671 Isaac Basire answers to the Bishop's Articles of Inquiry:
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'that the Cathedral Sermons are frequently supplied by Curates &amp; others, contrary to Canon xliii &amp; li, &amp; to the Lord Bishop's former Injunctions.'</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
        
            </body></text></TEI>
