<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol] [symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A disposition to preserve, and an ability to improve, taken together, would be my standard of a statesman. Everything else is vulgar in the conception, perilous in the execution.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2486">Burke</persName>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>I attended the Chapter meeting at 11 a.m. We appointed <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName> to the Rectory at Edmundbyers not without hesitation for his means are narrow and the income of the benefice is not large. However he is clearly anxious to go, &amp; it is difficult to see what living in our gift w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> suit him better. <hi rend="italic">We discussed the Report on our Electric Light Systems, &amp; in the course of the discussion (moved thereto by some very exasperating &amp; characteristic </hi><hi rend="italic underline">obiter dicta</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName>) I 'let myself go' in a vehement declaration to the Chapter on the subject of our dilapidations' arrangement. If the legality were disputed, let legal advice be forthwith taken: but if not, then let there be an end of hintings of conduct which was really dishonest. I would not permit any allusion of the kind. We were not a thieves' kitchen, in which alone such corrupt jestings were suitable! The Chapter was startled, &amp; silent!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
