<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">All Souls Day, 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
All–merciful God, I thank Thee for the long–suffering patience which has permitted me to reach this hour, for the unmerited bounty which has filled my life with manifold powers &amp; opportunities, for the persistent love which has followed me all these many years, &amp; I beseech Thee to give me a true repentance for my sins, &amp; grace to re–order the remainder of my life according to Thy holy Will. Grant me the Guidance of Thy Spirit that I may see the path of my duty, &amp; give me the desire to walk therein unto the end through Jesus Christ our Lord.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There was a good congregation in <orgName xml:id="61">S. Mary's</orgName>, even the undergraduates' gallery had a well–filled aspect. I preached on two passages – "The Kingdom of God cometh not with observation &amp;c" and "Mind not high things, but condescend to things that are lowly". The sermon occupied 45 minutes in delivery, &amp; was very well listened to. In the congregation I noticed <persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName>. Subsequently I heard that </hi><persName xml:id="553"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> <hi rend="italic">Headlam</hi></persName>, <persName xml:id="2142"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Oman</hi></persName>, <hi rend="italic">&amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Davis were present, and all approved the sermon.</hi> <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="41">Davis</persName> were there, &amp; they also were friendly.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi> [symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1008"><hi rend="underline">Simon</hi></persName> asked me to motor out to Fritwell, &amp; see his house. Accordingly a party consisting of <persName xml:id="2709">Robinson</persName>, <persName xml:id="2046">Brand</persName>, <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName>, &amp; I, went with him. We lunched in his charming Elizabethan home, which he has furnished with excellent taste. His two daughters, young girls growing long in the limb, were at lunch, &amp; afterwards showed us the ponies, the garden, &amp; the 'museum'. We motored back, arriving in college about 4.30 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> asked me to advise him as to the publication of a history of the Church of Scotland which he has prepared</hi>. It is, as far as I could judge, excellently written, &amp; I urged him to make no delay in arranging for its publication. There was a great party at dinner, no less than 57. As the Gaudy fell on Sunday there were no songs, save the Mallard Song, once sung in Hall. Simon, as Sub–warden, proposed the usual speeches: &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">he made me respond for the Quondams</hi>, together with <persName xml:id="1131">Ridley</persName>. I made a little foolish speech.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner I had some talk with <persName xml:id="2719">Williams</persName>, &amp; advised him to decline the offer of the Balliol chaplaincy, &amp; devote the remainder of his fellowship period to equipping himself for his career as a clergyman.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Also I </hi><hi rend="italic underline">almost</hi><hi rend="italic"> promised Robinson that I would write a weekly article or leader for the Times.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
