<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.  Edinburgh.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I wrote letters most part of the morning, leaving myself no more time for lunch than was sufficient for a brief glimpse of Princes Street, which looked very winning in the bright autumnal sun.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="268">Scottish Society for reforming the National Morals.</orgName> The room was full, &amp; the people were plainly in earnest: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but as usual I received the impression of pharisaic fatuity, which always seems to shadow movements of social reform</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I contributed a rather depressing little speech, which (I may judge from the aspect of the company) was not well liked. <persName xml:id="2499" display="no">Lang</persName>, a brother of the <persName xml:id="130">Abp. of York</persName>, read a sensible paper, the effect of which was greatly impaired by the pompous method of the reader.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The public meeting in the U.F. Assembly Hall was fairly attended, but the proportion of the ministers &amp; women seemed to me excessive. <persName xml:id="3474">Lord Salveson</persName> presided. The first speaker was <persName xml:id="3478" display="no">Buckland</persName>m who descanted on the evils of the press rather wearisomely. Then came <persName xml:id="3479">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> McKirdy</persName>, the author of <ref xml:id="737">"The Soul Market"</ref>, who spoke shortly after the manner of women. She was followed by <persName xml:id="2113">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Saleeby</persName>, who took for his theme what he called "race poisons". He spoke for about half an hour very lucidly and effectively. When he sate down, I was called upon, and <hi rend="bold">[31] </hi>delivered myself of a foolish screed on "The Problem of Leisure". I had prepared somewhat ample notes, which saved my oration from complete incoherency, but on no possible shewing could it be looked upon as a great performance. However it was well listened to, &amp;, when I sate down, there was considerable applause.
         </p>
        
            </body></text></TEI>
