<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The papers are more than usually interesting. <persName xml:id="234"><hi rend="underline">Lloyd George</hi></persName> opens his "Land campaign" or "Land crusade" by orations at Bedford, which will add nothing to his reputation.<note xml:id="229" n="1"></note> They are verbose, violent, &amp; practically void beyond even his own precedents! <persName xml:id="3451">Redmond</persName> repudiates <persName xml:id="2441">Winston Churchill's</persName> suggestion of separate treatment for Ireland.         
</p>
         <p>
A liner is reported to be burned at sea: most of the passengers (foreign emigrants) were saved by a small fleet of steamers summoned by wireless telegraphy.<note xml:id="230" n="2"></note>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[19]</hi> 
[symbol]
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Politics &amp; the Pulpit are terms that have little agreement</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">No sound ought to be heard in the church but the healing voice of Christian charity</hi><hi rend="italic">. The cause of civil liberty &amp; civil government gains as little as that of religion by this confusion of duties. Those who quit their proper character to assume what does not belong to them are, for the greater part, ignorant both of the character they leave &amp; of the character they assume. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Wholly unacquainted with the world, in which they are so fond of meddling, &amp; inexperienced in all its affairs, on which they pronounce with so much confidence, they have nothing of politics but the passions they excite</hi><hi rend="italic">. Surely the church is a place where one day's truce ought to be allowed to the dissensions &amp; animosities of mankind.</hi>

         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2486">Burke</persName>, <ref xml:id="349">'Reflections'</ref>, Works, III, p. 246
         </p>
         
</div>
            
         
         
            </body></text></TEI>
