<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day has been grievously wasted mostly in correcting proofs, &amp; writing letters.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Times" publishes two letters on the Kikuyu Conference</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi rend="bold underline">the belated one from the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName></hi>: and
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="bold underline">one from <persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName>, associating himself directly with <persName xml:id="2174">Bishop Willis's</persName> action</hi>.
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We dined with Bp. Tucker in order to meet Bp. Willis. I had a good deal of conversation with the latter on this Kikuyu business. He tells me that he is about to visit the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName>. This of course is the familiar procedure. It will be interesting to see whether he is strong enough to withstand the 'lobbying' skill of Bishop Talbot.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I inquired as to the Roman Catholics in Uganda, who already exceed the Protestants in number, though, owing to their inferior education, they do not equal them in influence. Of the 20 paramount chiefs, 11 are Protestant: 8 are Roman Catholic, &amp; 1 is Mohammedan. The Romans are much better staffed, having 2 bps &amp; 300 priests, as against 1 Anglican bp. &amp; 100 other workers, clerical &amp; lay including many females! Mohammedanism is failing mainly through its contempt of education.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
