<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Canterbury.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I lay in bed until nearly noon, feeling wretched enough. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I lunched with the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>, &amp; took him for a walk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We talked of the incident in East Africa, which has exercised the mind of <persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His Grace is fearfully cautious</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; emphasises the risks of High Church secessions. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But he said that he personally had no kind of objection to intercommunion</hi><hi rend="italic">. At present he is awaiting a correct &amp; detailed account of the facts. We discussed the grave inadequacy of the clergy, &amp; he said that after 35 years' experience of Ordination candidates, he was persuaded that, while the level of sincerity &amp; devotion was more than maintained, there was a marked absence of really able men. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He said of <persName xml:id="276">Moule</persName> that he was the most absolutely useless person in conference he had ever met. He contributed nothing to the episcopal counsels. He denied that the cost of prosecutions was a factor in determining the bishops not to prosecute; but admitted that the diocese of Durham might be an exception. He agreed that the outlook in the matter of female suffrage was hopelessly dark. <persName xml:id="404">Mrs Davidson</persName> is herself a suffragist!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Canon &amp; Mrs Vernon came in to tea: and the Hugenot pastor <persName xml:id="2363">M. Barnabas</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I preached in the Cathedral to a very large congregation but my voice was raucous &amp; hateful to hear, &amp; the exertion was certainly very great. I had chosen the sermon as congruous with the melancholy festivities of one's birthday: my theme was the mortality of man, &amp; his potency of immortality, &amp;, after my frequent custom, I chose a double text &#8211; "What is your life?" and "He that doeth the will of God abideth forever". The Abp. occupied his throne. <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> &amp; 3 canons were also present.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Monday the 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> we went to London, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> put up with the <persName xml:id="2938">Webbes</persName><persName xml:id="2939"></persName>, &amp; I with the <persName xml:id="636">Pearces</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The next day, Tuesday 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I travelled to Durham, and there occupied myself with writing many letters.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
