<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I attended the early Celebration, &amp; communicated. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> celebrated: there were present 3 canons, &amp; 3 minor canons. 
         </p>
         <p>
At Mattins there was a fine show of clergy. The whole Corporation of Dean &amp; 5 canons was present: all the 4 minor canons: 2 honorary canons: and the 2 schoolmasters, a total of 14 clergymen, 2 Bishops &amp; 12 priests. <persName xml:id="2533">The Bishop of Jarrow</persName> preached. I noted no less than 8 quotations, all familiar tags, in the course of his sermon.
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> &amp; I took a turn in the Banks before lunch.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName> came to lunch, &amp; made himself very interesting with stories of his experiences in Uganda.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
At Evensong there was a much smaller congregation than I expected, a much longer anthem than I approved, &amp; a much larger exodus after the Anthem than I liked! 
<hi rend="italic">Thus to an exiguous congregation I delivered a dull discourse on drunkenness, which would certainly exasperate total abstainers without kindling the enthusiasm of anybody. </hi>I had no voice, &amp; little energy. When we came out of the Cathedral, rain was falling rather heavily.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1178" display="no">Clarence Stock</persName>, <persName xml:id="2936">Boden</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1314" display="no">Gabrielsson</persName> accompanied me to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's where I preached to a full church. The rain hindered many people from coming to the service, which was none the less hearty &amp; devout.
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
