<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[67]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>I was engaged in writing a letter to the "Times" in answer to a long screed from the <persName xml:id="3490">Bishop of Kensington</persName>, when a telegram was brought in to me. <hi rend="italic bold underline">It was from <persName xml:id="3504">Lady Anne Lambton</persName> inquiring whether I should be at home at 2.30 p.m., and stating that the Queen would call at that time</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was already close on noon: <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had gone off to Bishop Auckland to open a Bazaar</hi>. I sent two telegrams, one to say that I should be on the spot at the time mentioned, the other to recall Ella.</p>
         <p>The Royal Party arrived in 4 motors, the Queen's being distinguished by a small flag. I received H.M. at the door, &amp; led her into the Deanery. Ella received her at the entrance to the drawing room. I showed her the King's room, the library, the kitchen, the Cathedral, &amp; then led her to the Castle, where I handed her over to <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>. The Queen was very pleasant &amp; energetic. <hi rend="bold underline">She mentioned <ref xml:id="754" display="no">my letter</ref> in the "Times", &amp; expressed her agreement with it. I was surprised &amp; gratified that she remembered our conversation at Windsor, and referred to it </hi><hi rend="underline">accurately</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, which indicated a point beyond the conventional coaching</hi>! I contracted a chill in the course of the afternoon, for though H.M. most considerately bade me put on my hat, the mischief <hi rend="bold">[68]</hi> had been done already. I caused a telegram to be sent to <persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarborough</persName>, with whom we were engaged to dine, excusing myself, and went forthwith to bed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>Charles II sent the D. &amp; C. a letter dated May 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1671 recommending Robert Collingwood to be register ('a fitt person for that employment we reflecting upon his &amp; his ffamilies loyalty to us &amp; our Royall Ffather of blessed memory &amp; their sufferings thereby')</p>
         <p>The D. &amp; Chapter were perplexed what to do, for M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Collingwood was totally destitute of qualifications, &amp; had moreover little intention of performing the duties; &amp; they had an excellent man, Robert Hedley, who had been 40 years in their service, &amp; whom they wished to appoint as Registrar.</p>
         <p>After attempting to effect an arrangement by which the office could be conferred on Collingwood &amp; the work done by Hedley as his deputy &#8211; an arrangement which was upset by Hedley's absolute refusal to serve under Collingwood &#8211; they petitioned the King to recall his nomination. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Carleton, holder of the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> prebendary, recorded his protest against this proceeding as disrespectful to the King, &amp; unfair to Collingwood.</p>
         <p>In this petition they point out the total unfitness of Collingwood, &amp; the special claims of Hedley ('who hath been brought up in the Office above 40 years, &amp; hath been allwaies loyall to your Majestie &amp; serviceable to the Church on many occasions both during the late rebellion in preserving their records with great peril to himself, and before &amp; since in assisting them to manage their evidences &amp;c.).</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p>This action was successful. The King recalled his commendation of Collingwood, &amp; suffered the Dean &amp; Chapter to appoint a man in whom they had confidence. </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
