<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
[symbol]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A bright morning after the rain. I was fetched in a motor to the episcopal palace to breakfast with the <persName xml:id="3489">Bishop</persName> &amp; his family. The palace is a large plain house built rather more than a century ago, &amp; surrounded by about 18 acres of garden &amp; meadow. In the grounds are the ruins of a large episcopal castle. After breakfast I was taken to see the cathedral, a building largely restored, mostly in the early Gothic style. I was particularly pleased with the Chapter House, &amp; the Norman arch behind the altar. There are a good many tombs with recumbent figures of bishops &amp; others. The cathedral is but modestly endowed. There is &#x00A3;700 a year for the Dean, &amp; &#x00A3;350 apiece for the four canons. I had much conversation with the Bishop who strikes me as a dull man, but well&#8211;intentioned. I returned to Cardiff about 11.30 a.m: &amp; walked with <persName xml:id="346">Henderson</persName>. <hi rend="italic bold underline">We called on <persName xml:id="522">Drane</persName>, &amp; were received most graciously. He insisted on our drinking some sweet wine which he called "Sion"; &amp; shewed us some of his treasures</hi><hi rend="italic">. But we had to hurry off, in order that there might be time for lunch before my departure.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I travelled to Oxford by a train which left Cardiff at 1.42 p.m. &amp; arrived at Oxford at 5.35 p.m. after changing at Bristol &amp; Didcot.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42] </hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
At Swindon a young man got in to the carriage, and speedily entered into conversation. He had been in the Army, but had left it because he could not live on his pay as an officer. Now he was an engineer. <hi rend="bold underline">He said that to his knowledge many officers had pledged themselves to send in their papers, &amp; join the Ulstermen, if there was trouble in Ulster</hi>. We talked of the state of the Army. He testified to the general sobriety of the officers, but said that betting &amp; gambling were common &amp; increasing. 
         </p>
         <p>
I dined in Hall. The portraits of <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> are in position, &amp; make a great addition to the interest of the collection of pictures. <persName xml:id="652">Compton</persName> is full of life &amp; fun, but his increasing deafness makes conversation difficult. I had a considerable discussion with <persName xml:id="2709">Robinson</persName> about things in general. <hi rend="italic bold underline">He asked me to undertake leader writing for the "Times": &amp; I promised to consider the matter: but I doubt whether I have the gift, and I am sure that I have not the time</hi><hi rend="italic">. However, in these evil days, it would be something to have a second string to one's bow in the event of a catastrophe, which might throw one on the world without resources. As things are moving, there is little security of tenure in an Anglican Deanery. I came to the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> about 11 p.m. &amp; then talked till midnight with him, and <persName xml:id="65">Lord Chelmsford</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
