<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[104]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
<hi>O Cleanse Thy Servant from presumptuous sins lest they get the dominion over me. So shall I be undefiled, &amp; innocent from the great offence, O Lord, my Strength &amp; my Redeemer.</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I celebrated at 8 a.m. The Masters &amp; boys of the School communicated &#8211; a moving sight. Why cannot I realize the greatness of my m&#x00E9;tier here, &amp; leave all the outside affairs to the Fanaticks?  I should be happier, more intelligible, &amp; probably more useful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> preached at Mattins &#8211; an extemporaneous sermon, wholly hortatory. 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[105]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I determined to preach in Oxford on <ref xml:id="755">'Kikuyu'</ref></hi><hi rend="italic">: and in the course of Tuesday &amp; Wednesday actually succeeded in composing a sermon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
On Wednesday afternoon, I opened the new County Girls' School. <persName xml:id="3455">Jevons</persName> presided, &amp; there was a considerable muster of officials, parents, teachers, &amp; girls. <hi rend="bold underline">The burden of my speech was an onslaught on the Examinations system</hi>. I urged that girls under 16 should be exempt from external examination. On Friday, 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> January, I presided at a lecture on the Canadian Rockies given by the <orgName xml:id="271">Victoria League</orgName>. The lady who delivered hailed from Durham. She said that she remembered meeting us in the Hotel at Banff four years ago. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> professed to remember the fact, so that I had perforce to assume the correctness of the lady's claim to be 'an old friend'.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I decided to publish the <ref xml:id="755">Kikuyu discourse</ref></hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; wrote to Macmillans, inquiring whether they would undertake the publication. On Sunday morning I received a civil letter from M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName>, consenting to do so.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[106] </hi><hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Commemoration of Founders &amp; Benefactors was duly</hi><hi rend="italic"> observed according to the Statutes on Tuesday, the 27</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> of January, 1914, after long disuse.<note xml:id="240" n="1"></note> Indeed, I cannot find reason for thinking that it had been observed since the accession of Queen Elizabeth. The weather was most favourable, and the services were by universal consent dignified, impressive, &amp; well attended.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At 11 a.m. the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">corporate</hi><hi rend="italic"> Function was attended by the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName>, 14 Hon: canons, the Schoolmasters and the King's Scholars, as well as the members of the Corporation (except <persName xml:id="555">Bp. Tucker</persName>). I celebrated, and before the Prayer for the Church Militant read the Form of Commemoration.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The great public service was at 8 p.m. In the procession were representatives of the <orgName xml:id="272">Senate of the University</orgName>, the <orgName xml:id="273">Council of the Durham Colleges</orgName>, and the <orgName xml:id="274">Miners' Association</orgName>. All the parish clergy of the city, as well as the Masters &amp; Scholars of the School, came also. The Mayor &amp; Corporation had their own procession. The Bishop preached an admirable sermon, prefacing it by the Form of Commemoration. There was a great congregation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
