<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
                    </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Durham by the 8.20 express, &amp; proceeded to Stratford via York &amp; Birmingham, arriving about 3.30 p.m. Avonbank is a charming modern house on the Avon's bank, and adjoining the parish church. I attended a performance of 'The Comedy of Errors' in the Memorial Theatre. Bourchier was very ludicrous. On my road, I bought the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">"Times" which contained <ref xml:id="763">my letters</ref> answering <persName xml:id="314">Lord Hugh Cecil</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The gardens attached to the house looked beautiful in the evening light. The vicar showed me the fine church, after Evensong, which was song by a choir of boys. A curate read the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> lesson in the teeth of a deadly stutter, which lay in wait for him in strange places! The choir&#8211;stalls are carved with many coarse &amp; indecent scenes: indicating a Rabelaisian humour rather than the devotional absorption proper to holy men in holy places. It may serve as another illustration of the grossness of Medieval life. Shakespeare's bust is obscured &amp; protected by some patent unbreakable glass, against the risk of attack from the Suffragettes. The non&#8211;militants on their recent march were allowed under humiliating oversight to deposit a wreath on the poet's grave.</hi>
         </p>
        
            </body></text></TEI>
