<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We took the <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;es</persName><persName xml:id="2127"></persName> with us on an expedition to the Roman Wall</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi><persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> drove the motor with skill &amp; success. Save for refusing to carry the party over one very steep hill, the car did its duty well. We inspected Corbridge Church, and then went on to the excavations at Corbridge. The magnificent masonry of squared stones moved our wonder &amp; admiration. We lunched by the road&#8211;side under a tree. Then we went on to 'Chesters', and examined the extensive &amp; most interesting remains of the Roman fort. The museum is full of treasures. Next we motored to Hexham. Here we visited the great Abbey Church, and had tea. We returned to Durham by a different route. Almost the whole way the road lay through open ground at a great elevation, bordered with gorse in full flower &#8211; a splendid spectacle. We were back in the Deanery about 8.p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Roman Wall makes on my mind an impression more profound than the famous ruins of Pompeii. Its situation in so remote a district undoubtedly adds to the impressiveness of a spectacle extraordinarily impressive in itself.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
