<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The brilliant warm weather continues. There are complaints of drought from the farmers, &amp; threatenings of a curtailed water&#8211;supply from the water&#8211;companies. Meanwhile the country looks brilliant under the sun&#8211;shine.
         </p>
         <p>
I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. Then (in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="3514">Laidler's</persName> car, mine own being in hospital) <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> motored me to Wolsingham, where I preached in the parish church. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="3551">Arnold</persName>, the incumbent, has but recently succeeded old Chancellor <persName xml:id="3552">Espin</persName>, whose long senility has depressed the ecclesiastical life of the parish. I returned to Durham after the service, &amp; was back at the Deanery in time to entertain <persName xml:id="3530">Major</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3531">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fishbourne</persName> at lunch, &amp; to shew them the Library.
         </p>
         <p>
Then I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; immediately afterwards motored again to Wolsingham, <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> going with me. I preached on "Liberty" to a large congregation. We returned to Durham without accident, but not without delay, the gearing&#8211;apparatus of the car proving intractable. In the morning I had to walk the last two miles of the return journey, &amp; in the evening our start was delayed while Cummings manipulated the machine in the inward parts.
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
