<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName> was buried today</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The service in the Cathedral &amp; in the Cathedral burial ground was most impressive in the bright sunshine. <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> read the lesson: I read the prayers: the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> took the graveside service &amp; gave a final benediction. So we laid to rest a good simple man, who had a vision of duty, &amp; pursued it right loyally unto the end. Then I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Trustees</orgName>: &amp; afterwards brought <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> in to tea, &amp; had some talk with him. Then <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; I motored through Brancepeth, where we looked at the fine parish church, &amp; walked round the castle. <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName> seems to have had a genuine passion for wood carving. His tenure of the Rectory of Brancepeth is indicated by the wealth of excellent woodwork, which adorns the church. I did venture to speak to the Bishop about <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, urging him particularly to appoint him to the vacancy created by Tucker's death. <hi rend="bold underline">But 'tis a sneaky saint, &amp; will probably find some available relative or wife's relative to bestow on us!</hi> I wrote to the "Times" on the Ulster question a letter headed <ref xml:id="767">'Novissima Hora'</ref>.
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
