<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[266]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet morning, infinitely depressing. I celebrated in the cathedral at 8 a.m. The post brought a long &amp; interesting letter from <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, narrating the experiences which she &amp; <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> have passed through since the war broke out. There was a very small congregation at 10.30 a.m. when I preached. It is doubtless very salutary that the Dean should understand that folks in Durham have no sort of interest in his preaching! The evening paper contained a long communication from the Press Bureau giving an account of the fighting of the British Expeditionary Force. For 4 days it seems to have been severe &amp; continuous. French places his losses as between 5000 &amp; 6000 men.</p>
         <p>Young Tucker came to return some books &amp; papers of mine which he had found among his Father's possessions. I gave <persName xml:id="1608">Bishop Mann</persName> my copy of Henry VIII's "Defensio Septem Sacramentorum".</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A persistent rumour that a Russian Force landed at Aberdeen has been pressing southwards in numerous trains is categorically contradicted in the evening papers. Yet <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> had been telephoning right &amp; left, &amp; had convinced himself of its truth. And there were many who had themselves seen the uncouth foreigners at divers points in their journey!!</hi><note xml:id="189" n="1"></note>
         </p>
 
            </body></text></TEI>
