<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[248]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "British Weekly" accepts the war as unavoidable, and calls for unity in front of the enemy. So far, so good. If the sentimental Dissent which finds expression in that organ takes this line, we may hope that our domestic divisions will be reduced to a minimum.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">American opinion, so far at least as it is expressed in the newspapers quoted in the "Times", appears to be decisively hostile to Germany. The publication of the communications which passed between the Imperial Chancellor &amp; <persName xml:id="3411">Sir E. Grey</persName> on the eve of war, will certainly not alter that opinion. It is impossible to imagine anything more Machiavellian than the German Policy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent a note to the Mayor offering him every assistance in my power. He called on me forthwith, &amp; we went together to <persName xml:id="3525">Colonel Doyle</persName>, who has his office in the County Bldgs. With him I arranged for a special service in the Cathedral at 9.30 a.m. on Sunday. Then we went to <persName xml:id="3455">Jevons</persName>, &amp; got authority from him to arrange a reading&#8211;room for the men in the Union Rooms on Palace Green. Finally, I saw the Precentor, &amp; agreed with him on a form of service.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
