<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[217]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Culloden, Craigavad, Co. Down.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then we motored into Belfast, and spent the morning in going over the great ship&#8211;building works of Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Clark &amp; Co. This firm divides with Harland &amp; Wolf the greatest industry of the city: has turned out a greater tonnage than its rival for 2 years past: &amp; employs 9000 men. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Clark himself went with us for some part of the way. He is a prominent figure in the fight for the Union</hi><hi rend="italic">. He asked me whether I w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">care to speak with some of the men: &amp; when I replied in the affirmative, he caused six of the more intelligent workmen to come into the office, &amp; state their views of the situation. There certainly can be no doubt as to the feeling of the men. The question is mainly religious. Nothing will induce them to accept a supremacy of the Papists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch we motored again into Belfast, and saw the Town Hall &amp; Municipal Buildings, which cost &#x00A3;300,000 &amp; are very fine. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I was taken to the weekly prayer&#8211;meeting, which is organized with direct reference to the crisis</hi><hi rend="italic">. I made a short speech on the special function of the church in the present circumstances. I suspect that my insistence on </hi><hi rend="italic underline">placableness</hi><hi rend="italic"> was not to the taste of the assembly. D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><persName xml:id="1385"><hi rend="italic"> Montgomerie</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the ex&#8211;Moderator of the Presbyterians, was very bellicose. He told me that </hi><hi rend="bold">[218]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi><hi rend="italic"> even </hi><persName xml:id="2052"><hi rend="italic">Carson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> would lose his influence if he were to  recede from the demands of the Ulstermen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After a visit to the club, where I was introduced to <persName xml:id="1372">Sir George Richardson</persName> (a short cheery looking man with the suggestion of much quiet determination) and had tea, the Bishop &amp; I went to dine with Canon [sic – space left blank]. Here mine host's sister developed a truculent advocacy of female suffrage during dinner. This, perhaps, was partly directed against her husband, a retired police inspector, who had ventured some ferocious observation as to the right treatment of militants! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner we went to the grounds of an adjacent house to witness the drilling of the volunteers</hi><hi rend="italic">. About 500 men were on the field; about half of them carried rifles. Here we were joined by M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Clarke, who gave me much information. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I made a brief address to the men: then "God Save the King" was sung: and the Covenant pledge was repeated with much fervour</hi><hi rend="italic">: "We will not have Home Rule"! It is said that the men generally insist on saying 'Rome Rule'! Then we went into M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Clarke's house, which adjoined the drill ground, &amp; had tea &amp; some talk with the ladies of his family. Then he sent us home in his motor. We got in about 10.45 p.m.: &amp; went forthwith to bed, having spent a busy &amp; remarkably informing day, not soon to be forgotten.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
