<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather became much warmer. There is talk of a shortage of water through the drought.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2800">The Precentor</persName> &amp; 4 of the choirmen &#8211; Peacock, May, Akeroyd, &amp; Colgan &#8211; came to lunch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On Friday, June 5</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 1914, the papers announced the death of <persName xml:id="228">the Warden</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">. In a few months it will be 30 years since I first came into the circle of his acquaintance. I loved him at the start, &amp; can truly say that I have never thought of him without affection. He never ceased to show me kindness: &amp; hardly a year has passed without my staying with him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Scheme of Ordination Sermon:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Text: 2. Timothy ii. 3, 4 'Suffer hardship with me as a good soldier of Christ Jesus. No soldier on service entangleth himself in the affairs of this life: that he may please him who enrolled him as a soldier'.</hi> 
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>The Preacher's subject prescribed by the Rubric, which suggests the 3 divisions of the sermon.</hi>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>
<hi>The "Duty &amp; Office" of the Christian Minister. The two may go apart. This disaster facilitated by a legal establishment of the church.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>A clear vocation indispensable: the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> Question of Ordination also the most difficult. The Duty is created by Vocation. The requirements of the Office have been variously stated.</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>How shall we obey the Divine Call? The first of the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> question: the Christian Ministry is accepted as conditioned &amp; interpreted by the C. of E. There is no rivalry bet: the Catholic Ch. &amp; the C. of E. The promise of Obedience: This is truly a 'Catholic' principle. We must recognize an allocation of responsibility. No zeal can justify disobedience.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The cause of religion at present embarrassed by the persistent disobedience of many clergymen. A lawless time. The clergymen cannot preach</hi><hi rend="bold"> [207] </hi><hi>civic duty with any effect, if he be known to disobey his lawful superiors.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Law, &amp; the Ministers of the Law, limited to sphere of externals. In the higher ranges of clerical life we must take our own course. The Bishop cannot read hearts. Subscription of formularies a clumsy method of securing an indispensable working agreement.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Meaning &amp; worth of clerical subscription now much debated. Two counsels. 1 Never be a party to 'heresy hunts', 2. Make no terms with your own indolence.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Teaching must always be carried on in connection with pastorate. The influence of the sermons mostly determined by the parson's reputation.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>II The necessity of the Orders morally conditioned. The fact that the Ministry is traceable to J.C. sufficient proof of its necessity. Specific form of the Ministry determined by the Church in light of experience.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>III The laity are not to regard the clergy as having a sacerdotal character. They are 'pastors &amp; teachers'.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Final appeal to the candidates to "endure hardness".</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
