<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dubious morning of clouds &amp; intermittent sunshine followed a stormy night. Some letters arrived by the Sunday post including one from </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName></hi><hi> which acknowledged receipt of the <ref xml:id="755">Oxford Sermon</ref>, and protested with some vigour against the </hi><hi rend="underline">text</hi> <hi>&#8211; "Let love be without hypocrisy". He seems to interpret it as a suggestion that he &amp; the other Zanzibaris are themselves hypocrites!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Tomorrow I am pledged to speak to a clerical company on 'Reunion'. It is difficult to know what to say:</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>The urgency of the matter at home &amp; abroad.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Two conceptions of X</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ity</hi><hi> bequeathed by History, emphasizing respectively a. the ideas b. the institutions of Christ's Gospel.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The Reformation disclosed the difference, &amp; divided Christians inevitably.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Union of the Future cannot </hi><hi rend="underline">return</hi><hi> to the older system which has already broken down.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The Position of the C. of E. &#8211; in what sense the 'via media' is to be understood = 'the glory &amp; crown of the Reformation'</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The choice must be made. There is no place for a </hi><hi rend="underline">tertium quid</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a large congregation at Mattins, when I preached on Acts xi. 26. "The disciples were called Christians first in Antioch". The collection amounted to over &#x00A3;525, which appeared to give much satisfaction to everybody.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the afternoon in my room, partly resting, &amp; partly revising my evening sermon. The gentlemen of the choir came in to tea after the service at 3 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a great crowd at Evensong. I preached about the Church of England, taking as my text the words of the proverb quoted in Isaiah 65: "Destroy it not for a blessing is in it". As the sermon was ending a man in the congregation fell into an epileptic fit, &amp; was removed with some commotion. A celebration of Holy Communion followed Evensong. All the first part of the service was omitted. There were 78 communicants mostly young girls. I remained &amp; communicated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At supper a number of clergy &#8211; curates &amp; ex&#8211;curates &#8211; came together, &amp; appeared to enjoy themselves. They sang the verse "Praise God from Whom all blessings flow" before separating.</hi>
         </p>
        
            </body></text></TEI>
