<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
We started from the house about 11 a.m., &amp; motored into Kendal, where we visited the parish church, a fine edifice with double aisles, capable of accommodating more than 1200 people. Then we went on to Hawkshead, where we looked at the Church, a quaint structure with the tombs of the Sandys family. We went on to Coniston, where we lunched in a pleasant hotel on the lake&#8211;shore. We visited the <persName xml:id="626">Ruskin</persName> museum, filled with many relics &amp;c of the great man. We went to the church (a woeful structure) &amp; looked at his grave in the churchyard. It is marked by a Celtic cross of granite. The churchyard is much defaced with those abominations &#8211; sham wreaths under glass protected by iron cages! From Coniston we went to Ambleside, where we had tea with <persName xml:id="1756" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rawnsley</persName>, brother of the well&#8211;known <persName xml:id="243">Canon</persName>. The latter was also of the party. <hi rend="bold underline">After tea I was taken to see <persName xml:id="1693">Miss Arnold</persName> of Fox Howe. The old lady received me with much graciousness, reminded me of my last visit with <persName xml:id="336">Arthur Galton</persName>, &amp; expressed her great approval of my public course</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>Then we motored back to Singleton Park. <persName xml:id="94">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Jackson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went first in our car: Canon Rawnsley, <persName xml:id="93">mine host</persName>, &amp; I followed. The road lay through the most amazing scenery.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi> <hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We stopped to see Christopher North's house, &amp; to enjoy the wonderful prospect of the mountains with Windermere. In the declining sun everything was entrancingly beautiful. We reached the house about 7 p.m., &amp; immediately dressed for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There came to dinner M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Sime, the vicar of Kendal, and Miss Cropper, a lady resident in the district.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I noticed on the roadside a public house with the sign 'The Eagle &amp; Child'; &amp; I was informed that this sign perpetuated an actual occurrence. An eagle carried off an infant. These glorious birds have long left the district. Canon Rawnsley said that he had spoken to people who remembered them: &amp; he had seen fish eagles on Ullswater, but not golden eagles. Ravens still linger in the remoter hills, &amp; there are divers fine hawks, extinct elsewhere in England.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Canon Rawnsley showed me a printed form of a petition to the bishops, bewailing the prevalence of heresy, &amp; begging them to suppress hereticks. He said this had been sent to him for signature, &amp; presumably to others. It is clear that a determined effort is being made by the Fanaticks under the triple leadership of Bishops <persName xml:id="3469">Weston</persName>, <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="166">Ingram</persName>. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
