<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Frewin Hall, Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A celebration of the Holy Communion at 7.45 a.m. inaugurates the sad ceremonials of this day. The mortal remains of <persName xml:id="228">the Warden</persName> are in the coffin placed before the Altar. It has been watched through the night by Fellows, replacing one another in a pious vigil every hour. There can be no doubt as to the depth &amp; sincerity of their sorrow. I think there is a twofold purpose in this Celebration. On the one hand, the College would surrender thus into the Hands of God the dearest object it has: on the other hand, the College in front of a great disaster would re–consecrate its own unity. Add the inevitable sense of helplessness which so sudden &amp; unexpected a departure must needs cause even in the least reflective mind, &amp; the special solemnity of this religious act can be perceived.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="130">The Archbishop of York</persName> was the Celebrant, <persName xml:id="2407">Johnson</persName> assisting. Everything was very solemn &amp; moving. I thought myself back to the time when first I worshipped in that place. It seems impossible to empty the Warden's stall of the slight trim figure. His reading of the College–prayer on Fridays is unforgettable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At 11.45 a.m. there was a short service in the Chapel. It was crowded with Fellows &amp; Quondams. Lang, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I</hi><hi rend="italic">, and Campbell sate in the Sedilia, &amp; Johnson in his stall. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">We</hi><hi rend="italic"> alone wore surplices: all the rest were in gowns without hoods. Johnson nearly broke down in reading the prayer: &amp; <persName xml:id="1008">Simon</persName> was visibly moved as he read the lesson. 'Let us now praise famous men'. Then we moved in procession to <orgName xml:id="61">S. Mary's</orgName> preceded by the University Beadles, one of whom at intervals rang a bell. At S. Mary's, we escorted the Coffin into the Chancel: &amp; there the relatives had their places. When the congregation had been seated, the officiating clergy came into the Church, &amp; sate in front of the Proctors. Lang &amp; Campbell on one side: Johnson &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I</hi><hi rend="italic"> on the other. Johnson read the sentences: </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I</hi><hi rend="italic"> read the Lesson: Lang read the Prayers: &amp; Campbell took the prayers beside the grave. Lang pronounced the final Benediction. <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> was in the chief place, as Chancellor: the Prince of Wales sate next the Vice–Chancellor (<persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName>): <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>, <persName xml:id="1590">Harcourt</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2216">Pease</persName> were also present. S. Mary's was filled with Heads, Professors, Doctors, &amp; Masters. The walk to Holywell Cemetery evoked an impressive demonstration of public respect, for great numbers of people lined the march, and showed in their behaviour much sympathy &amp; concern. Immediately after the Funeral, I returned to Frewen Hall, lunched with <persName xml:id="2141">Oman</persName> &amp; his family, &amp; then went off to the train. I reached Durham at 10.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At midnight on Friday 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> June 1915 [sic] I left Durham for Belfast, changing only at Newcastle. I left at 12.12 a.m. and arrived in Belfast at 8.35 a.m. on Saturday morning. [The Irish time is 25 minutes earlier than the English – such is the hasty habit of that nation!] The <persName xml:id="1361">Bishop of Down</persName> sent his car to meet the train, &amp; I travelled out to the Palace quite comfortably. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There is no sign of civic trouble in the streets of Belfast</hi><hi>. Peaceful processions of Sunday School children were the only organized forces I encountered!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>When I handed in a telegram to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>, the young man in charge observed as he read my name: "Ah, I have often read that name before"!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop motored me to Mountstewart, where we lunched with <persName xml:id="2816">Lord Londonderry</persName>. There were no other guests. After lunch we walked in the very beautiful grounds, &amp; finally took our seats in a summer house commanding a wonderful view of the Lough. Here we conversed with freedom of the political situation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord L. &amp; the Bishop are full of stories of the famous gun–running exploit</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><note xml:id="183" n="1"></note> <hi rend="italic">After we had had tea on the lawn, we bade our host farewell, &amp; motored back to Culloden having spent an unusually interesting afternoon. Then I went to my room, &amp; wrote a letter to my wife.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The situation in Ulster has reached a critical stage. There is but a single step now to the setting up of the Provisional Government, and there are many here who desire that that step should be taken.<note xml:id="184" n="1"></note> But this would imply open rebellion, &amp; could not but alienate many who heartily sympathise with the Ulster resistance to Home Rule. Lord L. expressed himself very temperately on this point: the Bishop assures me that his Lordship is a moderating influence on the movement.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There dined here five gentlemen – three laymen and two clergy – who had all been personally concerned in the gun–running, and were very full of the subject. I was assured that the moral effect of the Volunteer movement was very excellent. 'It has done more for my parish than 10 missions', said one parson: &amp; this was the general testimony. We discussed the economic situation, &amp; it was frankly acknowledged that there would be a renewal of strife, when the unifying pressure of the political crisis had ceased. The sympathies of the police &amp; the Army &amp; Navy are so confidently counted upon, &amp; expressed so naively, that the terrible dangers of the situation are in some measure concealed from the eyes of those who are responsible. It seems to them impossible to realize any process by which the existing amenities should give place to sanguinary violence.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
