<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Edinburgh.</hi></p>
         <p>
I spent the forenoon in the General Assembly of the Established Church, and the afternoon in that of the U.F. Church. In the past I listened to speeches about the Pensions for Aged Ministers: and the endowment of new parishes. In the last, I watched the election of a Professor of Dogmatic Theology to succeed the late <persName xml:id="3539">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Orr</persName>. The Assembly Hall was crowded, &amp; the galleries filled with visitors. There were 5 candidates, every one of whom was nominated in a speech of exactly 10 minutes, &amp; seconded in a speech precisely half that length. Then a show of hands was taken, with the result that 2 candidates were withdrawn. There were two votes. The first ran thus:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName> 366</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3540">Lamont</persName> 260</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3541">Macaulay</persName> 246 _ 872</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
This eliminated Macaulay, &amp; a 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> vote elected Forrest.
         </p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
<hi>Forrest 425</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Lamont 408 _ 833</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
Thus Forrest had a majority of 17 votes. Evidently everybody came with mind made up, &amp; probably vote promised. The speeches were a mere ceremony. On the whole, though everything was very well managed, I cannot approve such a method of choosing a Professor.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I breakfasted with the <persName xml:id="3543">Moderator</persName> of the Established Church at the North British Hotel.</p>
         <p>
In the evening we dined at Holyrood with the High Commissioner. This is the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year of the reign of <persName xml:id="1391">Lord Glenconner</persName>. Ella was allotted as a partner to <persName xml:id="1138">Fisher</persName>, formerly of Morningside, now of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's. I had <persName xml:id="1390">Clarissa Tennant</persName> (commonly called 'Clare') for my portion, &amp; was well content.</p>
         <p>
What ought a Christian man to think of all this parade of State? It must be frankly conceded that it is all purely symbolic. Not even a shadow of substance remains in the High Commissioner's office. He serves to remind the Scottish public that the State recognizes the Church: he enlivens Edinburgh with a parade: &amp; amuses the citizens with a fortnight's entertainment. His Grace according to his mind &amp; his means, contributes to various good works, &amp; seeks thus to ingratiate himself with the Scottish people. Beyond this, there is nothing in it. Yet its abolition would assuredly be unpopular: for the annual show is an assertion of national identity, and an appeal to history which is mainly flattering to Scottish pride. It may possibly tend to correct the merely ecclesiastical dispositions within the ranks of the clergy, &amp; so assist them to a larger conception of their duty.</p>

            </body></text></TEI>
