<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Monday, July 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1914 – Saturday, July 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1914</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[</hi>I went across to Lambeth on Saturday morning in order to make some preparation in the library there for my evidence before the select committee. I had an interview with his <persName xml:id="128">Grace</persName>, &amp; then settled to read such books as were relevant. <persName xml:id="44"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Armitage Robinson</hi></persName> arrived, &amp; we discussed the subject. <hi rend="italic">I stayed to luncheon, &amp; sate at table between the 2 Abps. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Primate pleasantly compared himself &amp; his <persName xml:id="130">northern brother</persName> to two tame elephants, bringing in a capture</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> <hi rend="italic">We discussed the desperate political situation, &amp; the strange frivolity which marked the course of society. The Archbishop mentioned as a case in point the behaviour of the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName>, who continued to play bridge with young women until the small hours of the morning, at a juncture which at any moment might emerge in civil war, a situation which would overwhelm the country with disaster, and himself with infamy. I returned to Little Cloisters, &amp; picked up </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">. We travelled to Winchester by the 4.50 p.m. from Waterloo, and there we spent the week end, as stated on p. 230f</hi><hi rend="i bold">] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left Winchester for Southampton by a morning rain, arriving in good time for lunch. We stayed with the <persName xml:id="1123">Bishop&#8211;Suffragan</persName> until Saturday, and enjoyed some delightful motor drives through the forest. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Thursday we visited Salisbury. Here we called at the Palace, and had some conversation with the <persName xml:id="178">Bishop</persName>. He spoke rather contemptuously of his <persName xml:id="1218">Brother</persName> of Chelmsford, who seems to be shaping for the usual transformation which overtakes the Evangelical on the Episcopal Bench. We visited Breamore, where is a most interesting church, largely prae&#8211;Norman. There is a round arch with a clear&#8211;cut Anglo&#8211;Saxon inscription: and some medieval frescoes in the priest's chamber within the porch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On Friday, the 17</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> July, I went to Westminster in order to give evidence before the Select Committee of the House of Lords</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><note xml:id="187" n="1"></note> <hi rend="italic">Their Lordships kept me for 2 hours: &amp; all asked questions except </hi><persName xml:id="703"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Halsbury</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, who contented himself with interjecting remarks.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
On Saturday, we left Southampton, and made our way to Vann, in order to spend the week&#8211;end with the <persName xml:id="648"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&#x00F6;es</hi></persName><persName xml:id="2127"></persName>. In the afternoon our hosts took us on an expedition to Bignor, to see the remains of the Roman Villa. The mosaic pavements are astonishingly brilliant.
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
