<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[269]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The anniversary of Sedan! I read through a little book full of surprising information, &amp; sinister suggestiveness – Cramb's "Germany &amp; England". He states that very nearly 700 books dealing with war as a science are annually published in Germany.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">After tea I motored to Houghton–le–Spring, &amp; joined <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> in a meeting held in the village square to assist enlistment</hi><hi rend="italic">. There was an assembly, as I judge, of about 2000 men. They received Lord Durham with much heartiness, &amp; listened to my speech with much attention. At the close they even manifested some enthusiasm: &amp; I left the place amid cheers like a prince!! It is perhaps unusual for a clergyman thus directly to associate himself with these warlike preparations, but surely it is not really unfitting. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">For there is no middle position possible on the question of individual duty. If enlistment is the duty of young Englishmen at this serious juncture, who could more fitly bid them enlist than the man, whose official character is precisely that of the advocate &amp; exponent of human duty? Accordingly, I propose to exert myself as a recruiting sergeant</hi><hi rend="i bold">!!</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>
