<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>I called at the Ecclesiastical Commission Office, &amp; saw <persName xml:id="909">Sir Lewis Dibdin</persName>. He seemed somewhat discomposed by his encounter with <persName xml:id="2715">Lord Sheffield</persName>, who has evidently laid himself out for an attack on the Convocations. I borrowed his (Dibdin's) notes. Then I attended the Representative Church Council. As I entered, some Suffragettes started protesting from the gallery. Scarcely had they been removed, before the disturbance was renewed in another quarter, where a young &amp; smartly dressed female held forth with astonishing vigour &amp; volubility. The Abp. was disposed to permit her to speak, but when she announced her intention of going on until she was removed, his Grace caused her also to be thrust forth.</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="112"><hi rend="italic">Ella</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; I lunched with </hi><persName xml:id="1731"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lowther</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">. She and Miss L. were good enough to profess great regret at my departure. They say that the congregation in S. Marg</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t's</hi><hi rend="italic"> is falling off. On our way back to Little Cloisters, we called in at the Church, and were warmly welcomed by M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="1033">Ramsay</persName>, whose estimate of my successor is clearly by no means flattering.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>We dined with <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, &amp; went to "When Knights were bold" at the Apollo Theatre.</hi></p>

            </body></text></TEI>
