<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
A cold, blustering day, inclining to rain. There was a very large congregation in the cathedral at the morning service. <hi rend="bold underline">I preached on "Civic Duty"</hi>, with designed reference to the present crisis. My text was "not looking each of you to his own things, but each of you also to the things of others". The people seemed to me attentive, &amp; certainly were very still in their places. I preached for about 25 minutes.</p>
         <p>
When we were leaving the cathedral, I was addressed by a tall man, with the speech &amp; aspect of a gentleman, who said that he had listened to the sermon with much interest, &amp; desired me to give him a message which he might disseminate at his own expense through the country. Adjudging him to be crazed, I answered briefly that he might say from me that at this crisis every Englishman worthy the name should set his country above his party.</p>
         <p>
At tea <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> had brought together some of my old boys from Westminster to meet me. Gilbert &amp; his fiancée, <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName>, Reggie &amp; <persName xml:id="2463" display="no">'Nimbus'</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1682" display="no">Colin Kennedy</persName> – they all seemed glad to see us. "The thoughts of a boy are long, long thoughts". Who knows how these things will look like in their retrospect?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p>
In the evening I preached in the Abbey. The weather was wet &amp; comfortless, yet the church was crowded. In the congregation I noticed a good many of the old faces from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. Both <persName xml:id="2527" display="no">churchwardens</persName><persName xml:id="156"></persName> were there. I preached on "Jesus Christ as the Example of the Life of Faith – the author &amp; Perfecter of Faith". There was no interruption from suffragettes, &amp; the attention was close &amp; sustained through 35 minutes. <persName xml:id="325">The Dean</persName>, <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>, &amp; Charles were present: &amp; two minor canons.</p>
         <p>
Charles rather communicative after supper. Clearly relations are strained between the Chapter &amp; the minor canons. These latter are more aggressively "Catholic" than heretofore. Certainly, it is difficult to imagine a more insolent proceeding than that of which 4 of them were guilty when they signed the memorandum to the Upper House of Convocation.
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>Fee from S. Paul's</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>£2.11.8</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>Fee from the Abbey</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>2.2.0</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>Manchester Guardian</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi rend="underline">3.13.6</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="left"/>
               <cell rend="left">
<hi>£8.7.2</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Monday, the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March, the weather was wretched. I walked in the rain part of the way to Westminster, &amp; took a taxi when the deluge was too violent. I spent the morning in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; wrote many letters. After lunching in the club, I walked back to the Deanery. Finding myself chilled, I went early to bed. This was the more annoying as both <persName xml:id="1261">Violet Markham</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2974">Lady Lugard</persName> were at dinner: &amp; I was dullness incarnate!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Tuesday, the 31</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> March, I went to Westminster, &amp; in S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Margaret's </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">married <persName xml:id="2121">Dorothy Tait</persName> to Hugh Russell Smith</hi><hi rend="italic">. There was no choir, &amp; a large congregation.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After the service we called on Lady Margaret: and then I attended a conference arranged by the <orgName xml:id="213">Anti–Slavery Society</orgName>, in order to consider the deplorable situation in the New Hebrides. It was decided to ask <persName xml:id="3411">Sir Ed: Grey</persName> to receive a deputation after Easter. Later, I dined pleasantly with <persName xml:id="601">Sir Kenneth Muir Mackenzie</persName>. <persName xml:id="633">Sir Henry Graham</persName>, Butler, &amp; <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> were of the party. We had much political discussion.</hi></p>
         <p>
On Wednesday, April 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, I called on <persName xml:id="122">Hine–Haycock</persName>, &amp; had some talk with him. Then walked to West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; called on <persName xml:id="2109" display="no">Miss Pearce</persName>: then went to the Athenaeum. Then lunched with <persName xml:id="2229">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mackenzie</persName> in his flat in Kensington, &amp; stayed talking with him until 4 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[148]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
He is a very alert &amp; interesting man. He told me that he had talked long with <persName xml:id="2633">Percy Dearmer</persName> over his book, <ref xml:id="747">"Body &amp; Mind"</ref>, but could do nothing with him, as he did not seem capable of understanding the force of his own statements. He said that while he found High Church clergymen very attractive, <hi rend="bold underline">he found High Church laymen extremely unpleasing</hi>: &amp; that he could not explain why. I could not help him here, as <hi rend="underline">all</hi> High Churchmen of a certain type seem to me exasperating.</p>
         <p>
I returned to the Deanery, where Kitty had brought together a numerous company of our friends. <persName xml:id="2622">Sir Lionel</persName> came, &amp; talked much of his son's experience in Dublin, where he had received a peremptory requirement, marked 'strictly confidential' to decide between serving in Ulster &amp; being dismissed the service! This is gross behaviour indeed. <persName xml:id="2228">Lady Emmott</persName>, <persName xml:id="728">Lady Flower</persName>, <persName xml:id="412">Parker Smith</persName>, <persName xml:id="2655">Arthur Smith</persName>, <persName xml:id="2563" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray Smith</persName>, divers relatives of <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Harold &amp; <persName xml:id="2056">Elsie</persName> – were there. We dined quietly at the Deanery, with <persName xml:id="427">our hosts</persName>.</p>
         <p>
On Thursday we lunched with the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>: and dined with <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName>.</p>
         <p>
On Friday we returned to Durham.</p>

            </body></text></TEI>
