<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[243]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">These critical happenings in the political world interfere sadly with one's mental state. It takes the heart out of everything to know that, for aught we know to the contrary, Harmageddon is actually beginning. Like the absorbed Adventists of Thessalonica one sinks into ignominious idleness through sheer lack of interest in everything. Here am I letting day after day slip by unused while I am pledged to a public lecture in the University, and a course of public lectures in Sweden: within the next few months: and have not so much determined the subject of the one, or the order of the other! The only thing that interests me is the "Times", and that degenerates daily.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We lunched at the School with a numerous company, and afterwards I distributed prizes, &amp; made a short speech. Then, by some blundering, we missed the car, (which was all the while standing at <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth's</persName> front door!) and walked to the Agricultural Show, which was proceeding in Dryburn. There we parted: <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> going to tea at North End, &amp; I going back to the Deanery for the Choir Committee which was appointed at the last Chapter to reconsider the conditions of the lay&#8211;vicars' service.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[244]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I reckon a lie in history to be as much a greater sin than a lie in common intercourse, as the one is like to be more lasting and more generally known than the other."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop <persName xml:id="1435">Burnet's</persName> Pref: to <ref xml:id="183">"History of his own times"</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I have given the character of men very impartially and copiously; for nothing guides one's judgment more truly in a relation of matter of fact, than the knowing the tempers and principles of the chief actors"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ibid.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Saturday, August 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1914, we left Durham, and went to visit <persName xml:id="230">Sir Charles Renshaw</persName> at Barochan</hi>. Miss <persName xml:id="1046">Bankhead</persName> accompanied me as far as Glasgow. The approach of the Bank Holiday made travelling unpleasant by reason of the crowds: but we had comparatively easy journeying.</p>

            </body></text></TEI>
