<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We dined pleasantly with the <persName xml:id="2141">Omans</persName><persName xml:id="2142"></persName> last night: <persName xml:id="93">Jackson</persName>, the late Rector of Exeter, &amp; his <persName xml:id="94">wife</persName> were there, &amp; <persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3482">his wife</persName>, with some of the younger dons. The conversation left no definite impression on my mind, being mostly frivolous. </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m.: and received the Holy Communion. The interesting custom of administering the sacrament to the congregation in their seats is said to be a tradition of the reign of John Owen, the Independent Dean of Christ Church.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read over my <ref xml:id="755">sermon</ref> before going to S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Mary's, &amp; felt more than ever doubtful as to its success! Still it </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">is</hi><hi rend="italic"> as clear &amp; honest a statement of the real situation as I can frame: &amp; such a statement does seem to me needed.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">At 10.30 there was a great congregation, floor &amp; gallery seemed quite full</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; the procession of Heads was imposing. I preached for the full hour, &amp; was well listened to, though I was conscious of a hostile element in my audience. The hymn was curiously well&#8211;chosen &#8211; <persName xml:id="337">Newman's</persName> "Lead Kindly Light". I introduced a reference to the University of Durham into the Bidding Prayer.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
I met Oman &amp; his Anglo&#8211;Indian friend after the sermon. <hi rend="underline">They</hi> were very much impressed &amp; of course entirely approved the discourse. Then I called in College, &amp; was picked up by a party &amp; walked through Mesopotamia. <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName> approved <hi rend="underline">more suo</hi>: &amp; <persName xml:id="205">Cunliffe Foster</persName> also. Later I saw the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, who dissented from my reference to the religious situation in the elementary schools: &amp; <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, who was of course wholly approving. Also I ran into <persName xml:id="2846">Parkin</persName>, who expressed himself warmly in favour.</p>
         <p>
I called, as had been arranged, on Bishop Mitchinson, the Master of Pembroke, who shewed me his volume of sketches etc. which he proposes to present to the Dean &amp; Chapter of Durham.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We had tea with Miss Anson, &amp; then went to Christ Church for service at 5 p.m. There was a large congregation &#8211; surpliced undergraduates in the centre, dons wives &amp; citizens elsewhere. I preached the sermon on "As the hart desireth etc.", &amp; had the closest attention throughout. The Dean told me subsequently that the men had been greatly pleased! There is a strong body of "Old Westminster" in Christ Church.</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> &amp; his <persName xml:id="2357">wife</persName> came in to dinner.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Monday Feb. 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, we travelled to London, where we drove to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; went our several ways. I went to the Athenaeum, where I lunched &amp; wrote letters. <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName> was there, &amp; Parkin.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I walked to Lambeth, &amp; called on the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>, whom I found in a state of much perturbation over Kikuyu. He told me that I had not made it easier for him to secure a settlement of the controversy. To this I could only reply that that depended on the nature of the settlement he meditated. Our interview was friendly, but agitated</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
In the evening I dined with the Brotherhood. <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName> brought tidings of two new bishops &#8211; to Ipswich goes Archdeacon Hodgson of Lindisfarne, to Chelmsford, <persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">It is certainly startling to have a man advanced to the episcopal Bench, who has had no academic training whatever</hi>.</p>
         <p>
On Tuesday, the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, I called on the <persName xml:id="325">Dean</persName>, who shared my dismay at the appointment to Chelmsford: on <persName xml:id="810">Radcliffe</persName>, &amp; on <persName xml:id="793">Lady Craik</persName>. Then I wrote more letters in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, lunched with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>, attended Evensong in the Abbey, and returned to Durham by the 5.30 express. My compagnons de voyage were five young sailors, returning home on leave.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Saturday, Feb. 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1914, I went to Newcastle, and addressed a great meeting of Christian Endeavourers in the Town Hall. The spectacle of so great a crowd, mostly young men, was very impressive, &amp; suggestive. Could the Church of England draw together such an assembly for such a purpose? I doubt it. These were Methodists, who are numerous among the mining population. I spoke for exactly half an hour, taking as my theme the Christian life. They listened well, &amp; were, I think, interested, though my manner of speaking is not familiar to them.</p>

            </body></text></TEI>
