<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
                  <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Again the weather was propitious. Bright sun &amp; cloudless sky from start to finish. <persName xml:id="243">Canon Rawnsley</persName> left immediately after breakfast. He said that the larks would not mount &amp; sing about Keswick through fear of the </hi><hi rend="underline">raptores</hi><hi> [sic] from the mountains. Here they sing freely.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We motored to Keswick, &amp; there went at once to Lodore. There was scarcely any water in the Fall, but the scene is romantic, &amp; after heavy rains, it is easy to imagine a mighty cataract. Here we lunched, &amp; strolled about the lake&#8211;side. Derwentwater is beautiful with islands, &amp; curious on account of the 'floating island' which appears in it at intervals. We returned as far as Grasmere, &amp; there stopped in order to visit the quaint church, &amp; the tomb of Wordsworth, &amp; Dove Cottage. The last is kept as far as possible in its original state &#8211; a very humble dwelling. Here Wordsworth lived in the earlier years, &amp; wrote much of his best work. The little house is stocked with various articles reminiscent of the poet, and many personal relics. We had tea comfortably in a pleasant hotel by the lake&#8211;side: &amp; then motored back to Kendal arriving about 6.30 p.m. Our way was made glorious by views of lake &amp; mountains, changing in the evening lights.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
