<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Stratford&#8211;on&#8211;Avon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A most glorious spring morning, with cloudless sky brilliant sun, fresh green trees, &amp; birds singing like angels at a festival. I went to church, &amp; received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m.
         </p>
         <p>
There was a great congregation at Mattins. The clergy &amp; choir met the Mayor's procession at the West door, &amp; there I shook hands with the Mayor. There was close attention to the <ref xml:id="766">sermon</ref>, which (if I may judge from sundry observations addressed to me later) seemed to give satisfaction. One incident attracted my notice, as indeed was probably intended. A man sitting near the chancel screen rose, as soon as I had taken my place in the pulpit, and left the church with much display of deliberation. I was informed that he was <persName xml:id="2039"><hi rend="underline">de Winton's</hi></persName> brother! Presumably the poor creature thought he was striking a blow for the "Catholick" church, by being rude to the Dean of Durham!
         </p>
         <p>
In the afternoon I motored to Great Comberton (?) [sic] to fetch <persName xml:id="898">Peile</persName> who was to preach at Evensong. The road lay through beautiful country, rich in blossoming orchards &amp; gardens radiant with flowers. I had tea with Peile &amp; <persName xml:id="1346" display="no">his wife</persName>. We motored back to Stratford: &amp; he preached rather a dull sermon at Evensong.
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
