<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[234]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Vann, Witley.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A dull day tending to rain. Staying here is a Norwegian friend of <persName xml:id="648">mine host</persName>, named Lund, who (as I understand) is an engineer of sorts. He asked me at breakfast whether I agreed with the total prohibition of alcohol: and when I replied that I did not, he expressed his agreement. He said that coffee had largely replaced beer in Norway, a change which in his judgment was regrettable.
         </p>
         <p>
The <persName xml:id="105">Bp. of Winchester</persName> being announced to preach at Whitley, mine hostess carried off <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> to hear him, &amp; perchance to bring him back to dinner. The rest of us &#8211; save the Norwegian lady, who stayed at home &#8211; walked across the hill to Dunsfold, &amp; there attended service. The Rector, who has recently succeeded Rolfe's friend, Wynn, is Ollard, a fairly well&#8211;known champion of "Catholicism". I observed that he crossed himself rather ostentatiously before beginning his sermon. I was rather surprised to hear him announce that instead of the Litany in the Prayer&#8211;book, there would be used a Litany issued for diocesan use during the present anxieties. Copies were distributed to the congregation by two of the choir&#8211;boys: &amp; we duly used the formula. It was, of course, very much "up to date" with prayers about Female Suffrage, Labour Conflicts, Ireland, the Welsh Church, and Kikuyu. As to the last, a special celebration of Holy Communion was <hi rend="bold">[235] </hi>[symbol] announced for Monday, the 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when the Lambeth Committee begins its work.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Christian took me for a walk on the hill. The air was thunderous &amp; heavy, but the prospects were spacious &amp; noble, &amp; our conversation grave &amp; intimate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner we passed the time pleasantly in the wonderful barn&#8211;drawing room. Fru Lund sings well: and with her husband. Car&#x00F6;e himself contributed to the entertainment; &amp; Christian fiddled charmingly. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I cannot overcome a certain resentment at the novel Litany of this morning</hi>. It may be the case that the actual words do not necessarily imply a particular view of the debated &amp; difficult questions, to which they refer: but, in the actual circumstances, they must needs do so. Thus with respect to Kikuyu, we were made to pray that we might have grace to 'be faithful to what we have received'. That can hardly be interpreted otherwise than as an assumption that 'the historic Episcopate' with its 'apostolic succession' must be at all hazards held fast. But there are some of us who have come to think that the <hi rend="underline">surrender</hi> of this fiction of "Apostolic Succession" is required of English Churchmen as the primary condition of fidelity to that spiritual Truth, which in receiving Christ's Religion, they necessarily received. After a course of these Litanies, there is little possibility left of <hi rend="bold">[236] </hi> [symbol] an open mind. Similarly, the prayers for help to treat wisely the "Woman question" assumed that some tremendous 'new departure' in the relations of the sexes was rightly demanded at the present time &#8211; an assumption which properly begs the very question at issue. Once accustom the congregations to this point of view, and it will be very difficult to bring them to face frankly the practical questions. And, generally, when once men are brought to pray about their politics, they cease to preserve the right political temper, &amp; must needs tend to become fanatical. How can you discuss as an open question what you have prayed the Almighty to prosper? For, whatever the formulas actually used, the real petition always is for victory, never for guidance, or for teachableness, or for truth. In fact all this pious parade of special prayer works out as a very clever tactical device. The Low Churchmen &amp; the Latitudinarian, to whom all ecclesiastical questions are necessarily secondary, can hardly resent or refuse an invitation to pray for the Divine Guidance: but their opponents do not seek Guidance, but grace to hold fast to their own position – a very different thing. Thus the one side emerge from the common Devotion with yielding &amp; placable minds, the other comes forth with an exalted certitude &amp; a religious fervour. In these circumstances, the results of the 'discussion' can hardly be doubtful.
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
