<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[172] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Mine host motored me to Leamington, where I caught the express to Paddington. On the way we passed through Warwick: the view of the castle from the bridge is superb. Having left my baggage at King's Cross, I went to the barber &amp; had my hair cut. Then I walked to Westminster, &amp; lunched with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>. We went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; voted for <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>, who came up for election.
         </p>
         <p>In the club I found several of my friends &#8211; <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray</persName>, <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName>, <persName xml:id="2467">Geikie</persName>, &amp;c. <persName xml:id="348"><hi rend="bold underline">John Murray</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the publisher assured me that he agreed with every word of my <ref xml:id="756">Edinburgh article</ref></hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I returned to Durham by the 5.30 express.
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Today's papers are full of the accounts of a great landing of rifles &amp; ammunition in Ulster. Events are marching quickly towards some terrible catastrophe.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Jarrow's</persName> acceptance of the Bishoprick of Bristol raises the question whether the suffragan&#8211;bishop ought to hold a canonry. I feel strongly that he ought not to do so: &amp; I wrote at length to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> to that effect, urging at the same time <persName xml:id="216">Gow's</persName> special qualifications for the canonry. I thought it right to let the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> know my views, &amp; also that I should place them before the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName>.
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday (April 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) I went to the prison, and addressed the prisoners on "The Great Fire of London as seen by contemporaries["]. It was truly a dolourous performance. The prisoners are of the lowest type, many of them being almost half&#8211;witted, &amp; almost all belonging to the lowest &amp; most ignorant class of the population. They were quiet enough, but not, I think, interested.
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday (April 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> &amp; I walked through the wood, which was beautiful with blue&#8211;bells.
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" reported a debate in the Upper House of the Canterbury Convocation, on a series of resolutions moved by the <persName xml:id="166">Bp. of London</persName>, &amp; supported by the <persName xml:id="49">Bps. of Oxford</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="105">Winchester</persName>. The new Bp. of Chelmsford (<persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName>) made his debut as an obscurantist. The <persName xml:id="475">Bishop of Hereford</persName> moved, &amp; the <persName xml:id="1643">Bishop of Lincoln</persName> seconded an Amendment.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
