<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[260]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Fall of Namur takes the heart out of everything. There can be no doubt that the Germans have gained a very considerable advantage. However the days pass albeit disastrously, &amp; the Russians [sic] hordes are steadily coming forward in East Prussia.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After tea I took the <persName xml:id="1608">Bishop</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi><persName xml:id="1607" display="no"> Mann</persName> with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3263">Lillington</persName> to see Finchale Priory. Since my first visit with Car&#x00F6;e, a good deal has been done in the way of rescuing the ruins from the ivy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> is reported to have stated in the House of Commons this afternoon that the British losses at the recent conflict were more than 2000 killed &amp; wounded.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning's post brought me a letter from an American lady, named Buxton, reporting that <persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> were on their way back to England by way of the Rhine, &amp; were being held up by the German authorities on the Dutch border. They hoped to be allowed to pass, though some informality in their passports was creating a difficulty. I shall be devoutly thankful when these poor ladies are safely in the country again.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
