<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I presided at the Chapter&#8211;meeting, where everything was amicable enough. We accepted <persName xml:id="2459">Bishop Mitchinson's</persName> gift of a bound volume of notes, sketches, and photographs, of the older churches of the Bishopric, &amp; I undertook to write a formal letter of thanks. We also agreed that the cases in the library which contain the Cuthbert Relics, &amp; the episcopal rings should be regarded as '<hi rend="underline">taboo</hi>', so far as opening them by our pass&#8211;key is concerned. We agreed to employ <persName xml:id="3526" display="no">Gaymer</persName> for the work in the cathedral.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I shewed a party of Freemasons over the Cathedral &#8211; stout men of the upper artisan &amp; lower middle class type. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I attended Evensong.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">We dined with the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName>, with whom were staying tomorrow's preacher, <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>, &amp; his <persName xml:id="992" display="no">wife</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">. Wilson and the <persName xml:id="2837">Pembertons</persName><persName xml:id="2843"></persName> were also there. We had a brisk discussion of the situation in Ireland. Rather to my surprise, I found myself (save for the silent sympathy of Wilson) alone against the three New College men. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is wonderful to me how sanguinary &amp; tyrannous Radical parsons become as soon as their projects are seriously opposed</hi><hi rend="italic">. Their political categories are too few &amp; too simple for the facts of life &amp; the minds of men. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received an excellent letter from <persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName>.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
