<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The day was chilly and damp, according well with the melancholy mood in which I set out for Oxford on the saddest of errands &#8211; to attend the funeral of my dear &amp; honoured friend, <persName xml:id="228">the Warden</persName>. I found the College filled with the Fellows, all showing signs of a genuine sorrow. The Sub&#8211;Warden, <persName xml:id="1008">Simon</persName>, was doing his sad duty well: he gave up a Cabinet meeting to hasten to All Souls, as soon as the dreadful tidings of the Warden's death reached him. </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName> had expressed a wish that <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> &amp; I should take part in the service: and so I hurried out into the town, &amp; bought a cassock, surplice, &amp; scarf. Then I returned to the college, &amp;</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> joined the Fellows in escorting the Coffin from the House to the Chapel, where <persName xml:id="2407">Johnson</persName> read Evensong: <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> read S. John XIV. As a special lesson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I had some talk with <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> about the vacant wardenship. The College has an extraordinarily difficult task to perform in finding a successor to Anson. His many&#8211;sided excellence makes him literally irreplaceable. Also I had a short talk with </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="66">Frank Pember</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic">. We agreed that we could recall no fault in the Warden. Differences of opinion with him we could remember, but never a fault. It is very wonderful.</hi>
         </p>
        
            </body></text></TEI>
