<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
Iam liber erat animus meus a curis mordacibus ambiendi, et adquirendi, et volutandi atque scalpendi scabiem libidinum: et garriebam tibi, claritati meoe et divitiis et saluti meoe, domino deo meo.<note xml:id="178" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
A 'sudden conversion' from sensual habits of thought and life needs no other authentication than itself. S. Augustine says that in his case nothing less had come to him than a prompt &amp; final liberation from the desires &amp; practices of long&#8211;accustomed sensuality. This truly is the miracle of Christianity, &amp; it lies open to none of the cavils of the critics.</p>
         <p>
I attended Mattins in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> preached on the discipline of the tongue, a good sermon but delivered with so little animation &amp; fervour as to leave a far smaller impression than its merits deserved. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> celebrated. I communicated &amp; ministered the chalice. There were but 8 communicants apart from the clergy. These included <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>, who looks more like Friar Tuck than ever!</p>
         <p>
I observe that two new nests are being constructed in our trees.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[139] </hi><hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Sunday post brought me two invitations, the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">one from <persName xml:id="2166">Prof. S&#x00F6;derblom</persName> to lecture on "Anglicanism",</hi><hi rend="italic"> the other from the Missionary Society of the U.F. College in Glasgow, to be their president for the coming year. These invitations illustrate the singular position which I have come to occupy in the religious world.</hi></p>
         <p>
Rashdall &amp; his <persName xml:id="992" display="no">wife</persName> came to lunch, &amp; <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> came also.</p>
         <p>
I attended Evensong in the Cathedral. Prayers for escape from 'the guilt &amp; calamity of civil war' were offered. Rashdall preached a sermon on 2.Cor: VI.I. "working together with Him". His sermon was execrably delivered.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We motored to Bishop Middleham, where I preached to a crowded church. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In the pulpit was an hour glass. It had been set there by Colonel Surtees, &amp; was (as I understood him to say) used by Wesley</hi><hi rend="italic">. We had supper in the Vicarage after service, &amp; then motored home, arriving about 9 p.m.</hi></p>

            </body></text></TEI>
