<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I worked at the sermon for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's, but with little success.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon, I presided at a Drawing Room Meeting which </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the <persName xml:id="2174">Bishop of Uganda</persName> addressed</hi><hi>: and, when the company had dispersed, I took him for a walk.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop dined with me. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> having gone to a meeting at Darlington, we were alone &amp; had much conversation about Uganda. He says that the population is still declining, largely through the ravages of venereal disease. No less than 75 per cent of the children born die as infants. This frightful spread of disease he attributes to the new facilities of intercourse between the tribes &amp; Europeans through the 'opening up' of the country, operating on the chronic licentiousness of the people. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He had himself persuaded the chiefs to adopt vigorous measures against illicit sexual relations</hi><hi rend="italic"> &#8211; the 'boy' was to be flogged, &amp; the girl's father to pay a fine to the chief &#8211; &amp; this had immediately affected the situation for good: but an appeal having been made to the British resident, he disallowed both flogging and fine as illegal.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
