<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Bishopthorpe.</hi></p>
         <p>
I got up in time for Mattins &amp; Holy Communion in the Chapel. After breakfast I motored in to York with <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>; &amp; spent the day (with a brief interval for lunch with the old <persName xml:id="2429">Dean of York</persName>) in <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>, being all the while miserably incommoded by headache. <hi rend="bold underline">I made four short speeches</hi> (1) on the question whether the Marriage Service might be used in the case of mixed marriages. A fanatical Ritualist from Middlesborough [sic], Burn, moved a resolution in a large &amp; truculent speech. It was about to be accepted unanimously when I intervened, &amp; finally it was agreed to ask for a joint&#8211;committee to inquire. (2) Welldon moved a resolution calling for an early answer to Letters of Business. I spoke against him, &amp; finally induced a modification of his motion. (3) I spoke shortly &amp; strongly against sales of next presentations: and (4) I spoke against Temperance Legislation, on the motion to support a Sunday closing Bill for England.<note xml:id="172" n="1"></note> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Welldon &amp; I walked back to Bishopthorpe.</hi></p>
         <p>
I sate between the <persName xml:id="477">Bishop of Liverpool</persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bickersteth at dinner, &amp; had much pleasant conversation with both. <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> &amp; I had some talk after dinner. As soon as prayers were over, I went to bed.</p>

            </body></text></TEI>
