<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
The "Times" reports the death of the <persName xml:id="1146">Duke of Argyll</persName>, &amp; of <persName xml:id="323">Silvester Horne</persName>. The first was expected: the last was tragically sudden. He had just been seeing Niagara, &amp; was found dead in his chair. Apparently he had given the Lyman Beecher Lectures on "Preaching" at Yale.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote a brief &amp; hostile review of <persName xml:id="3533">Wickham Legg's</persName> new book on 'English Church Life from the Restoration to the Tractarian Movement', &amp; sent it to the 'Manchester Guardian'.</hi></p>
         <p>
I attended Evensong in the Cathedral.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to <persName xml:id="3023" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Soltau Simmons</persName> &amp; met there <persName xml:id="3530">Major</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3531">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fishbourne</persName>. Then we went on to call on the <persName xml:id="3528">Salvins
</persName><persName xml:id="3529"></persName>, &amp; spent the rest of the afternoon in seeing their house &amp; gardens. They are Papists, &amp; have lived on that property since the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Tuesday, May 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1914, my wife and I went to York for the Convocation, and were entertained by the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> at Bishopthorpe. The Bishops of <persName xml:id="276">Durham</persName>, <persName xml:id="242">Manchester</persName>, <persName xml:id="1132">Newcastle</persName>, <persName xml:id="477">Liverpool</persName>, <persName xml:id="720">Carlisle</persName>, <persName xml:id="3229">Sodor &amp; Man</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3533">Sheffield</persName> were also staying at the Palace, &amp; of ladies <persName xml:id="3173">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knox</persName>, <persName xml:id="2797">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Moule</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3534" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3535" display="no">Miss Burrows</persName>. The conversation was, perhaps, rather more serious than usual on such occasions, for <hi rend="bold underline">all the bishops were laden with numerously signed petitions against "modernism"</hi>. I did my best to make them see that they ought to do nothing, and rather snub than encourage the busy&#8211;bodies who are trying to work up a 'heresy&#8211;hunt'. Certainly, their Lordships would <hi rend="underline">like</hi> to do nothing, but they are mortally afraid of their clergy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lang and I had a long talk on Thursday night. He expressed himself very fairly, &amp; assured me that he was resolved to resist any attempts at 'heresy&#8211;hunting'. I pressed him to take his courage in both hands, &amp; rebuke the petitioners. The Upper House at the Archbishop's bidding adjourned </hi><hi rend="italic underline">sine die</hi><hi rend="italic"> any discussion on the petitions, thereby showing itself wiser than the Southern Bishops, who passed a long series of question&#8211;begging resolutions. </hi></p>
         <p>
On Friday, May 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, Ella went to London, &amp; I returned to Durham.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Newcastle told me that <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> personal intervention at the last moment hindered the Lambeth Conference from agreeing to a recognition of Presbyterian Orders. The circumstances added force to his words: for Gore was recovering from an operation at the time: he was carried into the assembly on a litter, and jerked out a threat that he would resign his see if any recognition of a non&#8211;episcopal ministry were made. To that threat the Conference immediately surrendered. The substance of all this accords with what I was told by the American bishops, but the dramatic circumstance of his entrance was new.</hi></p>
            </body></text></TEI>
