<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>

         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi></p>
         <p>
A very stormy morning with deluges of rain: but later the weather cleared, &amp; there was sunshine.</p>
         <p>
I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were exactly 36 communicants.</p>
         <p>
At Mattins I preached in S. Margaret's, addressing myself mainly to young men, 'old boys' of the parochial school. <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> read the Litany. I preached a sermon, which had been originally composed for a congregation of young men, on Christian Liberty. Save for the coughing of some small children, I was listened to with very close attention.</p>
         <p>
M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Erith, the Vice&#8211;Principal of S. Chad's College, a very feeble looking creature, came to lunch, in order to meet <persName xml:id="642">Sir Peile Thompson</persName> who, as a subscriber to the college, wished to see how his money was expended!</p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Brandon Parish Church, &amp; there preached to a full congregation. The parson is evidently a Ritualist, &amp; there were not wanting factors of provocation: but the service was reverent, &amp; congregational. After I had suppressed some coughing, there was fairly close attention. </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
On Thursday, the 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> February, I went to London, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">stayed the night with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> at Westminster</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Friday morning, the 27</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, I </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">attended a deputation to the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> arguing the importance of National Service. <persName xml:id="218">Lord Roberts</persName> introduced the deputation, &amp; several members of it including myself, made speeches</hi><hi rend="italic">. The P.M. was not very encouraging.</hi></p>
         <p>
I lunched at the <persName xml:id="89" display="no">Athenaeum</persName>, and attended Evensong at the Abbey. Then I went to Oxford, rejoicing en route in a sunsetting of incomparable splendour. The Bursar's Dinner was an enjoyable function. <hi rend="italic">I stayed with the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> at All Souls until Monday afternoon. On Saturday evening I dined with the <persName xml:id="1170">Master of Balliol</persName>. On Sunday (March 1</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic">) I attended the sermon in S. Mary's &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">heard an excellent discourse from <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName>, the incriminated author of the <ref xml:id="715" display="no">Essay</ref> in 'Foundations</hi><hi rend="italic">'. After service I walked to the Orchard, &amp; had speech with <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>. <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName> was staying there. I lunched with <persName xml:id="41">Harry Davis</persName>, &amp; had much talk with Streeter. Later in the afternoon I walked round the Parks with <persName xml:id="652">Compton</persName>: &amp; then </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">went to Balliol, where I preached in the college chapel on "Gamaliel &amp; S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Paul</hi><hi rend="italic">". I dined in All Souls: &amp; on Monday, attended <persName xml:id="583">Driver's</persName> Funeral in Christ Church.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
There was a great <hi rend="underline">gathering</hi> of the University at Driver's funeral. I saw Ryle there, &amp; <persName xml:id="691">Fearon</persName>. After the service I returned to London, &amp; went directly to the Deanery of S. Paul's, where I spent the night. The Brotherhood dined there. Among the rest came <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName>, the Bishop of Southwark. It was all pleasant enough. The next day (Tuesday March 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1914) I returned to Durham, and there entertained the Judges &#8211; <persName xml:id="318">Ridley</persName> &amp; Bankes &#8211; with their marshals at dinner.<note xml:id="173" n="1"></note> On Wednesday March 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I dined with the said Judges in the castle: and on the next day, Thursday March 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I shewed them the Library. That evening we dined quietly with <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falconer</persName>, who lives in the Divinity House hard by the Cathedral. <hi rend="italic bold underline">He confessed himself a member of the Baconian Sect in the matter of Shakespeare</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi><note xml:id="174" n="1"></note> <hi rend="italic">In that house there is the ghost of a murdered schoolboy who looks over the bannisters disconcertingly! </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi></p>
         <p>
In "a representation of the lower house of convocation about the bishop of Bangor's sermon of the kingdom of Christ" (May 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1717) there is a recognition of the Sovereign's 'headship' of the church:&#8211;</p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
"That whereas his majesty is, &amp; by the statutes of this realm is declared to be, supreme heard of the church &amp;c."</p>
         <p>
<hi>[v. Cardwell's Synodalia. ii. 838]</hi></p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
On Saturday, the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March, 1914, I presided at the Chapter meeting. We decided to give May &#x00A3;50 in lieu of a house: &amp; also to get plans for making one of the canonical houses, now let to tenants, into two smaller houses for use by the Minor Canons. Also, we resolved forthwith to carry out the works recommended by the <persName xml:id="648">two architects</persName><persName xml:id="3444"></persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Later I travelled to Edinburgh</hi>, being accompanied as far as Newcastle by <persName xml:id="2918">Captain Apperley</persName>. <persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName> received me very kindly. He had drawn together a pleasant company for dinner. There were <persName xml:id="1140">Paterson</persName>, <persName xml:id="2026">Kelman</persName>, <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName>, <persName xml:id="2049">Sir Andrew Fraser</persName>, Welsh, &amp; two others. <hi rend="bold underline">We had much conversation about Kikuyu</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Kelman had just returned from Oxford, where he had met the <persName xml:id="49">Bishop</persName>. He seems to have heard great reports of my sermon in S. Mary's.</hi> It had divided Oxford &amp;c &amp;c.
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
