<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsuday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Surely never did we come to the Festival of the Holy Spirit with greater &amp; more evident need of Divine Guiding. What to do? &amp; how to do it? &#8211; these questions are pressing for answers, &amp; receiving none. Old sacred phrases are in our minds still, but we can hardly bring ourselves to speak them, so hollow they seem on our lips now, so empty &amp; futile. The best men among us feel the burden most. 'Insincerity' is the shadow of confession, not of denial. We are getting so fretful &amp; suspicious that the old great words of the liturgy wake criticism rather than devotion. The discrepancy between the actual statements and such conscious belief as remains to us is actually tormenting. We seem as we speak to stand outside the Worship and pass judgment on it. Of course there are quasi&#8211;corybantic enthusiasts who find their own fervour &amp; exstasy sufficient security for their faith: but we cannot be as they?  We know too much, and we feel too little. Meanwhile, all the old questions are clamouring for answer: and our lives are slipping away while we toss and moan on our Procrustean Bed! We are not sure enough of anything even to deny!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> &amp; his brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, <persName xml:id="2227">Sir Mackworth Young</persName>, arrived in time for Mattins. The Bishop preached at the Choral Celebration which followed. Both gentlemen lunch [sic] at the Deanery after the services.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After Evensong in the Cathedral I motored to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Gabriel's, Sunderland, and there preached on Jacob's vision. It was the commemoration of the Consecration of the Church. There was a large &amp; attentive congregation: the service was reverent and congregational: and the clergy gave me the impression of devoted &amp; sincere men. I returned to Durham after the service, &amp; arrived at the Deanery about 8.45 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2811">May</persName> in administering the chalice at the Holy Communion made the sign of the cross over every communicant. I called him aside in the Chapter House, &amp; told him that the use of the cathedral did not include that ceremony, &amp; that he must not use it for the future. He said that he had acted 'almost instinctively', and promised not to repeat his action!</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
