<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[265]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Our first naval victory is announced from the neighbourhood of Heligoland. This will hearten up the Navy, which has had a long spell of wearisome vigilance. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">From Belgium comes the horrifying &amp; well–nigh incredible intelligence that the Germans have deliberately burned down Louvain, reducing the University with its treasures to ashes. This is improving on the Napoleonic model. To transport art–treasures to Paris was hateful enough, but to destroy them altogether is equally stupid &amp; cruel</hi>.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch we motored our guests to South Shields and along the coast as far as Seaham Harbour in order that they might see the sinister &amp; unwanted spectacle of the entrenchments cast up on the shore against the attempt to land invaders. Two aeroplanes soaring above us added to the impression of peril.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="412">James Parker Smith</persName> sent me "The Anglo–German Problem" by C. Sarolea, a Belgian author of some note. It is an extremely interesting &amp; illuminating study. As it was written two years ago, it is possible to apply the test of fact to many of its forecasts: and they stand the test surprisingly well. The evil predominance of Prussia in the German world is well emphasized.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
