<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. The Hill School, Pottstown.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am in some confusion &amp; alarm at the prospect of extemporaneous praying &amp; preaching in this School Chapel. After 25 years of ministry it is humiliating to be so helpless with respect to matters which might be supposed to lie within the normal &amp; necessary limits of Christian ministry. But the use of a Liturgy has a paralyzing effect on the English clergyman: &amp; he is probably the most tongue&#8211;tied of Christian ministers! I intend to speak to these boys about the Putumayo Atrocities, using these as an illustration of the dreadful possibilities of greed &amp; irresponsibility. My text is the lawyer's question, "Who is my neighbour?"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Well: the performance is over &#8211; that is at any rate a consolation: but it was NOT a success. I felt futile, and almost absurd: &amp; the boys, though attentive, were evidently not impressed. At 49 one cannot resume the fluency one renounced at 24! I cannot honestly say that I think my service was 'money's worth' for 100 dollars, save possibly for the comfort it may have ministered to these sectaries by confirming in their prejudices against those 'dumb&#8211;dogs' of liturgy&#8211;bound Anglicans! However, the masters afterwards assured me that they had enjoyed the sermon. They seemed to speak sincerely, but, then, what else could they say?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Later in the day we were told that the boys had been much interested in my discourse, &amp; had been discussing it. One smart lad from Tennessee observed that 'the minister ought to have mentioned the <persName xml:id="2815">President</persName>, &amp; seemed to pray for the King as if he had to do it'. Evidently he had placed a mechanical construction on the well&#8211;worn formula which I had introduced into my prayer, 'as in private duty bound.' Another lad remarked that 'the English ministers seemed to speak more about social matters than the American'. This is true, &amp; it reflects two facts &#8211; the effect of Establishment in de&#8211;clericalizing the clergy, &amp; the growth of 'Christian Socialism' in their ranks.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After supper I had some conversation with a young Presbyterian minister, who has charge of the church in Pottstown. In this place with about 14,000 inhabitants there are 24 different 'churches'. Socialism is strong &amp; waxing, mainly among the Germans. The Episcopal Church, thanks to the unpopularity of the minister in charge, had shrunk to but 15 members. This young minister has evidently much to contend with from his own people. He says that Biblical Criticism &amp;c. has not yet dawned on them; they hold to an unsuspecting literalism: &amp; they were all but driven into schism by his use of the gown in the pulpit! His brother had renounced his paternal church, &amp; was now preparing for the Episcopal Ministry.</hi>
         </p>
        
</body></text></TEI>
