<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi>Rain fell heavily during the night, &amp; the morning broke on a sodden landscape, &amp; with a colder atmosphere. For a considerable distance there was a double track, but we were singular before reaching Winnipeg. The train arrived exactly 'on time'. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1095">Aubrey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName> were waiting on the platform to welcome us</hi>.
         </p>
         <p><hi>I found letters from Minneapolis inviting me to address a civic association, &amp; an assembly of Church people. I sent telegrams consenting to both requests.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">My brother walked into Winnipeg &amp; I purchased an umbrella to take the place of that which I foolishly lost at Niagara. On our return to the house, I was interviewed by a reporter: &amp; then was visited by <persName xml:id="2743">Max Dennistoun</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2744" display="no">his son</persName>.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I lent him the <ref xml:id="662" display="no">Putumayo Blue Book</ref>, as he had not seen it</hi><hi rend="italic">, though he </hi><hi rend="italic underline">had</hi><hi rend="italic"> read the correspondence with the <persName xml:id="2702">Directors</persName><persName xml:id="2705"></persName><persName xml:id="2706" display="no"></persName> in the <ref xml:id="658">"Times" of Aug 24</ref></hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather which, when we were in Toronto, had been so warm that we conjectured that the 'heat&#8211;wave' reported to be prostrating the citizens of Chicago had actually arrived, now changed to be quite cold, so that the cautious Lois caused her husband to gather the blooms on his Geraniums, that the frost might be cheated of some of its victims!</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
