<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, Sept 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>
The weather is milder, <hi rend="bold underline">though we are still glad of the fire</hi>. By some error the carriage ordered overnight failed to arrive, &amp; we hurried to church in some anxiety as to reaching it in time. However we were at Holy Trinity at least 3 minutes before service time. <persName xml:id="2750">Archdeacon Fortin</persName> took the service, which included a special litany <hi rend="bold underline">designed to prepare the way for the 'Mission of Help' which is to begin next week. There was a very large congregation, including (as I observed with satisfaction) a large proportion of men. I read the lessons, &amp; preached from the words: "As the hart panteth after water&#8211;brooks, so panteth my soul after thee, O God". <hi rend="bold underline">After I had suppressed the coughing of a choir&#8211;man, there was silence, and attention</hi>. After service, I spoke shortly to the choir&#8211;men &amp; women. Outside the Church a young couple claimed acquaintance &#8211; <persName xml:id="2769" display="no">Mary Ashmole</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2770" display="no">her husband</persName> &#8211; now citizens of Canada. They had heard me last 15 years ago, in Ilford! There was a reporter in church scribbling away, but I doubt whether he could make much of what I said, probably the words were in many cases unfamiliar &amp; unintelligible.</hi></p>
         <p>
A newspaper telephoned for the loan of the M.S. of the sermon, &amp; &#8211; anticipating my fate at the hands of reporters &#8211; I granted it.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
         <p>
After lunch we walked out for an hour, &amp; then returned to the house. After tea I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName>, <persName xml:id="1266">Ed. Moore</persName>, Gilbert, &amp; <persName xml:id="2739">Fleet</persName>. Also a card to <persName xml:id="1664">Lionel Box</persName>.</p>
         <p>
Divers folks came to supper, mostly relations of <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName>, but including one couple &#8211; <persName xml:id="2922" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName>
<persName xml:id="2923" display="no"><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Weir</persName>&#8211; the first a Presbyterian &amp; the last a Papist &#8211; which interested me. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Weir had, like most of the Canadians one meets, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the most vehement antipathy to the Americans</hi> (i.e. the people in the States): yet, he admitted that war between Great Britain &amp; the Republic could not be looked on as a possible contingency. He enlarged on the care with which the Canadian Government watched the immigration, but admitted that so long as railway construction on a large scale was proceeding, it would be necessary to allow the entrance into the Dominion of such persons as would consent to work as navvies i.e. <hi rend="bold underline">mostly Italians &amp; Galician Poles</hi>. <hi rend="italic">He gave an </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">excellent character to the Mormons, who have a considerable colony in the neighbourhood of Lethbridge;</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; spoke highly of the Mennonite Germans, who appear in some districts to provide most of the leading citizens. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is not a little humiliating to observe that the relative incompetence of the Englishman as a colonist appears to be rather an assumption than a matter for question</hi><hi rend="italic">. Yet I am not quite sure whether this circumstance is altogether so disgraceful to the English character as might appear.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
