<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>
There was a slight improvement in the weather, but the day was sunless &amp; depressing.</p>
         <p>
I preached in the morning at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Luke's Church. There was a very large &amp; very attentive congregation. I preached on Jacob's Vision, intercalating some references to the materialism which obsesses Winnipeg.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We lunched at Government House</hi>. The <persName xml:id="2855">Governor</persName> was absent but <persName xml:id="2856">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cameron</persName> received us. I took her in to lunch, &amp; found her extremely agreeable.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At 3 p.m. I addressed an audience of men only in the 'Auditorium' of Grace Church, a Methodist institution. My subject was 'The Problem of the Alien Immigrant from a Christian point of view'. <persName xml:id="2854" display="no">Prof. Osbern</persName> of <orgName xml:id="222">Wesley College</orgName> took the Chair. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I spoke for 3/4 an hour very plainly, rather to the surprize of my audience, who are accustomed to hear from visitors nothing but eulogiums on Winnipeg, &amp; the limitless prosperity which lies before it</hi><hi rend="italic">. However they were attentive, and applauded the right points.</hi></p>
         <p>
I preached at All Saints at Evensong. The Church was thronged. I was assured that as many as 1000 people were squeezed inside a wooden building which was designed to accommodate no more than 800.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Qu'Appelle (</hi><persName xml:id="2851"><hi rend="italic bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Harding</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline">) was present. He spoke to me of the difficulties of the Church in Canada. I replied that the first &amp; most pressing duty of the Church was to find a modus vivendi with the other Protestant Churches</hi><hi rend="italic">. He rejoined with some heat that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that</hi><hi rend="italic"> was out of the question: that no less than 6 non&#8211;episcopal ministers had applied to him for Ordination within the last 12 months: that the non&#8211;episcopal Churches were leavened with Unitarianism: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that everything turned on the Church of England's maintaining a firm front, &amp; making no concessions</hi><hi rend="italic">. I did not reply to all this, because there was no time, &amp; the occasion was unfavourable. But </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I reflected mournfully on the gross blindness which has fallen on the Anglican leaders</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
After the service the Bishop thanked me with some appearance of sincerity for my sermon: &amp; the parson of the Church (<persName xml:id="2848" display="no">Heathcote</persName>) also thanked me.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1095">Aubrey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName> came to supper, also a <persName xml:id="2852" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2853" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kohl</persName>, &amp; another Canadian lady.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2745">Jack Dennistoun</persName> went to the station, and managed the checking of our baggage to Minneapolis.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
