<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Little Metis.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Another beautiful day, bright and windless. We all attended service in the little wooden Presbyterian Church, where I officiated. There was a good congregation, very good in view of the fact that most of the visitors have gone back to Montreal. I read the service set out in the 'Book of Common Order': the hymns &amp; 'Psalm&#8211;selections' were well sung by the people: &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">I preached the sermon from <persName xml:id="505">Dean Stanley's</persName> favourite text</hi>:"<hi rend="underline">I see that all things come to an end, but Thy commandment is exceeding broad</hi>".</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2778"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Professor Hutton</hi></persName> of Toronto &#8211; he has the chair of classics &#8211; came to lunch. He is a nephew of <persName xml:id="2825">Hutton</persName> of the 'Spectator', was a fellow of Merton, came out here after taking his degree in 1880, and has stuck to the country ever since. We walked out to the lighthouse together after lunch, &amp; had much interesting conversation, though perhaps he was so eager to discuss English politics, that I did not gain as much information about Canadian affairs as might fairly have been expected. He told me that about the end of October the light was put out in the lighthouse, &amp; the buoys taken up from the river, which the winter closed to navigation until the spring. We met the <persName xml:id="2826" display="no">old Scotchman</persName> who is the 'squire' or seigneur of Metis. <hi rend="italic">He told me that there was a colony of Highlanders in the district, which had not yet wholly abandoned their ancestral Gaelic.</hi></p>
</body></text></TEI>
