<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Toronto.</hi></p>
         <p>We walked round to see <persName xml:id="2881" display="no">Edith Ripley</persName>, &amp; the new house into which she &amp; <persName xml:id="2882" display="no">her husband</persName> are establishing themselves. It is small enough, but sufficient &amp; well&#8211;arranged. <hi rend="bold underline">The bull&#8211;dog &amp; its little mistress are irresistibly comic or pathetic as the mood strikes one</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The loneliness of female life in this immense country is terrible.</p>
         <p>Next we were driven by <persName xml:id="2906" display="no">Miss Baldwin</persName> into the city. We called on <persName xml:id="2757"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Knox</hi></persName> in her college for girls. The good lady seemed glad to see us, &amp; insisted on shewing us over her establishment. It appeared to be efficient, commodious, &amp; flourishing. Through the telephone she arranged for an interview with <persName xml:id="2907"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon Cody</hi></persName><hi>, to whose house we next proceeded. There I found </hi><persName xml:id="2908"><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> O'Meara</hi></persName><hi> in conference with the Archdeacon. We had some conversation about the ecclesiastical situation in Canada. I tried to indicate to them that in my view there were other &amp; deeper questions which ought to interest Christian clergymen than those which filled the minds of the Canadian factions. Cody is a well&#8211;built, vigorous man, (like <persName xml:id="2909">Swayne</persName> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's Cranley Gardens to look at) who enjoys the dangerous reputation of a popular preacher. He was nearly elected Bp. of Toronto, but the High Church fellows just beat him in the clerical vote, &amp; <persName xml:id="2910">a non&#8211;committal duffer</persName> was made bishop! He took me to see the fine new Church which <hi rend="bold">[50]</hi> he was building. It will accomodate [sic] 2300 people on the floor.</p>
         <p>After lunch we were motored through and about Toronto, in a car kindly lent to us by <persName xml:id="2911" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Macdonald</persName>, our host's sister&#8211;in&#8211;law. The roads are excellent, and compare advantageously with the execrable ways of Montreal. I was impressed by the great extent of the city, &amp; by the evidences of prosperity which the long lines of well&#8211;built &amp; comfortable mansions provided. The cement pillars which carry the telegraph wires, &amp; the electric lamps are a conspicuous feature of the streets: &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">the gaunt steel erections which convey the current from Niagara force the observer to remember at what sacrifice of natural beauty the conveniences of Toronto are provided.</hi> We had tea pleasantly with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Macdonald, &amp; then betook ourselves homewards to our packing.  Our host's <persName xml:id="2912" display="no">brother</persName> came to dinner. <hi rend="italic">We discussed the tiresome &amp; difficult question of the liquor trade. He allowed that drunkenness was increasing in Canada, &amp; attributed the fact mainly to the incoming emigrants</hi> <hi>[sic]</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was interested in the Putumayo Episodes, &amp; read through the <ref xml:id="658">'Times' article</ref>. Then we made our way to the Railway Station, being accompanied thither by <persName xml:id="2905" display="no">our host</persName>. We left Toronto for Winnipeg at 10.20 p.m.<p></p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
