<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. En route for Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>
We passed the night tolerably. The new arrangement of sleepers is wonderfully convenient, though of course there is little comfort &amp; less cleanliness. Our position in the 'observation' car was more than commonly exposed to the motion of the train: writing was all but impossible, as this page attests. We breakfasted about 8.30 a.m. at a cost (including the tip) of 1.75. <hi rend="bold underline">The dust thrown up by the train made the observation car practically useless, &amp; the motion was so violent that letter&#8211;writing became a physical impossibility</hi>. Thus the journey tended to become very tiresome. The country through which we travelled was monotonously varied, stone thinly wooded, or burnt out trees alternating with lakes. It is but a single line furnished at intervals with sidings. The darkie who attended on our car made us a pot of tea, which was not supplied before 6 p.m. on the dining car. It may be inferred that English visitors are not yet the dominant factor in the tourist traffic to British Columbia.</p>
         <p>
About 6 p.m. the weather had changed for the worse: it began to rain, a circumstance which, if it added to our gloom, at least mitigated the plague of dust. <hi rend="bold underline">I beguiled the way by reading </hi><persName xml:id="2921"><hi rend="bold underline">von H&#x00FC;gel's</hi></persName> <ref xml:id="683"><hi rend="bold underline">"The Mystical Element of Religion as studied in S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Catherine of Genoa &amp; her friends"</hi></ref> &#8211; a book of great significance &amp; interest but difficult to read with due understanding in my present circumstances. However I had no other literature in my bag.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
