<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
     <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Little Metis.</hi></p>
         <p>
The day was cloudy at the start, but improved steadily, &amp; wound up with a fine &amp; promising sunset, the image of a human life which begins in misfortune, gathers strength by experience, &amp; ends in dignity &amp; repose. <persName xml:id="2739">Mine host</persName> carried me after breakfast to the store, the true centre of the common life where the gossips assembled to discuss all matters of interest &amp; to purchase all needful commodities. We viewed the golf course, &amp; tennis court, obtained the Montreal newspaper, &amp; then returned to the house, where I established myself in a separate room &amp; started work on my Boston lectures</p>
         <p>
After lunch <persName xml:id="2742"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Judge Greenshields</hi></persName> called; I showed him my correspondence with the <persName xml:id="2702">Putumayo directors</persName><persName xml:id="2705"></persName><persName xml:id="2706" display="no"></persName>, &amp; lent him the <ref xml:id="662" display="no">Blue&#8211;book</ref>. Then we went for a drive along the river shore, admiring the views. On our return, I again did an hour at the Lectures.</p>
         <p>
After dinner we went to a musical party. There were two Canadian professors there &#8211; one from Kingston, the other from Toronto &#8211; with whom I had some talk.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Toronto, they said, was both the most intensely British, &amp; the most completely Americanised town in Canada: the proximity of the Republic explained the one fact, the commercial activity of the City explained the other. For the norm of business methods is that of the States. </hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
