<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>
Today we transferred ourselves from 503 Wardlaw Avenue to 166 Roslyn R<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi>, from the hospitality of a brother to that of a cousin. The weather changed for the worse: &amp; there was a great rain.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Before leaving I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="600"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ernest Rudling</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">: also to Minneapolis about arrangements.</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2848" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Heathcote</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his </hi><persName xml:id="2849" display="no">churchwarden</persName><hi rend="italic"> called on me &#8211; a somewhat belated civility, as I am to preach for him on Sunday evening. He struck me as a feeble man, with no notions beyond those which may filter into his mind from his immediate environment. I heard of him subsequently as having dabbled unsuccessfully in real estate. This is, indeed 'to make the worst of both worlds'. It ought to be a fixed rule of the church in this country that the clergy are not permitted to speculate: of course such a rule would in equity have to be conditioned by their receiving a sufficient &amp; secure stipend. As things now stand, they appear to be grossly underpaid, &amp; are casting about for the means to live.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2743">Max Dennistoun</persName> entertained me in the Club at tea: &amp; then we motored home. In conversation, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he mentioned that the parson&#8211;novelist <persName xml:id="2850">'Ralph Connor'</persName> had told him that for the copyright of one of his books, he had received from the publishers no less a sum than 75,000 dollars &#8211; a larger sum than <persName xml:id="2732" display="no">Lord Beaconsfield</persName> received for <ref xml:id="651">'Endymion'</ref></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
