<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. White Marsh.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A beautiful fine day. We made our farewells, and left Pottstown by the 8.45 train reaching Philadelphia about 11 a.m. Here we recovered our baggage, and took train for White Marsh, where we were to be the guests of <persName xml:id="2898" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Toland</persName>. At the station I was addressed by a Presbyterian Minister named Mutch, who said he had seen me in Edinburgh.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After tea we were taken for a motor drive. The country is undulating &amp; well&#8211;wooded, much like some districts in England. The chauffer with whom I spoke, was a taciturn but intelligent man. He thinks that <persName xml:id="2815">Taft</persName> will hold the President's chair.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In Philadelphia we watched with interest the numerous pigeons in front of the municipal buildings being fed by a citizen. The birds treated him with the utmost familiarity: &amp; when he moved away, followed him for some distance. I recalled with melancholy the diminution in number of our Westminster pigeons, once so numerous &amp; cheerful, &amp; I wondered whether <persName xml:id="1208">Gilbert Box</persName> had fulfilled his promise to feed them daily.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We spent half an hour in a picture gallery, but found it very uninteresting. There were many portraits, but save for those of <persName xml:id="2963" display="no">Washington</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2964" display="no">Benjamin Franklin</persName>, they were mostly of local worthies, whose name &amp; fame were unknown to us. We were struck by the number &amp; size of the automobile works, &amp; other engineering shops.</hi>
         </p>
        
</body></text></TEI>
