<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather today has been all that one could wish. There has been no wind, a cloudless sky, and bright sun. In the morning I busied myself with those abominable Lectures, which seem more unworthy every time I look at them: and with writing letters declining invitations to lecture in one part of London, &amp; to attend &amp; address meetings at another. I also wrote to <persName xml:id="800">Westlake</persName>, who appears to be so absorbed in his love affairs as to find no time to send me any news<hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My Budget this morning included a charming letter from <persName xml:id="2166">Professor S&#x00F6;derblom</persName>, and a long &amp; racy letter from old <persName xml:id="2932">Sir Clements Markham</persName> anent the Peruvian atrocities</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He sets forward his objections to missions, especially those of dissenters, with great vigour &amp; vivacity. To a large extent I must needs agree with him. <hi rend="bold underline">I observe that the weekly edition of the 'Times' for Aug: 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> contained both an abbreviated edition of my <ref xml:id="668" display="no">signed article on 'Black Bartholomew'</ref>, and the friendly leader on <ref xml:id="658">'the Putumayo question'</ref> which had appeared in the daily issue for Aug 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi>. In the afternoon the afore&#8211;mentioned Lawyer motored us round the city &amp; through the spacious (600 acres) and beautiful municipal park, in which we saw a few specimens of the Bison &amp; other Canadian Fauna. We left cards on the <persName xml:id="2933">Abp:</persName> had tea with <persName xml:id="2934" display="no">Mrs Binnington</persName>: a walk with <persName xml:id="1095">Aubrey</persName>: dinner at home, &amp; so to bed.
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
