<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi></p>
         <p>
The weather has improved, but, though the rain has ceased, the clouds remain heavy &amp; threatening. After breakfast I prepared notes for my oration to the <orgName xml:id="216">Women's Canadian Club</orgName>, and also for the oration in Grace Church tomorrow afternoon. Also I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="1670">Reggie Woodyear</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName>.</p>
         <p>
There was a crowd of ladies at the Alexandra H&#x00F4;tel. I spoke for 40 minutes: &amp;, though the majority applauded, there was a strong hostile minority, which had to exercise self&#8211;suppression. <persName xml:id="2754" display="no">Miss Jones</persName>, the Head of the <orgName xml:id="218" display="no">Girls Training College</orgName> (a branch of <persName xml:id="2757">Miss Knox's</persName> institution at Toronto), presided very effectively.</p>
         <p>
Afterwards I paid away 30 dollars for our railway tickets from Winnipeg to Minneapolis.</p>
         <p>
We dined with <persName xml:id="2755" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2756" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Jones</persName>. I presented the Doctor with a copy of <ref xml:id="82">'Puritanism in England'</ref>. The <persName xml:id="2750">Archdeacon</persName> &amp; old <persName xml:id="2758">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dennistoun</persName> were the other guests. Our conversation was mainly about ecclesiastical affairs. Fortin does not impress me as a strong or lofty type of clergyman, but he has been a long time here, &amp; has known most of the people. <hi rend="italic bold underline">He says that the <orgName xml:id="219" display="no">Mission of Help</orgName> has been the occasion of much heart&#8211;burning: &amp; that Sacerdotal Anglicanism is practically a complete failure among the colonists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
