<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
It were better to be a Galley slave to a Turk than under the Spanish Inquisition. I would rather fall into the hands of a swaggering Good&#8211;fellow and notorious sinner, in a point of danger or disgrace, than stand to the mercy of a formal professor, &amp; proud Pharisee. Though the notorious sinner be further distant from the Christian in degrees of some kinds of goodness, than the formal Hypocrite, yet many times he is not so opposite in extremity of malice &amp; height of disdain.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2947"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robert Bolton</hi></persName> <ref xml:id="660">'A discourse about the State of true Happiness'</ref>. p.189 [A.D. 1631].
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
I walked into the City, and changed a cheque (&#x00A3;20) at the Bank. Then I wrote to <persName xml:id="2678">Lady Limerick</persName>, <persName xml:id="2691" display="no">Clarence</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon I attended a meeting of the Committee of the <orgName xml:id="213">Anti&#8211;Slavery &amp; Aborigines Protection Society</orgName> with reference to the Putumayo affair. I read to them the correspondence which has passed between me &amp; the solicitors of the <persName xml:id="2702">English Directors</persName><persName xml:id="2705"></persName><persName xml:id="2706" display="no"></persName>. </hi>Returning to my study I wrote a long letter to <persName xml:id="325">the Dean</persName> mainly about the question of <persName xml:id="824">General Booth's</persName> fitness to be buried in the Abbey. I <hi rend="bold">[15]</hi> decided against my feelings <hi rend="bold underline">that it would be a wise &amp; defensible procedure to offer burial</hi>. The Dean will probably have to take a decision on the subject very quickly, for the old man is reported to be dying.</p>
         <p>
I wrote cheques paying up all the tradesmen until last Saturday.</p>
         <p>
Then I went to Euston and met <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> returning from Glasgow. The train ran into the station almost exactly to time.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received a letter from </hi><persName xml:id="2687"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Harris</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the Secretary of the Anti&#8211;Slavery &amp;c. S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">y</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">asking permission to publish the correspondence between me and the Putumayo Directors, &amp; also giving me the address of </hi><persName xml:id="2700"><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline"> Hardenberg</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the American whose <ref xml:id="661" display="no">disclosures published in "Truth"</ref> first brought to light the abominations which have now been officially certified by the <ref xml:id="662" display="no">Blue&#8211;book</ref></hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hardenberg's address is</p>
         <p>
<hi>c/o <persName xml:id="2701">J. Grant MacGregor Esq</persName></hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>Red Deer</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>Alberta</hi></p>
         <p>
I wrote at once to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harris to say that I was content that the Society should make any use they would of the correspondence.</p>
       
</body></text></TEI>
