<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Winnipeg.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A reporter from the "Winnipeg Tribune" came to see me about 9.15 a.m. He was named <persName xml:id="2925" display="no">Stubbs</persName>, &amp; said he was connected with the bishops of <persName xml:id="2924">Oxford</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="647">Truro</persName>, &amp; had a cousin in <persName xml:id="2926">Brightman</persName> of the <orgName xml:id="225">Pusey House</orgName>.</p>
         <p>Then I was called to the telephone to communicate my views on the religious situation in Great Britain! I discoursed a few platitudes on the Welsh question. For the rest of the morning I worked very unsuccessfully at those Lectures which are becoming a night mare.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon <persName xml:id="1095">Aubrey</persName> &amp; I walked into the City. There I changed a cheque for &#x00A3;25 on my letter of credit, &amp; sent &#x00A3;10 to Montreal to retain berths in the 'Baltic' for our return to England on Nov. 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Next I went to a Barber's &amp; was shaved &amp; shampooed. The artist who performed on my head said that he had been 32 years in Winnipeg. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He tried to sell me real estate in the intervals of his professional activity</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi><hi rend="italic"> There was a plot of 50 feet frontage at 25 dollars a foot, which I might have at once! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This place reeks with the talk of speculators in 'real estate'</hi><hi rend="italic">; and one overhears calculations in dollars at every corner!</hi> The papers are so full of the <orgName xml:id="226">Oddfellows</orgName>, of whom some 25000 are said to be visiting the town, that everything else is crowded out.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="1812">Angel Colenso</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="113">Harold Knowling</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName> had arranged a little dinner party. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I was interested in the conversation of a lawyer, who described with knowledge &amp; intelligence the conditions under which the citizens of Winnipeg own motors &amp; grow rich. The whole population appears to be mortgaged &amp; gambling in 'real estate'</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I inquired where in the whole process there entered that element of honest work, which alone could give a moral basis for any material prosperity. He answered that honest work entered </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nowhere</hi><hi rend="italic"> into the process! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner we got on to the subject of Putumayo</hi><hi rend="italic">; &amp; I found that not only did he know nothing of the <ref xml:id="662" display="no">Blue&#8211;book</ref>, but had the vaguest notion of the whole question. Indeed, I noticed a constraint in his manner which seemed to disclose a certain resentment against the very notion of publicly criticizing a director! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My brother tells me that he suspects that my rough handling of the <persName xml:id="2702">Putumayo Directors</persName><persName xml:id="2705"></persName><persName xml:id="2706" display="no"></persName> meets with scant approval in Winnipeg where a rigid application of my doctrine as to the responsibility of Directors would probably work wide&#8211;spread havock</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="2927">The Dean</persName> of the little Anglican cathedral dined also &#8211; a small mild man with the sleekness &amp; deprecatory aspect of a well&#8211;bred guinea&#8211;pig &#8211; assuredly not the kind of man to represent effectively the Moral Law in a society of dollar worshipping speculators in 'real estate' such as this which boasts &amp; hustles on this prairie.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
