<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Little Metis.</hi></p>
         <p>
The morning was beautifully fine, the air fresh &amp; warm, &amp; the aspect of everything delightful. I started work again on the <ref xml:id="671">Lectures</ref>, but the noise of the maids packing up the furniture against the winter, disturbed me, and about noon I wandered forth into the sunshine &amp; took some photographs. The newspapers report that Labour day in Montreal was disgraced by an extraordinary amount of drunkenness: there being no less than 121 cases to be dealt with by the magistrate on the following day. <hi rend="italic">I received a telegram from the Y.M.C.A. in Montreal asking me to address a 'mass meeting' on Sunday afternoon, &amp; begging me to wire reply &amp; send subject. I sent a telegram stating that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I would address the young men on the Putumayo atrocities</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> We went to tea with <persName xml:id="2832" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2833" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Grier</persName>. There I had some conversation with <persName xml:id="2834" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wardrope</persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Grier's father, an aged Presbyterian minister, 94 years old, the oldest in the Dominion. He was remarkably alert &amp; well&#8211;posted, &amp; remembered the past with astonishing fulness &amp; accuracy. He spoke of <persName xml:id="2835">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Chalmers</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2836">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Candlish</persName> as men whom he had personally known. I gave the old gentleman a copy of my <ref xml:id="376">"Lee" lecture</ref>, which he appeared much gratified at receiving.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p>
M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Grier shewed me his house &amp; garden with much simple vanity. He had designed the one, &amp; laid out the other: clearly he had made a hobby of the work of his hands. He gave me the impression of the true colonist type, able, arduous, aggressive, strong in elementary virtues, entrenched in na&iuml;ve prejudices, exempt from enfeebling or exalting sentiments. He seemed to pursue some mild proselytising among the French <hi rend="underline">habitans</hi>. Thus he told me that he had given a French Testament to one of them, who was in his employment, charging him to read it, &amp; by no means to surrender it to the priest. All went well enough <hi rend="underline">until the good man's wife died. Then the priest pointed the obvious moral of the incident. The Testament was immolated: &amp; the penitent abstained for two years from any intercourse with his Tempter</hi>! <hi rend="italic">On our way homewards we stopped at a tent whereon a notice announced that it was tenanted by John Denis 'an experienced guide &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Moose&#8211;caller</hi><hi rend="italic">'. The last is a profession which must be confined to this continent. Here we purchased from an old Indian woman some trifles. The Moose&#8211;caller explained that the horn was used in his work.</hi> So we brought an extremely agreeable &amp; restful visit to an end. Tomorrow we must away to Quebec.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
