<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Montreal.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most glorious day. <hi rend="bold underline">I preached in the Crescent S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Presbyterian Church</hi>. The minister, <persName xml:id="2842" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dickie</hi></persName>, conducted the service; I read the first lesson: &amp; <persName xml:id="2885" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Campbell</hi></persName>, an ex&#8211;Moderator of the Presbyterian Church in Canada, read the second. I preached from 1. Sam: iii. I "<hi rend="underline">The word of the Lord was precious in these days: there was no open vision</hi>". There was large congregation, in which the men were numerous, &amp; the young men conspicuous.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In the afternoon I addressed a large meeting of men in the new buildings of the Y.M.C.A. </hi><persName xml:id="2268"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Prof. Adams</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> presided. My theme was the Putumayo Atrocities. Just before I left the house I was shown an <ref xml:id="684" display="no">ill&#8211;natured paragraph</ref> in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Montreal Standard</hi><hi rend="italic"> stating that the <persName xml:id="2702">Directors</persName><persName xml:id="2705"></persName><persName xml:id="2706" display="no"></persName> of the</hi> <orgName xml:id="214"><hi rend="italic">Peruvian Amazon C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">y</hi></orgName> <hi rend="italic">had cleared themselves of responsibility, &amp; that I was 'exploiting' the atrocities in the search for 'notoriety'. I read out this paragraph, &amp; answered it by reading the last paragraph of the </hi><ref xml:id="658"><hi rend="italic">leader in the Times for Aug: 24</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi></ref><hi rend="italic">. Mine audience listened with admirably close attention, &amp; applauded heartily at the end. I handed my M.S. to a Reporter. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">An old Barking lad claimed acquaintance &amp; proved his titles by exhibiting a photograph of a photograph of a football team of which I was President. I myself appeared in the photo, so I could say nothing</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the evening I preached in the Cathedral. There was a great crowd, so that I had to exert myself considerably in order to be heard. However I was assured that everybody <hi rend="underline">did</hi> hear. I chose a sermon which bore on the Union questions. The text was from Revelation: "<hi rend="underline">I saw no temple therein: but the Lord God &amp; the Lamb were the temple Thereof</hi>".</p>
         <p>The man <persName xml:id="2892" display="no">Ender</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2893" display="no">his wife</persName> were in church, &amp; saw me for a few minutes after service. He is a poor creature: &amp; she is no better.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My nephew, <persName xml:id="1097">Harold</persName>, &amp; my 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> cousin, <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, came to see me</hi>. They are both here preparing for their respective careers, as architect &amp; as parson.</p>
         <p>We had supper with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prof: Adams</hi>: but I was too tired to talk intelligently.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Barking man told Prof. Adams that he had walked in to Montreal from Lachine, some 9 miles out, in order to hear me. He spoke with enthusiasm of me, describing me as 'a great man for the working&#8211;man'. This is a pathetic reminder from a past phase of my life. The seven years at Barking were the spring&#8211;time of my ministry, when the motive of work was that 'first love', which can never really be renewed</hi>.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
