<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Pottstown.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We had to advance our watches an hour; &amp;, thus rectified, they recorded 7.20 a.m. when we steamed into Philadelphia. Changing trains, we got out at Broad Street Station, where we had breakfast very comfortably: &amp; I got shaved. While an Italian operated on my chin: a negro polished my boots! We travelled to Pottstown, about 40 miles distance. Here we were driven to the Hill School by a lad, whose name was Kurllin, &amp; who believed himself of English origin. He told me that he was 18 years old, already married, &amp; a supporter of <persName xml:id="2814">Wilson</persName>!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The Hill School is well&#8211;situated on a rising ground, &amp; commands a noble prospect. <persName xml:id="2886">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Meigs</persName>, the widow of the late <persName xml:id="2887">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> John Meigs</persName>, who inherited the school from his <persName xml:id="2960">father</persName>, carries on the school with the assistance of <persName xml:id="2961" display="no">her daughters</persName><persName xml:id="2962" display="no"></persName> &amp; a staff of masters. There are about 360 boys in the school at the present time. After lunch we looked on at the football for awhile, &amp; then had tea. This meal was speedily followed by supper. Then we had prayers in the chapel, which I conducted. After this the boys were entertained with an exhibition of 'moving pictures', dancing, &amp;c.: from which I withdrew myself in order to prepare myself for tomorrow.
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
