<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. New York.</hi></p>
<div type="verse"></hi>
         <p>
<hi>Our souls go too much out of self</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Into ways dark &amp; dim,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Tis rather God who seeks for us</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Than we who seek for him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>God is not even so far off</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As even to be near:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He is within, our spirit is</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The home He holds most dear.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>So all the while I thought myself</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lonely, forlorn, &amp; weary,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Missing my joy, I walked the earth</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Myself God's sanctuary.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="660">Faber</persName>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
I wrote to <persName xml:id="3102">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Kim</persName> thanking him for his Reinecker lectures.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The lads employed are mainly Papist if I may judge from their reverential attitude towards me. They call me 'Father' &amp; evidently infer from my black coat that I am a 'priest'. Presumably they are newcomers in the land. After a few years they retain no reverence for anything or anybody.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2340">Roosevelt</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2815">Taft</persName> were both in the city last night. The first addressed a great public meeting, <hi rend="bold underline">which cheered for 41 minutes without ceasing when he appeared</hi>.</p>
         <p>
M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fisher (n&#x00E9;e <persName xml:id="2857">Justine Mann</persName>) called for us about 10 a.m., &amp; took charge of us. After making some small purchases, we went to the Central Park, &amp; looked at the beasts which are there exposed to view. A bison of grand proportions moved my admiration. The carnivora were also unusually fine. We lunched at a quiet little restaurant, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">were joined there by a journalist named <persName xml:id="3326" display="no">Ireland</persName>, an Englishman by birth but resident in this city. He arranged to have a formal interview with me tomorrow morning</hi>. Then we went to the fine new Public Library, and were particularly interested in the arrangement for providing the blind with literature which they can read: and in the children's room. Here we met <persName xml:id="3353" display="no">Miss Moore</persName> (?) who presides over this section of the work. She was insistent on the good effect of this provision for the children. She said it helped to <hi rend="underline">unify</hi> the discordant immigrants, &amp; taught them to value public property. <hi rend="bold underline">She had recently returned from England, &amp; was very contemptuous of our public library arrangements.</hi> Next we went to 'Peg Woffington's Caf&#x00E9;', &amp; had excellent tea &amp; toast for a total expenditure, including a tip of 25 cents, of one dollar &amp; a half.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to President <persName xml:id="3354">Francis Brown</persName> proposing to divide my two lectures thus, 1. The Religious Situation in England in 1660. 2. The Act of Uniformity &amp; its consequences.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="3355">Dean Grosvenor</persName> called. I told him of my acceptance of the Deanery of Durham, &amp; he expressed himself with great kindness. He said that in Durham he had formed the impression that the great Cathedral had no concern with the grimy &amp; ill&#8211;ordered looking town which clusters about the foot of the hill on which it stands. I could not honestly offer him any prospect of doing anything effectual, for I am not a "Christian Socialist", &amp; extremely sceptical of clerical essays in social improvement. It almost always begins with the tall&#8211;talk of prophetic commission, &amp;, speedily ends in the squalidest &amp; most intemperate partisanship.</hi></p>
         <p>
We dined in the Hotel, and afterwards sat in the writing room, &amp; wrote letters. I wrote to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, and <persName xml:id="810">Radcliffe</persName>.</p>
         <p>
This day three weeks &#8211; as our plans now stand &#8211; we are to go on board the White Star liner 'Baltic' sailing from New York to Liverpool. Those three weeks are filled with engagements which are exacting, and entertainments which are exhausting. It is an ill preparation for the motions &amp; commotions of the wintry Atlantic!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
