<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[251]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The morning post brought a letter from <persName xml:id="1173">Willie Temple</persName> saying that he had accepted the offer of this canonry &amp; rectory. </hi>Later, however, <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> brought the disconcerting news that it had been discovered that he (Temple) was legally disqualified as being less than six years in orders! So everything is again hung up. I fell in with <persName xml:id="2478">Bonham Carter</persName> as I returned from the city during the afternoon, &amp; had some talk with him. I rather pressed that <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> should be appointed. <hi rend="bold underline">It is certainly very extraordinary that the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C.</persName> and the late Bp. of W., now </hi><persName xml:id="382"><hi rend="bold underline">Dean of W</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> &#8211; men who must have had much experience of appointments, should have been so ignorant or so forgetful of the law as to press the <persName xml:id="215">P.M.</persName> to appoint a man not legally qualified</hi>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2995" display="no"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Adeney</hi></persName>, the tailor, came to instruct me as to these garments: &amp; I had scarcely got rid of him before I had to go to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, &amp; conduct the funeral service for M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <persName xml:id="2741">Fedarb</persName>. This melancholy function was my last official act in that church.</p>
         <p>I was photographed in my room by an agent of the London Illustrated News. He was a manly&#8211;looking fellow, who said he had just returned from photographing Bulgars in the neighbourhood of Adrianople.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
