<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[119]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Albany.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="verse">
         
         <p>
<hi>As we rush, we rush in the Train,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The trees &amp; the houses go wheeling back,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But the starry heavens above the plain</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Come flying on our track.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>All the beautiful stars of the sky,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The silver doves of the forest of Night,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Over the dull earth swarm &amp; fly,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Companions of our flight.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We will rush ever on without fear:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Let the goal be far, the flight be fleet!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>For we carry the Heavens with us, dear,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>While the earth slips from our feet!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>James Thomson 1834&#8211;1882</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>A most lovely morning, our lordly room gave free entrance to the sunshine; &amp; when we had enjoyed our tea brought to us after the comfortable English fashion, we indulged the delusion that we also were of the Great World, which has its place in the sun. The squalid necessity of making out our route to Schenectady &amp; Ithaca destroyed the illusion.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[120] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The promised lecture on Labour weighs on one's mind.</hi> <hi>I must make specific mention, &amp; pass some judgment on these points:</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>The Trades Disputes Act with its legislation of 'peaceful picketing'.<note xml:id="196" n="1"></note></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><orgName xml:id="232">Ruskin College</orgName> with its assumption that education &amp; the labourer's status will consist so that the one will not disgust for the other.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The General Strike as an instrument for advancing the interest of Labour: &amp; its failure in the strikes of this year.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Socialism &amp; Syndicalism.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Co&#8211;partnership &#8211; successful in the case of the South London Gas Works: unsuccessful in case of the Furness Ship&#8211;building Works.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
The Labour Party in the House of Commons. <persName xml:id="891">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ramsay Macdonald</persName>, not himself an artisan.
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The change in the Trade Unions &#8211; the cult of inefficiency disguised by a parade of altruistic sentiment. Case of the brick&#8211;layers. The Ca'canny policy of protracting work in order to distribute employment really inconsistent with personal efficiency or public propriety.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The growth of revolutionary sentiments and methods among English Workmen.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>When we came down to breakfast, we learned that there had been a fire in the house during the night. It was easily put out by the fire engine; but there must have been considerable hustlement: &amp; we slept through it all! After breakfast the <persName xml:id="3055">Governor</persName> walked us both to </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the Capitol &#8211; a building which has become proverbial as an example of municipal extravagance, incompetence, &amp;, as some wd. add, dishonesty.</hi> <hi>He took us into his office and showed us an ample reception room in which twice a week the Governor, like an Oriental Kadi, holds informal reception of the citizens, &amp; hears their complaints &amp; requests. Then he sent us under the direction of an attendant (who didn't know the way) to visit <persName xml:id="2913">Bishop Doane</persName>. The old man wasn't down (it was about 11 a.m.) but his <persName xml:id="3105" display="no">grand&#8211;daughter</persName> was so eager to see us that I promised to call again tomorrow. Then we went to the Education Building, &amp; heard a vivacious paper from </hi><persName xml:id="3106"><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> William Starr Myers</hi></persName><hi>, Assistant Professor of History &amp; Politics on "The Private Schools: Their place in American Life". I joined the Governor at the Capitol, while <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went back to the Executive Mansion. We were both entertained at semi&#8211;public luncheons. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My feast at the Fort George Club was preceded by one of those hand&#8211;shaking performances, to which Americans are so strongly attached. The Governor, <persName xml:id="849">Ambassador Reid</persName>, &amp; I stood in a row while all the guests filed by, &amp; shook us by the hand! </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
Then I hurried home &amp; got my notes for my speech, &amp; my Master's gown. There was a crowded hall. <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="2087">Murray Butler</persName> spoke with much power &amp; eloquence on "The Aim of the Modern University". His speech occupied nearly ¾ of an hour in delivery, &amp; was received with great applause</hi>. Then followed <persName xml:id="3108">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Henry S. Pritchell</persName> on "Preparation for the Professions", in a speech of much good sense delivered in a straightforward way, which held the audience. He spoke for half an hour. Then I came, &amp; was received with much applause, the audience rising in their seats. I spoke for half an hour on 'The Value of Historical Studies'. When I sate down the applause was prolonged, rather to my surprize: but the audience were evidently bent on being very polite to an English visitor. After <hi rend="bold underline">this performance I was given a cheque for 100 dollars much to my astonishment</hi>. Then we returned to the Executive Mansion, where <persName xml:id="3071">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dix</persName> was engaged in 'receiving' the delegates &amp; visitors. Some extremely fine coloured photographs of the autumnal woods were shown. <hi rend="italic">After dinner we all went to the reception at the new building: there, for an endless time, we &#8211; the Governor, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dix, the Chancellor &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="2332" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Reid</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, Ella &amp; I &#8211; stood in the 'receiving line', &amp; shook hands with several thousands of men, women &amp; youths. The ladies retired for awhile exhausted, &amp; it really was an exhausting performance.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
