<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. New York.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>O Almighty God, who hast knit together thine elect in one communion &amp; fellowship, in the mystical body of thy Son Christ our Lord: Grant us grace so to follow thy blessed Saints in all virtuous &amp; godly living, that we may come to those unspeakable joys, which thou has prepared for them that unfeignedly love thee; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Our rest last night was broken by the arrival of a considerable budget of letters from home. We were both peacefully sleeping when we were knocked up to take in our post. There came also a telegram from the <persName xml:id="325">Dean</persName>, which may, perhaps, indicate that my appointment has appeared in the 'Times'. It ran thus: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">'Brotherly congratulations blended with real sorrow'</hi><hi rend="italic">. It appears that <persName xml:id="1920">Dean Kitchin</persName> died on October 12</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">: so that the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> has not made much delay in filling up the vacancy. The burial w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> hardly have taken place before the 16</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> or 17</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; it is thought decent to let things be until that event has happened.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[172]</hi> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>{<persName xml:id="3367" display="no">Stock's</persName> address at Cambridge, 28 Trumpington St.}</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2857">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fisher</persName> called to shew us her children &#8211; a <persName xml:id="3369" display="no">boy</persName> &amp; a <persName xml:id="3370" display="no">girl</persName> &#8211; &amp; to take <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> out for that detestable folly known as 'shopping'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1266">Prof. Ed. Moore</persName> also called to make sure that we understood our route correctly. It appears that he left the budget of letters himself.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then, the ladies having departed, <persName xml:id="3326" display="no">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ireland</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> interviewed me for more than an hour. He is a very superior variety of journalist, &amp; is evidently something of an authority on the subject of native labour. I delivered with fatuous courage opinions on the Putumayo question, on the likeness between <persName xml:id="2340">Roosevelt</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="879">Gladstone</persName>, on American education, on the American people generally, on Female suffrage, &amp; on several other inflaming topics.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">President <persName xml:id="3112">Richmond</persName> is in the Hotel, &amp; persuaded us to join him at the play tonight. He took me to see the <orgName xml:id="261" display="no">Twentieth Club</orgName>, which seems to be a kind of American <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then we went by the subway to the Cathedral, and there attended Evensong. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I read the 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> lesson, &amp; signed my name in the Church book at <persName xml:id="3355">Grosvenor's</persName> request, as Dean&#8211;designate of Durham. </hi><hi rend="italic">He said that my appointment had appeared in the papers.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[173] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">We dined with President Richmond, &amp; then all of us went together to the theatre &amp; saw a humourous play of <persName xml:id="1338" display="no">Bernard Shaw</persName>, "Fanny's first Play". It is of course full of clever witticisms, but there is no intelligible meaning or drift in it: &amp; the effect of such plays must be wholly bad. Besides, there were a good many offensive things in it. </hi><hi rend="italic">The illuminated signs in the streets make a wonderful show, bizarre, brilliant, infinitely vulgar. I wondered which was the most debasing &#8211; the play inside or the street outside. Neither could be other than debasing. The frightful speed with which this place works &amp; plays: &amp; the vehement clamour of its rushing, reduce me to a sort of dazed imbecility. I feel like a rabbit in a snake's cage in the zoo &#8211; no way of escape, &amp; a horrible kind of fascination drawing me to death. The streets of New York are like the newspapers in which the headlines correspond to the illuminated signs &#8211; all insolently false. The rain has clothed everything in discomfort.</hi></p>
         <p>
I wrote to <persName xml:id="3368">Frank</persName>, of whose health ill accounts came in the letters from <persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>. Also I wrote a short letter to Marion.</p>
         <p>
I expounded to President Richmond my question, why do Americans, a practical &amp; efficient people, adopt the preposterous practice of having every item of breakfast <hi rend="underline">served</hi> by a domestic &#8211; generally the only one in the house?</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
