<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. White Marsh.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant day. After breakfast I wrote to <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>. We motored into Philadelphia through a very charming country. The great extent of the city became apparent as we traversed </hi><hi rend="underline">miles</hi><hi> of streets before reaching the centre. I lunched at the Club with <persName xml:id="2897" display="no">mine host</persName>; &amp; then went to a dentist [D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> G. L. S. Jameson 1429 Spruce Street, Philadelphia] who attended to me, &amp; refused any payment for doing so. Then I rejoined <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and <persName xml:id="2898" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Toland</persName>, &amp; we motored to the University, where I had interviews with <persName xml:id="2967">Provost Smith</persName> &amp; the <persName xml:id="2968" display="no">Vice&#8211;Provost</persName>. It appeared that some confusion had taken place as to my preaching to the University on the 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>
<hi> inst. However they undertook to rectify this, &amp; let me know what was determined. We then motored to Bryn Mawr College, &amp; were fortunate enough to find the President, <persName xml:id="2969">Miss Thomas</persName>, at home. Finally we motored home, and arrived in good time for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was much pleased to hear Provost Smith speak with enthusiasm of the service in Westminster Abbey on the occasion of the Royal Society's Function. That seems to have appealed to the imagination of the Americans. It is reported that 'the Bull Moose' (<persName xml:id="2340">Rooseveldt</persName>) passed through Philadelphia today, &amp; harangued the workmen &amp; others on the platform.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
