<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Williamstown, Mass.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
The want of an energetic understanding of the sequence and real significance of events, which would be fatal to a practical politician, is ruin to a student of history, who is the politician with his face turned backwards.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName>. <ref xml:id="702">'The Study of History'</ref> p. 22.</p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>That address at Albany which I am pledged to make next week is hanging heavy on my mind which reflects in its own way the horribly dubiety which hangs over all the arrangements for that function. My subject, as given to <persName xml:id="849">Ambassador Reid</persName>, is 'The value of historical studies', but the occasion seems hardly suitable for it.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
<hi>'Do not mistake familiarity with historical occurrences for a knowledge of history. A laborious study of Baedeker can never make any man an historian, or enable any traveller, however intelligent &amp; painstaking, to look at the scenes of history from the historian's point of view.' 'The kingdom of Heaven is taken by violence'. There is no short &amp; easy road to the exquisite joys of historical reminiscence and historical sympathy.'</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>That is the sort of innuendo I propose to throw at the head of mine audience.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
After breakfast I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="1682" display="no">Colin Kennedy</persName>, &amp; then we strolled in the town. On the way we met M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jerome, a relative of <persName xml:id="1049">Lady Randolph Churchill</persName>. He spoke pleasantly for some short time. Returning to the house, we found <persName xml:id="3032" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3033" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Eels</persName> with their automobile at the door. They took us for a drive to North Adams &amp; then roundabout the town to see the foliage. Yesterday's storm has brought down many leaves, and dimmed the brightness of the colouring; but the spectacle still remains magnificent.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On our way we noticed crawling on the roads many large hairy caterpillars, black fore &amp; aft with a bright reddish brown patch in the centre.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>. After lunch our <persName xml:id="2891">host</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3031" display="no">hostess</persName> took us for a long motor drive in order that we might see the hills in their glory. The spectacle was indeed superb &amp; unforgettable. We returned through the Lebanon valley, &amp; saw the dwellings of the Shakers, who here dwell in community &amp; pursue divers trades. A more noble prospect than this valley provides cannot be imagined. Our journey was rendered the more delightful by the conversation of our host &amp; his wife. We returned to Williamstown about 6.30 p.m., cold in body but with minds enkindled by what we had seen, &amp; hearts warmed by the friendliest sentiments.</hi>
            
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
