<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
<hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather, which last night was oppressively warm, changed suddenly in the early morning, &amp; became quite cold. A cheerless drizzle escorted me to the Appleton Chapel, where I conducted prayers, speaking to the youth on 'Prejudice’. My lesson was taken from Mark vi. 1&#8211;7, the record of the repudiation of Christ by the men of Nazareth. My vigil in <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName> was broken by only two visitors, one of them <persName xml:id="2676" display="no">Gray Zabriskie</persName>.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">When I returned to the house, I received a call from the Rev. <persName xml:id="3328" display="no">James Sheerin</persName>, an Episcopalian parson in a poor part of Boston, formerly Rector of Christ Church, Warren, Ohio. He brought me a copy of <ref xml:id="27">"Moral Discipline in the Christian Church"</ref>, which he had purchased in England when he was there for the <orgName xml:id="94">Pan&#8211;Anglican Congress</orgName>, ^in order that I might write my name in it^. He had then been the guest of M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="102">Romanes</persName>, whom he had himself since entertained in Ohio. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">He was much amazed at her vehement advocacy of the confessional, which apparently she had urged him to adopt, and continued to urge him by letter!</hi><hi rend="italic"> He said that he had arranged for her a series of lectures: but she had not given much satisfaction, for "she seemed wholly devoted to persons with whom her husband c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have had little sympathy". The American public seems little attracted by our Sacerdotalists. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3336">Hodges</persName>, the wife of the <persName xml:id="3335">Dean</persName> here, told me that both <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3337">Bull</persName> failed to interest the men on account of their</hi><hi rend="bold"> [203]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">insistence on the confessional.</hi></p>
         <p>
We lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3334" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Burgess</hi></persName> at her Social Settlement. She had collected a number of workers &amp; supporters. I sate between two ladies, the past &amp; the present heads of the venture. <hi rend="bold underline">They were both filled with the madness of all the nostrums I most detest &#8211; female suffrage, socialism &amp;c. However I addressed the company in a few vague phrases, which went down well enough</hi>: &amp; then we went over the House. A roomful of Syrian mothers with their infants was a curious sight.</p>
         <p>
<hi>Later in the afternoon, I delivered the last of my lectures at Andover College. It was a very ragged affair, but was listened to with close attention: &amp; the audience applauded at the end. The subject "The Problem of Economics" was, of course, impossible for such treatment.</hi></p>
         <p>
The <persName xml:id="3338">Bishop of Rhode Island</persName> talked to me through the telephone, asking me to do some preaching in Providence on December 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, but, of course, this was impossible.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We dined with <persName xml:id="3207">President</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3333" display="no">Fitch</persName></hi>. <persName xml:id="3331">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3332">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Evarts</persName> were of the party. I sate next M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> E. at dinner, &amp; found her very agreeable. These banquets are commonly served without any offer of wine. <hi rend="bold underline">But mineral water is served with all the reverent ceremonial which might accompany champagne!</hi> The rain fell steadily all the evening, &amp; the weather outlook remained evil.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
