<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>
Another glorious day. We bade farewell to our hospitable friends, and took our departure. Leaving the little station of White Marsh at 10.51 a.m. we travelled via Philadelphia &amp; New York to Williamstown, Mass: where we arrived a few minutes before 9 p.m. We were met at the station by a carriage, &amp; driven at once to the president's house in Williams College. He is the <persName xml:id="2891">eldest son</persName> of the well&#8211;known <persName xml:id="2888">President Garfield</persName>. He tells me that he has decided to vote for <persName xml:id="2814">Woodrow Wilson</persName>, though he has hitherto been connected with the Republican party. In 1887 he was in England, &amp; worked at All Souls in the library. He knew many of my Oxford friends. His own subject is Political Science.</p>
         <p>
On both sides of the line the autumnal colours of the trees &amp; bushes is brilliant, quite equalling the enthusiastic descriptions of 'the fall' in which Americans are apt to indulge.</p>
         <p>
The President here is fine specimen of a man: about 6 feet in height, square&#8211;shouldered, &amp; well proportioned. He has a broad brow, kindly eyes, a strong mouth, &amp; an air of candour &amp; straightforwardness which is very taking. He expresses himself well, &amp; gives the impression of a well&#8211;informed &amp; wide minded man. On the whole, I must regard him as one of the best types of American it has been my good fortune to meet.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
