<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[235]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 11.30 a.m. I called by appointment at 10 Downing Street, &amp; had half an hour's conversation with the Prime Minister with reference to the appointment of my successor</hi>. He read out to me a list of names actually under consideration. These, as nearly as I can remember, were the following:&#8211; </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2955"><hi rend="underline">Carnegie</hi></persName> of Birmingham: <persName xml:id="1899"><hi rend="underline">Vernon Storr</hi></persName> of Winchester: <persName xml:id="1173"><hi rend="underline">Willie Temple</hi></persName> of Repton: <persName xml:id="216"><hi rend="underline">Gow</hi></persName> of Westminster: <persName xml:id="249"><hi rend="underline">Gamble</hi></persName> of Chelsea: <persName xml:id="898"><hi rend="underline">Peile</hi></persName> of Warwick.</p>
         <p>I offered some reasons for preferring <hi rend="underline">Storr</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Gow</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">Temple</hi> to <hi rend="underline">Carnegie</hi>: but I don't think I made much impression on Asquith. <hi rend="bold underline">He clearly inclines to Carnegie</hi>, but is impressed by the notion of making a bold experiment by appointing Temple.</p>
         <p>I thanked him for his confidence in me, shown by his nomination to the Durham Deanery. <hi rend="bold underline">He said he had been surprised &amp; pleased by the way in which my appointment had been received in almost every quarter. He begged that when I had settled in my place, I would write to him about the situation at Durham: of which he said I hear no good account</hi>. I thanked him for the permission, &amp; so took my departure, not having effected much but perhaps having done no harm. At least Asquith was very courteous &amp; kind.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
