<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I granted an interview to the 'Westminster Gazette' representative </hi><persName xml:id="2971" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Whitehorne</hi></persName>. The subject was limited to the matter of Ecclesiastical Union in America.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> came to see me.</p>
         <p>After dinner <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon Watkins</persName> came to see us. He was most kind &amp; communicative. He appeared to be greatly surprized when I mentioned the fact (as I supposed) that the Decanal income had been reduced to &#x00A3;2000, by the loss of the Chancellorship. He said that he felt sure that this was not the case. The <persName xml:id="1920">late Dean</persName> had at one time described his official income as consisting of two factors, &#x00A3;2000 for the Deanery, &#x00A3;1000 for the Chancellorship: but that he (Watkins) being then Treasurer of the Dean &amp; Chapter had pointed out to him the effect of such a view on the pension of a retiring Dean: whereupon Kitchin had abandoned his theory, &amp; described his income in "Crockford" as &#x00A3;3000 for the Deanery. The Archdeacon declared himself "morally certain" that no change in the income had been made. I devoutly hope that he is not mistaken. But I do certainly remember some statement in the "Times" in which the opposite was affirmed.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[234]</hi></p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> December 1912, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I travelled to Durham in order to take a preliminary view of our future home. The weather was abominable, passing from frosty fog to frosty rain. We arrived in a down&#8211;pour, &amp; were in time for Evensong in the Cathedral. <hi rend="bold underline">The service was comfortable &amp; suggestive</hi>.</p>
         <p>We then went into the Deanery, which was in the melancholy disarray which attends a sale of furniture. A local agent named <persName xml:id="2972">Rushworth</persName>, who had been commended to us by the Archdeacon as honest, attended us, &amp; received instruction as to some purchases we desired to make.</p>
         <p>I saw <persName xml:id="2806">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bailey</persName>, the assistant&#8211;Treasurer, &amp; learned to my infinite relief that the recent act which separates the Chancellorship from the Deanery does not affect the Decanal income, which remains at &#x00A3;3000. This information was the more welcome <hi rend="bold underline">since my brief survey of the house had convinced me that it w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be impossible to live in it on less</hi>. After dinner some of the neighbours came in to see me. <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop Nixon</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1898">Cruikshank</persName> of the canons, the Precentor (<persName xml:id="2800">Culley</persName>) who is also the Organist, &amp; some others.</p>
         <p>The next day, Wednesday, we again visited the Deanery: then went over the Cathedral with the Archdeacon: lunched with Cruikshank: saw <persName xml:id="473">Canon Knowling</persName> &amp; some more of the neighbours: visited the Castle under <persName xml:id="2920">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gee's</persName> guidance: &amp; returned to Westminster where we arrived about 11 p.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
