<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1912. Boston.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="931">Bishop</persName> sent me in to Appleton Chapel by the motor: and I conducted prayers</hi> there, giving a little discourse on 'Friendship' to the youth. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I went across to <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName></hi>, and there kept vigil, having no visitors save one of the Divinity professors, who talked about <persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName> and my late host, <persName xml:id="1266">Edward Moore</persName>, to whom I offer felicitations on his silver wedding. </p>
         <p>
Wadsworth House has an interest of its own, having been occupied by General George Washington from July 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> to July 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1775. It is a good specimen of the old wooden colonial house, &amp; would be comfortable enough if it did not abut on the street &amp; get the full disadvantage of the street noises. I wrote to my godson, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Divinity Professor talked of <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName>, who gave the 'Noble' lectures last year, on "Christianity at the Cross&#8211;Roads</hi><hi rend="italic">". I inquired how he had succeeded. Not at all, he replied. He denounced the existing situation of civilized men in a very intemperate way. '</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">That is how I think I used to speak when I was 23’</hi><hi rend="italic"> &#8211; observed one of his hearers. Then he created disgust by dwelling on the great sacrifices he had himself made in becoming a Mirfield Father. His plump &amp; comfortable aspect, &amp; his situation as a student residing in a pleasant Yorkshire village among books, seemed to render such emphasis unreal, &amp; even not a little absurd. </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">We (i.e. the Bishop, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; I) lunched with the <orgName xml:id="261" display="no">'Twentieth Century Club'</orgName></hi><hi rend="italic"> &#8211; a wonderful collection of 'progressive' reformers which reminded me of Lake Mohonk. I made a speech about the situation in the Balkans, which clearly did not match the general sentiment of an audience mainly composed of 'peace fanaticks'. I was followed by M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">c</hi><hi rend="italic">All<persName xml:id="3390" display="no"></persName> (?) a fine&#8211;looking &amp;, I was assured, an honourable man who spoke on the Panama Canal with good sense &amp; good feeling. Then came an astonishing person named <persName xml:id="3391" display="no">Thompson</persName>, the secretary of the rivers &amp; harbours commission, or something of that sort. He poured forth a stream of figures to illustrate the cheapness &amp; potential value of water&#8211;transit, &amp; wound up with an amazing peroration in which America, resistless in power, and &amp; over&#8211;flowing with money, w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> dictate peace to the warring nations of the world! It was an entirely Transatlantick performance, not to be paralleled in Great Britain.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After this feast of eloquence in an asphyxiating atmosphere we needed some fresh air, so the Bishop motored me out to a new house he is building near Milton, a place renowned for the manufacture of chocolate. We had tea with the <persName xml:id="3392" display="no">Bishop's sister</persName> who lives hard by, &amp; then returned, picking up <persName xml:id="3393">Freddie</persName> the Bishop's school boy son on the way. We returned to the house about 6 p.m: &amp; I set to making some preparation for tomorrow.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
