<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass. </hi></p>
         <p>
Lord, we beseech thee to keep thy household the Church in continual godliness: that through thy protection it may be free from all adversities, &amp; devoutly given to serve thee in good works, to the glory of thy Name; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A most glorious bright morning but with the bite of approaching winter in the air. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I preached in Appleton Chapel at 11 a.m. There was a large congregation of students</hi><hi rend="italic">. Since I was here in 1909 the interior of the chapel has been renovated, &amp; given a more churchly appearance. The general public are now limited to a single gallery, so that the aspect of everything is much more academic than before. I preached on the 'lukewarmness' of Laodicea; the sermon was followed with very close attention.</hi></p>
         <p>
Talking with mine host before lunch, I suggested to him that he should invite <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> to lecture &amp; preach in Harvard. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Incidentally he told me that I had not been invited to give the "Noble" lectures because M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3380">Noble</persName>, the widow of the <persName xml:id="3379">donor</persName> of the Trust Funds, being a very "orthodox" woman, indicated her disapproval of me as an heretick!! And this is a free country</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
I wrote to the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="227">Willie Murray</persName>.</p>
         <p>
Several persons came to tea including <persName xml:id="3382">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Allen</persName>, the widow of <persName xml:id="1802">Phillips Brooks's</persName> <persName xml:id="3381">biographer</persName>. She said that it was matter of common observation that the most familiar (as we might suppose) Biblical allusions were incomprehensible to American audiences. Political orators found this to be the case.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We motored to Newton, &amp; there took the train to Wellesley, where we were met, &amp; driven to the Ladies' College. There I read Evensong, &amp; preached on Hebrews XII.I. to a congregation of about 1100 young women. They sang very sweetly, &amp; carried themselves reverently</hi>. We got back to the house about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>
While 'thawing' in the study after a cold motor&#8211;drive, we discussed female suffrage, &amp; its probable consequences. <hi rend="bold underline">Mine host agreed with me that one consequence w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be both certain &amp; mischievous &#8211; the temperance question w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be dealt with fanatically with drastic unwisdom</hi>. He adduced his own experience in Rhode island, where 'prohibition' prevailed. The result was that, while no saloons were tolerated on the main streets of the cities, they swarmed in the side streets. Revenue statistics appeared to show that there is a larger quantity of alcohol consumed in 'dry' States than in 'wet'. The effect of this hypocritical system on the police, who perforce connived at it, was as bad as it was inevitable.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
