<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>	</p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I conducted Service at Appleton Chapel</hi>, speaking to the lads about 'the fatal force &amp; importance of words’. There was a succession of students to see me, so that I could do no work of my own. <persName xml:id="1266">Prof. Moore</persName> sent over a considerable bundle of letters which had arrived from England. <hi rend="bold underline">It consisted entirely of Congratulations on my appointment to Durham.</hi> I returned to 122 Constitutional Avenue, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">bade farewell</hi> to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <persName xml:id="949">Lawrance</persName>. Then we lunched with <persName xml:id="3329">Prof:</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3330" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Scofield</persName>. <hi rend="italic">Talking after lunch, the Professor stated his belief that the German Emperor is a student of Machiavelli: &amp; said that this view had been confirmed by the fact that a copy of Machiavelli's books was included in the Emperor's travelling books. This had been certified by somebody who had observed the volume in the Emperor's room. All this has a curious aspect.</hi></p>
         <p>
We motored to Mason Street, Cambridge, <hi rend="bold underline">to stay for the rest of our time in this place with <persName xml:id="1715">Prof:</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="2746" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline"> Max Kellner</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">. I gave the 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of my lectures at the <orgName xml:id="252">Andover Seminary</orgName></hi>. As I was walking to the place a student introduced himself as <persName xml:id="2890" display="no">Garfield</persName>, the son of the <persName xml:id="2891">President of Williams College</persName>.</p>
         <p>
Finally I went to a church in Brookline, &amp; gave an address on '<hi rend="underline">The Relation of Church &amp; State in England’</hi> to above 100 men of a superior type.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
This was a very singular function. The pastor of the church, <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3327"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Vernon</hi></persName>, was evidently a man of markedly 'progressive’ type, though he had voted for <persName xml:id="2814"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi></persName>. He was, however, a Princeton man, &amp; college loyalty may have determined his vote. I was put up to speak on a subject about which nobody knew anything, or cared to know anything. I started my speech with nothing more than their natural curiosity to secure attention. However when I proceeded to expound the mysteries of Anglican finance, their commercial instincts began to rally to me: &amp; they grew quite interested. I invited them to ask questions, which several of them did; &amp; this distinctly enlivened the proceedings, so that when finally I took my departure they assured me with every appearance of sincerity that they had greatly enjoyed the evening: <hi rend="underline">I took the opportunity of exalting the virtue of endowments as securing the independence of religious teachers; as I described the humiliating position of the Voluntaryist parson, dependent for the means to live on the goodwill of the very people it may be his duty to rebuke, I thought D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="underline">Vernon looked mighty sheepish. Some of the younger men who talked with me after the formal speech was ended gave me a good impression. There is fine material in this country, but all most miserably mishandled and wasted.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
