<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. New Haven, Conn.</hi>
         </p>
        
<div type="verse">
         
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The soul's dark cottage, batter'd and decay'd, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lets in new light through chinks that Time hath made: </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Stronger by weakness, wiser men become</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">As they draw near to their eternal home.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Leaving the old, both worlds at once they view</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">That stand upon the threshold of the new.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Edmund Waller. 1606&#8211;1687.</hi>
         </p>
        
</div>
        
         <p>
<hi>O God, forasmuch as without thee we are not able to please thee: Mercifully grant, that thy Holy Spirit may in all things direct &amp; rule our hearts, through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather is cool &amp; bright, a welcome change after the heat of yesterday. I wrote to <persName xml:id="836" display="no">Buff</persName> before breakfast. I preached to the University in the large Auditorium. This building is said to seat nearly 3000 persons. It was well filled, save for a small gallery at the back. I selected the sermon on 'The thirst of the Soul for God'. It took 36 minutes in delivery, &amp; was, I think, well heard. <persName xml:id="1565">Anson Phelps Stokes</persName> took the short service for me. He begged for my MS afterwards, that the sermon might be printed in the Yale newspaper.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2032"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Newman Smyth</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> came to see me</hi> <hi>with the purpose of talking over the Reunion Project in which he is so eagerly engaged. He is as ardent, as impractical, &amp; as optimistic as ever: but his mind stills [sic] plays round the old futile point of Orders, &amp; he reads into the polite compliments of English bishops a meaning which assuredly they do not bear.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Anson Phelps Stokes</hi><hi>, who has grown a beard to the surprise &amp; delight of his neighbours &#8211; I dubbed him forthwith 'the handsome Italian' &#8211; took me for a walk to the top of the East Rock, from which we obtained a noble view of the city stretched on the level plain between the two cliffs. We devoured the way with conversation. He is undoubtedly more at home with the older kind of Christian Socialist than with me. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Indeed I am a great perplexity to these American Broad Churchmen, who cannot understand how I can be so unsympathetic with 'progressive democracy'. But (as I told him) I am an old&#8211;fashioned 'latitude&#8211;man'</hi>. He was very confident that the Tractarian party had been losing ground in the Protestant Episcopal Church during the last five or six years. He said that <persName xml:id="931">Bishop Lawrence's</persName> influence had waxed steadily: but that <persName xml:id="3068">Bishop Greer</persName>, who had been unanimously elected successor to <persName xml:id="259">Bishop Potter</persName> in New York, had been something of a disappointment. He still clings to the plausible but mistaken notion that the Church of England would gain <hi rend="underline">spiritually</hi><hi> by Disestablishment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3053">Mine host</persName> has a brother&#8211;in&#8211;law who is a French cavalry&#8211;lieutenant &amp; also a Roman Catholic. He spent some months in France this summer visiting this gentleman. I inquired what impression had been made on him by the Roman Church in that country: &amp; he replied that he was astonished by the evident signs of increasing strength which that church presented. The deadness of the French Protestant churches could not be doubted. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I addressed between 200 &amp; 300 students on the Putumayo Atrocities. They seemed to be interested: &amp; some of them came to talk with me afterwards. It is evident that they had but the vaguest notion of what had happened. Also they spoke of my morning sermon, which appears to have interested them, &amp; which they wanted to read.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Mine host, who had accompanied me to the meeting &amp; waited patiently while I discussed with the students, walked home with me: &amp; thence sent off a telegram to <persName xml:id="3055">Governor Dix</persName> at Albany telling him we should arrive on Tuesday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>So ended a pleasant but laborious day. It is the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Sunday on American soil, the 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> since we deserted our poor flock in Westminster.  </hi>
         </p>
       
</body></text></TEI>
