<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[244]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>Pride is the greatest enemy to Moderation. This makes men stickle for their opinions, to make them fundamental: proud men having deeply studied some additional point in Divinity, will strive to make the same necessary to salvation, to enhance the value of their own work &amp; pains: &amp; it must be fundamental in religion, because it is fundamental to their reputation. <hi rend="underline">Yea as love doth descend, &amp; men doat most on their Grandchildren, so these are indulgent to the deductions of their deductions, &amp; consequential inferences to the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> generation</hi>, though scarce of the building of religion. Ancient Fathers made the Creed <hi rend="underline">symbolum</hi>, the shot &amp; total sum of Faith. Since which how many arrearages, and after&#8211;reckonings have men brought us in? To which if we will not pay our belief, our souls must be arrested without bail upon pain of damnation. Next to Pride popular Applause is the greatest foe Moderation hath, &amp; sure they who sail with that wind have their own vain&#8211;glory for their Haven.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2095" display="no">T. Fuller</persName>. <ref xml:id="352">"The Holy State"</ref>. p. 208. </p>
         <p>A.D. 1642</p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[245]</hi></p>
         <p>My throat is in an ill state. I made the fact an excuse for shirking the early service.</p>
         <p>At Mattins the congregation was large, but not crowded. <hi rend="bold underline">I saw <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1319" display="no">Lord Reay</persName> under the pulpit</hi>. My sermon was on the subject of the Last Judgement, how the belief in it ought to influence our present conduct. The people were very solemn &amp; attentive.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="758" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rutt</persName>, <persName xml:id="1195" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Barclay</persName>, <persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford&#8211;Bell</persName>, two Americans, Gilbert &amp; Reggie were at lunch making with ourselves, the ill&#8211;omened number &#8211; thirteen.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="541">Alington</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="777">his wife</persName> came to offer their congratulations on Durham, &amp; to sing the praises of <persName xml:id="1173">Willie Temple</persName> as my successor!</hi></p>
         <p>I called on old <persName xml:id="2703" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Tennant</persName> &#8211; she is 94 years old, &amp; still acute &amp; interested. Just now she is reading <persName xml:id="1084">Father Tyrell's</persName> <ref xml:id="669">Autobiography</ref>, &amp; is full of it.</p>
         <p>There was a crowd at Evensong. I read the Exhortation to Holy Communion for the last time, &amp; preached very briefly from the words: "The Lord is at hand". There was another large supper&#8211;party. <persName xml:id="1708">Alec Beechey</persName>, <persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName>, <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName>, Gilbert, &amp; <persName xml:id="206">Baddeley</persName>, besides <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1812">Angel</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
