<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[249]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>Let every man seek God apart, &amp; search out the Truth in the holy Scripture, preparing himself for a right understanding thereof, by steadfastly &amp; sincerely practising such things as are plainly &amp; uncontrovertedly contained therein, &amp; expect illumination according to the best communication thereof, that is, answerably to our own faculties: otherwise if we bid all Reason, &amp; History, &amp; Human helps &amp; Acquisitions quite adieu, the world will never be rid of Religious Lunacies &amp; Fancies.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2880"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry Moore</hi></persName>. <ref xml:id="696" display="no">Works</ref> "Cabbala". p. 184.</p>
         <p>2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> edition. London. 1662.</p>
</div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. There were but 15 communicants, among them <persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName>. It was almost impossible to realize that this was my last Sunday in this place. </p>
         <p>There was a large congregation at Mattins. I adapted the sermon which I preached at the Digbeth Institute in Birmingham, on March 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1909, after <persName xml:id="49">Bishop Gore</persName> inhibited me from preaching. By way of adding to its point, I introduced a quotation from yesterday's issue of the 'Westminster Gazette’, in which a gross exhibition <hi rend="bold">[250]</hi> <hi rend="italic">of wealth at a ball in Washington was justly censored.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After lunch I made a typed copy of most part of my 'farewell sermon’, &amp; carried it to the "Times" Office.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At Evensong the church was thronged; many hundreds were unable to gain admission. An effort had been made to give a preference to the regular congregation. <persName xml:id="1064">Burdett&#8211;Coutts</persName>, the member for Westminster, sate conspicuous in the Speaker's Pew. My text was taken from S. Paul's farewell address at Miletus; Acts xx. 32. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'And now I commend you to God, &amp; to the word of His Grace, which is able to build you up, &amp; to give you the inheritance among all them that are sanctified’. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I preached for nearly 40 minutes, &amp; was listened to with close &amp; sympathetic attention. </hi><hi rend="italic">Carols were sung instead of the Anthem, &amp; after the Benediction: &amp; everything was wound up with "Old Hundredth", which was sung with immense fervour. After the service various people waited outside the Church for a final hand&#8211;shake. So ends my preaching in S. Margaret's. May God forgive, &amp; accept it!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2678">Lady Limerick</persName> came to supper: also <persName xml:id="813">Arthur Rawle</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2775">his wife</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, <persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName>, Gilbert, Reggie, &amp; Bob. I sent the MS. of my sermon to the Editor of the "Church Family Newspaper" in response to his request.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
