<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>
We finished our packing &amp; left the Embassy by the morning train i.e. we left Washington. Before leaving the house I photograph [sic] <persName xml:id="389">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2896">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bryce</persName> with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> on the steps. Thus we travelled to Philadelphia, admiring the scenery on either side of the line. The brilliant sun shining through the leaves made a brave show. When we arrived at Philadelphia, we parted, Ella going to Brynn Mawr at once; &amp; I turning aside to lunch with <persName xml:id="2966">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Stuart Paterson</persName> at his club. He had brought together a very interesting company, including a fine old man with a caustic tongue &amp; a cheerful spirit, <persName xml:id="3141" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacVeagh</persName>, who did most of the talking, &amp; <persName xml:id="3067">Bishop Rheinlander</persName>. Most of the company were evidently strong Republicans (Taftites) but Rheinlander was a Bull Mooser, &amp; MacVeagh professed himself hostile to them all. I inquired how these great campaign funds were used, &amp; I was assured that the American farmer in many cases expected payment for the time spent in voting; &amp; did nowise regard himself as accepting a bribe. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Veagh's denunciations of the millionaires were good to hear. He told with much relish how he had been entertained at dinner by old Cornelius Vanderbilt, &amp; had congratulated him pleasantly on the entertainment in these words: </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[154] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3143"><hi rend="underline">"M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Vanderbilt</hi></persName><hi rend="underline">, you have got together a very notable company: fifteen millionaires &amp; one gentleman".</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>I was pounced upon by reporters after lunch, &amp; dictated to them some opinions on multi&#8211;millionaires &amp; female suffrage. Then I went to Bryn Mawr.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Here I found some letters and a telegram from the Dean marked official, asking me whether I would accept the Deanery of Durham if it were offered me, &amp; I replied that I would</hi><hi rend="italic">. As the telegram was already 3 days old, I made no delay in sending an answer. If, as seems most probable, since the </hi><persName xml:id="325"><hi rend="italic">Dean</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> added 'official' to his message, this telegram was sent at the request of the Prime Minister, then I have pledged myself to take a step which bisects my life, cutting me off at every point from what I have grown into. There is so much in it which I dislike &#8211; leaving the Southern Province for instance, &amp; going so far from London. Moreover, I know nothing certain as to the conditions of that Deanery. In any case I shall be straitened for money, &amp; the in getting must needs be very costly.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2969"><hi rend="italic">Miss Thomas</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> had invited some of her professors, of both sexes to dinner: &amp; the time passed well enough, save that I myself was rather pre&#8211;occupied with my own affairs, which made me duller than was expected!</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
