<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185] </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass.</hi></p>
         <p>
<div type="quote"></p>
         <p>
The sophisms of Columbus were worth more than all the science of Salamanca. The objectors who called him a visionary were in the right, &amp; he was obstinately wrong. To his auspicious persistency in error Americans owe, among other things, their existence.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName>. l.c. p. 61.</p>
         <p>
</div>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I received by the morning post the proof of the interview which I had in New York with <persName xml:id="3326" display="no">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Ireland</persName> (v. p. 172). It was on the whole a creditable piece of work, but it credited me with 'dark blue eyes'! This is a good illustration of the value of human testimony</hi><hi rend="italic">. We were together more than an hour, during most of which we sat opposite to one another, &amp; looked at close range into one another's eyes. It might fairly be presumed that a professional interviewer on duty, &amp; definitely designing to give a personal description of his victim, w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic">. have specially noted the eyes. There c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic">. be no possible reason for giving the wrong colour: 'brown', 'black', 'grey', or 'hazel' w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic">. have been equally interesting, &amp; equally irrelevant! Yet here a glaring error is made by an honest &amp; thoroughly competent man, giving evidence in his own way, with respect to facts within his personal &amp; recent knowledge.</hi></p>
         <p>
I conducted service in Appleton Chapel, &amp; gave a little discourse on Habakkuk i. 12&#8211;17.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
My vigil in <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName> was undisturbed save for the arrival of one visitor &#8211; <persName xml:id="3315" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Arthur Beane</persName>, who wished to show me <orgName xml:id="257">'<persName xml:id="1802">Phillips Brooke's</persName> House'</orgName>, a centre of social work founded in memory of the divine, whose name it bears. I promised to see it on Tuesday.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I preached for the 4</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> time on S. Paul's Cathedral. The congregation seemed to me less numerous &amp; less virile than yesterday</hi><hi rend="italic">. I preached on I. Cor: x. 26, 'The earth is the Lord's &amp; the fulness thereof'. It is the case that I have no comfort in preaching in this place. The atmosphere seems unfriendly. Everybody is almost elaborately polite, but there is an absence of genuine cordiality. I noticed not a few persons crossed themselves, when I made the invocation before the sermon. This may, perhaps, indicate the set of the wind. Possibly some of them suspect that they are imperilling their souls by listening to a notorious heretick! The assistant clergy are supporters of <persName xml:id="2340">Roosevelt</persName>, which probably means that they are 'Christian Socialists', &amp; in that capacity have their own reasons for disliking me. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I am actually here to preach in an undenominational University Chapel, and to lecture in a schismatical College!! Is it necessary to speculate on the reasons for an unspoken unfriendliness, which is very apparent to me</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
After service I was introduced to <persName xml:id="3317" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> George L. Parker</persName>, a <persName xml:id="3316" display="no">congregationalist minister's</persName>wife, who brought to me a <persName xml:id="3320" display="no">mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3318" display="no">two girls</persName><persName xml:id="3319" display="no"></persName>, who, she said, had recently come out from Westminster. Curiously enough, the mother said she had been employed by <hi rend="bold">[187]</hi> [symbol] <persName xml:id="3211">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kitchin</persName> to clean the Deanery of Durham, at the time when the <persName xml:id="1920">late Dean</persName> was appointed. She said it was a very large house.</p>
         <p>
In the afternoon the rain came on with vehemence, but none the less we <hi rend="bold underline">drove out to call on the late President, <persName xml:id="3375">Elliot</persName>, whom, however, we failed to see</hi>. Then we had tea with <persName xml:id="3321">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3322" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Merriman</persName>, who are friends of <persName xml:id="1427">Baker&#8211;Wilbraham</persName>. He is assistant&#8211;Professor of English History, &amp; deals specifically with the Reformation period. He agreed with me in regarding <persName xml:id="3323">Gairdner's</persName> book, <ref xml:id="727">'Lollardy &amp; the Reformation'</ref>, as a very scandalous production.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3384"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Councilman</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> came to tea here. I inquired respecting the progress of Psycho&#8211;Therapeutics, &amp; he assured me that it was a declining movement. The Immanuel Movement had moderated its claims, &amp; was now shrinking to very modest proportions</hi>. He said that three years ago <persName xml:id="2425" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Coomb</persName> had undoubtedly made much greater claims in its behalf than he did now. I asked whether his statement w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> extend to the Christian Science Movement. He said that there c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be no doubt that movement w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> decline: though it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> die slowly as it had ample financial resources. But it had been gravely damaged by the publication of a '<ref xml:id="675"><hi rend="underline">Life of <persName xml:id="2766">Mary Baker Eddie</persName></hi></ref>' [sic] by a lady named <persName xml:id="3387" display="no">Tarbell</persName>. We spoke of the female suffrage question. <hi rend="bold underline">He expressed his astonishment that the suffragettes were not allowed to starve themselves. He said that well&#8211;nourished young women of the upper classes </hi><hi rend="bold">[188] </hi><hi>[symbol] </hi><hi rend="bold underline">would easily stand fasting for 30 or 40 days: that they (the medical folk of Harvard) were making a study of the metabolism of fasting, &amp; found no difficulty in obtaining volunteers to fast for that period</hi>.</p>
         <p>
We went out in a taxi&#8211;cab to drive with the <persName xml:id="3324">Dean</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3325">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rousmani&#x00E9;re</persName>. The rain was falling in torrents when we started, and when we [were] scarcely half through our journey, the motor broke down, &amp; would go no farther. <persName xml:id="1266">Prof. Moore</persName> rushed to an adjacent telephoning station, &amp; brought to our rescue a second motor, in which we succeeding [sic] in reaching our destination, <hi rend="bold underline">arriving more than ½ an hour after time</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I found the dinner bad; the company dull: and the conversation tiresome. Probably the fault was my own</hi><hi rend="italic">, but the most enjoyable moment of the evening was that at which M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="2894">Moore</persName> gave the signal for departure. Even then our misadventures were not quite over: for we drove to the railway station to pick up <persName xml:id="2321">Dorothea</persName>, who was coming from Bryn Mawr to take part in celebrating the silver wedding of her parents, which falls on Saturday next, &amp; incidentally to 'come out' herself: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">her train was 40 minutes late</hi><hi rend="italic">. So we 'kicked our heels' aimlessly for all that time at the railway station. In the end we all returned home about 11 p.m., </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">chastened &amp; a little bored with ourselves, the weather, &amp; one another</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
