<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Hartford.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
<hi>The study of Modern History is, next to Theology itself, &amp; only next in so far as Theology rests on a Divine Revelation, the most thoroughly religious training that the mind can receive.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><ref xml:id="705" display="no">Stubbs. Lectures 9</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
A beautiful day. After breakfast I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="122">Hine&#8211;Haycock</persName>, <persName xml:id="1679">Charlie Oman</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1494">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sinclair</persName>. Also to Gilbert.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At lunch was a lively lady named <persName xml:id="3047" display="no">Robertson</persName> (?) whose <persName xml:id="3048" display="no">husband</persName> (so I gathered from her conversation) was an employer of labour in Hartford, &amp; had recently defeated a strike of his men. She spoke much of <persName xml:id="2508">F. E. Smith</persName> who had, if I understood her correctly, been her guest at Newport: &amp; whom she had dressed up for a fancy ball. I indicated politely but clearly the contempt I could not but feel for the costly follies in which American millionaires indulge at a time when the conscience of the community is really troubled with respect to the sufferings of the poor, &amp; the labouring class is deeply discontented. She took what I said in good part. </hi><persName xml:id="3039" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Burgess</hi></persName> <hi rend="italic">declared her admiration of the skill with which the <orgName xml:id="231">I.W.W.</orgName> ('Independent Workers of the World' &#8211; a pestilent labour Federation) had organized the workers at the strike in Lawrence, Mass.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>They had </hi><hi rend="bold">[102] </hi><hi>[symbol] collected the strikers in national groups under their several national flags. To every one the situation was explained in his own language, &amp; then the negociations with the employers were carried on in English. She describes the street as resembling a Fair, gay with flags. In that strike the whole mischief seems to have grown out of a misconception caused by ignorance of the language on the part of workers, most of whom were recent arrivals in the country.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We motored during the afternoon, &amp; were delighted with the country which is brilliant in its autumn hues as 'leaf by golden leaf, crumbles the gorgeous year'. Returning we had tea with <persName xml:id="2891">mine host's</persName> <persName xml:id="3050">brother</persName> who lives next door. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Goodwin said that he had been present at a wedding conducted by a Congregational minister. Rather to the surprise of the company he produced a prayer book, &amp; read the Marriage service of the Episcopal Church, &amp; greatly to the company's diversion he was so conscientious as to read out all the rubricks as well as the text!  The more I learn of the religious procedures of this astonishing country, the more I am disposed to value an Established Church as providing in the community a Norm of right conduct, &amp; creating a public taste for decency &amp; order.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I dined at the Golf Club House, where a considerable company of clergy &amp; laity had been brought together under the chairmanship of <persName xml:id="3043">Bishop Brewster</persName> to hear an address from me. Before dinner I had to go through the strange American custom of shaking hands with everybody. A company of ladies escorted by mine host came in after dinner, &amp; were provided with chairs. I spake for rather more than 35 minutes, taking as my subject the place &amp; function of the Christian Church in modern society. There were reporters present, &amp; they appeared to be active: but I shudder to think what they will have made of my utterances. <persName xml:id="3042">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mackenzie</persName>, a Congregationalist, spoke after me, mainly dwelling on Church Unity, &amp; distilling platitudes which were more complimentary than relevant.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>{Memoires of the Comtesse de Boigne. 1781&#8211;1814. Edited from the original MSS. by M. Charles Nicoulland, with Portrait. Charles Scribner's Sons. New York. 1907}</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This book seems worth getting as having some rather remarkable illustrations of the society which perished in the French Revolution.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
