<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>
A cold bright day. <hi rend="bold underline">I finished my duty in the Chapel</hi>, taking as my text the two conceptions of human life implied in the narrative of the request of the sons of Zebedee, &amp; the reply of Christ. I had several visitors at <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName>. One man, <persName xml:id="3395" display="no">Gulick</persName>, interested me greatly. He wanted to know what I meant by the expression, 'the moralisation of Privilege', which I had used in one of the morning addresses. We had an interesting conversation. He said that he was a socialist, but he was intensely convinced of the truth of Christianity. He was destined to be an architect. We parted on the understanding that he sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> visit Durham, &amp; go over the Cathedral with me!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We called on </hi><persName xml:id="2894"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Moore</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, &amp; said 'Goodbye'</hi>. Then we packed our trunks &amp;c, &amp; made our farewells to the <persName xml:id="1715">Kellners</persName><persName xml:id="2746" display="no"></persName>. We travelled by 'the Knickerbocker Limited' Express to New York. We lunched on the train.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2903"><hi rend="italic bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Coffin</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> met us at the station</hi><hi rend="italic">. We found a bundle of letters from England awaiting us, all congratulatory but some (e.g. those from <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, &amp; Gilbert) conceived in rather a sad vein, with a suggestion of 'et tu Brute' running through them. There was a small dinner party including D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3063">Brown</persName>, the Dean of the Divinity School at Yale. We discussed Social politics, &amp; I soon found that I was in an atmosphere of Christian Socialism.</hi>	</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
