<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. White Marsh.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another glorious day. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="2622">Sir Lionel Spencer</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="231">Elizabeth Asquith</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3010" display="no"><hi>D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harris</persName>, an Episcopalian parson lunched here. He told me that he had been 49 years in this place: that he had never left it even for a short annual holiday: that he had never been to Europe. But he was an intelligent old man, &amp; talked well. He gave me a dark account of the municipal life of Philadelphia. At present the process of 'cleaning up' is going on under an <persName xml:id="3011">honest German mayor</persName>. Mine host told me of a corrupt mayor whose malpractices exceeded the recognized limits. His fellow 'gangsters' remonstrated with him: 'the public', they said, 'would not stand such scandals'. 'I am in for four years' was his brazen reply: 'and the public be damned!'.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon we went to a local race&#8211;meeting, &amp;, for the first time in my life, I witnessed horse races. Everything was on a modest local scale: the pleasant air, bright sun, &amp; rich green of turf &amp; trees made a delightful scene in which to loaf for two hours. We had tea at the Club: &amp; then mine host drove me home in a queer little vehicle, accommodating just two persons. His horse, a trotter from Kentucky, went with the speed of lightning.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
In the evening there was a dinner party. I was much interested in <persName xml:id="3012" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Potter</persName>, who had been prominent in leading municipal reform in Philadelphia some years since. He told me that he had been elected mayor, but had been 'counted out' by a dishonest manoeuvre of his opponents. This falsification of returns appears to be a common expedient in American municipal politics. We had a considerable discussion about the Panama Canal question, with respect to which M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Potter expressed himself as wholly on the English side.<note xml:id="159" n="1"></note> We also discussed the relations of Great Britain &amp; Germany. He had been in Berlin some while since, &amp; had there formed the opinion that Great Britain was the victim of a scare. I tried to disillusion him. <persName xml:id="3014" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Newbolt</persName>, a member of the great financial house in which <persName xml:id="3013">Pierpoint Morgan</persName> holds empire, professed himself to have been convinced by the arguments of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="2815">Taft</persName> that the preference to American coasting trade was no breach of the treaty, but he allowed that the matter was not clear of doubt &amp; could not fitly be withheld from the Hague Tribunal. <persName xml:id="3015" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ingersoll</persName>, the other guest, concurred with the view that the Treaty had been violated. On the whole I suppose that these three gentlemen were fairly representative of educated and responsible American opinion.
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
