<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. New Haven, Conn.</hi>
         </p>
         
<div type="quote">
         
         <p>
<hi>It certainly appears strange that the men most conversant with the order of the visible universe should soonest suspect it empty of directing mind; and on the other hand, that humanistic, moral &amp; historical studies &#8211; which first open the terrible problems of suffering &amp; grief, &amp; contain all the repeated provocatives of denial &amp; despair &#8211; should confirm, &amp; enlarge rather than disturb, the prepossessions of natural piety.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Martineau. Essays. i. 122</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
         
         <p>
<hi>A dull cool day but without rain. I wrote to <persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName>, <persName xml:id="800">Westlake</persName>, <persName xml:id="2254" display="no">Travers</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2087">Murray Butler:</persName> &amp; then worked at that dreadful Albany address, which hangs over me like a cloud.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I addressed the Divinity students at noon. <persName xml:id="3053">Mine host</persName> presided, &amp; most of the professors were present. I repeated in substance the little address which I gave to the students at Hartford. <persName xml:id="3057">Bacon</persName> walked home with me afterwards. He is the best of men.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
After lunch I wrote to <persName xml:id="826">Ernest Bennett</persName>, <persName xml:id="1676">Noel Masters</persName>, <persName xml:id="1715">Kellner</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="251">Grant Robertson</persName>. Then mine host &amp; I walked for an hour: after which we returned for tea &amp; the abominable labours of packing. <persName xml:id="3061">Prof.</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3062">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Porter</persName> called to bid us farewell.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
We dined with <persName xml:id="2032">Newman Smyth</persName>. <persName xml:id="3069">President</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3070">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hadley</persName> dined also. We had much conversation about the present situation in Europe. It soon became apparent that <hi rend="bold underline">the President held strongly philo&#8211;German opinions</hi><hi>, which perhaps is only what might be expected in view of his close personal connection with Germany &amp; especially with the Court. He maintained that the Emperor was strongly pacific: that at the present juncture he was supporting France: that, if a general European war grew out of the trouble in the Balkans, America would probably be the gainer: that in the event of Great Britain being defeated by Germany, it was highly probable that America, led by the Irish &amp; German elements, would be disinclined to intervene in its behalf: though much would turn on the particular form the war would take. It distressed me to hear these sentiments, which on the whole received the assent of mine host &amp; of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Newman Smyth. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Is it possible that we in England are living in a complete fool's Paradise when we speak of solidarity of the English&#8211;speaking race as a latent force, making for peace, which would emerge as a 'Deus ex machina' for our national rescue, if the pinch of extreme crisis arose?</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We returned home, &amp; resumed the dreary and disheartening functions of packing.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
