<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>
We packed our much&#8211;battered trunks ('valises'), breakfasted, &amp; paid our reckoning &#8211; 18 dollars 10 cents for three nights, rather less than I expected, though, considering the pinched area &amp; perpetual gloom of our hired dwelling, enough in all conscience. A big porter carried our baggage over to the new Central station, &amp; put us on board the train. I gave him a dollar, &amp; he thanked me quite civilly. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">So we ended a costly &amp; rather barren visit to New York, a city which amazes while it disgusts the visitor</hi><hi rend="italic">. The 'sky&#8211;scrapers' grow ever more stupendous, though the 'flat&#8211;iron'; retains its pre&#8211;eminence for almost insolent disregard of all reasonable probability.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The papers report a suggestive incident. <persName xml:id="2320">Professor Moore</persName> of Yale has presented a report on the educational system of New York, which has so greatly exasperated the municipal authorities, that they have voted the document unworthy of publication, &amp; have decided not to publish it. The gravamen seems to be that the pundit has denounced the interference of 'politicians' with the educational organization, which he describes contemptuously. I asked <persName xml:id="3112">President Richmond</persName> whether Moore had any justice in his case. "He is absolutely right" he replied without a moment's hesitation, adding, however, that he had no special information.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I assume that the Dean of Durham has ceased to be ex officio chancellor of Durham University: &amp;, on the whole, I am disposed not to regret this, though, of course, the academic status would have added both to the interest &amp; to the importance of the post: but the titular headship of a modern university means more ceremonial prominence than I like. Nor am I at all convinced that I could fill </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that</hi><hi rend="italic"> office usefully.</hi><note xml:id="198" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After the government of a very aged Dean &#8211; &amp; he a conventional Radical &#8211; it is not improbable that much slackness, if not many specific abuses, will have invaded the working of the Cathedral. The minor canons, the choirmen, the choir school (if such exists), the attendance of the residential canons, all are likely to need some revising, &amp; 'screwing up'.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">We reached Boston about 3 p.m., &amp; drove to 21 Kirkland Street</hi><hi rend="italic">, which the cabman had some difficulty in finding. Here were some letters from home, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">telegrams congratulating me on my appointment from the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, <persName xml:id="601">Muir&#8211;Mackenzie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="227">Murrays</persName><persName xml:id="666"></persName></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1715">Prof:</persName> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="2746" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Max Kellner</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> called. They had not heard of my going to Durham, but professed great satisfaction when I told them.</hi></p>
         <p>
We had a quite agreeable evening with our hosts.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
