<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Williamstown.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The glorious weather still continues. Breakfast was enlivened &amp; protracted by a discussion with <persName xml:id="3031" display="no">mine hostess</persName> on the female suffrage question. That abominable folly is in the atmosphere as a new microbe; &amp; the disease breaks out everywhere.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a number of letters with reference to my engagements in this country which threaten to multiply beyond all tolerable limits.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2815">Taft</persName>, the President, visited Williamstown. He motored to this house where he was received by a number of representative people. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I were presented to him. He appeared to remember having met us at the White House, three years ago, which was creditable. In spite of his public anxieties he seems extremely well &amp; cheerful &#8211; a large round man beaming with good nature and elephantine small&#8211;talk! I was amused at the mode of address which a rather ruffianly&#8211;looking man adopted towards the Head of the State. "Hello, Bill: How's with you?". "Bully"!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Escorted by the shrill cheers of children the President down [sic] to the Campus where the students were gathered to receive him. Their </hi>
<hi rend="underline">maniacal</hi>
<hi> applause was rewarded by a short speech, which dwelt with perhaps unintended pathos on the fragility of friendships in later life compared with their strength in youth! The sinister form of the <persName xml:id="2340">"Bull&#8211;Moose"</persName> flitted across one's mental horizon while he was speaking. After the great man's departure, we returned to the house, &amp; I took some photographs.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>: as well as a whole sheaf of letters to American correspondents about my plans.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A sudden storm of wind &amp; rain put an end to a scheme for driving again in the hills. After it had passed I strolled through the town, or rather down the hill, &amp; on the way, identified the 'Heroes Monument', erected to some Williams College men who fell in the Civil War. I noticed that all the names were 'Anglo&#8211;Saxon'. It is this unquestioned dominance of the British stocks that blinds Americans to the risks of such an inrush of ethnical rubbish as is now filling the country.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Mine hostess &amp; I went for a walk in the gloaming: or rather since there can hardly be said to be any 'gloaming' here at this season in the interval after sunsetting. The wind was too high for easy conversation, &amp; I was in my most resolutely diplomatic mood: so that we avoided the rock of female suffrage!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3032" display="no"><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3033" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Eels</persName> of Cleveland with their <persName xml:id="3034" display="no">son</persName> who is a student here came to dinner. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> E. is a prosperous business man. He said he would vote for Taft, though with much hesitation, but he thought <persName xml:id="2814">Wilson</persName> was certain to be elected. We had a considerable discussion which interested me much. The frankly 'business' aspect of the situation was admirably stated by M</hi>
<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Eels; &amp; the academic point of view was well maintained by mine <persName xml:id="2891">host</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
