<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
It is a sign of the want of religious interest in the Renaissance, especially in Italy, that printing had been going on for sixty years, &amp; 24000 works issued from the press, some of them more than a hundred times, before anybody thought of the Greek Testament.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName> <ref xml:id="129">'Lectures on Modern History'</ref> p. 88.
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
Another brilliant morning, but cold. I made my start in the Chapel at 8.45 am. There was a good sprinkling of men including the <persName xml:id="3035">President</persName>. I took the passage in Amos iii, &amp; talked about privilege. Everything was very brief as the service had to end sharply at 9 a.m. Then for 2 hours I sate in <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName> expecting the youth, who didn't come save one sophomore who wanted to take my photograph! However I utilized the time by writing to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> for her birthday, &amp; to <persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName>, asking if <persName xml:id="3211">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kitchin</persName> were still alive. Then I returned to mine host's dwelling, from which <hi rend="bold underline">I was soon fetched by one of the clergy of the new cathedral (S. Paul's) which <persName xml:id="931">Bishop Lawrence</persName> has now started. He (the bishop) says the site is worth 2,000,000 dollars</hi>! The cleric who guided me was evidently an ardent devotee of the Bull Moose. He explained that <persName xml:id="2340">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Roosevelt</persName> was trying to do in America what <persName xml:id="234">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lloyd George</persName> was doing in England, apart of course from Home Rule!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold"> [179] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
There was a fair congregation largely consisting of women. I preached for 25 minutes which (as I afterwards learned) was 10 minutes to [sic] long. My text was the saying: 'Become trusted money&#8211;changers'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My first lecture on the </hi><orgName xml:id="251" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Southmore Foundation</hi></orgName><hi rend="bold underline"> &#8211; "Problems of organized Christianity" &#8211; was given in the chapel at </hi><orgName xml:id="252"><hi rend="bold underline">Andover Theological Seminary</hi></orgName>. There was a good attendance, &amp; the attention was close &amp; well&#8211;sustained. If I may believe the enthusiastic comments of <persName xml:id="3207">President Fitch</persName>, <persName xml:id="1266">Professor Moore</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3208" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burgess</persName> the lecture was very successful. But the subject of this lecture, "The problem of Ecclesiastical Unity", is probably the most generally attractive.</p>
         <p>
Mine host tells me that <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName>, when he lectured here on the "Noble" foundation, started with an audience of between two &amp; three hundred; but failed to retain their interest, &amp; wound up with but a dozen. When I inquired what might be the reason of his failure, my host replied that his whole attitude &amp; tone were so medieval that the men couldn't stand it. It will be interesting to see whether my lectures (which are certainly not open to the charge of medievalism) will escape a similar disaster.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We dined with the President &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="3210"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Lowell</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> &#8211; a very pleasant party. After dinner we had some brisk conversation. Everybody seems to agree that Germany means to fight Great Britain</hi>.</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
