<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[236]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>No prayer for light will save us from the trouble of conscientious labour, or bring us a miraculous knowledge; but it may woo to our side humility, sympathy, and candour, who will go with us, the angel guardians of our way, &amp; keep us from the slough of self&#8211;deception.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1869" display="no">James Drummond</persName></hi>. <ref xml:id="361">'Johannine Thoughts'</ref> p. 69.</p>
</div>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I preached a "Farewell" sermon at Mattins</hi>. There was a very large congregation, including <persName xml:id="539">Alfred Lyttelton</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1731">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowther</persName>. My text which of course was a mere label, &amp; had no other relation to the Sermon, was taken from Romans XV. 5.6. <hi rend="underline">Gilbert &amp; I carried the MS. to the 'Times’ Office during the afternoon. The 'Times’ sent me a telegram yesterday begging for the MS</hi>.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> preached in the evening at the Abbey, &amp; the overflow of his congregation thronged S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. Consequently the Offertory exceeded &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">11</hi>, making a total for the day of over &#x00A3;33.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[237]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" in its issue of Monday, the 9</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> December <ref xml:id="699" display="no">printed my sermon</ref> in extenso</hi><hi rend="italic">. If I may judge from the expressions of opinion which have come to me, it has pleased persons of very different types &amp; temperaments. Thus the Dean of Rochester (<persName xml:id="379">Lane</persName>) &amp; <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> write in quite ardent terms: <persName xml:id="325">the Dean</persName> here expresses himself favourably: the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> is very pleased with it. </hi><persName xml:id="1185"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Tait</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> writes that it seemed to him 'perfect’. <persName xml:id="1283" display="no">Arbuthnot</persName> was ardently laudatory. Several men whom I don't know came up to me in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> to thank me for it. Several strangers have written in the same strain. </hi><persName xml:id="2179"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Emmet</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, who counts as a Broad Churchman, thanks me warmly. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On Thursday we lunched with the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lowther. They were most kind, &amp; expressed much regret at our departure. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On Saturday we lunched with the Bp. of London, who was as ever affectionate. He would like to think that he is also large&#8211;minded: but it is not given to his type to be that. We parted in peace on the note of old memories.</hi></p>
         <p>In the evening I attended a meeting of the Guild.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
