<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Bryn Mawr.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>Grant we beseech thee, merciful Lord, to thy faithful people pardon &amp; peace; that they may be cleansed from all their sins, &amp; serve thee with a quiet mind; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>Amen</hi></p>
         <p>
A motor was sent to fetch us to the University. There I preached to six or seven hundred men &amp; a few women in the Gymnasium. I repeated the sermon on Jacob's dream which I preached in Winnipeg. Then we were motored back to Bryn Mawr. The Presbyterian Minister, <persName xml:id="3123">Mutch</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3124">his wife</persName> came to lunch. We got on to the risky subject of Female Suffrage, but a crisis was averted by some timely diversion. Then we went to our room, &amp; I rested for an hour. <persName xml:id="2321">Dorothea Moore</persName>, the daughter of <persName xml:id="1266">Professor Edward Moore</persName>, fetched us out to have tea in her rooms. Here she brought a number of her fellow students, bright, well&#8211;grown girls exceptionally charming &amp; intelligent. Among them came <persName xml:id="2889" display="no">Miss Garfield</persName> the daughter of the <persName xml:id="2891">Williamstown president</persName>. I had much conversation with <persName xml:id="3130" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Miss Lucille Davidson</hi></persName>, a girl from Texas, who professed herself of no church, but a Christian. I took a great fancy for her: &amp; promised to write on the subject, which that was no place to discuss.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p>
These girls are almost all eager advocates of female suffrage, &amp; mostly enthusiasts for <persName xml:id="2814">Wilson</persName>.</p>
         <p>
I preached in the Gymnasium to a considerable congregation of the students &amp; others. A choir of students sang an anthem very sweetly, &amp; led the singing of the Hymns. <hi rend="bold underline">I preached the sermon on <persName xml:id="505">Stanley's</persName> favourite text: "I see that all things come to an end, but Thy commandment is exceeding broad".</hi> The attention was close; &amp; there seemed a spirit of reverence &amp; worship among us all. The stillness of the scene illumined by a clear moon nearing the full was most solemn. There is an academic severity in the buildings, which is reminiscent of Oxford. The sight of so many fair girl's [sic] faces, beaming with intelligence &amp; aglow with physical health, compelled the mood of optimism: &amp; I felt ready to forgive <persName xml:id="2969">Miss Thomas</persName> her mistaken zeal for female suffrage in consideration of her conduct of this great college. Several girls claimed recognition &#8211; Dorothea Moore, a cousin of <persName xml:id="3140">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scott</persName> our archivist, a daughter of <persName xml:id="2611">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Napier</persName> who was a member of the abortive Welsh Church Committee, &amp; Miss Garfield.<note xml:id="239" display="no" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
I wrote to my godson <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="803">Dams</persName> bidding him give the Choirboys a shilling apiece on my Birthday. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> also wrote to <persName xml:id="3146" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Berry</persName> bidding her make &amp; despatch the Birthday cake as in former years. I suppose it is probably that this will be the last of such benefactions.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
