<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge Mass.</hi></p>
         <p>
A most beautiful warm day. I conducted prayers in the chapel as usual, taking for my subject 'the Rule of Just Criticism’ as laid down in Matthew vii. 1&#8211;5. then I went to <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName>, where I was undisturbed. <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote a letter to the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> in response to a not very gracious letter in which he was good enough to inform me that in his judgement <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon Watkins</persName> should have been appointed Dean!</hi></p>
         <p>
At 11.a.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3315" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Arthur Beane</hi></persName> came to fetch me to the <orgName xml:id="257">'Phillips Brooks’ House</orgName>, a centre of social &amp; religious work founded in memory of <persName xml:id="1802">Phillips Brooks</persName>. I was interested to observe the characteristically American arrangement by which a separate chapel &amp; room was set aside severally for the Episcopalians, the Christian Young Men, &amp; the Christian Scientists. The latter number about 25, &amp; are said to mix easily with other men. The Roman Catholics, of whom there are said to be about 250, once had their home here also, but they went forth on the plea that they must smoke in the House, which is contrary to rules. They are said to be almost entirely Irish. <hi rend="underline">Roman priests have been invited to conduct the services at Appleton Chapel, but the invitation has never yet been accepted. 'They hold all together, &amp; keep themselves close, while they lay wait for men's souls’.</hi><note xml:id="201" n="1"></note> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi></p>
         <p>
We lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3376">Prof.</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="3377" display="no">Peabody</persName></hi>. An Episcopalian clergyman, the Rector of Grace Church, M<hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="3331">Evarts(?)</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3332">his wife</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1715">Prof. Max Kellner</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2746" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Kellner</persName> made up the party. After lunch we walked, and then I managed to get the long&#8211;deferred 'cut &amp; shampoo’ performed very vigorously by a French&#8211;Canadian for the sum of 70 cents.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The evening paper reports the assassination of the </hi><persName xml:id="3394"><hi rend="bold underline">Spanish Premier</hi></persName>: &amp; the most harrowing account conceivable of the state of the population in Constantinople. </p>
         <p>
After an early dinner at 6.p.m. we went over to the <orgName xml:id="259">Episcopalian Seminary</orgName>, and there I discoursed for three quarters of an hour to the students on the relations of Church &amp; State in England. Some questions were asked at the end, which somewhat lightened what would otherwise have been a dull performance. Then there was a reception in the house, and we kept the pot of promiscuous talk in perpendicular attitudes boiling for some while. Then we went to bed, I for my part feeling more than usually fatigued. </p>
         <p>
I gave my remaining volume of <ref xml:id="82">'Puritanism in England’</ref> to <persName xml:id="946"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Appleton Lawrance</hi></persName>, who is a student at the Episcopalian Theological Seminary. I am informed that there are at the present time forty one students in residence, &#8211; this is aid to be a fair average number.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
