<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[217]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>	</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. New York.</hi></p>
         <p>
A bright, beautiful day but somewhat misty, &amp; with a keen breeze. <persName xml:id="3400">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fisher</persName> came for us after breakfast, &amp; we went at once to the White Star C<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi>'s office. There I paid the balance of my ticket&#8211;charge (&#x0024;150), and then, leaving my companions to bestow themselves as they would, I returned to the house, where I was almost immediately claimed by <persName xml:id="3401" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Knox</hi></persName>, and taken to the Chapel of Columbia University, where a considerable number of students &amp; dons had assembled together for a brief service. <hi rend="bold underline">I addressed them for 10 minutes </hi>on the subject 'The Meaning of Privilege'. Then I lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knox, &amp; two of his friends. <hi rend="italic bold underline">The conversation turned on the Jews</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was stated that 30 or 40 years ago Jews were received into clubs &amp; society without difference or difficulty: but that now there was a great change. It was all but impossible to secure equal treatment for Jews in academic &amp; social life. Mention was made of a club in New York which had been founded some years ago by a Jew, whose son was recently refused admission. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The main reason alleged for this melancholy change was the change for the worse in the type of Jewish immigrant. The Sephardim have given place to Ashkenazim. Add the formidable numbers of American Jews, &amp; it is perhaps not necessary to seek farther for an explanation. But the fact is in no slight measure humbling &amp; disconcerting.</hi> I was assured that <hi rend="bold">[218]</hi> [symbol] no similar prejudice obstructed the way of the educated Japanese or Chinaman. <hi rend="bold underline">The Jew shares with the Negro the dolorous distinction of a racial antagonism which neither ability nor virtue can disarm</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi>I took a short walk along the esplanade which runs for some distance along the cliff beside the Hudson. It is a really noble adornment to the City. The large monument to General Grant makes a fine show.</hi></p>
         <p>
I attended in hood and gown the inauguration of the new 'Browne Professor of Homiletics', <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3402"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Johnston Ross</hi></persName>. The function took place in the Chapel, which is an unusually fine building, acoustically above the average of lofty buildings. There was a 'charge' to the new Professor delivered by one of the 'Directors', who was plainly 'a pillar of orthodoxy', &amp; felt himself called upon to bear testimony against those minimizing hereticks, who placed notes of interrogation against the Virgin Birth &amp; Physical Resurrection &amp;c. He passionately exhorted the new professor to preach 'a big Christ', 'a colossal Christ'. To which the said new Professor made response in an inordinately long 'inaugural address' in which he emphasized the primary need of dwelling on the Unity of God! <hi rend="bold underline">The whole proceedings took more than 2 hours, &amp; wearied me inexpressibly. </hi>We went in to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3352" display="no"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Hall</hi></persName> afterwards, and had some tea, &amp; wrote our names in her visitors' book.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[219] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">We dined with <persName xml:id="2087">President Murray Butler</persName> in his fine new official house. It was a very interesting party.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I sate next </hi><persName xml:id="3085"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Carnegie</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> at dinner, &amp; had much conversation with her. She is a very pleasant, unassuming person, &amp; merits the excellent reputation which she possesses. She told me that she greatly admired </hi><persName xml:id="109"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archdeacon Wilberforce</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; attended his preaching when she was in London. <persName xml:id="3084">Her husband</persName>, the redoubtable millionaire, also merits his reputation. We got into conversation after dinner on the great question of peace, on which, perhaps, I ought to have remembered that he is fanatical. He was very impertinent to me over the Panama Canal business. </hi><persName xml:id="3068"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Greer</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> said to me "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I hope you won't judge us by that little man, who thinks he can say anything because of his millions</hi><hi rend="italic">". To which I rejoined that I trusted the Bishop had observed that I had remembered my position as a guest, &amp; had suppressed a resentment both natural &amp; well&#8211;grounded. I think the little man was dimly conscious that he hadn't distinguished himself, &amp; made advances afterwards in the music room: but I reflected sadly on the immense homage which he expected &amp; received on no other ground than that provided by his immense, &amp; almost incredible wealth. <persName xml:id="3069">President</persName> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3070"><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Hadley</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> were among the guests.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
