<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi>	</p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Boston, Mass.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>3.30 a.m.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The position of the Unitarians in this country puzzles me</hi>. They seem to be nowise distinguished from the rest of non–episcopal denominations. <hi rend="bold underline">Their distinctive, &amp; wholly disqualifying, heresy does not seem to be regarded as of any special significance</hi>. Unitarian ministers are as freely admitted to episcopalian pulpits as others: and there is no question save among the strictest sacerdotalists of excluding Unitarians from Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="931"><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> assured me that Unitarianism was now a mere label, without any distinctive meaning: that Unitarians both repeated the Apostles Creed, &amp; worshipped Christ: that there could hardly be said to be any organized Unitarian Church, but that Unitarians were just the liberal section of the Christian community in Massachusetts. I inquired what might be the rule with respect to Baptism. He replied that generally they used no Baptism, &amp; that where the ceremony was used, the orthodox formula was not employed. All this seems to me to constitute a grave practical bar to free religious intercourse. Indeed, it is hard to imagine any conceivable basis of unifying the Churches, if the worship of Christ as Divine be made a matter of option</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195] </hi>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop expressed himself somewhat contemptuously of the Committee for Church Unity, which </hi><persName xml:id="3013"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Pierpont Morgan</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> has endowed with 100,000 dollars.</hi> I agree in thinking that no result of value can come from negotiations which have not first found a reasonable platform.  <hi rend="italic">'It was just a piece of Morgan's impulsiveness, the giving of that money’, observed the Bishop, 'but he was taken with the notion that Episcopalians should be willing to negotiate, &amp; offered his gift at once. It is only the money that gives any special importance to the movement.’</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">(10.a.m.) The position of the millionaires in the religious world is not pleasing, &amp;, probably, is not helpful to Religion. It was with something of a shock that I read the name, </hi><persName xml:id="3209"><hi rend="italic underline">'John Jacob Astor’</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> inscribed largely on the base of one of the large pillars of the apse in the cathedral in New York. Other names of less well–known millionaires are carved on the other pillars. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The suggestion of a church built on Mammon, bridled by gold, &amp; running on lines of metal, is insistent &amp; hateful</hi><hi rend="italic">. I must needs think that the general conscience is offended by such a parade of millionaire–patronage. I said all this to mine host &amp; he agreed. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Bishop Lawrance is alone among his episcopal brethren in standing outside the cathedral–building fashion, which has set in generally, notably in Washington &amp; New York</hi><hi rend="italic">. His modest cathedral is, &amp; will remain, a working church.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3215" display="no">Miss Lawrence</persName> went with me in the motor to Appleton chapel. There was a good congregation – larger than last Sunday. <hi rend="bold underline">Miss L. told me that the undergraduates turned out for me much more numerously than for the Bishop of Winchester, a fact which pleases my modest and generous spirit! </hi>I conducted the whole service, using the prayers from the Prayer Book. My sermon was from the text "the Word of the Lord was precious in those days: there was no open vision."</p>
         <p>
A curious fact was told me by Miss L. Since the river has been dammed to make a lake, there has been a plague of flies. These in turn have attracted a multitude of spiders, which have become such a nuisance as even to affect the letting value of the houses which border the lake. She said that her aunt, who occupied one of these infested houses, had spent hundreds of dollars in a vain effort to destroy them! </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Boston Globe" has a <ref xml:id="714" display="no">report of my speech</ref> to the <orgName xml:id="261" display="no">Twentieth Club</orgName></hi><hi rend="italic">. The headlines are rather alarming; but the substance of the report is not substantially incorrect. An old reporter called during the afternoon to beg the MS. of my sermon, &amp; to have an interview. I promised the first but the last came to nothing before my statement that a proof must be sent to me. He could not guarantee a proof as everything had to go in to the Editor this afternoon.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi></p>
         <p>
I preached in Trinity Church at the 4.p.m. service. There was a considerable congregation. I used the sermon "No temple in Heaven", which I preached in Montreal on Sept. 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> (v.p. 42). Then we had tea with the <persName xml:id="3216">Rector</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3217" display="no">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="946"><hi rend="underline">Appleton Lawrence</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1017">his wife</persName> came to an early supper at 6.30.p.m: &amp; accompanied me to the cathedral. <persName xml:id="949">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lawrence</persName> also came. There was a very large congregation, to which I preached from the words <hi rend="underline">"Behold the lamb of God, which taketh away the sin of the world."</hi> The Bishop picked us up after the service in his motor–car.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">So ends the 11</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sunday spent on American soil. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I have preached no less than 25 times, of which 6 sermons were on week–days, &amp; 19 on Sundays. </hi><hi rend="italic">I have also given 11 addresses, &amp; 3 lectures, besides the daily talks to the students at Harvard, &amp; several similar addresses elsewhere.</hi> </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
