<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi></p>
         <p>A bitterly cold morning. I did not feel well enough to adventure the 8 a.m. service: but I preached at Mattins to a full &amp; attentive congregation, taking for my use the much&#8211;used sermon on the words: "I see that all things come to an end: but Thy commandment is exceeding broad". It seemed quite impossible that within a few weeks I shall be a stranger to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, with no more right there than anyone else. I celebrated the Holy Communion. There were no less than 116 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>I sent in to the Bank three cheques, valued respectively &#x00A3;103.1.10: &#x00A3;31.12.0: &#x00A3;50. total &#x00A3; <hi rend="underline">184.13.10</hi>, together with the Columbia preaching fee of 25 dollars, &amp; my Letter of Credit for &#x00A3;200, of which only &#x00A3;105 had been drawn. I trust these demented Suffragettes will respect the Post Box in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>!</p>
         <p>The weather changed during the afternoon. By Evensong there was heavy rain. In spite of this there was a considerable congregation in S. Margaret's. I preached another old sermon, from the text: "Behold the Lamb of God which taketh away the Sin of the World".</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2970" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kirby</persName>, our ship's comrade, came in to supper. Also <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
