<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday November 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">'So teach us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom.’</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Shew Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee.</hi></p>
         <p>
<div type="quote">
<hi rend="italic">'History is often made by energetic men, steadfastly following ideas, mostly wrong, that determine events.’</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName> l.c. 70.</hi></p>
         <p>
</div>
<hi rend="italic">It is my Birthday. 49 years have slipped away since I was granted an individual existence on this planet. My various activities &amp; my actual situation today are suggestive of many experiences &amp; conflicts. I start by taking prayers &amp; giving an address in an undenominational university chapel. Then I preach in the episcopal cathedral. In the afternoon, I lecture in a congregational Seminary. I start the day as the guest with a congregational minister: I end it as the guest of the local Bishop! This Birthday belongs to the series of critical times in my life (v. p. 162). Will it be the starting point of some genuine service? or is it the first page of another chapter of failure? Assuredly as one grows older, &amp; knows more of one's self &amp; the world, one does not become more hopeful, or more self&#8211;confident.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
         <p>
There was a budget of letters at breakfast, including one from <persName xml:id="1185"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Tait</hi></persName>, dated Oct. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and written in much consternation after seeing the announcement of my appointment in the <ref xml:id="676" display="no">'Times'</ref>.</p>
         <p>
I conducted prayers in Appleton Chapel, taking as the subject of my little address the answer of the Three Youths to Nebuchadnezzar. My vigil in <placeName xml:id="57">Wadsworth House</placeName> was much disturbed by visitors. First, came <hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3386" display="no"><hi rend="underline"> D. Howard Fletcher</hi></persName> who wished to express his sense of the courtesies shown to him in a recent visit to England! Next, came Professor <persName xml:id="3376"><hi rend="underline">F. Peabody</hi></persName> who wished to arrange a luncheon party, &amp; stayed to discuss my lecture at Andover, which he had heard. He expressed his vehement disapproval of the 'Eschatological' interpretation of Christ adopted by <persName xml:id="574"><hi rend="underline">Burkitt</hi></persName>. Then, came a very pleasant young fellow, <persName xml:id="3357"><hi rend="underline">James P. Gifford</hi></persName>, who wanted to talk over the taking of Orders. He was followed by <persName xml:id="3388" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Eldon Griffen</hi></persName> (1683 Cambridge St. Cambridge Mass. His home address is 418 West Park Avenue, Enid, Oklahoma), who talked in general: &amp; at last came <persName xml:id="3389" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Charles Hoffman</hi></persName>, who discussed theology. These visitors hindered me from doing any work on my lecture, which was in consequence more than commonly unfinished.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Meanwhile <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had been packing our possessions. She went with them to 122 Commonwealth Avenue in the Bishop's car: while I made my way by the tube to the Cathedral, &amp; there preached on 'Incommunicable</hi> <hi rend="bold">[191]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="bold underline">responsibility'. There was a good attendance</hi>. After service <persName xml:id="2462"><hi rend="underline">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</hi></persName> came into the vestry to see me. <persName xml:id="949">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lawrence</persName> picked me up, &amp; carried me home. Here <hi rend="bold underline">I met at lunch a vivacious clergyman, <persName xml:id="2071" display="no">Leighton Park</persName>, <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Lady Barran's</persName> father</hi>.</p>
         <p>
After lunch we all (the Bishop, Park, &amp; myself) motored to the Divinity School Chapel at Cambridge, and there attended the funeral of the late <persName xml:id="3361">Professor Nash</persName>. The chapel was quite full: &amp; the service very impressive.</p>
         <p>
Then I took refuge in <persName xml:id="946">Appleton Lawrence's</persName> house (5 Fuller Road, Cambridge Mass.) &amp; there read over the MS of my lecture. <hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="931">Bishop</persName> walked round with me to <orgName xml:id="252">Andover Seminary</orgName>, &amp; attended my 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Lecture</hi>. The subject was "The problem of moral discipline". There was again a good attendance.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The company at dinner included D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Worcester, the founder of the "Immanuel Movement". He is a large, fresh&#8211;coloured man, with a curious suggestion of <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> in his manner &amp; aspect. Bp. Lawrence tells me that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">when <persName xml:id="280">Boyd&#8211;Carpenter</persName> gave the 'Noble' lectures some years ago there was difficulty in finding a room big enough to contain the audiences</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
