<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912. Cambridge, Mass.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
The great fact which we have to recognize is that he (Luther) did more than any single man to make modern history the development of revolution.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName> l.c. 105.</p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>"These that have turned the world upside down" &#8211; is one of the earliest descriptions of genuine Christians we possess. It is hardly true of the admirable professors, whom we now meet.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I conducted the prayers in the Chapel, taking the Oracle in </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Micah VI</hi><hi rend="italic"> as my theme, &amp; linking it on to the Gunpowder Plot. There was a good attendance of men, &amp; they were very attentive. No inquirers emerged in the 'Preacher's room' so I spent my 2 hours in revising tomorrow's lecture, &amp; abbreviating today's sermon.</hi>	 </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I went to the Cathedral, &amp; preached a Guy Fawkes sermon</hi><hi rend="italic">, rather to the amazement of everybody, for, as one of the clergy observed afterwards, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">'we never mention the Jesuits here: it isn't safe to do so in Boston!' And this is the ancient citadel of Puritanism! There is evidently a very large Roman Catholic population in the place</hi><hi rend="italic">, for I find myself being reverently saluted by the 'organ&#8211;grinders' at every turn. After the service a reporter came in to the vestry, &amp; demanded my views on <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd&#8211;George</persName>. '</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Lloyd&#8211;George is a parishioner of mine', I replied gravely, 'and I make a rule of never criticizing my own parishioners</hi><hi rend="italic">.'</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[181]</hi> 
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At breakfast this morning our conversation turned on the English Congregationalists. I said that their vehement political partisanship greatly impaired their spiritual influence. <persName xml:id="1266">Mine host</persName> observed that on his visits to England he had been deeply and unfavourably impressed by the bitterness of his co&#8211;religionists, so markedly unlike their temper in this country. He told me that <persName xml:id="3383">Fairbairn</persName> had desired that he (Moore) sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic">. have been his own successor in the headship of Mansfield: that this wish had never matured in an actual invitation to accept the position; but the suggestion had induced him to think over the situation in England, &amp; he </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">had come to the conclusion that the Congegrationalist leaders their [sic] were not playing a good part, &amp; that, if he were to accept office in England, he w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> have perforce disappointed them</hi><hi rend="italic">. 'After all', he continued, 'it is not so many years since the Congregational Church in New England was itself an Established church, &amp; it </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">has preserved something of that largeness of outlook &amp; sympathy which belongs to Establishment, &amp; makes amends for much that is otherwise objectionable.' I rejoiced to hear such a testimony from such a source</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">There was a dinner&#8211;party in the evening. The <persName xml:id="3035">President</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3210"><hi rend="bold underline"> Lowell</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> were among the guests</hi>. He had brought with him a copy of the Hay&#8211;Pauncefote Treaty in order to prove to me that the American contention was not so flagrantly wrong as it certainly at first view seems to be. But he didn't quite succeed in convincing me: though I see his point, which was new to me.<note xml:id="159" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
