<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[280]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
My last Sunday in Westminster was spent in a house half&#8211;dismantled by preparations for the contractor's men tomorrow. How impossible it seems to realize that I shall cease to have any rights in this house!</p>
         <p>
My wife &amp; I went to the Abbey Church for Mattins, and stayed to receive the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="277"><hi rend="underline">Lord Portsmouth</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2777">his Countess</persName> shared the sub&#8211;Dean's pew with us: and behind us, in the Dean's pew, sate <persName xml:id="539"><hi rend="underline">Alfred Lyttelton</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1333">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> came in for lunch, &amp; that excellent fellow <persName xml:id="1384"><hi rend="underline">Bailward</hi></persName>. My godson went with me to Evensong, where <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> preached a very wandering discourse: after which I called on <persName xml:id="326"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="underline"> Ryle</hi></persName>, &amp; presented her with my photograph. Also, I presented my photograph to <persName xml:id="216"><hi rend="underline">Gow</hi></persName>, &amp; <hi rend="italic">obtained his leave to present copies of </hi><ref xml:id="82"><hi rend="italic underline">"Puritanism in England"</hi></ref><hi rend="italic"> to his VI</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> Form</hi>.</p>
         <p>
Then I wrote to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName>.</p>
         <p>
There came to supper <persName xml:id="1650">Bridget Hole</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2056">Elsie</persName>, &amp; Gilbert.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[281]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">A very important letter from <persName xml:id="3220">Lord Stamfordham</persName> marked 'Private &amp; Confidential' reached me this morning (Monday) &amp; I immediately drafted a Memorandum, &amp; sent it with this covering letter</hi>.</p>
         <div type="letter">
<p>Dear Lord Stamfordham,</p>
         <p>
Your letter went from the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> to Durham, &amp; thence to Westminster. It reaches me this morning amid the confusions of departure, the workmen having just arrived to pack up furniture &amp;c. But I have at once prepared the enclosed, which, unless my memory deceive me, represents very much what I urged on you at Windsor. Of course it needs not that I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> remind you that I am neither a professed politician, nor a constitutional lawyer, only an ordinary citizen who follows the course of affairs, &amp; is very deeply concerned at the situation into which we have been brought. <hi rend="bold underline">I understand &amp; appreciate the strictly confidential character of your letter: &amp;, of course, I send you the enclosed in strict confidence</hi>.</p>
         <p>
Let me add how much pleasure it gave me to meet you at Windsor, &amp; how greatly I enjoyed my little visit to the Castle. Their Majesties were so kind, &amp; everybody delightful.</p>
         <p>Believe me, &amp;c.
         </p>
         </div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[282]</hi></p>
         <p>
We lunched with <persName xml:id="2712" display="no">Miss Mundella</persName>, who had gathered a pleasant company to meet us. I sate between mine hostess &amp; <persName xml:id="1386">Miss Haldane</persName>, with whom I had much interesting conversation. She expressed great approval of the part I played in the Putumayo business. After lunch she kindly motored us back to Westminster, stopping at Buckingham Palace on the way in order to write her name in the book. I took the opportunity to write my name also.</p>
         <p>
Then, on reaching our house, I took Logic round S. James's Park for the last time. <persName xml:id="2955">Canon Carnegie</persName> with <persName xml:id="3086" display="no">his daughter</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3234">Sir Francis Crawley&#8211;Boevey</persName> his brother in law were at N<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi> 17 taking measurements for carpets &amp; wall&#8211;papers.</p>
         <p>
I drove to the Athenaeum, &amp; left directions as to forwarding my letters. Then I went to Holborn, &amp; took the train for Birchington.</p>
         <p>
So I turned my back finally on the house which for more than 12 years has been mine. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went to stay with <persName xml:id="542">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gow</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[283]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
Copy of Lord Stamfordham's letter dated Feb. 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1913, and marked 'Private &amp; Confidential'.</p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dean,</p>
         <p>
Thank you truly for the Memorandum which accurately records what you said at Windsor, and is valuable as coming from one who is in touch with all sorts of opinion &#8211; indeed to me, <hi rend="underline">more</hi> valuable than the views of the "professed politician" &amp; "constitutional lawyer".</p>
         <p>
All you say regarding your visit to Windsor is, I can assure you, reciprocated by Their Majesties &amp; by those of their Household who had the pleasure of meeting you.</p>
         <p>
Believe me, yours v. truly.</p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[284]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Friday morning (Feb. 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1913) I returned from Birchington to Westminster, joined Ella at N<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi> 19, &amp; lunched with Gow. Then I went to the Athenaeum, &amp; later travelled to Durham with my wife. The next day (Saturday, Feb. 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) I presided at a Chapter Meeting from 11 a.m. to 1.15 p.m. All were present except <persName xml:id="555">Tucker</persName>, who is in Sicily.</p>
         <p>
The next day, the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Sunday in Lent (Feb. 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) I attended Mattins in the Cathedral, &amp; afterwards celebrated. There was but a handfull of communicants, &amp; everybody had left save one minor canon. This seems an unedifying state of affairs. But the service is inordinately long.</p>
         <p>
At 2.20 p.m. <persName xml:id="3233"><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Raw</hi></persName> from Sunderland arrived in an open motor&#8211;car to fetch me for divers functions in that town. The day was bright &amp;, for the time of year, warm: so the drive was agreeable. We stopped at the entrance to the town in order to see the Children's Hospital. Then we went on to the Victoria Hall, where I addressed a large meeting in aid of the local Hospital. While I was speaking, my head began to ache badly, &amp; I could hardly continue my speech. However, I got through somehow: &amp; then went to to [sic] the Bishop Wearmouth Rectory, where a party of citizens came in to be introduced. I went to the Church and preached to a very large congregation. Then I dined with the Mayor &#8211; an amiable old Quaker. I returned to Durham by train, feeling quite miserable! </p>
         <p>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
