<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[285]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="2987" display="no">High Sheriff</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2988" display="no">his wife</persName> came to breakfast &#8211; both very pleasant people. He told me that the Antarctic hero, <persName xml:id="2982">Scott</persName>, was staying at his house just before he left England on his last &amp; fatal enterprize, &amp; that the last words he said were "<hi rend="bold underline">Be sure that I shall either find the Pole or die in the attempt</hi>." At Mattins the <persName xml:id="2989" display="no">Judge</persName> and the <persName xml:id="2990" display="no">Commissioner</persName> attended service in the Cathedral. The National Anthem was played after the Psalms &#8211; an odd arrangement. I shook hands with the Judge at the North door, &amp; then his procession went before the choir &amp; was placed in the stalls. Similarly after service we bowed the great man out.</p>
         <p>We (i.e. the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> &amp; I) went to York by the 2.10 p.m. train arriving at 3.48 p.m. or thereabouts. Here we parted. I went to Bishopthorpe, where <persName xml:id="211">Woollcombe</persName> received me kindly, &amp; we had tea comfortably. Lang took me for a walk. A squad of Bishops &#8211; <persName xml:id="2074">Ripon</persName>, <persName xml:id="720">Carlisle</persName>, <persName xml:id="2980">Wakefield</persName>, <persName xml:id="1132">Newcastle</persName>, <persName xml:id="242">Manchester</persName> &#8211; arrived for the Convocation.</p>
         <p>The Archiepiscopal house is large &amp; well&#8211;appointed. It has been continuously occupied since the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, &amp; represents the successive architectural styles which have flourished between the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> and the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries. The river Ouse flows under the dining room windows.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
