<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[265]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Oxford.</hi></p>
         <p>
The morning was bright &amp; frosty: the ground hard. I walked with a happy freedom from mire to the Barber, &amp;, after he had done his duty, called in at Blackwell's and turned over some books but bought nothing. Then I went to All Souls, &amp; wrote letters: lunched in the Buttery, where was much talk with that odd military Professor, <persName xml:id="3218">Spencer Wilkinson</persName>; loafed all the afternoon in the coffee room talking with <persName xml:id="205">Cunliffe</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="41">Davis</persName>: had tea, &amp; walked back to the Orchard through the snow. I bade mine hostess farewell in her room: &amp; then wrote letters.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> &amp; I dined in College: &amp; had a great discussion with <persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName> &amp; the junior Fellows on the Putumayo question: then on Female Suffrage: finally on the Welsh Church. Then home through the slush &amp; sleet.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[266]</hi>         </p>
         <p>
On Thursday the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> January 1913 I left Oxford &amp; returned to Westminster. On the station I awaited the train from Cheltenham which brought <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> back, and together we went to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>. In the evening I dined at Gray's Inn as the guest of <persName xml:id="313">Vesey Knox</persName>, who is treasurer this year. Old <persName xml:id="3219">Lord Ashbourne</persName> drove me back to Westminster.</p>
         <p>
On Friday the 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> January Ella &amp; I received a present from members of the Congregation &#8211; a silver bowl with an inscription, a “jewel” for the lady, &amp; a cheque. <persName xml:id="794">Sir Henry Craik</persName> made the presentation in rather an 'excessive' speech, but it was kindly meant.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="554">Gilbert Simpson</persName> was with us, having come to spend the week&#8211;end. <persName xml:id="2533">Nixon</persName>, the Bishop of Jarrow, stayed the night having come up for a consecration in Lambeth Chapel.</p>
         <p>
On Saturday the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> January (S. Paul's Day) I received the Holy Communion in Henry VII's Chapel <hi rend="underline">as a mere visitor</hi>. It was an odd &amp; unpleasing sensation to feel without rights or authority in that place. I walked with the Bishop to Lambeth; &amp; bade him farewell. Then I looked at carpets with Ella: &amp; finally went through &amp; destroyed many letters with Gilbert.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
