<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[377]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I hired a motor, and was swiftly carried to <hi rend="bold underline">West Hartlepool</hi> accompanied by <persName xml:id="1095">Aubry</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2936">Boden</persName>. The weather, which had been very threatening all day, improved at the critical time for the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anti&#8211;Welsh Church</hi><hi rend="underline"> Demonstration</hi> approached, &amp; the proceedings were undisturbed by rain. There was a great assemblage of Church&#8211;people, perhaps as many as 10,000, so that the scene was striking. I was the sole speaker (apart from the Chairman) at one of the 3 platforms. My speech occupied just half an hour in delivery. Speaking is always difficult in the open air, &amp; on this occasion it was more than usually difficult because 'the winds were contrary'. As I spoke my admiration was moved by the new moon riding in a stormy sky &#8211; a beautiful spectacle. We were motored back to Durham, where we arrived about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>I was much pleased with the chauffeur &#8211; a clean looking lad of 19. His name is <persName xml:id="2935"><hi rend="underline">Robert Wray</hi></persName>: he is the son of a pitman: has been confirmed &amp; is a communicant. He attends <persName xml:id="590">Watson's</persName> Bible Class at S. Margaret's, &amp; is a total abstainer.</p>
         <p>I wrote a letter of condolence to <persName xml:id="2065" display="no">Mary Lyttleton</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
