<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[438]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>We walked in to the little Episcopalian Church, &amp; there attended service. The sermon was preached by <persName xml:id="3199">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Skinner Wilson</persName>, the Dean of Edinburgh, from the words in the Sermon on the Mount. 'Be not anxious for your life &amp;c.' It was a simple exhortation, not inappropriate to the occasion of a harvest thanksgiving. We stayed to the Holy Communion. When we came out of church, the rain was falling heavily.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to the <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>, telling him that I should ask for a loan from the chapter in order to carry through the restoration of the crypt.</hi></p>
         <p>Then I once more went through that hapless Congress Sermon, 'Ideas &amp; Institutions'. It pleases me less every time I read it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After dinner I ran through a small book called <ref xml:id="716" display="no">"The real Lloyd&#8211;George"</ref> written apparently as a rejoinder to some worshipper's account of that Idol. It makes some good points, &amp; is not ineffective: but the violence with which it is expressed defeats its object: &amp; leaves a candid reader with the impression that whatever else he has gained, he has not gained a view of 'the real Lloyd&#8211;George'. I do not myself think there is any complex problem in the man.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
