<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[390]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>Jesus, on Whom be peace, had said: "The world is but a bridge over which you must pass, but must not linger to build your dwelling."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Agraphon engraved in Arabic on the chief gateway of a mosque at Sikri, about 24 miles from Agra.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> preached at Mattins an excellent sermon on the text: "The hope of the Gospel".</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2846">Parkin</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3098">his Wife</persName>, with two friends halting at Durham for a few hours on a motor journey called on us. I shewed them over the Cathedral before Evensong: they came into tea after service, &amp; saw over the House.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[391]</hi></p>
         <p>
I went to Newcastle, and there visited the dentist. In the train I had as fellow&#8211;traveller, <persName xml:id="3096">Judge Greenwell</persName>, an acute &amp; friendly person.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Tuesday</hi>, <persName xml:id="3087" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> J. Smith</persName> arrived ostensibly to convey <persName xml:id="3088" display="no">his wife</persName> to South Wales on Friday. In the faith of their departure I wrote to the Superintendent of the G.E.R. at York, ordering tickets to Antwerp for Saturday.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I dined with <persName xml:id="3089" display="no">Captain</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3090" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Roberts</persName>, with whom <persName xml:id="2806">Bailey</persName> was staying.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi>, <persName xml:id="3091">Sir Hugh</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3092">Lady Bell</persName> called for tea on their way by motor to Scotland. Later there arrived to stay the night <persName xml:id="3095">Lady Cohen</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, also motoring to Scotland.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Friday</hi>, <persName xml:id="3093" display="no">Miss Bell</persName> came to lunch bringing with her a strange &amp; talkative German, <persName xml:id="3094" display="no">Miss de Bunsen</persName>.</p>
         <p>
I took tickets to Brussels via Antwerp. They cost &#x00A3;8. 9. 0 for the pair of us. Then, greatly daring, I had my hair cut &amp; shampooed by the local practitioner.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Saturday</hi> we left Durham, and travelled to Brussels by way of York, Harwich, &amp; Antwerp. The train was 3/4 of an hour late owing to the Saturday afternoon tourists, but the sea was calm, &amp; we had an easy passage, arriving in Brussels on Sunday morning about 10 a.m.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
