<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[416]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913, The Hague.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
'The history of the last forty years shows that the theory of Infallibility, since it has become a dogma, is not more harmful than it was before.[']</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2999">Bury</persName> <ref xml:id="697">p. 210</ref></p>
</div>
         <p>
This dictum of the Professor will not command the assent of any save Rationalists like himself &amp; Infallibilists. The harmfulness of the dogma has of course shown itself within the Roman Church, where the whole intellectual level has been lowered, and in the relations of Churches, which have become embarrassed &amp; embittered by the new factor.</p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
The achievement of religious liberty in England in the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century has been mainly the work of Liberals. The Liberal party has been moving towards the ultimate goal of complete secularization &amp; the separation of the Church from the State – the logical results of Locke's theory of civil government.</p>
         <p>
Bury p. 106</p>
</div>
         <p>
What is precisely 'religious liberty'? The right of a sect to oppress its own members without interference by the State? Because the goal of the Liberal party implies the squalidest oppression known to human experience, I must decline adherence to that party in spite of its considerable achievements.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[417]</hi></p>
         <p>
We walked round the Mauritshuis, &amp; looked at the pictures. The Rembrandt's [sic], notably the repulsive Anatomy picture, are amazing: &amp; Paul Potter's 'Bull' more fascinating than ever. Holbein's portraits have a distinction &amp; freshness of their own, &amp; a courtly finish which only Vandyck rivals. There is a charming Murillo of the Madonna, with a green velvet skirt which is the acme of earthly splendour! The Wouvermans are interesting: &amp; the Jan Steens as alluringly repulsive. This gallery is so compact, &amp; so full of good things, that one must needs remember it kindly.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2997">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ratford</persName> called at 11 a.m. &amp; took us under his wing. We left cards at the British Legation, which is located in a building, leased from the Jesuits, which formerly housed the Ambassador of Spain. The Spanish Royal Arms are over the portal. It is a curious &amp; arresting transformation! Then I left a card on <persName xml:id="3079" display="no">M. Keinbeiken</persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">the 'directeur' of the Palace of Peace, who had sent me an invitation to the function on Thursday, which, however, I must needs decline</hi>. We next walked to the <hi rend="underline">Huis ten Bosch</hi>, the Queen's Villa. It is a modest &amp; attractive brick building with a strong suggestion of Kensington. There were many preparations being made for illuminations on the occasion of the Celebration of the Centenary of the Dynasty, or rather of the Restoration of the dynasty. The ornamental water, deer, &amp; trees were all admirable.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[418] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ratford gave me some account of the state of feeling here during the South African War. Feeling against Great Britain ran high, &amp; found vehement expression. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Transvaal had been 'the milch cow' of Holland: and the British conquest sent home a flight of adventurers, the hope of whose gains was lost. Many volunteers from the Dutch army went to aid the Boers, but their reception did not accord with their expectations: and not a few returned with changed sentiments</hi><hi rend="italic">. There was a rapid exodus of those members of the congregation who had Dutch relations, and the Chaplain had his windows broken besides being overwhelmed with vituperative post cards. This bitter feeling had now died down, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but the English were still unpopular. In this matter, however, they were being assisted by the superior unpopularity of the Germans, who are invading Holland in ever waxing numbers, and almost confessedly contemplating its absorption in the Reich</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
After lunch we hired a carriage, &amp; were driven about the city for an hour. We were passed on the road by <persName xml:id="3078">Prince Henry</persName> in his motor–car, but knew not that it was he until he had gone from view. So being deprived of the opportunity of saluting the Prince Consort, we bought orange favours, &amp; therewith bedizened ourselves! We went into the Groote Kerk, which (or rather, the choir of which) is being elaborately restored. We saw the statue of Spinoza, a quaint figure crouched into a chair, the very genius of resolute meditation!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[419]</hi></p>
         <p>
We had tea with the Ratfords. <persName xml:id="3021">Lady Meath</persName> was there, &amp; some Austrians. Then we bade them farewell &amp; walked back to the Hotel. We bought a few gifts for the maids, &amp; then had dinner. After this we packed, &amp; left the Hague on our return journey. By a small payment (3/– on each ticket) we were allowed to exchange our Antwerp tickets, &amp; travel via Hook of Holland. The steamers are better: &amp; the voyage is shorter. We left the Hook at 12 midnight, &amp; arrived at Harwich about 6 a.m. The sea was smooth as a mill–pond. At 7.20 the special train left for the North: we breakfasted comfortably on the train, &amp; travelled pleasantly to York. At Doncaster a gentleman with a lady entered our carriage, &amp; soon introduced himself to me as the Earl of Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3465"></persName>, &amp; one of my neighbours at Durham. At York we changed trains, &amp; so came to Durham: having completed a brief &amp; costly but interesting visit to the Low Countries.</p>
         <p>
On the way we bought a copy of yesterday's issue of the "Times". It contains most part of a column of my <ref xml:id="704">sermon</ref> at the Hague. No other paper appears to have made any report however brief.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[420]</hi></p>
         <p>
We found <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> already arrived: &amp; the next day came <persName xml:id="3266" display="no">Walter Smith</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3076" display="no">his wife</persName> with their daughter <persName xml:id="3077" display="no">Elizabeth</persName>. The latter went away on Friday, the 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> August. The same day <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I with the Inges motored to <placeName xml:id="53">Wynyard</placeName> &amp; there attended <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry's</persName> garden party. The great lady was conspicuously affable.<note xml:id="267" n="1"></note> <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName> arrived here.</p>
         <p>
On Saturday, the <persName xml:id="3018">Dean of Belfast</persName> called here: I showed him over the Cathedral. Also the Rev. <persName xml:id="3019">Walter Tod</persName>, an ex–Fleet chaplain, came to see me: &amp; I invited him to dine. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> arrived, &amp; dined with us.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
