<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[386]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful summer day. I celebrated in the cathedral at 8 a.m. The boys of the school communicated in some numbers, it being the last Sunday in term.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>At Mattins about 50 members of the 'Tutorial Classes' attended service. I preached an old sermon on Jacob's vision, &amp; read the lessons.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I showed my guests the church and library. We all attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards walked round the wood.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[387]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Tuesday, the 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, I distributed Prizes for swimming at the <orgName xml:id="234">Johnston School</orgName> of which I am Chairman.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3226"><hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Eustace Hill</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the medical officer of the County, lunched here, &amp; had some talk with me on the Housing question. He said that here in the City of Durham there was nothing to be done beyond pressing for the closing of the worst houses.</hi></p>
         <p>
On Wednesday, the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, I distributed prizes at <orgName xml:id="234">Durham School</orgName>, &amp; laid the foundation stone of the new house. There was a considerable gathering of old Dunelmians &amp; much enthusiasm. My speech was well received.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName> came here for a short visit. On Thursday &amp; Friday Car&#x00F6;e made a thorough inspection of the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I went to Morpeth on the 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> July, &amp; I distributed prizes at the Edward VIth Grammar School. On Friday afternoon, Olaf &amp; I went with Car&#x00F6;e over the cathedral. On Saturday, Car&#x00F6;e &amp; Olaf went off to Norway. In the afternoon about 80 members of the students' Educational Association went over the cathedral with me, &amp; afterwards came to tea at the Deanery.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="541">Cyril Alington</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="777">his wife</persName> arrived to spend the week&#8211;end</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
