<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[443]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A beautiful day after the rain of yesterday. The valley looked ravishingly beautiful. The little becks &amp; burns were flowing freely &amp; noisily down the hill sides.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3251" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Macdonald</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the parish minister came to lunch. He looks like a farmer, &amp;, indeed, is of farmer stock. His people for generations have been </hi><hi rend="italic underline">crofters</hi><hi rend="italic"> of a substantial kind in the sacred island of Iona. There he was born, and there, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">when a school boy, he met </hi><persName xml:id="1817"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Bishop Lightfoot</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">. He had spread out his books on the turf, &amp; was reading, when he became aware of a stranger's presence. Looking up he saw a heavy stout man with a kindly face, who seemed much interested in him &amp; his books. Taking up one of the latter, which happened to be the Iliad open at the VI</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> book, the stranger asked him if he could read the Greek, &amp;, when he found he could do so, sate with him for an hour reading the Author with him. His pronunciation was unfamiliar, but his comments were illuminating. Afterwards the lad learned with pride that he had been reading Homer with the greatest scholar of the Church of England. I inquired as to the feeling of the people with respect to Church Union. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Macdonald told me that there was but little interest anywhere; &amp; in some places </hi><hi rend="i bold">[444]</hi><hi rend="italic"> strong prejudices against the scheme. He said that one difficult factor was the partisan fervour of the U.F. minister. At the last election, while the ministers of the Established Church almost everywhere stood aside from the political conflict, the U.F. ministers generally presided at the Radical meetings.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch we drove with <persName xml:id="1077">our hostess</persName> to Pitlochry. After dinner I had some talk with <persName xml:id="2780">Pringle Nicol</persName> in the smoking room. He has known many men at Oxford in his time. His <persName xml:id="2783">father</persName>, the Glasgow Professor was a friend &amp; contemporary of <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>. He knew at Oxford the repulsive but now again popular <persName xml:id="2779">Oscar Wilde</persName>, also that poor miserable creature <persName xml:id="2781">Lord Alfred Douglas</persName>, who, he says, has now become a Papist.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In "The new Statesman" &#8211; a Christian Socialist paper of the pseudo&#8211;independent type &#8211; I read an article on 'Larkinism', which represented the Irish demagogue <persName xml:id="2782">Larkin</persName> as a serious, successful, &amp; sincere organizer of Labour, a total abstainer and only censorable for violent speaking! In another article </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I stumbled on a reference to 'Canon Hensley Henson' as desiring to expurgate the Bible for popular use</hi><hi rend="italic underline">!</hi><hi rend="italic"> This, of course, is an allusion, rather belated to be sure, to an old article on <ref xml:id="33">'the Future of the Bible'</ref>, which I wrote for the 'Contemporary' some years ago.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
