<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[303]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
The Special Chapter for settling the question of building a new House for the School lasted barely an hour &amp; a half, and resulted quite satisfactorily. I took the precaution of drafting some resolutions, &amp; taking them across to <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> before breakfast. He undertook to move them as Bursar of the School, &amp; did so very effectively. Our discussion was animated, but not unfriendly; &amp; we finally carried everything unanimously.</p>
         <p>
Then the Forester waited on me to consult about the garden. I ordered some poplars to be planted in the bare space.</p>
         <p>
After lunch the [sic] <persName xml:id="555">Bp. Tucker</persName> &amp; I went to Pittington in order to inspect the Font in the parish church. This Font was formerly in Durham Cathedral, but some seventy years since was presented by vote of the Chapter to this church. It is a 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century work, presumably part of <persName xml:id="2820">Bp. Cosin's</persName> benefaction. I was disappointed, for I had tacitly assumed that it would have been the original Norman Font of the Cathedral, which had gone astray. This later Font probably looks better in Pittington church than in Durham Cathedral. The church is unusually interesting from an architectural point of view. The parson, <persName xml:id="3309">Guest Williams</persName>, is an ex&#8211;Durham schoolmaster.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[304]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Resolutions adopted unanimously by the Chapter:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>That in view of the Inspectors' Report of 1907, and the opinion of the Inspectors expressed to the Chapter at its last meeting, &amp; taking account of the present position &amp; prospects of the School, the building of a third Boarding House is desirable in the interest of the School, &amp; that it be carried through without further delay.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>That the new House be adapted for the accommodation of not less than 35 &amp; not more than 40 boarders.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi rend="italic">That the proposed House be built on the vacant ground bordering the road &amp; adjoining the Second Master's House.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi rend="italic">That the Dean, Treasurer, &amp; Bursar be a Committee to prepare plans &amp; estimates of expenditure, &amp; to report to a special meeting of Chapter on April 26</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> next.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[305]</hi></p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Friday, the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> of March</hi>, we went to Edinburgh, where we parted company for the night, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> going to <persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford Bell</persName>, and I to <persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName>. Mine host had prepared a pleasant little bachelor's dinner party. Old <persName xml:id="581">Donald M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Leod</persName>, <persName xml:id="1140">Paterson</persName>, <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName>, <persName xml:id="2026">Kelman</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1139">Wallace Williamson</persName> were the guests besides myself. The next morning Ella &amp; I together walked about Edinburgh, which looked very beautiful under a bright sun. We lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford Bell; &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">then left for S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Andrew's. Here we were met at the station by <persName xml:id="2491">Principal Stewart</persName>, &amp; driven to S. Mary's College, where we stayed until Monday afternoon</hi>. On Sunday &#8211; a very boisterous cold day &#8211; we saw a good deal of the place. I preached in S. Salvator's Church, which serves as the chapel of the University. The acoustics of the building are execrable, &amp; the ventilation as bad as possible: however I got through my duties without disaster. The afternoon we spent in visiting the ruins of the Cathedral &amp; the Castle, winding up with a visit to <persName xml:id="3312">Professor Herkless</persName>, whose house is said to stand on the scene of Hamilton's execution. In the evening I preached in the parish church – Trinity Church – a very commodious &amp; dignified building, which reflects the greatest credit on the architect. Though almost entirely a new structure, it has retained the aspect &amp; spirit of an old one. It seats no less than 1850 persons on the floor – there are no galleries: &amp; the acoustics are excellent.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[306]</hi></p>
         <p>
I preached from <hi rend="underline">Hebrews xii.2.</hi>: &amp; was listened to with very close attention. The Minister, <persName xml:id="3313">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Playfair</persName>, is a son of Anak, with a voice of thunder. His zeal &amp; energy have enriched the Church of Scotland with the finest parish church (which is not as in Glasgow an adapted cathedral) which I have yet seen. The next morning was bright, &amp; had not the wind been cruelly cutting, we had had an ideal day for seeing S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's. As it was, we gazed &amp; shivered. Among other things, this place is memorable for the three maces, all of the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, which are carried before the Heads of the University. They must be among the finest examples of that sort of work in the country. <persName xml:id="3314"><hi rend="underline">Bishop Kennedy's</hi></persName> tomb in S. Salvator's Church is a complete exposition of the medieval theory of Christianity. Of course it is lamentably destroyed.</p>
         <p>
We left S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's on Monday afternoon, &amp; went to Glasgow, in order to visit Jordanhill, before it passes finally out of the possession of the <persName xml:id="412">Parker&#8211;Smiths</persName><persName xml:id="275"></persName>. On Tuesday morning, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of March, we motored to the new house which the Parker Smiths have leased: &amp; then went off to Newcastle in order to preside at a Livingstone Centenary Meeting, which had been arranged by the <orgName xml:id="179">Congregational Union</orgName>. This was a most enthusiastic meeting: the Wesleyan Church was crowded to the roof. The appointed speakers, <persName xml:id="2687">Harris</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2688">Horton</persName>, acquitted themselves well. I returned to Durham by the 9.52 p.m. express.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
