<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[302]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
After Mattins I called on <persName xml:id="3191" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jepson</persName>, &amp; talked over the situation at the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Hospital</orgName>. He seemed to think that the governors might be glad to get out of the existing dead&#8211;lock, &amp; I forthwith wrote to <persName xml:id="3189">Sir Lindsay Wood</persName>, asking his opinion, &amp; suggesting that he should act with me at the next Governors' meeting on April 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. I marked my letter 'Private &amp; Confidential'.</p>
         <p>
In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="245">Discharge Prisoners' Aid Society</orgName>, and I made a short speech. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The <persName xml:id="3190">Warden</persName> of <orgName xml:id="276">Bede College</orgName> called on me, &amp; urged the necessity of making some change in the situation with respect to his students. They are compelled to attend the morning service in the Cathedral, but the service is such that they can join in nothing. They can hear neither prayers, lessons, nor sermon: &amp; are in revolt!</hi></p>
         <p>
After the special service <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> detained me in order to talk about the proposed new House at the School. He went on to press me to take immediate steps to stop the litigation between the University &amp; some tenants of the Ecclesiastical Commission. But it is hard to see how I can thrust myself into a controversy of which I know nothing.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
