<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[380]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. All my house party came &amp; communicated &#8211; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, <persName xml:id="267">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gore&#8211;Booth</persName>, <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, <persName xml:id="1095">Aubrey</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName>.</p>
         <p>
At Mattins I preached on "Christianity &amp; Patriotism". <persName xml:id="3238"><hi rend="bold underline">The Kabaka of Uganda</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, attired in bright blue garment, sat beside me</hi>. <persName xml:id="555">Bp. Tucker</persName> celebrated the Holy Communion. The party from Uganda communicated.</p>
         <p>
After we entertained at lunch &#8211; Bp. Tucker, <persName xml:id="3239">Archdeacon Walker</persName>, <persName xml:id="3237">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sturrock</persName>, the Kabaka, &amp; 3 chiefs. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[381]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Thursday, the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July 1913, I made a second expedition to inspect the farms.<note xml:id="254" n="1"></note> We visited five tenants, all seemed hard&#8211;working &amp; respectable men. One <persName xml:id="3235" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nightingale</persName> was superior to the rest. He gave us tea. Another, <persName xml:id="3236" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Tidyman</persName>, had views on prophecy &amp; assured me that the return of the Jews to Palestine was near at hand, as a river which he called 'the mystic Euphrates was drying up! I suspect that he is a local preacher. There were Methodist symbols on his walls.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1930">Walter Smith</persName> arrived on a short visit.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Friday, the 18</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> July, 1913, </hi><persName xml:id="2806"><hi rend="italic">Bayley</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> came as he had arranged, &amp; took me, </hi><persName xml:id="1095"><hi rend="italic">Aubrey</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; Walter Smith in tow for </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">an expedition to the Ushaw Moor Colliery</hi><hi rend="italic">. We were received very courteously by the Manager, </hi><persName xml:id="3243" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Peel</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, who shewed us plans of the mine, &amp; explained in advance where we should be taken, &amp; what we should be shown. Then he took us into the office where the miners were receiving their pay. Every man's weekly earnings were set out in an elaborate pay&#8211;sheet, &amp; the requisite amount of money placed on his number which was marked on a square in an immense chess&#8211;board. All this struck me as wonderfully well organized. Then we were handed over to </hi><persName xml:id="3244" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Davies</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="3245" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hutchinson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the mine manager</hi> <hi rend="bold">[381]</hi> <hi rend="italic">and deputy manager. We were shown the ventilating fans on whose action everything turns; then we descended the mine, and, at a depth of about 350 feet, reached the Brockwell seam. Here we saw the stables of the pit ponies, &amp; then carrying safety lamps &amp; stooping to save our heads, proceeded to the face of the coal, &amp; watched a miner at work. I took his pick &amp; with difficulty got out a small piece. As the coal was thrown into the tubs, &amp; these were filled, a 'putter' pushed the tubs as far as a junction where the pit&#8211;pony drew two tubs at once as far as the mechanical haulage (steam) which carried the coal to the shaft. Here it was raised to the surface, weighed, cleansed of stone, &amp; sent off. From the Brockwell seam we descended by an inclined passage about 80 feet to the Victoria seam. Here the channel was very muddy, and low: the last piece of the distance to the face of the coal I was carried on a little trolly. The spectacle of the hewer at work lying on his side quite naked save for short drawers was very amazing. This man (<persName xml:id="3246" display="no">Johnson</persName>) was very cheerful &amp; pleasant: his 'deputy' (<persName xml:id="3247" display="no">Stimson</persName>) who pushed my trolly was also a good fellow. Then we examined the pumping engine which strives to keep down the water which is ever invading the mine, &amp; so we returned to daylight.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[383]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Peel had prepared tea for us in his office, &amp; this we were very willing to accept when we had removed some part of the coal&#8211;dust from hands &amp; face. Then he motored me to the Institute, a comfortably arranged corrugated iron building equipped with billiard tables, a lending library, reading room &amp; newspapers. We returned in the car to Durham, arriving about 5.30 p.m. somewhat fatigued but greatly interested with all that we had seen.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Saturday, July 19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1913, there was a Chapter Meeting, all amicable enough. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then at 3.20 p.m. came the Miners' Service in the Cathedral</hi><hi rend="italic">. There was an immense congregation, &amp; it was very well behaved. I read Job. XXVIII as the special lesson, &amp; preached from the concluding verse &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">But unto man He said: The fear of the Lord, that is Wisdom: and to depart from evil is understanding</hi><hi rend="italic">". I fear that the Sermon was rather long, &amp; perhaps went over their heads. </hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
