<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[373]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
We attended service in the Cathedral at 10.30 a.m. &#8211; Mattins &amp; Choral Communion. The singing of the Choir impressed me as very good, &amp; the music devotional, but the sermon by the Canon in Residence on the character of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter was a poor performance.</p>
         <p>
After lunch we called on the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName>: &amp; had some talk with the great man &amp; <persName xml:id="3173">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>
At tea we had some discussion on the ecclesiastical situation in this city. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. asserts that the Church of England is very weak, being discredited by the bitterness of the rival factions. The present Bishop is described as a thorough&#8211;going partisan. Papistry is said to be strong &amp; advancing. Religion generally but weak, though Churches many.</p>
         <p>
I preached in the evening in the Cathedral to a great congregation. My sermon was 'above the heads' of my hearers: &amp;, though they listened their hardest, they could make nothing of it!! However, <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> pledged me to preach to the Railway Men at their annual service on the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Sunday in October, 1914.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
