<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[310]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, Saturday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended the celebration at 8 a.m. &amp; received the Sacrament. After breakfast I wrote at some length to <persName xml:id="2879" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wright</persName> of London, Ontario, giving him all the information I possess on the episode of my inhibition in 1909. He is equipping himself for conflict on behalf of <persName xml:id="1567">Symonds</persName>. Also I wrote a <ref xml:id="682">letter</ref> to the "Times" on the Divinity Degrees question, which is agitating men's minds. <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName> has a long and excellent <ref xml:id="681" display="no">letter</ref> in today's issue on the same theme.</p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards laboured at arranging my books on their shelves, being assisted in the work by <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName>, who is spending Easter here with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[311]</hi></p>
         <div type="verse"></hi>
         <p><hi rend="bold">'</hi>He is a bungler in the trade, &amp; has been an indocile scholar of his dark master, the father of lies, who cannot make an assertion pass for a fact with an ignorant multitude'.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2152">S. T. Coleridge</persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="verse"></hi>
         <p>Those who commence the examination of a system by identifying it with its abuses or imperfections, degrade their understanding into the pander of their passions, &amp; are sure to prescribe remedies more dangerous than the disease.</p>
         <p>S. T. Coleridge.</p>
         </div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
