<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[457]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Tillypronie.</hi></p>
         <p>
I picked up in mine host's study <persName xml:id="2107">Fisher's</persName> <ref xml:id="721">Biographical Sketch of <persName xml:id="3261">Frederick William Maitland</persName></ref> (Cambridge, 1910). It is very good reading. I was particularly interested in the description of Maitland on p. 178:</p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
'Conscious theory or method of style he neither claimed nor cared to possess; he wrote as the spirit moved him, finding with astonishing ease the vestment most appropriate to his thought, &amp; composing with such fluency that his manuscript went to press almost free of erasures. The literary &amp; artistic conventions of the hour did not appeal to him. He never went to picture galleries: in later life he seldom read poetry, though as a boy he been fond of it: &amp; he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> profess to be unable to distinguish a good sonnet when he saw one. Knowing the thing which he c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> do best, &amp; judging that it was worthy of a life, he stripped himself of all superfluous tastes &amp; inclinations that his whole time &amp; strength might be dedicated to the work. Even music had to give way… He w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> sit in an armchair with a pipe in his mouth &amp; some ponderous folio propped against his knees, steadily reading &amp; smoking far into the night, <hi rend="bold">[458]</hi> thinking closely, taking no note, but apparently retaining everything. For a man who wrote &amp; taught so much his knowledge was amazing both in range &amp; accuracy: but his panoply might have been of gossamer so lightly did he bear it'.</p>
</div>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3259"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="973"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lawley</hi></persName> came to lunch with their <persName xml:id="3263" display="no"><persName xml:id="3264">wives</persName></persName>. We had much converse together. <hi rend="bold underline">Both men are excellent, but quite petrified by the Anglican convention</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3265"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jones</hi></persName>, the Episcopal minister from Aboyne, came to dinner. He is a typical Celt: has done much journalistic work: &amp; reached his present position by way of the Dissenting ministry. <hi rend="italic">He says that he has known </hi><persName xml:id="234"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> well in the past, but is now regarded by him with aversion. The present insistence on Disestablishment is partly explicable as an anti&#8211;Lloyd&#8211;George movement. He expressed a very unfavourable opinion of the Chancellor's personal character, &amp; quoted <persName xml:id="3285">Principal Edwards</persName> of Aberystwith [sic] as his authority. But, when I pressed him on the point, he could give no evidence: &amp; I was perforce driven to conclude that either </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lloyd&#8211;George</hi><hi rend="italic"> is the worst&#8211;libelled politician in the world, or that Welsh public opinion is more complaisant on the subject of personal immorality than one can well believe possible in so religious a democracy.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
