<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[384]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A bright sunny morning with clear blue sky. The Archdeacon suggested that this clearness &#8211; so rare in this place &#8211; is explicable by the fact that the pits were closed yesterday. <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m., &amp; I assisted.</p>
         <p>
I preached at Mattins from Romans XIV. 7. "For none of us liveth to himself; &amp; none dieth to himself". Also I celebrated the Holy Communion.</p>
         <p>
After Evensong we all walked round the wood, &amp; then into the Cathedral.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[385]</hi></p>
         <p>
On Tuesday, <persName xml:id="1541" display="no">Miss Curtis</persName> departed: on Wednesday, <persName xml:id="2056">Miss Graham</persName>. On Thursday, <persName xml:id="3213" display="no">Walter</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3214" display="no">his sister</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1812">Angel Colenso</persName>. <persName xml:id="1696">Olive's</persName> departure leaves a great void: her brightness &amp; good temper make the house cheerful: &amp; her singing is delightful.</p>
         <p>
On Friday, the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, we went to Middlesborough, where I distributed prizes to the boys &amp; girls of the High School. <hi rend="bold underline">We stayed the night with <persName xml:id="3091">Sir Hugh Bell</persName>, at Rownton Grange, Northallerton. He is the owner of Mount Grace Priory, the Carthusian house which I visited many years ago.</hi></p>
         <p>
On Saturday, the 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, we were motored to Stockton whence we proceeded by train to Sunderland. We lunched with <persName xml:id="3206">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Victor Williamson</persName>, &amp; then I addressed a meeting in the Rectory Garden in the interest of the <orgName xml:id="253">Waifs &amp; Strays Society</orgName>. We returned to Durham afterwards, arriving just in time to receive the <persName xml:id="378">Dean of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's</persName> &amp; his daughters, who are breaking their journey to Scotland by a week&#8211;end at Durham.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
