<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[439]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
I am bothered about this 'opening address' to the <orgName xml:id="229">Worker's Educational Association</orgName>, which, if my calendar deceives me not, I am pledged to deliver on the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> October. A few days later I am to speak in Edinburgh on 'The Problem of Leisure'. Perhaps I might fairly make one performance a rehearsal for the other. The Problem is (1) novel, (2) urgent, (3) extremely difficult. On these 3 pretty obvious heads, I may have some observations. Then must come some suggestions for solving the Problem: &amp; here one must needs distinguish between the young and the adult. </p>
         <p>
The former have two distinctive needs which must be satisfied out of working hours &#8211; exercise of muscles, &amp; courting. We may, perhaps, add a third, amusement, for, though recreation in some form is indispensable for every age, in the case of the young it must take a specific form. It must also be remembered that for most young people under 20 years of age, leisure must still serve an educational purpose. Civic &amp; social duties will, of course, fill the leisure of those who are able to recognize &amp; fulfil them: but these will be limited to that section of the artisans which is intelligent, informed, &amp; trusted. Religious interest may come under this head.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[440]</hi></p>
         <p>
We drove out with our hostess after lunch into Aberfeldy, &amp; there had tea with <persName xml:id="3253" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Russell</persName>, whose <persName xml:id="3254" display="no">husband</persName>, a K.C., rents a house from <persName xml:id="3252">Lord Bredalbane</persName>, in which his Lordship was born. The garden is a dream of beauty. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Russell, evidently an enthusiast for flowers &amp; a born gardener, himself plans everything: &amp; the work is done by one gardener &amp; a lad! The blend &amp; blaze of colour was indescribable. One thought with sadness of the near &amp; fatal ravage of the frost.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At tea came the <persName xml:id="3240">Bp. of Edinburgh</persName> who is staying somewhere near, a bland unangled man, welcome at tea&#8211;tables!</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then we drove to Castle Menzies, the stripped and vacant mansion of a notable Highland family now sunk into irrecoverable decline. <persName xml:id="1077">Our hostess</persName>, whose knowledge of the personal histories of Scotland is astonishing, told us the melancholy &amp; rather sordid story, while we admired the magnificent garden, built up against the mountain side, &amp; commanding a noble prospect. The mansion and property are now in the market, &amp; will probably be bought by some new millionaire, who will efface the past by some brazen edifice &amp; new habit of splendour. The only Highlander left here will be the bronze figure who stands beside the Tay at General Wade's Bridge to commemorate the 42</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> ! The views of the mountains in the level evening light were wonderful.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
