<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[366]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended the morning service at St Paul's &amp; received the Communion. There was an immense congregation of which, however, a great part left before the sermon. The preacher was <persName xml:id="2288">Arthur Robinson</persName>, but his voice was too feeble for the place, &amp; his sermon (not an impressive production) was mainly unheard.</p>
         <p>We lunched with <persName xml:id="2244">Sir John Struthers</persName>: &amp; called on <persName xml:id="2768">Lady Charnwood</persName>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="554">Gilbert Simpson</persName> brought his <persName xml:id="2763" display="no">young lady</persName> to tea at the Deanery. She seemed a harmless person.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; I walked together on the Embankment. I attended the evening service in the Cathedral, &amp; heard a violent sermon from <persName xml:id="2954">Hudson Shaw</persName>. He railed at the 'upper classes' in fine demagogic style, &amp; was relished by a very large congregation. It was a very mischievous performance.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[367]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">We left the Deanery on Monday, the 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of June 1913, and returned to Durham</hi>. The week was frittered away in many little futile functions &amp; Committees.</p>
         <p>I gave away prizes &amp; made a speech at the <orgName xml:id="231">Darlington Training College</orgName> &#8211; an unsectarian institution.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I preached in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles' Church to the students, past &amp; present, of <orgName xml:id="230">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hild's Training College</orgName>: &amp; then I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Trustees</orgName>, convened to consider the revision of the constitution which we have decided to attempt. Then we travelled to Hexham, missing by 2 minutes, our train connexion at Newcastle, &amp; arriving late for dinner. <persName xml:id="2767"><hi rend="italic">Old M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sumner</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> of the <orgName xml:id="220">Mothers' Union</orgName> was staying in the House. To listen to her talk is to be baptized with hoary shibboleths! Heaven forgive the involuntary hypocrisy which left the old creature with the notion that she had made a valuable recruit in the Dean of Durham!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
