<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[293]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>An important Chapter at 11 a.m. The <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> moved two resolutions which I had drafted beforehand, &amp; passed to him across the table.</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>That the Dean be requested to Order that on &amp; after Easter Day next the lessons at Mattins &amp; Evensong be read in the Cathedral from the Revised Version.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="italic">That the Treasurer be instructed to confer with the Dean &amp; Sub&#8211;dean as to the copy of the Revised Version to be used at the Lectern in the Cathedral, &amp; to provide the copy that they shall approve.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName> moved a resolution to this effect:&#8211;</p>
         <p>
'That the Dean, Sub&#8211;dean, &amp; Bp Tucker together with the Sub&#8211;Treasurer be a Sub&#8211;Committee to consider the state of S. Cuthbert's Tomb, and the Font of Pittington &amp; make recommendations to the Chapter.’</p>
         <p>
Three of the Examiners of the School &#8211; Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <persName xml:id="3196" display="no">Fletcher</persName>, <persName xml:id="2471">Strachan</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3197">Bridge</persName> &#8211; attended the Chapter, &amp; stated their opinions both as to the present state of the school, and the project of a third House. They were definitely favourable to the latter. <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> the Head master also attended. He is, of course, strongly favourable to the building scheme.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[294]</hi></p>
         <p>
We also appointed a small Committee (Dean, Sub&#8211;dean, &amp; Treasurer) to draw up a statement as to the Services for which a Canon in Residence is responsible, &amp; to make report at the next ordinary Chapter.</p>
         <p>
Everybody was placable &amp; practical: we got through our business in less than 2 hours.</p>
         <p>
I paid away just over &#x00A3;<hi rend="underline">10</hi> in wages &amp;c.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At last we transferred ourselves to the Deanery, where some rooms had been hastily made ready for our occupation. The rest of the house will be in the workmen's hands for some while to come.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
