<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[286]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Bishopthorpe.</hi></p>
         <p>
The Holy Communion is celebrated daily in the Palace Chapel at 8.15 a.m: &amp; Mattins is said at 8. There follows short Household Prayers: &amp; then &#8211; at 9 a.m. breakfast. This is a cheerful &amp; conversational meal. Lang makes <hi rend="italic">a dignified &amp; kindly host. I could not but marvel at the strange fortune which has brought him and me into our present relative situations &#8211; he the <persName xml:id="130">Archbishop of York</persName> &amp; I the Dean of Durham.</hi>         </p>
         <p>
The <persName xml:id="3227">Dean of Carlisle</persName> motored me into York, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">I made my first appearance in Convocation</hi>. It is an odd little foolish assembly, &amp; bored me inexpressibly. The President with the members of the Upper House attended, &amp; opened proceedings with a speech. In this I was mentioned with some flatterous words: &amp; an eulogy was pronounced on that boisterous fanatick, <persName xml:id="3231">Gray of Helmsley</persName>, whose death is just announced. I lunched with the <persName xml:id="3228">Bishop Suffragan of Sheffield</persName>, who is Canon of the Cathedral &amp; now, as Residentiary, occupies the prebendal House. On returning to Bishopthorpe I went for a walk with the <persName xml:id="3177">Lord Mayor of Liverpool</persName> who has just been appointed chancellor of that diocese. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[287]</hi></p>
         <p>
The Lord Mayor is, he told me, 45 years old. He is greatly interested in religion, &amp; himself friendly to 'liberal Anglicanism'. The <persName xml:id="477">Bishop of Liverpool</persName>, of whom he spoke in terms of the highest admiration &amp; regard, is hostile: &amp;, when he listened to <persName xml:id="427">Inge's</persName> sermon, looked the picture of misery. "<hi rend="bold underline">That does for the last fragments of my belief" &#8211; was the observation of some layman to the good prelate</hi>, as he came away from the said discourse, &amp; of course this prompt confirmation of his worst fears deepened the poor man's gloom.</p>
         <p>
At dinner I sate between the Bishops of Ripon (<persName xml:id="2074">Drury</persName>) and Sodor &amp; Man (<persName xml:id="3229">Denton Thompson</persName>). With the first I had an interesting conversation on "Foundations". <hi rend="bold underline">I asked </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">him point&#8211;blank whether he w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> refuse Ordination to a man</hi><hi rend="italic"> holding the views expressed in <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter's</persName> <ref xml:id="715" display="no">Essay</ref>. He said that he c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not bring himself to ordain a man who held that the Body of Jesus "saw corruption" in the grave. We talked at some length, &amp; with much frankness. I promised to send him a copy of <ref xml:id="83">"The Creed in the Pulpit"</ref>, and he to send me his criticisms on it.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
