<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[299]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A tremendous tempest was blowing when the day broke, which moderated somewhat as the morning advanced. When I descended to the study – our sole resting&#8211;place in this palace of confusion – I found to my horror a painter hard at work on the doorway into the library thus making the study also practically uninhabitable! For <hi rend="underline">weeks</hi> past I have been assured that the rooms for our own occupation were ready for our entrance! "<hi rend="underline">Put not your trust in princes, or in any child of man!</hi>"<note xml:id="208" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
After Mattins I joined <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop Nixon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> in making an inspection of the documents &amp; treasury, with the object of having a proper catalogue of our corporate possessions made.</p>
         <p>
Then after Evensong <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I walked for an hour, returning in time to dress for dinner. We dined with <persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName>, who interested me much by his conversation about Uganda. He is a fine artist, &amp; has painted much. His walls are adorned by his sketches, &amp; his hall is full of weapons &amp;c brought from the scene of his missionary labours. He formed a hostile opinion of the notorious <persName xml:id="2666">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Karl Peters</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
