<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[409] </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A brilliant day. We packed after breakfast, and then walked into the city to take a farewell view thereof, and withal to buy a leathern strap whereby to strengthen my much dilapidated 'valise', which burst asunder in the midst with much public ignominy at Antwerp on our arrival. This we succeeded in obtaining for the modest sum of 3 francs. Then we returned to the H&#x00F4;tel, and I paid my bill &#8211; 289 f. 80 c. for 6 days. We got away in a crowded train, &amp; travelled to the Hague via Malines, Antwerp, Dordrecht, &amp; Rotterdam. The Dutch custom&#8211;house was encountered, &amp; passed at Rosendaal: &amp; so <hi rend="bold underline">we reached the Hague</hi>, where was a vast &amp; hustling crowd. <hi rend="italic">We made our way to the Grand Hotel Central, where a room had been secured for us by </hi><persName xml:id="2997"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Ratford</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Embassy Chaplain, whom we found waiting to receive us. After an unsatisfactory tea, we walked in the town renewing our recollections. The town seems to be very full of visitors. We walked round the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Vyver</hi><hi rend="italic">, which looked very charming in the evening light, with its verdant islet &amp; little company of ducks. This hotel is quite near the Binnenhof, and seems to be equipped with all modern requisites. Its only apparent fault is an inordinate multitude of visitors!</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[410]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We dined with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="2998" display="no"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ratford</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> at a restaurant hard by the Hotel. He has been chaplain to the Embassy here for the last 18 years. <persName xml:id="683" display="no">Lake</persName> has acted as his colleague, and in that capacity has aroused the suspicions of the orthodox, who have complained to <persName xml:id="166">the Bp. of London</persName>. But Ratford very properly refused to abandon his colleague, and (in his own belief) was passed over in the appointment to a West London Church in consequence. He says that the Queen is less popular than her husband: that she affects so ardent a patriotism as to refuse to read any but Dutch newspapers: that she has a dislike of the English: that German influence is omnipotent at this court.</hi></p>
         <p>
He says that the "orthodox" combination of Papists and Calvinists has been defeated at the polls: that in a House of 100 representatives, the Socialists now command 18 votes: that they hold the balance between the other parties: &amp; that the Liberals can only carry on the government by arrangement with them. So in Holland also the same situation is developing &#8211; a disintegration of historical parties, and the rise of a new party formed, not on a political, but on an economic basis. The older parties draw together against the common enemy: but their mutual hatreds are so strong, that the unnatural alliance cannot sustain itself, &amp; a process of unprincipled compromises is inaugurated, leading to chaos.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
