<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[257]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Epiphany, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>Along my earthly life, the thought of death</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And judgment was to me most terrible.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I had it aye before me, and I saw</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Judge severe e'en in the Crucifix</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="337">Newman</persName> <ref xml:id="695">'The Dream of Gerontius'</ref></p>
</div>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I walked by way of the Embankment to Christ Church, Newgate Street, in order to make our farewells to <persName xml:id="122">Hine&#8211;Haycock</persName>, erstwhile Precentor of the Abbey, now Rector of that Church. It was his Sunday at the Chapel Royal, so his place was taken by <persName xml:id="803">Dams</persName>. There were about 24 persons in the big church apart from the choir, but the service was simple &amp; reverent. Hine&#8211;Haycock came to us in the church before the service started, &amp; explained the situation. We pledged him to come to lunch. <persName xml:id="2564">Miles Thompson</persName> was in church, &amp; after service walked as far as the Embankment, where we went by tram to Westminster. <persName xml:id="2622">Sir Lionel Spencer</persName> &amp; Hine&#8211;Haycock were at lunch: also <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName>.</p>
         <p>At 4 p.m. a lady, <persName xml:id="2992" display="no">Miss Bacon</persName>, came (by appointment) to consult me about exchanging the Roman Catholic Church for the Church of England. Her main reason appeared to be general disgust of the system as she had seen it in <hi rend="bold">[258]</hi> Ireland. I told her that she ought to be inwardly persuaded of the moral obligations of her action: that mere vague dislike of abuses was insufficient: that she was, as a baptized &amp; confirmed Englishwoman, free to present herself for Holy Communion in the English Churches: &amp; that she could exercise this legal franchise rightly if she had deliberately &amp; intelligently decided that her duty required her to leave the R.C. Church &amp; join the C.O.E. I recommended her to read <persName xml:id="2993">Salmon's</persName> <ref xml:id="694">'Infallibility of the Church'</ref>: &amp; gave her leave to write to me on any specific points which were doubtful to her.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There was a very large congregation in the Abbey Church at 7 p.m. when I <ref xml:id="718">preached</ref> my first sermon as Dean of Durham.</hi> My text consisted of the two passages from the Sermon on the Mount &#8211; S. Matt V. 16 &amp; VI. 1, which seem at first view to contradict one another. I preached for nearly 40 minutes.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="2181">Sir W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Vincent</persName>, Mary &amp; <persName xml:id="1256">Ranee Scott</persName>, <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, <persName xml:id="2994" display="no">Bowden</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; Reggie formed the supper party.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[259]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="379">Lane</persName> died rather suddenly at the Deanery, Rochester, on Thursday the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 1913. He was a very sweet&#8211;natured &amp; loveable man, &amp; has shown much affection for me.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName> sent me a cheque for <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;175</hi>: the sum collected for a personal testimonial from the congregation of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Margaret's. Ella &amp; I purchased a piece of plate competent to carry an inscription for <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;47.10.0</hi>. The balance we reserved for expenditure in other ways. Ella went to visit <persName xml:id="2704">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Perceval</persName> at Daglinsworth on Friday the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> January.</p>
         <p>I had the more melancholy business of visiting the dentist. As usual he left alone the repairs which seemed to me urgent; and pulled about things which were well enough.</p>
         <p>Then I made my preparations, &amp; took my departure to Oxford <hi rend="bold underline">where I stayed with <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName></hi>. Here also I found Mary Scott staying for the weekend &amp; on this occasion, at least, I could find it in my heart to prefer her absence, for I had designed in coming to Oxford, to escape from Westminster. <persName xml:id="649">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dicey</persName> is upstairs with rheumaticks: &amp; <persName xml:id="2991" display="no">Miss Thackeray</persName> is fatter than I can remember on any previous occasion!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
