<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[308] </hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Good Friday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
<div type="verse"></hi>
         <p>
<hi>O man, strange composite of heaven &amp; earth!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Majesty dwarfed to baseness! flagrant flower</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Running to poisonous seed! and seeming worth</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Choking corruption! weakness mastering power!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Who never art so near to crime &amp; shame,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As when thou hast achieved some deed of name.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="337">Newman</persName> <ref xml:id="695">"The Dream of Gerontius"</ref>. </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2267">General Gordon</persName> marked with doubled pencil line the last three lines. Who does not endorse the affirmation which he thus disclosed? The practical paradox – the higher you rise, the nearer you fall – is fulfilled in lesser men than the Hero&#8211;Saint of the Sudan!</p>
         <p>
The Cathedral looked very beautiful in the morning sunlight. There was but a small congregation at Mattins: had the Grammar school boys been absent the nakedness of the land would have been very marked. The service consisted of Mattins, Litany, Ante&#8211;Communion Office, &amp; Sermon – all unaccompanied. According to a custom of some standing the Preacher was the Sacrist. He preached quite pleasantly. After service I wrote at some length to <persName xml:id="1567">Symonds</persName> of Montreal with reference to his difficulty with the <persName xml:id="3193">Bishop</persName> on account of preaching in a Presbyterian Church.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[309]</hi></p>
         <p>
There was a very fairly numerous congregation in the Cathedral at Evensong, more numerous by far than I had ventured to expect, as the University has gone down, the boys don't attend the afternoon service, &amp; the faithful have been mostly going to the "Three Hours" service in one or other of the city churches. I preached an old sermon on S. John xix.12,16 making a study of Pontius Pilate, as he is disclosed in the record of the Passion.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
