<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[338]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
I attended the college chapel, breakfasted pleasantly in the coffee room, &amp; got away by the 10 a.m. to London. Having deposited my bags in the cloak&#8211;room at King's Cross I walked to Westminster, &amp; seeing the door of <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> open, entered the church which had been central to my life for 12 years. <persName xml:id="159">Scholes</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1033">Ramsey</persName> were in the vestry: &amp; <persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName> chanced to come in. They all seemed very content with themselves &amp; their <persName xml:id="2955">new chief</persName>. Then I called on the <persName xml:id="325">Dean</persName>, &amp; had some little talk with him. <persName xml:id="636"><hi rend="underline">Pearce</hi></persName> was not at home, but I fell in with <hi rend="underline">Carnegie</hi> as I was leaving <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; we walked across the Park together. He is evidently putting his back into the work, &amp; likes the prospect of playing a great part at the centre of things. I lunched at the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, where I saw <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="66">Pember</persName>. Also the <persName xml:id="2146">Bp. of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> David's</persName>. I remained in the Club until it was nearing the time for me to go to King's Cross, had tea, &amp; so took myself off. I travelled to Durham by the 5.30 p.m. express, indulging in the senseless extravagance of a first class ticket.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[339]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Installation of the <persName xml:id="3129">D. of N.</persName> as Chancellor.</hi></p>
         <p>
The great function, which had monopolized everybody's thought for so long, passed without incident or accident. The weather was brilliantly fine, but sultry &amp; thunderous. My own enjoyment of the proceedings was marred by a splitting headache. Our guests arrived on Friday &#8211; the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, the <persName xml:id="120">Dean of Christ Church</persName>, <persName xml:id="794">Sir Henry Craik</persName> during the afternoon, &amp; <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> after dinner. We had dinner parties in the large dining room on Friday &amp; Saturday. <hi rend="bold underline">The Chancellor's Installation &amp; the giving of the honorary degrees took place in the Castle Hall. I was well received by the undergraduates, when I came forward for my degree. After this function there followed the Thanksgiving Service in the Cathedral</hi>. Old <persName xml:id="3131"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Philipson</hi></persName> read the lesson: <hi rend="bold underline">I preached</hi>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> gave the Benediction from the Throne. Everything was most impressive. <hi rend="bold underline">Then followed the lunch in Hatfield Hall &#8211; rather tiresome</hi>. After lunch I took the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName>, <persName xml:id="956">Lord Haldane</persName>, Curzon &amp; <persName xml:id="672">Rayleigh</persName>, &amp; shewed them the cathedral. We went through the Library, &amp; so came into the Deanery, where <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> gave them tea, &amp; I shewed them the Kitchen.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On the next day, I preached at Mattins a special sermon addressed to the undergraduates</hi>. They attended in considerable number, &amp; appeared to be impressed. Strong &amp; Craik stayed until Monday, the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> May, &amp; returned to town by the early train. <persName xml:id="2751">Ethel Gore&#8211;Booth</persName> went back to Scotland the same morning.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[340]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">On Thursday, May 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> 1913, Ella &amp; I travelled to Sunderland, where I was pledged to address a public meeting in protest against the Welsh Disestablishment Bill</hi>. The weather was desperate – violent &amp; continuing deluges of rain. In spite of this, however, a considerable company came together in the Victoria Hall. I was the first speaker, <persName xml:id="2610"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Forasgue Bradley</hi></persName> the second. As we had to catch the 9.18 train, I did not hear his speech. Mine was sufficiently dull. For 35 minutes I examined the various arguments by which Welsh Disestablishment is recommended &amp; justified, leading to the conclusion that none of them would hold water.</p>
         <p>
This was the third meeting I addressed since Sunday. On Tuesday, the 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I spoke for the Diocesan Fund in a very sparsely attended meeting presided over by the Bishop. On Wednesday evening Ella &amp; I attended a meeting of the Band of Hope children. <persName xml:id="555">Tucker</persName> presided, &amp; <persName xml:id="3132">his wife</persName> distributed prizes to the children. I made a speech in which I observed that much drunkenness came from indigestion, the result of bad cooking. Therefore I urged the girls to learn cookery. This harmless platitude was reported in the local papers, &amp; even found its way into the august columns of the <ref xml:id="708">"Times"!</ref></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>