<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[341]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A heavy mist lay over the city, shutting out the larger views, &amp; oppressing one's spirit. The cawing of the rooks took a sinister note, &amp; seemed like the ominous croaking of ill night birds: yet the thrushes sang bravely under the mantle of gloom, &amp; the cathedral bells would not be stayed. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were about 115 communicants, for the <orgName xml:id="234">Grammar School Boys</orgName> came. It was a wonderfully uplifting service. We <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to be a united body here, with that Altar to hold us together. <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName>, <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1898">Cruikshank</persName> were there: one hon. Canon, <persName xml:id="2786">Mosse</persName>: two senior canons, <persName xml:id="2800">Cully</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2811">May</persName>: and the <persName xml:id="2692">Headmaster</persName>. Ah, if we 'could live more nearly as we pray', we should be the best Chapter in the world! Mattins was read at 10 a.m. with Athanasian Creed &amp; Litany. I was somewhat disposed to wonder that a comparatively large congregation came together for this service. Then followed the Choral Eucharist. We sang the processional &amp; recessional hymns altogether <hi rend="underline">inside</hi> the Cathedral, instead of <hi rend="underline">partly</hi> in the Cloisters as heretofore. I preached on "the Spirit of Truth". <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> sang the service admirably. There was a considerable number of communicants so that it became necessary to consecrate more wine. Taking all things together the services were very consoling.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[342]</hi></p>
         <p>
Three of the <orgName xml:id="178">King's Scholars</orgName> came to lunch – <persName xml:id="3133" display="no">Cumming</persName>, the Captain of the School, <persName xml:id="3134" display="no">Moses</persName>, and [space left by Henson for third name]. After lunch we went over the House &amp; onto the Roofs.</p>
         <p>
At Evensong the sermon was preached by one of the hon. Canons – <persName xml:id="2786">Mosse</persName> – in aid of the <orgName xml:id="23">S.P.G.</orgName> It was a dreary performance: and my power of attention was rendered less than usual by the heaviness of the atmosphere, a circumstance which was forced on one's notice at intervals by growlings of thunder.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[343]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The Lay Vicars of Durham Cathedral:–</hi> </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2787">John Nutton</persName>. 14 Alexandra Crescent</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2788">John Duncanson</persName>. Wood View, Church Street Head.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2789">William Peacock</persName>. Highcroft, Framwellgate Moor.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2790">F. H. Knight</persName>. 18 May Street.</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2791" display="no">William Brown</persName>. 3 Mountjoy Crescent.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2792">G. C. Cradock</persName>. 21 the Avenue.</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2793">J. S. Lisle</persName>. 2 May Street.</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2794" display="no">Herbert Harden</persName>. 4 Western Hill.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2795">C. A. V. Jones</persName>. Bank View, 31 May Street.</hi>  
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2796">J. C. K. May</persName>. 12 East Atherton Street.</hi>  
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[344]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">On Tuesday, 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> May 1913, we paid our first visit to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>. We were kindly received by the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="2797"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="underline"> Moule</hi></persName><hi rend="underline">, who seem strangely insignificant in the great house. The chapel is very fine: <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName> is everywhere, &amp; next to him <persName xml:id="1817">Lightfoot</persName>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="underline"> M. talks much, &amp; whiningly, of the enormous expenses of the great house, but forgets </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">that</hi><hi rend="underline"> the income also is great, &amp; for the very reason that the house is large</hi>. After dinner I joined the chaplains with <persName xml:id="3135">Lazenby</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3136">Tristram</persName>, who were staying in the Castle, in the smoking room, &amp; talked much on various exasperating topics.</p>
         <p>
The next day, May 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, we returned to Durham. I entertained the Choirmen of the Cathedral at lunch with <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>, the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1243">Janey Fleet</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2669">Jean Bovey</persName> arrived for a short visit. I showed them over the house, library, &amp; Church, &amp; walked them round the Banks. Then we went to dine with <persName xml:id="555">Bishop Tucker</persName>.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>Feb. 20</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Mar. 29</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>April 24</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>May 15</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
