<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[271]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Windsor Castle.</hi></p>
         <p>
My guardian servant called me at 7.30 a.m., &amp; brought me some excellent tea. I had a bath quite comfortably, &amp; managed to find my way to S. George's Chapel, where the Holy Communion was celebrated at 8.30 a.m. I received the Sacrament, marvelling at the strange Providences which have led me to do so here &amp; now.</p>
         <p>
Then I returned to the Castle &amp; had breakfast pleasantly enough with the Household. The intervening hour before service time was spent in giving a final revision to my poor little discourse, &amp; in writing a letter to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. Then I was fetched at 10.45 a.m., &amp; escorted to the Chapel, where I found the <persName xml:id="382">Dean of Windsor</persName>. Here I robed, &amp; (after raising pins from the servants) got my medals on to my scarf. There was a Choir of 6 men &amp; 8 boys from S. George's. <persName xml:id="3344">Sir Walter Parratt</persName> was at the Organ, &amp; the service was excellently rendered. The Dean read &amp; monotoned the service: I read the lessons, &amp; preached. The Chapel is an Octagon, one facet of which provides (in the gallery) the Royal Pew. This was occupied by the <persName xml:id="2727" display="no">King</persName>, the <persName xml:id="2728" display="no">Queen</persName>, <persName xml:id="239">Princess Christian</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3406">Princess Mary</persName>. In the next pew was <persName xml:id="3407">Prince Alexander of Teck</persName> with <persName xml:id="3408">his wife</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3409" display="no">child</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[272]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
The congregation consisted of the Household, &amp; the Servants. Perhaps there may have been about 60 persons present. My sermon occupied about 17 minutes to deliver, &amp; was listened to with the closest attention. There was no coughing. Afterwards I returned to my room, &amp; remained there until lunch&#8211;time. Here I sate beside <persName xml:id="3410">Lady Ampthill</persName>, &amp; had a pleasant enough meal. <persName xml:id="3349">Fortescue</persName>, the Librarian, is a great talker, but he seems also keen &amp; well&#8211;informed. After lunch he took me into the Library, which is a noble Elizabethan gallery full of interesting things. <persName xml:id="3350" display="no">Miss Baring</persName> joined us here, &amp;, when M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fortescue withdrew, she walked me through divers parts of the Palace pointing out the pictures &amp;c. About 3.15 p.m. I went out, picked up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at the Deanery, &amp; walked with her to Eton, where we called on the <persName xml:id="203">Provost</persName>. He reports himself as having been recently prostrated by influenza: &amp; indeed seemed extremely feeble on his legs. We walked back to the Deanery, &amp; had tea. Then we went into S. George's Chapel for Evensong. The singing is marvellously sweet &amp; finished. After Service we called on <persName xml:id="2383">Canon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2726">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dalton</persName>: &amp; then returned to the Deanery, where I chatted with the Dean &amp; the ladies for half an hour; after which I made my way back to my room, and wrote up my journal.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[273]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">At dinner I took in </hi><persName xml:id="3221"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Adeane</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the daughter of </hi><persName xml:id="3220"><hi rend="bold underline">Lord Stamfordham</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">: &amp; was placed next Princess Christian, who herself was next the King</hi>. My poor lady got nothing out of me at all for I was held in conversation by her august rivals without intermission! The conversation took an ever more direct political colour. <hi rend="bold underline">His Majesty expressed himself with astonishing freedom. He had been reading the "Spectator", &amp; was much excited over the article on Home Rule. He is evidently very bitter about the humiliation which the Government inflicted on him by exacting 'pledges': &amp; talks darkly about 'something he has up his sleeve', which, at the eleventh hour, shall prevent the Home Rule Bill from becoming law</hi>.<note xml:id="205" n="1"></note> Princess Christian strongly supported His Majesty's determination, &amp; begged me in a whisper 'to keep him up to it'! When we had gone into the Drawing Room, <hi rend="underline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> had an earnest conversation with me on the same themes. I said that the King must assert himself: that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> never have so good an opportunity: that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> but take the right, which had been wrested from the House of Lords, of appealing to the people: that the nation w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> understand &amp; support him if he took his course strongly &amp; clearly. <hi rend="bold underline">The King, on his return from the Smoking room, came directly to me, &amp; drawing a chair sate down, &amp; bade me be seated. He then renewed the conversation with much earnestness. His Majesty is evidently</hi> <hi rend="bold">[274]</hi> <hi>[symbol] </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">in much confusion &amp; distress of mind</hi><hi rend="italic">. 'I speak to you in confidence', he said, 'but I was basely treated in that matter of guarantees. They knew I was in a difficult position, &amp; forced my hand'. He seemed to feel strongly the unpopularity in Ireland, which his vetoing of Home Rule would bring. 'I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> never be able to visit Ireland', he said. He entered on quite an elaborate exposition of the constitutional position of the monarchy, &amp; certainly his views did not err on the side of exaggeration. He said that <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> seemed to him a weak man: that <persName xml:id="3411">Grey</persName> was well known to him &amp; well liked, but unhappily was a sentimental Radical. It is sufficiently evident that the Ministers have been pressing him sore.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Queen came across the room to me before retiring, &amp; said some pleasant words to me. I begged her, when going to Scotland, to break her journey at Durham, &amp; let me shew her the Cathedral.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Sir Walter Parratt was dining. I had some conversation with him. He says that the choirboys of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic">George's are mostly the sons of gentlemen, that their parents have to contribute no less than &#x00A3;70 for the first year, &amp; not less than &#x00A3;20 for the last. Only 2 candidates applied for the last vacancy. At Durham, where the whole cost of education is provided, we had no less than 60 candidates for admission at the last vacancy.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[275]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
Reflecting on this conversation with the King, I could not but feel distressed: for either His Majesty is wont to pour out himself thus freely to everybody, &amp; then he must be amazingly indiscreet: or he did so to me specially for some unimaginable reason, &amp; then he must be greatly troubled. <hi rend="bold underline">He certainly gave me the impression of a well&#8211;intentioned but weak man, who was conscious of an obligation to take some decisive action, but unable to determine what precise action that should be</hi>. Evidently Princess Christian, a stronger character by far, was in a great concern about him, &amp; very eager to stiffen him to decision. He harps frequently on the theme that he was badly treated by the Ministry, &amp; indeed on that point expresses himself with some vigour. <hi rend="bold underline">He has no 'personal magnetism' as the Americans would say, &amp; gives an impression of feeble perplexity, which must needs alarm a considering patriot. I find it difficult not to think that he is at the mercy of the latest speaker: &amp;, indeed, in a discussion with such men as the present Ministers, he could not but be overborne</hi>. I told him that the suspensive veto which was until the Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Act possessed &amp; exercized by the House of Lords must now be claimed &amp; used by the Crown: that if he used it in the case of the Home Rule Bill, he would be supported by the country: but if not supported, he could give his Assent to the Bill when endorsed by the constituencies without any loss of credit.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[276]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The King said that in his opinion the Sovereign ought always to be a woman, because no one would put such pressure on a woman as had been put on himself</hi>. 'You mean, Sir', I said, 'that chivalry would restrain them'. 'Yes', he said, 'chivalry would make it impossible'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I reminded him of the fate of Louis XVI</hi> who gained a brief popularity by sacrificing the Church &amp; the Nobility, which had stood between him &amp; the mass of the people, &amp; who soon found himself crushed. His Majesty admitted the relevance of the parallel to his own position.</p>
         <p>
The next day, Monday the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Feb., I returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, having picked up Ella on the way. Of tips to the Royal Servants I gave &#x00A3;1. to the kindly youth who looked after me, &amp; 10/&#8211; to the footman who placed my bag in the railway carriage. Also I left 5/&#8211; on the dressing table for the housemaid. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[277]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>Ballade Tragique &#8211; a double Refrain.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>Scene. Windsor Castle. Time. Present.</hi>   </p>
         <p>
<hi>Enter a Lord &amp; Lady in Waiting.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>She.</hi>		  </p>
         <p>
<hi>Slow pass the hours, ah, passing slow!</hi>   </p>
         <p>
<hi>My doom is worse than anything</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>Conceived by Edgar Allan Poe.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Queen is duller than the King.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>He.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lady, your mind is wandering,</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>You babble what you do not mean,</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Remember for your heartening</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>The King is duller than the Queen.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>She.</hi>	 </p>
         <p>
<hi>No! most emphatically No!</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>To one firm rooted fact I cling</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>In my now chronic vertigo</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Queen is duller than the King.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>He.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lady, you lie. Last evening</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>I found him with a Rural Dean</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Talking of district Visiting &#8211;</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>The King is duller than the Queen.</hi>	  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[278]</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>She.</hi>	 </p>
         <p>
<hi>At any rate he doesn't sew,</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>You don't find him embroidering</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yard upon yard of calico.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Queen is duller than the King.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Oh that I might have had my fling</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>With, say, the Empress Josephine.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>He.</hi>		 </p>
         <p>
<hi>Enough of your self&#8211;pitying</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>The King is duller than the Queen.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>She.</hi>		 </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Queen is duller than the King.</hi>  </p>
         <p>
<hi>He.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then death for you can have no sting.</hi>		  </p>
         <p>
<hi>(Stabs her, &amp; takes a phial out of his pocket)</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>Nevertheless, sweet Friend, Strychnine</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>The King is duller than the Queen.</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi>(Drinks &amp; dies in agony)</hi> </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2416">Lady Ilbert</persName> sent me the above lines, of which she did not know the authorship. I heard them attributed to <persName xml:id="1915">Hilaire Belloc</persName>.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[279]</hi></p>
         <p>
My last week was filled with farewell dinners in defiance of Lent. On Monday the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, the <orgName xml:id="66">Brotherhood</orgName> dined with me. There were present <persName xml:id="1052">Shelford</persName>, <persName xml:id="417">Alford</persName>, <persName xml:id="966">Woods</persName>, <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>, <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName>, &amp; myself. On Tuesday the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> we dined with the <persName xml:id="2544">Ballances</persName><persName xml:id="2695"></persName>. <persName xml:id="2696">Sir Thomas Barlow</persName> was there, &amp; <persName xml:id="1185">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Tait</persName>. Mine host privily expressed to me his disgust at the mismanagement of the testimonial. Herein I think he was unfair to the Churchwardens: nor did he realize that what was fitting in such a church as S. Peter's, Vere Street, would not suit the dignity of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. Of course, if more considerable &amp; experienced men (in these matters) than the excellent Churchwardens had had the business in hand, they would undoubtedly have raised three times as much money: but perhaps it has been as well as it is. Anyhow, I devoutly hope that the indignant Ballance will restrain his criticisms: <hi rend="italic">for they must give pain, &amp; can do no possible good. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">For my part I still hold that testimonials are mainly degrading</hi>.<note xml:id="206" n="1"></note> </p>
         <p>
On Ash Wednesday we dined quietly (!) with the <persName xml:id="227">Murrays</persName><persName xml:id="666"></persName>. <persName xml:id="836" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Buff</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> is amazingly attractive</hi>. On Thursday the 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> I dined with <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> in his own house. The party (<persName xml:id="633">Sir Henry Graham</persName>, <persName xml:id="601">Sir Kenneth</persName>, <persName xml:id="132">Liddell</persName>, <persName xml:id="2221" display="no">Jack Scott</persName> &amp; myself) was depressed by memories, and (considering its components) wonderfully dull. On Friday the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> we dined with that dullest of good men, <persName xml:id="2685">Godfrey Benson</persName>, now Lord Charnwood. <persName xml:id="3347" display="no">General Munro</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3348" display="no">his wife</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3345">Ernest Moon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3346">his wife</persName> made up the party.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
