<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[451]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Tillypronie.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Eagles</hi> &#8211; <persName xml:id="1241" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Coltman</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> tells me that eagles are so numerous in the deer forests that the keepers poison them</hi>. A fine stuffed specimen in my dressing room is a case in point: it dropped dead on this estate. These noble birds build in this neighbourhood; the hill was pointed out to me. A local naturalist watches their nests, &amp; photographs them. <hi rend="bold underline">He reports that the eaglets are fed on grouse &amp; lamb</hi>! <hi rend="underline">Capercailzie</hi> are said to be numerous this year, and almost insolently tame.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We had much talk at breakfast about the Churches. Clearly mine host &amp; his wife have no great regard for the Church of Scotland; they &#8211; like so many of the landowning class &#8211; frequent the Episcopalian Chapel. How hard it is for any of us to transcend the limits of temperament, training, &amp; interest! The strength of sectarianism is the acceptance &amp; quasi&#8211;consecration of those limits. Yet more often than not it prides itself on transgressing them!</hi></p>
         <p>
After breakfast mine host and I walked on the moors. We fell in with <persName xml:id="3267" display="no">Denman</persName>, the Police magistrate, on his way to join a shooting party. A good number of grouse &amp; black&#8211;cock shewed themselves, but not capercailzie; but I was shown a deserted capercailzie's nest, in which fragments of egg&#8211;shell yet lingered.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[452] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
About 300 acres planted 60 years ago brought in &#x00A3;1400 for the timber. This represents about &#x00A3;24 per annum, i.e. 13/&#8211; per acre. What would have been &#x3B1; the original cost of planting. B&#x3B7; the rates, taxes &amp;c. &#x3B3; the cost of felling &amp; selling?</p>
         <p>
We motored to <hi rend="underline">Castle Fraser</hi>, and lunched with <persName xml:id="3272" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Crawford</persName>, who is renting it for the summer. <persName xml:id="3279" display="no">Professor Miller</persName> of Edinburgh &amp; <persName xml:id="3280">his wife</persName> were at lunch. We were shown over the house, which is a fine example of an old Scottish baronial mansion. It dates from the end of the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century: the greater part of the fabric belongs to the early decades of the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century: substantial additions were made at the beginning of the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>: The house is set in an ample &amp; well wooded park: &amp; possesses a very fine walled garden. Many portraits adorn the walls: &amp; there is in one of the rooms a curious spying device known as a 'lugg'.</p>
         <p>
After lunch <persName xml:id="3275">Lord Sanderson</persName>, <persName xml:id="3273">Lady Burghclere</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3274">Professor Hume Brown</persName> called. Our expedition was favoured by the best of weather. We returned to Tillypronie about 6 p.m. well&#8211;satisfied with our day's exertion. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Crawford</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> had known </hi><persName xml:id="3276">Dean Lake</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> well when he (Lake) was Fellow of Balliol</hi><hi rend="italic">. He appears then to have had the reputation of a dominating &amp; unconciliatory person. He was wont to relate with complacency how he had been mistaken for a layman, when he went abroad as the only clergyman on an Educational Commission. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Crawford is an intimate </hi><hi rend="bold">[453] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi> <hi rend="italic">friend of <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, whom he has known for a long time. They were contemporaries at Balliol. He said with truth that Dicey is now obsessed by Home Rule; but he did full justice to his remarkable intellectual powers. He pointed out the curious limitations which Dicey laboured under in having no interest in, &amp; no acquaintance with, natural objects. He could not distinguish one bird from another &amp;c.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After dinner we had some conversation about the working of the Church in England, &amp; in Scotland respectively. Mine hostess is evidently disposed to take a severe view of the Kirk in its local representatives. The episcopalian minster at Aboyne &#8211; 11 miles distant &#8211; to whose congregation mine host &amp; his family have attached themselves is obviously a favourite, &amp; of course no praise is too high for him and his ways. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It distresses me to hear the national church spoken about with so little respect, and &#8211; so I must needs think &#8211; with so little justice</hi><hi rend="italic">. Having heard similar complaints, not less vehemently expressed, against the rural clergy in England, I am but little impressed by them. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">All ecclesiastical systems are unsatisfactory, yet none is so fatally bad as to paralyze the Christian ministry: &amp; none is so good as to make the personal quality of the clergy unimportant</hi><hi rend="italic">. Christianity in no respect shows its Divine character more plainly than in the fact that it works its blessed effects in all circumstances &amp; under all conditions.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
