<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[406]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913. Brussels.</hi></p>
         <p>
We occupied the morning with a visit to <hi rend="bold underline">Louvain</hi>, which is easily reached in about 30 minutes. Arriving at 10.40 a.m. we left again at 11.53 a.m: the hour intervening was spent in driving about the city, &amp; visiting the principal objects of interest. The aspect of Louvain is clean &amp; severe as becomes a seat of learning: the atmosphere is heavily charged with the feeling of restraint, &amp; the <hi rend="underline">soutane</hi> is everywhere. There is a very fine <hi rend="underline">Hotel de Ville</hi>, &amp; opposite to it a fine late Gothic Church, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's. The screen with its rood is a splendid example of 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century work. Also there is a noble tabernacle rising to the height of the choir arcades, also of that date. As mass was proceeding, &amp; every corner of the Church disclosed a penitent, we could not make a detailed inspection. Two other churches &#8211; S. James &amp; S. Gertrude &#8211; we visited. The first was being white&#8211;washed with more than a Churchwarden's zeal: it contains a fine Gothic tabernacle, enclosed by a brass grille cast in the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. The last is enriched by magnificent wooden choir stalls, carved in the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, &amp; justly reckoned the finest extant example of Belgian wood carving. We saw the Building occupied by the University. It was originally erected in the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century as a warehouse for the clothmakers' Guild.<hi rend="bold">[407]</hi>'<hi rend="underline">L'Ind&#x00E9;pendance Belge</hi>' contains a 'Lettre du Vatican' written in a very unfriendly spirit. It discusses the revenues of the Papacy, their sources, &amp; their disposition: and dwells on the fact that they are mostly spent on Italians, who yet make hardly any contribution to them. The article ends with some words of the <persName xml:id="3025">abb&#x00E9; Lemire</persName> spoken in Rome twenty years ago: </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
"Les Romains, dit il, sont les chr&#x00E9;tiens de saint Pierre qui s'&#x00E9;tablit sur son si&#x00E8;ge, vivant des aum&#x00F4;nes des fid&#x00E8;les. Nous autres, nous sommes les chr&#x00E9;tiens de saint Paul, qui montrait ses mains calleuses, vivait de son travail et se vantait de n'avoir jamais re&ccedil;u l'aum&#x00F4;ne."<note xml:id="252" n="1"></note> </p>
</div>
         <p>
Both '<hi rend="underline">L'Ind&#x00E9;pendance Belge</hi>' and '<hi rend="underline">l'Etoile Belge'</hi> give much space to the Balkan crisis, &amp; dwell on the atrocities perpetrated by the Bulgarians. Much contempt is expressed for the European concert, &amp; the retention of Adrianople by the Turks is spoken of as probable.</p>
         <p>
The result of the Chesterfield by&#8211;election is published, and gives little encouragement to those optimistic Unionists who are counting on victory at the polls. The Government candidate is returned by an increased majority in spite of 583 votes being thrown away on a Socialist candidate. The Unionist vote is slightly increased, but scarcely more than the Liberal&#8211;Labour vote.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[408]</hi></p>
         <p>
After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off into the city to sate her soul with shopping: &amp; I dawdled in the Hotel. On her return we chartered a cab for two hours, &amp; were driven round the <hi rend="underline">Bois de la Cambre</hi>, a beautiful park. We had tea in La Laiterie Restaurant very comfortably.</p>
         <p>
After dinner I read the 'Times" for today, which had just come in, also the 'Daily Telegraph'. The last paper, in yesterday's issue, had a most terrible account of the Bulgarian atrocities at Adrianople. This was furnished by the correspondent <persName xml:id="3024">Ashmead Bartlett</persName>, who had been allowed to see the report which a Russian Commissioner had sent in to his own government. The effect of this disclosure must be considerable, &amp; very unfavourable to the Bulgarians. It is, perhaps, hard that similar reports on the Greek &amp; Servian atrocities have not been published, for there is but too good reason for thinking that all the Christian belligerents have been guilty of fearful cruelties. The Turk has been made normal.</p>
         <p>
I wrote a long letter to <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>: &amp; gave notice to the porter of our intention to leave tomorrow for the [sic] Hague. Our short stay in Brussels has been favoured with delightful weather. Heavy rains are reported from Scotland, where the prolonged drought had begun to have serious effects. Belgium is still anxious to have more sun. There was much rain earlier in the year.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
