<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[459]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
A most dreary morning, dark &amp; damp with a rising wind. We breakfasted early, and got away by the early train from Aboyne. Our hospitable host added a capercailzie to our luggage. We travelled by the East coast express very comfortably as far as Newcastle, and there caught a train to Durham. <persName xml:id="241">Sir Fred: Bridge</persName> was our <hi rend="underline">compagnon de voyage</hi>. We arrived in the Deanery about 6.15 p.m. As we entered the college we saw the choirboys evidently excited: they soon told us the reason. A fire had broken out in the School house, &amp; had but just been extinguished.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On the journey &#8211; at Aberdeen &#8211; I happened to see "</hi><ref xml:id="679"><hi rend="italic underline">The Picture of Dorian Gray</hi></ref><hi rend="italic">" set out in the list of shilling reprints on the book&#8211;stall. The book has been so continually pressed on one's notice, &amp; recently has been produced on the London stage with so much publicity, that I determined to seize the opportunity of a railway journey in order to read it. I found it extraordinarily brilliant, and horribly fascinating. It is certainly bad in the worst sense, not because its moral is bad &#8211; indeed it points the old &amp; inevitable moral that 'the way of transgressors is hard' &#8211; but because of its concentration on radically corrupt and </hi><hi rend="bold">[460]</hi><hi rend="italic">corrupting thoughts &amp; pictures of life. The atmosphere is that of the rotten coterie in which the infamous author poured out his eccentric &amp; richly dowered spirit. Perhaps one's knowledge of the squalid tragedy &#8211; illuminating as squalid &#8211; in which the star of <persName xml:id="2779">Wilde's</persName> genius finally disappeared, operates disadvantageously on the reader's mind, &amp; creates a disposition to find an autobiography where one ought only to perceive a literary work: but the book throbs with personal feeling, &amp; only a very bad man could have written it. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
