<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<hi rend="bold">[267]</hi> 
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
To S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul Christ is not a person of the past, with whom he can have intercourse only by meditating on his words that have been handed down, not a great 'historic' figure, but a reality &amp; power of the present, an 'energy' whose life&#8211;giving power is daily made perfect in him.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2729"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Deissman</hi></persName> 'S. Paul the Christian' p. 124</p></div>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> accompanied me to <orgName xml:id="215">Gray's Inn</orgName>, where I preached to the Benchers. The little chapel was crowded, many people being unable to obtain admission. My text was “<hi rend="underline">What God hath cleansed make not thou common”</hi>, &amp; my subject 'Teaching by Experience'. After service Ella &amp; I lunched with the Benchers. It was all very pleasant &amp; interesting. Gilbert walked round the Park with me &amp; Logic.</p>
         <p>
I attended service in the Abbey, &amp; heard a strangely vapid &amp; foolish sermon from <persName xml:id="2716">Willink</persName>, now Rector of Birmingham. <persName xml:id="2717" display="no">Miss Faithfull</persName>, <persName xml:id="206">Baddeley</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2710" display="no">his sister</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2056">Elsie</persName>, <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, Gilbert &amp; Reggie made up the supper party.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[268]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>On Monday the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Jan</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi>, Ella had a numerously attended “at home” in order to bid farewell to her friends. Gilbert continued with us until Tuesday afternoon, when he accompanied me to Paddington. I journeyed to Oxford where I was entertained by <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName> in the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Lodgings. I dined in college on Tuesday, Wednesday, &amp; Thursday: &amp; made myself acquainted with some of the junior fellows, <persName xml:id="2719"><hi rend="underline">Williams</hi></persName>, <persName xml:id="2718">Crutwell</persName>.</p>
         <p>
On <hi rend="underline">Friday the 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="underline"> Jan</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> I returned to Westminster travelling pleasantly with the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>. That evening a money&#8211;lender waited on me with a strange story about <persName xml:id="1687" display="no">Albert Stewart</persName>. The young fool had borrowed &#x00A3;10: &amp; in order to provide some sort of a personal security had forged a testimonial from me, &amp; made many false statements. He had since got into prison for travelling on the railway without a ticket. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I dined with the <persName xml:id="543">Murray Smiths</persName><persName xml:id="2563" display="no"></persName>. <persName xml:id="2724">Gibbs</persName>, <persName xml:id="2722">Lord Aldenham's Brother</persName>, was there with his <persName xml:id="2723">wife</persName>: &amp; <persName xml:id="2720">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2721">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Yates Thompson</persName>.</p>
         <p>
On Saturday the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> of Feb., we lunched with <persName xml:id="269" display="no">Miss Stanley</persName>. Her brother, <persName xml:id="2715">Lord Stanley of Alderley</persName>, was there, &amp; <persName xml:id="2416">Lady Ilbert</persName>. Later we proceeded to Windsor, where Ella went to the Deanery: &amp; I to the Castle.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Here, for the first time, I was the guest of <persName xml:id="2727" display="no">His Majesty</persName>.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[269]</hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2725" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Verney</persName>, one of the Castle Officials, shewed me to my room, &amp; there &#8211; since I brought no valet &#8211; handed me over to a tall but not unkindly servant, who dealt with me mercifully. Indeed he made me as comfortable as possible, &amp; displayed an almost natural solicitude over my wanderings in the corridors! The dinner hour was 8.30 p.m. &amp; I spent the interval before dressing in writing letters<hi rend="bold">[</hi>to <persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName>, Gilbert &amp; <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon Watkins</persName><hi rend="bold">]</hi>. About 8.20 p.m. I descended &amp; was guided by divers persons whom I encountered <hi rend="underline">en route</hi> into the Drawing room where we awaited the entrance of their Majesties.</p>
         <p>
There were only two guests beside the household &#8211; <persName xml:id="2383">Dalton</persName> &amp; myself &#8211; &amp; I was placed first in the order. The King &amp; the <persName xml:id="2728" display="no">Queen</persName> walked round the company shaking hands with every one, &amp; then we went into the dining room. I took in <persName xml:id="2726">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dalton</persName>, &amp; sate next the Queen. We had a good deal of conversation, &amp;, on the whole, found no lack of topics. Rather to my surprise she herself raised the subject of the Suffragettes, who are reported to have done some damage to the Regalia cases in the Tower. I told her that I had been staying with Sir W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Anson in Oxford &amp; had heard from him an encouraging account of the Prince of Wales's studies. This evidently pleased her. She was amused by my story of the papooses hung on nails round the walls of the wooden house in which the squaws of the Mohawks performed their dances.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
We walked arm&#8211;in&#8211;arm with our ladies back to the Drawing Room; there the party divided. The King going off with the smokers: the ladies &amp; a few non&#8211;smokers remaining. Here everybody remained standing as long as the Queen stood, &amp; as her Majesty appears to be tireless &amp; to have a partiality for the perpendicular attitude, we stood most of the evening. There was much privy groaning audible among the lords &amp; ladies in waiting! <hi rend="bold underline">After a while the King returned, &amp; made tracks for me. We had a long &amp; vivacious conversation, rather discursive but extraordinarily 'free &amp; easy'. He speaks with much vehemence against Socialism, &amp; evidently regards with particular dislike those who play with Socialism</hi>. He said that Norway was very socialistic; that all titles of nobility had been abolished there: &amp; that a movement for abolishing Orders was now making head. He advised his brother in law, the <persName xml:id="2730">King of Norway</persName>, to make no concessions to this movement, as he (the said King) was indispensable to the country which he alone prevented from being abolished by the Germans. If Norway became republican this fate in His Majesty's opinion w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> immediately befall them. <hi rend="bold underline">The King spoke freely of his Indian visit, &amp; especially on the religious veneration, of which he found himself the object. He found this rather embarrassing at first, but soon grew accustomed to it. We went to bed when H.M. retired, about 11.30 p.m</hi>.</p>
         <p>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
