<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[449]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We left Pitnacree by the 9.50 train from Grandtully, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">travelled to Tillypronie by way of Perth and Aberdeen</hi><hi rend="italic">. We lunched at the latter, &amp; walked in the town for half an hour. At Dinnett [sic] the motor car met us, </hi><hi rend="i bold">and we arrived at the house about 5.30 p.m</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read in the "Glasgow Herald" an account of a meeting at which the lecturer warned his hearers that the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Union of the Scottish Churches might be injurious to the cause of Temperance</hi><hi rend="italic"> (i.e. total abstinence). He gave statistics of the churches which used unfermented wine at Holy Communion, &amp; drew the inference that zeal for temperance advanced </hi><hi rend="italic underline">pari&#8211;passu</hi><hi rend="italic"> with the democratic constitution of the churches. Establishment implied indifference to the urgent evil of drunkenness! I incline to think that the Fanatick pointed to a serious &amp; as yet unperceived rock in the way of re&#8211;union. The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">temperament</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the established churches is radically different from that of the so&#8211;called voluntaryist communions. On this matter of temperance, I think the moderate position of the Established clergy is right, &amp; the vehement intolerance of the Sectaries represents the natural ardour of the ignorant &amp; undisciplined, who form so large a </hi><hi rend="bold">[450]</hi><hi rend="italic"> proportion of their most active members. It is, perhaps, true that the Established Clergy in Scotland do not take as firm a stand as they ought against a vice, which none can deny to be flagrant, frequent, &amp; socially mischievous. I have heard it said that among the country clergy in the remoter districts drunkenness is not infrequent: and certainly there is vastly too lenient a view generally taken of that disgusting vice. The dissenting bodies, by their violent denunciation of drunkenness &amp; their passionate insistence on total abstinence are able to draw to themselves the support of the general conscience. To a much less degree the case in England is similar: but there total abstinence has spread very widely among the established clergy: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">temperance</hi><hi rend="italic"> has almost ceased to retain a place among Christian virtues!</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This house is little altered from the state in which it was some years ago when <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I visited it as the guests of <persName xml:id="1205">Sir John Clark</persName>, who then was the proprietor. The present owners have made a point of minimizing the unavoidable changes. I am interested to learn that <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> is well known in these parts. <persName xml:id="649">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dicey</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> is a connection of our hostess.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">She (M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> D.) unfortunately has been bitten by the Suffrage mania. The Professor is resolutely set on the other side, a circumstance the more creditable to his candour, since he once advocated female "rights</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
