<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[333]</hi> </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi> </p>
         <p>
The Chapter Meeting was fairly harmonious. We got the plans approved after some grumbling from <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="555">Tucker</persName>: &amp; the financial problem was handed over to the Treasurer for solution. A new &amp; grave point was raised respecting the site. Will it be rendered unsafe for building on by the re&#8211;opening of the disused mine beneath it?</p>
         <p>
This matter seemed too important to leave unsettled. We ordered <persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName> to get a report from a mining expert: and I undertook to write to the Charity Commissioners protesting against the re&#8211;opening of the mine.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="3160">Chief Constable</persName> of the County called to see me, with respect to the precautions against Suffragettes which he thinks it prudent to take on May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi>. I undertook &#x3B1; To allow nobody into the Cathedral except by ticket: and &#x3B2; To lock all the College gates. Later in the day <persName xml:id="3159"><hi rend="underline">Moulsdale</hi></persName>, the junior Proctor, called about the same matter.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3161">Dawson Walker</persName> called on me to explain that my not being invited to the opening of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's Hall was not an intentional insult. Indeed, he privately intimated that the reason was an absurd personal squabble between <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> &amp; Watkins!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
