<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[353]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The glorious weather continues. I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> before breakfast. Then we made our dispositions for departure. <persName xml:id="203">Edmund Warre</persName> made his appearance half an hour before we left. We motored to Slough, &amp; proceeded thence to London, arriving in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> about noon. Here we were hospitably received by <persName xml:id="2109" display="no">Miss Pearce</persName>, her <persName xml:id="636">brother</persName> having gone off to the General Assembly. After lunch we went to the Hotel Windsor <hi rend="bold underline">to find <persName xml:id="1095">Gilbert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName></hi>. Then we called on <persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName>, and went on to Lambeth to inquire of the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> health. I was allowed to see him for a few minutes. He is recovering, but evidently is still in no fit state for work. <hi rend="underline">He said that if he had had the opportunity of seeing me before I accepted the Deanery of Durham he might have offered me reasons for not leaving London</hi>. It is plain that he didn't like my having gone there: some plans must have been upset by it.</p>
         <p>We returned to Westminster &amp; had tea. <persName xml:id="793">Lady Craik</persName> came in &amp; joined us. Then I went to the barber &amp; was clipped &amp; shampooed. <hi rend="italic bold underline">After this I called on <persName xml:id="280">Bishop Boyd Carpenter</persName> &amp; had some talk with him. He is much perturbed at the sacerdotalist proclivities of <persName xml:id="2955">my successor</persName>, who is a tower of strength to aspiring minor canons!</hi> <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="542">his wife</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2949" display="no">Mr Taylor</persName> came to dinner.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
