<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[260]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
We breakfasted at 9 a.m: afterwards <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> &amp; I went to the University Church, &amp; listened to a dull sermon from the text: 'Art thou he that cometh, or look we for another?' The preacher was one <persName xml:id="2986">Wood's [Woods]</persName> of S. John's. Of course he was <hi rend="underline">eschatological</hi> meandering through paradoxes to the inevitable Christian&#8211;Socialist peroration! He was, however, brief: &amp; we were on the streets again by 11.15 a.m. The congregation consisted of about 30 dons, &amp;, perhaps, as many undergraduates. There is but one University Sermon now &#8211; the evening sermon to Undergraduates being a private venture.</p>
         <p>
We walked round the Magdalene walk, &amp; then round Christ Church. The low&#8211;lying meadows which these walks contain were all flooded. The placid sheets of water in which the towers, roofs &amp; spires of Oxford were reflected gave a distinctive &amp; melancholy beauty to the scene.</p>
         <p>
Returning home, we lunched: &amp; then for an hour <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName> talked with me mainly on politics: he has just completed another book on the Home Rule Question, &amp; is very full on that subject.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[261]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Incidentally, he told me an observation which <persName xml:id="2983">J. R. Green</persName> made to him concerning <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName>, now Dean of Canterbury. Dicey had remarked that Wace was a remarkably clever person. Yes, replied the philosopher, 'he is clever enough;</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">but he thinks that because he can see the weak points in his adversary’s case, &amp; point them out incisively, he has thereby proved his own case.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I could not but consider this an illuminating judgement on a very able controversialist, who is also an extremely absurd reasoner.</hi></p>
         <p>
The rain, which had been descending with some vehemence having now moderated, I went down to All Souls: and there sate talking with the junior fellows for an hour, when I called at the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Lodge, &amp; had tea with <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName>. Then I walked back to the Orchard, &amp; wrote up my journal before dressing for dinner.</p>
         <p>
We dined in All Souls. There was a very pleasant company, including the Warden, <persName xml:id="2141">Oman</persName>, <persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName>, <persName xml:id="1008">Simon</persName>, <persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName>, &amp; some of the junior fellows. I thought of some old faces which are no more.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
