<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[378]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> and <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> came to see me respecting the laying of the Foundation Stone of the new school house on the 30</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> July</hi>. The former undertook to have the article on the school prepared for the 'Times': I undertook to write to the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName>.</p>
         <p>
In the afternoon, I went with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>, Bayley, and <persName xml:id="2808">Rowlandson</persName> to visit the estates, according to the statutes. We inspected a number of cottages: &amp; had tea with a farmer named Hardy &#8211; a hearty person who gave us an honest welcome.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1696">Olive Smith</persName> came to pay us a visit. She has grown a fine young woman, &amp; carries herself well. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[379]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi></p>
         <p>
I telegraphed to the <persName xml:id="378">Dean of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's</persName> declining attendance at the Deans' meeting on the score of chill &amp; voicelessness. On Wednesday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, I took Olive over the Cathedral, &amp; found her an exceedingly appreciative disciple, very different from the gapping praters, whom one commonly meets in such functions. On Friday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I) <hi rend="bold underline">dined with </hi><persName xml:id="555"><hi rend="bold underline">Bp. Tucker</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, &amp; met the young </hi><persName xml:id="3238"><hi rend="bold underline">Kabaka of Uganda</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; his chiefs, with </hi><persName xml:id="3237"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Sturrock</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the tutor &amp; bear&#8211;leaders</hi>.</p>
         <p>
On Saturday, the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold Knowling</persName> came to spend the week&#8211;end. We had a small dinner party that evening, &amp; here Olive distinguished herself again by singing some Scotch songs after dinner, while Harold played accompaniments. The <persName xml:id="3240">Bishop of Edinboro</persName> was of the party: also <persName xml:id="3241">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3242">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cavendish</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The B. of E. told <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> a story of his being troubled by a ghost or something analogous when he slept in the King's Room. Of course the boy took it very seriously to heart, and went to bed quakingly receptive. He came down the next morning with a fine story of a troubled night. He seems to have spent most of the time in a fearful vigil, waiting for the day! His concern was sufficiently evident to make us think it well to transfer him to my dressing room, where he slept soundly. This seems to be a plain case of suggestion</hi><hi rend="italic">.]</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
