<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[354]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1913.</hi></p>
         <p>
The day was shadowed by the prospect of <hi rend="bold">making a speech at the <orgName xml:id="183">Literary Fund</orgName> Dinner</hi>. I prepared my notes, &amp; then walked round to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> where I found <persName xml:id="645">Sir Courtney Ilbert</persName>. In the afternoon we picked up <persName xml:id="1095">Gilbert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2672">Lois</persName> and attended the Military Tournament. I stayed to the end of the Restoration Pageant, &amp; then came home to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>.<note xml:id="155" n="1"></note> The dinner was held in the large room of the Savoy Hotel, &amp; was a brilliant affair. There were many Socii there &#8211; the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray</persName>, <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName>, <persName xml:id="2709">Robinson</persName>, <persName xml:id="313">Knox</persName>, <persName xml:id="319">Prothero</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> himself. Curzon made a very interesting speech; &amp; then I proposed a Toast of Literature, coupling it with the name of <persName xml:id="341">Lord Morley</persName>, whose speech in response was charming, but I fear to many present quite inaudible.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My speech took about 15 minutes to deliver, &amp; had been very carefully prepared. It was listened to with attention, &amp; well received. Several of my friends assured me that it was a success: &amp; I can but hope that they were not mistaken.</hi></p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
