<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">December 14, 1913.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">KIKUYU</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2174"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Willis</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> had an interview with me in my study with reference to the visit which he is about to make to Farnham.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I warned him that the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName> was an adept in talking men into acquiescence with his own projects: that he was probably designing to patch up the dispute which the <persName xml:id="3469">Bishop of Zanzibar</persName> has so fatuously undertaken: &amp; that he would probably try to get from him something which could be twisted into a retreat. I advised him to make no promises, &amp; give no undertakings: if pressed to do so, to insist on taking counsel from his friends. I pointed out that the local issue was now absorbed in a larger one, &amp; that he had himself become the representative of Evangelicalism within the English Church. Bishop Willis is candid, sensible, and courageous: but he doesn't know much about the situation in England, and he has little acquaintance with the historical questions raised by his own action. I told him that he might write to me when he would, &amp; that I would help him in every way in my power. He said that he proposed to stand mainly on his personal knowledge of the requirements of missionary work, &amp; should avoid controversy as much as possible. This course I approved adding that if he would stand to his guns, he would be supported here. I also urged him to take a firm line with respect to the Bishop of Zanzibar's charge of heresy! It must be withdrawn with as much publicity as has marked its preferment. I gave him copies of my <ref xml:id="376">Lee Lecture</ref>, the <ref xml:id="80">'Road to Unity'</ref>, the little book <ref xml:id="372">'Ecclesiastica'</ref>, and <ref xml:id="27">'Moral Discipline in the Christian Church'</ref>.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
