<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">49</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I finished the Article for the Church Quarterly, &amp; sent the MS. to <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName></hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3497"><hi rend="underline"> Pease</hi></persName><hi> lunched here before attending the Sub–Committee of Organization. I presided over that body, &amp; wasted my afternoon in the process. </hi><persName xml:id="3259"><hi rend="underline">Donaldson</hi></persName><hi>, the Master of Magdalene, called &amp; had tea. He had never seen the Deanery before, &amp; seemed impressed by it. After dinner </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi> came to see me, bringing the dolourous tidings that no less than 3 cruizers have been sunk in the North Sea by German sub–marines. This disaster, following so quickly on </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the boastful taunts of <persName xml:id="2441">Winston Churchill</persName> reported in this morning's papers, is very regrettable</hi><hi>.<note xml:id="220" n="1"></note> Italy &amp; Roumania are waiting on events, &amp; any failure on our part at this juncture might decide their action or inaction against us.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Wednesday, Sept. 23</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi>, we left Durham, and were absent until Tuesday, the 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> of Oct., when I returned, leaving <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to follow later.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">NORWICH</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Wednesday, the 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Sept, I <ref xml:id="868">preached</ref> in Norwich Cathedral on the occasion of the Dedication Festival</hi><hi><ref xml:id="884"></ref>. We stayed at the Deanery with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="208">Beechings</persName><persName xml:id="804"></persName></hi><hi> until Monday, the 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, spending the time pleasantly in motor expeditions to see the churches. On Sunday evening, the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I preached<ref xml:id="868"></ref> to an immense congregation in the nave of the Cathedral. The next day we proceeded to </hi><hi rend="underline">London</hi><hi>, &amp; stayed two nights with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> &amp; his sister in Little Cloisters. On Wednesday, the 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, we went to Birchington to visit <persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, Here we stayed until Saturday,</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">CANTERBURY</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>when we went to Canterbury to visit the <persName xml:id="383">Spooners</persName><persName xml:id="2162"></persName>. I preached on Sunday (October 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) twice in the Cathedral, first to the soldiers in the nave, &amp; next to the evening congregation in the Choir. The spectacle of 2500 young men in khaki was very moving. A curtain had been </hi><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi><hi> suspended in the nave to assist the acoustics, which had been found hopeless without some such arrangement. I was subsequently assured that my sermon was well heard, but there was too much coughing for my liking. After service I stood with the General, &amp; saw the men file past. They looked vigorous &amp; determined. </hi><hi rend="italic">On Monday morning I had </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">a long talk with the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">,</hi><hi rend="italic"> who was staying with the </hi><hi>Spooners together with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="404">Davidson</persName>. He spoke very frankly about the Kikuyu business, &amp; was at some pains to persuade me of the soundness of his cautious position. He said that all the members of the <orgName xml:id="114">Lambeth Conference</orgName> Committee had attended except the <persName xml:id="3283">Abp. of Sydney</persName>: that they sate without consultant divines: that they examined at length all the three bishops immediately concerned: that they all signed the Report which they had presented to the Archbishop. Numerous statements from various parts of the Anglican communion had been sent in: &amp; some, as for instance one from <persName xml:id="931">Bishop Lawrence</persName> of Massachusetts, had been of considerable value. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then <persName xml:id="2161">Ruth Spooner</persName> shewed us over the Cathedral</hi><hi>: we all lunched with the General &amp; Officers at the Old Palace: &amp; I went with the Archdeacon for a walk afterwards. On Tuesday the 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> of Oct. we left Canterbury, &amp; travelled to London. We lunched at S. Paul's Deanery. <persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> came to lunch. <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; I walked in the Temple–Garden until it was time for me to get away to King's Cross to catch the 5.30 p.m. express for Durham. I travelled with no other excitements than those provided by occasional irruptions of the Archdeacon, &amp; an invasion of soldiers. The train reached Durham shortly after 10.30 p.m.; <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> and the car met me at the station.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
