<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[15] </hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">37</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dank mist after yesterday's rain. I went across to <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName>, &amp; arranged for an emergency Chapter tomorrow at 9 p.m. &amp; to shift the date of the next ordinary Chapter from the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> to the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Oct. We lunched with the <persName xml:id="2785">Quirks</persName><persName xml:id="2689"></persName> to meet the <persName xml:id="3831">Bishop of Lichfield</persName>, who is conducting a retreat for the Sisters. He wears his hair long like an artist. At tea&#8211;time D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Franks of Jarrow made his appearance, &amp; stated that he wished to introduce himself as a candidate for the vacant mastership of <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Hospital</orgName>, but added that he was 2 years older than the age stated in the advertisement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> accompanied me to Birtley, where I was pledged to join <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> at a recruit&#8211;raising meeting. There were two [sic] many speakers. I was followed, &amp; the effect of my speech was neutralized, by Sir W. <persName xml:id="990">Runciman</persName>, a boisterous buffoon, who tub&#8211;thumped in mighty style. A Labour member, Tom <persName xml:id="3853">Wing</persName>, spoke effectively. He is a most butcherly&#8211;looking man, &amp; has a vast bellowing voice, but his words were well&#8211;arranged, &amp; to the point. Lord Durham spoiled the effect of his speech by a vain attempt to quote poetry. There were not less than 1500 men in the audience, perhaps as many as 2000. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The news from the front is re&#8211;assuring. The Allies maintain their offensive, &amp; are pushing the Germans back. Guns &amp; prisoners are reported to have been captured by the British. <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> has carried a vote for yet another 500,000 men.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
