<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">40</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious bright morning after the rain. The war news is altogether favourable. A German retreat quickly degenerating into a rout, &amp; leaving many prisoners &amp; guns in the hands of the Allies, on the West is matched by an Austro&#8211;German d&#x00E9;bacle on the East. A son of the Kaiser is reported to have died of wounds in the Hospital at Brussels. The service in the afternoon was attended by the Mayor &amp; Corporation: &amp; also by the members of the <orgName xml:id="286">D.C.E.L.</orgName> which filled the North Transept. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> attended in uniform, &amp; walked by my side in the procession. The congregation filled the Cathedral, but was not overwhelmingly great. I preached from two passages, 2. Maccabees vii. 36 and 2. Corinthians iv. 18. In the course of my sermon I suggested a parallel between Antiochus <persName xml:id="3670">Epiphanes</persName> and the Kaiser, which impressed Lord Durham so much that he forthwith borrowed <persName xml:id="1029">Bevan's</persName> "House of Selencus" in order to learn more about the older tyrant! The <persName xml:id="1237">High Sheriff</persName> &amp; a party came in to tea. The collection amounted to no less than &#x00A3;149 &#8211; a record in Cathedral Offertories!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
