<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">32</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters of condolence to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3988">Shafto</persName>, <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName>, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3438">Rogerson</persName>. Also I replied to a letter from the Bishop of Pretoria (<persName xml:id="1602">Michael Furse</persName>) rather angrily expressed. He challenges my quotation from Canon <persName xml:id="1029">Bevan's</persName> Pan–Anglican Paper: &amp; I incline to explain his action by the theory of a bowdlerised edition of the said Paper. For the paper originally printed by <orgName xml:id="23">S.P.C.K.</orgName> in 1908 does certainly contain the words I quoted. On this view, Canon Bevan must be a very disingenuous, as well as a very bigotted [sic] man.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2720">Yates–Thompson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2721">his wife</persName> came to lunch. He is a pompous &amp; quarrelsome person, but grew more amiable when we shewed him over the house!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The meeting in the Guildhall yesterday must take high place among the historic occasions on which that Hall has echoed oratory. The <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> spoke with extraordinary fire &amp; force: &amp; his words were received with unbounded enthusiasm</hi><hi>.<note xml:id="215" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3814">Benson</persName> &amp; her son left us for Edinburgh</hi><hi>. They are fervently attached to the British side in the War: &amp; will carry back to America some useful antidotes to the fictions which the German Ambassador, <persName xml:id="3835">Count von Bernstorff</persName>, is there circulating. I called on <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> at the school. He told me that he had already obtained about 50 recruits for the Public School &amp; University Corps. Among these is <persName xml:id="3836">Pater</persName>, the usher at the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir School</orgName>. <persName xml:id="3695">Steinthal</persName> desires to enlist, presumably to demonstrate that a German name can coexist with British patriotism! In his case there arises the question of making provision for his wife during his absence. If he were to fall, or be permanently disabled, presumably there is some provision made by the Country, though probably most wretchedly inadequate. In time of war there seems no limit to the soldier's valid claim on the nation, whose shield he is, but in times of peace who is going to endow too comfortably the loafers of the barracks?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
