<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">110</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Chapter Meeting &amp; Audit occupied the whole morning. Thanks to the war, our financial outlook is worse than it has been for many years. The estimate for altering the lighting in the Sanctuary was approved. We agreed to increase the wages of the workmen by two shillings per week. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> went with me to the rooms of the <orgName xml:id="239">Y.M.C.A.</orgName>, which, though poky &amp; small, are more convenient than I supposed. <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> went to Newcastle, &amp; fetched back the car, to which, however, nothing had been done. The War provides an excuse for everything! I wrote to the youth Reich, who prayed for my assistance in order that he might start residence at Keble, that on a review of my circumstances I could not add to my financial responsibilities. It really distressed me to do this, but the prospect of the doubled income tax paralyzes charity itself! </hi><hi rend="italic">I had a long letter from </hi><persName xml:id="403"><hi rend="italic underline">Dicey</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, commenting on my Article '</hi><ref xml:id="868"><hi rend="italic underline">Christianity &amp; War'</hi></ref><hi rend="italic">, which I had sent him. He is now about 80 years old, and his mental vivacity seems to show no sign of failure, while he retains all his interests. Also, he uses a type&#8211;writer with his own hand.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
