<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">111</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> appeared at the starting&#8211;hour with the dismaying tidings that he could nowise induce the car to make a start! He rushed off to <persName xml:id="3514">Laidler</persName> &amp; borrowed such car as he could provide, but this he reported to be useless! <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> came to the rescue, &amp; lent us his new 'Ford', which served our turn. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Gateshead, where I preached twice, first, to soldiers in S. Chad's, next, in the Parish Church in aid of Belgian refugees. The soldiers had been up &amp; on duty since 6 a.m., and were tired, listless, and immensely clamourous with coughing! The congregation at the Parish Church was very small. So the expedition which began in disorder, ended in failure!! The Offertory just exceeded &#x00A3;7: and the church&#8211;wardens evidently thought the amount creditable! It is sufficiently evident that Gateshead is a poor parish: &amp; its church a feeble force. Something, perhaps, must be set down to the nervous excitement prevailing in the district. The inhabitants have been warned that they may have to evacuate their houses at a moment's notice! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Yet nobody seems really to believe in the probability of a German invasion</hi><hi>. I baptized my chauffeur's son &#8211; Herbert S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> George Cummings &#8211; in the Cathedral under Bishop <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin's</persName> noble font&#8211;cover, but alas! not in Bp. Cosin's font, which still remains at Pittington.<note xml:id="221" n="1"></note> Then I attended Evensong, &amp; heard a delightful anthem of Mendellsohn [sic], excellently well sung.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At tea there came <persName xml:id="3830">Major</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3829">Lowe</persName>, &amp; the young American artists who have been staying with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3696">Steinthal</persName>. After tea I wrote a series of letters. Later I had some conversation with Lillingston, who has accumulated some pastoral experiences which might, perhaps, be worth adding to one's own stock.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
