<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">125</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went for a short walk before attending chapel. The streets are full of strolling soldiers, and a great red&#8211;cross flag hangs outside the New Schools. Johnson looks very grey &amp; broken. He read the Prayer for the Church Militant as part of Mattins, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">introduced into it the name of young <persName xml:id="3646">Anderson</persName>, whose death at the front is greatly lamented in the college</hi><hi>. There was a large congregation of dons, and a considerable sprinkling of undergraduates, though as term ended yesterday, many had gone down: &amp; the university is reduced by the war to slender proportions. I preached on "The Supremacy of the Individual Conscience"<ref xml:id="889"></ref>, and took occasion to criticize with some sharpness the attempt to represent the Prussian Doctrine of the State as the proper effect of Protestantism. My audience were very still &amp; attentive. <persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName>, <persName xml:id="1008">Simon</persName>, <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Davidson expressed themselves afterwards very approvingly, but of course they are likely to be biased in my favour. After the sermon I went to Raleigh's rooms, &amp; then went to lunch with Sir W</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2540">Osler</persName>. He had drawn together some guests, among them D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3647">Fremantle</persName>, a son of the <persName xml:id="214">Dean of Ripon</persName>. We talked with much energy until 3 p.m. when I went off to the station. </hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I was interested to hear Sir W. Osler declare his unbelief of the German atrocities. He said that his experiences in the military hospital had led him to this conclusion</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi> My journey from Oxford to Durham was cold, wearisome, &amp; unrefreshed. Nothing could be obtained on the train or off it. Every station was crowded with men in khaki returning after leave to their stations, &amp; all escorted by troops of girls. They behave well enough, but the ubiquity of the civil petticoat is disconcerting. I arrived at the Deanery about midnight.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
