<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday, 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> after Trinity, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">83</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. The congregation mostly consisted of boys &amp; students. The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> preached on the War at Mattins. </hi><hi rend="italic">It was a fine sermon, finely phrased &amp; well delivered, tailing off into fanaticism at the end, when he spoke of Temperance. To speak of 'the criminal folly &amp; sin of treating' seems to me excessive. How otherwise is the Artisan to show hospitality or express kindly feeling?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> preached at Evensong in the interest of Temperance, taking his text from the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> chapter of Daniel. Of course the inevitable Bernhardi came in for his meed [sic] of denunciation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I grow weary of these pulpit&#8211;references to the War.</hi> <hi>It started to rain during service. We motored to Sunderland through heavy rain. There I preached in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Columba's. The congregation was much reduced by the weather, &amp; did not fill much more than half of the church. After service we had supper in the clergy&#8211;house. <persName xml:id="3832">Jupp</persName> is brother in Law of <persName xml:id="3831">Bishop Kempthorne</persName>, &amp; evidently a very pronounced sacerdotalist. His curates are even more so. I was rather amused to hear him complaining with some bitterness that men like </hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="3690">Mackay</persName> of All Saints, Margaret Street, were not promoted to the Bench. As well make Generals of your deserters! </hi><hi>It was stated that artillery had been brought from Newcastle to Sunderland, &amp; many troops. Also that <persName xml:id="3556">K. of K.</persName> had personally visited the district. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There is clearly an expectation that an invasion will be attempted.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
