<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">103</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright frosty morning. The reporter from the Newcastle paper came to beg the loan of my M.S.: which I granted exhorting him to return it today. I asked him why he had not enlisted, &amp; he pleaded a wife &amp; child, &amp; also unsympathetic employers. It is a difficult situation. This afternoon I have to go to Thornley to attend the opening of some <orgName xml:id="235">'Aged Miners' Homes</orgName>, and of course to make a speech. It is a relief to speak on another theme than the War. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me, and we carried out our progamme. The weather was bitterly cold, but, in spite of it, a fair number of the people came together, &amp; for more than an hour listened to speeches in the open air. Old <persName xml:id="3137">John Wilson</persName> spoke after his fashion: &amp; then I spoke. After the function we went in to tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Curry, the manager's wife. We motored back to Durham in time for me to go into the Cathedral, &amp; see the Mayor, &amp; Major <persName xml:id="3894">Tristram</persName>, who were arranging with the <persName xml:id="2953">Sacrist</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName> for the seating of tomorrow's congregation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
