<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">144</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A hard frost. I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. The Choral Eucharist was attended by 290 soldiers, that is, the first part of the service, for they sang "God save the King", and left after the sermon. I preached from the words "The foolishness of God is wiser than men: the weakness of God is stronger than men"<ref xml:id="890"></ref>. They coughed so furiously that I omitted great part of my discourse! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I lunched at the Castle with Colonel <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName>, and about 400 of his men. After the meal they all marched past the regimental colours in the Chapter House. I caused the two candles on the Altar to be lighted at Evensong. The Choir sang very well. After service Colonel G. brought his wife to tea, &amp; I shewed her the house, for which she expressed a copious admiration. <persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName> came to dine &#8211; a cheerful &amp; intelligent person who, as I learned with interest, is grand&#8211;daughter of old <persName xml:id="3680">Canon Christopher</persName>, so well&#8211;known in Oxford by his ear&#8211;trumpet &amp; missionary breakfasts. After dinner I followed a long&#8211;established custom of my household, by reading aloud Milton's "Ode on the Nativity".</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
