<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">80</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3860">Alan Davis</persName> came to fetch his book of autographs. What could I write but Nelson's traditional message, "England expects every man to do his duty."? I finished the sermon for Sunderland, &amp; then tried to put together some ideas for the meeting at Middlesbrough tonight. I wrote a long letter to <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> justifying my contention (which she jibbed against) that war is unfavourable to religion. Then I went into the cathedral in order to visit the workmen engaged in the repair. I found M</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3526" display="no">Gaymer</persName> in the triforium, and examined the roof &amp; buttresses under his enthusiastic guidance. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; then made tracks for the station, only, however, to find that my train had already started. This was wholly the fault of the Middlesbrough Sectary, who, having bidden me catch a train at 5.5 p.m., had clearly been deluded by an old time&#8211;table! A later train brought me to the meeting about 20 minutes after the proceedings had begun. These took place in a large Congregational Chapel, which was fairly filled in spite of the rain. I spoke for about 45 minutes on "Christianity &amp; the War". The minister, <persName xml:id="3692">Gibson</persName>, appeared to be an intelligent man. He told me that the people of Middlesbrough were mainly Methodist, so far as they were non&#8211;conformists: that Congregationalism here shaded off into Presbyterianism which grew ever stronger as the Scottish border was approached. </hi><hi rend="italic">He was rather perturbed by my saying that war had an unfavourable effect on Religion. He had in fact been engaged upon a sermon designed to set forward the precisely opposed view. There is an element of truth in his contention, &amp; perhaps it is the more obvious opinion. But I think mine is truer to the facts of history.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
