<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">146</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Rather warmer: deluges of rain. I went to the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillington</persName> was the celebrant. After the service in the Chapter House I said that I had noticed some uncertainty in our coming &amp; going: &amp; that I wished the college order to be followed; the <persName xml:id="590">Sub&#8211;dean</persName> always coming next to the Dean. There was but a scanty gathering of soldiers at 10 a.m. I preached briefly on 1. John II. 17, "The world passeth away &amp; the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever". They listened fairly well. At Mattins we had rather a flamboyant sermon from Lillingston on the inevitable subject of the War. </hi><hi rend="underline">Lieut: <persName xml:id="3818">Lyon</persName></hi><hi> arrived from Gateshead to spend the day: I took him for a walk through the wood, in spite of the mud, for the rain had ceased, the wind had fallen, &amp; the day had become bright and serene. But these pleasant conditions were of brief duration: &amp; by the time of Evensong rain was again falling heavily. We all went to the Cathedral for Evensong. Lyon returned to Gateshead after dinner. I read Macaulay's Essay on "Frederick the Great" aloud to my family. The parallel with William II is arresting and sinister.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
