<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">131</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Furious gale with floods of rain driving before it; the wind fell as the day advanced, but the rain settled into a steady downfall, which lasted all day. I began the day by writing to the <persName xml:id="215">P.M.</persName>, as I had promised <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> to do. <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> approved the letter, which, even if it be without effect, can hardly do much harm. Then I spent the rest of the morning in shewing the Cathedral to my guests. In the afternoon I attended both the organ recital, &amp; Evensong. The new arrangement of electric light in the sanctuary was very effective. I took Beeching to dine in Hall at the castle, thus for the first time using my privilege. There was a pleasant company. Gee, <persName xml:id="3825">Ritson</persName>, <persName xml:id="3830">Lowe</persName>, <persName xml:id="3828">Stocks</persName>, <persName xml:id="3459">Ellershaw</persName>, and some others whose names have escaped me. Some curiosity was manifested as to the course I should take in the matter of Dean <persName xml:id="3665">Whittingham</persName>, whose reputation has been so grievously assailed by <persName xml:id="3666">old Canon Fowler</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We returned to the Deanery about 9.45 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
