<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">150</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I struggled all the morning with the attempt to write a sermon on prayer, as a fitting prelude to the Intercession service. But I had no success. The subject is beyond me. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I lunched with the <persName xml:id="3822">Ritsons</persName><persName xml:id="3823"></persName>. Their <persName xml:id="3824">son</persName>, an officer in the Inniskillens now on the staff of General French, was home for short leave. I had some interesting conversation with him. He says that the German soldiers behave well enough, &amp; get not rarely into kindly relations with our men. Thus he knew of a football match being arranged in one place between the hostile troops! But the officers were an unpleasing set. He said that the Indians had been cut about a good deal, that they were perforce recognizing the superiority of the white soldiers, that they could not stand the trenches. He thought the war would be over by June.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then we called to inquire for <persName xml:id="3137">John Wilson</persName>. I went to his bed&#8211;room, and found the old man very weak &amp; broken. Then I looked in at the Town&#8211;hall, &amp; said grace at the tea which some good ladies had arranged for the children of soldiers. Before &amp; after midnight the bells of the cathedral rang out merrily to mark the passing of one tragical year, &amp; the beginning of another. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> insisted on my reading (!) a dolourous poem of Leonardi addressed to the moon, &amp; conceived in the mood of suicidal melancholia!! Truly the happenings of this year might excuse the suicide, &amp; compel the melancholia. During the last 12 months I have preached in the following Cathedrals:&#8211; 1. Durham. 2. Oxford. 3. Belfast. 4. Winchester. 5. Norwich. 6. Canterbury. 7. Manchester. 8. Carlisle. 9. S. Paul's. 10. Glasgow. 11. Edinburgh. Also I preached in Westminster Abbey, Stratford on Avon, &amp; Aston. On only two Sundays in the year have I not officiated, &amp; of the remaining fifty there are scarcely any on which I have not preached once or twice. I have preached in sixteen parish churches within the diocese.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
