<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
     </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">132</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Heavy rain still continues. Colonel <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName> sent a message to say that in consequence of the rain he should bring no troops to the Cathedral. The military service was cancelled accordingly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. The screen looked very splendid, as the church was in darkness save for its illumination.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="2141">Oman's</persName> young friend, 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="3818">Lieut. Lyon</persName>, arrived shortly before church&#8211;time, and spent the day here. I found him an ingenuous &amp; well&#8211;mannered lad, evidently interested in the things of interest which this place contains</hi><hi>. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston's</persName> sermon at Mattins was a curious example of the homiletic embarrassment, which the progress of Biblical Criticism is bringing upon Evangelical preachers, who are young enough to be affected by the changed atmosphere of the religious world. He preached about the Second Advent, but dwelt mainly on the complete break&#8211;down of the ancient theories. Without having assimilated the modern views, he was so far acquainted with them as to perceive that they cannot be swept aside, &amp; yet that they make havock of the Apocalyptic rhetoric, which has been the back&#8211;bone of Evangelistic oratory for generations.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="208">Beeching's</persName> sermon at Evensong was mainly a criticism of Marcus Aurelius. He made too much of the blessed Blandina. The Suffragettes have knocked the bottom out of all arguments from martyrdoms!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Sunderland in order to fulfil my promise to preach in S. Thomas's Church. Scarcely had we mounted the hill, &amp; were free of Durham, before we were held up by the bursting of a tyre. However we managed to arrive in time for service. In spite of the rain there was a considerable congregation. I returned to the Deanery immediately after service, arriving about 9 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
