<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">97</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The party at <placeName xml:id="53">Wynyard</placeName> consisted of </hi><hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="2278">Bonar Law</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; <persName xml:id="3867">his daughter</persName>: <persName xml:id="3864">Becket</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3865">his daughter</persName>: the <persName xml:id="3681">Editor</persName> of the "Morning Post", and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Wynne [Gwynne]</hi><hi rend="italic">: and a relative of the host, </hi><hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="4051">Vane Tempest</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, a feeble&#8211;looking Papist, besides ourselves.</hi><hi> Politicks &amp; personalia formed the staple of conversation, in which our noble hostess played the principal part. Nothing could exceed the bitterness with which the present ministry is regarded in this circle. The Irish situation partly accounts for this, since the Ulster folk look upon themselves as the victims of the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister's</persName> guile. I indicated as politely as possible my dissent from the violent opinions expressed, insisting on the paramount duty of keeping an united front to the enemy. Bonar Law professed agreement with this view, but he speaks very bitterly of Asquith's bad faith.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Sunday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, I kept my Birthday in these unwonted surroundings</hi><hi>. We attended a shortened form of Mattins in the private chapel. I was agreeably impressed by the heartiness of the service, &amp; especially by the zeal with which Lord L. took part in it. He read the Lesson, &amp; with evident interest. He expressed to me the ardour of his admiration for the Bible, of which he said that he knew great part by heart. On Sunday afternoon I motored into Stockton, &amp; lectured on "Christianity &amp; War" to a large body of men: and I preached at Evensong in S. James's Church; there was a large &amp; attentive congregation. </hi><hi rend="italic">We got back to Wynyard in time to raise the number at dinner to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">thirteen</hi><hi rend="italic">! </hi><hi>After dinner we embarked again on a political discussion, which was sustained with much vigour until after midnight. Then we went to bed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
