<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[37]					</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">October 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914. Carlisle.</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi> 
       </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Saturday, Oct. 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, we travelled to Carlisle, &amp; stayed with the <persName xml:id="243">Rawnsleys</persName><persName xml:id="3990"></persName> till Monday, the 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, when we returned to Durham. At dinner on Saturday we met Miss Creighton, a sister of the late <persName xml:id="118">Bishop of London</persName>, and a Presbyterian minister named <persName xml:id="3838">Falconer</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic">He impressed me very favourably, contrasting tragically with the Dean (<persName xml:id="3227">Barker</persName>) whose conversational extravagances exceeded the bounds of decency. It seemed strangely whimsical that he should be the Dean, &amp; the other a Dissenting minister! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Sunday, the 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I preached twice in the Cathedral, first, at Mattins for the <orgName xml:id="23">S.P.G.</orgName>: and then, in the afternoon, at a special service for doctors &amp; nurses<ref xml:id="886"></ref>. The festival of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke was held to be a suitable occasion for a medical function. There were not many doctors, but a large company of nurses in uniform. After service D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Murray, an old Dunelmian came to tea, &amp; had some conversation with me. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He had been physician to <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName>, and knew the whole sad history of his marriage, concerning which he told me privately some remarkable circumstances</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi><note xml:id="259" n="1"></note> We lunched with the <persName xml:id="3227">Dean</persName>, and were shown the Deanery, which includes one feature of considerable interest &#8211; an old peel tower, which provides the morning room below, the drawing room (with fine painted 15</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century beams) above that, and at the top another room, used as a study. <persName xml:id="506">Tait</persName>, when Dean, built the present dining room, as well as erected the window in the north transept of the Cathedral to the memory of his children. Before leaving Carlisle I went into the Cathedral, &amp; looked at <persName xml:id="3691">Paley's</persName> monument. The great east window makes a grand show in the light of a sunny morning.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
