<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1914.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">91</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A comfortless wet day, good for the cisterns but bad for the temper! The <persName xml:id="1132">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3165">Straton</persName> lunched here &#8211; both deaf &amp; doddering! I motored to South Shields by way of Sunderland, and there read a paper to about 24 clergy in S. Hilda's Vicarage. The subject was the inevitable one &#8211; "Christianity &amp; War". Such discussion as followed flickered speedily out, &amp; never rose above detached reminiscences of newspaper&#8211;articles! Then I went on to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> James's Church where about a dozen men, including the two churchwardens, had assembled. I made sundry inquiries as to the parish, &amp; promised to do what could be done to send them a good parson. <persName xml:id="3869">McCullagh</persName>, the out&#8211;going parson, now Vicar of Christ Church, Sunderland, accompanied me, but I shut him into the church during my interview with the parishioners! He returned with me as far as Sunderland, &amp; told me something about the diocese. He says that the falling in the quality of Ordination candidates is lamentable.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
