<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[353]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">386</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It being S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Bartholomew's Day, I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3857">Gregory</persName>, one of the lay&#8211;vicars, came to ask permission to go to Walsall, and do munition work for the Government. He says that he is a worker in leather by trade, &amp; that Walsall is the main centre of that industry. The coming&#8211;in of motors has dispersed the workers in leather, &amp; now (when an urgent &amp; very large demand for their labour has arisen) it is difficult to find men. I told him that we would keep his place open for him. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards took Logic for a walk. </hi><persName xml:id="2341"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dugald Malcolm</hi></persName><hi> [Dougal Malcolm] &amp; his wife arrived about 6 p.m., motoring from Leeds. He doesn't give a very hopeful account of affairs: but, perhaps, something must be discounted on the score of his extreme eagerness for conscription, &amp; his strong dislike of the <persName xml:id="215">P.M.</persName> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2464">Malcolm</persName>, having seen both the Niagara Falls and the Victoria Falls on the Zambesi, is enthusiastically an advocate for the superiority of the latter. But she admits that the volume of water is greater in the former, &amp; more constant.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
