<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">153</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A clam dark morning, not notably cold. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 3 canons &amp; 3 minor canons present, &amp; but a scanty company besides. There was a good muster of troops at 10 a.m. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> preached in the approved 'mission' style amid a tempest of coughs. The congregation at Mattins was but modest in point of numbers. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I preached for 35 minutes from the words of the Lord's Prayer: "Thy Kingdom come, Thy Will be done, as in heaven, so on earth</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="882"></ref>. The attention was good throughout. After Evensong, instead of the sermon, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">we had the service of intercession issued by the two <persName xml:id="128">Archbishops</persName><persName xml:id="130"></persName>, &amp; composed (if the general belief be well grounded) by Armitage <persName xml:id="44">Robinson</persName></hi><hi>.<note xml:id="225" n="1"></note> I read the address from the pulpit, &amp;, remaining there, called the general subjects of the intercession. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> intoned the suffrages.<note xml:id="226" n="2"></note> There was a considerable congregation, which considering the presence of the Mayor &amp; Corporation, would have been small, only the very wet weather made all church&#8211;going difficult. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3553">Mead&#8211;Falconer</persName></hi><hi> came in to tea, &amp; took away my portions of Hartlepool shells in order to examine them. He says that there are as many as 140,000 men in and about Newcastle. After dinner I read the first book of 'Paradise Lost' to the family circle: and this, while it raised the admiration of <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, also moved her national pride, &amp; she must needs demonstrate that Italy could equal England in drawing the portrait of a colossal rebel. Accordingly we ended the day with my toiling along with a wholly unintelligible Dante before me, and listening to her expositions. Thus ends the first Sunday in the New Year. I wrote no letters, though a whole pile wait to be answered, &amp; there are a crowd of friends who have a real claim to remembrance at this time. But a paralysis is upon my mind, &amp; upon my fingers, &amp; I can bring myself to write nothing to anybody.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
