<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[267]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">342</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">'Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee'</hi><hi>. That is the Alpha and Omega of legitimate Christian prayer for personal boons. And in public affairs it is just "</hi><hi rend="underline">Fiat voluntas Tua</hi><hi>" and no more. To live in the spirit of these prayers, with one's thoughts ever running to them, &amp; one's will uttering itself silently in them, is to obey S. Paul's precept, &amp; to 'pray without ceasing'. Against such prayers there is 'no law' either of charity, or of reverence, or of reason. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But by the episcopal 'prayer&#8211;wheels' one's soul is troubled &amp; challenged at every 'turn'</hi><hi>! Their Lordships appear to have but a single notion of their duty. If only the faithful could be persuaded to 'batter the gates of heaven with storms of prayer', then the old miracle&#8211;working powers of Faith might be released, &amp; the Germans smitten wondrously! It is all very naïve, very foolish! So low is the level of intelligence in the religious public, however, that it wakes no audible protest anywhere. Meanwhile in that larger public which is not technically religious, because it holds loosely by the churches, there is much trouble of mind over this 'prayer&#8211;wheel' business.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached to the soldiers at 10 o'clock. There was but a small number present, for the Artillerymen have been inoculated, &amp; sent to say that they couldn't come! However those who did come were very attentive.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName> preached at Mattins. I celebrated afterwards. I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards went to Penshaw &amp; preached in a squalidly plain church to a congregation largely composed of children. The occasion being the "Sunday School Festival" may account for this. The parson &#8211; <persName xml:id="3884">Holme</persName> &#8211; struck me as a woebegone, rather namby&#8211;pamby creature, but he has some vigourous [sic] sons, one of whom accompanied me to the station. He has joined the Army, but intends to take Holy Orders. I got back to the Deanery shortly after 9 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
