<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[321]</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">371</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Let us know</hi>
         </p>
<hi>Our indiscretion sometime serves us well</hi>
         <p>
<hi>When our deep plots do pall: &amp; that should learn us</hi>
         </p>
<hi>There's a divinity that shapes our ends,</hi>
         <p>
<hi>Rough&#8211;hew them how we will.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Hamlet's words disclose a faith in Providence which is at once instinctive and reasoned. Expressed Christianly it becomes St. Paul's brave declaration. "</hi><hi rend="underline">We know that all things work together for good to them that love God".</hi><hi> This calm assurance was the strength of Calvinism as a practical creed, but it was based on an impossible Theology. Cut this away, and connect it with a belief in the universal &amp; equal concern of God for all His children and it becomes indistinguishable from a feeble kind of optimistic fatalism, quite satisfying to the mind, and quite uninspiring to the will. Yet it </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi><hi> instinctive always in the case of religious men, &amp; they will always cast about for some sufficient theological reasons.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather continues to be extremely warm, damp, &amp; enervating. It suggests Sierra Leone rather than the North of England. The continuous rain, moreover, threatens a harvest which, if it could be gathered, would be bountiful. I attended Evensong, &amp; then went to tea with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> in order to see <persName xml:id="3799">Patterson</persName> of Trinity who is staying with him for the night. </hi><hi rend="italic">He tells me that <persName xml:id="1171">Raper</persName> dined in college before his death, which came upon him in his sleep quite peacefully. He was a man of not very prepossessing appearance, who made devoted friends, &amp; wielded a widely extended influence. I met him frequently in the company of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>, who was his intimate friend, a fact which is itself a sufficient certificate of character.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
