<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[351]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">385</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Glasgow at 8.40 a.m., and arrived at the Deanery about 1.45 p.m: beguiling the road by a disreputable novel, <ref xml:id="785">"Ann Veronica"</ref> by <persName xml:id="2734">Wells</persName>! I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards had tea in the garden with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. The brilliant weather made all things glorious. After dinner I wrote to <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName>, <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName>, and <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The newspapers report a telegram sent by the German Catholic Bishops to the Kaiser. It runs thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Bishops who are assembled at Fulda during this terrible war feel that they must respectfully thank your Majesty for the powerful protection wherewith the Supreme War Lord &amp; his glorious Army have guarded the homes &amp; altars of our Fatherland against a host of enemies. </hi><hi rend="underline">We pray God that He will bless &amp; protect His Prince &amp; people</hi><hi>, &amp; speedily grant an honourable peace."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The Kaiser's reply is eminently characteristic:&#8211;</hi>
        </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'God has so far graciously heard our prayers for the victory of our arms. He will, I confidently hope, after the struggle &amp; victory cause an honourable &amp; beneficent peace to arise from this bloody seed so fruitful in sacrifices. To Him be the honour.'</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>'</hi><hi rend="underline">His Prince &amp; people</hi><hi>' &#8211; the phrase carries the same suggestion of fanatical nationalism as </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Milton's</hi><hi> famous passage in the 'Areopagitica':&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Now once again …… God is decreeing to begin some new &amp; great period in his church, even to the reforming of reformation itself: what does He then but reveal Himself to His servants, </hi><hi rend="underline">&amp; as His manner is, first to His Englishmen</hi><hi>.'</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Perhaps the Germans really are at the point of morals where the XVII</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century stood.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
