<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[277]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">347</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> writing letters, and revising the sermon which I mean to preach in the Abbey on the 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> July. On my way I sent a telegram of condolence to the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Lord <persName xml:id="601">Muir Mackenzie</persName> lunched with the <persName xml:id="636">Pearces</persName> to meet me. He told me this story. Lord <persName xml:id="292">Rosebery</persName> being asked whether he proposed himself to follow the King's Example, &amp; become a total abstainer, replied that he was a sound constitutionalist, &amp; preferred to follow the example of the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName></hi><hi>! I attended Evensong in the Abbey. I looked in at the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; found <persName xml:id="389">Lord Bryce</persName>, with whom I had some conversation. He said that the <ref xml:id="780">Commissioners</ref> had found some evidence that the Germans in destroying children had the notion of destroying potential conscripts! It is a horrible extension of the militarist system. I also had some brief conversation with Lord S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="193">Aldwyn</persName>. He said that the terms of the War Loan were unnecessarily favourable, &amp; might bear hardly on the tax&#8211;payers of the future. <persName xml:id="290">Charlie Parker</persName> entertained <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; me to dinner at the Carlton Restaurant, &amp; afterwards at an amusing play. It is only at very long intervals that I visit the theatre, &amp; then (though I am vastly amused at the time) I never escape a sense of extreme incongruity. Assuredly tonight was no exception. Indeed, the presence of khaki&#8211;clad officers in the stalls intensified my normal disquietude, for it forced on my thoughts the immense tragedy, which is being played on the stage of the world. But life has become a continuing paradox.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
