<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">165</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3828">Stocks</persName> came to lunch in order to talk over the Report on the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir School</orgName>. He said that <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> professed himself a 'higher critic', &amp; explained thus his indifference to the precise knowledge of Scriptural narratives, which Stocks had found to be so absent from the minds of the choristers! This is an odd development of the critical idea! Then I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Trustees</orgName>; where we elected D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Meachem to be the new doctor. He is a strange being to look at, with good recommendations, &amp; a candid almost cataractic manner. Then we elected a pensioner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The morning post brought me from the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> <persName xml:id="302">sisters</persName>, as a memento of the dear &amp; ever memorable friend, a little volume of his verse, written for the behoof of the Trinity College law students. The little volume is the more welcome because it is adorned with a very excellent photograph of <persName xml:id="228">Sir W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Anson</persName>. I wrote to <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName>, thanking her for this most acceptable gift.
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
