<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[347]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">382</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An outward&#8211;bound "White Star" liner, 'Arabic', is reported to have been sunk by the German submarines: and a long list of British vessels. There is much violent fighting everywhere, but with no perceptible result save more waste of life. Our long succession of ill fortune shews no sign of ending yet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Everybody went for a motor&#8211;drive (Sedgefield, Norton) leaving me alone. But I did no work, being more than ever restless at the ill news of the morning. I changed a cheque in preparation for our journeys next week. Later, I took the <persName xml:id="383">Spooners</persName><persName xml:id="2162"></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2803">Walter</persName> to Finchale, &amp; showed them the ruins of the <placeName xml:id="64">Priory</placeName>. The day was now overcast &amp; threatening rain, but even so the place had an alluringly peaceful aspect. A number of boy's scouts, encamped in an adjacent meadow, was the only suggestion of War, and [in] their case youth excused &amp; half&#8211;concealed the outrage. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I were stricken with a sudden reluctance to leave Durham while the Zeppelins are so active, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">so we wrote to the <persName xml:id="3797">Dunbar Bullers</persName> cancelling our visit</hi><hi>. I received an affectionate letter from Mary <persName xml:id="1204">Radford</persName>, saying </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that she hoped to claim my promise to be god&#8211;father to her <persName xml:id="3886">child</persName></hi><hi>. So marches the great Paradox of the World. Life springing from fields of Death. After dinner, I made Olive sing all her songs. What a difference it makes to have the sweetness &amp; charm of her singing! I hate this modern craze of contemning accomplishments in women. Their true metier is to please, console, and soften the bruized &amp; perverse minds of men: &amp; they cannot do this without their weapons i.e. </hi><hi rend="underline">inter alia</hi><hi> accomplishments.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
