<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[335]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">376</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to ask whether it would be wrong for her to communicate both in the episcopal, and in the presbyterian church, now that she is living in Scotland with her parents. The practice is certainly common, and as certainly is very odious in the eyes of our 'Catholicks'. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="508">Arthur Balfour</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> told me that he communicated in both churches, having been confirmed at Eton. It raises the question whether the confirmation may not impose a shackle on liberty which, apart from it, would not exist. For Confirmation may be regarded as a specifically Anglican rite, &amp; therefore implying submission to Anglican rules. If it be a rule of the English Church that none of its members may communicate in a non&#8211;episcopal church &#8211; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">and the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> <ref xml:id="849">'Kikuyu' statement</ref> would seem to assert this &#8211; then such communion in both Churches as Kathleen desiderates would seem to be disallowed</hi><hi rend="italic">. But is the Archbishop's view of the Anglican position as true as it is obviously important? </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I think not, &amp;, therefore, I shall advise Kathleen to follow the right instinct of her heart, &amp; by no means to refuse to communicate with her Presbyterian neighbours</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The atmosphere was again sultry &amp; thunderous. I wrote a short preface to the volume of sermons, &amp; sent it to Macmillan. At Evensong I was almost overcome by slumber. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Morgan</hi><hi> called, &amp; had some conversation with me about his son <persName xml:id="1916">Arthur</persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The upshot was that practically I made myself responsible for most of the expenses of his schooling</hi><hi>! After tea, I walked for an hour with <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>, &amp; had much pleasant conversation with her. Two more of <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> relations arrived for the week&#8211;end &#8211; Miss <persName xml:id="1806" display="no">Lily Dennistoun</persName> and Miss Devlin. With the assistance of Olive's singing, I sustained the evening!! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The War news is on the whole re&#8211;assuring. The Germans are being held at Kovno: &amp; everywhere else the Allies are marking time, that is, making ready for the long postponed offensive in the West.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
