<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[305]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">355</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Somebody writes from Scotland to ask me to write something about Reunion by way of preparing 'for the return&#8211;thanksgiving services, when our poor men return, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">who have been so united in their prayers &amp; religious services "on the field"</hi><hi rend="italic">.' No doubt they have: but not those of them who here at home obstruct every approach to fellowship. These make a great figure in the ecclesiastical world which looks to the <orgName xml:id="114">Lambeth Conferences</orgName>, &amp; reads the Church Times: but their following among the sections of the people, which provide the rank &amp; file of the British Armies, is not considerable. When the war is over they will return to their position of hypocritical supremacy: &amp; we shall find that, so far as they are concerned, nothing has changed. And, indeed, why should it be otherwise? </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The War has disturbed men's imagination by its unprecedented scale &amp; horror, but it has disclosed no new factor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast we walked into the City, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="18">Gerald Marshall</persName>, &amp; on <persName xml:id="122">Hine&#8211;Haycock</persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The former was full of the new ardour for 'prayer&#8211;wheels':</hi><hi> the latter was cumbered with the parcels &amp; cares which befall a man on the near approach of matrimony. He is to be married in a few days. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He expresses a proper disgust of the episcopal 'prayer&#8211;wheels'</hi><hi>. Then I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athanaeum</orgName>, and read the papers. After lunch <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; I walked along the Embankment to the Club, where I remained for about 2 hours: &amp; then walked back to St. Paul's. Just outside the Cathedral I fell in with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, and walked up the Embankment with her. Thus I traversed that noisy route no less than 3 times, which perhaps may amount to as much as 8 or 9 miles.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
