<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">237</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>More snow fell last night. The bright morning sun shines on a wintry landscape. I notice that for the fourth time an attempt to build a ninth nest in the main tree is being made. Will the stern old birds pull it down as they pulled down its three predecessors? What intolerant bigots they are! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. At 10 a.m. I addressed the troops. There were more than usual, &amp; the coughing was tremendous. At 11 a.m. I attended Mattins, &amp; read the Passion Lesson. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillington</persName> concluded his sermons on the Atonement, with a marvellously crude &amp; confused harangue. <persName xml:id="4039">Lady Tullibardine</persName> brought a party to lunch, &amp; be shown the Cathedral: but I had to hurry off to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Giles's there to take part in the funeral of old Hopper, who had been in the Chapter's employment for 70 years. The <persName xml:id="590">Sub&#8211;dean</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> also attended, &amp; the Choir sang two hymns. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; heard an unusually good sermon from </hi><persName xml:id="3566"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Foakes&#8211;Jackson</hi></persName><hi>. Then I hastily had tea, &amp; consigning Lady Tullibardine to the care of <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName>, I motored (in Lillington's car) to South Shields, where I preached in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Hilda's to a considerable congregation. The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> accompanied me, &amp; sang the service. We got back to the Deanery about 9.15 p.m. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName></hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Foakes&#8211;Jackson</hi><hi> talked for an hour &amp; so very interestingly. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
