<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[385]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">406</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Hugh Rees sends me '</hi><hi rend="underline">A Miscellany containing Richard of Bury's Philobiblion &amp; other pieces</hi><hi>' edited by Henry Morley, &amp; published in 1888. This translation is stated to be that published in 1832 by Thomas Rodd the bookseller. It was made by J. B. Inglis from the first printed edition of 1473. I took out of the Chapter Library the volume of the <orgName xml:id="244">Surtees Society's</orgName> Publications CXIX, which contains some 'Fragments of Richard de Bury's Register &amp; other documents' edited by Dean Kitchin, &amp; published in 1910. In the Preface, the Editor discusses the authorship of the Philobiblion, &amp; decides on internal evidence that it belongs to the Bishop. He quotes 'the greatest modern authority on the subject M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Thomas' to the same effect: "I have no hesitation in saying that, so far as the evidence of style goes, there appears little reason to assign the Philobiblion to <persName xml:id="4062">Holcot</persName>". Yet the documentary evidence seems really to be decisive for Holecot.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[387]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName> left after lunch. She goes on to Cloam to stay with the <persName xml:id="956">Haldanes</persName><persName xml:id="1386"></persName>. She tells me that Haldane feels his ejection from office very keenly, &amp; that his <persName xml:id="3887">aged mother</persName>, whose ambition for her son has always fastened on the Woolsack as the crown of his career, will feel it also. The envenomed comments of the party press added bitterness to an experience in itself necessarily bitter. <persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName> arrived after Evensong, &amp; I walked with him for two hours. <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2895">his daughter</persName> came to dine, and also <persName xml:id="3816">Bilson</persName> the architect who is visiting old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He said that Durham Cathedral was the one English Cathedral which had European significance architecturally.</hi><hi> He is co&#8211;operating with <persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robertson</persName> in the production of a history of the very fine cathedral at Wells.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
