<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[275]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">346</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[small drawing of a hillock with a French flag on top in margin]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended the Holy Communion in S. Anselm's Chapel. <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> celebrated, taking the 'North end', and reading both the prayers after the Administration. When so rigid a legalist breaks the rubric, who can deny that 'the game of law &amp; order is up'? Instead of going to Mattins in the Cathedral, <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> and I walked and talked in the Archdeacon's garden. Then we attended the Conference of Deans in the Cathedral Library. For two hours we discussed some rather petty matters, and then were photographed in the Deanery garden. The functions were ended by a luncheon in the Deanery. Ralph, <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> and I travelled to London together. I went to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> to be there until Saturday. At the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> I found a bundle of letters, &amp; with them a telegram from <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> announcing that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="276">Moule</persName>, the <persName xml:id="2797">Bishop's</persName> wife, had died suddenly, &amp; that the funeral would take place on Saturday in Durham Cathedral. As the trains would not permit me to attend that function, &amp; fulfil my promise to preach to the troops at Saffron Walden on Sunday, I decided that my duty lay with the last, rather than with the first, &amp; wrote to Watkins accordingly. The death of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Moule may precipitate further changes. I doubt whether so uxorious a man as the Bishop will care to hold on, when his wife is no longer at hand to order him &amp; the diocese! Lang will have an opportunity of securing such appointments as may revolutionize the churchmanship of the Northern Provinces! How quickly these things come about! </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
