<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[393]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">409</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName> went off to Scotland after breakfast. I laboured at a sermon for the Gateshead Freemasons. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I walked in the country after Evensong. Old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> was sitting out on the College lawn when we started. He is 96 years old, &amp; fully alive to everything that happens. When we reached the Deanery we found luggage in the hall. It was speedily followed by the owners, <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>, who had arrived by an earlier train than they had intended &amp; announced. Christian <persName xml:id="1951">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> also arrived before she was expected, &amp; had to make her way from the station without guidance. Ralph says that <persName xml:id="956">Haldane</persName>, with whom he has been staying, shewed him the memorandum which he presented to the Cabinet on returning from his famous visit to Berlin.<note xml:id="290" n="1"></note> There can be no doubt of Haldane's good faith, but clearly he was fooled. His <persName xml:id="3887">aged mother</persName>, a fine old Scotchwoman of the Covenanting type, who at the age of 90 still rules the house, takes his political fall most philosophically, &amp; professes a robust confidence in the issue of the War, which is in itself stimulating.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
