<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[409]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">419</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Gateshead &amp; Stanhope &#8211; a centre of the squalidest industrialisation &amp; the placid scene of a calm philosophy, a demonstration of Freemasons &amp; a Harvest Thanksgiving &#8211; that is my paradoxical destination for this Sunday, while over, through and in everything is the War. I fill most of my Gateshead sermon with a review of the history of Freemasonry, which I 'vamped up' out of a book which the 'Encyclopaedia Britannica' refers to as the main authority, &amp; which I borrowed from the 'London Library', &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">History of Freemasonry, from its rise down to the present day by J. G. Findel, translated from the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="underline"> German edition. London. Asher &amp; Co. 1866.</hi><hi>" To the people of Stanhope I discourse on their quondam Rector, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Joseph <persName xml:id="1856">Butler</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; of the famous "</hi><ref xml:id="788"><hi rend="underline">Analogy</hi></ref><hi>" which he wrote in their midst, &amp; of which the argument does not accord badly with Harvest Thanksgiving. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4065">Youd</persName></hi><hi> arrived in good time, and (with the exception of a puncture at the entering of Chester le Street, which compelled us to drive on the Stepney&#8211;wheel as far as Gateshead,) the motor in his hands behaved beautifully throughout the day. The Freemasons came to church in considerable numbers, &amp; listened to my sermon with close attention. I surrendered the MS to their Reporter afterwards. One of the Freemasons was taken suddenly ill, &amp; no cab being obtainable to carry him home, appeal was made to me for my car, which of course was willingly lent. I lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3883">Stephenson</persName></hi><hi>, the Rector, a man who seems strangely inadequate to his position, but of course one can never safely judge from cursory impressions. From Gateshead I motored over the moors to Stanhope which I reached in about 1½ hours. The hill by which one descends into Stanhope is very dangerous, &amp; has been the scene of many motor tragedies, including that which cost the Mayoress of Gateshead her life a few months ago.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[411]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="2438">Bishop of Richmond</persName> shewed me the flower&#8211;garden which he has substituted for a cabbage patch. It is a notable improvement. I never see the scene of the writing of Butler's 'Analogy', &amp; pace the very walk, sun&#8211;bathed &amp; sheltered, where its immortal author is said to have composed it, without emotion. I preached in the Parish Church to a congregation which was much smaller than I expected, &amp; mainly composed of youngish women. It was explained to me that the Dissenters were also observing their Harvest Festival, but even so I could not think it other than strange that a parish containing over 2000 inhabitants could not produce more than 40 or 50 elderly men &#8211; there were no young man in church &#8211; on an occasion which generally draws even non&#8211;church&#8211;goers into the Churches. Moreover I noticed a considerable number of young men loafing in the little market&#8211;square as we passed to Church. I am informed that very few recruits have come from Stanhope: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the men &#8211; quarrymen &amp; agricultural labourers &#8211; openly saying that for their part, William II would serve as well as George V!</hi><hi> There has been sowing of political tares in the district, &amp; the harvest is apparent. After service I was shown Butler's signature in the parish&#8211;register. The drive back to Durham was uneventful. I arrived in the Deanery at 9.30 p.m. To preach on the same Sunday at Gateshead and Stanhope, &amp; not to sleep away from Durham would be an achievement quite beyond the bounds of possibility before the advent of the motor. It is a question, not wholly without interest &amp; importance, whether this new mobility of the clergy is, or is not, favourable to religion. That it is unfavourable to the pastoral character there can, I think, be little doubt in any informed &amp; considering mind.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
