<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[265]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">341</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> lunched with us. He told me that the Evangelicals of Newcastle had already been holding a meeting in order to discuss candidates for the vacant bishoprick: that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">they had had the impudence to discuss my name at length: and, apparently, to set it aside in favour of a sounder Protestant!!! </hi><hi rend="italic">This illustrates once more the vice of these religious parties. Probably the other side are setting out to pull all the strings they can in order to reverse poor old <persName xml:id="1132">Straton's</persName> policy. And both, when they have succeeded in their machinations, will cant sublimely about the Divine response to their prayers, &amp; point to the choice of Bishop as quite manifestly a Divine Nomination!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 2 p.m. the Council of the Durham Colleges met at the Castle, &amp; interviewed the four selected ladies, who were candidates for the headship of the <orgName xml:id="281">Women's Hostel</orgName>. The choice fell on Miss Donaldson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Partly owing to the heavy thunderous weather, and partly to the chronic disturbance of my mind, I have wasted this whole week, with difficulty answering the inevitable letters, and preparing two poor discourses for tomorrow!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
