<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[419]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">423</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The morning paper announces the appointment of Archdeacon <persName xml:id="1980">Wild</persName> of Nottingham to be Bishop of Newcastle</hi><hi>. He is said to be 50 years old, and a moderate man. But I notice that he owes his present position to the Bishop of Southwell &#8211; a very narrow High Churchman. On the other hand, he contributed to <ref xml:id="790">'Contentio Veritatis'</ref>, which would suggest that he has sympathies with the 'liberal' clergy. We must 'wait and see' how he will turn out. I wrote to welcome him to the North. I attended Mattins in the Cathedral: and afterwards went over the building with <persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="937">his wife</persName>. We made a little motor expedition during the afternoon, visiting Brancepeth, Sherburn, and Pittington, and winding up at Finchale <placeName xml:id="64">Priory</placeName>, where we had tea at the farmhouse. On returning to the Deanery, I wrote letters. <persName xml:id="4065">Youd</persName> tells me that his name is not uncommon in Cheshire, and that his family was of Huguenot extraction. Probably its original spelling was Eudes. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName> together with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3263">Lillingston</persName> made up our dinner&#8211;party.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
