<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[363]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">392</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Religion itself is apt to come to terms with the temper of the day. Immorality is thrust into the background. Christian civilization takes the place of the Kingdom of God; &amp; morality, that of eternal life. The Churches chatter progress, &amp; the secular &amp; clerical arm are linked together in the interests of sanctified worldliness."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>(Father <persName xml:id="1084">Tyrrell</persName> 'X</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ity</hi><hi> at the Crossroads' p. 156)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read through this book. It is very brilliant, &amp; almost painfully interesting, but it does not satisfy me. A vein of almost insolent paradox runs through it. After all, the Roman Church today has a far </hi><hi rend="italic underline">closer</hi><hi rend="italic"> likeness to that proud hierarchical system which Jesus defied, &amp; which destroyed Him, than to Jesus Himself. Liberal Protestantism is pretty wide of the truth in its interpretation of the Lord, but it is much nearer than Roman Modernism. I attended Evensong; took Logic for a walk through Houghall wood; &amp; wrote letters to my <persName xml:id="3128">brother</persName> in India, and also to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, now settled in his new house in Oxford. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
