<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">299</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A wet day, &amp; very cold. Hindered by head&#8211;ache I spent the morning on the sermon very fruitlessly. After lunch I stood about in a deluge of rain watching a practice of the fire&#8211;men. They could throw the water on to the great rose&#8211;window in the 'Nine Altars'. I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards ascended the Tower with the Choir in order to sing the customary anthems. <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> also came. The rain fell all the time. After tea we motored to Hexham. The rain had ceased, &amp; the country looked beautiful in the evening lights. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">In Lanchester, on the bridge we ran over a dog, &amp; killed it instantly</hi><hi>. The creature caused its own death by a suicidal invasion of the car at short range. A fine rain&#8211;bow cheered us shortly after we had left the scene of slaughter. We arrived at the Rector's house in Hexham about 7.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Both the "Nation" and the "Spectator" have articles conceived in a tone of severe &amp; scornful censure dealing with the attacks on Lord <persName xml:id="3556">Kitchener</persName> in the <persName xml:id="4024">Northcliffe</persName> press. It is noteworthy that they both assume that the Proprietor has sole responsibility for the conduct of the papers. Nothing seems credited to the <persName xml:id="2709">Editor</persName> of the 'Times'. This must be very galling to that gentleman, &amp; marks a grave change in the fashions of journalism, &amp; sinister as grave. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
