<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">244</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
A most glorious morning fulfilling the promise of a glowing sunset with which <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh</persName> &amp; I were entranced last night. The Holy Communion was preceded by Mattins &amp; Litany at 7.45 a.m. I celebrated as the Statutes direct, &amp; of my brethren <persName xml:id="2785"><hi rend="underline">Quirk</hi></persName><hi> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="473"><hi rend="underline">Knowling</hi></persName> only were present. There were about 60 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> which is unusually few. <hi rend="italic bold underline">At breakfast <persName xml:id="403">Dicey's</persName> loquacity threatened his total starvation! </hi><hi rend="italic">He told us one curious fact viz: that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4007">Lord Palmerston</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> was a convinced Baconian, &amp; was only held back by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1336">Lord Shaftesbury</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> from publishing the fact. If he </hi><hi rend="italic underline">had</hi><hi rend="italic"> done so, his political career might have been rightly terminated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowling</hi><hi> addressed the troops at 10 a.m. while I read over &amp; gave final revision to my sermon. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName></hi><hi> sought to take photographs with his pocket camera. There was a fair congregation in the Cathedral at the Choral Eucharist, when I preached from S. Paul's words "</hi><hi rend="underline">Thanks be to God who giveth us the victory thro' our Lord Jesus Christ"</hi><hi><ref xml:id="892"></ref>. I limited myself severely to the subject of the Festival, &amp; would not stray even for a sentence into the polemics suggested by the Tee&#8211;total faction. Col. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName></hi><hi> &amp; his wife came to lunch. At Evensong the singing was, I thought, unusually good. The service was preceded by a procession all round the cathedral. The acoustics of the Nine Altars are for this purpose admirable. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3553">Mead&#8211;Falkner</persName></hi><hi> &amp; his wife came to tea. He is very depressed about the situation; says that ammunition &amp; guns are pouring into Constantinople: that the Turks are fighting with extraordinary efficiency: that no one really knows how great an accumulation of War material the Germans possess. He speaks strongly about drink, &amp; inclines to prohibition of the sale of spirits. Total prohibition of all alcoholic drinks he deprecates as imprudent, &amp; not unlikely to provoke men to reprisals. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh</hi><hi> &amp; I walked up the hill to get a final view of the Cathedral, &amp; then we all abandoned ourselves to the delights of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicey's</hi><hi> conversation until bed&#8211;time!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
