<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[239]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915. London.</hi>
             </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The sermon in the <orgName xml:id="79">Temple Church</orgName> was delivered to a very large congregation, in which there was a strong infusion of khaki</hi><hi rend="italic">. I preached<ref xml:id="896"></ref> from the text S. Lk. VI. 37, 38. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"New wine must be put into fresh wine&#8211;skins"</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; I based on it a discussion of the probable effect of the war on Religion. While the churches w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> lose: Christianity w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> gain. A young soldier ran into the vestry afterwards, &amp; told me he was back for short leave after 8 months in the trenches &amp; 'felt that he must tell me that I had just spoken what everybody out there thought'. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I lunched with the Benchers. Justice <persName xml:id="4032">Darling</persName>, as Treasurer, presided. We walked back to the Abbey with the <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, &amp; then I had tea in <persName xml:id="636">Pearce's</persName> little garden with him &amp; <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>. At the Evening service in the Nave of the Abbey Church, there was a great crowd. The <persName xml:id="128">Abp. Of Canterbury</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="404">Davidson</persName> were in the congregation. I preached<ref xml:id="895"></ref> for the 4</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> time the sermon on "The Kingship of Jesus". It took 35 minutes to deliver, &amp; was listened to very closely. We had supper with the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Monday, I had my hair cut: wrote letters: lunched in the Club, where I had much talk with <persName xml:id="2846">Parkin</persName>: finally, rejoined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at the Deanery, &amp; bade farewell to the <persName xml:id="325">Ryles</persName><persName xml:id="326"></persName>. Then we went to stay for the night at Stubbers, &amp; [sic] quaint &amp; comfortable house not far from Upminster, where we were entertained by the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4033">Champion Russells</persName></hi><hi>. A London magistrate, Clarke Hall, &amp; his wife came to dinner. On Tuesday morning, we loafed in the garden, &amp; after lunch went to London, &amp; were taken by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1209">Inge</persName> to hear <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> lecture on "The spirit of Italy" at King's College. There was a very large company, &amp; the lecture was much applauded. We went to spend the next two days at Gaynes with old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Joslin. There came to dinner <persName xml:id="4035">Sir Montagu</persName> &amp; Lady Turner, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> R. Strutt.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[241]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Wednesday afternoon our host drove us to Havering&#8211;atte&#8211;Bower &amp; there introduced us to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Mackintosh. This lady shewed us her truly wonderful garden. The rhododendrons, whose full glory had passed, were still an amazing spectacle. On Thursday, we bade farewell to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Joslin, &amp; returned to town. Having deposited our baggage at King's Cross, we parted to meet there again for the evening express. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I went to S. Sepulchre's, &amp; there preached<ref xml:id="897"></ref> to the <orgName xml:id="38">Churchmen's Union</orgName> about Magna Carta, protesting against the attempt to connect the agitation for "Church Reform" with that famous document</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>I lunched with the Committee, &amp; attended the meeting in <orgName xml:id="47">Sion College</orgName>. Here was read a rather remarkable paper by D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName>, very egotistical &amp; vague. Being invited by the President (<persName xml:id="402">Percy Gardner</persName>) to address the assembly, I made a brief fierce speech, equally sincere, unwelcome, &amp; unwise! Then I rejoined <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>, &amp; we returned together to Durham.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
