<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">275</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote cheques for the month's Housekeeping accounts. I wrote to Scott <persName xml:id="1009">Lidgett</persName> 'crying off' the article in the "Contemporary": and sent a short note to the <persName xml:id="128">Abp.</persName> saying that I had done this. <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> tells me that 6 of the London incumbents, including <persName xml:id="3690">Mackay</persName> of All Saints, Margaret Street, are threatening to resign their benefices by way of protesting against the "Statement". If they would carry out their threat there would be compensation for one's disappointment; but there's little prospect of this. We motored to Brandon where I presided at a performance of Haydn's 'Creation' by the 'Musical Union' of which our lay vicar, Vincent Jones, is the conductor. In one of the 'intervals' I made a brief speech about Serbia as the proceeds were to be given to the Serbian Rad Cross Fund. I was amused by the speeches of the mover &amp; seconder of a vote of thanks to me. The one was conceived in ample &amp; indiscriminating terms; the other was cautiously limited. I inferred that the speaker was a total abstainer, and anxious not to be supposed to approve my attitude towards the Drink Question.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
