<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">272</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful but distinctly cold day. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Ethel <persName xml:id="2751">Gore&#8211;Booth</persName> went with me to Hartlepool, where I preached in the old church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Hilda. The congregation, rather to my dismay, consisted largely of soldiers. On the journey back to Durham, we were implicated in an accident. </hi><hi rend="italic">Two young men riding a motor&#8211;cycle, which they could not rightly control, attempted to pass our motor on the wrong side of the road &amp; scarcely avoiding collision with it ran into the bank &amp; overturned. Neither was seriously injured, though one was cut about the face, &amp; the other about the hands. The machine was put out of action, but not greatly damaged. We carried the youths to <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Hospital</orgName>, where they were looked after: &amp; subsequently I sent the car back to carry them to their homes in Hartlepool. </hi><hi>These happenings caused so much delay that it was nearly 2 p.m. before we reached the Deanery. Here we found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major John Murray</hi><hi> waiting for us. He lunched &amp; then returned to <placeName xml:id="62">Lumley</placeName>. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; then took Logic for a walk. Colonel <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName> came to see me, &amp; sate talking for an hour. After dinner I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
