<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[313]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">362</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="2693" display="no">Olive</persName> was married in the Cathedral to <persName xml:id="2867">George Blakey</persName>. </hi>We lunched with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> in order to leave the Deanery free for the marriage guests. Then we drove to Belmont, where I 'dedicated' colours for the Girl Guides, whom <persName xml:id="2895">Penelope Pemberton</persName> governs with sage rigour, and made them a speech. From Belmont I went to the Market Place in Durham, and took part in a <hi rend="underline">Recruiting Meeting. The Mayor presided, <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> &amp; I were the speakers. Col. <persName xml:id="3512">Darwin</persName> told me afterwards that 17 recruits joined after the meeting!</hi> General <persName xml:id="3223">Gainsford</persName> arrived to spend the night. <persName xml:id="4051">Major Vane Tempest</persName>, that queer little papist connexion of the <persName xml:id="2818">Londonderry's</persName><persName xml:id="2819"></persName> who commands the artillery here, came to dinner. The General was sent to the front to make the round of trenches, &amp; see how the war actually was being conducted. His account of things was very interesting. I note that he holds that an attempt at invasion is more than probable, and by no means to be considered unimportant.
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
