<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[359]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">390</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a short sermon on 'Friendship' for the troops in the Cathedral. Then I answered the Unitarian Minister's letter, &amp; corrected some more proofs of the sermons. They are very disappointing in cold print! The morning post brought affectionate letters from <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; walked with Logic. On the way I came upon the excellent Librarian, <persName xml:id="3828">Stocks</persName>, busily engaged in trimming the hedge which parts his allotment garden from the road. He has been patriotically planting every kind of crop in the space available. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler's</persName></hi><hi> famous <ref xml:id="787">"charge"</ref> to the clergy of Durham: it is, indeed, amazing that anyone could have found in it the signs of popery! Incidentally the Bishop indicates the age of Confirmation: 'the usual age for Confirmation is that time of life, from which youth must become more and more their own masters, when they are often leaving their father's house, going out into the wide world with all its numerous temptations: against which they particularly want to be fortified, by having strong &amp; lively impressions of religion made upon their minds.' It would appear that the rubric requiring notice of an intention to receive the Confirmation to be given beforehand to the Curate does not seem to have been altogether obsolete, as the Bishop indicates it is an occasion on which religious instruction might be given.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> and to Hugh Lyon. The last is at home on short leave from the front. He expresses himself very well, insisting on 'the positive side of patriotism' and repudiating the too&#8211;fashionable hate.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
