<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[223]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">294</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The brilliant weather continues. It is <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton's</persName> Birthday, &amp; a general holiday. There is no resisting the suggestion, threefold and converging. In effect, we do not resist: but, provided with an ample luncheon, set out on an excursion to 'High Force'. At Barnard Castle we visit the Museum, where Hutton, who was at one time working in that parish, introduces us to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Scott, the custodian. There is a considerable collection of china, pictures, &amp;c, exhibited in an unusually fine &amp; convenient building. We lunch pleasantly in a little wood by the road&#8211;side, &amp; then continue to High Force, where we find the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName>, &amp; have tea with them very comfortably. The water&#8211;fall is remarkable for the imposing rock&#8211;setting. There is said to be a fine flow of water in wet weather: today the quantity is not magnificent, but sufficient. On the whole, I incline to give this cascade the primacy among English waterfalls. We motored home by way of Staindrop, where we visited the interesting parish church, which contains some fine monuments of the Neville family. Raby <placeName xml:id="65">Castle</placeName> makes a fine show as the traveller leaves Staindrop. We arrived in Durham about 6.30 p.m. when <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, after a hasty dinner, went off to London. Hutton &amp; I had some conversation about affairs ecclesiastical after dinner. He appears to me to be quite impervious to the frankly anarchic tendency of the claims which the so&#8211;called "Catholics" are making. His contention that coercion must fail where consciences are concerned sounds well enough, but it throws no light on the practical issues. It is hardly so much conscience as a policy, deliberately planned &amp; pursued, for transforming the system of the English Church. It is hard to justify a prompt &amp; total surrender of the Bishops to such a policy, even although it be pressed on them in the great &amp; abused name of 'Conscience'.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
