<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[339]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">378</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A great rain: and still the demoralizing thunderous atmosphere. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; besides did scarcely anything. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName></hi><hi> gave me some account of his experiences in the Government service. He says that at Birmingham a factory worked mostly by women is turning out 5000 shells daily for the Russian Government: &amp; that an immense accumulation of these shells is awaiting the downfall of Constantinople. Then, &amp; not till then, it can be sent to its destination.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The lowest wage paid to these women is at the rate of 28/&#8211; weekly. Will the girls be easily persuaded to go back to the smaller earnings of normal times?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> was due to arrive at 6.23 p.m.: &amp; I was on the platform to meet him. But in vain. The connexion at York had been missed, &amp; there was no train earlier than 7.59 p.m. This very provoking contretemps upset both our plans for dinner, &amp; our tempers!! However </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bryce</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his wife arrived a few minutes before 9 p.m. when we had just gone in to the dining room, and the rest of the evening passed without any unfortunate incidents save that a maid precipitated the mint sauce over </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, whereupon his Lordship gaily observed that it was very proper that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">mint sauce should go with a Lambton</hi><hi rend="italic">! </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bryce</hi><hi rend="italic"> looks very white and wizened but he is as wiry &amp; active as ever, &amp; talks with all his old vivacity.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
