<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">230</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A comfortless blustering morning, but not so cold. I did not go to the early service, but revised the two discourses which were to be preached to the soldiers, &amp; the folk at Bishopwearmouth respectively. Preaching does not become easier as the years pass, &amp; bring with them a disconcerting knowledge of one's own life, and of the lives of others. The holding power of Christianity lies in the fact that there is no possible alternative. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Lord, to whom shall we go? Thou hast the words of eternal life</hi><hi rend="italic">". That is the final apology of discipleship. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> preached about the 'reconciliation' effected by the death of Christ &#8211; a very confident, crude pronouncement. I preached at the military service. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="1862"><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Bonney</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> went with me into the Cathedral after lunch. His loving enthusiasm over its different features of skill &amp; beauty was delightful. He preached pleasantly at Evensong. Then I motored to Sunderland accompanied by </hi><persName xml:id="1204"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mary</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">. There I preached in Bishopwearmouth church to a crowded congregation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We motored back to Durham immediately afterwards, conversing about the past &amp; the future. She leaves us tomorrow to go to India to be married to Alan <persName xml:id="3885">Radford</persName>. On arriving at the Deanery, I gave her a small book on Durham as a reminder of our little expedition</hi><hi rend="italic">. Bonney talked very interestingly on geological &amp; seismical themes. I was immensely impressed by his wide &amp; accurate knowledge of many things.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received letters from <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName>, <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName>, <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName>, &amp; a strange parson named </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Buckley</hi><hi rend="italic"> expressing approval of my letter in the "Times". </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bonney</hi><hi rend="italic"> also approved after reading it. The sad thing is that any criticism of total abstinence perplexes &amp; distresses a multitude of very good people, who cannot distinguish between total abstinence &amp; temperance, &amp; who &#8211; often for strong reasons &#8211; regard 'the Drink' as the sum of all Evil.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
