<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[373]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">396</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Still glides the Stream, and shall forever glide;	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Form remains, the Function never dies:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>While we, the brave, the mighty, and the wise,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We Men, who in our morn of youth defied</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The elements, must vanish –</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2271" display="no">Wordsworth</persName></hi><hi> was more a pantheist than Christian when he conceived those lines, though he adopts a more permissible attitude in his lines which follow:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>&#8211; be it so!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Enough, if something from our hands have power</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To live, and act, and serve the future hour;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And if, as towards the silent tomb we go,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Through love, through hope, and faith's transcendent dower,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We feel that we are greater than we know.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The whole sonnet is a poet's variation of the Apostle's dictum: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The world passeth away &amp; the lust thereof, but he that doeth the Will of God abideth for ever"</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName></hi><hi> went off after breakfast, &amp; I went in to the military service, &amp; preached to a rather small congregation of soldiers on the 'Royal Law' of mutual consideration. Then I attended Mattins, and listened to a sermon from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName></hi><hi> about the War. He assumes as if it were self&#8211;evident that God is punishing England for its irreligion by bringing upon it this dreadful visitation: &amp; he suggests that reformation is the only road to victory. As an example of the wickedness for which the nation is being visited, he mentioned that he himself had recently visited a camp of 5000 soldiers &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion at 7 a.m., and that only 3 communicants presented themselves! After Mattins, I celebrated the Holy Communion, &amp; then walked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2685">Charnwood</persName></hi><hi> before lunch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[375]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2360">Captain</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3023" display="no">Soltau&#8211;Simmons</persName> came to lunch. At Evensong old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> appeared in his stall to hear Blow's Anthem. After service we (i.e. the <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName> &amp; ourselves) walked round Houghall wood. The sunset was most beautiful, &amp; the Cathedral suffused by crimson light which deepened to purple was superb. <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> came to supper, and talked with much animation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
