<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[337]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">377</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The mildest optimism is fatal when it refuses to recognise abuses that must be corrected, as the gentlest pessimism is fatal when it sneers at and discourages everything that tries to work in hope… Of the two the workings of pessimism are both the most dangerous and the most painful."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop Stubbs.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. Among the communicants I noticed </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName></hi><hi> of Magdalen, who is staying with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi>. He is quite white though I should suppose that he can hardly be more than 2 years older than myself. The post brought an invitation to attend the autumnal meeting of the Congregational Union at Leeds in the beginning of October: but I returned a refusal on the score of other engagements in the South of England. I preached to the troops at 10 a.m., taking as my text the same verse as had served me last Sunday, "</hi><hi rend="underline">The earth is the Lord's, &amp; the fullness thereof</hi><hi>": but the sermon was different. The men seemed to me to be attentive: but I was assured afterwards by my guests that </hi><hi rend="underline">they</hi><hi> in the South Transept were with difficulty able to hear me on account of the echo! It is the case that I turned towards the North Transept, which was filled with soldiers, more than has been my wont. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><hi> preached at2 Mattins on the Parable of the Pharisee &amp; the Publican, &amp; took occasion to warn us against an undue depreciation of the Germans! The admonition is needed, but I wish the Germans would not facilitate our transgression! The heaviness of the atmosphere is almost over&#8211;powering. </hi><persName xml:id="1696"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive</hi></persName><hi> coming to my study to fetch the library keys, caught me out in undignified slumber! After Evensong I walked vigorously with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter</hi><hi> for an hour in the effort to shake off this demoralizing stupor. On my return I found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3553">Mead Falkner</persName></hi><hi> in the drawing&#8211;room, &amp; had a long talk with him. He thinks the War will last another two years.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[339]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3553">Mead Falconer</persName></hi><hi> &amp; I tarried in the Cathedral, &amp; meditated on its majesty. It is '</hi><hi rend="underline">the embodiment of the sinister splendour of the North</hi><hi>', he said: &amp; I rejoined, "</hi><hi rend="underline">It is the Dies Irae in stone</hi><hi>". The most distinctive &amp; suggestive memorials of the Middle Ages are </hi><hi rend="underline">Durham Cathedral</hi><hi> &amp; the </hi><hi rend="underline">Dies Irae</hi><hi>. We lamented the decline of the Church of England, though our points of view are very different.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
