<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">202</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright morning with slight frost. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were about 70 communicants, but most of them stayed in the nave where they could not possibly have heard the service, a circumstance of some importance since many were young. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> preached an excellent little discourse to the troops, who sang the hymns with great heartiness. At Mattins <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> preached a long &amp; characteristic sermon on "Self–control". It was very interesting but disjointed, &amp; delivered in a very lifeless, supercilious manner. There was a large congregation. After service I took <persName xml:id="3997">Westcott</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName> (who had turned up from Gateshead) to call on <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName>, &amp; see the new House. It appears that <persName xml:id="3997">Westcott</persName> has a nephew at the school. The</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> lad, rather shy &amp; awkward, came to tea after Evensong</hi><hi>. Westcott's sermon was well composed, &amp; (save for the mechanical intonation which is distinctive of deaf persons) well–delivered. He took for his text S. Paul's words in Eph. VI. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Our wrestling is not against flesh &amp; blood</hi><hi>&amp;c": &amp; made an earnest argument for the reality of evil spirit–forces as the enemies of the human soul. In the course of the sermon he referred to the fact that it was just 30 years since he had himself been ordained in the Cathedral. Gee &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2762">Watkins</persName> came in to tea in order to see Westcott: &amp; the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> had lunched here with the same object. We easily persuaded Hugh Lyon to stay the night, and risk the displeasure of the military authorities! But he has been in hospital recently, &amp; is clearly not very robust. <persName xml:id="3997">Westcott</persName>, <persName xml:id="648">Caröe</persName>, and I had much discussion on many subjects. It is interesting to hear from</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="2128">his son's</persName> pious &amp; ardent words an account of the great <persName xml:id="1047">Bishop</persName>, whose tenure of the see has left so great a tradition: but it makes the actual circumstances of the diocese seem more squalid than ever.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
