<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[215]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">289</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I made some notes for my speech, &amp; then we motored to Hartlepool, where I was pledged to open the extension of the Public Library. We lunched at the Grand Hotel as the guests of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Horsley, &amp; then performed the function. There was a considerable gathering of invited guests. I made a speech which took about half an hour to deliver, &amp; was very well received. Then we had tea in another room of the library, and this finished, motored back to Durham, where we arrived about 6 p.m. Then I walked with <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> along the river&#8211;bank. We encountered a good many soldiers, among them three of the wounded from the little Red Cross Hospital in the Bailey. Of these two had been poisoned by the German gas. I promised to shew them over the Cathedral. The Hartlepool Committee presented me with a copy of a book on Hartlepool with a suitable inscription. The papers are full of political reconstructions. <persName xml:id="2441">Winston Churchill</persName>, <persName xml:id="956">Haldane</persName>, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi><persName xml:id="372">Kenna</persName> are said to be the Ministers whose removal is to be arranged.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
