<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[253]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">328</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">The opinion of the Church does not matter. There is no longer a Church of Christ. There is a Church of England, a church of Germany, a church of Russia, of Italy and of France, colouring their humanity with their political convictions, &amp; their patriotic desires</hi><hi>" – such is the language of an article on "Reprisals" sent to me last week. It appears in a paper called "Town Talk", and is vigourously [sic] written. This brings us to a practical victory of Thomas Hobbes of Malmesbury!<persName xml:id="2150"></persName></hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="249"> 
 Gamble</persName></hi><hi> writes to me suggesting that some effort should be made by the Church to bring about peace, but I cannot think that the time has come yet. Until the German armies have evacuated Belgium, &amp; the German government consented to compensate the Belgians, so far as is possible, for the infamies committed against them, I cannot see that Peace would be morally tolerable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached to the troops from the words "A man's foes shall be they of his own household". There were about 600 men in the Cathedral, as I judge. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingstson</persName> preached at Mattins. It was hardly in any sense a regular discourse but a discursive exhortation to prayer framed in much purple invective against 'drinking'. He seems to consider prayer as a more effective kind </hi><hi rend="bold">[255] </hi><hi>of shell, manufactured more easily and at vastly smaller cost! This cheap ranting would have better matched a street–corner than a cathedral pulpit, yet I suspect that the congregation for the most part approved it, &amp; applauded the preacher. So long as there is a public welcome for such stuff, there will not lack purveyors: but I could wish that they were not found among the holders of our capitular stalls. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, &amp; afterwards shewed some officers over the building. Finally I wrote letters.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
