<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">301</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast, we motored to Borcovicus (Housesteads) on the wall. Canon <persName xml:id="3167">Savage</persName> &amp; his curate M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4027">Ballance</persName> went with us. The wind was too strong &amp; keen for comfort, and there was a stormy sky, but even so, the scene was remarkably impressive. On our return journey we burst a tyre. After lunching in Hexham, we motored back to Durham by way of Shotley Bridge and Lanchester. The day had now cleared up, &amp; we journeyed through a smiling country under bright sun. We arrived in the Deanery about 4.30 p.m. </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Savage</hi><hi> assures me that the <persName xml:id="1132">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> is in a very bad state of health, &amp; can hardly be expected to outlive this year. It is not without a certain suggestiveness that so many of our Bishops should for one reason or another be so decrepit as not to achieve their tasks. </hi><persName xml:id="276"><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Moule</hi></persName><hi> has been ailing for many months, taking little or no duty. </hi><persName xml:id="2074"><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Drury</hi></persName><hi> has been long on the sick list. </hi><persName xml:id="477"><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Chavasse</hi></persName> <hi>&amp; </hi><persName xml:id="1727"><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Jayne</hi></persName><hi> are both supposed to be more or less ill. Yet the Church stumbles along with or without the Apostolical Indispensibles!!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
