<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[381]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">403</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3526" display="no">Gaymer</persName> came to see me. He was evidently labouring under some unusual perturbation, which was sufficiently explained by the fact that he had been a witness, &amp; almost a victim, of the Zeppelin raid in London on Wednesday night. He lodges somewhere in the neighbourhood of Gray's Inn, &amp; had hardly got into bed before two explosions aroused him: he went to the window only to see the house in front of him fall into ruin. He says the range &amp; fury of the conflagration were astonishing: but he was most impressed by the stoical &amp; almost amused demeanour of the crowd. The spectacle of two little children slain before his eyes almost overcame him. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Gaymer's account confirmed the letter of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4063">Cowan</persName> which reached me this morning: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The great white Zeppelin hovering over the square (i.e. Queen Square W.C.) was a wonderful though terrible sight</hi><hi>". Later, the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> told me that his daughter <persName xml:id="3697">Helen</persName>, who is nursing in the London Hospital, had seen the Zeppelins. Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName> who arrived from town at tea&#8211;time reported much confusion &amp; disturbance. Wood Street, which is quite near S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's is said to be still burning! I met <persName xml:id="3438">Rogerson</persName>, who has just heard good accounts of <persName xml:id="3861">his son</persName>, a prisoner in Germany, but the treatment of the Russian prisoners continues to be abominable. It appears to be the case that Woolwich arsenal had a very near escape from the bombs on Wednesday.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
