<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">174</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m. Three boys were carried out fainting! At 10 a.m. the Cocken men turned up at the Military Service, &amp; made a brave show. I preached to them in the teeth of a hail of coughs! <persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> preached an excellent sermon at Mattins, in the course of which he alluded to the death of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3988">Shafto</persName>. I celebrated after Mattins. At lunch we had a military party – Col. <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName>, Major <persName xml:id="3879">Murray</persName>, his friend Gordon, &amp; <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName>. Also M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hardy of the Record Office. After lunch I took everybody into the library, &amp; through the Cathedral. </hi><hi rend="italic">Major Murray told me that his father, the publisher, had sent the MS. of Byron's 'Childe Harold' to the Exhibition at Leipzig, and that it had been lost or destroyed. Inquiries as to its fate had so far proved abortive.</hi><hi> Colonel <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName> brought a nephew, who had returned wounded from France. He had been one of the officers of the Durhams, to whom I preached at Cambridge. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="3685">Prof. How</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3686">his wife</persName> came in to tea. Then Jim &amp; I walked for an hour. </hi>
         </p>
               </body></text></TEI>
