<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">152</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The year begins with very bad news. Yesterday (New Year's Day) witnessed a very bad railway smash at Ilford<note xml:id="263" n="1"></note>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">and the sinking of the battleship </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">"Formidable" in the Channel</hi><hi>. It seems certain that the bulk of her complement (750) has perished. This sub&#8211;marine warfare is horrifying: it has the fell mystery of unsuspected poison as well as the fearful mortality of war. I attended Mattins in the Cathedral, &amp; then finished my sermon for tomorrow. After lunch I walked with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> for an hour: &amp; then went to Evensong. Then I wrote letters until dinner. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Two telegrams from the <persName xml:id="2709">Editor</persName> of the "Times" asking whether I was preaching tomorrow, &amp;, if so, that I would send a summary of my discourse</hi> <hi>indicated that the services tomorrow are regarded with more public interest than I had supposed probable. I allowed a brace of local press men to make some extracts. In the course of the afternoon </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I visited old Canon <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName>. He said that he remembered well the invasion of Hungary by the Russians after the troubles of 1848</hi><hi>. After dinner the indefatigable Linetta again assaulted the well&#8211;defended citadel of my ignorance. Thirty years ago, when the power to learn had not yet wholly deserted me, she might had had some result of her efforts: but the reluctant intelligence of middle age presents an insuperable barrier to the entrance of every kind of new knowledge</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
