<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[325]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
         <hi rend="bold">373</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I took <persName xml:id="601">Muir Mackenzie</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="18">Gerald</persName> in the motor to <placeName xml:id="65">Raby</placeName></hi>, which we viewed under the house&#8211;keeper's guidance. As we left the castle, we fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1559">Lord Barnard</persName></hi>. He said that he had found three red deer does dead through lightning during yesterday's storm. The creatures had taken sanctuary under a tree, &amp; perished by its fatal neighbourhood. I had some interesting conversation with my guest as we drove homewards. He says that he cannot reconcile the society which we know and Christianity. I say that Christianity has nothing directly to do with any society: &amp; that every society can serve its turn. But I am not wholly contented with my arguments. <persName xml:id="3585"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Boutflower</hi></persName> lunched here: &amp; afterwards he &amp; I attended a most tiresome meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Governors of Sherburn Hospital</orgName>. Later I took <hi rend="doubleunderline">Muir Mackenzie</hi> for a walk through Houghall Wood, &amp; home by way of the Banks. He was admirably appreciative of the views, both of the country &amp; of the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> with <persName xml:id="2659">her mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2803">her brother</persName> arrived on a visit.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">A letter from</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName></hi> <hi rend="bold underline">arrived, accepting a volume of war&#8211;sermons.</hi><hi> After dinner Olive sang some of her songs. Her voice is richer &amp; more under her control than it was. Indeed I think that her singing is altogether on a higher plane.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
