<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[353]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">387</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3223">General Gaisford</persName> sends me a newspaper&#8211;cutting containing a report of a sermon by the <persName xml:id="720">Bishop of Carlisle</persName> in which his Lordship spoke about the angelic apparitions at Mons.<note xml:id="271" n="1"></note> The fact was certain, he said, but it might have been either objective or subjective. Vague references to Joan of Arc &amp; much rhetorical whipt&#8211;cream assisted to give the impression that the angels had really appeared, but, as a prophylactic against criticism, there was the little convenient reserve about 'objective or subjective'! I wrote to the General at once pointing out that everything important in the discussion did precisely turn on the point whether the visions were objective or subjective. The former could be tested: the latter cannot.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[355]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I took </hi><persName xml:id="2341"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm</hi></persName><hi> &amp; his <persName xml:id="2464">wife</persName> round the Cathedral, they took their departure about noon. I attended Evensong, &amp; later walked with <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; Logic.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to ask me to preach in the College Chapel on All Souls Day: &amp; I cannot refuse: though the task is hard. A certain M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Walter Laidlaw</hi><hi rend="italic"> sends me a Life of Dean <persName xml:id="3796">Granville</persName> with a note: "From one of your congregation of yesterday forenoon: with very respectful &amp; sincere gratitude. W. L. Glasgow 23/8/15". The writer's address is also given viz. 103 Fotheringay Road, Maxwell Park. This book I read through with some interest. It is mainly a reprint of the volumes of the <orgName xml:id="244">Surtees Society</orgName> which contain Granville's 'Remains', but there are some interesting documents added. The correspondence about his appointment to the Deanery is sufficiently squalid. But though sincerely religious, Granville laboured under two great disadvantages &#8211; a habit of extravagance bringing a load of debt, &amp; an inordinate pride of birth. He must have possessed a certain charm of manner, which made people condone much: and his extraordinary zeal for the Rubricks which ordered daily service in parish churches, and weekly communion in cathedrals, argues both a sincerity of conviction, &amp; some lack of proportion. He must have been a fearful bore: &amp;, I suspect also, something of a butt. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sancroft</hi><hi rend="italic">, who had a long knowledge of him, opposed his appointment as Dean of Durham, and said that he wasn't fit to be a Minor Canon. His quarrels with his father&#8211;in&#8211;law, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, reflect the utmost discredit on both men: but one cannot withhold sympathy from a man who found himself bound to a wife who at intervals 'went off her head'. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cosin</hi><hi rend="italic"> was evidently a very difficult person to live with.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
