<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[295]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1915</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">352</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A newspaper cutting from America reports the death of old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> James <persName xml:id="3050">Goodwin</persName>, who entertained us so pleasantly at Hartford, Conn., three years ago. The fore&#8211;noon was spent in writing letters. I accepted <persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie's</persName> invitation to preach in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> on Oct: 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> which he proposes to keep as the Dedication Festival of the Church: also, I promised to preach in the Crypt of Canterbury Cathedral on Oct: 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, when the French pastor observes a Thanksgiving for the Victory over the Spanish Armada: also, I promised to preach to the troops at Darlington on Aug: 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. The traditional indolence of the Decanal Office is subject to some mitigations! I walked to the Close, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="691">Fearon</persName>, who welcomed me with affection. We talked briskly for half an hour. With his habitual loyalty to superiors, he strives to show that the Kikuyu <ref xml:id="849">'Statement'</ref> is not as bad as it looks, &amp; that the Archbishop has been no worse than 'diplomatic', but the task is beyond even his powers. The arrival of the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName> cut short our conversation. I exchanged a few words with his Lordship, who regards me with the melancholy of settled suspicion. I suppose we are, &amp; know ourselves to be, frankly opposed on all religious issues. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> joined me at the Deanery where we lunched with the <persName xml:id="1378">Dean</persName> &amp; his daughter. Miss Furneaux looks very well in the garb of a Red&#8211;Cross Nurse. We walked back to the house, &amp; then motored with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3563">Dennistoun</persName> to Petersfield, where we had tea with her eldest brother, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hamilton Russell. The weather became dull &amp; threatening. The air was heavy, &amp; there were splutterings of rain. However we returned without more than splutterings. At dinner <persName xml:id="2381">Archdeacon</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Robinson joined the party &#8211; pleasant people, &amp; I should suppose very serviceable on severely conventional lines of respectable Anglicanism.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
