<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">218</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful day, but still very cold. The </hi><persName xml:id="250"><hi rend="underline">Watsons</hi></persName><persName xml:id="2372"></persName><hi> left for Oxford after breakfast. I attended an extraordinary meeting of the Council of the Durham colleges, convened to consider the present state of the litigation between the University &amp; the Ecclesiastical Commissioners in the matter of the way&#8211;leave at Bearpark.<note xml:id="277" n="1"></note> I offered, perhaps rashly, to attempt to effect a peaceable settlement with the Commissioners, or at least to discover through </hi><persName xml:id="909"><hi rend="underline">Sir Louis Dibdin</hi></persName><hi> how far they were disposed to go in that direction. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle, &amp; there attended a meeting in the Church Institute, organised by Sir </hi><hi rend="underline">Thomas <persName xml:id="3808">Oliver</persName></hi><hi> in aid of a Fund for relieving Polish Refugees. A Russian actress, Princess </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3807">Bariatinsky</persName></hi><hi>, was the principal speaker. Her strong &amp; virile voice &amp; foreign accent added impressiveness to the vigorous paper which occupied nearly an hour in reading. I made a short speech: and was followed by the secretary, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="4000">Pollock</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; Prof: </hi><hi rend="underline">Shaw</hi><hi>. Then we all went to Sir T. Oliver's house, &amp; were regaled with a rather elaborate dinner. We motored back to Durham afterwards, and got in to the Deanery about 20 minutes before midnight.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
