<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[341]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">379</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After shewing my guests the house, I took them (i.e. <persName xml:id="389">Bryce</persName> &amp; his wife, &amp; <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>) in the car on a little tour of church&#8211;inspection. We began with Pittington, where the Vicar, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3309">Guest&#8211;Williams</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, long&#8211;winded &amp; discursive, but not either ill&#8211;informed or uninteresting, shewed us the Church: then we went on to </hi><orgName xml:id="227"><hi rend="italic underline">Sherburn Hospital</hi></orgName><hi rend="italic">, where we failed to find the Master, <persName xml:id="3585">Boutflower</persName>: finally, we came to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Brancepeth</hi><hi rend="italic">, where we looked at the Church with its wealth of wood&#8211;carving, &amp; walked round the Castle, which seemed to be filled with wounded soldiers, in various stages of convalescence. Then we returned to Durham.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Bryce told me that Henry Charles <persName xml:id="3798">Lea</persName>, the American historian, was at the time of his death engaged on an elaborate History of Witchcraft: that he (Bryce) had had much correspondence with Lea's family on the subject of his unfinished MSS.: &amp; that these had been handed over to Burr, the Librarian of Cornell, who would shortly publish the work</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1559">Lord Barnard</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> came to lunch. Also <persName xml:id="3991">Colonel</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Grimshaw. Then I attended Evensong: and afterwards took my guests over the Cathedral. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bryce's</hi><hi rend="italic"> amazing wealth of knowledge impressed me greatly. He can suggest a parallel in some quarter of the world to almost everything he is shown. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> of Magdalen came to see </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bryce</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; laboured to enlist his support for a Patristic dictionary.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; his niece came to dinner; and afterwards Olive sang to the delight of the company. But our society was shadowed by ill&#8211;tidings. A British transport is reported to have been sunk in the Egean, and 1000 lives to have been lost. The Germans are gaining ground at Kovno. The fall of that Fortress may happen at any time now. It is really a case of Amateurs v. Professionals when England fights Germany.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
