<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">241</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in <placeName xml:id="77">S. Gregory's Chapel</placeName> at 8 a.m. Then I finished my Easter Sermon. After lunch I went to the Choristers' Field, &amp; watched the boys at their sports. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName></hi><hi> is evidently on good terms with them: &amp; seems to be very happy in this place. Later I went to the station to meet </hi><persName xml:id="403"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicey</hi></persName><hi>, who was coming from Oxford to pay us a visit.</hi><hi rend="italic"> The train was a full hour late. The excellent professor is more vigourously loquacious than ever. At the moment he is keen on investigating the politics of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wordsworth</hi><hi rend="italic">, in whom he believes himself to have unearthed a supporter for his own attitude towards the War. It is almost pathetic to hear him frankly unsaying the severe criticisms of sport &amp; sportsmen, in which he once indulged. Not the least attractive feature of his character is a certain naïve candour, which never hesitates for one moment to acknowledge error, not perhaps always with full justice to it. He talks so much that he eats nothing, which worries his host!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
