<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[383]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">405</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Moreover, our Saviour exercised the office of the scribe when He stooped down and with His finger wrote on the ground (John VIII), that no one however exalted, may think it unworthy of him to do what he sees the wisdom of God the Father did. O singular serenity of writing, to practise which the Artificer of the world stoops down, at whose dread name every knee doth bow! O venerable handicraft pre&#8211;eminent above all other crafts that are practised by the hand of men, to which our Lord humbly inclines His breast, to which the finger of God is applied, performing the office of a pen! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We do not read of the Son of God that he sowed or ploughed, wove or digged: nor did any other of the mechanic arts befit the divine wisdom incarnate except to trace letters in writing</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="underline">that every gentleman &amp; sciolist may know that fingers are given by God to men for the task of writing rather than for war.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'Philobiblion' c. xvi.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The excellent author has either forgotten that our Saviour is described by his contemporaries as 'the Carpenter', or he regards the description an insulting calumny. In any case the feudal contempt for manual labour breathes through the passage. Elsewhere our Saviour is represented as the model of carefulness in handling books:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'But the Saviour also has warned us by his example against all unbecoming carelessness in the handling of books, as we read in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke. For when he had read the scriptural prophecy of Himself in the book that was delivered to him, He did not give it again to the minister, until he had closed it with His own most sacred hands. By which students are most </hi><hi rend="bold">[385] </hi><hi>clearly taught that in the care of books the merest trifles ought not to be neglected.</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. and at 10 a.m. preached to the troops. There were, perhaps, about 500 present, &amp; they seemed to me more than usually attentive. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillington</persName> preached at Mattins, continuing his application of Hosea to modern circumstances. It was all very crude &amp; childish. I walked in the Banks with Logic, &amp; fell in with <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>, and the architect <persName xml:id="3816">Bilson</persName>. Two American ladies came to lunch, as also <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> &amp; his daughter <persName xml:id="2895">Penelope</persName>. I attended Evensong: and afterwards <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> brought in the Cheadles &amp; his niece to say Goodbye. They all go away for some time next Tuesday. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName>. After dinner we sate in my study, and I read poetry until prayer&#8211;time.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
