<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[357]</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">389</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Brest Litovsk, the last of the great Russian Fortresses, has fallen! It now seems doubtful what the objective of the German Armies really is, for Moscow is perhaps even more accessible than Petrograd. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Meanwhile, 7000 Welsh miners have gone on strike</hi><hi>! In the course of my afternoon's walk I fell in with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3438">Rogerson</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; had some talk with him. He says that the Roman Catholics, (of whom he has many related to him,) are furious with the Pope, &amp; indulging in a kind of language about his Holiness, which is equally novel and suggestive. As usual he complains of the dearth of good officers, &amp; the inadequacy of the new men. <persName xml:id="3982">Young Darwin</persName>, who is back from Flanders on short leave, reports that everybody is reconciling himself to a continuance of the trench&#8211;warfare, as neither side can now hope to break through the other. It is a wretched kind of warfare.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This morning brought a letter from an 'Unitarian Christian' minister, who desires to connect himself with the Church of England. This decision he connects with a speech of mine which he heard 3 years ago, in <persName xml:id="2688">Horton's</persName> chapel at Hampstead on the occasion of a celebration of the 250</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of the ejection of the Nonconformists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[359]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to Harrogate to visit a Friend, and did not return before 9 p.m.: the train being very late.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
