<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">159</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The post brought me a letter from </hi><hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="1261">Violet Markham</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, announcing her engagement to be married to Major </hi><persName xml:id="3876"><hi rend="italic underline">James Carruthers</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, now at the front. In no previous war, I think, has marriage played so considerable a part. The marriage bells play duets with the cannon! </hi><hi>Also I received a considerable fragment of a German shell from Hartlepool for the Chapter Library. I presided at the Prize&#8211;distribution of the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir School</orgName>. There was a little company of parents, friends, and quondams. </hi> <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName></hi><hi> had evidently taken great pains in preparing a short concert, &amp; a representation by some of the boys of the Trial Scene in the 'Merchant of Venice', Geoffrey <persName xml:id="3875">Heseltine</persName> as the Duke, <persName xml:id="3999">Abbey</persName> as Portia, &amp; Thompson as the merchant were all good, while a terrible cold assisted to a blood curdling hoarseness the voice with which </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3860">Alan Davis</persName></hi><hi> delivered the barbarous sentiments of Shylock. Altogether, it was a very creditable performance. In the short speech which I made before distributing the prizes, I emphasized the connexion which the statutes establish between the Choir&#8211;school &amp; the Grammar school scholarships. I said that, while I desired to restore &amp; develop this connexion, I was resolved to allow no lowering of the scholarship standard. Hence the special importance which belonged to Latin in the scheme of the school&#8211;teaching. I urged the boys to 'put their backs into' Latin in order that they might stand a reasonable chance in the scholarship examinations. Divinity had not been reported as good, &amp; therefore I made some observations on this point also. The evening post brought me a very ardently&#8211;expressed letter of thanks from <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, who had just received the book which I ordered Hugh Rees to send her on my behalf.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
