<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[261]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday,July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">336</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName>, having passed the doctor's certificate, took his departure, leaving on my hands <persName xml:id="3806">his wife</persName> &amp; three little children! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A party of 22 dissenting ministers from Sunderland came to see the Cathedral, &amp; then had tea in the Deanery. They indulged in some frothy rhetorick before going their way! It is an odd position which these men hold, for many of them have a difficult task to make a living. They are quite evidently </hi><hi rend="italic underline">de trop</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; have no endowment or tradition (as we have) to conceal the fact. Their one operative principle of combination is opposition to the Church, and this they can hardly avow, &amp; would probably deny. Yet there they are, with a 'mixed multitude', forming in the aggregate a very large proportion of the organized Christianity of the country, behind them. I would like to give most of them some kind of supplementary &amp; non&#8211;humiliating ordination, &amp; use them in the National church. Their ideas are not more chaotic or more absurd than are those of most of the curates, &amp; their humble standard of education is not conspicuously inferior! They are more exasperating than culpable, for their fondness for a windy kind of flatterous rhetoric makes their speeches loathsome, &amp; suggests a larger measure of humbug than the facts really require. Partly this is the result of their habit of life. Emotional rhetoric is their notion of eloquence: &amp; eloquence is their test of ministerial efficiency: so the talking proclivities of their class (a loquacious one) are stimulated to an amazing extent. Pecksniffs are numerous in these circumstances, &amp; even in the case of those whose intrinsic honesty makes Pecksniffery impossible, there is an aspect and manner of pompous unreality which make the average man 'see red'!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
