<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[217]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">290</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I worked at Roger de Wendover: attended Evensong in the Cathedral: motored to Brancepeth with <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName>, &amp; saw the Church under the guidance of the Rector, to whom, by way of recompense, I promised to preach in the Church on the evening of June 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> at 6.30 p.m. My predecessor, <persName xml:id="1920">Kitchin</persName>, extracted two couplets from the </hi><hi rend="underline">Philobiblion</hi><hi><note xml:id="279" n="1"></note>, &amp; caused them to be printed on a card, &amp; set above the grave of its author, Richard de Bury, Bishop of Durham, 1333&#8211;1345. They are the following:</hi>
         </p>
        
<div type="verse">
        
         <p>
<hi>"Delectant libri prosperitate arridente:</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>Consolantur nubila fortuna terrente.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Ecce per libros adjuti beatitudinis nostrae,</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi>Mercedem attingimus, dum adhuc existimus viatores.</hi>
         </p>

</div>
         <p>
<hi>I rendered them into English somewhat freely in this way: &#8211; </hi>
          </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>When prosperous winds our bark assist</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi>Books bring us daily cheer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>When clouds our bark have wrapped in mist,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Books drive away our fear.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<div type="verse">
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Through Books assisted, while on earth we stray,</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi>Heav'n's bliss befalls us on the stony way. </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>These rough verses served well enough to suggest a peroration for my little oration at Hartlepool yesterday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening papers report that the <persName xml:id="4023">alleged spy</persName>, who is now on his trial, has removed all question as to his character by committing suicide in prison. He had the grace to leave a written statement to the effect that his trial had been a fair one. Suicide must be strangely near the thought of the German officer. Many suicides are reported from the seat of war.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
