<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[407]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">417</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started on the Huguenot sermon, and made some progress. I project an answer to the question, Ought we to thank God for the Reformation? As the occasion of my preaching is a thanksgiving for the same, the inquiry can hardly be thought irrelevant. I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards walked for an hour with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName></hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then I called on old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> &amp; had some interesting talk with him. I asked him when &amp; how he became an antiquary.</hi> <hi>He told me that when he was shooting at Ford, then the seat of the Marquess of Waterford, the keeper brought to him a bronze dagger, which had been found on the estate. This interested him in such findings, &amp; he was gradually led to exert himself both to collect the remains of prehistoric man, and to study the subject. Lord Waterford introduced him to <persName xml:id="2323">Sir Tatton Sykes</persName>, by whom he was introduced to other landlords, who gave him facilities for 'digging' on their properties. He told me that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3498" display="no">Payne</persName></hi><hi>, the foreman in the Cathedral, had been to see him &amp; had impressed him favourably. I wrote a short letter to the "Record" </hi><hi rend="bold underline">protesting against <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> breach of the 'Truce' between parties by his publication of a highly controversial article on the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> <ref xml:id="849">"Statement"</ref> on Kikuyu.</hi> <hi>I dined with the <persName xml:id="3263">Lillingstons</persName>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Webb&#8211;Peploe</hi><hi> is staying there.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
