<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">246</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The paper reports that the King has issued an order for the total exclusion of wine, beer, &amp; spirits from all his houses. This is a strange proceeding, &amp; creates a situation of some difficulty for the loyal subject who dissents from the Royal example. The tee&#8211;totallers are delighted, and already taking steps to organize their forces for forcing the community into following the King's Example. What ought the Dean of Durham to do? All that loyalty rightly demands he must take the lead in doing, but does a self&#8211;respecting loyalty require him to admit the governing law of the King's example within his own house? Does not his duty rather require him publicly to differentiate loyalty from such servility? And is not this consideration the more cogent in his case, since the King is the Author of 'preferment', and any demonstrations of independence on his part may adversely affect the Royal mind?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I walked </hi><persName xml:id="403"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dicey</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> in the Cloisters, as the weather was unfavourable, and then took him to Evensong in the Cathedral. I have started him on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pascal's</hi><hi rend="italic"> '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Provinciales</hi><hi rend="italic">', which he has by some extraordinary omission never read. He is evidently much delighted with them, but characteristically is moved to put up a case for the Jesuits at every turn. He is very keen on many questions of New Testament criticism, and constantly raises points for discussion. On the whole the movement of his mind seems to be towards Christianity: &amp; he speaks with contempt of the more extravagant critics.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
