<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[271]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">344</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An almost oppressively hot day. After breakfast we walked in the Park, &amp; watched the drilling of numerous bodies of recruits. Save for the soldiers, the place seemed to be deserted. Then we parted company. I went to the '<orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>', and there spent most of the day. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> effected a junction with <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName>, who had motored from Hampshire. Jim leaves for the front at the end of this week. In the Club I had some talk with <persName xml:id="2141">Oman</persName>, who did not seem very cheerful. <persName xml:id="372">McKenna</persName> announced in the House of Commons that &#x00A3;570.000.000 had been subscribed to the new War Loan, which is less than the sensational figures which have been circulated unofficially, but is an immense sum, &amp; makes a record in war&#8211;loans.<note xml:id="284" n="1"></note> The South Welsh miners have refused the very liberal terms offered by <persName xml:id="990">Runciman</persName>, and seem to be bent on a strike. It is announced that the Government have issued a Proclamation threatening with penalties under the Munitions Act any man who joins in the Strike. I had a good deal of conversation with <persName xml:id="2846">Parkin</persName>, who has just been attending a Laymen's Conference in Oxford, convened to consider the spiritual responsibilities created by the war. <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> appears to have impressed him greatly. The narrowest Theory has the most attractive of exponents. The ordinary Englishman cannot believe that so rigid an intolerance could lie behind an exterior so devout &amp; affectionate. The broad effect of Gore's influence discloses its real character, but, as it is perceived by individuals in the charm &amp; light of his presence, it seems the fullness of tolerant charity. His opponents have the aspect of a number of half&#8211;obsolete bigots, striving for shibboleths which have lost meaning for reasonable folks!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
