<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[301]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">354</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="3566">Foakes&#8211;Jackson</persName> <ref xml:id="850">Article</ref> still haunts me, &amp; its possibility grows doubtful. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">What are the probable consequences of the War on Religion</hi><hi>? How will these find expression in the Church of England? There is nothing new or surprising about the 'religious revival' which is reported from </hi><hi rend="underline">all</hi><hi> the armies. It is only an illustration, impressive because of the scale of which it has been displayed, of Tertullian's aphorism </hi><hi rend="underline">"Anima humana naturaliter Christiana"</hi><hi>. But experience w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> seem rather discouraging as to the quality &amp; effect of this war&#8211;born religiousness. Already we are displaying many signs of spiritual crudity which must utter itself superstitiously. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">In today's "Times" I notice a letter headed "Spiritual Forces", &amp; signed by <persName xml:id="3611">Sheppard</persName>, the new Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Martin's in Trafalgar Square.</hi><hi> He pleads for the setting up of 'some central machinery for controlling &amp; directing the whole of the nation's spiritual forces on a national basis'. He proceeds to speak specifically of prayer, &amp; suggests the immediate convocation of a conference 'of all the leaders of the Christian religion with a view to arrangements being made by w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">h</hi> <hi>every citizen sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be given the opportunity of filling in a form stating his or her willingness to take a definite &amp; regular part in the nation's work of prayer &amp; intercession, &amp; what time each week c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>be given by them to this work'. This singular suggestion sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be compared with the Sermon on the Mount. Truly a satirist, severe but not unjust, might write up on the doors of our Churches the Lord's summary of pagan devotion: </hi><hi rend="underline">"They think that they shall be heard for their much speaking</hi><hi>". Of course there is no conscious hypocrisy in this queer process of 'organizing our spiritual resources', but it sets religious men on a road which can only lead to the abyss of hypocrisy: &amp; the devout will go quickest therein, &amp; fall deepest therein.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[303]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left Winchester in a down&#8211;fall of rain, by the 11.23 a.m. express, &amp; reached Waterloo shortly after 1 p.m. Foolishly committing ourselves to a hansom drawn by the most decrepit of cab&#8211;horses, we drove first to Aldwych where <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> got out in order to lunch with her suffragette friend M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2939">Webbe</persName>: &amp; I went on to the Deanery at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi>. Paul's. Here I found nobody in, but lunch prepared, &amp; the Archbishop's sister&#8211;in&#8211;law awaiting the Dean's arrival! I invited her to lunch, and we lunched amicably together. Then I betook myself to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athanaeum</orgName> where I found <persName xml:id="2846">Parkin's</persName> gift of the convenient collection of diplomatic documents. I had my hair &#8211;cut and shampooed: &amp; then, returning to the Club, read </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="427">Ralph's</persName> article on "Patriotism" in the Quarterly, </hi><hi>&amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>. Then I walked back to the Deanery. On the way I ran in to Miss Troutbeck &amp; her sister&#8211;in&#8211;law. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Simpson, the wife of the <persName xml:id="423">Canon</persName>, is said to be dying: indeed, unlikely to survive the night. The poor man is much distressed &amp; cast down. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="102">Romanes</persName> is staying here &#8211; a fanatical woman enough in mind, but well&#8211;behaved enough to conceal the fact. Her son, a youth in Khaki, was at dinner. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> also dined, looking very well indeed, &amp; mightily pleased, as well she might be, over the Italian lectureship. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ralph told a good story of <persName xml:id="1153">Jowett's</persName> reply to an undergraduate</hi><hi rend="italic"> who inquired whether a good man could be happy on the rack. "Well", said the Master with deliberation, "perhaps he might, if he were a very good man on a very bad rack". We talked away pleasantly enough, but there must have been mighty little substance in our talking, for with an effort I can recall nothing beyond this mot with merits noting.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
