<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[367]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">394</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most beautiful autumn morning after the rain: everything filled with water but radiant under the sun&#8211;light. How good it would all be if but this hateful back&#8211;ground of slaughter were taken away! The paper reports the illness of the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName>. If his Grace should be taken away at this juncture, the outlook for the Church of England would be dark indeed. I worked at the sermon on "The Function &amp; Future of National Christianity", and finished it, but it is rather incoherent, &amp; nowise satisfies me. In the course of the morning M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Armes appeared, &amp; told me that his mother, the <persName xml:id="4060">widow</persName> of the <persName xml:id="4059">late organist</persName> died yesterday. He wanted permission for her burial to take place tomorrow, &amp; for the service to take place in the Cathedral. This I granted.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Janey <persName xml:id="1243">Fleet</persName> sent me a photograph of herself in a nurse's dress. She has been transmuted from a hearty&#8211;looking Canadian girl into an anaemic Sister of Mercy:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Alack, Philosophy!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Despite the chop &amp; change, diminished or increased,</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Patched&#8211;up and plastered&#8211;o'er, Religion stands at least</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">I' the temple&#8211;type</hi><hi>. But thou? Here gape I, all agog </hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>These thirty years, to learn how tadpole turns to frog;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And thrice at least have gazed with mild astonishment,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As, skyward up and up, some fire&#8211;new fabric sent</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Its challenge to mankind that, clustered underneath</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To hear the word, they straight believe, ay, in the teeth</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>O' the Past, clap hands and hail triumphant Truth's outbreak &#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Tadpole&#8211;frog&#8211;theory propounded past mistake!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In vain! A something ails the edifice, it bends, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It bows, it buries… Haste! cry "Heads below" to friends &#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But have no fear they find, when smother shall subside, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Some substitution perk with unabated pride</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I' the predecessor's place!	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>('Fifine at the Fair'.)</hi>
         </p>
        
</div>
            <p> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
