<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">266</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The battle in Flanders still rages, and is still doubtful. By their gases the Germans evidently gained a considerable initial success, but whether they can maintain it is still in question. We must prepare ourselves for some long casualty lists. </hi><hi rend="italic">I wrote to the Archbishop thanking him for his gift of a copy of <ref xml:id="849">'Kikuyu'</ref>, &amp; telling him frankly what was my first impression of it: 'mainly I incline to conclude that the Bishops of Uganda &amp; Mombasa are civilly condemned ("Not guilty, but don't do it again"), &amp; that the <persName xml:id="3469">Bishop of Zanzibar's</persName> theory of the church is confirmed'. If I write on the judgement publicly that will be the text: and it can hardly make me popular. It would appear that I am entering again into a phase of acute unpopularity.</hi><hi> I wrote to <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName> seeking information about the man <persName xml:id="3664">Hooper</persName> who is being pressed for Bossall. The worst thing against him is the strenuous support of the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName>! In the afternoon I walked with Logic. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went to Newcastle, &amp; fetched <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName>, whom I am to carry with me to London tomorrow. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> came in to see me, &amp; reported on the authority of his brother, who is serving in France, that the French soldiers were practicing as part of their regular drill the throwing of vitriol. This truly detestable device has been adopted by way of reprisals for the "dirty tricks" in which the Germans so freely indulge. It would appear that the fighting is assuming a most savage character on both sides, and practically no prisoners are taken. The worst traditions of the Thirty years war are prevailing without the mitigating excuse of religious fanaticism. The German atrocities in France &amp; Belgium have waked a spirit of vengeance which nothing can now restrain. We must expect some fearful proceedings when once the war has been carried into German territory.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
