<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I travelled to town with <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName> by the early express, arriving at King's Cross more than half an hour after time. Then I drove to the British Museum, &amp; deposited Kathleen with her relatives, &amp; went on to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>. Leaving my baggage with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Rush, I went to the Barber &amp; had my hair cut. The artist commented on its length and thickness!! From the Barber I walked to Rectory Chambers in Lambeth Hill, where <persName xml:id="18">Gerald Marshall</persName> has his dwelling. He went with me to Froarde's warehouse where we ordered a lectern copy of the Revised Version, which (at his request) I have presented to St Nicholas Cole Abbey. </hi><hi rend="italic">Then I went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; there dined. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Halifax was in the club. He expressed his agreement with me in that matter of Drink, &amp; told me that the Royal servants at Windsor had dressed the cellar door in crape</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> <hi rend="italic">I noticed that almost everybody dining at the Athenaeum was drinking wine. Clearly the King's example was not being taken very seriously. </hi><hi>On Wednesday the 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I met <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> at the Office of the Eccles</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi><hi> Commissioners, &amp; together we had an interview with Sir Lewis <persName xml:id="909">Dibdin</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4001">Downing</persName>, about the Bearpark litigation. I suggested the purchase of the land by the Commissioners, &amp; the idea was received with courtesy &amp; even with goodwill. We came away with the impression that a solution might be found in that direction.<note xml:id="277" n="1"></note> <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> was sitting. Divers members came into lunch with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>, including the <persName xml:id="44">Dean of Wells</persName> &amp; his wife, <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, <persName xml:id="3946">Newbolt</persName>, <persName xml:id="383">Spooner</persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="1816">Bp of Norwich</persName>. The last told me many significant stories about <persName xml:id="590">'iste archideaconus'</persName>. Later Pearce &amp; I went to Freemasons' Hall for the investiture of 'grand officers'. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I was duly invested as a Grand Chaplain</hi><hi>, &amp; subsequently dined with the Brethren. Lord S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="193">Aldwyn</persName>, <persName xml:id="3206">Victor Williamson</persName>, &amp; Col: <persName xml:id="838">Lockwood</persName> were all present, &amp; spoke.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Thursday the 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> April I returned to Durham by the morning express, arriving fairly to time. On my arrival at the Deanery I found that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2131">Harold Cox</persName> </hi><hi>was already on the scene. I took him over the Cathedral, and walked up up [sic] to the observatory for the view. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> came to dinner. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with some female friends to Darlington for a lecture on Serbia.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
