<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[327]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">375</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful morning but hot, &amp; probably destined to end in thunder. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My correspondence includes two more letters about my Abbey sermon, that is, about its reference to the 'Angels at Mons'. One was anonymous, but eminently typical of many others</hi><hi> which I have received during the last fortnight. It runs thus:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
        <p>
<hi>'We </hi><hi rend="underline">were</hi><hi> very greatly distressed to see in the papers that you had preached in the Abbey </hi><hi rend="underline">against</hi><hi> the appearance of the angels at Mons &#8211; just as people </hi><hi rend="underline">were</hi><hi> beginning to become a little more spiritual &amp; inclined to religion, and to a firmer </hi><hi rend="underline">belief</hi><hi> in God &amp; in His protecting Love. I, in common with thousands more believe </hi><hi rend="underline">most</hi><hi> firmly in the Vision &amp; intervention of those Angels there &#8211; A member of the English Church.'</hi>
        </p>
</div>
        <p>
<hi>This is clearly the production of a fairly educated person: and it is highly suggestive. Rather more urgent &amp; sentimental is another letter also anonymous, which I received on August 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. Internal evidence, &amp; a newspaper cutting of an anti&#8211;drink diatribe of <persName xml:id="109">Archdeacon Wilberforce</persName>, suggest that the writer is a vehement tee&#8211;totaller, and, if she had not subscribed her letter 'A daughter of the Church', it might reasonably have been conjectured that she was a sectary of some description or another. This epistle runs thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[329]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Rev. Sir, At this time of National anguish &amp; trial </hi><hi rend="italic underline">do you not fear to do your Master disservice</hi><hi rend="italic"> by merely posing as military and political critic or throwing a wet blanket of unbelief on any phase of faith or enthusiasm. If ever the command 'Comfort ye my people' was urgent, surely it is now. Surely the ministers of our Church should strive to give comfort on the battlefield &amp; help &amp; uplifting to the wretched victims of drink &amp; poverty &amp; filth in our slums. There is work there alone for all the Church of Christ. England cannot be called Christian till that work is done, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">there is power in Christ's name to do it</hi><hi rend="italic"> if His accredited, but too often slothful &amp; unbelieving servants, would begin the task in His strength. You have been preaching against 'Superstition' which after all must have some element of spirituality about it &amp; is better than stark materialism. If our dear lads who are giving their lives for England can visualize their Saviour &amp; His Angels come to help &amp; comfort them in that hell of carnage &#8211; the battlefields &amp; trenches of this fearful War &#8211; who shall be so cruel, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">cruel</hi><hi rend="italic">… as to tell them they are wrong? And they are </hi><hi rend="italic underline">not</hi><hi rend="italic"> wrong for where should the aid &amp; ministry of Heaven be found if not there? God works miracles of help &amp; salvation even in our days. "Art thou a master in Israel &amp; knowest not these things?" If you would go &amp; fight or work in the trenches God might open your eyes also.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I pray that he may.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours faithfully	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A daughter of the Church.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[331]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The general drift of the protesting letters is expressed in this brief note inserted in some little tracts, narrating the alleged angelic appearances:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Why "limit the Holy One of Israel"? "With God </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">all</hi><hi> things are possible".'</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
      
<hi>Another correspondent writes in the same key thus:&#8211;</hi>
            </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Thank God "The Angel of the Lord encampeth round about them that fear Him &amp; delivereth them." Elisha saw the company of angels &amp; chariots too. All things are possible with God.'</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Another concludes that scepticism as to the Angels at Mons can only proceed from an unconverted heart, &amp; encloses suitable tracts to effect the required conversion. One anonymous writer touches on the important point of evidence in this way:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>'A man writes to me:&#8211; "You ask if I have any first&#8211;hand evidence of a visible manifestation. Yes, I have from a close friend of mine, an officer who returned home wounded from the Front. I can only say that his simple conviction assured me beyond all question, of the reality, &amp; the visible proof, of an angelic intervention at a very critical moment. "2 Don't be too sure, Reverend Sir. You may sometimes be mistaken. The curtain which hides the other side is very thin. True that these things are only spiritually discerned. 'The secret of the Lord is with them that fear Him.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>If </hi><hi rend="underline">you</hi><hi> do not see these things &#8211; leave them alone &#8211; don't preach about them. Remember the breaking hearts…. The superstitions will take care of themselves.</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi>[The] Wife of a late official of the Gov</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi rend="bold">[333]</hi> <hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> W</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi> Ellis writes to me from Morpeth bewailing the general credulity:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"Two of my friends &amp; neighbours who are officials in the diocese lost their heads, &amp; preached on this angelic interposition: &amp; a nearer neighbour whom you know told me he thought it possible, &amp; I believe wants to think it possible. </hi><hi rend="underline">When the <persName xml:id="130">Archbishop of York</persName> is said to have referred to it, it is not to be wondered at that others should do the same</hi><hi>."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I took </hi><persName xml:id="1696"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive</hi></persName><hi> into the cathedral, &amp; shewed her the vaulting, &amp; the scaffolding in the Tower. Also, I attended Evensong; the Lesson was that dreadful passage in S. Matthew which has been called the Commination Service of the Gospel: &amp; the Anthem was a rendering of Christ's comfortable Words, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Come unto Me</hi><hi>". I shivered at the first: &amp; thanked Heaven for the last. After tea, I walked with </hi><persName xml:id="2803"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter</hi></persName><hi> round Houghall Wood. He gave me an account of his experiences in the Cameroons, where he has taken part in the conflict with the Germans. He says that the latter are very brutal in their treatment of the natives, but allow their native soldiers great licence. Their treacherous conduct makes relations with them difficult. He thought the Mohammedans of that part of Africa took but little interest in the fate of the Sultan of Turkey: a nearer potentate, the Sultan of Socoto [sic], is a British subject. The Spaniards had served as instruments for bringing in to Africa the lies by which the Germans attempted to influence foreign opinion. They were disposed to favour the Germans because, unlike the English, they tolerated the slave&#8211;trade. We received the official forms issued under the National Registration Act, and filled them up for Collection on Monday next.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
