<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">177</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather is mild and still: if nothing cataclysmic happens in the course of the day, it may still be considered favourable to the ecclesiastical functions of this Festival.</hi><hi><note xml:id="240" n="1"></note> </hi><hi rend="italic">Last year I recall that my friend <persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell's</persName> was here, and that he communicated in the Cathedral at the Choral Eucharist. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Now he is dead</hi><hi rend="italic">, leaving a considerable gap in the narrowing circle of my friends.</hi><hi> At 11 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion, &amp; read the Commemoration Form. The service was all that could be desired, but the attendance was very disappointing. All the canons were present save <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, who pleaded (but mistakenly) that he had lectures. Of the Hon. Canons there were but 6. Archdeacon <persName xml:id="3689">Derry</persName> came also. The Grammar School was represented by the Masters &amp; the King's Scholars, of whom however all did not communicate. The Choir&#8211;men communicated, &amp; both <persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>. Of others certainly not more than a dozen. I entertained the canons, minor canons, hon canons, &amp; others at lunch. The party numbered exactly thirty persons, which is as many as my table can comfortably accommodate. At the end of the meal there arrived </hi><hi rend="bold">[135] </hi><hi>a kindly expressed telegram from the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName>. After Evensong <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had a numerous tea&#8211;party. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3814">Benson</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3801">Lady Gort</persName>, &amp; the High Sherriff (<persName xml:id="1237">Priestman</persName>) were among the number present. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> arrived about 4 p.m</hi><hi>: &amp; somewhat later <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> &amp; Sir John <persName xml:id="2069">Barran</persName>. Col: <persName xml:id="1659">Burdon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2981">his wife</persName> &amp; 2 daughters came in for the service. The service went through without hitch, &amp; was very impressive. Four battalions sent representatives to take part in the procession. The addition of 24 officers in Khaki gave an unusual &amp; striking aspect to the long line of folk in surplices, to which also the bright hoods and gowns of the Academicks gave colour. The Mayor &amp; Corporation attended in state: &amp; the Chapter Workmen sate together beside the Grammar School. There was a large congregation, which would have been larger if the weather at the last moment had not changed for the worse.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
