<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[315]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">363</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 o'clock. But few communicants were present. At 10 a.m. I preached to a small congregation of soldiers, and at 11 a.m. I attended Mattins. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> preached from the words "A Hebrew of Hebrews" and began a course of sermons on <persName xml:id="4052">Montefiore's</persName> conception of St Paul. It was fairly interesting, but of course wholly unedifying. After Evensong <persName xml:id="3223">Gaisford</persName> and I walked through Houghall Wood. He gives a good account of the Chaplains at the front. The conduct of the war is evidently becoming dreadfully savage. No quarter seems to be given, for nothing less can be implied in the sinister statement that no prisoners are taken. No doubt the main responsibility rests with the Germans, whose methods of fighting are infamous, &amp; whose treachery is shameless. But some blame must needs rest on those who stimulate the resentments, which have been provoked, &amp; who never even attempt to bring from Christianity some measure of mitigating magnanimity. Gaisford is certainly a religious man, but his hatred of the Germans is extreme. He went off after dinner &amp; I wrote a series of letters.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
