<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">293</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The most beautiful summer's day conceivable. I celebrated before breakfast. Only <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> of the canons was there. The communicants numbered about 85. Then I preached to the soldiers at 10 a.m.: and again at the Choral Eucharist. Only </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName></hi><hi> was present of the canons: &amp;, as May is on holiday, and <persName xml:id="2800">Cully</persName> was at the organ, I myself read the Gospel from the Chancel step. There were but few communicants, but rather more non&#8211;com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi> stayed to the end. </hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> preached at Evensong from S. Paul's words, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Know ye not that your body is a temple of the Holy Ghost</hi><hi rend="italic">'. He connected the text with Confirmation, &amp; allowed himself in the now fashionable sneer at German criticism! Otherwise the sermon was well enough, &amp; as no ordinary English Churchgoer w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> dream of linking the notions of 'Confirmation' &amp; the indwelling of the Holy Ghost, the references thereto would pass harmlessly by! Yet it is certainly perplexing that a man of 55, who has necessarily seen a good deal of the working of the ecclesiastical system, sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> even pretend to himself that he believes in such a doctrine of Confirmation. Are the bodies of the unconfirmed Christian </hi><hi rend="italic underline">not</hi><hi rend="italic"> 'the temples of the Holy Ghost'? Just as Roman Catholics go on professing to believe in the Infallibility of the Pope in the teeth of experiences which demonstrate at every turn the falsehood of the dogma, so our Anglicans with the theoretical absurdities of our system! Divers officers including Col: <persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName> &amp; Major <persName xml:id="3817">Iremonger</persName>, came to tea, &amp; I shewed them over the Cathedral. Finally, after dinner, <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> appeared to see Hutton. </hi><hi>The Sunday Paper accounts of the Railway Accident record a very terrible catastrophe, probably the most destructive accident in the annals of British Railways. It is pathetic, indeed, that so many young men should be destroyed ignobly before drawing sword in the 'Holy War'. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
