<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[225]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">295</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The brilliant weather continues. <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> went off after breakfast. I worked at the "Magna Carta" lecture, &amp; then succumbed to the lure of the sunshine, &amp; sate in the garden. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards walked around Houghall Wood with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>. The flowers, foliage, &amp; singing birds are all at their best. Then I wrote a series of letters, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">including one to Lord <persName xml:id="3220">Stamfordham</persName> to condole with him on the loss of his only son, whose death is announced in the casualty list of today</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner, at 9.30 p.m., there was an emergency test of our fire&#8211;extinguishing arrangements. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Newby, the plumber, appeared in about 20 minutes after the first alarm: <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName>, our responsible man, emerged a little later: and, under their guidance, we hurried into the Cathedral, &amp; went through the process of getting out, linking up, and bringing to play the hose provided at certain danger&#8211;points. It was quite 40 minutes before anything effective had been achieved, and by that time, I should suppose, in the case of a fire the building would be in flames, &amp;, perhaps, lost. The Treasurer had provided coffee in his hall: and thither we all betook ourselves. It is to be noted that all the canons took part in this drill, save only the <persName xml:id="590">Sub&#8211;Dean</persName>, who had been most of all dogmatic on the subject in the Chapter!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A Fall of soot in my study made the room uninhabitable, and covered everything with a coating of black dirt, infinitely injurious. Thus my little plan for escaping the horrors of a 'spring&#8211;cleaning' by postponing it until my absence in June appears to have broken down: &amp; I am immersed in the filth and hustle of that annual abomination.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
