<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[391]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
         <hi rend="bold">408</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">There is a reference to women in the "Philobiblion" which is illuminating.</hi> <hi>Books complain that they are cast out from the houses of the clergy:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"For our places are seized now by dogs, now by hawks, now by </hi><hi rend="underline">that biped beast</hi><hi> whose co&#8211;habitation with the clergy was forbidden of old, from which we have always taught our nurselings to flee more than from the asp &amp; the cockatrice."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Imagine the attitude towards the female sex really implied in such language deliberately penned by the most cultivated English prelate of the age, or by his direction. Yet </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Richard de Bury,</hi><hi> as he moved about the Bishoprick, must constantly have seen little girls, as we see them, fair &amp; winning as angels: &amp; playing with the charming freedom of innocence with their brothers. He must have met many good women, from Queen Philippa downwards. Yet he could write brutally about 'that biped beast'! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It takes a good many cathedrals to compensate for so great an injury.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="251">Robertson</persName></hi><hi> &amp; I attended Evensong, &amp; then drove to Finchale where we viewed the ruins of the <placeName xml:id="64">Priory</placeName> in the level lights of a declining sun. I had some conversation with the Farmer's daughter, a nicely spoken, but rather delicate&#8211;looking woman. She said that they had the greatest difficulty in persuading any servant to live with them on account of the loneliness of the place: that there was fish, including trout &amp; salmon in the river: that a fox had recently killed 13 fowls, &amp; that no compensation had been paid. The vigourous&#8211;looking girls were her children. We drove back to Durham in the light of a wonderful sun&#8211;setting. After dinner we sate in my study, &amp; talked until bed&#8211;time, that is, Robertson talked, and I listened. He describes a rather serious financial situation caused by the War in Oxford.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
