<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[421]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">426</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m., and there received the Sacrament. <persName xml:id="800">Westlake</persName> celebrated, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; <persName xml:id="3788">Gordon</persName> assisted</hi><hi rend="italic">. The congregation consisted of a score of women &amp; four young men. I did not recognize so much as one. The Church continues unaltered in its grave beauty. At Mattins there was a large congregation, among which I observed many familiar faces. The service was well rendered. In the choir there is improvement. <persName xml:id="121">Goss&#8211;Custard's</persName> departure has justified itself here. <persName xml:id="344">Craik</persName> read the first lesson, &amp; <persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie</persName> the second. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Authorized Version has thrust out the Revised. This change is regrettable on many grounds. Also, the reference to the <orgName xml:id="100" display="no">Church of Scotland</orgName> has been cut out of the Bidding prayer</hi><hi rend="italic">. I preached<ref xml:id="900"></ref> for half an hour, &amp; was listened to with close attention, though the sermon was rather heavy. The subject &#8211; 'National Christianity' &#8211; hardly leant itself to emotion or rhetoric. Outside the Church was a collection of old choirboys, &amp; others including Sir Charles <persName xml:id="230">Renshaw</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2678">Lady Limerick</persName>. <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName> in khaki, and <persName xml:id="2463" display="no">Nimbus</persName> took me for a little walk on the Embankment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[423]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We lunched with the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>. Sir Henry was very severe on the decrepitude &amp; incompetence of the present chapter of Westminster. He is excessive &amp; unjust, but there is a modicum of justification for his indictment. Carnegie was insistent on the same subject. After lunch we walked to the British Museum, &amp; had tea with <persName xml:id="1170">Arthur Smith</persName> &amp; his wife. They took us into the Museum, &amp; shewed us the Elgin Marbles swathed in or rather built in by sand bags. We returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, picked up my robes, &amp; drove to the Deanery of S. Paul's. Finding <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">his wife</persName> absent, we walked to the Rectory in King Edward Street, and called on the newly&#8211;married <persName xml:id="122">Hine&#8211;Haycock</persName>, who has not yet realized the extent of the bondage into which he has brought himself. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then we walked to <persName xml:id="18">Gerald's</persName> lodgings, &amp; so went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Nicholas Cole Abbey, where I preached to a congregation which (in spite of the darkness into which the Zeppelins have plunged London) filled the little church</hi><hi>. Gerald was vested in a brilliant cope, &amp; was preceded by some tall youths (who ought to have been in khaki) as he processioned round the church. Otherwise the service was hearty &amp; reverent. We got back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> for supper. </hi><hi rend="italic">R. J. <persName xml:id="392">Campbell</persName> of the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName> had been invited to meet me. I asked him whether it was indeed the case that he intended to take Orders in the Church of England, &amp; he replied in the affirmative. "I hope you will not join the sacerdotalists" was my comment, &amp; he looked significantly sheepish. Subsequently, he explained to me that 'he was to be received by the <persName xml:id="49">Bishop of Oxford</persName> as an old friend'! The true</hi> <hi rend="bold">[425] </hi><hi rend="italic">direction of his mind was perhaps disclosed by his observation that he thought Prayer book Revision would have a better chance of success if the Bishops conceded exposition of the Sacrament!! His experiences at the Front have made him wondrously tender to the Roman system. I can have no doubt as to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">his</hi><hi rend="italic"> ecclesiastical destination. After his departure, <persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie</persName> started to talk again, &amp; held on in spite of my fatigue with amazing vigour. His egotism, confusion, &amp; pertinacity are equally wonderful!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
