<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[549]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">507</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2021">Frere</persName> went off to Edinburgh after lunch. I shewed him the treasures which we have put away for fear of the enemy. He had never seen them before, and was delighted with them. It was pretty to see the dainty reserve with which he handled the venerable objects: the scholar's sympathy blending with the ascetic's veneration! There is nothing which so reveals the mind &amp; habit of a man as his manner of handling a book. I walked with Logic, and again I lost him somewhere in the neighbourhood of <persName xml:id="3438">Rogerson's</persName> kennels, where, I suspect, he has formed attachments. However, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> picked him up in the town later. <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> made his appearance. He is home for a few days. This may be his last leave, for he has volunteered for service in the Balkans. The War will have widened </hi><hi rend="underline">his</hi><hi> universe, &amp; (if he has the potency of moral and mental growth) increased his stature. The post brought me a cheery letter from <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, who will not get home for Christmas. He too is becoming a man, 'finding himself' in the great catastrophe. The process of re&#8211;making men proceeds in so many instances that it is scarcely an exaggeration to say that the nation itself is 'born again'.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
