<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[539] </hi>
 </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">502</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at the meeting of Chapter. We voted &#x00A3;10 to <persName xml:id="2950">Turner's</persName> project of a Dictionary of Patristic Greek. I listed to the Organ Recital in the Cathedral, sitting alone at the very end of the nave. There was a considerable assembly of people. Here I picked up two young soldiers, &amp; took them round so much of the Cathedral as could be 	seen in the brief interval between the Organ Recital and Evensong. They belonged to the 16</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> (S.) B</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> Highland Light Infantry, and came from Glasgow. The one had assisted his father in a draper's shop; the other had been an elementary school teacher. Both were now officers. They gave me their names: the first was J. R. C. Philips, the last Thomas Neilson. I showed them the Library, &amp; the Deanery. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived in time to give them tea. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> came to see me about School matters: then <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> arrived, &amp; kept me at talk until dinner time. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He shewed me a very interesting letter which he had just received from <persName xml:id="1083">Loisy</persName>. It dealt trenchantly with the attitude of Benedict XV. I asked what manner of man to look at was this M. Loisy: &amp; he said that before he grew his beard, Loisy bore a curious facial resemblance to the Holbein portrait of Erasmus. His cold detached manner, however, went along with a heart capable of profound emotions; he had to the full the French love of humanity</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi>We spoke of the recent meeting of the <orgName xml:id="38">Churchmen's Union</orgName>. He said that there were evident signs of a disposition to capture that association for the "Catholic" party: that the President, <persName xml:id="402">Percy Gardner</persName>, inclined this way: and that this explained the suggestive acquiescence which the Union had exhibited towards the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> most unhappy pronouncement on <ref xml:id="849">'Kikuyu'</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
