<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[485]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">465</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The strong winds of the last two days have brought down nearly all the leaves, &amp; reduced the country to a winter&#8211;like nakedness: but the sky was blue, &amp; the sun bright, so that some incorrigibly optimistic birds were moved to essay some modest singing. I walked with <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> through Houghall Wood, enjoying both his conversation and the views of the Cathedral. I revised and extended the Cambridge Sermon. After dinner I wrote </hi><hi rend="italic">letters, &amp; then read <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes's</persName> article aloud to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. He lays it down as 'matter of certainty </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">"that one of the results of the war will be a notable weakening of and falling away from the Roman Catholic Church</hi><hi rend="italic">'. He bases this expectation on the offence taken in France &amp; Belgium especially at the Pope's neutrality. But I think he doesn't allow enough for the crude emotionalism wakened by the fearful experiences of the War, &amp; the wave of superstition which will sweep over Europe in the wake of so much misery &amp; suffering. Probably the more distant consequences of the War will be unfavourable to organized Christianity, but the immediate effects will give new strength to the Churches, &amp; especially to the least&#8211;rationalist of them. </hi><hi>The newspapers report another dreadful outrage &#8211; the torpedoeing of an Italian liner by an Austrian or German submarine. Among the victims are said to be a number of Americans. This circumstance can hardly fail to renew the </hi><hi rend="italic">sentiments of repugnance which were so loudly expressed when the 'Lusitania' was destroyed: but beyond explosions of indignation in the newspapers it is hardly probable that anything will happen. The Americans give a positive value to moral protests forcibly expressed. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">They think they shall be heard for their much speaking</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi><hi><note xml:id="294" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> But they acknowledge no practical obligations as implicit in their speech.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
