<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[507]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915. </hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">482</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached to the troops at 10 a.m. taking as my text S. Paul's words in 1. Cor: III.13, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Every man's work shall be made manifest: for the Day shall declare it</hi><hi>". The men were fairly attentive though, of course, there were some bad coughs. I did not attend Mattins, but came in to the Cathedral afterwards, celebrated the Holy Communion. Four of the King's Scholars (viz. Macdonald, Kirby, Fenwick, &amp; Ellis) came to lunch, &amp; stayed till it was time to go to Evensong. There was a surprisingly small congregation to listen to the <persName xml:id="4088">Bishop</persName>. Had not the School been present, the Cathedral would have appeared almost empty. There is something perplexing in this, which I hardly understand. Partly, perhaps, there is to be reckoned with a circumstance which I certainly observed in Westminster, where the congregation of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret's, like the cathedral congregation here, was drawn from all quarters, i.e. in plain terms was composed of deserters from various parish churches. The congregations were always smallest in Advent &amp; Lent, probably because the parish churches were then more than commonly attractive since 'special' preachers often replaced the incumbents! I suspect that parochial pressure is at its strongest at these seasons, &amp; since the parishioners are pledged to attend Evensong in the parish church at 6.30 p.m. they have no mind to go to Evensong in the Cathedral at 3.30 p.m. The Bishop had not prepared his sermon. Indeed he asked me what he had best 'talk about' a few minutes before going to the Cathedral! He has a pleasant voice, &amp; talks with much fluency. His manner and intonation are almost comically suggestive of his chief, the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>: the substance of his address was mostly stories about the soldiers at the front, who appear to me very godly &amp; edifying people!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[509]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We motored to Stockton, where I was pledged to preach in the parish church. But we had to stop on the way and put the chain on the tyre, as the wheel 'skidded' on the frozen show, which was lying on the high ground beyond Coxhoe. So we arrived during the Creed. I preached with some discomfort on account of the organist's coughing! We had supper with <persName xml:id="3856">Canon Martin</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4091">his wife</persName>, &amp; heard many blood&#8211;curdling stories about drunkards!! Then we motored home, and arrived in the Deanery about 10.45 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
