<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[543] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">504</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked with <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> before lunch, &amp; had much talk with him. He says that the Chapter at Hereford is not favourably regarded by the clergy of the diocese: that they actively dislike <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3618">Lillie</persName> [Lilley], practically ignore <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>, &amp; regard <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName> with a mild hostility! The saying passes on men's lips in Hereford: "We respect the Bishop, but don't like him. We like the Dean, but don't respect him". An ill proverb! We spoke of 'Fasting Communion', &amp; Fawkes said that he had noticed in the course of his life as a Roman priest that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the rigid rule of fasting before Mass bore directly on the too&#8211;frequent vice of drunkenness</hi><hi>. Priests, feeling faint from want of food, had recourse to whiskey as a 'pick&#8211;me&#8211;up': &amp; so by degrees fell into the habit of excess. It is not surprising. Nature has a habit of asserting itself in surprising ways against the violences done to it in the name of Religion. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> dined with us. He was fresh from the Ordination at Bishop Auckland yesterday. Some of the candidates, in spite of his express admonitions, had insisted on fasting until the whole long service had been completed. Surely this was a proceeding as little reasonable in itself, as edifying in its effects. These men had been trained at Kelham. Eight deacons were ordained, and there was only one of them who had a degree! '</hi><hi rend="underline">Clerus Anglicanus stupor mundi</hi><hi>!' [The Anglican clergy are the stupid of the world.] I gather from Fawkes that the social quality of the Roman priests is generally very low; &amp; the intellectual standard often contemptible. The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3448">his wife</persName> also came to dinner: I sent copies of my <ref xml:id="84">"War&#8211;time Sermons"</ref> to the Bp. of Jarrow &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
