<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[453]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">443</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Thirteen years have slipped away since <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I exchanged vows before the high altar of Westminster. It is something that we should still be willing to recall the event, &amp; desire to stand together in a world which grows more cheerless &amp; difficult as the years pass. I spent the day mostly in reading Balfour's <ref xml:id="855">Gifford Lectures</ref>. They are brilliantly written, &amp; extremely interesting. I went to Evensong, &amp; afterwards (as the rain made walking out of doors unattractive) took a constitutional with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in the great Library. Then I wrote a long letter to <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>. After an early dinner we attended a lecture in the Mayor's chamber organized by the <orgName xml:id="247" display="no">Citizen's League</orgName> with the object of promoting thrift. The lecturer was Professor <persName xml:id="3304">Hallsworth</persName> of Newcastle, &amp; there was but a scanty attendance. There was a discussion afterwards in which I took some part. <persName xml:id="3455">Jevons</persName> made an old fanatical speech in which he denounced the rich, and spoke with extraordinary vehemence on the duty of dismissing servants &amp;c.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
