<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[481]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">462</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Teach me to know mine end, and the number of my years that I may be certified how long I have to live".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="290">Charles</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="950">Dorothy</persName> went off at 8.20 a.m. They had time to wish me 'many happy returns of the day' before leaving: &amp; they embodied their goodwill in a Birthday gift of some charming cut glass. The morning post brought me affectionate letters from the ladies at Birchington, and <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>. Also I received a Birthday card from 'A storm&#8211;tossed Woman, one greatly uplifted by your beautiful sermons of 1906.' Probably, Anonyma is also weak&#8211;witted! <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> sent me a kind little note. By the midday post came a letter from <persName xml:id="22">W. P.</persName>; and a card from <persName xml:id="807">Helen Beeching</persName>. Also an anonymous post card from 'one of your old hearers at <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, who regrets your absence every Sunday'! She (I assume that to be the sex of my friend) adds a quotation from Mark Twain: "Praise is well, blame is well; but affection is the final &amp; most precious reward that any man can win". <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to Newcastle to see the dentist: so that I lunched alone. After lunch I started for a walk with Logic, but was sent back by the rain. Then I attended Evensong. The senior choirboy came and thanked me for the cakes &amp; sixpences. After dinner I wrote a number of letters, &amp; then read <persName xml:id="1083">Loisy's</persName> brochure to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> until bed&#8211;time. What a day&#8211;full of infinite fatuity! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> sent me a letter of Birthday congratulations, and exhorted me with the authority of a well&#8211;preserved veteran of 95 1/2, not to over&#8211;work myself. How little he knows me!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
