<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[439]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">435</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather is brilliantly fine, and almost oppressively warm. We called on <persName xml:id="1381">Canon Moore</persName>, &amp; were shown his house. It is on a grand scale, &amp; remarkably interesting. Many of its best features were obscured under the rather squalid regime of old Rawlinson, his predecessor: but he had spent much money, &amp; made many improvements. Then we went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Augustine's<placeName xml:id="69"></placeName>, &amp; were shewn the recently–discovered graves of the first Archbishops, &amp; the extensive foundations of the earliest churches which preceded the Norman church. What an impression of power &amp; majesty is made on the mind by the spectacle of these vast relics of two great Monasteries side by side in one little city, which contained besides many parish churches &amp; other religious foundations! M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Pott, the Sub–warden, acted as our guide, &amp; shewed himself equally well–informed &amp; interesting. After lunch we motored to Sandwich, &amp; viewed that ancient &amp; decayed city. The Town Hall, an Elizabethan building, is notable. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It appears that the Mayors of Sandwich alone in England wear black official robes, &amp; carry as their symbol of office a black–thorn stick. We were shewn a thumb–pressing machine formerly employed in the examination of reluctant witnesses</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi>We visited two parish churches. Then we went on to Deal Castle, but found the Hamiltons absent. However we were shewn over it. We had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Molins, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">then started for the return journey to Canterbury via Dover</hi><hi>. We were held up by the soldiers, &amp; only allowed to go through Dover on condition that we reported ourselves at the Police Station, &amp; got a permit! Such incidents serve to bring home to the mind the fact of War.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
