<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[425]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">427</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I paid my too&#8211;long deferred visit to the Barber, and returned the lighter&#8211;headed for my visit! Then I lunched with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>. <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> I saw in the school&#8211;yard: and had some talk with. He seems melancholy &amp; discontented. Then I joined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, recovered my bags, &amp; so went off to Birchington, arriving about 5 p.m. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Globe" had a hostile paragraph, attacking the Dean of Durham for observing that 'there was too much talk about "reprisals" which hardly had a Christian sound.' It is a curious indication of the state of mind which war induces that so obvious an opinion should strike men as unreasonable. I fear that the critics of Christianity have but too good reason for their bitter comment that, however lofty its theory, its practice accords severely with the humble convention which non&#8211;Christian society accepts. To love one's friends &amp; hate one's enemies is the principle on which the world, as we know it, does on the whole proceed: &amp; it were difficult to show that any different principle is actually shaping the action of Christian men. Yet, if anything be certain, it is that the Founder of Christianity definitely &amp; explicitly disallowed that principle for His disciples</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
