<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[545]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">505</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me the following post&#8211;card written in an educated hand, and bearing the post&#8211;mark, 'East Grinstead':&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName> in "Speculum Animae", page 24, describes your career in the following words. "The world belongs to those who think and act with it, who keep a finger on its pulse." "The way to be successful is to give the public exactly what it wants, and about ten per cent more of it than it expects."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The writer piously adds the date '4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Sunday in Advent'. By the same post it so happened that there came a letter from Inge, in the course of which he observes: </hi><hi rend="italic">"I liked your war sermons immensely, and hope they will be widely read."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="909">Sir Lewis Dibdin</persName> respecting the prompter payment of sums due to the Chapter from the Fabric fund: and to the Vicar of Bossall respecting his project for selling the glebe. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> came to see me, and stayed to lunch in order to see <persName xml:id="2021">Frere</persName>, who has come here to study MSS. in our library. I have given him a room to work in. It is not inappropriate that the secularized Prior's chapel should shelter the labours of an Anglican medievalist.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> went off after breakfast. I walked with Logic: &amp; attended Evensong. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3518">Hodgson Fowler</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> with his wife came in to dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The evening post brought me a long letter from <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>. He expresses himself warmly in commendation of the sermons, &amp; then branches out into a discussion of the qar</hi><hi>. His sentiments are vehemently anti&#8211;German. Nothing will satisfy him but the complete defeat of Germany, &amp; the punishment of the Kaiser. But this goes beyond anything that can reasonably be accounted practicable.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
