<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[479]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">461</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, and afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion. Then we all walked in the Banks, admiring the autumn colours &amp; the clear&#8211;cut reflections in the water. After lunch I shewed the Library to my guests, &amp; handed them over to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> for the Cathedral. Two old choirboys &#8211; Geoffrey <persName xml:id="3875">Heseltine</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3999">Charles Abbey</persName> &#8211; came to see me, &amp; I offered to take the former home to Newcastle in the car, securing thus a serviceable guide through the streets for my little chauffeur. After attending Evensong, when Wesley's 'Wilderness' was very well sung, I motored with Geoffrey to Newcastle. We arrived at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Thomas's church after service had begun. I preached the rough draft of the sermon which I have been preparing for Cambridge, &amp; I think it was rather 'over the heads' of the congregation. Probably not half a dozen persons had so much as heard of M. <persName xml:id="1083">Loisy's</persName> name, and their knowledge of his opinions was as slight as their interest in them! Accordingly, they were rather puzzled than assisted by the critical examination of his opinion about the incompatibility of Patriotism and Christianity. There were a good many officers in the congregation, &amp; they seemed to be listening hard, with a look of perplexity on their faces! The faithful Geoffrey reclaimed me after the service, &amp; guided my chauffeur to the bridge&#8211;head, from which the road back to Durham is direct. We motored back without disaster, but at a slow pace, and arrived at the Deanery about 9.30 p.m. <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> had called, and made himself very agreeable to my guests: also <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; his niece, who being Devonshire folks had much in common with <persName xml:id="290">Charles</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="950">Dorothy</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
