<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[461]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">448</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="31">Cecil</persName></hi><hi> went off after breakfast. He asked me when I would again come to Hatfield, &amp; I promised that I would do so on the first suitable opportunity. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName></hi><hi> walked with me to the barber, where I was shampooed. The man expatiated on the Dean's popularity. "He's just worshipped in Manchester: every rough boy in the place knows him, &amp; touches his hat". This is very creditable to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon's</hi><hi> character, &amp; must indicate some genuine goodness of heart. With cleansed head I walked into Manchester, made inquiries about my train, &amp; so returned to the Deanery. I called on the way at the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester's</persName> house, &amp; found that his Lordship was in London. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><hi> &amp; I lunched together, &amp; then went to the <orgName xml:id="38">'Churchmen's Union'</orgName> meeting. Just before we left the house, the sky was spanned by the loveliest of rainbows. The room, not a large one, was fairly filled. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="401">Sir Edward Russell</persName></hi><hi> presided. I addressed the meeting for 35 minutes on "Some probable effects of the War within the sphere of English Christianity", speaking from fairly copious notes. There was no discussion, only a vote of thanks. The whole business was over in an hour. Welldon took me to the Club in order to while away the interval before my train started. Here I found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="389">Lord Bryce</persName></hi><hi>, busily engaged in preparing a speech for the public meeting in aid of the Armenians which had been arranged for tonight. We had a brief conversation, from which I gathered that he takes rather a gloomy view of the situation in the Balkans, and thinks that our affairs in that quarter have been mishandled. I left Manchester at 6.40 p.m. and travelled to Durham changing at Leeds and York. I arrived in the Deanery about 11 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
