<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[529]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">497</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> returned to London by the early train: and I betook myself again to Parker's Correspondence. I was interested to find in a letter of 1572 a reference to the Durham Statutes, which rather suggests that the lost original statutes were then at Lambeth. They may, of course, have been lost or destroyed in the 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century. The nervousness of the Elizabethan bishops, &amp; their consciousness of the ill&#8211;will with which the people regarded them, could hardly be better illustrated than by Bishop <persName xml:id="4093">Parkhurst's</persName> objection to Parker's proposal that he should have <persName xml:id="3616">Jewell's</persName> "Defence of the Apology" set up in the parish churches. He feared that the people would prefer the quotations from <persName xml:id="3617">Harding</persName> to the text of Jewell, &amp; thus would be confirmed in their errors! Parker's expression "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Queen's Religion stabilized by law &amp; Injunction</hi><hi>" gives the point of view of the Elizabethan Englishman. The salient fact was the Royal Will. This explains the amazing facility with which the Nation accommodated itself to the quick &amp; violent changes of English Religion.<note xml:id="337" n="1"></note> At a later stage, Puritans &amp; Jesuits developed an individual conscience on the subject, &amp; then the Government found itself committed to the necessity of suppressing minorities, which 'moved the previous question' when the Queen's Authority was pressed on them as a final argument for their conformity to the official system. But in the early years of Elizabeth's reign this development was only beginning to show itself.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
