<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[515]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">489</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached at the military service to a considerable company of soldiers. My text was “</hi><hi rend="underline">The sword of the Spirit which is the Word of God</hi><hi>”, and my subject the Bible. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName></hi><hi> preached at Mattins, a sermon which was not only extremely interesting, but also spiritually helpful. Both he and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName></hi><hi>, who was the preacher at Evensong, took 'Hope' for their theme. I celebrated at midday: &amp; attended Evensong. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dolphin</hi><hi>, the late British consul at Li&#x00E9;ge, came to lunch with his wife. He told us much that was interesting about the defence of Li&#x00E9;ge, &amp; the behaviour of the Germans; against whom he expresses himself with considerable vigour. I shewed them the House, &amp; the Library. I asked </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dolphin</hi><hi> whether the Belgians generally, after their terrible experiences of German Power &amp; barbarity, were still confident that their government had acted rightly in standing out for Belgian independence. He replied that they were, &amp; that they would rise against the Germans on the first opportunity. In Li&#x00E9;ge, especially, where the manufacture of small arms was the staple employment, everybody was armed, &amp; there might easily be a modern 'Sicilian Vespers'. He said that there were numerous Germans resident in Belgium, &amp; that these were active spies. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Compston</hi><hi> accompanied me to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Cuthbert's where I preached to a small congregation (the church was not much more than half filled), repeating a sermon which I have used on both sides of the Atlantic on 'The Broadness of the Divine Law'. "</hi><hi rend="underline">I see that all things come to an end but Thy Commandment is exceeding broad</hi><hi>". This is said to have been Dean </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="505">Stanley's</persName></hi><hi> favourite text. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Compston</hi><hi> 'discoursed sweet music' from the piano after dinner: &amp; we had much talk before going to bed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
