<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[451]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">442</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brings an offensive anonymous post&#8211;card, evidently from some 'shop&#8211;boy ritualist'. It is regrettable that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi><persName xml:id="372">Kenna</persName> has yielded to popular clamour, &amp; given up his excellent purpose of abolishing the half&#8211;penny post. I wrote to Archbishop <persName xml:id="2166">S&#x00F6;derblom</persName> &amp; sent him six copies of the <ref xml:id="376">"Lee"</ref> lecture; also to James <persName xml:id="412">Parker&#8211;Smith</persName> returning <persName xml:id="603">Wilmot's</persName> letters; and to <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName>. I attended Evensong, &amp; walked with Logic. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1864">Balfour Wilson</persName>, who is for the nonce school&#8211;mastering at Broadstairs.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined with <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName>, we two alone very pleasantly and had much talk. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">He told me the true legend about the burning of his father's papers &amp;c, of which the false legend was told me by <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> (v.p. 405). He rescued from the bon&#8211;fire some leaves of a Sarum missal of great rarity. The other contents of the boxes which were so absurdly destroyed, not by a dispute between the old man's sons but by a strange agreement between them, are unknown! </hi><hi rend="italic">We had some talk about religion, in which M&#8211;F takes up a purely medieval attitude. What the Church orders or does must not be criticized or resented! I told him that was well enough until the private conscience was really offended, &amp; then it broke down at once. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">We must obey God rather than men</hi><hi rend="italic">" was the first public declaration of Christianity &amp; the most characteristic. He is a very strange man, &amp; makes his conversation a shrouding veil for his thoughts more successfully than most men whom I know. There can be no doubt of his unusual ability, and of the manifoldness of his interests, and (I am disposed also to think) of the depth of his religious conviction. Though the last is generally concealed by a sardonic humour. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
