<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[553]</hi>
 </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, Saturday, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
     </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">509</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral for Mattins at 7.45 a.m: and celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There was a fair number of communicants. At 10 a.m. there was the Military Service, at which carols were substituted for the canticles and the sermon. A good many soldiers were present, &amp; seemed interested in the proceedings. The Choral Eucharist followed at 11 a.m. I preached from the words: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Let the peace of Christ rule in your hearts</hi><hi>". The congregation was disappointingly small, but the music was devotional, and the atmosphere worshipful. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> was the Celebrant. After service <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I visited the little Red&#8211;Cross Hospital, and gave Christmas greetings to the wounded soldiers. After lunch, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi> and I walked for an hour: and then came Evensong, to which a considerable congregation assembled. We began with a procession round the Church &amp; Nine Altars. The Choir sang admirably. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName></hi><hi> and his wife came in to tea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The extreme mildness of the weather, and the sunshine more suggestive of May than of December, made all things agreeable. The Post brought very kind letters from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName></hi><hi> and Colonel </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3991">Grimshaw</persName></hi><hi>. Also </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey <persName xml:id="3875">Heselton</persName></hi><hi> sent me his photograph, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3128">Arthur</persName></hi><hi> sent me a post&#8211;card from India. There was no newspaper to disturb us with false tidings and false comments on them! After dinner I read Milton's "</hi><hi rend="underline">Ode on the Nativity</hi><hi>" aloud to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName></hi><hi> called to see me, &amp; stayed for an hour. He is very discontented with the Government, and would like to make a 'clean sweep' of Ministers. He thinks that <persName xml:id="2884">Lord Derby</persName> might be a possible substitute for <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>. Rather to my surprise, he spoke darkly of possible developments in the German navy during this long sojourn in their home waters.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
