<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[475]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">458</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me from <persName xml:id="3874">Watson</persName> a presentation copy of his <ref xml:id="794">"Life of Bishop John <persName xml:id="1554">Wordsworth</persName>"</ref>. I read half through the volume, and found it unusually interesting. What an extraordinary amalgam of surprising combinations, moral &amp; intellectual, that erudite bishop was! He certainly carried into the grave three&#8211;fourths of the learning which had lingered on the Episcopal Bench. The 'Times' wired to me, that is, the Literary editor did so, asking me to review <persName xml:id="1083">Loisy's</persName> <ref xml:id="853">"The War &amp; Religion"</ref>, which Arthur <persName xml:id="336">Galton</persName> has translated. This I consented to do, and duly received a copy of the brochure. It is extremely good reading: its satire on Benedict XV's attitude is inimitable: but I observe with distress that the ex&#8211;leader of French Modernism adopts a confessedly non&#8211;Christian attitude. His little book suggested to me a subject for my Cambridge sermon. I propose to examine the incompatibility of genuine Christianity with patriotism which M. Loisy affirms. Of course, he adopts the convenient controversial device of identifying essential Christianity with "the programme of the Sermon on the Mount". <persName xml:id="950">Dorothy Parker</persName> arrived shortly after lunch, and I took her for a short walk. The weather was showery, but we had some interludes of sunshine.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
