<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[511]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">485</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The new Bishop of Newcastle (<persName xml:id="1980">Wild</persName>) was consecrated yesterday</hi><hi> in York Minster. <persName xml:id="427">Inge</persName> preached the sermon, which is reported at some length in the Newcastle paper. It was, indeed, a notable pronouncement. He spoke of "the strain upon that marvellously dexterous Elizabethan settlement which fixed the constitution &amp; character of the Church of England when separated from Rome". He described the settlement thus:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The object of that settlement was to include all Catholics who would renounce the Pope, and all Protestants who were not anarchical of principle, &amp; it was wonderfully successful: but it will require all the statesmanship of our rulers to avert disruption in the 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Is this a true description? I incline to think it gravely inadequate. About the pope there was not much difficulty: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the Mass was the crux</hi><hi>. The Henrician tradition, which Elizabeth professed to recover, had abolished the first, and jealously guarded the last. The 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Prayer&#8211;book of Edward VI was an essentially Protestant book, and the petty changes made by Elizabeth's Act did not really affect its character.<note xml:id="310" n="1"></note> <persName xml:id="3780">Whitgift's</persName> language goes far beyond the eloquent Dean's:&#8211; </hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I pray God make me thankful for the queen's majesty, who hath not been slack in this point, but hath, like a virtuous, religious, &amp; godly prince, in the very entering into her reign, notwithstanding the multitude of her adversaries, both at home &amp; abroad, abolished all superstition, and restored the simplicity of the gospel". [v. Works. vol. I. p. 263. P.S.]</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Every parish church in the kingdom proclaimed that 'simplicity' by its wrecked altars &amp; broken windows!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[513]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There is not much of the 'via media' about Whitgift's declaration with respect to the papists. "I place them among wicked &amp; damnable idolaters". The question is, how far did Whitgift express the true mind of the Elizabethan Reformers, &amp; exhibit the spirit of the Settlement? </hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi>We went to Bishop Auckland, in order to dine with the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName>.</hi>
        </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
