<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[445]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">437</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning papers report a serious Zeppelin raid on London last night, in the course of which eight people were killed, &amp; more than 30 injured. I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, where I wrote a short preface to the Huguenot sermon, &amp; took it &amp; the sermon to Hugh Rees for printing. On returning to the club I found Sir Courtenay <persName xml:id="645">Ilbert</persName> there. He says the Members ran out on to the Terrace as soon as the Zeppelins were reported, &amp; had a fine view of them. Also I fell in with <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName>, &amp; walked with him for half an hour. He is evidently wearying of his London work, &amp; covets a Deanery. I lunched with <persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName> at the <orgName xml:id="44">Reform Club</orgName>. Here I found several acquaintances, &amp; among them <persName xml:id="3345">Moon</persName>, who had returned from Serbia, where he has been ill of typhus. He told me that he had been in Greece, when <persName xml:id="3787">Venizelos</persName> resigned the first time, &amp; that it was an error to suppose that King Constantine was mainly swayed by political considerations. He flatters himself on his ability as a strategist, &amp; disapproved the strategy of the Dardanelles expedition. He refused to allow the Greek army to be committed to it. Most people would now admit that his Majesty had considerable justification for this view. I met <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName>, who was much annoyed at having had his pocket&#8211;book stolen while he stood in the crowd looking at the wreckage caused by the Zeppelin near the Lyceum theatre. Then I turned in to the National Portrait Gallery, where the attendant told me that more than 100 of the best pictures had been removed to the cellars. Then I returned to the Club, &amp; had tea. After reading for an hour, I walked back to Elvaston Place.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[447]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There came to dinner M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice <persName xml:id="4071">Younger</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4068">Andrew Lang</persName>, the <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, the <persName xml:id="290">Charlie Parkers</persName><persName xml:id="950"></persName>, and the <persName xml:id="2244">Struthers</persName><persName xml:id="2708"></persName>. Younger told me that the painted widows in Lincoln's Inn Chapel had been completely destroyed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
