<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[557]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">511</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName></hi><hi> sent me a few days since the remarkable inscription which he quoted in his sermon. It refers to the Birth of Augustus:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"This day has given the earth an entirely new aspect. The world would have gone to destruction, had there not streamed forth from him who is now born a common blessing. Rightly does he judge who recognizes in this birthday the beginning of life and of all the powers of life. The providence which rules over all has filled this man with such gifts for the salvation of the world as designates him as the Saviour for us &amp; for the forthcoming generations. Of wars shall he make an end, and establish all things worthily. By his appearance are the hopes of our forefathers fulfilled. It is impossible that one greater than he can ever appear. The birthday of God has brought to the world glad tidings that are bound up in him. From his birthday a new era begins."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowling</hi><hi> adds: "Date B.C. 9: found I think at Triene, in what is called the Calendar Inscription". He told me yesterday that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Deismann</hi><hi> accepted it as genuine. This inscription seems to disclose something more than an extravagant adulation; there is a poignant consciousness of the world's misery, and an eager welcome of rescue. But what a tragically inadequate response could the cold selfishness of Augustus make to such sentiments! The anthem of the Angels over Bethlehem announced another kind of Saviour, and brought a higher conception of happiness to men. The new era is Christian not Augustan.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[559]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3566"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Foakes&#8211;Jackson</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to say that the first edition of <ref xml:id="877">"The Faith and the War"</ref> is exhausted, and that Macmillan calls for a second. This is satisfactory, and suggestive. There appears to be still a market for these composite volumes, which offer to the public the opinions of many authors. It is a development of the 'snippet literature' tendency which has revolutionized journalism, since compulsory education created a vast class of illiterate &amp; mentally untrained readers. There is little interest in processes &amp; premises, only concern for results!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> sent me as a Christmas gift an edition of Hutchinson's <ref xml:id="797">History of Durham</ref> in 3 volumes. It brings the record a generation later than the edition which I already possess.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
