<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[477]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1915.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">460</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a brief and peaceful Chapter&#8211;meeting at 11 a.m.: and then, tempted by the sun, walked round Houghall Wood with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi>. The autumnal colouring is superb. Later I shewed <persName xml:id="950">Dorothy</persName> the Library: attended Evensong: and wrote letters. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="290">Charles Parker</persName></hi><hi> arrived from London. He asked me in the course of conversation what I thought of the alleged apparitions of angels during the retreat from Mons, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">seemed a shade disappointed when I acknowledged a brutal disbelief</hi><hi rend="italic">. After he had gone to bed I finished <persName xml:id="3874">Watson's</persName> Life of Bishop John <persName xml:id="1554">Wordsworth</persName><ref xml:id="794"></ref>. It is, perhaps, a pity that the author has exercised such severe self&#8211;repression, for the materials on which his keen sarcasm might have been employed are abundant. He has been well advised in keeping his work within the limits of a single volume, for the public has certainly grown impatient of the swollen biographies of inferior ecclesiastics which have so frequently issued from the press during recent years. Certainly Bishop John Wordsworth poured out his great powers on many inadequate objects.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
