<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[649]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">556</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName> at last. From Frederic <persName xml:id="1189">Harrison</persName> I received the permission I has asked for, and wrote to <persName xml:id="1289">Reginald Smith</persName> enclosing the copy of F. H.'s letter, which she had kindly made. After lunch <persName xml:id="2685">Godfrey</persName> (for such is now my mode of addressing him) and I walked into Lichfield, &amp; called on the Dean. <persName xml:id="1815">Savage</persName> made a display of pleasure at seeing me, which seemed somewhat excessive &amp; was, therefore, somewhat suspicious. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">When I asked him whether he was student of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton, he professed never to have heard of him. This argued either an all but impossible ignorance, or an extremely discreditable prejudice. As the Dean is not an ignoramus, I feel myself 'shut up to' the latter alternative</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi>He agreed with Godfrey in saying that Lichfield was one of the most windy places in England: affirmed that the Cathedral stood on the loftiest site of all the cathedrals (some 300 feet above the sea): and said that airmen found the air&#8211;currents over Lichfield so difficult to traverse that they commonly avoided this district. On our return to the house a telegraph message was at the door with a telegram from <persName xml:id="2819">Lady Londonderry</persName> asking us to dine &amp; sleep next Monday. As <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was not available, I returned an affirmative answer. I wrote to <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName> at the Front. To dinner came the <persName xml:id="3702">Bishop of Stafford</persName> and his wife (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Crawford [Crawfurd]). These had but recently arrived in the diocese, &amp; had formerly lived in the north. He seemed a fair specimen of a modern suffragan, &amp; rather more natural than most. He said that he was a friend of <persName xml:id="775">Bowlby</persName>, &amp; had once been carried by him to the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName> in Bethnal Green, where he had met me. This is a 'far cry'!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
