<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[698]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
            </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">609</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another glorious morning. I watched at close range a thrush absorbing a large worm. It is an elaborate and prolonged performance, infinitely delightful to the bird, rather less so presumably to the victim. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m. I received the Holy Communion. The paper reports that 16 people were killed in Saturday night's air&#8211;raid. Last night's casualty list is not yet announced. </hi><hi rend="italic">A reporter called for yesterday's sermon, but I refused it. The little appendix on Total Abstinence would be a toothsome morsel for the Pot&#8211;house keepers &amp; their stalwarts; but I attach more importance to other parts of my discourse which however have no attraction for the journalists! I have frankly wasted this day spending most of it out of doors. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Mayor called on me with a very sheepish, even hang&#8211;dog aspect, to make excuse for not having acknowledged my letter</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He promised to give me the assurance I asked for so soon as the work at <placeName xml:id="73">Langley House</placeName> had been finished. He had much to say in self&#8211;excuse, with respect to which I would, &amp; could say nothing. My little letter, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">headed <ref xml:id="878">"Liquor restrictions &#8211; a Correction"</ref>, appeared in the "Times"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi>I worked again at the removal of the ivy&#8211;bed from the front garden. After lunch I looked on at the school reports for a short time. I attended Evensong, and wrote to <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, sending him a copy of <ref xml:id="85">"Robertson"</ref>. Miss Susie Ramsay arrived on a visit for some days. The school goes down on Wednesday: the 8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Durham L.I. left last Friday. There is now nothing left but the Cadets at <placeName xml:id="61">Hatfield Hall</placeName>, &amp; they are under orders to leave shortly. It seems probable that the military service after having continued for 20 months will cease for lack of men.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
