<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[388]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">770</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName> before breakfast.<note xml:id="320" n="1"></note> At breakfast we had a great political argument. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3759">Verney</persName> &amp; Sir Douglas <persName xml:id="3758">Dawson</persName> against the pleasant little military man whose name I don't know, and myself. Then I took my departure, &amp; it is to be noted that I gave &#x00A3;2 .2.6. in tips viz. &#x00A3;1. to the servant who 'did' for me, &amp; packed my bags. &#x00A3;1. to the elderly flunkey who acted as my "Guardian Angel", &amp; 2/6 to the footman who handed my bags into the railway carriage. I said 'Goodbye' to the Dawsons in friendly wise on the platform. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3756">Austen Leigh</persName> came into the railway carriage, &amp; introduced himself. He has become so stout and brown that I could not at first recognize him. He has been employed recently in teaching cadets at Oxford. Arrived in London, I drove to Westminster Abbey, &amp; deposited my bags in the Porter's Lodge. Then I went to the Barber, &amp; had my Phrygian locks curtailed and cleansed. Then I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; lunched. The Club swarmed with officers in khaki, the members of the <orgName xml:id="286">Constitutional Club</orgName>, evicted by the Government's requisition of their club&#8211;premises. I walked back to Westminster, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName>, whom I found at home, &amp; had tea with him. Then I went to 3. Little Cloisters, and picked up my letters. Then I went to Hugh Rees L</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">td</hi><hi>, &amp; brought two books as literary </hi><hi rend="underline">provender</hi><hi> for tomorrow. Returning to Westminster, I fell in with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Wright, the Clerk of the Works, who gave me a vivid account of the destruction of the Zeppelin, which he witnessed from his windows. He told me that his son Walter has joined the Flying Corps, &amp; is somewhere in France. Major <persName xml:id="2531">Hills</persName> M.P. has not been killed, but his nephew. The Cathedral bell was tolled mistakenly: but happily the correct report had been received in time for <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> to cut out his obituary notice from his sermon!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
