<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[644]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">639</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrestled vainly with the problem of my Westminster Sermon. The occasional discourse in London becomes an anxious matter, for everybody expects you to say something important, &amp; too often you have nothing important to say! I attended Evensong, and afterwards drove with <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> to Brancepeth, where M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4017">Glyn</persName> in acid manner showed us the church. A plan hanging in the vestry, and bearing date in the year 1790, affirms that it represents the pews as "settled" in 1639. After walking round the castle, we drove home through the Park. <persName xml:id="3585">Boutflower</persName> from Sherburn brought his <persName xml:id="1793">brother</persName>, the Bishop of Tokyo, to see me: and I fear I shocked him by speaking lightly of the "National Mission", and refusing to take the gloomy view of the Nation, which their Lordships now affect. He said that our hesitation to accept compulsory service was affecting Japanese opinion as to the value of the British alliance, and professed himself disposed to accept the Japanese view. But I dissented, pointing out that the Japanese conception of patriotism was essentially national in the old pre&#8211;Christian &amp; non&#8211;Christian sense; and that it was not really to the discredit of the British nation that it had assumed too confidently that Christendom was more Christian than it actually was. After dinner Ernest read to me some more of his letters, preserved in his book of press&#8211;cuttings: on the whole, they raise my opinion of his powers. That he made himself a leader among the students at M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Gill is evident. He expresses himself with vigour and good sense, if also with excessive vehemence &amp; with reference to too many subjects. Also, he shewed me the list of the books he had read. This he has kept since 1902. It contains the names of many excellent, &amp; too many worthless, works: but mainly it does him credit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[642]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3582"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> J. Dennant</hi></persName><hi> (54 Denmark Villas, Hove, Sussex) was a hearer of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName>. In a letter to me dated 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> Feb</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi><hi> 1916, he says:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I remember being especially interested &amp; impressed on one occasion by a special service for Working Men, held in Trinity Chapel on a week night &#8211; I think in 1852 &#8211; at an early hour, so as to catch the men as they left work. The Chapel was crowded, nay, packed in every available place, including the Pulpit stairs. The men were in their working&#8211;clothes &#8211; some in shirt&#8211;sleeves &#8211; for there evidently had been no time for the usual clear&#8211;up before the service. I was much struck by the rapt attention given to the speaker, and the look of intense interest in their up&#8211;turned faces as he delivered his message. He held them &#8211; not by rhetoric, which he despised &#8211; but by the earnest expression of his mind &amp; soul, in attempting to reach their hearts: much facilitated doubtless by his high type of physique, his rich &amp; tender voice, a flushed cheek, &amp; at times a brilliant flashing of the deep blue eye, when he made a strong point."</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi>A correspondent in the "British Weekly" on the authority of a sister&#8211;in&#8211;law who, with her parents, was a seatholder in Trinity Chapel in M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> R.'s time says:</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The chapel was filled with the &#x00E9;lite of Brighton, &amp; there was never a vacant seat. My father&#8211;in&#8211;law was frequently requested early in the week to secure a seat for some ardent hero&#8211;worshipper. R. found time to visit all the members of his congregation, &amp; he … always talked of lofty matters. There was nothing of the gossip about him, all his conversation being pervaded by earnestness &amp; sincerity."</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
