<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[579]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">522</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Military Service Bill was carried last night on the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> reading by a majority of 298 (403 to 105), and the minority was largely Irish, though the Bill does not extend to Ireland. On the other hand, the Labour Congress has declared against compulsion by a large majority. It will be interesting to see how far the men will respond to this leading.<note xml:id="298" n="1"></note> The papers announce </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="636">Pearce's</persName> appointment to be assistant Chaplain General, honorary and temporary</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> This is interesting and may be important. Pearce has great powers of work, considerable organizing ability, a facile pen, &amp; a good temper &#8211; all admirable qualities for a position of administrative character. I received a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George <persName xml:id="2735">Askwith</persName>,</hi><hi> the Labour conciliator, expressing warm approval of the views expressed in the "Times". He has a large &amp; various experience of the artisans, &amp; his testimony to their opinions is valuable. There were several other letters of approval, none of denunciation. I was interested also to observe that both the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi><hi>" and the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Record</hi><hi>" maintain a stony silence: the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Challenge</hi><hi>" has a hostile paragraph: &amp; the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi><hi>" a friendly one. The "</hi><hi rend="underline">British Weekly</hi><hi>" says nothing. Partly these papers are embarrassed by the impossibility of defending either </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3777">Burrough's</persName></hi><hi> </hi><hi rend="underline">theodicy</hi><hi>, or </hi><persName xml:id="166"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingram's</hi></persName> <hi rend="underline">arithmetic</hi><hi>! Partly, they are really at a loss how to deal with the Dean of Durham! &amp;, partly, they don't know which way the episcopal cat designs to jump! Then I expect that there has been so much approval expressed in many quarters of my protest against the fanatical insistence of the total abstainers that they are a little perplexed as to the course which prudence requires them to take. The resentment against this rapidly improvised 'Reign of the Saints' has gone far, and is very strong.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
