<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[558]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">684</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most glorious morning, the first for at least a fortnight. If but such days had come while <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> was here, we might have done something. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote a second letter to the "Challenge" under the heading "Festina lente" [make haste slowly], answering criticisms from two correspondents in this week's issue</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>Then I presided at a Meeting of Chapter, at which we had an application for a Maughan Scholarship. [N.B. Maughan was a clergyman who taught a Durham King's Scholar so successfully that he (Gent) 'swept the Board' at Oxford. In recognition thereof a sum of &#x00A3;500 was collected by Gent's friends &amp; invested. The proceeds of the money were to be given to a boy belonging to the old parish of Stanhope, and for one year educated in an elementary school there, who should be at the Durham Grammar School, &amp; approved by the Trustees (i.e. the D. &amp; C.) after examination.]. I attended Evensong: and afterwards, at <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> instigation, picked up two officers whom she had observed in the Cathedral, brought them in to the Deanery, gave them tea, &amp; showed them the house. [Their names were Major F. E. Barnett, 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> S. Staffordshire Reg</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> &amp; Capt: A. G. C. Sims, 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> S. Staffs. They were stationed at Richmond.]. Then the candidates for Ordination came to tea. I gave them copies of <ref xml:id="27">'Moral Discipline in the Christian Church'</ref>, or <ref xml:id="85">"Frederick Robertson of Brighton"</ref>. [Of the one book 15 copies, of the other 7 were taken.] Later they came to the Chapel for an abbreviated Evensong, and the Bishop's final address. The Chaplain had succeeded in raising a harmonium, which was played by one of the candidates. A singing bird poured his soul in musick at his own Evensong, &amp; so accompanied and assisted ours. I bethought me of Cuddesdon 29 years ago, and traced again my troubled way across the years.	</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
