<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[400]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916. Windsor.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">768</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Durham by the 8.20 express proceeding to the station in the omnibus of the Three Tuns Hotel, as M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Peel's cabs were all engaged. The train was crowded with soldiers. We arrived in King's Cross at 2.25 p.m.: &amp; I got on board a taxi, proceeded to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> &amp; dropped my bags, and then went on to Westminster Abbey, where I had appointed a meeting with <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, who was returning from his course of range&#8211;finding instruction at Hythe to his old camp at Seaford. He soon appeared, and we walked in the Victoria Garden, had tea, &amp; then went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, and there parted. I recovered my bags, &amp; drove to Paddington. Here I was addressed by an elderly clergyman who said he had attended my lectures at Oxford!! <persName xml:id="203">Edmond Warre</persName> came into my carriage, &amp; formed a pleasant railway companion to Windsor, where I was met by a Royal Carriage, &amp; driven to the Castle. My rooms are 352 Edward IIIrd's Tower, and are both pleasant &amp; convenient. I walked into town, &amp; got shaved. On my return a telegram was handed me, on a very pompous&#8211;looking official form. It ran thus: &#8211; "Private news of undoubted accuracy has reached me of the death at the front of Captain Hills member for Durham." <persName xml:id="3830">Lowe</persName>. This is sad tidings.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dinner was at 8.30 p.m. I was fetched, and conducted along a noble corridor (500 feet long) with many pictures, to the drawing room, where we awaited their Majesties. <persName xml:id="3406">Princess Mary</persName>, a very pretty girl, came with them. I sate next the Queen, and found her very pleasant. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">There was no wine offered to the guests; so the King's total abstinence is maintained. But it certainly has the effect of blanketing conversation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Perhaps it is merely association of ideas, but a wineless&#8211;dinner seems dull. After dinner, I followed the King into the smoking room. He started </hi><hi rend="bold">[398]</hi><hi> at once on the subject of the Somme Films. He enlarged with much energy on the achievements &amp; sufferings of the troops, and on the importance of bringing these home to the people. I did manage to say that there were some things too sacred for exhibition on the stage, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but H.M. is so loquacious that it is difficult to get in a word</hi><hi>. He has been reading an account of the Austrian outrages in Serbia, and expressed with much vigour his detestation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then he spoke of <persName xml:id="252">Casement</persName>, and enlarged on his infamous private character. I noted with regret that he was inclined to throw doubt on the Putumayo Report</hi><hi>: but I reminded him that the incriminated company had accepted its statements of fact. He spoke with much contempt of the German theologians, especially of <persName xml:id="716">Harnack</persName>, whom he remembered meeting when, at the instigation of the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName>, he received them at Buckingham Palace. Sir Douglas <persName xml:id="3758">Dawson</persName> was next called up, and spoken to. The Marquie de <persName xml:id="3905">Soveral</persName> claimed acquaintance with me. He had accompanied the Queen when she visited Durham Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Queen spoke of <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham's</persName> calamitous marriage</hi><hi>, of which she attributed the principal blame to <persName xml:id="3748">Lady Durham's</persName> family.<note xml:id="259" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Edmund Warre said this afternoon that he held with me respecting the Somme Films: and Ernest told me that the subject had been discussed in his Mess, and the prevailing opinion was on my side. The King's open patronage, however, will more than outweigh any opinions adverse to the exhibition, &amp; one must reconcile one's self as best as maybe to the fact. I am pledged to see the <persName xml:id="382">Dean</persName>, Canon <persName xml:id="2383">Dalton</persName>, and D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Warre tomorrow. Also to write at least three letters.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
