<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[675]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">569</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2898">Toland</persName> a book written by her son <persName xml:id="3705">Edward</persName>, describing his experiences of hospital work in France during the dreadful period from August 1914 to February 1915: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Aftermath of Battle. With the Red Cross in France" by Edward D. Toland</hi><hi>. I found this simply written diary so absorbing that I perforce read it through at a sitting. It may go with the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Diary of a French Army Chaplain</hi><hi>" by</hi><hi rend="underline"> Abb&#x00E9; F&#x00E9;lix Klein</hi><hi>. They are classics of War as seen by the non&#8211;combatant on duty.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To see one's self as others see one is said to be an edifying, if not rarely a mortifying process. </hi><hi rend="italic">Macmillan's send [sic] me this morning two small newspaper criticisms of <ref xml:id="84">'War&#8211;time Sermons'</ref>, which may assist me in this regard, &amp; which certainly have no other value. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The 'Middlesex County Times' heads its notice</hi><hi rend="italic"> 'A Virile Preacher', &amp; proceeds to comment thereupon. 'I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> characterise him as "A Christian Man of the World"' &#8211; Is this the same thing as 'A worldly Christian'? The writer goes on to observe that 'he sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have had a more active post than a deanery, especially in the prime of his life'. Many will agree with this: but many more considering that 'no more active post' than a bishoprick could have been found for the gentleman, will hesitate! The sermons are commended, but 'if they lack anything it is fervour, wh. our forefathers used to call "unction"' &#8211; we may add that some of them preferred to call it "enthusiasm", &amp; to connect it with many unpleasing things from Hugh Peters to Stiggins &amp; Pecksniff! "I can imagine," so he concludes, "one of the old Cambridge Platonists, if his lot had been in our own times, preaching such sermons as these". I should really like to believe that!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
