<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[464]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">734</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. The post brought a card from <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> saying that he had been 'slightly wounded', and was 'being sent down to the base'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">When I was last in town I fell in with, or rather was addressed by a gentleman who introduced himself as M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3916">Charlewood</persName> of Manchester. I recalled his face as familiar, &amp; remembered that he was a representative of Manchester in the York House of Laymen. We had some conversation in the street, and, as we parted, he said: "Do you know, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dean, whom you remind me of?" "Indeed not", said I, "but I trust nobody disreputable". "No truly", he rejoined, "for you remind me of Bishop <persName xml:id="3915">Moorhouse</persName>: for like him you always make me think". That was an unexpected, and not unwelcome compliment; for I respected Moorhouse.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, &amp; heard an excellent sermon from <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> on the Transfiguration. <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> came in to lunch.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a great congregation at Evensong, when the service was specially arranged as a commemoration of the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> anniversary of the Declaration of War. The Bishop attended, &amp; gave the Benediction from the Throne. The Mayor &amp; Corporation came in their pomp, &amp; about 200 special constables. About a dozen choirmen from the parish churches assisted the Cathedral Choir: &amp; in the procession came most of the parochial clergy, including for the first time, <persName xml:id="4019">Loxley</persName> of St. Oswald's. Also a number of <orgName xml:id="45">Church Lads Brigade</orgName> boys sate together in the south transept. I preached<ref xml:id="912"></ref> from Psalm 97.1,2,11,12. At the end of the service the National Anthem, all three verses, was sung with great fervour. The collection was for the <orgName xml:id="264">British Red Cross Society</orgName>. The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> came into the Deanery, &amp; had tea with his ladies. The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3448">his wife</persName> came to dinner. <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh</persName> returned to his camp.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
