<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[640]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">640</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="889">Birrell</persName> has resigned. He announced the fact in a very dignified speech. Of course it was inevitable after Dublin had been wrecked. <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>, <persName xml:id="3451">Redmond</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2052">Carson</persName> all spoke well &amp; in excellent good taste. The House of Commons is at its best in this sort of business.<note xml:id="306" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Elizabeth Bannister, a relative of the traitor <persName xml:id="252">Casement</persName>, who had appealed to me to use my influence, so far as was possible, on his side. Of my letter I kept a copy, not knowing where it might be carried. No past services could reasonably be pleaded in face of treason so gross, so aggravated, &amp; in some of its manifestations so base. Yet I am really very greatly distressed that the Hero of the Putumayo should have come to this</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in working on my Westminster Sermon, of which I wrote nearly half. I attended Evensong. The <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName>, who was at York for the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>, says that the Zeppelins came over York, &amp; dropped bombs. He saw the air&#8211;ship at a great height. He describes the Archbishop (<persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>) as wearing a wig, and having a pinched &amp; elderly aspect, possibly due to some re&#8211;arrangements of his teeth. Thus time works havoc on us: but I recall with a start that his Grace is my junior by a whole year!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> &amp; I actually started on an expedition to Finchall Abbey [sic], but turned back when the rain began falling. Then we went into the Library for an hour, and looked at books. In a volume of Layard's Monuments of Nineveh, I found some water&#8211;colour pictures of the frescoes in the Galilee dated 1839, and signed by one Smith. That is an odd thing, to use the blank pages of a book in the Chapter Library for a purpose completely alien to the subject&#8211;matter of the book itself.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner we sate in my study, and read to one another selections of poetry until bed&#8211;time.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
