<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[584]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> June, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">672</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather today has been wet &amp; gloomy with deceiving intervals of sunshine. In one of these I ordered a carriage to go to Pittington, but as the hour of starting drew near, 'the heavens grew black with wind &amp; rain', and I had but just time to cancel my order. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> spent the forenoon in going over the cathedral with the vergers, while I laboured at my Whitsunday sermon. We attempted a walk after Evensong, but the threatening weather drove us quickly homewards.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The later reports of the naval engagement tend to mitigate the disastrous impression which the earlier ones did undoubtedly convey. The Admiralty now professes to be convinced that the German losses were not merely relatively but absolutely greater than ours. Practically the whole personnel of the lost ships have perished. Comment in France, Italy, Holland, Denmark, and the United States appears to be fairly sane and sound. Even in Germany there are signs that the first fervours are being replaced by a more sober disposition. After all, the blockade continues in undiminished severity, and the losses on the German side have been considerable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Ernest and I are growing very confidential. I shewed him some of my old journals: and he read me some of his old sermons! It were, perhaps, invidious to determine which was the most bored</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">But at least it is something gained if a link of intimate confidence is created between us. </hi><hi>It is just 29 years since I was ordained as Deacon in Cuddesdon Parish Church, for Trinity Sunday in 1887 fell on June 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. I remember that it was a warm summer's day, and that the country about Cuddesdon looked winningly peaceful, and quite wonderfully beautiful.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
