<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[434]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">751</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A heavy thunderous day. The morning post bought a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, and one from <persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName> saying that they thought there would not be sufficient demand for a 2/6 book on the Abps's <ref xml:id="817">Report</ref>. So that is off, unless I try some other publisher.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I worked rather vainly at the Article: then went with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to Bow Church where a considerable company had assembled for the funeral of old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Thomas Jones, aged 91, who had been a choirboy in the Cathedral. Then I walked with <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>. We went along the river to 'Old Durham', &amp; then through the corn&#8211;fields to Shincliffe. A Zeppelin or quasi&#8211;Zeppelin, of ours appeared in the sky, &amp; rapidly passed out of sight. On our return Olive &amp; I had tea together very pleasantly, and then I went to my study for 'work'! <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> came in to tell me that he had found the origin of the Episcopal patronage of the Durham Canonries, which are in the gift of the crown by our statutes. Letters patent of Feb:7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1555/6 from Philip &amp; Mary transferred the patronage to Bishop Tunstall and his successors. The document is printed in full in Hutchinson's <ref xml:id="797">History &amp; Antiquities of Durham</ref>, vol.I. p.438. After dinner our little programme of entertainment was again followed. Olive sang divinely; and then we all moved to my study where for more than an hour I read to the rest of them divers favourite poems of mine.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
