<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[416]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">761</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful day from beginning to ending. The Times contains three letters on the 'Cinema' question all hostile to me: &amp; several rude things came to me through the post: also several letters of thanks. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> sent me a note in which he says, "Your kindness and loyalty to your colleagues on the Chapter have ever been a notable characteristic of your life here". This is pleasant: but would the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> endorse it? Well: it is true, even if he wouldn't: </hi><hi rend="underline">so there</hi><hi>! I wrote some portion of the Windsor sermon, taking for my text a very noble passage, Jeremiah ix. 23,24, to which <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> called my attention. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Thus saith Jehovah, Let not the wise man glory in his wisdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might, let not the rich man glory in riches: but let him that glorieth glory in this, that he understandeth &amp; that he knoweth Me, that I am Jehovah which doeth kindness, judgement, and righteousness in the earth: for in these things do I delight, saith Jehovah</hi><hi>". This passage deserves to stand beside the famous oracle of Micah, as marking the 'high&#8211;water mark' of Old Testament Religion. These could not be paralleled elsewhere.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
