<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[631]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">548</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Yes, Sir, I heard all M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> wonderful sermons: &amp; thank god, I've never entered a place of worship since he died" &#8211; this was the rather surprising observation of one Wingfield, an old Brighton tradesman, who had been one of the great preacher's admirers, &amp; was in that character questioned by <persName xml:id="3984">Asher</persName> about him. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Asher also told me an anecdote which he himself had received from Charles <persName xml:id="3971">Robertson</persName>, the Preacher's only son</hi><hi rend="italic">. When Charles was at home preparing his lessons, the tame canary, a familiar &amp; insistent creature, interrupted him by hopping on to his book. He moved it away with his hand, but the bird, continuing its advances, finally got its leg broken against the young student's fingers. Robertson arrived. "Where is the canary?" he asked. "It has flown up there", replied the boy. "I think its leg is broken," &amp; he told how the disaster had come about. "That cannot be true: you have tortured the poor creature: &amp; you have lied as well": and forthwith the unhappy Charles was whisked off to his father's room, &amp; flogged. Later, he repeated his story to his mother, &amp; she became his advocate with Robertson, when after some hours of miserable wandering in the open air, he returned to the house. He received the narrative in silence, went at once to his son's room, &amp; rousing him from sleep, bad him hold out his hand. "Let us shake hands, Charles: I apologize to you for doubting your word, as one gentleman to another!" In this story, what is the most significant, the hot impulse which induced precipitate and unjust action, or the prompt repentance expressing itself in almost excessive &amp; formal self&#8211;humiliation?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[633]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I left Durham by the early express, and travelled comfortably to Brighton, where I arrived shortly after 4 p.m., and drove at once to 7 Alexandra Villas which serves as Holy Trinity Vicarage. Here I was welcomed by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Felix Asher</hi><hi rend="italic">, who is handicapped as to movement by a damaged foot</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">/</hi> <hi rend="italic">After dinner </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3700">Fairfax&#8211;Cholmeley</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, a Yorkshire land&#8211;owner, who sojourns at Brighton, came in: &amp; we had much talk of an ecclesiastical character. He is a member of one of the old Roman Catholic families, but has himself broken away from the Roman Church, &amp; worships in Asher's congregation. He has an honest appearance, a frank manner, &amp; displays in his conversation much intelligence &amp; an unusual information on matters ecclesiastical. Asher is evidently much affected by a book on the church written by one Hamilton, a Canadian divine. I remember that this book was received with suspicious enthusiasm by the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">', and has been found serviceable in providing a method of inducing liberal minded Anglicans to cast in in their lot with our 'episcopalians'. As I have not read the book, I cannot pass any judgment on its quality, but as its conclusion is in my judgment wholly inadmissible, I am not likely to approve its premises, or to be impressed by its argument. It is clear to me that many clergymen, formerly liberal in their opinions, are reconciling themselves to the Lambeth formula.</hi><hi><note xml:id="300" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> They are advancing in years: many of them have growing families: they are hungry for some preferment: &amp; they see that the key to promotion by bishops is a parade of zeal for bishops. There is no resisting </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that</hi><hi rend="italic"> logic!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
