<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[532]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th, </hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">694</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brought an affectionate letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. He is still in camp at Seaford, &amp; not yet well enough for active service: but he writes cheerfully. I attended Mattins, and then spent the time before lunch in shewing </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName></hi><hi> over the Cathedral. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2360">Soltau&#8211;Simmons</persName>, and Major &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Stephenson came to lunch. Then I donned my doctor's robes, and attended the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>. The <persName xml:id="3129">Duke of Northumberland</persName> presided as Chancellor, and bestowed degrees of many kinds on a host of young men &amp; women. I was much struck by the plainness of the blue stockings! They would appear to avoid all approached to Venus! Then I walked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName></hi><hi> for more than an hour, &amp; then talked with him. He is well read, intelligent, wide&#8211;minded &amp; good natured. So far as our conversation disclosed his opinions on matters theological and ecclesiastical, I found myself more completely in agreement with him than with any other clergyman of my acquaintance. Nevertheless, if he had been an Anglican, I doubt whether his easiness of temper would not have carried him into the camp of the majority. He reminded me of a discussion some years ago in </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell's</persName></hi><hi> house, when I expressed strongly my belief that Germany was bent on forcing a War on Europe, and when he had strongly opposed my views. He admitted that events had confirmed with woeful emphasis the views I then maintained.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
