<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[534]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">693</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wasted the morning in reading Sander's 'Rise and Growth of Anglican Schism' in the translation published by Burns &amp; Oats in 1877. It is, of course, very scurrilous, but not, perhaps, worse in that respect than the Protestant writings, with which it is comparable. It was published in 1585, and may be accepted as the Roman Catholick reading of the English Reformation. He concludes his narrative with the account of the deaths of Queen Mary &amp; Cardinal Pole, and observes sorrowfully: "Then came the hour of Satan, and the power of darkness took possession of the whole of England". The book is discredited by the author's constant reference to a horrible and baseless scandal that Henry VIII was himself the father of Anne Boleyn. So degraded were the morals of Henry's court, and so notorious were Henry's relations with both the Boleyn sisters, that it can hardly be surprising that even such a monstrous tale should find belief: but undoubtedly Sander's Book would have had more influence, if he had omitted that disgusting canard. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
T. G. Law in the article on Nicholas <persName xml:id="3935">Sanders</persName> in the Dict. Of Nat: Biog: after stating that this book 'was the proximate occasion of <persName xml:id="3829">Burnet</persName> writing his <ref xml:id="183">'History'</ref> in wh. he catalogues &amp; conflates the alleged calumnies of Sanders', he adds:</p><div type="quote"><p>'Recent historians have, however, shown that notwithstanding his animus and the violence of his language, his narrative fact is remarkably truthful. In almost every disputed point he has been proved right and Burnet wrong'. </p></div><p> In respect to information derived from Roman sources, Sanders is particularly accurate. Even the 'impossible story regarding Anne Boleyn's birth' was no invention of Sanders but 'was repeated by him, in apparent good faith on the authority of Rastell's 'Life of More' to which he refers, &amp; of common gossip. Sanders was born 'about 1530' and died 'almost certainly in the spring of' 1581.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[532]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I rolled the lawn, and attended Evensong. At tea&#8211;time there arrived from Harrogate that quaint little Scottish pundit, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName>, now one of the Professors of the Galsgow U.F. College. I took him for a walk through Houghall Wood. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; his niece, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> &amp; Miss Story and <persName xml:id="3496">Dennet</persName> came to dinner. There was much Conversation, but I recall nothing worth remembering.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
