<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[456]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">740</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a brief chapter to sanction an incumbent's pension. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> and </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling</persName></hi><hi>. I picked up a young soldier with his female relations in the Cathedral, and spent an hour in shewing them about the place. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. I finished reading <ref xml:id="860">"England &amp; the Catholic Church under Elizabeth"</ref> by Arnold Oskar Meyer. The book has been translated from the German by a London Oratorian, &amp; is published by the Roman Catholic publishers, Kegan Paul &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi><hi>. The Author is 'not himself a catholic' but his work is so agreeable to Papists that it is issued with official sanction. It deals with an aspect of our religious history which is very little observed, &amp; it seems to be written with ample knowledge. I found it extremely suggestive &amp; informing.</hi>

</p><div type="quote"><p>"Reformation and counter&#8211;reformation synchronized in England. Movements which followed each other on the continent, &amp; consequently did not collide with the full shock of their first encounter, appeared simultaneously on the scene in England, &amp; the result was a life &amp; death struggle. In this conflict the puritans were, so to speak, the rocks against which the waves of counter&#8211;reformation beat in vain" (v. p.7).</p></div><p>This is true, &amp; illuminating.
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
