<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[546]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">689</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning was bright, but the day became very sultry. I had a heavy cold which of itself predisposed me to stupidity: with the assistance of the atmosphere I became positively owlish. I made a typed copy of </hi><persName xml:id="554"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert's</hi></persName><hi> last letter, in order to lend it for general reading. I attended Evensong, after which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2790">Knight</persName></hi><hi> came to claim "protection" from the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>, with whom he has had some friction!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Plutarch relates of the elder Cato that 'he never paid more than 1500 drachmas for a slave, since he did not want them to be delicately beautiful, but sturdy workers, such as grooms &amp; herdsmen, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">that these he thought it his duty to sell when they got oldish, instead of feeding them when they were useless</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; that in general he thought nothing cheap that one could do without, but that what one did not need, even if it cost but a penny was dear'. Plutarch speaks with just condemnation of the Roman's cruelty: 'However for my part, I regard his treatment of his slaves like beasts of burden, using them to the uttermost, and then, when they were old, driving them off and selling them, as the mark of a very mean nature, which recognizes no tie between man and man but that of necessity …. A kindly man will take good care of his horses even when they are worn out with age, and of his dogs too, not only in their puppyhood, but when their old age needs nursing.' This whole passage is admirable, and expresses the Greek spirit at its best (v. Plutach's Lives. Marcus Cato V).</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
