<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[362]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">781</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Jackson endured the operation</hi><hi rend="italic">, but is reported to be in a lamentably weak condition. We prayed for him by name at Mattins &amp; Evensong. How odd are the contrasts of human history! We are all vastly concerned </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">to preserve the life of one, obscure &amp; unimportant lad: we eagerly send to the shambles of War our choicest men</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in finishing the paper on, "Social Problems after the War", which I had promised the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> to read at the forthcoming <orgName xml:id="126">Diocesan Conference</orgName>. I sent the M.S. to <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> for criticism, as he is pledged to read a paper on "Economic Problems after the War" on the same occasion. Such performances are futile enough for events always disappoint expectations, and disconcert theorists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="4098">Percy Elliot</persName> drove me in the motor&#8211;car to Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne, a village buried in the country, not far from Darlington. It has the distinction of including <persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler</persName> in the list of its Rectors. He held the benefice for three years, 1722&#8211;1725, before moving to Stanhope. He left his mark for good in the place by building, or re&#8211;building the Rectory. A part of the house, I was assured by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3903">Fellowes</persName>, the present incumbent, dates from the 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century. The church appears to be an interesting fabric; it contains panelling and communion rails which date from the memorably fatal year, 1649. I preached (with the requisite modifications) the sermon I prepared last year for the Harvest Festival at Bishop Butler's other parish &#8211; Stanhope. The congregation was small; the Rector thought it necessary to explain that its smallness was partly caused by a shower of rain, which had cut off the contingent from Darlington. We returned in the darkness, at a very moderate pace, arriving at the Deanery shortly before 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
