<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[658]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">628</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The sun shone brightly through oppugnant clouds when I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. I received the Holy Communion; May was the celebrant, that vast, vacant man, whose career is an insoluble problem.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I worked at the Windsor Sermon but made little progress. <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> re&#8211;appeared, so lamentably deaf that I could not converse with him. Here emerges another problem to be solved. What is my duty towards complete, though innocent, incompetence? So deaf a man could never be trusted to drive a motor&#8211;car: yet to cast him adrift with wife &amp; 4 children has an ill aspect. After lunch, I walked with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3981">Gilbert Darwin</persName> &amp; a friend named Taylor came to tea, &amp; afterwards viewed the House, Library, and Cathedral. On our way towards the Shrine of S. Cuthbert (i.e. its site) I picked up two young men, of whom one was in khaki. He looked a mere boy, but he had been at the front for many months, going through tremendous experiences. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName> arrived</hi><hi> to spend Easter Day here, but he has a bad cold, &amp; went to bed early. I completed the reading of 'King Lear' to my family.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
