<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[548]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">688</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> has made no delay in filling up the vacant appointments, and, though neither appointment is sensational, both may be considered excellent. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3933">Woods</persName></hi><hi>, the Vicar of Bradford, goes to Peterborough as Bishop: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName></hi><hi> of Holy Trinity, Chelsea, goes to Westminster, as successor to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="109">Wilberforce</persName></hi><hi> in the Canonry &amp; Rectory of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's. The Archdeacon tells me that he had speech with the Bishop&#8211;elect last night, and was told by him that the outgoing Bishop will take &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">1500</hi><hi> per annum as a pension. This appears incredible, and is certainly scandalous. Anyway, if any such deduction had to be made from the official income, it would have been impossible for a poor man to hold it. Happily </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wood</hi><hi> [Woods] is credited with considerable private means.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>While showing </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Fry</hi><hi> round the Cathedral before lunch, I fell in with a lad, who said that he was up for examination for a scholarship. I asked him to tea, &amp; promised to shew him also the church. He kept tryst, and I learned that his name was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Noel Forge</hi><hi>: that he would be 18 in December: that he was now at Bedford School: that his father was the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev: John Francis Forge</hi><hi>, Vicar of Walmley, near Birmingham: that he was the eldest of 3 children: that he hoped presently to be a clergyman. We went round the Cathedral, and I formed a favourable opinion of the youth. I am growing almost superstitious about making acquaintanceships. It is a leap in the dark, a net cast into the deep, a bow drawn at a venture. You never know what fates are hanging on a chance encounter. Nor can you surmise the impression you are making on the sensitive plate of a young man's mind.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[546]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a letter from </hi><persName xml:id="1696"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive</hi></persName><hi>, who is staying at the Llandrindod Wells: and also one from the Australian 'Reg </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Naughton</hi><hi>', who heads his epistle "Somewhere in France". Both these letters I answered after dinner.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
