<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[486]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">710</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Most of the Deans attended the Holy Communion in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> celebrated very reverently. His voice is clear &amp; pleasing, &amp; he has no aggressive "tricks". After breakfast we assembled in the Drawing&#8211;room for the conference. The discussion was curiously informal &amp; desultory. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Saving the <persName xml:id="44">Dean of Wells</persName>, I think every one expressed some degree of doubt and discontent as to the National Mission</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> brought forward the question of the projected Dictionary of Patristic Greek. I moved a resolution, which <persName xml:id="1814">Moor[e] Ede</persName> seconded, &amp; which ran thus:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>That the Deans assembled in conference at Peterborough have heard with great satisfaction that a Dictionary of Patristic Greek has been projected, &amp; hopes that the project will be carried through successfully, &amp; that as far as possible it may be supported by Deans &amp; Chapters.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>After the Conference we were all photographed in the garden. Then I went to see Hutton's hired house, which is charming, &amp; has a delightful garden. Then followed luncheon at the Deanery, and, after that, a rapid dispersing of the company. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> returned to London, there to visit her friend M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2939">Webbe</persName>. I went back to Durham, having the company of the Dean of Worcester as far as Darlington, where I changed trains. I arrived in the Deanery about 8.30 p.m., and there busied myself with correspondence until the arrival of <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName>, who came shortly after 11 p.m. Among my letters awaiting me here was another long screed from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Victor <persName xml:id="3774">Horsley</persName></hi><hi>, fanatical enough but perhaps somewhat less offensively truculent than before. I wrote several cheques, and sent them off to the claimants.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
