<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[442]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">747</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName> suggesting that I should write a detailed examination of the Report of the Archbishops' Committee on <ref xml:id="817">"Church &amp; State"</ref>. As soon as the letter had been despatched, I wished to recall it!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I walked to the station with <persName xml:id="30">Shadwell</persName>: and, on my return to my study, finished reading Von Hügel's most interesting &amp; informing book.<ref xml:id="820"></ref> General <persName xml:id="3849">Montgomery</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3850">his wife</persName> with one of his officers &amp; two ladies came to see the Cathedral. I spent the whole afternoon in shewing them round, and thy proved both interested and interesting. Among other things, the General told me that he had vainly tried to get 2 battalions stationed in Durham during the coming winter, but that the authorities prefer to stack the troops in Newcastle. I am rather sorry for this, as the Parade Service gave me a tiny piece of war&#8211;work to do duty </hi><hi rend="underline">in foro conscientiae</hi><hi><note xml:id="318" n="1"></note> as my "bit".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner we had much singing, Shadwell, <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> all exerted themselves. Olive's voice is better than ever, &amp; she sings with great feeling &amp; excellent taste. Hughes's voice sounds wonderful in the Drawing room: &amp; Shadwell's, though rather worse, is still pleasing. After the ladies had gone to bed, Shadwell &amp; I sate on talking. I showed him my correspondence with Sir Victor <persName xml:id="3774">Horsley</persName>. He denies that there is any such consensus of medical opinion as to the ill effects of alcohol, even when taken moderately, as that vehement Apostle of Prohibitionism asserts. In his own case he finds, as I think I have found, that total abstinence, while no&#8211;wise affecting his general health, seems to impair his power of work. Alcohol, which in his case as in mine means wine at dinner, appears to assist mental processes. Of course there is the element of pleasure. One would not drink wine if one didn't like doing so: but neither would one eat willingly what one did not like. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
