<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[530]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">695</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Miss <persName xml:id="2315" display="no">Maxwell</persName> sends me the following note &#x00E0; propos of some conversation which passed at dinner during her visit here:&#8211;</hi>
         </p><div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Under the rose' (sub ros&#x00E2;) = in strict confidence. Cupid gave Harpocrates (the God of silence) a rose, to bribe him not to betray the amours of Venus. Hence the flower became the emblem of silence. It was for this reason sculptured into the ceilings of banquet rooms to remind the guests that what was spoken sub vino (under the influence of drink) should not be uttered sub divo (in the open air). In 1526 it was placed over Confessionals. The banquet&#8211;room ceiling at Haddon Hall is decorated with roses. (French &#8211; parler sous la rose).</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi>I remember that one of my guests affirmed that the rosette on the parson's shovel&#8211;hat signified properly that the wearer was a Confessor. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Professor <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName> left for Cambridge after breakfast. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to Sunderland. The Rev. J. R. Husband, Vicar of Hursley, called to ask leave to photograph the Cathedral. I asked him to lunch, he came and afterwards saw the house. I placed &#x00A3;100 on deposit: &amp; drew out &#x00A3;40 for present use. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, taking occasion to tell him something about the Festival of Corpus Christi, which the Papists would have his regiment join in celebrating! [v. Hardwick's Church History. Middle Age p. 303f. The Festival was authorized by a bull of Urban IV. 1264.] I attended Evensong &amp; then made notes for my address at Eppleton. After tea I motored to Eppleton through falling rain. It is a dismal &amp; populous mining parish carved out of Hetton le Hole. The church, which is rather above the average of these parts, was well filled: some of the local clergy had come together &amp; I unveiled an East Window as a memorial to soldiers fallen in the War, &amp; made a speech.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
