<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[597]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">532</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a long letter on the Temperance v. Total abstinence question to a brewer, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> H. A. Blanch (Hillfield, Stroud), who wrote to me, enclosing a letter which had been sent to him by a local Dissenting minister on the same subject. Then I occupied myself with the works of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName> went home in the course of the forenoon. I gave her a copy of <ref xml:id="84">"War&#8211;time Sermons"</ref>, &amp; we parted in much affection. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with her as far as Newcastle, &amp; left my watch to be repaired by one of the silver smiths of that city.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3981">Gilbert Darwin</persName> came to lunch, and then walked with me for an hour. He returns to Winchester this week.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I ran through Robertson's "Corinthians" rather hastily</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> It is in many respects a very remarkable work. The intense egotism of the great preacher, temperamental but rendered acute by his chronic suffering, &amp; encouraged to give itself free expression by the habit of that generation, colours the pages. Particularly in his discussion of the 'thorn in the flesh', and his ardent description of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul, one cannot avoid the conclusion that he sees both through the medium of his own experiences. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> sent across <persName xml:id="3975">Pfleiderer's</persName> "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Development of Theology</hi><hi rend="italic">"<ref xml:id="854"></ref> which includes some very laudatory references to Robertson, whom the German Scholar declares to have been 'equal to (<persName xml:id="687">Maurice</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3629">Kingsley</persName>) in nobility of character and their superior in the wealth and depth of his mind'. This is the higher praise when it is remembered how comparatively small was the output of Robertson compared with that of the two Christian Socialist leaders. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
