<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[462]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">735</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning paper announced the death of <persName xml:id="1261">Violet's</persName> brother, Sir <persName xml:id="3771">Arthur Markham</persName>. He has made himself very prominent recently as a violent critic of the Government, and his indecent attack on Lord <persName xml:id="3556">Kitchener</persName>, but a few days before the tragedy of the "Hampshire" will not soon be forgotten or forgiven.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After Mattins I had an interview with <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>, &amp; told him that I could not sanction his absence from the college, while the other minor canons were away.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent most part of the morning in reading the little volume "</hi><ref xml:id="816"><hi rend="italic underline">Our Place in Christendom</hi></ref><hi rend="italic">", which has just appeared with the inevitable Preface by the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>. It is a curiously suggestive book, suggestive, I mean, of the state of mind which now exists among the Anglican High Churchmen. The evident obsession of all the writers is the Roman propagandism, which, one may fairly conjecture, is active and successful. There is barely an allusion, even indirect, to contemporary Protestantism. That seems to be wholly outside the concern of such Anglicanism as the writers represent. There is marked incoherence, almost reaching the point of mutual contradiction. <persName xml:id="3520">Mason</persName> represents the prae&#8211;historic Tractarian point of view. <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName> is far gone in the newer school of evolutionary Catholicks. <persName xml:id="3912">Whitney</persName> would root the Roman claims in Feudalism: Figgis would rather trace them to the imperialistic theories based on Roman Law. <persName xml:id="1191">Scott&#8211;Holland</persName> is verbose, inconsequent, &amp; enormously positive. <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> makes an immense parade of evangelical directness &amp; simplicity as a prelude to the crudest sectarianism. A. W. <persName xml:id="2288">Robinson</persName> brings all to an end in a little outburst of what the C.Q.R. [Church Quarterly Review] calls "cheerful journalism".<ref xml:id="921"></ref> The book is thus extremely vulnerable: but it is not without merits. Figgis &amp; Whitney know what they write about, &amp; say many true things in an effective way. To the half&#8211;educated this volume may well appear cogent, &amp; even convincing.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
