<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[402]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">769</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked for an hour with Prof: <persName xml:id="3569">Bower</persName> after breakfast. The morning was misty with all the promise of a brilliant day. In the changing light the Banks and the glorious buildings which look down upon them were extraordinarily beautiful. We walked to the Observatory, and then looked at the School and went down South Street to get that amazing view of the Cathedral. Then we descended to the river&#8211;side, &amp; wondered at the reflection of the mighty church in the still water. And all the way we talked voraciously. So we parted very good friends, and I gave him a copy of <ref xml:id="85">"Robertson of Brighton"</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The day became excessively hot, and I responded by an incapacitating head&#8211;ache. However, I made a start at a sermon for Glasgow, and wrote some letters. I had some conversation with <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> about Norham. He is now 39 years old, and has a young family. I pointed out to him that there were cogent reasons why he should not leave Durham with its exceptionally good educational facilities, until the problem of his boys' education had been solved: that he had now sufficient work of a varied kind: that ten years hence he would not be unduly old for taking a parish. Also I told him that he must not assume that the Dean &amp; Chapter would be willing to appoint him. I wrote to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> suggesting a meeting in town tomorrow afternoon, and to Canon <persName xml:id="2383">Dalton</persName> sending the text for my sermon "Ad Aulam" [to Court], and asking him whether he could explain the origin of the custom of requiring the preacher to send in his text beforehand. Is it a survival of the "Supreme Head's" former activity as "Rector Theologie" and Summus Episcopus? <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was at Newcastle all day attending the meetings of the British Association, and only returned to the Deanery in time for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
