<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[438]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">749</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1381">Moore</persName> told me this story of old Bishop <persName xml:id="274">Phillpotts</persName>, who held a canonry of Durham with the Bishoprick of Exeter. <persName xml:id="3763">Bishop Villiers</persName> of Durham was lauding <persName xml:id="3763">Spurgeon</persName>, then rising into fame as a Dissenting preacher, and brought a rather extravagant panegyric to a close with these words '</hi><hi rend="underline">O utinam si noster esset</hi><hi>' [O if only it were ours]: whereat Phillpotts murmured audibly: "Thou shalt not covert thy neighbour's ass". I suspect he was a caustic old humbug.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[line break]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'The Reformation Settlement was imposed on the clergy by the Nation against their will. It is now being destroyed by the clergy against the Nation's Will. Even this is an inadequate account of the extraordinary situation. The 'Establishment' will perish at the hands, not of the Clergy as a whole, but of a minority of the clergy, organized and carried forward by the logic of a false ideal. This great wrong to the Nation will have been wrought in the interest, not of the Church, but of a clericalist party within the Church. The Church of England, losing contact with the national life &amp; absorbed in its own affairs, can have but one future. It must shrivel ignobly into another sect, differing from the rest only in its episcopal polity, and in the extravagance of its spiritual pretensions.' &#8211; Is this too severe to be said with justice, or only too true to be said with prudence?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brought me from the London Library the book which seems to have influenced <persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName> &amp; even A. L. <persName xml:id="1170">Smith</persName> so deeply &#8211; <ref xml:id="866">"Political Theories of the Middle Age"</ref> by D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Otto Gierke, translated by F. W. Maitland. The translator's 'Introduction' is learned, suggestive, and racy, that is, it is thoroughly characteristic of the writer.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[436]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Arthur <persName xml:id="1916">Morgan</persName> came to see me about his continuance at the School. He was evidently rather uncomfortable in mind, and, as soon as I gave him the opportunity, made some surprising discoveries as to the state of the school. I told him that I would speak to the Headmaster, &amp; that he would perhaps send for him in due course. Then I took <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> for a walk, which was pleasant, as she is a good walker &amp; a good talker. After dinner <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> brought in one of the Vicars Choral of Lincoln, &amp; they sang much.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
