<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[617]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">538</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The sun&#8211;rise was magnificent, a 'radiant morn' indeed. The whole heaven glowed with rosy light. I preached to the troops from the phrase, "</hi><hi rend="underline">A thorn in the flesh</hi><hi>". They were very attentive. At Mattins I installed Canon <persName xml:id="3832">Jupp</persName>, who stayed to lunch. General <persName xml:id="3223">Gaisford</persName> came to spend the day here. The <persName xml:id="3438">Rogersons</persName><persName xml:id="3439"></persName> also lunched. I was surprised to hear him say that no less than 47 per cent of the recruits now coming in from this county had to be rejected, mainly for defective chest&#8211;measurement. Of course, as he points out, these are the mere leavings of our manhood, for the number of men already recruited from the county has been so great that nothing but rubbish is now left. I received a very pleasant, cheerful letter from </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName></hi><hi>, who has been at the front for some weeks: also a pleasant letter from <persName xml:id="1567">Symonds</persName> of Montreal. He has two sons at the front, who have been through most of the fighting unscathed. <persName xml:id="3969">Lord Goschen's</persName> heir &amp; only <persName xml:id="3970">son</persName> has been killed, that is, he has died of wounds in Mesopotamia. <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> and <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName> arrived before dinner. He has a short leave home from the front. He seems to be very depressed &amp; discontented, but his reports hardly justify his mood. Many deserters come in to us from the German trenches, and there would be many more, if it were not for the belief, sedulously encouraged by the officers, that they would immediately be shot by the English. Desertions from our trenches are, of course, unknown. General Gaisford went back to Newcastle after dinner. I read out to my family a very full &amp; informing appreciation of the present state &amp; future prospect of the War from "The Observer", which he left behind him.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
