<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[350]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">785</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was another Zeppelin raid last night, and it is said that bombs were dropped on York and Darlington, but we have no details, and the London papers are held up. There are rumours of considerable damage having been done.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Bank, and directed M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3901">Moult</persName> to purchase for me &#x00A3;500 of “War Savings".<note xml:id="321" n="1"></note> This costs &#x00A3;387.10.0: and still leaves in my deposit account </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;212.10.0.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 2 p.m. there was a special service for the Freemasons in connexion with the annual meeting of the Provincial Grand Lodge. Over 600 Freemasons attended the service, and made a fine spectacle in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="1559">Lord Barnard</persName> as P.G.M. occupied the Dean's stall, and <persName xml:id="3206">Victor Williamson</persName> as P.P.G.M. sate beside him. At 3 p.m. the annual meeting was held in the Chapter House which was filled to its utmost capacity. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I was admitted to the office of P.G.C. for the coming year.</hi> <hi>Lord Barnard, Victor Williamson, Lord <persName xml:id="3839">Maitland</persName>, <persName xml:id="3719">Gerald Liddell</persName>, and a stranger came into the Deanery, &amp;, had tea after the meeting.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received, corrected, &amp; returned the proof of my <ref xml:id="779">Edinburgh Review Article</ref>. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> wrote to me, &amp; enclosed the document which I have transcribed on the next page, and which she wants to have again in order that she may return it to its owner. It certainly "gives one to think". The authority of Christianity must have fallen very low in any community which could tolerate such a plan for repairing the wastage of war: but there is no reason why the 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Commandment should receive more consideration than the 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, when once War has claimed to govern its procedure by the plea of "Necessity".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[348]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Translation of a German document dated 20/2/16, found on a German Prisoner recently captured.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Committee for the increase of the Population"</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>Notice . No. 13875.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Sir,</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi>On account of all the able bodied men having been called to the Colours, it remains the duty of all those left behind, for the sake of the Fatherland, to interest themselves in the happiness of the married women and maidens by doubling or even trebling the number of births.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your name has been given to us as a capable man, &amp; you are herewith requested to take on this office of honour and to do your duty in right German style. It must here be pointed out that your wife or fianc&#x00E9;e will not be able to claim a divorce: it is in fact to be hoped that the women will bear this discomfort heroically for the sake of the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You will be given the district of …………. Should you not feel capable of coping with the situation, you will be given three days in which to name someone in your place.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On the other hand, if you are prepared to take on a second district as well, you will become a "Deckoffizier" and receive a pension.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An exhibition of women &amp; maidens as well as a collection of photographs is to be found at our office. You are requested to bring this letter with you.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your good work sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> commence immediately &amp; it is in your interests to submit to us a full report of results after 9 months.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>1ct Army 						</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>22/3/16</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>W. L. O. Twiss, Major</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>General Staff						</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>[marginal note:] It is, I think, now universally allowed that this document was an independent fabrication: but it passed as genuine with us in the fog of malicious credulity in which we were living in 1916. Herbert Dunelm: March 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1921.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
