<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[613]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">536</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> walked with me after lunch. He says that his mother, who is still living, was in her youth an admiring auditor of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> in his chapel at Brighton. The circumstances in which Robertson contracted his marriage were unfortunate. He was accused by the lady's father of paying too marked attention to his daughter, and so driven to make an offer of his hand. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is abundantly evident that the union was not happy</hi><hi rend="italic">. Reading between the lines both of his Letters and of his Sermons, one can discern the note of domestic desolation. He is one more instance of a strangely familiar phenomenon &#8211; the failure of great men's marriages. It is not easy to distribute the blame. The great man is many&#8211;sided, enigmatic, and surprising. He displays an aspect of himself to the lady with whom he is enamoured, which is as little representative of his character as, nay, far less representative than, his public performances in the pulpit, on the platform, in literature, on the stage, which create his fame.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The poor lady feels herself deluded and cast aside. It is as if she loved a man, &amp; found him in her arms transformed into an icicle! In Robertson's case the whole blunder was the more lamentable since he possessed an ardently affectionate nature which sought female affection, and found nothing better than the appropriating regard of that rather formidable Deborah, Lady <persName xml:id="3977">Byron</persName>, who perhaps did no good either to his character or to his influence. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3973">Robertston</persName> makes two appearances in the Biography, the one at her marriage, the other at his death!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
