<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[635]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">549</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>BRIGHTON
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The 'Times' gives a good place to my letter on <ref xml:id="869">"<persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton"</ref>, who was born just 100 years ago</hi><hi>. A clergyman, whose name I forget, volunteered very kindly to take me to the Monument in the extra&#8211;mural cemetery. It is much grown over by ivy, &amp; is less impressive than I had expected. I lunched at the Rectory with </hi><persName xml:id="3579"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon Hoskyns</hi></persName><hi>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Hoskyns is unusually pretty, &amp; attractive, not at all like the conventional parson's wife. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The lecture was well&#8211;attended, many persons being unable to find seats</hi><hi>. The Mayor, <persName xml:id="3232">Otter</persName>, son of a former <persName xml:id="3699">Bishop of Chichester</persName>, made too long an introductory speech, but well&#8211;conceived &amp; well&#8211;expressed. I spoke for nearly an hour. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">An old gentleman was introduced to me as one of Robertson's hearers. He said that he owed his religion to the teaching he heard in Trinity chapel</hi><hi>. The Dean of <persName xml:id="3967">Chichester</persName> told me that the Head of Barclay's Bank had told him that he was now so devoted to Robertson's sermons that he always carried a volume of them about with him, and read one daily, but that in his youth, though he resided in Brighton during Robertson's ministry, he would never allow himself to hear him preach lest he should create a scandal among his religious friends! It is certainly difficult to imagine such fanatical bigotry. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest Henson</persName></hi><hi>, in khaki, came to me afterwards. He has a commission in a Lancashire regiment, &amp; looks more manly in his uniform. The little girls, Ruth &amp; Joan, have struck up a mighty fondness for me, &amp; insisted on invading my bed&#8211;room, where I was writing, to smother me with Goodnight embracements! Bless them!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
