<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[701]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">586</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather continues to be wintry, but there were signs that the snow would soon be replaced by rain. The post brought me some letters from Bishops acknowledging copies of <ref xml:id="85">'Robertson'</ref> which, at my direction, the publishers had sent them. The Bishops of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="356">Alban's</persName> and <persName xml:id="602">Southwark</persName> wrote in terms of warm regard for a teacher, who had been much to them. I spent the morning mainly in an attempt to prepare notes for the lecture in Newcastle tomorrow. But the task is no easy one. <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> life is curiously uneventful, and uninteresting: and the psychological problem he himself presents is not attractive to the mixed multitude who resort to Sunday lectures. Probably it will be best to 'talk large' about the times in which he lived! The "Spectator" prints my letter <ref xml:id="871">"Sectarianism &amp; Secularisation"</ref>, &amp; adds a penitent editorial expressing agreement! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored through sleet to Hetton, &amp; there attended a squalid function in connection with the opening of another batch of <orgName xml:id="235">Aged Miners' Homes</orgName>. We got back about 9 p.m. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
