<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[458]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">737</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>About 11.30 p.m. my electric light went unsteady, &amp; then went out suddenly. This indicated the approach of Zeppelins. However, I went to bed. About 1 a.m. I was awaked by the sounds of exploding bombs, &amp; the whirring of a machine. I got up &amp; dressed hastily. For two hours we (for <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had followed suit, &amp; the maids had descended from their bedrooms to the wine–cellar) were in the College, listening &amp; waiting. About 3 a.m. we returned to bed, and an hour later the electric light assured us again of security.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is reported that very little injury was caused by the bombs. At one place the Zeppelins appear to have mistaken a burning slag heap for a munitions factory, and poured bombs into it. It is alleged that the 'Terror that flieth by night' was plainly visible from Palace Green: and that, among many other places, Jarrow was bombed. I wrote to <persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarbrough</persName> 'crying off' our engagement to spend the next week–end with her. It would be highly indecent for the Dean to be absent from the wrecking of the Cathedral!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> arrived just before Evensong: and <persName xml:id="2937">Penelope</persName> with her attendant nurse followed shortly afterwards.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
