<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[346]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">787</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most beautiful autumnal day, unfavourable by reason of its beauty to occupation indoors. I revised a sermon for tonight. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> brought me my quarter's cheque, which I forthwith paid into the Bank. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Thomas, the little shrivelled Welshman, who rules over S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi>. Giles', came to ask me to preach a Harvest Sermon, &amp; I weakly consented. I attended Evensong, &amp; later motored to Beamish, and preached at the Harvest Thanksgiving in the Parish Church. The Vicar, W. <persName xml:id="3841">Philp</persName> [Philps], says that his parish now contains 25,000 people: that the church, accommodating about 400 persons, and two Mission Rooms, which together may do as much, provide all the church accommodation there is. 800 sittings for 25,000 folk &#8211; a poor provision. I was interested to observe as part of the "decorations", three miner's picks with lighted lamps "piled" above a large lump of coal. The congregation sang with much heartiness, &amp; listened very attentively. I repeated the sermon which I preached at Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne. <persName xml:id="4065">Youd</persName> had to drive with extraordinary care &amp; caution, as there was a heavy mist. I gave a lift home to a young assistant &#8211; mine manager. Rutherford. On arriving in the deanery, I found that <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had returned from Scotland.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
