<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[611]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">535</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Oakley, an architect from Clifton, came to see the Kitchen. I showed him and a friend over the house.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName> sent for my acceptance a complete set of the Vanity Fair Album. The cartoons of public men of the last generation is of much interest, and no inconsiderable value. I am glad to possess them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I worked at the <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> Lecture all day, but with very unsatisfactory result. It is difficult to make much of a career which was obscure until its last six years, which was cut short at 37, and which was linked with no great personalities or great events of a stirring time. A proprietary chapel at Brighton is an uninviting kind of Nazareth for a modern prophet to come from! Even as a character&#8211;study Robertson is unsatisfactory, for he was plainly morbid. Incipient brain disease suggests itself throughout, &amp; makes it difficult to give a just value to his vehement language. It is the more difficult to explain his sudden, wide&#8211;spread, &amp; practically undisputed popularity after death because he has no personal connexion with any really considerable issue which divided men. The annals of Chartism would hardly include a reference to a few more or less sympathetic words spoken by an obscure man, in an obscure (relatively) pulpit. The fierce controversies which rent the Anglican Church, &amp; absorbed </hi><hi rend="underline">its</hi><hi> mind, when Europe was traversing the revolutionary crisis of 1848, did not receive from him any direction perceptible at the time: &amp; probably nobody outside Brighton knew that he had sought to mitigate the 'No&#8211;Popery' zeal of 1851.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
