<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[344]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">788</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished preparing a sermon for Sunday, and wrote to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to Muggleswick. The train carried us as far as Shotley Bridge, and there M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3822">Ritson</persName> met us with the car, and took is to his house on the moors, 850 feet above sea level, hard by the little church of Muggleswick. Here I preached at the Harvest Thanksgiving, repeating the sermon which I had already preached at Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne and Beamish. The little church was fairly filled, a congregation of about 70 persons sufficed for the purpose. As this parish adjoins Stanhope, there was a special fitness about the references to <persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler</persName>, which my discourse contained. The parson, A. H. <persName xml:id="3840">Smith</persName>, is a rather pompous little man, with a very clerical manner, but he appears to work hard, and to have plenty to do. His small population (362) is scattered over a large area, and served by two churches. The endowment, about &#x00A3;350 net, arises mainly from glebe. One farm is some 15 miles distant. This he desires greatly to sell to the Eccles: Com</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">S</hi><hi>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Ritson supports him strongly herein, &amp;, indeed, it seems a reasonable desire. "I like ye well enough as a minister, but I don't like ye as a parson" &#8211; was the observation of the wife of one of his glebe&#8211;holders; and it is probably a general sentiment. There is an apparent conflict between the character of pastor and landlord which inevitably occasions friction. On the other hand, the severing of a link with the secular life of the parishioners implies a diminution of social importance &amp; the loss of at least the potency of spiritual influence. A very similar case was that of the clergy being Justices of the Peace.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
