<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[639]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916. Westminster.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">552</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Abbey at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. Then at Mattins I preached at <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. There was a great crowd. Outside the church were <persName xml:id="1670">Reggie Woodyear</persName> and <persName xml:id="2197">Aleck Pleasaunce</persName> in khaki. The latter has been through many experiences culminating in Suvla Bay, but he retains the childish, almost babyish, face. <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> came into the vestry, looking very smart &amp; soldierlike [sic]. He said that he had got some weeks sick leave. I preached for exactly half an hour on "<persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton". There was some coughing which annoyed me: but mainly the congregation was attentive. <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName> &amp; Harold went with us some way on our walk to Sir Aleck Lawrence, where we made a call to see him &amp; his wife. Then we lunched pleasantly with the <persName xml:id="65">Chelmsfords</persName><persName xml:id="1857"></persName>. They are evidently pleased (and how could they be otherwise?) with his appointment to the Viceroyalty of India. I had a long talk with Chelmsford. He told me that the income &amp; allowances of the Viceroy amount to about £</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">60,000</hi><hi> a year: &amp; that there is abundance of money. This is as it should be. He evidently thinks that the situation in Mesopotamia is precarious. <persName xml:id="3966">Townshend</persName> had provisions for a month on Jan</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ry</hi><hi> 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. With economy, he might hold out to the end of February. He said that the appointment of a Hindoo [sic] as legal member of the Viceroy's council led to the curious anomaly that appeals on ecclesiastical causes from Christian Churches in India w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> come before a pagan!! He proposed to mitigate this by taking such appeals, of which there are not many, into his own hands. From the Chelmsfords we went to <persName xml:id="2069">Sir John</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Lady Barron</persName> [Barran] &amp; then to Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName> (where we met Goad, the author of "the Kingdom"), and the <persName xml:id="973">Lawleys</persName><persName xml:id="3264"></persName>. Finally we had tea with <persName xml:id="1391">Lord</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1388">Lady Glenconner</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
