<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[652]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">631</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A warm, clouded, rather blustering day. I went to the Cathedral, and received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> was the Celebrant. There were 13 communicants beside the clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The newspapers report the capture of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Roger <persName xml:id="252">Casement</persName></hi><hi> in an attempt to land German guns in Ireland. There can be no question of </hi><hi rend="underline">his</hi><hi> treason, yet many of us will be distressed if the man who exposed the horrors of the rubber&#8211;hunters in Africa &amp; in S. America should perish as a traitor. His extravagant conduct suggests mental aberration. One cannot play the Paladin in the tropics with impunity.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The reception of the German gun lent by the War&#8211;Office for public exhibition in the city of Durham is to be made the occasion of oratory! What can be usefully spoken is not apparent. A German gun is the symbol of that Militarism, which Prussia embodies, &amp; which must be destroyed. It is also a symbol of Modern War, in which artillery plays the decisive part. A captured German gun is the pledge of coming victory, the first&#8211;fruits of the conquest of militarism which is to recompense us for the sorrows &amp; sacrifices of the War. It reminds us of the cost of victory, for it is an instrument of mutilation and death. Its public exhibition is designed to strengthen our resolution; and to cheer our hearts. We pledge ourselves to support the men at the front, to hold loyally together, &amp; to see the War through. I should like to seize the opportunity of saying what I really think of <persName xml:id="4024">Northcliffe</persName> &amp; the other plotters against the Government: but, perhaps, one has best steer clear of anything even remotely polemical (in the domestic sense of the word). I changed a cheque for &#x00A3;40: and gave half of it to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> for wages &amp;c. Then I made some essays in clearing up my study &#8211; a hopeless task. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[650]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="676">Tennyson</persName> on <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName>:</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'My father would say: "The first time I met Robertson I felt that he expected something notable from me because I knew that he admired my poems, that he wished to pluck the heart form my mystery: so for the life of me from pure nervousness I could talk of nothing but beer".'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>v. Alfred Lord Tennyson, A Memoir vol. I. p. 264.</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3629">Kingsley</persName> on Teetotalism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>v. "Charles Kingsley, His Letters &amp; memoirs of his Life, edited by his Wife. 2 vols." vol. I. p. 270 ff.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a considerable gathering of people in the market&#8211;place, when the German gun arrived: it was escorted by a troop of the D.L.I. commanded by Major <persName xml:id="3922">Johnson</persName>. The Mayor formally received it from the Major, &amp; then made a speech: after him I spoke, &amp; <persName xml:id="3438">Rogerson</persName>, &amp; one of the officers. Then the band played "God Save the King", &amp; we went home. I shewed M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Barclay the Cathedral relics, and the Deanery: and then attended Evensong.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
