<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[502]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">703</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"On seeing certain wealthy foreigners in Rome carrying puppies and young monkeys about in their bosoms and fondling them, Caesar asked, we are told, if the women in their country did not bear children, thus in right princely fashion rebuking those who squander on animals that proneness to love &amp; loving affection which is ours by nature, and which is due only to our fellow&#8211;men." (Plutarch 'Pericles')</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This is a sarcasm which can be transferred from the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> century B.C. to the 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> A.D. without losing its point. The coincidence of the Report on 'The Falling Birth&#8211;rate' with the appearance of long casualty lists is painfully suggestive. Can modern society with its present habitudes &amp; ideals replace the myriads who are perishing in the War?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the course of the forenoon I called on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Serres, the Vicar, whom I found in his little study, busied with preparing a sermon. We talked for half an hour, mainly about the forthcoming Mission. I did not find any clearer understanding of this spiritual venture here in the Archbishop's diocese than elsewhere: and I inferred from the Vicar's language that the clergy of Thanet are more perplexed than eager. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Serres himself would appear to take a sufficiently simple view of the religious situation. War is God's punishment on national sins: &amp; will not cease until adequate national repentance has been evoked. Hence the urgency of the Mission! I bought some cigarettes for <persName xml:id="77">Marion's</persName> wounded heroes, on my way home.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked on the cliffs in the direction of Minnis Bay. We observed with interest the barbed&#8211;wire defences which were ranged along the exposed places on the coast. On the way we fell in with a wounded soldier who had arrived yesterday from France. He was from Edinburgh, &amp; belonged to the Borderers.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
