<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[410]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">763</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="1682" display="no">Colin Kennedy</persName>, who is in the great push. It contains the following:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"What I see out here, makes me wish more than ever that the war was over. The things one sees are too awful to mention. We have just come out of action, I, personally, without a scratch, but other, unfortunately, not so fortunate. I have always realised, Rector, that at times of crisis there is nothing so wonderful as one's religion, and during the last week this has been proved over &amp; over again. It will, I am perfectly convinced, help me to the very end".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Mostly the letters anent the Somme Films are hostile, some also abusive. I discern three streams of opinion in the defence of the exhibition: 1. The </hi><hi rend="underline">political</hi><hi>. 'It will stimulate &amp; sustain the war&#8211;spirit in the nation. 2. The </hi><hi rend="underline">popular</hi><hi>. "It is enormously welcome to the 'thrill&#8211;seeking' crowds which fill normally the cinematograph halls. 3. The </hi><hi rend="underline">sentimental</hi><hi>, mostly feminine. Bereaved women want to see what their dear boy saw &amp;c &#8211; a morbid feeling capable of gross developments. Probably we should add an element of genuine </hi><hi rend="underline">curiosity</hi><hi>. The "Times" contains some more hostile letters, &amp; one on my side from that amiable savant, Ray <persName xml:id="3761">Lankester</persName>. I wrote letters, &amp; fooled away the morning. After Evensong I took <persName xml:id="1318">Cunningham</persName>, (who is our guest for the meeting of the British Association) for a brief walk. He also tends to grow old: and privately confessed to having had a slight stroke. So we soon turned back, and spent the remainder of the day quietly. He retired to bed about 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
