<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[492]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">707</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Am I altogether wrong in not only disapproving the project of the so&#8211;called National Mission, but also resenting the method by which it was determined upon? Am I wholly unreasonable in resenting the issue of prayers for the Divine Blessing on a project, which I disapprove, and which I am thus indirectly coerced into supporting? Am I sinfully sceptical in thinking that such Prayers can have little value, &amp; may be actually debilitating?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished <persName xml:id="1318">Cunningham's</persName> "Christianity and Politics", which I found to be both interesting, suggestive, and informing. His account of the English Reformation is affected, but less than I expected by his Tractarianism; and he certainly exaggerates the difference between English and Scottish Religion: but his criticisms on the Nonconformist position are acute, &amp;, though often severe, rarely unjust. I think he exaggerates both the value of political party, and the powerlessness of the men [sic] who stands [sic] outside parties. He points his moral effectively by references to the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon we went to a party for the wounded given by the officers who are staying in a hotel on the cliff. The entertainment was marred by a sudden and violent downpour of rain, after which I slipped away, finding myself bored. Later we attended a performance of the National School children in aid of the children of Belgium. I was moved to reflection by the two most applauded items &#8211; the one represented the flirting of a young couple in the cornfields, the other exhibited the police in a ludicrous aspect. The first would hardly assist the chastity of the girls: the last would certainly weaken the discipline of the boys! '</hi><hi rend="underline">And what will ye do in the end thereof</hi><hi>?'</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
