<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[689]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
      </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">577</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The snow was falling briskly when I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., for the Holy Communion. Three minor canons present, but no major. The Canon&#8211;in&#8211;Residence has an excuse, being a Professor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote some more of the "Judges" sermon, but it goes badly. The scanty congregation of old ladies, &amp; college girls, the one bigotted the other frivolous, is not like the congregation of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret's.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName></hi><hi> dilates on the character of Abp. Tillotson in a letter to <persName xml:id="3957">Hurd</persName> written in 1752, the very year of <persName xml:id="1856">Butler's</persName> death. </hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"As a preacher, I suppose, his established fame is chiefly owing to his being the first City&#8211;divine who talked rationally and wrote purely."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>What does W. mean by this? The London clergy had been strongly Presbyterian at the Restoration: then they became ardently Anglican, &amp; vehemently Protestant &#8211; characters not then thought to be incongruous.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"No orator in the Greek &amp; Roman sense of the word, like Taylor: nor a discourser in their sense, like <persName xml:id="3892">Barrow</persName>; free from their irregularities, but not able to reach their heights. On which account I prefer them infinitely to him. You cannot sleep with Taylor; you cannot forbear thinking with Barrow. But you may be much at your ease in the midst of a long lecture from Tillotson; clear, &amp; rational, &amp; equable as he is. Perhaps the last quality may account for it."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Warburton did not himself excel as a preacher. He was pompous, vapid, &amp; stilted, save when he dealt with historical &amp; political topics when he was as discursive &amp; paradoxical as in his more elaborate compositions. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2663">his wife</persName>: &amp; attended Evensong. Also I wrote to the <persName xml:id="4080">Master of Jesus</persName>, and to <persName xml:id="3513">Cummings</persName> who is [in] hospital with a leg damaged in a motor accident.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
