<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[641]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">553</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters at the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; lunched with the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>. The War is not improving either of them. They can talk of noting else: &amp; religion has come to be but the parasite of animosities &amp; anxieties. <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> took me for a walk in the Parks, and shewed me his children, charming to look at all of them. He presented me with a German rifle. We had some talk about his experiences at the front. He categorically assured me (and as this is first–hand testimony, I record it) that he had himself seen the body of a Belgian woman with the breasts cut off, &amp; otherwise mutilated; also that of man from which the genitals had been hacked off. He said that the R.C. priests who served as British chaplains were often low fellows given to telling loose stories: that he had only heard of one man being shot for rape: that the French women in billets solicited the British soldiers with considerable success: that there was much swearing &amp; comparatively little serous vice: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that the hatred of our men against the Germans was intense: that there was rarely any quarter given on either side</hi><hi>: that the German sniping was greatly superior to ours: that the incompetence of the British staff was flagrant, confessed, and bitterly resented: that the personal superiority of the British over the German soldiers was completely established: that there was the utmost confidence in our ranks. This was the gist of Harold's testimony which, perhaps, may be accepted as the echo of the opinions which had found expression in the companies which he has frequented: possibly it may be representative of more. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[643]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined with the <orgName xml:id="66">Brotherhood</orgName>, which met at <persName xml:id="216">Gow's</persName> house. The War and total Abstinence have well nigh killed social intercourse: &amp; we all grow older! Perhaps, also, my absence from London has isolated me from the general life more than I had quite realized. Anyway I did not enjoy the evening, &amp; felt that such conversation as proceeded went aside from me – a new sensation more wholesome than pleasing. </hi><hi rend="italic underline"><persName xml:id="1173">William Temple</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> grows monstrously fat. He will look like the pictures of Tom <persName xml:id="2095" display="no">Fuller</persName>, but I doubt whether he has his geniality and humour. </hi><persName xml:id="3581"><hi rend="italic underline">Barnes</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, the new Master of the Temple, has rather a sleek aspect, &amp; submissive manner: but he has a thoughtful face, &amp; improves on acquaintance.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
