<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[663]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">564</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Two officers called on me to arrange for the church&#8211;going of their officer&#8211;training company. They decided to attend the military service if they could have seats reserved, &amp; would number between 50 &amp; 60. Both these officers had been at the Front, &amp; had been wounded. They expected to go out again: meanwhile they are usefully employed in training the new officers. I wrote a little sermon for next Sunday. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="494">Mark Pattison</persName></hi><hi> says that the latter half of George II's reign is 'perhaps the least&#8211;known portion of the history of the English Church'; and that 'the life of <persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName>, which was passed wholly on the highways, and open to public inspection, is peculiarly calculated as a mirror of the clerical life of the XVIII</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century, or at least of the clerical section of it'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Warburton</hi><hi> "was well acquainted with the history of the Civil War, and told <persName xml:id="3957">Hurd</persName> that '</hi><hi rend="underline">there was scarcely a memoir or a pamphlet published between 1640 and 1660 which he had not read'</hi><hi>." It would hardly occur to most men to suggest a likeness between Warburton and Gladstone, yet Pattison succeeds in doing so: </hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"In reviewing the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Divine Legation</hi><hi rend="italic">, we cannot help being forcibly reminded of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Homeric Studies</hi><hi rend="italic"> of M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gladstone. The differences between the two men are many and radical: the intellectual character of the two works is the same. A comprehensive general reading; an heroic industry in marshalling the particulars of the proof: a dialectical force of arm which would twist a bar of iron to its purposes: and all brought to bear to prove a perverse and preposterous proposition. The mischief done by such powerful efforts of human reason is not in the diffusion of erroneous opinion, but in setting brilliant examples of a false method."</hi>
         </p>
         
</div>
            <p>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
