<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[550]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">687</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brought me two very interesting letters from 'the Front'. One from my godson, </hi><persName xml:id="554"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi></persName><hi>, who is 'in a valley which has earned for itself the unenviable name of "the Valley of Death"'; the other, from </hi><persName xml:id="1708"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aleck Beechey</hi></persName><hi> who 'is patrolling the Suez Canal'. The last contains this rather discouraging account of the soldier's religion:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"You asked me about the religious feelings of the men. At Gallipoli, if we had a chance, we usually had a fairly well attended evening service on Sundays, but I usually found that the most plucky and best fighters were conspicuous by their absence. I met a good many R.C., and we had a few in the Regiment: and their Religion seemed to have a greater hold on them than ours. They very seldom missed early Mass on Sundays. I think the average English soldier is a fatalist, </hi><hi rend="underline">when your number is up, you have to go sort of style</hi><hi>."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I managed to write both to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi> and to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi><hi>. It were [sic] ungenerous to keep such letters as theirs unanswered. I attended Evensong, and walked with Logick [sic]. Then I went to the Post Office, and obtained a petrol&#8211;reporting form, &amp; filled it in as best I could without guidance. Then I copied out more of the Reformation entries from my transcript of the <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, Westminster, records. They certainly give a vivid picture of the religious changes which accumulated with dazzling rapidity during the years 1540&#8211;1560. That period of 20 years has but two rivals in our history viz. 1060&#8211;1080 and 1640&#8211;1660. Later </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Fry</hi><hi>, a Shakespearian reciter, who is to perform in aid of the little hospital tomorrow, arrived to be our guest at the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
