<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[452]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">742</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="1261">Violet Carruthers</persName>, condoling her on the death of her brother, <persName xml:id="3771">Sir Arthur Markham</persName>, whose factious conduct in Parliament has long been notorious. Also I wrote <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, sending him a copy of "Discipline &amp; Law".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, &amp; then spent the morning in reading Usher's <ref xml:id="819">"Rise &amp; Fall of the High Commission"</ref>, which is not precisely exhilarating! But it brings out the profoundly suggestive fact that the High Commission, which figures so largely in the accepted version of Laud's tyranny, did by no means merit the abuse of the Puritans. It was an exceptionally competent, expeditious, humane, and (among suitors) popular Court. Indeed its merits were a main reason for its overthrow, since it was the most effective agent for restraining Puritanism. 'After all,' observes M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Usher, 'the vehemence of the Puritans was caused less by the Commission's methods than by its objects'. There is an impressive resemblance between the attitude of the Puritans towards the High Commission, &amp; that of our modern Ritualists towards the Courts.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked with Logic round Houghall Wood: &amp; attended Evensong. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The afternoon post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName> now at Edinburgh. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> kept to her bedroom all day, not feeling well. The weather was close &amp; unwholesome.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
