<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[587]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">528</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"I wish I did not hate preaching so much, but the degradation of being a Brighton preacher is almost intolerable. '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I cannot dig, to beg I am ashamed</hi><hi rend="italic">;' but I think there is not a hard&#8211;working artisan whose work does not seem to me to constitute him a worthier and higher being than myself."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> wrote this when he was on the pinnacle of such fame as preachers can obtain. Nor was this a fleeting sentiment. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Again and again he protests his contempt for preaching, especially for popular preaching</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Yet nothing is more certain than that preaching was his very life: and its effectiveness as a moral and spiritual agent has hardly ever been exceeded. His contemporaries, indeed, mainly ignored him: but his posthumous influence has been, and still is, enormous. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> tells me that a German translation of the sermons has been published within the last few years</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">/</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to church at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> was the celebrant. In the afternoon I walked with <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName> in the Library, and then went to Evensong in the Cathedral. I wrote to Mary <persName xml:id="1204">Radford</persName>, and returned his sermon to the <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol</persName>. It is a well&#8211;intentioned discourse, &amp; well&#8211;expressed, but it is carefully guarded after the well&#8211;known episcopal manner against any risk of being applied to the immediate issue of Kikuyu. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">On the whole, I incline to think that the position of an English Bishop is so unfavourable to any real independence of thought or action, that the acceptance of a bishoprick would involve some forfeiture of self&#8211;respect. It is the hateful milieu of diocesan secretaries &amp; holy women which does the mischief. Smothered by the pettiest routine, the mind grows to the measurements of the hierarchical strait&#8211;jacket, &amp; ceases to move or grow</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
