<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[681]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">573</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached on 'The Fall of Man' to the troops, taking for my text the pregnant sentence of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John: "Sin is lawlessness". The men were very attentive, especially, perhaps, because I read as a lesson the narrative of the Expulsion from Eden, and discussed it frankly. I attended Mattins &amp; listened to another sermon from <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName>. Then I celebrated the Holy Communion. After lunch Charles Abbey accompanied me to Tanfield, where I preached to a large congregation in the parish church, at a special service of "Thanksgiving for mercies received during the War". I made a speech, rather than delivered a sermon, proposing 4 special subjects for Thanksgiving: 1. Because we were led to a right decision in August 1914: 2. Because the Empire had proved its loyalty so magnificently. 3. Because our soldiers and sailors had carried themselves so nobly. 4. Because the nation had been so united. These were the pegs of my discourse, which I brought to an end with some earnest words of self&#8211;criticism. The people listened very closely, &amp; were, I hope, usefully impressed. We got back to the Deanery about 5.30 p.m. <persName xml:id="4065">Youd</persName> drove the car admirably. There was much snow in the higher reaches of the country. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> came in to see me after dinner to 'ask my advice'. This meant that he was casting eyes of coveting on the organist's position at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi>Paul's Cathedral left vacant by the death of Sir <persName xml:id="2648">George Martin</persName>. He wanted me to write to the Dean on his behalf: and this I could not but promise to do, though, indeed, I have little doubt that the Dean &amp; Chapter have long since made up their minds as to the matter. The mere notion of Cully's [Culley's] departure alarms me. If he were to go, &amp; <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> take the living of Norham which will be vacant after Easter, I should truly be faced by a difficult situation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
