<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[454]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">741</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>"O God, whose never&#8211;failing providence ordereth all things both in heaven and earth; We humbly beseech thee to put away from us all hurtful things, and to give us those things which be profitable for us; through Jesus Christ our Lord." Amen.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Both Epistle and Gospel place a threatening emphasis on congruous living as the indispensable accompaniment and consequence of genuine discipleship. "</hi><hi rend="underline">For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of God</hi><hi>", writes </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">S. Paul</hi><hi>. "</hi><hi rend="underline">A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit; neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit</hi><hi>", said </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Christ</hi><hi>, adding with reference to "</hi><hi rend="underline">false prophets</hi><hi>", "</hi><hi rend="underline">Wherefore, by their fruits ye shall know them</hi><hi>."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, &amp; heard a characteristic sermon from <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> on the text: 1. Peter iv.16, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Let him glorify God in this Name</hi><hi>". The effect of his preaching was curiously affected in my mind by recollections of the absurdities of "conscientious objectors". At least they have succeeded in disestablishing the Christian martyrs in my mind, and, I suspect, also in the minds of many others. After Mattins I celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 9 communicants other than the clergy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I picked up in the cloisters a young Canadian soldier &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="underline"> lieut: </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Samuel Gardiner</hi><hi> from Toronto &#8211; &amp; brought him in to lunch. Afterwards I went round the Cathedral with him. He told me that he was 23 years old, &amp; ambitious of becoming a lawyer. I found him a modest and intelligent youth, eager to learn all he could. He is stationed near Blyth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked for an hour. The sultriness of the atmosphere makes all exertion unpleasing, and predisposes to slumber.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[452]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="117">Rashdall's</persName></hi> <ref xml:id="818">"<hi rend="underline">Conscience &amp; Christ</hi>"</ref> is an excellent &amp; timely piece of work. Naturally it receives but a sneering welcome from the "Church Times". I found unexpectedly 3 copies of a little book of Lenten addresses, which I published in 1898, while resident in Ilford, under the title <ref xml:id="7">'Discipline &amp; Law'</ref>. What a chasm parts the Incumbent of the Ilford Hospital from the Dean of Durham! The difference in status is but an inadequate index of the deeper differences in mind, feeling, interest, &amp; purpose. There is something terrifying in this <hi rend="underline">necromancy</hi><hi>!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
