<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[498]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">705</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a long &amp; affectionate letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi>: &amp; this I answered in the course of the morning on the view that one knows not how long the War will spare the boy. There are no less than 26 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> lieutenants reported dead in this morning's 'Times'. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><hi> describes the cashiering of a young officer for drunkenness:&#8211; </hi>
</p><div type="quote"><p>"It was a very sad but quite impressive sight. All the officers of the whole Brigade were summoned to brigade headquarters. We had to fall in two deep, forming three sides of a hollow square, &amp; while standing to attention the prisoner was marched into the hollow of the square by the adjutant and an officer of his own rank acting as escort. The prisoner, deprived of his Sam Browne Belt and hatless, had to stand thus in front of about 200 officers of all ranks while the Brigade Major read the sentence out in the form of a letter to the Officers of the Brigade from the Secretary of the Army Council. The prisoner, after the reading of this letter, was dismissed by the General, and had to walk away alone, no longer an officer. The General gave us a short lecture after the proceedings in <hi rend="bold">[496]</hi><hi> which he said that since the beginning of the War 6040 officers had been dismissed for drink, women, and money difficulties. We all felt very sorry for the poor chap who had to go through such an ordeal, as it seemed rather brutal, and savoured somewhat of medievalism. This particular youth was only 21 years of age, but quite irresponsible, and seemed to have no control over his appetite for drink. His morals too seemed sadly affected."</hi>
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi>All this accords with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3719">Gerald Liddell's</persName></hi><hi> account of his experiences at Havre (v. 510). On the other hand, the Vicar here at Birchington assures me that he has observed no ill consequences to the parochial morals from the presence of the soldiers quartered here. But, indeed, is it really doubtful that the sudden removal of conventional restraints would have lamentable consequences in the case of the young men of the lower middle class, to whom, with culpable rashness, commissions have been given? They take up most easily those elements of the Army&#8211;tradition which are most intelligible, and easiest to learn. These unhappily are precisely the worst elements &#8211; profanity, lechery, a devil&#8211;may&#8211;care recklessness. Chivalry, an almost pastoral concern for their men, a loyal obedience to superiors, a noble self&#8211;respect &#8211; these higher constituents of the British Officer's character are not soon understood or soon acquired. There are 'natural gentlemen' like </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi><hi>, who do acquire them, or, rather, find themselves accordant with them, &amp; so without effort adopt them in practice, but for the most part of men, the case is otherwise, &amp; the failure as complete as it is almost inevitable.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
