<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[647]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916. Lichfield.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">555</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright frosty morning leading in a fine cold day. I walked with mine hostess in the garden after breakfast, and then wrote letters. To luncheon came M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3624">Palmer</persName>, reputed a poet, and his wife. The young man is the son of <persName xml:id="3623">Sir Alfred Palmer</persName> our High Sheriff, &amp; bears some facial resemblance to his sire. In spite of a rather bumptious manner he did not offend me, &amp;, as he had visited &amp; was keen about the Yellowstone Park, I found some common matter for conversation. After luncheon <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwood</persName> walked with me in the fields. We conversed mainly about politics: in spite of many &amp; awkward styles set in the midst of lakes of trodden mire, I enjoyed the exercise, &amp; felt the better for it. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After tea I wrote several letters, including one of condolence to Canon <persName xml:id="3832">Jupp</persName> on the death (long&#8211;expected) of his wife.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There came to dinner the officer commanding this district, Colonel Thorold, a relative, he told me, of the late <persName xml:id="4075">Bishop of Winchester</persName>. He talked freely and well, with much intelligence and humour. He told me that the Amir of Afghanistan was admitted to the same Freemasons' Lodge as that to which he himself belonged, and that he had been present at his admission. He said that he knew General <persName xml:id="3966">Townshend</persName>, now beleagured [sic] by the Turks in Mesopotamia, &amp; that he was fully persuaded that in no circumstances would he capitulate to the enemy. He avouched himself fully confident of our victory over Germany, but would venture no prediction as to the date of that happy event. The 'Times' military correspondent reckons that Germany still possesses a reserve of at least 2,000,000 men!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
