<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[667]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">566</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A white frost giving everything an aspect of winter, but bright &amp; beautiful. <persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName> celebrated, rather slowly but with reverence. I communicated, and ministered the consecrated Bread. I preached to the soldiers at 10 a.m.: but there was much coughing from the grammar&#8211;school cadets. For my text I took the opening verse of Genesis, &amp; added the sentence about the creation of man in God's image. The men seemed to be attentive. After Mattins, when L. preached a very conventional sermon (filled with those pietistic phrases, which Robertson called "sickening cant") the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> &amp; I walked for nearly an hour.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A stranger, the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. Harold E. Bucke</hi><hi>, writes to me the following:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"In a delightful chat I once had with <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> son, Charles Boyd <persName xml:id="3971">Robinson</persName>, he told me </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that on one occasion the whole of the then Cabinet Ministry came down to Brighton for the week&#8211;end in order to hear his father preach</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I suspect that this is an unintentional exaggeration, based perhaps on a misapprehension. If </hi><hi rend="italic underline">some</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cabinet ministers happened to be present, it would be the most natural thing in the world for some one [sic], perhaps the Preacher himself, to say "We had the whole Cabinet here this morning". Charles Boyd Robertson was still a small boy when his father died.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1696"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Olive</hi></persName><hi> writes from her hospital about the wounded soldiers. </hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The hardships &amp; horrors through which the men have past seem without exception to soften the older men, &amp; harden the young ones. It is very seldom that they will talk of their experiences, and only when they are alone with you, &amp; it just makes you hate yourself because you can't do more for them."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
