<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[676]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">618</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A cloudy damp morning, but improving as the day advanced. I went to the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> celebrated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Sir William <persName xml:id="3673">Worsley</persName>, who is here for the <orgName xml:id="276">Bede College</orgName> Meeting, was very interesting at breakfast. His two sons are soldiers: &amp; one was wounded at Suvla Bay, &amp; recommended for the Military Cross. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brought me a cheerful letter from <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>. He has been home on leave, &amp; has now gone back to the front, where his duties have been sufficiently gruesome. He had to go trench&#8211;digging in ground which had been the scene of some fierce fighting last year:</hi>
         </p>

<div type="quote">

         <p>
"Wherever the pickaxes &amp; spades were thrust they encountered dead Germans &amp; French. Body after body was desecrated, &amp; all along the sides of the trench we were digging, arms and legs protruded, &amp; scraps of clothing &amp;c. The smell was overpowering, and many of our men, who seem to stand a good deal by this time, were violently sick. The night was inky dark, &amp; it began to rain. The whole business was pretty gruesome." </p></div><p> Could anything be more horrible &amp; disgusting?
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the Easter Sermon. We entertained at lunch the members of the <orgName xml:id="95">National Society's Commission</orgName> &amp; the Bede College Committee. These were <persName xml:id="3583">Lord Armstrong</persName> (a large flabby man, with an impulsive manner, &amp; a feeble face), the <persName xml:id="2980">Bishop of <persName xml:id="2980">Wakefield</persName></persName>, Sir William <persName xml:id="3673">Worsley</persName>, Canon <persName xml:id="3672">Paterson</persName>, <persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName>, the architect, the Secretary, and <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>. After lunch <persName xml:id="1178" display="no">Clarence</persName> &amp; I went to work at clearing away the ivy bed, &amp; removed 40 barrow&#8211;loads of earth in two hours. I attended the special service in the Cathedral, &amp; heard a careful discourse from <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic">May came to ask me whether he ought to offer himself for a commission. That was more than I could answer!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
