<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[580]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">674</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I began the day by slipping on the steps to the Hall, and bruizing my arm and ribs uncomfortably. This untoward occurrence disinclined me for work. Beyond writing some letters, and attending Mattins and Evensong, I did little but read the newspapers. These are, of course, filled with obituary notices of Lord <persName xml:id="3556">Kitchener</persName>. An order has been issued requiring officers to wear an armlet of crepe for a week. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> went into town, and got himself properly equipped. I ordered the "Dead March" to be played at the end of Evensong. The afternoon post brought back to me the little letter which I had addressed to the "Times", together with an editorial explanation rather offensively worded as I thought. At dinner I got together a little company &#8211; the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>, <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, <persName xml:id="3585">Boutflower</persName>, <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>, a Winchester master who is examining for the King's Scholarships, and a Winchester minor canon, who is being examined for a B.D. degree. After the visitors had departed, Ernest read from "Martin Chuzzlewit" the ludicrous description of the dinner&#8211;party at 'Todgers', when M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Pecksniff became enormously drunken, &amp; irrepressibly didactic. He read very well, and with such evident enjoyment that he compels his hearers to enter into the fun. It is apparent that literature has much attraction for him. His love of Shakespeare is deep, &amp; sincere. The proof of it is his habit of carrying a little volume of plays on his person, and 'memorizing' (such is his phrase) the salient passages. Whatever may be thought of the range of the studies at McGill University, it must in fairness be allowed that the method of teaching cannot be altogether faulty, since it leaves a continuing intellectual interest in the minds subjected to it.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
