<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[484]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">711</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> took me with him on a visit to Lindisfarne, which he had to make on ecclesiastical business. So we made a day of it. Leaving Durham by the 8.15 train, we went as far as Alnemouth [sic], &amp; there were met by a motor, which took us first to Alnwick where the constable (Kyle) and the Librarian shewed us over the castle. Most part of the great pile is <persName xml:id="3917">Salvin's</persName> work in the early part of the last century: but there are substantial portions which date from the early 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> and 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> centuries. There are many fine pictures by Italian Masters in the state rooms. The view across the park is magnificent. Leaving the castle, we went to the "Northumberland Arms", &amp; lunched. Then we got into the motor &amp; started for Beal, which is the point of departure for Lindisfarne. We had proceeded but a few miles, when our progress was arrested by a puncture. The "jack" which was requisite for raising the car in order to remove the punctured tyre, &amp; replace it, proved altogether useless: &amp; we were in a quandary. However we were fortunate in getting from an adjacent house &#8211; the lodge of some gentleman's park &#8211; the loan of a crow&#8211;bar. With this we were able to prise up the car &amp; get a sound wheel in position. Resuming our journey we went forward &amp; arrived on the beach only to find ourselves confronted by a considerable expanse of water. It was just on the turning of high tide. However the tide runs out so quickly that the delay was much shorter than we feared. The postman &#8211; a deaf but not doltish youth who had been rejected for the army &#8211; drove us across, the waters at one stage rising above the axle tree. In about an hour we were safely deposited at the village. Here we were hospitably entertained at tea by the Church warden (Wilson) and afterwards escorted to the church and </hi><hi rend="bold">[482] </hi><hi>ruined Priory. The first is not uninteresting, but the last is most fascinating. Seen in the warm light of a declining sun in July the red sandstone glows, and the light green grass out of which the ruins rise forms a pleasing contrast. Add a circumference of blue sea, dotted by the dark lines of the Farne Islands, and the mass of Bamborough Castle, and you have the salient features of a romantically beautiful scene. An old fisherman who was mending his nets told me that he had seen the wild duck lying on the shore with their wings glued together by the petrol from the sunken German submarines, unable therefore to fly, &amp; so perishing of hunger. How unexpected are the consequences of war! We returned across the sands from which the tide had now completely receded. On the platform at Beal station I talked with 3 wounded soldiers, of whom two were Durham men, so cheerful &amp; brave. We got back to Newcastle about 10.30 p.m., &amp; had supper at the station restaurant. There we parted, Car&#x00F6;e going for the night to stay with the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName>: and I returning to Durham by the 11.19 p.m. train. Four 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Lieutenants shared my carriage with me: three of them were under 20 and two under 18. Yet all had been some months in the army, &amp; were actually going to various destinations to take up work as C.O.'s! I never met more attractive &amp; well&#8211;mannered lads. I got them to write down their names for me, that I might be able to follow their course.</hi>
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>A. G. Bell</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Lieut:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Durham Light Infantry</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>W. Rice</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>" " "</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>P. Owen</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>" " "</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>P. N. Schone</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>"</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>S. Staffordshire</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi>We parted in much friendship at Durham.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
