<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[604]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">662</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="42">Steele&#8211;Maitlands</persName><persName xml:id="701"></persName> [Steel&#8211;Maitlands] left after breakfast. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with them as far as Newcastle. I had too much headache to do any effective work: after some vain essays I gave up the attempt, and rolled the lawn. At lunch <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> came, &amp; afterwards accompanied me to the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Governors</orgName> meeting. Here we signed an application for a new Scheme in the teeth of <persName xml:id="3585">Boutflower's</persName> protest, which was extravagant, untimely, &amp; impracticable. He has his good points, but these do not include an aptitude for business. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked to Dryburn, and had tea with <persName xml:id="3512">Colonel</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3813">Darwin</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I cross&#8211;examined M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Darwin about the Pilgrimage of Prayer, which she had performed last year in the Diocese of Southwell, &amp; which is now projected as part of the National Mission in this diocese</hi><hi rend="italic">. Though she asserted her belief in the spiritual value of the exercise, she admitted that she was doubtful whether it was not being injured by over&#8211;organization. Certainly this so&#8211;called "National Mission" places the clergy, who disapprove &amp; even dislike that religious method in a very disagreeable position. We are being flooded with prayers for public, domestic, &amp; private use, all of which invoke the Divine Blessing on the project, and use very ardent expressions. It is difficult to use these sincerely &amp; effectively without immersing one's self in hypocrisy, or being coerced into conduct which runs counter to one's deliberate judgment. The issuing of prayers for use in the churches is a subtle method of compelling the reluctant clergy to 'come into line' with episcopal directions! Personally, I disapprove and dislike Missionary Methods. I think that the world has moved beyond them. The pre&#8211;supposition on which they depend, &amp; which alone can give them a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">raison d'être</hi><hi rend="italic"> have largely vanished even from religious minds. But I shrink from cold&#8211;shouldering good efforts.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
