<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[544]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">690</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Writing last night to </hi><persName xml:id="1708"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aleck Beechey</hi></persName><hi>, who is now stationed in Egypt, I expressed the natural hope that he would find opportunity of visiting the famous monuments of the country. But reading Plutarch's Life of Lucullus I came on the following statement as to the Roman soldier's behaviour in Egypt:&#8211; "It is also said that he neither went up to Memphis, nor sought out any other of the famous wonders of Egypt: this he held to be the privilege of a leisurely and luxurious sight&#8211;seer, not of one who, like himself, had left his commander&#8211;in&#8211;chief encamped under the open sky alongside the battlements of the enemy". Was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lucullus</hi><hi> right? His reasoning, perhaps, reflects more credit on his heart than on his intelligence. It belongs to that patriotic logic which leads people to practice all manner of comfortless little personal economies during the War: and, we may connect it even with that sombre devotion which among Christians has associated the commemoration of Christ's Passion with many severe disciplines. Yet the cheerful wisdom of the man who 'going through the vale of Barca uses it for a well' has perhaps a superior attraction. In the case of Christian asceticism, of course, there is the crucial factor of repentance to be reckoned with. Self&#8211;punishment as a proof of sorrow for personal transgression belongs to the reasoning of the conscience, &amp; stands in a separate category. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lucullus</hi><hi> would have shown no disregard for Sulla's hardships, and might even have assisted </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sulla's</hi><hi> interests, if he had interested himself in the wonders of Egypt: and Aleck Beechey, or any other British soldier, will improve his military competence by freshening his mind and enlarging his knowledge by using whatever opportunities of sight&#8211;seeing the fortunes of War may bring within his reach.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[542]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral for Evensong and afterwards took such part as a thunderous headache permitted me to take in entertaining 16 of the wounded soldiers from the little hospital in the Bailey. They had tea in the dining room, &amp; then sate in the garden. I read to them </hi><persName xml:id="554"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert's</hi></persName><hi> letter, &amp; talked incessantly. They were interested in my account of the Yellowstone Park, and evidently impressed by Raemaker's pictures which they had not seen previously. "What is the difference between the A.S.C. and the R.A.M.C.?" is a conundrum proposed at the front, &amp; the answer is "The one robs the living: the other the dead…". I asked them what was left for the Chaplains to steal! Their opinion of the chaplains was clearly confused. On the one hand they had a 'soft job', &amp; so far were not entitled to sympathy: on the other hand they were often brave and generally helpful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><persName xml:id="3715"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. David Cowling</hi></persName><hi>, vicar of Eppleton, Hetton le Hole, called on me, &amp; extracted a promise that I would go to his parish next Wednesday, and unveil a window as a memorial of parishioners who have fallen in the War. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Cowling</hi><hi> was chaplain in Munich at the outbreak of the war, and his churchwarden was an Englishman resident for many years in that city as a designer of stained glass windows. On his expulsion by the Germans </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Cowling</hi><hi> was appointed by the Crown Vicar of Eppleton, and he is doing a good turn to an indigent friend by employing him to design a memorial window. It is not, perhaps, a very satisfactory way of selecting an artist for a public work of this kind; but in the circumstances one can understand the motives. This is the first war&#8211;memorial which I have been asked to 'dedicate'. When the war has ended there will be a fearful multiplication of these functions.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
