<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[643]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">554</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Among my letters I received a long &amp; very interesting one from Frederic <persName xml:id="1189">Harrison</persName> replying to my inquiry about the secret of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> posthumous fame</hi><hi>. Acting on a hint which it contained I wrote to <persName xml:id="390">Lathbury</persName> asking him the same question. I also asked F. H. to let me print his letter as an appendix to my published lecture. I called on <persName xml:id="648">Caröe</persName>, and heard from him an account of the proceedings at the meeting of the <orgName xml:id="248">Society of Antiquaries</orgName>. He had been himself unable to be present, as he had to lie up with his bad knee. He had therefore written a letter, requesting that it would be read. (He read to me the letter, which emphasized the faulty measurements on which the reasoning of the C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>'s report was based.) This letter was read, and then <persName xml:id="3965">Warren</persName>, the <persName xml:id="2521">President of Magdalen's</persName> brother, made a protest against the action of the Society in criticising an Architect without his knowledge to his clients. This, he said, was grossly unprofessional. This opinion seems to have received much support, for the discussion </hi><hi rend="bold">[645] </hi><hi>'fizzled out' rather ignobly. I hope devoutly that we shall hear no more of the matter. The squabbling of architects, like the merriment of parsons to D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1276" display="no">Johnson</persName>, is 'mighty offensive'. Leaving Caröe I called at the Deanery, but found the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop</persName> out. So I went into the Abbey Church and looked at the sand–bags heaped around S. Edward's shrine, the Tombs of Henry VII, Mary Q. of Scots, Elizabeth, &amp; the Lady Margaret. Also I noticed the new cross on the altar in Henry VII's chapel, &amp; was told that it had been presented by the <persName xml:id="582">Marquess of Salisbury</persName> in memory of his <persName xml:id="3701">daughter's</persName> wedding. I was interested to observe the number of Canadian &amp; Australian soldiers straying about the Church. To some of them I spoke, &amp; pointed out objects of interest. On leaving the Abbey Church I fell in with the <persName xml:id="325">Dean</persName>, &amp; promised to preach on May 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> in the evening. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spoke to him about placing a tablet to Robertson's memory in the Abbey, &amp; he seemed favourable to the notion</hi><hi>. Then I went to lunch with <persName xml:id="503">Winnifred</persName>. <persName xml:id="502">Aylwin Parker</persName> also lunched. He says that Italy is not going well. Large supplies are getting into Germany through Italy, &amp; at any moment she might break away from the Entente. I gather that we are now adopting the policy of buying up the supplies which the neutrals would endeavour to sell to Germany. This seems an unexceptionable method of assisting the blockade. On leaving 18 Cowley Street, I fell in with <persName xml:id="1676">Noel Masters</persName>, a battered–looking warrior, who has been through much fighting. Then we drove to Euston, &amp; proceeded to Lichfield to stay until Saturday with the <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName>. We found M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4013">Thorpe</persName> very well, &amp; apparently nowise perturbed by the Zeppelins, which passed close at the last raid.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
