<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[717]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">600</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright morning with a hard frost. There are 8 rooks' nests in the tree in the front garden, and as yet none in that in the back garden. The thrushes and blackbirds make glad musick. I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Sacrament. All the canons were present except <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>, who has gone to Canterbury to preach. I wrote a sermon for the troops on "Temptation", allowing myself some explicitness of language, which, perhaps, I should not have ventured, had it not been for what <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> told me of his experiences. After lunch I walked through Houghall Wood with Logic, &amp; joined <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName> on the way. I attended Evensong: and afterwards read the account of Abp. <persName xml:id="3945">Herring</persName> in Rowden's <ref xml:id="804">"The Primates of the Four Georges"</ref>. If he had not been a Broad Churchman, his reputation would have been fair enough. But as he was, he is habitually belittled &amp; abused as a compendium of all the horrors of "Erastianism" and "Latitudinarianism"! M. Demelle called on me: &amp; I paid him my account. He shewed me, with legitimate pride, a photograph of his grandson, a fine young Frenchman, who is now fighting at Verdun. I could not but order some more claret! The old man is greatly agitated by some new anti&#8211;drinking restriction which have been announced, &amp; which prohibit the soliciting of orders for alcohol. This will transform the habit of his life&#8211;time into a criminal act! One can hardly be surprised that the French should be restive and suspicious under our new zeal against every form of alcohol. They see a menace to one of the few surviving industries of France, &amp; they feel our conduct to be unfriendly. I received letters from <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. The wind changed bringing a rise of temperature, rain, &amp; wind.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[716]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>Drill Hall, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Durham,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>March 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Reverend Sir,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I beg to inform you that the Battalion move from Durham to Gosforth tonight.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On behalf of the officers, N.C.O's, &amp; men of this Unit under my command, I wish to thank you most heartily for the untiring care you have taken towards their spiritual welfare.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Personally I shall miss the Sunday morning Church Parades, but shall look back upon them with thankfulness when I reflect what a great help they have been to all.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>In closing may I wish you God's&#8211;speed in your good work.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours sincerely,</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>J. <persName xml:id="3922">Burgoyne&#8211;Johnson</persName> &#8211; Major</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>Commanding 3/8</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> D.L.I.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>The Very Reverend</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>The Dean of Durham.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
