<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[567]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after X</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">mas</hi><hi rend="bold">, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">517</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The wind has fallen, &amp; the morning is calm. The weather continues strangely warm. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were but few communicants. I preached to the soldiers at 10 a.m. from the words. "</hi><hi rend="underline">If God is for us: who is against us?</hi><hi>" At Mattins the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> preached a suitable and well&#8211;expressed sermon on Psalm 65.8 "</hi><hi rend="underline">Thou makest the outgoings of the morning &amp; evening praise Thee</hi><hi>". The weather grew worse as the afternoon came on: by service time it was raining dismally. The special service of Intercession was attended by the Mayor &amp; Corporation who were escorted by about 300 soldiers. Considering the weather, there was a good muster of citizens. I preached<ref xml:id="902"></ref> on Isaiah 37.14: "</hi><hi rend="underline">And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers &amp; read it: &amp; Hezekiah went up into the House of the Lord, &amp; spread it before the Lord</hi><hi>". After the Benediction we sang the National Anthem, all three verses. The collection was for the Mayor's Belgian Relief Fund. Altogether during the day a sum of &#x00A3;24.17.5 was collected. Some of the officers came in to tea, and I shewed them over the house.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
