<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[648]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">638</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Durham via the early express, and travelled comfortably to King's Cross in the company of General <persName xml:id="3923">Lawson</persName>, the commander of the Northern district, into whose reserved carriage I had been mistakenly introduced. I found him an agreeable &amp; intelligent companion. He professed himself a devoted friend of Bishop Ryle. On my arrival at King's Cross, I drove at once to Paddington, &amp; caught a train to Windsor. Canon <persName xml:id="3610">Sheppard</persName>, the Sub&#8211;Dean of the Chapels, was my companion. I found the Dean very feeble, &amp; rather depressed. The Mayor &amp; Corporation were entertained at tea before the service in the Nave of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> George's. That service was attended by an immense congregation. I preached my sermon, &amp; was well&#8211;listened to. So far as I could gather, the discourse was regarded with approval, &amp; the service considered "a great success"!! An aged prelate, the Archbishop of Belgrade, attended the function, &amp; "dined" at the Deanery. The next day (Thursday, the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> April) I returned to London, &amp; put up in 3. Little Cloister. Most of my time was spent at the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>. On Saturday afternoon I travelled to Seaford, being joined by <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> at Lewes where I changed trains. We put up at the Esplanade Hotel for the night. Before turning in, Ernest walked with me to the camp, which is well placed on the cliff. The brilliant sun&#8211;setting illumined the country nobly. Sunday, the 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> April, was a glorious day. The motor arrived at the Hotel in good time to take us to the Camp, where the Chaplains (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Neale, an Essex Vicar, &amp; Barnsley) expected me. I preached to four parades in succession, being "at it" from 9.45 a.m. to 12.30 p.m. At the three first parades the men were attentive, &amp; apparently interested: at </hi><hi rend="bold">[646] </hi><hi>the 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, they were listless, clamourous &amp; resentful. I made a quick end of the preaching. These men belonged to a "Labour" Battalion, and had in many cases been on duty during the night. Having thus finished my duties, I lunched at the Loyal Lancashire Mess, where I heard the evil, but not unexpected, tidings that General <persName xml:id="3966">Townshend</persName> had surrendered to the Turks. Ernest &amp; I spent the afternoon in visiting Alfreston, a most interesting village. Here we had tea, &amp; then motored back to Seaford, where we caught the train to Brighton. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the night with Ernest's <persName xml:id="546">people</persName><persName xml:id="4026"></persName> in Brunswick Square, Hove</hi><hi>: and on Monday (May 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>) returned with him to London. We amused ourselves by visiting the Zoo, the new arrangements of which (Mappin Terraces) are astonishing. We lunched together at the Criterion: &amp; then separated. I attended the Tercentenary of Shakespeare's Birth Celebration in the Mansion House, the dullest meeting conceivable: &amp; then went back to Little Cloisters. <persName xml:id="636">Ernest P.</persName>, <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, &amp; I walked to the Temple, &amp; there dined at the <persName xml:id="3581">Master's</persName>. Barnes &amp; <persName xml:id="1820">Charles</persName> made up the party. On Tuesday (May 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>) I packed my bags (i.e. the maid did) and parted from mine hosts, &amp; travelled back to Durham without incident, having rejoined Ernest at King's Cross. We arrived about 3.45 p.m. The weather which had been threatening at the start, improved as we went northwards. We found Durham in sunshine. After tea, I walked with Ernest through Houghall Wood. The wind was cold, but the sun shone brightly, &amp; shewed the views to advantage. Later, he brought his book of news&#8211;paper cuttings, and read to us many of the letters wh. he had written on many subjects to the Canadian newspapers. They are often crude, but disclose an alert &amp; enterprising spirit, &amp; some literary power.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
