<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[432]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">753</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A wet warm day very unfavourable to work. I worked at the Article, but I must have more elbow&#8211;room than it affords if the <ref xml:id="817">'Report'</ref> is to be dealt with effectively. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> told me that <persName xml:id="508">Balfour</persName> never attended any of the meetings of the Committee: &amp; that the <persName xml:id="368">Duke of Devonshire</persName> attended but twice, &amp; then mainly went to sleep! Also, that the <persName xml:id="477">Bishop of Liverpool</persName> took practically no part in the proceedings, &amp; was hardly ever present. It is easy to see that the C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> resolved itself quickly and comfortably into a family party of neo&#8211;Anglicans. In spite of the rain, <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> and I walked for an hour and a half, &amp; were much better for it. On my return I wrote to Mary <persName xml:id="1204">Radford</persName>, from whom I received a long letter this morning. I attended Evensong. After dinner Olive shew</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ed</hi><hi> me her Hospital book, filled with sketches &amp; verses by her soldier&#8211;patients. There runs through most of these a note of genuine regard, which is creditable to her, and to them. Then she sang: &amp; afterwards I read poetry. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Morgan writes to say that he could no longer contribute to his <persName xml:id="1916">son's</persName> education, &amp; that he would take steps to secure some work for him. I wrote to ask him two questions. 1. What Arthur's own feelings on the subject were? 2. Whether he (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> M.) could contribute anything? I incline to suspect that, having told me so much adverse to the present condition of the school, Arthur's courage has failed him in prospect of an interview with the Head&#8211;master.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
