<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[480]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">712</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of Chapter. There was but little real business, but the <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> none the less managed to make himself very exasperating. We settled not to meet again until October 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. Nominations for the living of Norham are to be sent in by Sept 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. Then I discussed the arrangements for August 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> with the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>. I attended Evensong, and afterwards wrote a sheaf of letters. I wrote to the Durham Incumbents inviting them to the service on August 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and asking that their choirmen should assist the Choir of the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> &amp; I dined with the <persName xml:id="2785">Quirks</persName><persName xml:id="2689"></persName>, &amp; met one of the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop's</persName> friends from Sheffield who had been active in promoting the Bishoprick scheme. He seemed to think that a mistake had been made in fixing the limit of the episcopal income at so low an amount as &#x00A3;2500: &amp; gave an instance in which for so petty a sum as &#x00A3;15 for the legal expenses incurred in a necessary &amp; successful prosecution an appeal for subscriptions had been issued! <persName xml:id="412">Parker Smith</persName> writes to me about an offer which Lord <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> has made to set up a crucifix and stone altar in the school chapel at Winchester as a memorial to his son who died in Mesopotamia. His Lordship insists on these 'as being what W. of Wykeham w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have done'. This reason would justify some drastic alterations of the system &amp; tradition of a modern English public school. Why does not Selborne acknowledge that he is really influenced by the stream of medievalising fashion which carries all before it in the Anglican Party to which he belongs, and which has received immense impetus from many circumstances of the War. The wayside crucifixes of 'atheistic' France are likely to give the </hi><hi rend="underline">coup&#8211;de&#8211;grace</hi><hi> to the simplicity of 'protestant' England! Sentiment prevails over reason &amp; much besides!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
