<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[444]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">746</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"O God who hast ordained that whatever is to be desired should be sought by labour, and who, by Thy blessing, bringest honest labour to good effect, look with mercy upon my studies and endeavours. Grant me, Lord, to design only what is lawful and right; and afford me calmness of mind and steadiness of purpose, that I may so do Thy will in this short life, as to obtain happiness in the world to come, for the sake of Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This prayer of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1276" display="no">Johnson</persName></hi><hi> is dated July 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1776, when he was 67. <persName xml:id="1329" display="no">Boswell</persName> adds: "It appears from a note subjoined, that this was composed when 'he purposed to apply vigorously to study, particularly of the Greek and Italian tongues'."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast the <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwoods</persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName> took their leave. A message from Coxhoe came by way of the telephone at the porch asking me to come out on Sunday and address the men. They have organized a Thanksgiving service for their escape from damage from the Zeppelins. More than 20 bombs were thrown into the district without causing any loss of life. I promised to go there as soon as I had ascertained that I could hire a chauffeur. But it is not very obvious what I ought to say to them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> took <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2659">her mother</persName> to lunch at Tudhoe. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> &amp; I lunched together. The rain fell persistently all the afternoon. I attended Evensong, and afterwards read Baron <persName xml:id="2921">von Hügel's</persName> little book on <ref xml:id="820">"The German Soul"</ref>. Arthur <persName xml:id="30">Shadwell</persName> arrived from Newcastle in time for dinner: he played accompaniments for Olive &amp; Hughes afterwards, and himself sang. We had much talk in my study after the ladies had retired. <persName xml:id="2748">J. G. Wilson</persName> came to dinner.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
