<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[578]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">675</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in <placeName xml:id="77">S. Gregory's Chapel</placeName>. The morning was frittered away in futile essays at sermon composition. At 2 p.m. I presided at the election of King's Scholars. There was a very poor field, only eleven boys being examined: we gave scholarships to 3 of them. Maxwell Backhouse and his brother Kendal: and Leslie Ward. The brothers are the sons of the Wolsingham Schoolmaster, and the other's father is a 'Printer &amp; Publisher'. Then I went to the Town Hall, and attended a meeting in the Mayor's Parlour in the interest of the Lord Roberts Memorial Workshops for the disabled soldiers &amp; sailors. Miss Carey was fluent &amp; eloquent but vague. I suggested that the money she pleaded for (&#x00A3;100,000) might well be voted by the Prince of Wales's Fund. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> concurred, &amp; promised to ascertain whether the Fund would make a grant.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName>, who is still at Cambridge training. It is these many months with the colours at home that brings so severe a strain on the character of these young soldiers. The first fervours burn themselves out, and are followed by a moral lassitude which itself constitutes a situation of great danger. They are besieged by women &amp; girls, many of whom are swept along by a wave of sentiment, but some of whom are definitely corrupt in mind or habit, or both. The tone of conversation &amp; conduct among the regulars, who have the handling of these youths, are in respect to women painfully low: and the entrance into vice is facilitated in a hundred ways. I have no doubt at all, from what I learn from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> and many others, that the War has broken down, and is breaking down, that personal chastity which was distinctive of the general body of middle&#8211;class Englishmen.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
