<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[408]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">765</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A glorious morning. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The morning post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> expressing warm agreement with my protest against the Somme films</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi> Also, in the papers appears the announcement that the films were exhibited in Windsor Castle, and that the King had expressed his warm approval! My prospects for next Sunday's visit are not improving. Lord <persName xml:id="3220">Stamfordham</persName> writes that he himself will be absent on holiday, so that I shall have no </hi><hi rend="underline">amicus curiae</hi><hi> [friend at the court]! I shall enjoy the experience of a disgraced courtier!! However, the situation is certainly interesting in a high degree: &amp; I ought to be able to make some additions to my Journal, which will be worth reading.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[406]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle, and attended a Reception given by the Lord Mayor and Principal <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> to the members of the British Association. Among the company were very few acquaintances. I had some talk with Sir Thomas <persName xml:id="3808">Oliver</persName>, who told me that he had seen the Somme Films, and thought them inoffensive save for two scenes &#8211; carrying the wounded through the trenches, and burying the German dead &#8211; which were in his opinion repulsive. Also I had speech with <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>, Sir <persName xml:id="3091">Hugh Bell</persName>, Sir <persName xml:id="3131">George Philipson</persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName>. As we drove through Birtley we noticed large numbers of the munition workers &#8211; vigorous young Belgians of military age. We wondered that they were not with King Albert, &amp; conjectured that they were skilled workmen, who were more profitably employed in making munitions than in providing 'fodder' for the German cannon. We drove cautiously through the darkened streets, and reached the Deanery about 10.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
