<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[637]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">551</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; received my letters. These included a very interesting </hi><hi rend="underline">letter from Frederic <persName xml:id="1189">Harrison</persName> about <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton</hi><hi>. I wrote to him in reply, asking the question which I cannot get answered viz: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">How did the relatively obscure preacher obtain at a jump such posthumous fame</hi><hi>? I lunched with the <persName xml:id="636">Pearces</persName>: saw <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in Cowley Street: walked in the Parks with Ernest, who received the salutations of the numerous soldiers with much dignity &amp; satisfaction: finally rejoined my bags at 17 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; dined there. <persName xml:id="3580">Herbert Pelham</persName>, the new Vicar of Barking, came to dinner. He seems the right sort of man for the parish. Then I talked with <persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie</persName> until midnight. As I passed through the Horseguards I was saluted by Bingley, whom I have not seen for many years. He appears to be now employed by the Government, his knowledge of Dutch making him very useful just now in Holland. He gave me a lively account of the method by which young Belgians are smuggled in barrels through the barbed wire fences into Holland, &amp; thence transferred by sea to the little corner of Belgium in which King Albert still holds out against the Oppressor.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
