<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[440]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">748</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received the Holy Communion at 8 am. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> celebrated, and I read the Gospel. Also I attended Mattins, &amp; heard an excellent sermon from <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>. Then <persName xml:id="30">Shadwell</persName> and I walked to the station in order to secure (if possible) a sleeping berth in the night train: but the station was fast closed, &amp;, though we waked up the station master, we could get no certainty as to the sleeper. After lunch, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2659">her mother</persName> and I motored to Coxhoe, where a 'Thanksgiving Service' had been arranged in recognition of the almost miraculous circumstances that although about 40 bombs were thrown into the parish, no injury either to life or limb or property had been effected. The weather was fine but unstable and thunderous. An open&#8211;air service in these circumstances was not without risk; &amp;, in point of fact, we had a brief shower, while I was speaking. On the whole the service was a success. There were three speeches, two from local sectaries, and one from me. I wore my doctor's habit, which drew the admiring gaze of the children. As I walked off the field a young man presented me with a piece of a bomb, which he had picked up. We had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3910">Wood</persName> at Coxhoe Hall; and then returned to Durham. The car took Shadwell's bags to the station: which again we found shut: but we roused the assistant station&#8211;master, &amp; got him to take charge of the bags. As the evening drew on the rain fell heavily. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. Shadwell </hi><hi rend="underline">would</hi><hi> see the Castle, &amp; Elvet Bridge, so I tramped round with him through heavy thunder&#8211;showers, and he achieved his purpose. Then we returned to the Deanery for dinner, &amp; music. At 11.15 p.m. I put him in the way to the station. The night was not wholly dark, and the rain had ceased. He assured me in parting that he had enjoyed his visit, &amp; would repeat it.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
