<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[677]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">570</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral, and received the Holy Communion. Then I wrote a little sermon for the Troops on the most difficult of Themes. Fancy having to discuss the Fall of Man in fifteen minutes! I was interrupted by Capt</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> Lamb &amp; Capt</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> (?) [sic] Bradford, who came to see me about a place to drill in. I took them at once to the Crypt, &amp; showed them </hi><hi rend="underline">that</hi><hi>: they approved it. <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3457">Robinson</persName> came to lunch, &amp; stayed to discuss some fool's business of Imperial Lectures, which it is proposed to arrange for next winter. Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I walked round Houghall Wood in an icy wind. <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> came in to tea after the service in the Cathedral. </hi><hi rend="italic">We dined with the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> to meet M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> John <persName xml:id="3706">Bailey</persName>, who had come to lecture on Shakespeare to the English Association. We all attended the Lecture in the Town Hall. It was on the whole interesting &amp; suggestive: but he made one or two curious blunders. He said that De Dominis, the notorious humbug, who was R.C. Abp of Spalatro, &amp; then ratted &amp; became Dean of Windsor, died an Anglican: whereas he was lured back to Papistry, &amp; properly rewarded for his behaviour. Two things which he quoted from some learned German who lectured recently in Oxford on Shakespeare are worth noting. Shakespeare's milieu was brutal &amp; roystering, such as has long been outgrown in England, but yet survives in Germany. Hence the plays are more 'actual' there than here. Also, Shakespeare is only known to Germans in a modern translation. He is practically a modern author. Where as in England his language is archaic, &amp; sometimes almost unintelligible. Hence the production of his plays is less natural in England than in Germany. Both these considerations are interesting and, I think, also sound. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
