<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[528]		</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Peter's Day, Thursday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">696</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Cathedral, and received the Holy Communion. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3813">Darwin</persName> writes to me a letter, which is not without interest just now: she is anxious as to the form which the intercessions &amp;c recommended for August 4</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, when the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> anniversary of the declaration of War falls, may take.</hi>
</p><div type="quote"><p>
<hi rend="italic">"I see the Archbishops are calling us to prayer on Aug. 4</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi><note xml:id="313" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> If you have a service in the Cathedral on that day, please make it a prayer service for </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Victory</hi><hi rend="italic">. I cannot stand any more of this bleating about suffering, losses, &amp; mourning. The soldiers and sailors do all that willingly, &amp; so do we their women&#8211;folk. What they want, what we want, and, I believe, what God wants is Victory. Why can't we ask for it? We believe that we are fighting for God's cause. So we ought to put our will in correspondence with His Will by praying that His cause may be victorious." </hi></p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">That is a candid disclosure of the very temper, which needs correction. It frankly enlists the Almighty as a British Ally: &amp; makes the strength of our conviction of right the final proof of our rightness. So perhaps it must be for ourselves, but, then, we should not exclude the possibility of our being therein mistaken. What can we do but act steadily on our vision of duty, and pray that God's Will may be done? I doubt whether their Graces are well&#8211;advised in renewing their exhortations to prayer. As the War drags on, the tidal wave of mere emotional fervour ebbs in many minds, and the reasoning faculty again becomes active. The range, purpose, &amp; effect of legitimate Christian prayer are subjects which do not become less difficult as they are reflected upon. There is a real risk of provoking moral repugnance. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[526]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi>, and then attended Evensong. After service I had an interview with the lay vicars about the arrangements for August. They were disposed to 'kick against the goad', since, owing to the fewness of them, they would have to dispense with Sunday holidays. The fat </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2789">Peacock</persName></hi><hi> seemed to me the centre of revolt: but I spoke clearly, &amp; left them in no doubt as to my mind. Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> and I walked to the school, where a cricket match was in progress, &amp; had tea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then we returned to the Deanery, packed our bags, and came away to visit the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3100">Ravensworths</persName><persName xml:id="3722"></persName></hi><hi>. At Lamesley Station </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="3718">Liddell</persName></hi><hi> met us with the motor, &amp; carried us to the Castle. The weather became beautifully fine at eventide, and shewed up the Park to great advantage. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Liddell</hi><hi> and I walked in the Park for an hour before dinner. The rhododendrons have declined from their first glory, but still make the scene splendid with their colour. After dinner we talked pleasantly enough until bed&#8211;time. We were shown a golden snuff&#8211;box which had been taken by the Duke of Wellington from Napoleon's carriage. I confided to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> L. my project for the reredos: and he expressed cordial approval. He is to be High Sheriff next year: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon <persName xml:id="3688">Derry</persName></hi><hi> is to be his chaplain. I received a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh's</persName></hi><hi> sister who is now in Oxford looking after her brother. Her account of his condition is not very encouraging, though more cheerful than that which I had received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Oliver</hi><hi> on Sunday. It is but too evident that, although his life may be protracted for some time, my friend has been brought to the end of his career. His death, which cannot be long deferred, will make a great gap in the narrowing circle of those who love me, &amp; whom I love.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
