<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[704]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">606</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright warm morning but with clouds. The rooks are enormously busy, &amp; uncommonly quarrelsome. For the second time a ninth nest is being constructed on the tree: will it be suffered to remain? </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; then breakfasted alone, as <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had gone off by the early train to Harrogate to see an ear&#8211;doctor about her deafness. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the Secretary of the Licensed Victuallers Defence Association disclaiming any objection to drastic regulation of the Liquor trade: &amp; I sent this letter with another to cover it to the 'Times'. This was done in deference to an appeal from Sir John <persName xml:id="2069">Barran</persName></hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The day matured nobly into a warm &amp; brilliant </hi><hi rend="underline">spring</hi><hi>&#8211;day, rather unfavourable to work but very enjoyable out of doors. I made a start at gardening </hi><hi rend="underline">in me&#x00E2; propri&#x00E2; persona</hi><hi> [in person]. I rolled the lawn, and made a vigourous [sic] start at the removal of the circular ivy beds which have annoyed me for so long. I walked through Houghall Wood with Logic &amp; <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, &amp; attended Evensong.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have read with something like consternation a horrible book <ref xml:id="805">"Degenerate Germany"</ref> by Henry de Halsalle. It accumulates a mass of statistics &amp; quotations designed to show that Germany is rotten through &amp; through. But it seems to 'prove too much': for, after all, these miserable degenerates are proving themselves doughty warriors. I dread the effect of such books on our own people. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> returned a little before 9 p.m. having received a favourable report from the doctor, which, I trust, may be well&#8211;founded, for truly of all physical handicaps in human intercourse scarcely any can be reckoned more displeasing than deafness.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
