<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[596]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">667</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An unpleasant, blustering day with essays at rain. I re&#8211;typed and revised an old sermon for use next Sunday: and wrote to <persName xml:id="18">Gerald Marshall</persName> advising him not to trouble himself about the Papist proselytisers. I attended Evensong, rolled the lawn, and delivered the Lecture on <persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName> to a considerable company. Old <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> came across, which for a man in his 97</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> year, I thought very decent of him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I cashed a cheque at the Bank, and placed &#x00A3;500 on deposit at 3 per cent interest. In these evil days one must begin to take every loophole of opportunity to add to one's income.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. <persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName></hi><hi> sent me a beautifully bound copy of "</hi><hi rend="underline">A speech made at the Enthronement &amp; Installation of the Right Rev. Richard, Lord Bp. of Durham by the Hon. &amp; Rev. Spencer <persName xml:id="3768">Cowper</persName> D.D. Dean of Durham</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="837"></ref>. 1753. The most part of the speech consists of an ardently expressed eulogy of <persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler</persName>, who had died after a very brief episcopate in Durham. "He was one of those truly good &amp; holy men 'of whom the World is not worthy'". After referring to the speech he had made on Butler's enthronement, the Dean proceeds: "His years, his great temperance, &amp; his seeming sufficient strength of habit seemed to make these Hopes reasonable &amp; well&#8211;grounded…..Nevertheless tho' his duration amongst us was short, it was glorious to himself &amp; beneficial to his diocese." He dwells on Butler's 'munificence', and instances the Infirmary at Newcastle which "owes if not its rise yet at least its present surprising Advance to his munificence &amp; protection". He mentions Butler's "serenity and calmness". His welcome to Trevor, the new Bishop, is not extravagant, &amp; leads up to a glowing panegyric on George II, as the model of all regal virtues &amp; a very nursing Father of the Established Church.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
