<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[376]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
            </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">775</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>Our host entertained us at breakfast with a characteristically vivacious account of his daughter Betty's "war wedding". She carried through the hastily improvised arrangements with a vigour &amp; determination which mark her out as a leader of men! <persName xml:id="230">Sir Charles</persName> had hoped to hear that the Railway men's controversy had been settled, but he was disappointed. Sir W. <persName xml:id="3846">Robertson</persName> met the men's representatives last night, and explained to them that a strike could not be tolerated at this juncture. 5000 tons of shell must be exported every day, for 5000 tons were daily fired away. The locomotive men were willing to accept the employers' offer (3/&#8211; addition to weekly wages, &amp; reference to arbitration) but the others won't. However, Sir Charles thinks that a settlement will probably be reached. He says that all the difficulty comes from S. Wales and Liverpool, the two places where the railwaymen are in close contact with very highly paid workmen, miners and dockers. We motored to Knockwinnock (?) [sic] and lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Macdowall, a charming old man. He told me that he had sure information that another 'push' in a fresh place was arranged for next week. A "gala" took place in his grounds for the military funds, and was attended by a great crowd of people. Sir Charles opened it formally with a speech, &amp; then I was called upon, &amp; made a brief speech. We had a very pleasant motor drive back to Barochan, through Kilmalcolm. The views of moorland and meadow interspersed with opulent harvest fields and backed by mist&#8211;vested mountains were very beautiful. There is an autumnal feeling in the air with almost a suggestion of winter. The crops appear to be excellent, and they are being gathered in under excellent conditions.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[374]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"In an agricultural country like France in the sixteenth century, the distress of the provinces through the failure of the harvests was sometimes nearly universal, and the retroactive effect of such conditions in promoting popular discontent had a marked influence upon the religious and political issues."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="183">Thompson</persName>. <ref xml:id="331">"The Wars of Religion in France, 1559&#8211;1576"</ref>. p. ix</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"The decline in the birth rate which began before the war must be overcome! The first years after the war will probably decide whether or no this will succeed. After the war we must begin afresh, and in this respect more ever than in anything else. Mid&#8211;Europe needs children, children, children! This the presupposition of all prosperity both military and economic now the urgent, heartfelt, beseeching call must resound, mingled with the ringing of the peace bells, calling to men &amp; women in town &amp; country: Beget children!"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>(v. F. Naumann. <ref xml:id="864">"Central Europe"</ref> v. p. 203/4.)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
