<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[488]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">709</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We were up betimes, completed our preparations for departure, breakfasted, and then took our leave. <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> escorted us to the station. We arrived at Victoria after a comfortable journey, and went at once to the Deanery, St Paul's, where we lunched with <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> and <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>. Ralph accompanied us to Peterborough, where the annual meeting of Deans was convened. No less than seventeen deans attended. Ralph, the <persName xml:id="1332">Dean of Salisbury</persName>, <persName xml:id="3741">Hereford</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3967">Chichester</persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were lodged in the Deanery, the rest of the company found entertainment in the capitular houses. After tea we attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and then were shown over the building by the Dean. I was more impressed than ever before by the spaciousness &amp; height of the Church. Durham, though far more magnificent &amp; impressive, seems by comparison to be almost pinched in size. The Choir exhibited a war&#8211;time appearance: there were but three men, who were eked out by two brace of boy&#8211;altos. Peterborough, like Durham, is very destitute of historic monuments. Modern recumbent effigies are too many: and a hideous mosaic of Bishop <persName xml:id="118">Creighton</persName> offends </hi><hi rend="underline">every</hi><hi> sense of beauty &amp; fitness. There is a mural monument to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2984">Cosin</persName>, who died while <persName xml:id="2820">her husband</persName> held the Deanery of Peterborough. I think the date is 1642. We walked into the Palace Garden from which a noble view of the Cathedral is gained. The Palace itself covers much ground, &amp; was (quite indefensively) added to by <persName xml:id="176">Carr&#8211;Glyn</persName> [Carr Glyn]. To live in so extensive a house, and to keep up several acres of gardens would require a far more considerable income than the See provides. When the pension to his predecessor, &amp; the <orgName xml:id="296">Q.A.B.</orgName> payment has been made, the new Bishop will have but a petty official income.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
