<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[661]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">563</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Fred. <persName xml:id="3962">Palgrave</persName> called on me, and came to lunch. He is now a tutor at the Missionary college at Warminster, having retired from his work as a missionary in the Canadian North&#8211;west five years ago. He was a resident at the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName> in Bethnal Green, when I was Head there nearly 30 years ago. He is a strange, odd being, who has great powers of self&#8211;sacrifice, and, perhaps (though of this I have no knowledge) of service. Like his <persName xml:id="3961">father</persName>, the Professor of Poetry, he is extremely garrulous. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The newspapers announce a military success of real importance &#8211; the capture of Erzeroum by the Russians. It is thought, even taken for certain, that this will compel the abandonment of the projected attack on Egypt. It may possibly also relieve the pressure on the British forces in Mesopotamia. We may allow ourselves to believe that the Grand Duke Nicholas has recovered his nerve.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1289">Reginald Smith</persName> sent me a letter he had received from Stopford <persName xml:id="3960">Brooke</persName>, the Editor of <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> Letters. It contains the following:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I did not know any of the Robertson family. I once met the son in the street, but that is all, nor have I any information concerning the others. Henry King of Cornhill had most of the MSS in his hands for a time, &amp; I think that all that was worth publishing was published. The bulk of the letters were in my hands, &amp; I sent them back to the owners. I should think that Kegan Paul &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi><hi> would know where the Robertson family were or are." </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This hardly looks promising for a 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> series of Sermons.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
