<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[714]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">601</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was another sudden change of the weather last night. There was a violent wind with snow&#8211;showers. The morning sun shines on a white landscape. Before breakfast I wrote a 'Collins'<note xml:id="276" n="1"></note> to <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>, and letters of thanks for the books they had sent me to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Woods &amp; <persName xml:id="1318">Cunningham</persName>. Also I sent copies of <ref xml:id="85">'Robertson'</ref> to Cunningham, <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>. I preached at 10 a.m. to a scanty assembly composed of the cadets from the school, the members of the Officers Training Corps, and a few of the Army Medical Corps. I delivered the little sermon which I wrote yesterday, and, if the attention of the men may permit a hope that they received the message, then </hi><hi rend="underline">my</hi><hi> message went home. I attended Mattins, and celebrated the Holy Communion. We lunched with the <persName xml:id="3553">Mead&#8211;Falkners</persName><persName xml:id="3554"></persName>. I preached at Evensong to a </hi><hi rend="underline">very</hi><hi> scanty congregation. It was the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> sermon of my course on 'Christian Liberty'<ref xml:id="905"></ref>. Among my hearers were <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>, <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName>, Mead&#8211;Falkner, Heywood, <persName xml:id="3159">Moulsdale</persName>, <persName xml:id="3459">Ellershaw</persName>, &amp; the two school&#8211;masters. Mayor <persName xml:id="3944">Gwynn</persName> and his wife came to tea, and were shown over the house. He says that the officers are leaving <placeName xml:id="61">Hatfield Hall</placeName> almost immediately. They complain that they can get no hot&#8211;water there, a hardship which appears to them intolerable! After the Gwynns had taken their departure, I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="2936">Jack Boden</persName>, acknowledging the gift of his book, and making some comments on it, which (since I have done no more than look at it) was, perhaps, rather 'temerarious' than fair.<note xml:id="305" n="1"></note> Then I read the account of Archbishop <persName xml:id="3943">Secker</persName> which Rowden gives in his book on the <ref xml:id="804">Primates</ref>. He seems to have had many good points, but he gave some people the impression of being a humbug, a trace probably of his Nonconformist breeding, and he certainly has a disconcerting look of the present Bishop of Carlisle!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
