<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[665]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">565</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="590">"Iste archidiaconus"</persName> has anticipated me in asking the Judges to luncheon on March 5</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">my</hi><hi rend="italic"> invitation is of course declined! It were a curious &amp; useless task to discover why it is that so trivial a circumstance exasperates me (as it certainly does) out of all proportion to the injury (if any) which it inflicts. Perhaps it is the reminder which it brings that one is always being </hi><hi rend="italic underline">chivied</hi><hi rend="italic"> [sic], &amp; often </hi><hi rend="italic underline">under&#8211;cut</hi><hi rend="italic">, by a busy &amp; unwearying schemer, for whom nothing is too small to interest, and nothing too considerable to abash! Well, well.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of the Chapter: there was not much business, and there was no quarrelling, though "iste archidiaconus" was extremely provoking. However I was not to be further humiliated into fresh rages! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I walked for an hour and a half. Falling in with <persName xml:id="2810">Pool</persName> [Poole] I questioned him about the man B___y, &amp; gathered that he had been required to leave the school mission for the habit and vice of secret drinking. As P. is not himself a total&#8211;abstainer, I incline to believe him: and shall strike B.'s name off my preferment list.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3958">Thomas</persName>, the vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Giles's, left the 2 vols. of 'Life &amp; Letters of <persName xml:id="3704">Rowland Williams</persName> D.D." edited by his wife (Henry S. King &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi><hi>. 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> ed. 1874)<ref xml:id="801"></ref> for me to look at. There are a few references to <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of no great value. I read the account of "Essays &amp; Reviews" with much interest. It is new to me that <persName xml:id="1551">Thirlwall</persName> shewed himself so hostile to the writers throughout. On the whole it was a straighter issue than I had supposed. Williams must have been a born fighter, &amp; probably very provocative: but his letters of advice &amp; counsel give one a high opinion, both of his ability and of his character, and the private prayers suggest that he was a genuinely devout Christian.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
