<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[636]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
 </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">642</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day being the anniversary of the King's Accession, there was a Celebration of the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. I celebrated: and there were present 3 canons and 2 minor canons. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> received the Holy Communion. It was a great happiness to minister to him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of the Chapter. We appointed the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3578">S. K. Wilkinson</persName> to be Vicar of Heighington. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> De Vere came to lunch. I attended Evensong, and afterwards took Ernest for a short walk. Also I gave him a copy of Kitchin's book on the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler</persName></hi><hi>:&#8211;</hi></p><div type="quote"><p>"There are people absurd enough, to take the supposed doubtfulness of religion for the same thing as a proof of its falsehood, after they have concluded it doubtful from hearing it often called in question. This shows how infinitely unreasonable sceptical men are, with regard to religion, and that they really lay aside their reason upon this subject as much as the most extravagant enthusiasts." </p></div><p>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
