<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[506]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">700</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We left <placeName xml:id="63">Ravensworth Castle</placeName> after breakfast, bidding affectionate farewells to our very kind host &amp; hostess, interlarding them with promises of return. We motored to Newcastle, &amp; there caught the express, which brought us to Durham about 10.30 a.m. On arriving at the Deanery, I wrote cheques for the household accounts, &amp; divers other bills.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Among the letters awaiting me was one from a private soldier in camp at Ripon. It begins thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I have read your letters in the "The Challenge" with great interest, especially as I know that you are always to the front when anything is mentioned about Church Reform. While paying my respects to your experience and learning, I cannot, as a Christian, agree in what you say, and, as I have said before, it is curious that you don't resign your position in the English Church, because your opinions are entirely contrary to what the </hi><hi rend="underline">whole</hi><hi> Catholic church has done since Apostolic times." </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>It would appear that the good man has addressed me on a previous occasion, but his letter had left no impression on my mind. He ends his epistle in these terms:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Let me give you a little bit of advice, straight from the shoulder. Don't interfere with other people's convictions, and don't despise them. We respect your convictions, and allow you to act as you think right. Please have the goodness to do the same to us."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>And the whole pother is about a </hi><hi rend="underline">change</hi><hi> in Anglican procedure urged with extraordinary vehemence by these demurely tolerant folks, who resent any plea for the traditional system as a gross violation of charity, &amp; a wrong to themselves!!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
