<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[386]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">771</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> begins the "National Mission" by another apology for his official income. Thus the note which he strikes is squalidly controversial, &amp; can by no manner of glazing optimism be interpreted religiously. He follows it up by discoursing, as he asserts, on "Conscience", a noble &amp; relevant theme; but he only makes it the occasion for a rechauff&#x00E9; of his recruiting speeches! With this beginning, &amp; carried on by this method, what other consequence can really follow from the "National Mission" than a new accession of absurdity to the already discredited Church? Bishop <persName xml:id="4088">Bury</persName>, whom I met in the Park yesterday, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">tells me that the Bishop of London was pressed to treat of his income; &amp; when I asked, By Whom?, he told me, <persName xml:id="3611">'Dick Sheppard'</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to Durham by the 10 a.m. express from King's Cross, and arrived in Durham at 3.40 p.m. or thereabouts. As no cab met me at the station, I left my bags to follow by the carrier, and walked to the Deanery. Among the letters awaiting my arrival was one from Richard Bagot, dated from Bologna, Sept. 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He expressed agreement with me on the question of exhibiting the Somme films. Later, <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> came to dine, and he said as much, adding that nothing would induce him to go to see these films. It is pleasant to find that one is not absolutely alone. <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> has been seeing <persName xml:id="128">Cantuar</persName> recently. His Grace told him that Exeter had already been offered to two persons, and declined. As the outgoing Bishop is taking no less than &#x00A3;1600 per annum as a pension, there is not sufficient money to 'run' the see. The <persName xml:id="215">P.M.</persName> has once more, as in the recent case of Peterborough, to find a clergyman with private means. Apart from other questions altogether, the poverty of the sees would exclude me from ever going on the episcopal Bench.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
