<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[654]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">630</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I did not go to the early Celebration, being re&#8211;actionary, depraved, and "Mondayish" after the fervours &amp; labours of the Festival! This is the shadow on all extraordinary efforts! They breed a listlessness, which may become an ebb&#8211;tide carrying far out from the shore. I laboured at, and completed: a very poor sermon for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> George's Windsor. The poor thing oscillates between the lecture&#8211;room and the platform, never reaching the pulpit for an instant! And I haven't the least notion of the quality of the congregation, or of the acoustics of the nave, or of the conditions of the preaching! After lunch I walked with <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> through Houghall Wood, stopping at Mountjoy Farm on the way to pay 5/6 for the potatoes, sent to the Deanery some while ago. I attended Evensong. As there were many holiday&#8211;folks in the Cathedral, I had a verse of the National Anthem sung after the service. The <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName>, with <persName xml:id="1981">his wife</persName>, chaplain, &amp; 2 boys, came in to tea; and went over the house. We dined with the <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingtons</persName><persName xml:id="3263"></persName> to meet M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Barclay who is visiting them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Newcastle is evidently not favourable to the Mission, from which none the less he conceives himself unable to dissociate himself</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I told him that the Bishops ought to put a bridle on the jaws of <persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName>, if they would prevent the Mission from becoming ludicrous.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Arthur <persName xml:id="2288">Robinson</persName>, of All Hallows, Barking, has been appointed by the <persName xml:id="128">archbishop of Canterbury</persName> (with whom for this turn the appointment lay) a Canon of Canterbury, in succession to <persName xml:id="1262">Canon Danks</persName>, whose death was announced a few days ago. His Grace will be more closely invested than ever by the Robinson family, with their blend of Evangelical unction, &amp; sacerdotal assumption!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
