<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[586]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">671</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Jesus, the living, answered and said to His disciples: "Blessed is he who is crucified unto the world, and whom the world did not crucify". (From the Coptic)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The author of this logion could hardly have meant by the striking phrase 'whom the world did not crucify' nothing more than a reference to the crucifixion of the body, for martyrdom was rather held to be a matter for solemn congratulations than for regret: but he must have meant rather that death in life which the '</hi><hi rend="underline">love of the world</hi><hi>' implies. Thus the apostle says of the worldly&#8211;minded widow that "</hi><hi rend="underline">she that giveth herself to pleasure is dead while she liveth</hi><hi>". The reference to that cruellest of all methods of capital punishment, crucifixion, carries the same suggestion as that of the Puritan phrase, (which may also be patristic) "</hi><hi rend="underline">the devil's martyrs</hi><hi>". Modern novelists, and satirists both ancient &amp; modern, dwell on the worry &amp; labour implied in a life of fashion. This is the secular analogue of the apostolic idea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; there celebrated the Holy Communion. There were but few communicants, partly owing to the proximity of the Festivals, &amp; partly to the dull dampness of the morning. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">A letter from <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> tells me that his youngest son, <persName xml:id="817">Roderick</persName>, was killed in that disastrous sea&#8211;fight</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>I wrote to condole with Gow. I preached at Mattins on "the secularisation of Christianity"<ref xml:id="909"></ref>. The movement of people leaving the church, when the Preacher mounts the pulpit, is very scandalous. I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked with <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> in the cloisters, and in the cathedral, for the rain hindered us from walking beyond the protection of the college. The vaulting of the nave now looks very solemn &amp; beautiful.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
