<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[692]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">613</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>A dull morning with rain. I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. I spent the whole morning on letter–writing as follows:–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>1. To Rev. Charles Green, thanking him for Robertsoniana</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>2. To M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Arbuthnot,		"	"	"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>3. To <persName xml:id="909">Sir Lewis Dibdin</persName>, thanking him for his answer to my inquiry</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>4. To Sir James <persName xml:id="3949">Crichton–Browne</persName>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">declining</hi><hi> an invitation to lecture at the R.I.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>5. To <persName xml:id="648">Caröe</persName>, welcoming his proposed visit on the 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> inst.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>6. To G. W. <persName xml:id="319">Prothero</persName>, thanking him for his Tractate on "German Opinion &amp;c"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>7. To Canon <persName xml:id="1780">Gouldsmith</persName>, declining an invitation to preach on the 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> inst.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> &amp; I visited the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir School</orgName>, and were shown over it by <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>. I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards took some exercise in the garden. Then I wrote a letter to an old papist colonel, <persName xml:id="3772">Leadbitter–Smith</persName>, answering some questions about the ecclesiastical incomes in these parts before the re–settlement in 1835. Captain <persName xml:id="3524" display="no">Lewis</persName> called after dinner &amp; brought back Buchan's History of the War which I had lent him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName> sent me two copies of "The "Whizz Bang"</hi><hi> a monthly from the Front, written and edited in the Trenches". It is certainly above the average of such ephemeral publications, &amp; is written in an admirable spirit. There is a vigorous poem above the initials "P.H.B.L" which are Hugh's. The sly young rascal never hinted that he had enriched the print with his own verses, when he demurely proffered me the gift of the copies.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The afternoon post brought me a long &amp; pleasant letter from <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic">His modest allusion to religion suggested a good deal more than it said, &amp; was thoroughly good. The War is a sifting experience for all these young men, and must have deep &amp; lasting effect on all of them who are worth anything in mind or spirit. Bob is worth much.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[690]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Sir Lewis Dibdin to the Dean. April 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> 1916</hi> <hi rend="italic">(cf. p. 674)</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Dean,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I do not know of any general law or Act of Parliament regulating the preaching obligations of a canon. I think it depends on the Cathedral Statutes and canon 43 of 1603. I think at Durham under the Phil: &amp; Mary Statutes a canon may appoint a deputy to preach but his choice is limited by Canon 51 (1603)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very truly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lewis T Dibdin</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Canon 43 of 1603</hi><hi> ("Deans &amp; Prebendaries to preach during their Residence") orders that the deputies must be such preachers "as by the Bishop of the diocese shall be thought meet to preach in Cathedral Churches".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Canon 51</hi><hi> ("Strangers not admitted to preach in Cathedral Churches without sufficient authority") runs thus: "The Deans, Presidents and Residentiaries' of any Cathedral or Collegiate Church, shall suffer no stranger to preach unto the people in their churches, except they be allowed by the Archbishop of the Province, or by the Bishop of the same Diocese, or by either of the Universities".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>One of the 'Articles agreed upon at a meeting between Bishop <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName> and the Dean &amp; Prebendaries of Durham' in 1665 is the following:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"That country Curates be no longer suffered to preach the Prebendaries' courses". [v. Cosin's Correspondence [Surtees, vol. 55] p. 136.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>In 1671, Isaac <persName xml:id="3925">Basire</persName> replies to the Bishop's Articles that 'the Cathedral Sermons are frequently supplied by Curates &amp; others, contrary to Canon 43 &amp; 51, and to the Lord Bishop's former Injunctions' [v. Ibid. p. 290.]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[688]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Character of <persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName></hi><hi>:–</hi>
</p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"'Learned' does not characterise him: it confounds him with the Bentleys and the Burmans. Learning implies skill in ancient languages. Many exceeded the Bishop in that. His character was uncommon ingenuity, bright parts, and great general knowledge, ancient and modern. Learned, you see, would not convey those ideas. Bishop <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> was a far more learned man than Warburton, with no genius at all." (dated Oct: 17</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1779)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"v. 'A country clergyman of the XVIII</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century,' (Rev. Th</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">os</hi><hi> Twining) p. 72. (London, 1882)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
