<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[572]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">678</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dull damp morning, very depressing. I ran round to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest's</persName> room, to report my bath&#8211;room empty &amp; ready for his use; and thus made sure that he was awake, and preparing himself for what must be a very solemnly important communion for him, and might even be his last. Indeed, for all of us, after all that has passed these ten days past, this Holy Eucharist of Whit Sunday ought to mean much. May the Holy Spirit help our infirmities, &amp; make possible the fulfilment of our vows! I celebrated at 8 a.m. All the Canons communicated, a godly &amp; pleasant spectacle. The number of lay communicants seemed to be very large. Among them were Col: <persName xml:id="3512">Darwin</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3813">his wife</persName> with their <persName xml:id="3980">naval boy</persName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Ernest knelt together at the rail. At the Choral Eucharist I preached<ref xml:id="910"></ref> on Rom: VII. 14. "</hi><hi rend="underline">For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are sons of God</hi><hi>": &amp; Gal. V. 18. "</hi><hi rend="underline">But if ye are led by the Spirit, ye are not under the law</hi><hi>". <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> brought two of his sisters to church, and himself occupied the Bishop's stall, which I allow him to use in his capacity as Lord Lieutenant. After service I took him into the Cathedral, and expounded to him my scheme for filling the empty niches of the Neville Screen, as a Memorial to the soldiers &amp; sailors of Durham. He expressed himself as cordially favourable. Later, I discussed the matter with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, who was also friendly to it, but anxious about the ideals. Lord Durham and his sisters lunched here, &amp; were very agreeable. I attended Evensong, and heard an excellent sermon from <persName xml:id="3161">Dawson Walker</persName>, the Principal of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's College in this city. A very pretty little lady, the wife of one of the assistant schoolmasters, Little, came to tea, &amp; also the <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphins</persName>. I walked with Ernest &amp; <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh</persName> after tea. Hugh went back to his duties after dinner: &amp; Ernest read poetry to us.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
