<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[694]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">612</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>Brilliant sun, but with it a white frost. I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. The <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> celebrated. Bishop <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName> was held up for 7 hours last night in the train as he returned from Hartlepool to Durham. I finished the sermon for Sunday, &amp; then started to work at removing the ivy&#8211;bed. The Precentor, coming in opportunely, was impressed into the labour. The commandant of the cadets sent me a note to say that he had just received orders to break up the school, &amp; that consequently there would be nobody in Durham on Sunday. In these circumstances I ordered that the military service should be suspended. It has been kept up without break since Advent Sunday November 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1914. After lunch I walked with Logic, &amp; talked with Bishop Quirk. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I have a letter from Sir James <persName xml:id="3949">Crichton&#8211;Browne</persName> asking me to lecture to the <orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName> on the 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> June on "any literary or historical subject"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>It is difficult to decline invitations of this kind, but extremely inconvenient to accept. The diversion of interest, &amp; waste of time involved in the preparation of lectures of this sort are distressingly great. <persName xml:id="909">Sir Lewis Dibdin</persName> replied to my letter, sending me a privately printed account of some proceedings at Chester, where he was called upon to give an opinion on 'the claim of the Bishop of Chester to officiate and preach in the Cathedral, at his pleasure and without the consent of the Dean &amp; Chapter'. To this claim Sir Lewis Dibdin himself is opposed, but the Bishop (<persName xml:id="1727">Jayne</persName>) obtained favourable opinions from <persName xml:id="1736">Cripps</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="105">Talbot</persName>. The latter, however, are written in a very non&#8211;legal tone, &amp; suggest rather an essay on the powers of the Episcopate written in the interest of their revival &amp; extension than an honest attempt to state the law. On the question of Canons' preaching Dibdin holds that the matter is determined by the local statutes, &amp; that there is no general law.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
