<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[693]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">579</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was an appreciable snow&#8211;fall last night, perhaps two inches: it continues to be very cold. The heating apparatus in the Cathedral has chosen this moment to get out of order, and suspend action! The Judges will come to a vast refrigerator! I presided at a short meeting of Chapter, and afterwards went into the Cathedral with the Treasurer to see on the spot what might be done with the practical question, How to light the <placeName xml:id="77">Gregory chapel</placeName>? Also we went into the Nine Altars, and there I showed him the Southern windows, which I desire to have filled with stained glass as a County Memorial to the Durham troops. He expressed his approval.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> arrived about tea&#8211;time. I found him awaiting my exit from the Cathedral. We had a long and intimate conversation. It is not yet finally decided whether the British Association will meet in Newcastle this year. I hope not: but the organizing people will probably insist upon it. He tells me that the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> informed the deputation of Senate which went to him about the 'opening' of the theological degrees, that the <persName xml:id="532">Bishop of Ely</persName> had persuaded him to accept the Cambridge arrangement, which secures the Christian character of the degrees, so far as it can be secured, by manipulating the scheme of examination in the Christian interest. This action of the Bishop will terminate a foolish and too&#8211;long maintained inequality. For my part, I would encourage the better education of the sectaries on any terms. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3950"></persName><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Alan <persName xml:id="3951">Hutchinson</persName> &amp; the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> came to dine: and, later, <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest Henson</persName> arrived in khaki. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Hutchinson is of the intimate society of the County, representing a belt of old Durham families &#8211; Wilkinsons, Surtees, &amp;c &#8211; &amp; she is also intelligent.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
