<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[614]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"As to religion in general, it is a practical thing, &amp; no otherwise a matter of speculation, than common prudence in the management of our worldly affairs is so". <persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler's</persName> <ref xml:id="787">'Charge'</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>In 1751 Butler could say to the clergy of Durham, "It is highly reasonable now to instruct the people in the importance of external religion", for an almost total neglect had fallen upon most of it: but now, when external religion even in its pettiest forms has almost monopolized clerical concern, would that great prelate have spoken so?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at the meeting of the General Chapter, where we had nothing but formal business: and also at an ordinary Chapter which followed, when but little business had to be done.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I donned my new Convocation Robe, &amp; thus attired addressed the Churchwardens in the Galilee. My speech last about 10 minutes, and fell rather flat! Then I attended Evensong, &amp; thereafter watered the rhododendrons &amp;c in the garden &#8211; a messy proceeding!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Flexner's</hi><hi> Book, which is extremely well arranged and persuasive. It has corrected some opinions of my own, formed without any adequate basis of knowledge. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After dinner I read <persName xml:id="3601">Lecky's</persName> account of the Irish Rebellion in 1798, when the British troops gave some fine displays of "frightfulness"<ref xml:id="806"></ref>. </hi><hi>Our reading was interrupted by young <persName xml:id="3711">Lamb</persName>, the clock&#8211;winder, who came to order the clocks in the Deanery according to the "Summer time Act" which comes into force at 2 a.m. tomorrow.<note xml:id="308" n="1"></note> Later, about midnight as we now reckon, <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> and <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName> arrived from London by the late train, which was running fairly to time, &amp; by no means over&#8211;crowded.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
