<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[619]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">539</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliantly fine day, though rather cold. <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> went hunting with the <persName xml:id="3438">Rogersons</persName><persName xml:id="3439"></persName>: &amp; I worked at the <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> lecture, which has become nauseous to me. He must have been an ill person to live with: and he talked to everybody as if he were addressing a public meeting! Then </hi><hi rend="bold underline">beneath the vehemently asserted indifference to public criticism, it is impossible not to see that he resented it fiercely, &amp; positively hungered for praise</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> He was in a false position, the falsest possible position for any man, that of a fashionable preacher to idle supercilious people, who were for ever criticising people more earnest if less elegant than themselves. He was far too clear&#8211;sighted not to see this: &amp; far too honest not to understand it. In fact, '</hi><hi rend="underline">the iron entered into his soul</hi><hi>'. Do I not know the fact, &amp; the feeling? Though, at its worst, <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> could never have fallen to the level of a proprietary chapel at a fashionable watering&#8211;place! What a desert pulpit for a John Baptist! As I returned from my afternoon's walk, I fell in with a very young soldier in the Banks. He was going home on leave from Scotland to Cornwall, &amp; had hit on the very intelligent notion of breaking his journey on the way, to see as many interesting places as possible. I showed him the Cathedral, gave him a stall at Evensong, and afterwards fed him. It gave me an ill impression to see a lad who could not have been more than 16 years old passing as a soldier. He told me that there were many others no older than himself in the Army. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2663">his wife</persName> came in to dine. <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> arrived shortly before dinner, looking very grey &amp; tired. The War is wearing us all out with work, or grief, or the continuing chagrin of enforced idleness. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
