<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[577]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Epiphany, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">521</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. Three canons, two minor canons, &amp; a schoolmaster also present. My morning post was mainly favourable. It included letters from <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName>, Sir H. <persName xml:id="344">Craik</persName> &amp; Lyttelton <persName xml:id="3778">Gell</persName>. There came also a rude postcard from <persName xml:id="3927">Lady Russell</persName>. The "Times" had three letters, none of which called for an answer. Sir W</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2502">Chance</persName> was brief, angry, &amp; irrelevant. The <persName xml:id="3574">Bishop of Willesden</persName> was rude &amp; vehement: the <persName xml:id="3779">Secretary</persName> of <orgName xml:id="188">C.E.T.S.</orgName> sorrowfully indignant! None worth my notice. The afternoon post brought me several more approving letters, including one from <persName xml:id="390">Lathbury</persName>, &amp; another from the parson&#8211;antiquary, <persName xml:id="3985">Clark</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The entertainment of the college staff &amp; their wives went off without disaster. The choir&#8211;boys acted "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Merchant of Venice</hi><hi>" (the Trial Scene), and "</hi><hi rend="underline">Julius Caesar</hi><hi>" (Mark Antony's oration) with great energy: &amp; the Choir&#8211;men sang in the interval &amp; afterwards. The drawing&#8211;room makes an excellent theatre. There were 10 wounded soldiers from the little hospital, making about 100 altogether. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> was good enough to say that he had never known so good a spirit in the Cathedral Body during the 33 years since he had known it, as now obtained: &amp; he ascribed it to the influence of the Deanery. This was gratifying</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I accepted <persName xml:id="3984">Asher's</persName> invitation to give a public lecture in Brighton on the centenary of F. W. <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson's</persName> birth. It is an unfortunate addition to my work, but the notion of establishing a public right to speak on the occasion appealed to me. In one respect at least I may claim to be like the great preacher. As little as he am I to be classed in any recognized category, or brought under any conventional description. Moreover, whatever influence I possess (&amp; it is not much) is also derived from the ministry of preaching.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
