<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[660]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">627</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A dull mild morning, eloquent of tragedy! I read the ante&#8211;Communion service at 8 a.m. This, preceded by the Litany, took about 35 minutes. I wish our statutory services on Good Friday varied from the norm. It is a curious thing, not very easy of explanation, that our Reformers clung so undeviatingly to the conventional type of service. I attended Mattins, and heard a good little simple sermon from <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>. The service occupied an hour and 20 minutes. Then I rolled the front lawn by way of exercise. </hi><hi rend="italic">There was but a small congregation at Evensong, but it was very attentive. I preached from the First Word from the Cross, and bent my whole sermon to an attempt to rebuke the bitterly uncharitable feeling towards the German People, which (for very intelligible reasons) is spreading among us. I had a striking illustration of this to my hand in a wretched booked </hi><hi>[sic]</hi><hi rend="italic">, styled <ref xml:id="805">"Degenerate Germany"</ref>, which actually prints on its front page the words: "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Father forgive them for they know not what they do</hi><hi rend="italic">"! And Lord <persName xml:id="292">Rosebery's</persName> name appears on the cover as commending this hateful production!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The newspapers announce that a Russian contingent has landed at Marseilles to act with the French Army: that the Cabinet has reached agreement on the recruiting question, and will expound the proposals at a secret session of Parliament: and that America has taken what looks like decisive action on the submarine issue. Also it is announced that a young London parson, named <persName xml:id="3586">Mellish</persName> has received the V.C. for very gallant conduct. He was an A.K.C., and held a curacy at Deptford. After dinner we sate in my study, and I read some more of the Tragedy of 'King Lear', surely the most sombre of all Shakespeare's tragedies. The old King's consciousness of approaching madness, &amp; his dread of it, are heart&#8211;piercing indeed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
