<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[422]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">758</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3066">Figgis</persName> dominates the committee: &amp; Figgis is the disciple of <persName xml:id="1125">Lord Acton</persName>, who was a Roman Catholic. This suggestive paragraph in the Introduction to the volume of Lord Acton's Essays, <ref xml:id="173">"The History of Freedom"</ref>, edited by anecdotes &amp; Laurence is worth noting: &#8211; "There are not wanting signs that his (Lord Acton's) view of the true relations of States &amp; Churches may become one day more dominant, for it appears as though once more the earlier Middle Ages will be justified, and religious bodies become the guardians of freedom, even in the political sphere". This supposition is the thesis maintained in the book. "Churches in the Modern State", which seems to have been the quarry from which the Archbishops' Committee drew their materials.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3721">Miss Liddell</persName> lunched here, &amp; brought with her Colonel X, and his daughter. We all went to the Gymkhana, which was a great success. The weather, happily turned out favourably.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Morgan called to see me about <persName xml:id="1916">Arthur</persName>. He explained that for divers reasons he could no longer continue to contribute to his education. He said, however, that he would give the boy house&#8211;room &amp;c at home, if the cost of his schooling could be provided. I said that next term's expense should be met, &amp; that I would postpone any more complete arrangement until Christmas. Thus do responsibilities grow, and one's freedom of action gets filched away by one's softness of heart! In this case, while I think Arthur is a good youth enough, I suspect that his powers are somewhat less than moderate. It is no case of a young genius being given his opportunity, set free from the tyranny of '</hi><hi rend="underline">angusta res domi</hi><hi>' [narrow matters at home]. However, the disappointment of the young is always a very hateful thing, &amp; the boy's purpose has held steadily for some years now. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I dined alone.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
