<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[560]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">683</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I took the <persName xml:id="31">Cecils</persName><persName xml:id="3921"></persName> across to the Castle, and handed them over to <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>, who had kindly undertaken to act as their guide. I attended a little meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Trustees</orgName> to allot exhibitions to the school&#8211;children. After lunch the Cecils took their departure.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="75">Society for preventing cruelty to Children</orgName>, and made a speech. Then I prepared my sermons (old ones) for Jesmond next Sunday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Colonel <persName xml:id="3512">Darwin</persName> proposed a vote of thanks to me</hi><hi> in the meeting this afternoon, and used many kind expressions, which were very pleasant to listen to. He took up the observation which the speaker from town had used, as to the regret felt in Westminster at my departure for Durham, and said that they in Durham had gained much from my coming, and were always eager to hear me. This kind of compliment is wonderfully welcome to a man sceptical of his role, &amp; not at all easy in his conscience!	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have been dipping into "The Declining Birth&#8211;rate, its causes and effects", and find it contains much dolorous information. The use of preventives to conception appears to be well&#8211;established among the well&#8211;to&#8211;do classes, and widely extended among the artisans. An active missionary movement by the advocates of limiting birth&#8211;rate is in progress, and seems to inspire men with an almost religious fervour. The specialists seem unable to affirm that the methods employed are necessarily, or normally injurious to health: and they do not dispute the grave effect on morals which the general knowledge that such methods are physically harmless, would naturally have. The decay of religious conviction, which we are all lamenting, stands perhaps in closer relation to the extension of these evil practices than it is altogether pleasant to acknowledge.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
