<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[606]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">661</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; received the Holy Communion in <placeName xml:id="77">S. Gregory's Chapel</placeName>. Then, after breakfast, I finished the Edinburgh Sermon, and showed the <persName xml:id="42">Steel–Maitlands</persName><persName xml:id="701"></persName> over the Cathedral. Colonel <persName xml:id="3512">Darwin</persName> and his <persName xml:id="3813">wife</persName> came to lunch. I attended the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>, when a degree was given to D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3770">Bradley</persName>. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> presented him in an address of some length &amp; much merit. The undergraduates, a mere handful, made much uproar, but disclosed no wit. Then I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards went to Prof: <persName xml:id="3197">Bridges's</persName> Lecture on "Shakespeare &amp; Music", which was full of information &amp; very entertaining. After this, I went to the Lodge, &amp; shewed the Cuthbert relics, &amp;c to the Steel–Maitlands, &amp; D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3770">Bradley</persName>. After dinner I excused myself from to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2663">Cruickshank's</persName> reception, &amp; busied myself in my study.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Here is an example of unfortunate episcopal nervousness, which was related to me by M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Darwin. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">When Bishop <persName xml:id="1817">Lightfoot</persName> officiated</hi><hi rend="italic"> at the marriage of Archdeacon <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> &amp; Miss Thompson, he was very nervous, and pronounced the crowning formula in this form, "Those whom God hath put asunder, let not man join together". This must have struck a chill into the bride's heart, one might have supposed, but</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> <persName xml:id="2762">Watkins</persName> herself related the occurrence to M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Darwin</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Six more volumes of the Loeb Classical Society came in from the booksellers – two vols. of Ovid's Metamorphoses, another vol. of Plutarch's Lives, a volume of Marcus Aurelius, one of Plautus, and a volume of Virgil. It is pleasant thus to be assured that some human activities are persisting through the fearful obsessions of the War. </hi><hi rend="underline">That </hi><hi>tragedy is as yet quite unrelieved. Indeed an anxiety is being confessed in some quarters whether a satisfactory conclusion is possible.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
