<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[656]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">629</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright morning, though many clouds were about, &amp; more wind than I like. There were over 90 communicants, including <persName xml:id="3818">Hugh Lyon</persName>, <persName xml:id="3981">Gilbert Darwin</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3512">his parents</persName><persName xml:id="3813"></persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphins</persName>. I celebrated according to the Statute. It was to me an unusually moving service, but why is easier asked than answered. The Choral Eucharist was better attended than in the past, and more people stayed to the end. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I preached<ref xml:id="908"></ref> on a double text</hi><hi>: Eccl: III. 11 </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"He hath set eternity in their heart"</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; Col: i. 27 </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"Christ in you, the Hope of glory"</hi><hi rend="italic">. The congregation was extremely still, for which I was the more grateful as my voice was not in good form. </hi><hi>At Evensong the Cathedral seemed to be well filled. The procession went all round the church, and the singing was very fine. After the Benediction we sang one verse of the National Anthem. I took Logic for a walk after tea, escaping thus from a whole bevy of females! Hugh Lyon went off after dinner: and I settled down to letter&#8211;writing.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The morning post brought me a long letter of abuse on account of some report of my Good Friday Sermon. The writer classes me with the <persName xml:id="130">Archbishop of York</persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="3584">Headmaster of Eton</persName> as "one of the greatest traitors to the country"</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">Probably he, or she, is some half&#8211;witted person, who can hardly be held as responsible. But such persons have a certain value as indicators of opinion. Like the reeds on the river banks which bend &amp; rustle with every movement of the wind, they point the direction in which many minds are turning. Is it not as certain as anything could be that we have among us all the materials for the very fanaticism of hatred, which is now blinding the eyes of the German People to horrors which make all other civilized peoples shudder? "Let him that is without sin among you first cast a stone at her". </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
