<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[476]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">714</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> went off after an early breakfast, and I settled down to some necessary work. I wrote to <persName xml:id="412">Parker&#8211;Smith</persName>, <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2128">Olaf</persName>. I drew up a form of Service for August 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and gave it to the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>. I went to the Bank &amp; cashed a cheque. Finally I corrected the proofs of the <persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName> Article, and sent them back to the Secretary of the <orgName xml:id="107">Literature Society</orgName>. This brought me to lunch&#8211;time. I rolled the lawn, and attended Evensong.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[Symbol] Car&#x00F6;e tells me that the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> in the recent meeting of his <orgName xml:id="126">Diocesan Conference</orgName> at Lambeth made a new departure by putting up M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Davidson to address the members on the subject of the mission. We are getting on, as the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> said.. [sic] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Harris declining to sign a petition seeking clemency for the traitor Sir Roger Casement. His treason is unpardonable. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather today has been heavy but by no means warm, very dark and damp. The effect on one's energy &amp; spirits is deplorable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have decided to announce the service on August 6</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> as a 'Special Service of Prayer &amp; Thanksgiving after Two Years of War'.</hi><hi><note xml:id="313" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> This will suffice to differentiate it from those melancholy functions which suggest, or even affirm, that the War is a judgment on us for our sins, &amp; that it will continue until we have become Total Abstainers or Socialists or Papists or all three together! Crude praying for victory is one extreme, this Jonah's&#8211;call&#8211;to&#8211;the&#8211;Ninevites&#8211;attitude is the other. Is it not possible to find a middle course of modest &amp; manly religion, which, owning a most difficult duty, seeks from the Author of Duty the moral strength to fulfil it, &amp; thanks the Giver of all Good Things for what He has already granted?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[474]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Meanwhile, what is happening to the god of the Christians? Governments and peoples are behaving as though they knew him not; though the world is still crowded with his official representatives, who assuredly will not remain silent in the present crisis, which is the most uncompromising challenge ever made to their faith since it came into existence.["]</hi>
 </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1083">Loisy</persName> <ref xml:id="853">"The War &amp; Religion"</ref> p. 27</hi>
 </p>
         <p>
<hi>"The great moral forces of the past influence our present conditions no longer. The abominable scene which we are witnessing at present may well be more disquieting for that which is described popularly as belief than for what we define usually as unbelief."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ibid. p. 57</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This is the XX</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century counterpart of the monastic wail during the anarchy of Stephen's reign, when 'they said openly that Christ and his saints slept'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[472]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Durham on Tuesday, July 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, &amp; travelled to London. There I stayed at the Deanery, S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's, with <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>, until Saturday, the 22</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> when we both went to Windsor in order to spend the week&#8211;end with Ernest's <persName xml:id="546">parents</persName><persName xml:id="4026"></persName> at the Hermitage, Clewer. Ernest lunched with us at the Deanery, &amp; travelled with us, but had to return to Seaford on Sunday evening. He and I went together to the Holy Communion at Clewer Parish Church; &amp; later we all attended Evensong at St. George's, Windsor, calling first on that queer old stick <persName xml:id="2383">Dalton</persName>. We returned to St. Paul's Deanery on Monday the 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and stayed until Wednesday the 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. On Tuesday, the 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I lunched with <persName xml:id="1225" display="no">Meicklejohn</persName> at Brooks', attended a little conference of the "True Temperance Association" at the Westminster Palace Hotel, and dined with Lord <persName xml:id="601">Muir Mackenzie</persName>. On July 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, we went to Oxford, &amp; stayed for two nights at the Clarendon Hotel. We dined with the <persName xml:id="66">Pembers</persName><persName xml:id="937"></persName>, &amp; lunched with them on Thursday, when I attended <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray's</persName> Funeral at Mattins. On Friday, the 28</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, we lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2142">Oman</persName>, &amp; then parted, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> going to visit her relatives at Charlton Kings, &amp; I going to All Souls. After seeing <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> off at the station, I walked to the Acland Home to see <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>. I found him in the garden attended by his nurse. He is barely able to manage his speaking, &amp; he is very helpless, one side being paralyzed, but he seemed pleased to see me, &amp; I talked with him for half an hour. Then I returned to College, where I dined with <persName xml:id="2718">Cruttwell</persName>. He has been invalided home with rheumatism acquired in the trenches, &amp; is now employed in teaching the cadets at Oxford. On Saturday, the 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I lunched in the Buttery with Cruttwell and <persName xml:id="355">Fletcher</persName>, &amp; then walked with the latter to Somerville College, which </hi><hi rend="bold">[470] </hi><hi>is now used as a military hospital: &amp; then to the Acland Home to see Raleigh. On Sunday, the 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> July, I went to the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in St. Mary's. </hi><hi rend="italic">After breakfast I had a good deal of talk with Cruttwell about the chaplains at the front. He gives a very depressing account. They seem to be a mean&#8211;spirited &amp; feeble folk, little regarded by the men, and despised by the officers. This is confirmed by <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, of whom I had made specific inquiry. </hi><hi>I attended Mattins at S. Giles's: and then lunched with <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> in Christ Church. Cruttwell &amp; I went to see Raleigh: &amp; then I had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Oman. There was present a daughter of old General <persName xml:id="1129">Maurice</persName>. She introduced herself to me as a former member of my congregation. I dined in college with a very pleasant party. <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, <persName xml:id="2141">Oman</persName>, <persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName>, Cruttwell, <persName xml:id="2407">Johnson</persName> were all present, also <persName xml:id="3475">Rait</persName>, now a Professor in Scotland. We sate in the Quadrangle after dinner, and talked until 11 p.m. The warmth of the atmosphere was remarkable. On Monday, the 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> July, I loafed about the College all day; the heat making all exertion tiresome, &amp; dined with <persName xml:id="3708">Cholmondely</persName> in the Common Room. I finished reading through <persName xml:id="2685">Charnwood's</persName> book on <ref xml:id="814">'Abraham Lincoln'</ref>, and wrote him a complimentary letter. On Tuesday, August 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>, I left Oxford and travelled to Durham, where I arrived shortly after 5 p.m. I spent the remainder of the day in clearing off some correspondence which awaited me. </hi><hi rend="italic">I wrote to <persName xml:id="2131">Harold Cox</persName> to ask where he would care to have an article on the Archbishops' Committee on Church &amp; State for the October issue of the "Edinburgh", &amp; saying that, if so, I would be willing to write one</hi><hi><ref xml:id="779"></ref>.<note xml:id="316" n="2"></note></hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
