<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[651]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">557</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning began with rain, and passed into snow, which, however, melted as soon as it touched earth. But a slight fall of temperature might alter this, &amp; bar our way back to Durham with snow&#8211;drifts. I wrote some letters to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName>, and <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>. This, and reading the "Times", engaged me during the morning. After lunch we played with the children for awhile [sic], &amp; then <persName xml:id="2685">Godfry</persName> &amp; I walked for an hour and a half. Then tea, and pleasant talk with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4013">Thorpe</persName>. Taking down the Life of Charles <persName xml:id="3629">Kingsley</persName>, I happened to light upon a notable pronouncement on the subject of Teetotalism (vol. I p. 270&#8211;276) which contains the following rather notable prophesy:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"There will be from time to time reactions, as there were in the case of monkery, all the world knows. The substitute with the teetotallers of A.D. 1900 will be, I apprehend, laudanum. I expect, and hereby warn all friends, that the sale of laudanum will increase henceforth rapidly."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Thus wrote Kingsley in 1851. The "Times" states today that no less than 40 Canadian soldiers in a single regiment are victims of the drug habit. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3703">Maurice Peel</persName></hi><hi>, grandson of the great <persName xml:id="3097" display="no">Sir Robert</persName>, came to dine. He is now Vicar of Tamworth, and seems to be starting his work well. He is already a widower with two small children. I had some interesting talk with him about his experiences at the front, where he served as a chaplain for some months, was wounded, &amp; decorated for gallant conduct. He speaks with much affection of <persName xml:id="18">Gerald Marshall</persName>, under whom he was curate in the parish of S. Simon Zelotes, Bethnal Green.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
