<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[666]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday in Holy Week, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">623</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A cloudy morning, but higher temperature, and an end of the East wind. I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> celebrated, and all the Canons now in college communicated, together with 3 of the minor canons. The morning post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. He writes from hospital where apparently he is down with influenza. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Also a very characteristic letter from <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName></hi><hi> in continuation of his last letter about <ref xml:id="85">"Robertson"</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The worst violence of the Revolution was the work of cultivated bourgeoisie – professors, lawyers, &amp;c, possessors of that classical education which is supposed to soften the manners".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This is a depressing sentence enough: but its truth cannot be doubtful to any student, &amp; finds daily confirmation among ourselves. Gustave Le Bon is miserably suggestive.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Ernest, and to the Senior Chaplain of his camp, promising to preach to the troops on April 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> at Seaford. It is inconvenient enough, but I want to see him again, &amp; this gives me the chance. Of course, he may have been moved to France before then. In any case, the vacant Sunday will have been decently utilized. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName> walked with me to the golf course, &amp; through Houghall Wood. I attended Evensong, &amp; then wrote letters to <persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName>, <persName xml:id="113">Harold Knowling</persName>, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName>. After dinner I read poetry to my family, until bed–time.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"In war more than any other time there is no better inspiring force than hatred: it was hatred that made Blücher victorious over Napoleon".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Fear plays almost as large a part in revolutions as hatred. During the French Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> there were many examples of great individual courage &amp; many exhibitions of collective cowardice". (G. Le Bon)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
