<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[697]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">581</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The snow&#8211;storms still continue: but in spite of them the Zeppelins came here yesterday, and got across much country. I spent the forenoon in writing a letter to the "Spectator", headed <lb/>"</hi><hi rend="underline">Sectarianism &amp; Secularisation</hi><hi>", &#x00E0; propos of the proposal, which the editor approves ecstatically, and which the War Office seems to encourage, to organize battalions on a sect. basis. This appears all one with the gradual but sure secularisation of the Army as such. After lunch I took <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> for a walk in wind and snow. He gives rather a bad account of the sexual morality of the officers, and thinks that irregularities are winked at, or even encouraged, by some of the older officers, who probably represent a tradition of license which has been generally outgrown. The amount of venereal disease is certainly disgracefully great. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral. <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> arrived from Aberdeen, where he delivered the Murtle Lecture, &amp; preached yesterday. He, as everybody else, is delighted with Sir <persName xml:id="244">George Adam Smith</persName>. I dined with Major <persName xml:id="3948">Sharp</persName> [Sharpe] and the Officers instructing the young fry in <placeName xml:id="61">Hatfield Hall</placeName>. All these soldiers have been at the front, &amp; returned home wounded. They have strange experiences to relate, and they relate them with a very delightful modesty. Major Sharp has had much service in Africa, &amp; speaks with intelligence of the fauna. The rats in the trenches climbed trees when the German gas&#8211;attacks were made, &amp; the nightingales sang through these horrors! It is suggested that the hawks have been scared away, &amp; that their normal victims, the smaller birds, find the vague dangers of human warfare comparatively undisturbing! I had a good deal of talk with Ralph before he turned in. He is evidently more than ever out of harmony with his colleagues, &amp; the Cathedral traditions! </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
