<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[556]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">685</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Last night I sate with the candidates, and thought myself back to the time when I was myself also a candidate. My note book has this entry under date 'Saturday, June 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1887':</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I wrote a letter to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> thanking him for the help he had given me by his example and counsel </hi><hi rend="underline">to shake off the claims of the pseudo&#8211;Catholic theory</hi><hi>: also I finished the letter to the Abbot which I have put together at intervals during the last few days, </hi><hi rend="underline">stating as far as I could my "attitude" on 'burning questions'</hi><hi>. Then I walked into the meadows beyond the church, and sate on a style to meditate. And as I thought, the desire came to me to pledge myself to God there and then: which I forthwith did, bare&#8211;headed under the open heaven, promising to be loyal to the Truth, wherever I found it, wheresoever it should call me to seek for it".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked to the station, and took the 9.17 a.m. train to Newcastle. Here we were the guests for the day of Judge <persName xml:id="3918">Bonsey</persName> &amp; his wife. I preached twice in Jesmond Parish Church. In the morning my subject was the Christian Ministry<ref xml:id="911"></ref>, a subject which appeared to be suitable for 'Ordination Sunday'. In the evening I repeated the often&#8211;repeated sermon on Psalm 119.96. "I see that all things come to an end but Thy Commandent is exceeding broad". The congregations at both services were large &amp; attentive. At lunch we met an interesting old seaman, Admiral <persName xml:id="3932">Tate</persName>, &amp; his wife. During the afternoon we had tea with the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1981">Wild</persName>. They were engaged in entertaining the newly&#8211;ordained parsons &amp; their friends. We had supper with the Bonseys, and then returned by train to Durham, arriving in the Deanery about 10.20 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
