<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[378]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">774</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2311">Lady Renshaw</persName> carried off <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to see the Clyde. <persName xml:id="230">Sir Charles</persName> went into Glasgow on business. I was comfortably established in the Billiard Room, and left to myself. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName>, Arthur <persName xml:id="1916">Morgan</persName>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName></hi><hi>, and Commendator Richard <persName xml:id="4058">Bagot</persName>. Also I revised my sermons: and wrote up my journal. After lunch I went to meet mine host and brought him back to Barochan in time for tea. Later, we walked over his farm together. The fields were being cleared of their crops, from which a crowd of feeding pigeons rose as we approached. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Renshaw said that after the war he expected the most serious labour troubles</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He pointed out that transport workers of every kind were now linked up, and could act together. He feared that their political action might result in the serious attempt to establish in England the labour policy which prevails in Australia. The influence of <persName xml:id="3847">Hughes</persName>, the Commonwealth Premier, would tell in this direction. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Probably the five shilling income tax would be a permanent arrangement, for the post&#8211;bellum Budget</hi><hi> could hardly be less than that which is now being provided. It is certainly a depressing outlook. There came to dinner a neighbour named Speirs who holds a large property in these parts. Though already over 45 he is still unmarried having been 'hodden doon' by his mother, a masterful and appropriating lady who died recently at the age of 92! This gentleman expressed much discontent with the elective method of appointing parish ministers. But I assured him, all churches are at their worst in their systems of ministerial appointment. Probably the root of the difficulty lies in the irreconcilable conflict between spiritual office and professional preferment, between the '</hi><hi rend="underline">cura animarum</hi><hi>' [cure of souls] and the '</hi><hi rend="underline">benificium</hi><hi>' [promotion]. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
