<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[358] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">783</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"In the Paradise Lost &#8211; indeed in every one of his poems &#8211; it is Milton himself whom you see; his Satan, his Adam, his Raphael, almost his Eve &#8211; are all John Milton; and it is a sense of this intense egotism that gives me the greatest pleasure in reading Milton's works. The egotism of such a man is a revelation of spirit".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2152">Coleridge's</persName> <ref xml:id="337">Table talk</ref>. P. 278.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>How far does this give the key to the interpretation of the poet?</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There was but the Sub&#8211;dean of the corporate body, and 3 minor canons. After breakfast I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On any shewing, lumping into a single description the whole numbers certified as Roman Catholics, Jews, &amp; Salvationists, and adding the sum to the communicants, both Anglican and Nonconformist, the total is under 7 ½ millions out of a population (1911) of 36, 071,000, of whom in round numbers as many as 25,000,000 are above the age of fifteen. Something between 1/3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> and 1/4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> of the people may be deliberately religious. It is difficult to resist the suspicion that nearly as many may be deliberately hostile to religion. The formal Christianity of England turns on the attitude which the residuum of </hi><hi rend="underline">unconnected</hi><hi> people may adopt. </hi><hi rend="italic">It has been hitherto friendly: it may easily become hostile, or contemptuous. The last is what I fear most. The presentation of Christianity in our Church Papers impresses me often as contemptible. How would it impress me if I were neither a clergyman nor a professed Christian, but just a 'man of the world', neglectful of the conventional habits of religious observance, and interested in some branch of science, or in Art, Literature, or Politics? How can it be anywise surprising that men weary of the clergy and their doings? How can the nation accept a mission from the Church?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[356]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was alone at Mattins, (i.e. no major canon was present), an unprecedented occurrence. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> read the first lesson for me, &amp; I read the 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> and preached. The sermon (which has already done duty at Windsor and Glasgow) served me again. There was but a small congregation, and that more than commonly feminine! <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName> has some gossip about another Zeppelin raid last night, and the destruction of another air&#8211;ship, but these comfortable legends are apt to shrink wonderfully when Monday's newspaper gives the actual occurrences! I attended Evensong, and afterwards motored to Eppleton, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">taking with me two of the choristers, <persName xml:id="3571">George Nimmins</persName> and <persName xml:id="3572">Edgar Dobbie</persName></hi><hi>. As we drew near to the church our progress was impeded by the crowds of people, and soon reduced to walking pace by a procession of ambulance brigades, nurses &amp;c who filled the centre of the roadway. Eppleton Church was crowded to its utmost capacity, Freemasons, Special Constables, Ambulances &amp;c were all present. I preached again from Jeremiah ix. 23, 24; but extemporaneously from notes. The people were very attentive, and seemed to be impressed. We motored home in the dangerous half&#8211;light, the two boys being mightily pleased with themselves, as they had been placed in the choir &amp; made much of! We arrived back at the deanery about 8.20 p.m. I wrote to Ralph, and to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Coleridge</hi><hi> has this just observation on his Table&#8211;Talk (p.271):&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The cosmopolitism which does not spring out of, and blossom upon, the deep&#8211;rooted stem of nationality or patriotism, is a spurious and rotten growth".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This was spoken in 1833, and apparently with special reference to the Quakers, who were both cosmopolites and philanthropists.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
