<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[599]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">533</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received the books from the London Library: &amp; proceeded to read them. Arnold's book (<ref xml:id="800">'Robertson of Brighton, with some notes of his times &amp; contemporaries'</ref>) is tiresomely discursive &amp; egotistic, but it is useful as correcting the rather too idolatrous volumes of M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Stopforde [Stopford] <persName xml:id="3960">Brooke</persName>. An observation of Henry Crabb <persName xml:id="3974">Robinson</persName> entered in his Diary under the date Oct. 23</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rd</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1846, when he first met <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> at Heidelberg, sums up the great preacher's attitude very justly:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"He is liberal in his opinions: &amp; though he is alarmed by the Puseyites, he seems to dislike the Evangelicals much more."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">But Robertson was always conscious of a certain instability in his opinions</hi><hi rend="italic">. 'He once said to a friend, who reported to me the incident', says M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Arnold, "These are my present ideas: I am not quite sure what they will be next year".' He must have been a strange, volcanic creature, full of surprises for his friends. "His very calm was a hurricane" said Lady <persName xml:id="3977">Byron</persName> who knew him well. C&#x00E9;sar <persName xml:id="3976">Malan's</persName> prophetical speech was abundantly justified, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Mon tr&#x00E8;s cher fr&#x00E8;re, vous aurez une triste vie et un triste minist&#x00E8;re</hi><hi rend="italic">". [My very dear friend, you would have a sad life and a sad ministry.] But the speaker was accustomed to take a sombre view of the Christian minister's lot. He told Arnold 'that within his experience very few ministers were happy men'. I can affirm the truth of this for one. There is a very acute &amp; illuminating comment on Robertson's catholicity in a letter of <persName xml:id="3775">Campbell</persName> of Row. (v. Memorials. ii. p.109), whose sympathy with the English divine was not unmixed with a certain suspicion of his tendency. It is extremely difficult in 1915 to understand the tremendous hold on devout &amp; independent minds which the doctrine of the Atonement possessed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
