<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[653]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">558</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We bade farewell to our friends, and returned to Durham. The train left Lichfield at 9.52 a.m., and went as far as Burton, where we had a wait of about 45 minutes. This we utilized by strolling into the town the see the ravage of the Zeppelins, and the majesty of Beer. It is a city of breweries. The church, a pretentious &amp; costly edifice in the Gothic style, is inscribed with the name of the Principal Brewer, whose statue stands outside it in regal prominence clad in peerage garb. <persName xml:id="3964">Lord Burton's</persName> wealth has flowed over Burton, as Lord Burton's beer has flowed over Britain. The very children in the streets have the aspect of infant draymen &amp; pot&#8211;boys &#8211; fat, somnolent, florid, &amp; humourous! Leaving the Metropolis of Beer at 11.8 [sic] a.m. we proceeded with frequent stops to York where we changed, and went on to Durham, arriving about 4.45 p.m. The last stage of the journey was relieved by the company &amp; conversation of some officers of the Sutherland &amp; Argyllshire regiment, week&#8211;ending from Ripon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Church Papers treat <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> of Brighton with suggestive neglect. There is no reference to him at all in the "Church Times": none at all in the "Record": a ludicrously inadequate paragraph in the "Guardian", ludicrous &amp; misleading for it misses the whole point of his career, assuming that like the general run of popular preachers he had enjoyed a great celebrity in his life&#8211;time, and a sudden eclipse after his death. Whereas, the precise contrary was the fact in Robertson's case. The "British Weekly" alone did justice to the great Preacher's memory. Except the "Times" &amp; the "Westminster" I cannot find that the secular press has noticed the centenary</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
