<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[478]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">713</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> and I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName> celebrated. </hi><hi rend="italic">The morning post brought me a very delightful &amp; characteristic letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi>. I read an excellent article by Alfred <persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> in the current issue of the "Modern Churchman". It is full of good things well expressed e.g.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>"The clergy are becoming to an increasing extent the private chaplains of the devout".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"The unity of the church is one of direction, not of creed&#8211;content".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>We attended Mattins, &amp; heard a rather windy harangue about the Mission from Brother <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName>. Then we walked for an hour returning to lunch with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3805">Fearne</persName>. I attended Evensong and afterwards gave tea to the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName> &amp; their guests, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Sandford. <persName xml:id="2806">Bailey</persName> also came bringing with him a letter he had received from his brother who is a staff officer at the front. He describes some of the recent fighting. It is rather disconcerting to hear that our own troops (London <orgName xml:id="92">Territorials</orgName>) are still 'amateurs' as against the Germans; that they suffer from lack of experienced N.C.O.'s: &amp; that they hardly know how to use their ammunition to the best advantage. I was pleased to hear that the Germans let us bring back our wounded, &amp; even gave them assistance. We dropped a letter of thanks from an aeroplane, after arresting attention with a bomb! That appears to be the established procedure in that kind of correspondence. After dinner I shewed Car&#x00F6;e the volume of <persName xml:id="3934">Raemacker's</persName> cartoons which were mostly new to him. They certainly are wonderful in their power, their depth of feeling &amp; extraordinary suggestiveness. As a record of the Great War this volume is superior to all the histories now written, or being written.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
