<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[430]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">754</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Instigante diabolo</hi><hi> [at the instigation of the devil] (as my excellent wife thinks) I wrote a short letter, more or less in identical terms, to the Challenge, the Guardian, the Record, &amp; the Church Times on the Council of the National Mission, asking who the members may be, &amp; which of them attended the meetings at which the Resolutions on Women's Preaching and the Distribution of Church Endowments were adopted. I worked at the Article. After lunch I had a delightful walk with <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>. The view from the golf&#8211;course was splendid. I attended Mattins and Evensong. <persName xml:id="1559">Lord Barnard</persName> wrote to ask me to become Provincial Grand Chaplain for this year, and I consented though my knowledge of Freemasonry is ridiculously small, &amp; the functions bore me abominably. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, and to <persName xml:id="2936">Jack Boden</persName>.<note xml:id="319" n="1"></note> After dinner Olive sang all her songs very sweetly, &amp; I listened with the sad knowledge that her delightful presence was about to be withdrawn. We went into my study, and there I read poetry for an hour. Olive listens with extraordinary appreciation &amp; ardour. It is a delight to have such a listener. I read some poems of William Watson, &amp; <persName xml:id="660">Faber</persName>, ending with the glorious passage in Milton's 'Comus', which I had quoted in the course of our walk:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>	So dear to Heaven is saintly chastity,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	That, when a soul is found sincerely so,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	A thousand liveried angels lacky her,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	Driving far off each thing of sin and guilt;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	And in clear dream and solemn vision,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	Tell her of things that no gross ear can hear;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	Till oft converse with heavenly habitants</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	Begin to cast a beam on the outward shape,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	The unpolluted temple of the mind,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	And twin it by degrees to the soul's essence,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>	Till all be made immortal &#8211;</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
