<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[428]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">755</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"A creed, a theory of the origin and order of the world is not necessarily religion; but whatever the case with other men, no religious man ever doubted that he had a direct &amp; immediate relation to God, that he was God's choice &amp; handiwork &amp; care. Religion, in its earliest and most perfect form, rests on this faith, as the first axiom and foundation for all that it speaks and does and endures". (Dean Church. Pascal &amp;c. 312)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> before going to the cathedral for Mattins: also to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Morgan, bidding him come &amp; see me about <persName xml:id="1916">Arthur</persName>. Then I went to Mattins, &amp; listened to a sermon from <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> delivered to the accompaniment of such a deluge of rain as made the preacher's voice almost inaudible. Then, I celebrated the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; our guests communicated. After service I took <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> round the Church for a last view: and we renewed our covenant very solemnly. <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211; Falkner</persName> came to lunch: he was more than commonly paradoxical. Then I went to Evensong. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> and <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName> came in to tea: the latter had never before seen <persName xml:id="3934">Raemacker's</persName> pictures, &amp; was much impressed with them. After dinner Olive sang those of her songs which were congruous with Sunday evening: and then we moved into my study, and I read poetry for an hour. <persName xml:id="1348" display="no">Browning</persName> and Matthew <persName xml:id="1460">Arnold</persName> were again chosen. So we came to the end of a visit which has given me very much pleasure. Olive's singing, and sweetness of character, make her presence in the house delightful. I would give much to have such a daughter living in my house: perhaps, she divined my thoughts, and was not displeased. Anyway, I left her in no doubt as to the pleasure she had given.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[426]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Letter from D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>, dated October 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1915.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Dean,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Henson will be interested in a small discovery I have made connected with the Deanery. I had told you about the 16</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century </hi><hi rend="underline">Iter Boreale</hi><hi> [Northern journey] of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3907">Eades</persName> with its account of the installation of Toby Matthew. An obscure reference in it to <persName xml:id="3908">Walsingham</persName> led me to look up the State Papers of 1583. I have found that Walsingham stayed five days at the Deanery Sept. 21&#8211;26, 1583. During that short period the house was the centre of his many policies, and I have come across five letters actually written by him in your house, &amp; references to correspondence received there from Elizabeth and others. Messengers kept coming and going all the time. I am working out the details for the Newcastle Antiquaries to whom I read a paper on the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. I am curious to know what the </hi><hi rend="underline">Codex Deacani Dunelmensis</hi><hi> [Codex of the Deacon of Durham] may be. I tried to get it from Miles and found you had anticipated me. A journal of Matthews would be a real discovery. What is the MS.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Gee</hi>
         </p>
</div>
            <p></p>
            </body></text></TEI>
