<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[696]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">611</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright but clouded morning, &amp; rather cold. I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> celebrated. The morning post was late but, when it arrived, brought me a long &amp; very welcome letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. Also a long and valuable letter about <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName> from a parson named Charles Green, enclosing some newspaper cuttings of value on the same subject. I wish I had seen all this before my book had gone to press. If ever it should be re&#8211;issued, there would be an opportunity for utilizing a good bit of material that has come to hand during the last month. I wrote great part of the sermon for next Sunday. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3675">Stobart</persName>, the wife of Lord Durham's <persName xml:id="3677">agent</persName>, came to lunch. I walked with Logic round Houghton Wood. Falling in with Lillingston I tried to discover from him what precisely was intended by the "National Mission" of which in these parts he is the principal organizer: but he could tell me nothing coherent. All is so far phrase &amp; vapour! I wrote a long letter to Ernest, dealing very plainly with the matter named in his letter to me. Then I went to the special service in the Cathedral &amp; heard <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> preach an excellent little sermon. As we sate together after dinner in my study we were cast into sudden darkness by reason of the Zeppelins!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
