<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[695]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, March 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">580</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Again snow, and at intervals snow&#8211;showers, making a very uninviting aspect. I celebrated at 9 a.m. There were but few communicants. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> preached at the military service. At Mattins the two Judges, <persName xml:id="3403">Sankey</persName> and <persName xml:id="3739">Low</persName>, accompanied by the <persName xml:id="3622">High Sheriff</persName> attended the service. I preached from Proverbs VIII. 15, </hi><hi rend="underline">'By me kings reign, and princes decree justice. By me princes rule, and nobles, even all the judges of the earth'</hi><hi>. The congregation seemed to me little, if at all, larger than ordinary. In order in some degree to mitigate the effect of the absence of heating, the old gas&#8211;jets along the triforium were lighted, &amp; contributed a slightly asphyxiating character to the chilly atmosphere. <persName xml:id="3801">Lady Gort</persName> &amp; her son, <persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2895">his daughter</persName>, Miss Dalton, and two of the officers, Major <persName xml:id="3948">Sharp</persName> [Sharpe] and Captain Walsh, came to lunch. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest Henson</persName> walked with me: and then I attended Evensong. Mendelssohn's "Hear my prayer" was admirably sung. I never heard Kay sing with more feeling.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As we sate round the fire in my study after dinner the electric light grew dim, and then failed altogether, driving us to the candles, which have been so long discarded as to have acquired the curious interest of new discoveries. There has been talk of intentions in high place [sic] to make experiments in sudden darkness as a prophylactic against Zeppelins, &amp; presumably this is what happened. Ernest is as voluble as ever, &amp; the account which he gives of our military preparations (so far as his personal experiences during the last 18 months has given him any knowledge of them) is not without disquieting features. The complete mutual ignorance of men and officers cannot assist discipline, or strengthen attack.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
