<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[524]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">697</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read the Psalms appointed for the day to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> as she finished her self&#8211;arrangement before descending to breakfast. Always when I read the Psalms I marvel at them, and acknowledge their strange power. That they should ever have been composed is much: that they should continue from century to century to arrest and retain the affectionate interest of religious men is much more. The inherent spirituality of human nature alone can explain this most impressive fact. It is certain, I think, that the Psalms rise in the regard of educated men: that they commend themselves more to manhood than to youth: that the type of religion they express &#8211; unceremonial, unlegal, profoundly individual &#8211; is particularly congruous with the modern mind. The high literary quality of the Prayer&#8211;book version, and its familiarity by reason of its use in the public worship, are other factors which strengthen the hold of the Psalms on the minds of Englishmen. Does there not arise from all this a weighty practical objection to any changes in the Prayer&#8211;book, or in the customary services of the National Church, which would have the effect of removing the Psalms form the habitual use of English Churchmen? And could any other result be reasonably anticipated from the substitution of Holy Communion for Mattins, which is now being so eagerly pressed for? Apart from the objection, itself very weighty, that the change could not but mark a notable advance in the process of assimilating the Anglican to the Roman system, is it not a sufficient objection to such substitution that it would endanger the hold which the Psalms now possess on the knowledge and habit of English Christians? </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[522]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The paper reports the conclusion of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Roger Casement's</hi><hi> trial in his condemnation to death as a traitor. No other verdict was possibly [sic], for he was captured red&#8211;handed in his treason. He read a statement of rather a melodramatic sort, posing as a martyr for Ireland; but he left unexplained the fact that his single&#8211;minded devotion to Ireland had been consistent with life&#8211;long service to the King, and only forced him to separate his duty to Ireland from his duty to his Sovereign, when by such separation he had a chance of doing his Sovereign the gravest injury. He has been condemned to be hanged, but there will be great exertions made to prevent the carrying out of the sentence. My sense of justice would be offended if he should be reprieved, when humbler men, his victims, have been left to their fate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote some letters, and then walked for an hour with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3720">Bob Liddell</persName></hi><hi> in the woods. Then came lunch, and with it the <persName xml:id="3938">Vicar</persName> of Lamesley &#8211; an elderly dull man, with an obsequious underbred manner. He asked me to preach on Sunday, but I declined perforce as I had neither sermon nor robes. It always provokes me when the clergy thus take for granted that one never takes any pains in preparing one's sermons. No doubt they do but draw an inference from their own procedure, &amp; are guiltless of any insulting purpose. Nevertheless the assumption is insulting to a serious preacher in no common degree. The Vicar spoke of the projected Mission with much dubiety &amp; dejection: and of the new scheme for Diocesan Finance with evident aversion. He said that the 'Pilgrimage of Prayer' threatened to invade his parish, where it would be neither welcome nor effective! Outside the organizing faction I can discover nobody who approves this 'National' Mission!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[520]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3721">Miss Liddell</persName></hi><hi> motored us into Newcastle, where we visited the exhibition of German War&#8211;Cartoons. They throw an ugly light on the spirit of Germany. Coarseness, brutality, cynicism, occasional obscenity are the prevailing notes. Then we visited the old castle, which is a relic of the early Norman period filled with many&#8211;sided interest. Having picked up at the station the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marquess of <persName xml:id="3936">Normanby</persName></hi><hi> &amp; his wife, we returned to <placeName xml:id="63">Ravensworth</placeName> for tea. I wrote letters, &amp; read a novel until dinner. Conversation turned much on Ireland which Lord Normanby evidently knows well. He described in a very interesting manner his visits to the West of Ireland, the primitive ignorance of the peasantry, &amp; their crude superstitions, also their charming politeness &amp; simplicity. We discussed education, &amp; I learned with surprise that the Headmaster of the Manchester Grammar School had (this was 30 years or more ago) affirmed that he found his best classical scholars had been trained in the National Schools. There they had received a thorough grounding in the "3 Rs.", and this provided an excellent foundation on which it was possible to raise the fabrick of a classical education.<note xml:id="314" display="no" n="1"></note> My own observations hardly accord with this. It seems to me that the mental environment of the ordinary National School&#8211;boy is so unfavourable to intellectual interests, habitudes, and ideals, that the lads who have no other in their early years are hardly able to rise above mediocrity later. I must needs ascribe some importance also to heredity. The transmitted nature of the artisan is not well&#8211;adapted to an intellectual career. Sometimes in boyhood or adolescence there is a fallacious appearance of brilliant promise, but there is rarely any staying power: &amp; the bright spring leads most often to disappointment &amp; failure.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
