<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[576]</hi>
  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">676</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a letter from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> A. Kneel including a photograph of the young naval officer whom I met in the train on the way to London on May 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He wrote to tell me that the lad, his son, had been killed in the recent naval battle, when his ship, the 'Defence' was destroyed. I wrote immediately to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Kneel, sending him a copy of <ref xml:id="84">"War&#8211;time Sermons"</ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "Record" and the "Challenge" publish the letters "Festina lente" [make haste slowly] which I sent to both papers on the rather impudent proposal that in the view of the "National Mission" the Evangelicals should consent to substitute "Holy Communion" for Mattins as the 'principal service on the Lord's Day[']. I think there are clear signs of mutual suspicion and misgiving among these 'Missioners'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a letter from <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> (now Archdeacon in succession to <persName xml:id="109">Wilberforce</persName>) respecting the letter which the 'Times' rejected (v .p. 580). </hi><hi rend="bold underline">As I suspected, he had been sounded by the <persName xml:id="2709">Editor</persName> of the "Times", and had championed Bishop <persName xml:id="3765">Gwynne</persName></hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards rolled the lawn. "Land and Water"<note xml:id="312" display="no" n="1"></note> has a very cheering article on the Naval Battle, making out that it was a considerable British victory, &amp; that the German fleet has been so knocked about that a long time must elapse before it will be in a condition to fight again. There is also a careful, apparently well&#8211;informed, and extremely eulogistic article on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>, which may perhaps be serviceable. The under&#8211;current of insulting innuendo which sets through the nation from Printing House Square is strong enough to affect some sections of public opinion, &amp; needs checking.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
