<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[222]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">842</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright morning with a white frost on the ground, very wintry to look at. Still bad news from Roumania &#8211; Craiova has fallen. It uncovers Orsova, the Key of the Danube; and almost certainly opens the "Iron Gates", giving again free passage for munitions down the great river, &amp; relieving the German invader of dependence on the Carpathian passes. Also, </hi><hi rend="underline">the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">death of the old Emperor, <persName xml:id="3737">Francis Joseph</persName>,</hi><hi> is reported. The political effects of this event have probably been fully discounted during the long period of senility which preceded it. Still, it may add something to the general sense of dissolution, which is spreading in Austria.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a presentation copy of a book entitled <ref xml:id="831">"Church Divisions and Christianity"</ref> by Prebendary <persName xml:id="3736">Grane</persName>, the same foolish and prolific writer who published that curiously silly book (which ran through four divisions!) <ref xml:id="832">"The Passing of War"</ref>. He appears to think that the problem of reunion will be solved by the antiquarians! As if fanaticks could be so easily cured! "Wilt thou bind him for thy maidens?" I apprehend that the sacerdotalist frenzy is a more formidable monster than Leviathan. The prosing of antiquaries will be no more effective than the bleating of the pacifists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. At 4 p.m. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip le <persName xml:id="3919">Mesurier</persName></hi><hi> took me out for a walk. We had much conversation on religious matters; &amp; I allowed myself to speak very frankly to him. He seems a good youth, not disinclined to rebel against the rather aggressive sacerdotalism of his present surroundings. Walking &amp; talking were no unimportant part of the educational process to which the undergraduate was subjected at Oxford. Why not also at Durham?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[220] </hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>November 22</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> 1916</hi>
         </p>
<hi>My dear <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName></hi>
         <p>
<hi>I should be grateful if you would put together for my use so much information as, in your judgment, seems requisite on the "preliminary factors" of a career (e.g. family, home life, childhood &amp;c &amp;c) up to the time when the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> went to Eton,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Next, I want you to consider who w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> give me a trustworthy account of his life at Eton, &amp; Balliol. I have it in my mind to write to <persName xml:id="1394">R. E. Prothero</persName>, and the <persName xml:id="2521">President of Magdalen</persName>, both of whom w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have known him well. For his career as a politician, that is, in Parliament, I think, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2091">Rawlinson</persName>, the member for Cambridge University, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="508">Balfour</persName>, Colonel <persName xml:id="838">Lockwood</persName>, and the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> might help us. What do you think of these names? If you can suggest others, I shall be grateful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You will see that my mind is revolving what I look upon as a sacred task, though, as I told you before, I cannot really set to work until the New Year.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear Miss Anson</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Most sincerely yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
