<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[248]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">827</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> went off to West Hartlepool, and I 'wrastled' with a sermon for Assize Sunday. At least I have a text: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The law hath been our tutor to bring us unto Christ</hi><hi>"; and I wrote a few pages, enough to disclose to myself a possible treatment! I attended Mattins and Evensong, and lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi>. The afternoon post brought me a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi>. He is evidently more cheerful, and has been reciting Shakespeare to his brother officers! He has made the acquaintance of Lord Darnley &amp; shown the treasures of Cobham Hall. After Evensong I wrote to Ernest. Cruickshank and <persName xml:id="2806">Bailey</persName> came to dinner; we had a good deal of architectural conversation. Car&#x00F6;e ventured the assertion that the Neville Screen, the monument of Edward III in Westminster Abbey, and Cardinal Bourchier's monument in Canterbury Cathedral were all the work of the same artist. He based his theory on the identity of the ornamentation in all these works, but I should like the evidence of identity before me before pronouncing on it.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
