<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">844</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="2763" display="no">Alice Barwick</persName> giving me some information about <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>. He 'was wounded on Nov. 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He was 'in the great advance of that day, &amp; only reached the first line of German trenches when a shell exploded near him wounding him in the hip, hand, &amp; throat'. Later in the day I wrote to him. After attending Mattins, I worked at next Sunday's sermon, being interrupted by visits from <persName xml:id="2806">Bailey</persName>, Col. <persName xml:id="1659">Burdon</persName>, &amp; the Mayor. Col. Burdon stayed to lunch. I attended the Mayor's meeting at the Town Hall. Two officers from Gen. <persName xml:id="3849">Montgomery's</persName> staff attended, and explained that the Government intended to place in Durham a battalion (1600&#8211;2000 men) of dockers. A committee was appointed to act with them in arranging for the housing of the men. After the meeting I walked with <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> for an hour. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Guardian" contains three letters criticizing <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> <ref xml:id="828">'Manual'</ref>, severally from <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName>, from myself, &amp; from Bethune&#8211;Baker</hi><hi rend="italic">. Ralph includes in his letter an extremely severe, but thoroughly well&#8211;merited rebuke of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, whose insulting reference to him &amp; to me, appeared in the "Guardian" of last week.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, who is still at Gravesend. He writes rather despondently of himself, &amp; his observations on religion and the Church do not wholly please me. His real interest is for the present directed almost exclusively to Shakespeare &amp; Dickens. Perhaps, I ought not to exert any influence in the direction of getting him to seek Ordination. I cannot honestly say that so far I see any clear evidence of what it is the general custom to describe as 'a vocation to Orders'! (cf p. 709)</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
