<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[218]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">843</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to my study after the sweep's operations, and the subsequent cleaning up. The morning was strangely wasted: no progress being made with the sermon for next Sunday. Then <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came in, &amp; I gave him the two volumes "Quentin Durward" and "Anne of Geierstein", as a Birthday present. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. Then I walked with <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>. He shares the consternation with which I regard the present action of the Archbishops. After tea I wrote a letter to the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>", under the heading:&#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Transformation of the Church of England &#8211; a warning &amp; a protest</hi><hi>". It was occasioned by a long pronouncement signed by both the Primates, announcing various arrangements designed to follow on the 'National Mission'. I don't know whether the "Times" will publish my letter: but it seemed worth while trying the Editor once more. In the course of this performance, <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> appeared. He said that my references to the Archbishops' Committee, though severe, could not be disputed, as every member of the Committee knew them to be true. There would probably be no answer to my "Edinburgh Review" Article<ref xml:id="779"></ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received a letter from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, written from Norwich, where he continues his flying instruction. He had rashly lent &#x00A3;20 to some impecunious &amp; faithless 'chum', from whom he could not recover his money. Hence his account was overdrawn by &#x00A3;15, and he dreaded disastrous consequences. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I sent him the money, of course, adding some good advice, &amp; warning him that I would not in any circumstances do as much for him again. But it was intolerable to me that the youngster should spoil himself thus ignobly at the start</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
