<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[310]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">803</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The problem of filling up Exeter is solved by the appointment of </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord William Gascoyne <persName xml:id="31">Cecil</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, Rector of Hatfield. On the whole it is a good appointment, and I felt myself able to write a letter of cordial congratulations &amp; goodwill to the Bishop&#8211;designate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a Special Chapter at which we appointed Canon <persName xml:id="4031">Roberson</persName> to the living of Norham&#8211;on&#8211;Tweed. I gave notice that at the great Chapter in November, I would bring forward a proposal for reforming our method of administering the patronage. After the meeting I wrote to Canon Roberson, to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Percy <persName xml:id="3900">Corder</persName> (respecting a picture which it is thought he may present to the D. &amp; C.), to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3848">Taylor</persName> (thanking him for his gifts to the Library), and to the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I read through R. J. <persName xml:id="392">Campbell's</persName> Apologia &#8211; <ref xml:id="826">"A Spiritual Pilgrimage"</ref></hi><hi rend="italic">. It is very readable &amp; extraordinarily inconsequent. The acceptance of <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> version of Anglicanism is almost comically complete. Surely there never was a disciple more dog&#8211;like in his worship of the master of his choice. Again &amp; again a controversial intention is repudiated, but, of course, the book is acutely controversial: and the most offensive part of it (so far as Nonconformists are concerned) is the concluding Irenicon. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The real problem that calls for solution is not Campbell's Anglicanism, but his Nonconformity</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is obvious from the first that the man is temperamentally repugnant to Nonconformity. His "spiritual home" is beyond all reasonable doubt the Church of Rome: he has joined or rejoined the Church of England because he has invested it with the Roman character, &amp; is hypnotized by the personal influence of Bishop Gore. The Nonconformists, assuredly have much to forgive.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
