<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[286]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">809</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Our anniversary falls again in the shocks &amp; shadows of a fearful War, and the relatively calm routine of such a life as ours takes an aspect of almost tragical futility, when it has to be seen in a setting of conflict &amp; sorrow. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Give peace in our time, O Lord</hi><hi>' &#8211; that is the inevitable prayer now.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning brought me, "With grateful thanks from his Father and Mother", a little memorial of their son </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward Wyndham <persName xml:id="1389">Tennant</persName></hi><hi>, who at the age of 19 years, has fallen in action. It includes a very winning picture of the lad, and his wonderful letter to his mother, written on the eve of the fatal conflict, and in conscious reckoning with its stern possibility. I have never read a nobler or more moving composition. I wrote to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, and to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. In the afternoon I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Governors</orgName>: &amp; afterwards had some talk with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName></hi><hi>. He advises me to undertake the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> "Life". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> brought in </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Bishop <persName xml:id="3745">Frodsham</persName></hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, who has come to Durham in the character of "Archbishops' Messenger", &amp; will deliver his message in the Cathedral tomorrow afternoon</hi><hi rend="italic">. He is a stout man very </hi><hi rend="italic underline">episcopal</hi><hi rend="italic"> in aspect &amp; manner: rather disposed to think the colonies the homes of wisdom: &amp; to look down upon the non&#8211;colonially experienced. He appeared to be nowise very confident of the policy of the "National Mission", which, he said, had been "as ill&#8211;managed as possible from above", though, he thought, it had stirred much devotion in some quarters. He indicated that, though he was the Archbishops' Messenger, their Graces had nothing to do with shaping his "message". He admitted that there was considerable risk of the trumpet giving an uncertain sound, as the Missioners had arrived at no agreement as to their "Message"!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
