<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[266]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">819</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, prepared notes for my address tonight; went through the various recommendations of clergymen for preferment; &amp; sent in three nominations for Edlington &amp; Bearpark. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I travelled to Carlisle, leaving about 2.19 p.m. and arriving about 4.30 p.m. Canon <persName xml:id="243">Rawnsley's</persName> car met me at the station, &amp; carried me to his prebendal house, where I was kindly entertained. After an early dinner we (Canon &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3990">R.</persName> &amp; myself) went to the Town Hall, where the annual meeting of the <orgName xml:id="198">Bible Society</orgName> was arranged to take place. I made a speech mainly about the change which had passed upon our views &amp; treatment of the Bible, and its permanent value. The audience, which numbered about 100 persons, was attentive, but not, perhaps, altogether pleased. The darkened state of the streets, and the drenching rain were hostile conditions, under which to hold a meeting. I reflected sadly that time &amp; travelling expenses were ill rewarded by so scanty a gathering. I had a good deal of conversation with mine host, a well&#8211;meaning, fussily active little man, with a passion for writing indifferent sonnets, of an immense belief in the value of signed documents of every kind! He was not very enthusiastic over the "National Mission" though he thought the women&#8211;pilgrims had done good. He had been entertaining the Dean of Salisbury (<persName xml:id="1332">Page Roberts</persName>) who had preached to Doctors &amp; nurses on S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Luke's day, and, in spite of his four&#8211;score years, was in great form. Of his own Dean, the egregious <persName xml:id="3227">Barker</persName>, he gave but an ill account, not pleasant to hear. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
