<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[240]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">832</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There were not many communicants, but very varied. A wounded soldier, a boy (<persName xml:id="3571">George</persName>), four students, a score of women, &amp; two or three elderly men, besides the five clergy &#8211; these cover by representation a considerable range of life. I doubt, however, whether the vast artisan class was represented, though the soldier may have belonged to it. At Mattins there was a considerable congregation. The Judge (Sir Fred</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">k</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3739">Low</persName>) attended in state. I preached on "</hi><hi rend="underline">The didactic function of Law</hi><hi>"; taking as my text Gal: III. 24. "</hi><hi rend="underline">So that the law hath been our tutor to bring us unto Christ, that we might be justified by faith"</hi><hi>. We entertained the Judge &amp; <persName xml:id="3622">High Sheriff</persName> at lunch. <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry</persName> (the dowager) brought two friends from <placeName xml:id="53">Wynyard</placeName>: &amp; we made up with other guests a party of seventeen. Then to Evensong came the Mayor &amp; Corporation escorted by a great body of the citizens. I preached on </hi><hi rend="underline">"High Motive &amp; Commonplace Duties",</hi><hi> taking for text two passages, S. Matt.vi.33. </hi><hi rend="underline">"Seek ye first His kingdom, &amp; His righteousness</hi><hi>", and Rom. Xii. 16. </hi><hi rend="underline">"Set not your mind on high things, but condescend to things that are lowly</hi><hi>". The singing of the National Anthem (all three verses unexpurgated) was memorable. In the course of my sermon I took up my parable against the hoardings with their squalid advertisements which spoil the noble prospect of the cathedral from the Railway station. I offered it as an illustration of those "lowly things" to which in the exercise of their municipal functions they might "condescend". There came to tea Capt</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2918">Apperly</persName> [Apperley], his son, &amp; his two ^married^ daughters, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3636">Warre</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3635">Bell</persName>. Also Major &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Low, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2663">Cruickshank</persName> with a friend. The weather has been fine &amp; so far favourable, but the unseasonable warmth made effort irksome.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
