<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146] </hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">869</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A heavy snow&#8211;fall occurred during the night, &amp; compelled <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> and <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName> to postpone their departure. I wrote to <persName xml:id="909">Sir Lewis Dibdin</persName> about the refusal of the Commissioners to sanction the sale of the glebe at Witton Gilbert to Coroner Graham for a recreation ground. Beyond attending Mattins &amp; Evensong, and sawing up logs, I did nothing useful. I did however call on old D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName>, who ages visibly. He is nearly 97, &amp; though deaf, can talk with intelligence &amp; animation when seised of the subject of conversation. The afternoon post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName> with a post&#8211;card photograph of herself &amp; donkey&#8211;cart.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I have realized the War more than I did before since being here &amp; see how it is the much criticized spirit of FATALISM which carries the men along at all. I feel it myself talking to men &amp; officers alike. They all say the same &#8211; it is only a matter of time, &amp; they don't expect to last much longer. Death is entirely an incident. How can it really be otherwise? One feels it oneself, &amp; often I feel I'd far rather go up the line with these boys &amp; be killed than live on without them. For all that they are cheerful &amp; brave beyond words &#8211; </hi><hi rend="underline">all</hi><hi> delighted at the change of Government."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> kept her room today by reason of a severe cold. After dinner I wrote to <persName xml:id="923">Newsom</persName> congratulating him on his appointment as Vicar of Newcastle. I received a letter from <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName>, who is still in hospital at Southport, and a card from Ernest, who has gone to France with a draft. He writes with the evident desire to remain abroad. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Bishop <persName xml:id="1817">Lightfoot</persName> on the 'Quicunque vult</hi><hi>':&#8211; v. York Journal of <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> July 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> 1879. </hi><hi rend="italic">He proposed 'a simple substitution of "may" for "shall" in the rubric.<note xml:id="191" n="1"></note><note xml:id="15" n="1"></note> "Personally I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> prefer to see it (the Creed) removed altogether; but I do not think that theological education has gone so far that it w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be wise to press for the total removal at present." He quoted a memorial presented to the Professors of Divinity at Cambridge &amp; signed by 'something between 150 and 200' persons, 'not only men of very considerable intellectual standing, a large number of Junior Fellows &amp; Scholars of the Colleges, but the very men, one with another, almost without exception, on whom I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have laid my finger as the hope of the Church in the years to come.' The Bp. concluded his speech thus:&#8211; "I cannot shut my eyes, whatever others may do, to these facts: and therefore I feel that my allegiance to my Master Christ, my allegiance to that Nicene doctrine wh. I thoroughly &amp; completely hold, &amp; my allegiance to this Church of England, wh. I venture to think the noblest Church in Christendom, require me to do what I can to remove this stumbling&#8211;block wh. stands in the way of so many." The resolution was supported by the Abp. (<persName xml:id="3385">Thompson</persName>), and the Bp. of Manchester (<persName xml:id="3379">Fraser</persName>).</hi>
</p><div type="quote"><p>"Nor is it always in the most distinguished achievments that men's virtues or vices may be best discerned; but very often an action of small note, a short saying, or a jest, shall distinguish a person's real character more than the greatest sieges or the most important battles." (Plutarch 'Alexander')
</p></div><p>
</p><div type="quote"><p>How true this is! If one could but keep it steadily in mind, there would be an end of 'letting oneself go' when 'off duty'. "<hi rend="underline">In whatsoever I find you therein will I judge you</hi><hi>" runs a significant Logion of Christ uncanonical but surely authentic.</hi></p></div><p>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
