<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[322]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">798</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read <persName xml:id="3049">Bailey's</persName> life of <persName xml:id="2095" display="no">Fuller</persName><ref xml:id="825"></ref>. It is crammed with information more or less relevant. The worst of starting a book of this kind is that one must go through with it: &amp; that process consumes vastly more time than ought to be given to it. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked round Houghall Wood. The sun shining through autumn&#8211;tinted leaves, and touching with glory the landscape, made a glorious view. Old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3848">Taylor</persName> arrived with his gifts to the chapter library, and told stories of the time when he was a Durham student. He remembered still a sermon preached by Dean <persName xml:id="3300">Waddington</persName> on the text, "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?" It is something to have a sermon remembered after the lapse of nearly half a century.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The afternoon post brought a letter from <persName xml:id="3797">Dunbar&#8211;Buller</persName>. It contained a rather formidable proposal:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"The <persName xml:id="302">Miss Ansons</persName> are most anxious to have as you know a short sketch of <persName xml:id="228">Willie Anson's</persName> Life written about 200 pages or so.' Perhaps in size double or treble the fatness of the Book of Ballads' &#8211; and they are most anxious to get you to undertake it. They don't however like to write direct as they very rightly think you would be able to have greater freedom in writing to me &#8211; in fact have no scruple in telling me to go and be dammed &#8211; ….<persName xml:id="66">Frank Pember</persName>, when I suggested you, said it was an inspiration, that you would do better than any of those I have mentioned, and so thought the Ansons when he mentioned the subject to them &#8211; ….We do hope that in spite of all your work you will see your way to do what the Ansons so want".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This is a very difficult proposal either to accept or reject.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
