<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[256]	</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">824</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This has been a beautiful day, clear fresh, and sunny. If only it could be followed up by some fine weather, there might yet be some movement on the Western frontier. I received from my Life Assurance Office the announcement of the quinquennial bonus. On the one policy the amount is &#x00A3;198.16.0: on the other, &#x00A3;586.18.0. This sum of &#x00A3;785.14.0 is capable of being reduced to a present value in cash. I shall probably think it advisable to take the money! I presided at a meeting of Chapter. It was agreed that <persName xml:id="1916">Arthur Morgan's</persName> grant be renewed on condition that his father contributed &#x00A3;30 to his education, not otherwise. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong and revised an old sermon for use tomorrow. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Also I wrote a long letter to the 'Church Times' offering some observations on the leading article.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary <persName xml:id="1204">Radford</persName></hi><hi> sends me a Birthday letter, mainly filled with maternal laudations of her <persName xml:id="3886">son</persName>, my godson. She speaks of returning to England next May. That costly &amp; elaborate book published in connection with the Shakespearian Tercentenary Celebration arrived. It is full of interesting matter, but more expensive than in these ill times I care to remember. The illustrations are numerous and varied. Several are borrowed from Bishop <persName xml:id="3743">Carleton's</persName> <ref xml:id="829">'Thankful Remembrance'</ref>, which I possess, &amp; have read. </hi><hi rend="italic">It is in my opinion an illuminating exhibition of the sentiment &#8211; Biblical, fanatical, &amp; patriotic &#8211; which reigned in the ordinary Englishman's mind at the beginning of the 17</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century. Shakespeare's historical plays disclose the same spirit in a lay setting. The amazing success of Elizabeth had given a swaggering self&#8211;confidence to her subjects which they excused or explained by the theory that they were truly a 'chosen people'.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
