<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">880</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> went off by the early train. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> and Norman <persName xml:id="3542">Henderson</persName> before breakfast. Then I attended Mattins. </hi><hi rend="italic">The devil entering into me, I wrote a letter to the "Times" headed "Festina lente" [make haste slowly], commenting on the proposal to use the income of the Dean of Exeter to provide the income for a Bishop of Plymouth.</hi><hi> Probably the Editor will not print it. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="3724">Arthur</persName>. I attended Evensong: and wrote to <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> failed to arrive as he had arranged, for the motor car which he had hired in Newcastle broke down in the market–place of Durham, when on the way out to Bishop Auckland. Bishop <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName> volunteered to send his car to fetch the Diocesan tomorrow morning. <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> dined with us. I had some talk with him on church matters.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I have preached 18 sermons in the Cathedral during the year, 14 in the parish churches of the Diocese (besides some on week–days), and 15 away from the Diocese, making a total of 47</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The only places of exceptional interest preached in were:–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>S. Cuthbert's, Edinburgh</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Windsor Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Glasgow Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Manchester Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, Westminster</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Westminster Abbey.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I have not included the preaching to the troops at the Church Parades during the first 3 months of the year: nor yet the S. George's Day Sermon in the Nave of S. George's, Windsor, on the Wednesday after Easter, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"A great man of antiquity (i.e. Cato) is reported to have said, that as he never was indulgent to any one fault in himself, he c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not excuse those of others. This sentence c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> scarce with decency come out of the mouth of any human creature. But if we invert the former part, &amp; put it thus: that he was indulgent to many faults in himself, as it is to be feared the best of us are, &amp; yet was implacable: how monstrous w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> such an assertion appear! And this is the case in respect to every human creature, in proportion as he is without the forgiving spirit."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1856">Bishop Butler</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
