<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[272]</hi>
          </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">816</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="2364">Robinson</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> of the <orgName xml:id="23">S.P.G</orgName> wrote to ask me whether I would be willing to undertake to edit a popular edition of F. D. <persName xml:id="687">Maurice's</persName> Letters, and to write an Introduction. This morning I replied that I would not be unwilling, if I could find the time.</hi><hi> After attending Mattins, I settled down to an attempt to preface a sermon for Asize Sunday. After attending Evensong I went to see <persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName>, who is down with something like influenza. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip le <persName xml:id="3919">Mesurier</persName></hi><hi> came to see me. He said that his application to the army had come to nothing, apparently on account of his Jersey residence. We has some conversation together, from which I gathered that the atmosphere of S. Chad's is rather more "Catholick" than he relishes. The "Guardian" contains a very vivaciously written criticism of <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> little book on Anglican doctrine by <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName>, who "lets himself go" with considerable effect, and perhaps with some imprudence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The picture "</hi><hi rend="underline">A Legend of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi rend="underline">Cuthbert</hi><hi>" by W. Robert Spence, which he has presented to the Dean and Chapter, arrived from Newcastle, during Evensong, and was placed in the entrance to the Library. In Walter Bagehot's </hi><hi rend="underline">Essay on Lord Brougham</hi><hi> there is a striking account of the situation in England, at the close of the Napoleonic War. It is certainly disquieting enough when considered as a probable precedent for the state of things which will follow the present war. </hi><hi rend="italic">Save for a brief unfriendly notice in the "Guardian", the church papers ignore my "Edinburgh Review" <ref xml:id="779">article</ref> altogether. The "Westminster Gazette" mentions that the <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> and I are opposed to the scheme of the <ref xml:id="817">Archbishops' Committee's Report</ref>, and that Lord <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> will probably answer our objections.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
