<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">870</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning post brought me the following letter from <persName xml:id="389">Lord Bryce</persName>, dated from the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, December 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1916:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Dean,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your <ref xml:id="779">article</ref> in the Edinburgh on the present position of the Church of England &amp; those who would 'reform' it (not in the XVI</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century sense) is too good for any review. I wish you would expand it into a book, following out more fully some of the lines of historical reflection you have only indicated: and pointing out the course which offers the best prospect of giving the laity some real power. As a sympathetic observer from without, I have been tending to despair at least until the force of the Romanizing movement, now so strong among the Clergy, has spent itself, which may not be in our time. Yet some attempt ought to be made. Your remark that the English are essential Erastians (they were even in the Middle Ages) &amp; the Scotch Ultramontane is true, tho' the Scotch clerics would be startled at your adjective. Another very just reflection is your comparison of the Socialist movement in politics and Economics with the "corporate ecclesiastical" movement in Christianity. The danger in both to true Liberty is the same. We relished very much your letter the other day about Episcopal claims, though Lambeth at least does not, at least in the person of the present successor of Augustine, desire any more personal power. To me, remembering fifty years ago &#8211; indeed more &#8211; it seems some bishops count for less than in those days, certainly among the laity, &amp; I should think among the clergy also. Their defeat by the Ritualists completed</hi> <hi rend="bold">[140] </hi><hi>the process begun by the large addition to the number of sees. Are there not fewer strong personalities? I have other reflections and questions I meant to put, but must stop for today.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Always truly yours, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bryce.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon I received a letter from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Greene, the Senior Chaplain of the Tyne Garrison, saying that I had been 'appointed as officiating clergyman to troops under Col. <persName xml:id="3608">Maclean</persName> quartered in Durham'.</hi>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
