<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[164]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916. Liverpool.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">862</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName> accompanied me to the station, when I left at 11.28 a.m. for Liverpool. I arrived (nearly an hour after scheduled time) at 6.10 p.m: and was met at the station by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Lawrence <persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName>, who was to be mine host. He had collected an interesting party to dine, mostly men interested in education. There was M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Philip <persName xml:id="3659">Rathbone</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jones (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Holt's partner), M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3656">Hobhouse</persName> (brother of the imprisoned Pacificist, <persName xml:id="3657">Stephen</persName>), M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3661">Weisser</persName> [Weisse], the Head&#8211;master of the Liverpool Institute, and two others, whose names have gone from me. We talked with much ardour, but mainly on more interesting subjects than that of education; I was particularly interested to notice that there was a marked absence of approval or of confidence, so far as the new government was concerned. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is taken for granted, as a fact needing no proof that <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd&#8211;George</persName> has lent himself treacherously to the Northcfliffe&#8211;plot against <persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName>.</hi><hi> These men were all Liberals, and I suspect that their indignation against Lloyd&#8211;George's 'treachery' is not unconnected with their resentment at the openly&#8211;expressed approval of it by the Conservatives, who dominate the little world of local politics. Yet I cannot doubt that they do no substantial injustice to the new Prime Minister. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hobhouse is employed in M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Holt's shipping office, and has felt it imperative in view of his brother's behaviour to join the Army in spite of the exemption which he enjoys. The shipping difficulties are evidently regarded by these Liverpool ship&#8211;owners as very formidable, and as probably destined to grow worse. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Rathbone spoke very gloomily of the military situation, &amp; held that we ought not to be too eager to refuse discussion of peace. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
