<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Andrew's Day, Thursday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">850</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. All my brethren were present except <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> and <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>. After attending Mattins, I resumed the rather futile task of preparing materials for the Lecture. <persName xml:id="3730">Selden's</persName> dedication of the treatise on "Titles of Honour" is expressed in a dedicatory epistle in which he dilates on the significance of such dedication of books. This volume is dedicated to his 'friend and chamber&#8211;fellow', Edward Heyward.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended a meeting in the Mayor's Chamber about a "Naval Flag Day".</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">The afternoon post brought me a letter marked 'Private' from the <persName xml:id="602">Bishop of Southwark</persName></hi><hi>. He begins by thanking me for my 'interesting &amp; valuable' article in the <ref xml:id="779">"Edinburgh Review"</ref>, &amp; then goes on to disclose his discontent with his present situation. "I don't think anyone pays the slightest attention to what I say." He adds some interesting information:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"There is now going forward an attempt to unite the Bishops in a clear stand on the subject of reservation &#8211; '</hi><hi rend="underline">that reservation is only used for the sick &amp; for no other purpose whatsoever</hi><hi>' &#8211; <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> is particularly keen about this, &amp; especially in order to safeguard doctrine. Suppose we do all unite in our declaration (which I think is very probable) does anyone imagine that it is going to have the smallest influence with the Committee of the E.C.U. &amp; the orders they issue."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Then he seems to suggest that the Edinburgh Article should be followed up by a Supplement 'which sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> put out something constructive or suggest a line of recovery from the welter of dishonesty, individualism, &amp; jargon.' He writes in a tone of deep despondency, and is plainly much disturbed. Unfortunately I have no comfort to offer. There is nothing for us now but to go on to the rocks of disruption.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
