<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[242]</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
            </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">831</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> before breakfast, and attended Mattins. Both <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I attended the Meeting at the Shire Hall on Maternity &amp; Child care, and I made a short speech. There was a considerable company present: a good many of the women were, I suspect, suffragists. The medical officer of Newcastle, ^D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Kerr^ read a paper, and the Medical Officer of Durham County, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Eustace Hill</hi><hi> made an useful speech. </hi><hi rend="italic">After lunch the High Sheriff, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><persName xml:id="3622"><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Houston</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, called. He is a dapper little pleasant man, who once attended my History Lecture at All Souls. He was, however, then called Hopkins. He said that I hadn't changed my appearance at all. A host of the Social Science people came round the Cathedral: &amp; then came to tea.</hi><hi> Between 40 and 50 had announced their intention of coming to tea, but it was nearly twice as many who actually came. After they had taken their departure, I walked into the city &amp; brought some cigarettes for tomorrow. Taking a large party (that which followed me this afternoon contained more than 100 persons) over a cathedral is really tiring. To improvise or rehearse for an hour on end is itself fatiguing: but when there must be added the petty bothers of the marshal to the serious anxieties of the teacher, the fatigue is greatly increased. It certainly was the case that, after we had at last succeeded in getting rid of the party (a process wonderfully delayed by old <persName xml:id="3868">Galbraith</persName> who insisted on pouring out upon me </hi><hi rend="underline">all</hi><hi> his choicest quotations, besides a detailed account of his own manner of life, and elaborate Biblical studies!) I felt quite extraordinarily tired, and after a vain attempt at reading, betook myself to the sanctuary of my bed at 10.30 p.m.!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
