<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[234]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">837</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3453">Heylyn's</persName></hi><hi> Introduction to </hi><hi rend="underline">Cyprianus Anglicus</hi><hi> is a terse &amp; effective summary of the Laudian version of Anglicanism, &amp; could hardly be improved upon by the modern High Churchman. He is extremely anxious to make clear that the Reformers owed nothing to the foreign Reformers.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"And yet it cannot be denied, but that the first Reformers of it (i.e. the Church of England) did look with more respectful eyes upon the Doctrinals, Government, &amp; Forms of Worship in the Lutheran Churches, than upon those of Calvin's platform".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Heylyn appears to understand nothing beyond the Cope to be indicated by the Ornament Rubrick. He has a vivacious denunciation of the Lecturers.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"No creature so like them as the Bats or Reremice, being neither Birds nor Beasts, and yet both together."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>He applies "the vulgar proverb, neither flesh, nor fish, nor good red herrings". There is the same perverse ingenuity in collating odd &amp; end survivals, &amp; weaving them into a single argument for demonstrating the precise contrary of that which the Anglican standards affirm, as that which marks the modern Ritualist. But Heylyn could plead the excuse of his sufferings &amp; losses during the interregnum. He knew the Papists mostly as fellow&#8211;sufferers for the King's cause, &amp; their most vehement enemies were precisely the men who had turned him out of house &amp; home.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232] 	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3099">Stuart</persName> condoling with him on the death of his only son. The youth was killed in action on the Somme. It is very melancholy. I attended Mattins. <persName xml:id="3444">Macartney</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> came to lunch. I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked with Logic.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3738">Elliot</persName> in answer to his letter on the "Edinburgh Review" article<ref xml:id="779"></ref>. The "Guardian" contains several letters anent <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> Book, including one from Gore himself, and a characteristically rude effusion from <persName xml:id="3994">Headlam</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
