<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">840</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The paper reports the re&#8211;capture of Monastir by the Serbo&#8211;French Army. This is good, but cannot have much effect, if any, on the really critical situation in Roumania. Old Canon <persName xml:id="3845">Fleming</persName> took his departure about the time that I went into the Chapter House to preside over the Great Chapter. Everything went well enough until we came to my Patronage Resolutions, when </hi><persName xml:id="590"><hi rend="underline">iste Archidiaconus</hi></persName><hi> developed an opposition which met with more success than I had supposed to be probable. The actual form in which the resolution was passed ran thus:&#8211;</hi>
</p><div type="quote"><p>
<hi>That for the purposes of administering the Cathedral patronage the Dean &amp; Canons will constitute a Patronage Committee for selecting candidates to be considered in Chapter.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That Patronage Committee shall present the names of selected candidates in alphabetical order, &amp; shall keep a register of selected clergymen.</hi>
</p></div><p>
<hi>This is a poor substitute for my project, and will, I fear, fail to effect any improvement on our present system. It only substitutes discussion in a committee, for discussion by the same persons in Chapter. The last has the superiority of being carried on under the statutory obligation of secrecy. But that doesn't come to much while <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> is a member of the Chapter. We must make the best of it. I walked in the cloisters with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>; attended evensong; walked on the Banks to view the rain&#8211;swollen river, and the waterfalls now full and foaming. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip le <persName xml:id="3919">Mesurier</persName></hi><hi> came to tea, and undertook to walk with me on Wednesday. I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="3099">Stuart</persName></hi><hi> a letter about his son, who was recently killed in France. He seems to have carried himself admirably.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
