<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[284]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">810</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A copy of the "Edinburgh Review" containing my article on <ref xml:id="779">"Church and State in England"</ref> arrived. The article is given the first place, &amp; will, I hope, catch the eye of some people, who now move in a mist of ignorance along the oiled ways of faction. It contains the paragraph about Scotland, which is, I think, an improvement.</hi><hi> Then I attended Mattins, and afterwards presided at a Meeting of the Chapter. Three matters, not of the pleasantest were left to me to be dealt with (1) The discovery of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Morgan's ability to contribute to his <persName xml:id="1916">son's</persName> education. (2) The condemnation &amp; eviction of the goat which <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> has brought into the College. (3) The discussion of the school report with <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName>. As the Chapter broke up, <persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarborough</persName> appeared with <persName xml:id="4041">Stephen Graham</persName>. I gave the keys of the Strong room to the <persName xml:id="590">Sub&#8211;dean</persName> in order that he might shew them the Cuthbert's relics. After lunch I went off to Manchester; journeying comfortably enough save for an inrush of soldiers &amp; others at one station. They all got out at the first opportunity, &amp; I had no further discomfort. A gentleman (who said that his name was Greenhouse) addressed me, saying that he had heard me preach at the Hampstead Garden suburb. His wife said that she had been through Serbia, &amp; was now engaged in lecturing on the Serbians. On arriving at Manchester I drove in a taxi to 65 Ardwick Green, where <persName xml:id="3746">Canon Scott</persName> received me. The <persName xml:id="532">Bishop of Ely</persName> had already arrived. He is to be the preacher tomorrow. We had some pleasant conversation at dinner &amp; afterwards. <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> was one of the party. The ladies had been to see the Somme Films, &amp; were loud in their approbation of them, but I gathered that the Bishop &amp; mine host were rather disposed to share my objection. Welldon, as might be expected, took the popular view.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
