<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">817</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. and afterwards spent my morning in preparing the Assize Sermon, of which, however, so far I have no clear or coherent plan. I attended Evensong, &amp; then walked with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruikshank</persName>, who is now bent on starting a branch of the <orgName xml:id="38">"Churchmen's Union"</orgName> in Durham, unwisely as I must needs think. <persName xml:id="2918">Captain Apperley's</persName> <persName xml:id="3637">two sons</persName><persName xml:id="3638"></persName> &#8211; both officers who have done duty at the Front &amp; been invalided home &#8211; came to lunch. I gathered from their account of their experiences that the men are mortally tired of the war. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> brought me a photograph of the Chorister's Eleven, &amp; a note from <persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName> thanking me for the fruit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> professes himself an optimist because he is a Christian, &amp; builds on his optimism a belief in "democracy", &amp; all its most recent developments (e.g. feminism.) Indeed, he is at the call of every new fad, which grows from the teeming soil of popular politics. I do not dispute his primary assumption. As a Christian I must needs believe that God means well by his Universe; that he has a purpose in Creation not unworthy of Himself; &amp; that that purpose is, however slowly &amp; with many set&#8211;backs through human obstinacy &amp; folly, marching to its fulfilment. I believe the Universe has a pre&#8211;determined </hi><hi rend="underline">finale</hi><hi>, &amp; that its purpose is not to be conceived of as something here attainable, which </hi><hi rend="underline">ex hypothesi</hi><hi> would be reached &amp; then perish: but rather is being attained continually as "Time" is traversed. We do not know </hi><hi rend="underline">what </hi><hi>that purpose is. There may be truth in the old Calvinism with its emphasis on 'election'. God </hi><hi rend="underline">may</hi><hi> be making up 'the members of his elect': and, when that is complete, suffering the disruptive forces of evil to work their natural effects in the destruction of the purposeless universe. Who knows?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
