<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">873</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather has been very comfortless &amp; depressing &#8211; no sun, but mist, fine falling snow, &amp; thaws. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="2463" display="no">Nimbus</persName>, <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came in, &amp; assisted me in tying up letters. He stayed to lunch. <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> and I talked much together: and, after dinner, I read from <persName xml:id="2095" display="no">Fuller's</persName> Church History<ref xml:id="841"></ref>, the very amusing account of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Antonius de Dominis</hi><hi rend="italic">, Archbishop of Spalato. We had much talk on palmistry &amp; such like arts for reading the future. Automatic writing appears to be the popular method, and according to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="542">Gow</persName>, this is being extensively practised with the worst possible consequences. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, like a true Italian ultimately a pagan, professed a larger measure of belief in these foolish tricks than I should have thought possible in any person of her intellectual quality: but, of course, when you are dealing with this subject, all estimates &amp; expectations are worthless. Certainly the climate of a prolonged war, especially on a great scale &amp; with its course marked by large disasters is enormously favourable to all these squalid superstitions, which lie buried in the unsuspected substructures of our conscious life, always waiting their resurrection when some great shock paralyses the self&#8211;controlling factors of human nature. To morality in the conventional sense War is frankly disastrous. Gow tells me that Sir E. Henry avers that since the outbreak of War there has been a notable increase of sodomy in London. From other sources it is reported that venereal disease is being greatly extended throughout the community. The mere breaking up of social "use &amp; wont" implies the destruction of the conditions of personal morality for multitudes, in some measure for all.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
