<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[330]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">794</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion in <placeName xml:id="77">S. Gregory's Chapel</placeName>, making my particular petition that I should not be suffered to take any false step in the ordering of what remains to me of my life. Then I revised last night's discourse in view of its use again tonight. The post brought me a long letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> and I attended the Prize&#8211;distribution of the High School. I gave away the prizes which consisted of partly&#8211;filled war&#8211;savings vouchers. Also I made a speech, and sate out a rather dreary concert. Later in the afternoon I motored to Whitworth (Spennymoor), and preached in a tiny church, competent to contain at the most about 100 people. It was full, but not crowded, though it serves a population of about 2000 souls. The parson, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3577">Wilkinson</persName>, is a young&#8211;looking man, of a tiresomely slow manner of speaking, and, I suspect, afflicted with deafness. After the service, a one&#8211;legged soldier was brought to me as doubting by what means he could return home. So I took him there in the car, and with him a shaggy&#8211;looking local parson, whose way lay in the same direction. I was back in the Deanery about 9.30 o'clock.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> called to see <persName xml:id="3842">Craster</persName>, and to discuss with him the business of the <orgName xml:id="244">Surtees Society</orgName>. There is a considerable body of antiquaries here, who find their Nestor in <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName>, and their organ in the Surtees Society. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> and perhaps <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> are neophytes. <persName xml:id="3666">Canon Fowler</persName> is one of the leaders; and <persName xml:id="4079">Gradon</persName>, the present Mayor, is a working member. I should incline to think that Durham Cathedral is more closely studied &amp; watched than any other. Its capitular archives have been more frequently searched and sacked. Possibly the presence of the University may go some way to explain this.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
