<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[326]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">796</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I wrote a letter to Reggie, and to <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>.</hi> <hi>Also I sent letters of introduction to the <persName xml:id="931">Bishops of Massachusetts</persName>, <persName xml:id="3068">New York</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3043">Connecticutt</persName> [sic] for the use of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Grant Allen, who is going to America to raise funds for the Professional Classes Relief Council. I attended Mattins and Evensong, after which I walked round to the hospital, and saw <persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName>, who is now approaching a state of convalescence. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, &amp; others. A telegram from Bishop <persName xml:id="3694">Mercer</persName> announced that he had lost his train connection, &amp; would not arrive until the last train. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> dined with us.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Burke's warning against hasty generalizations as to the opinions of a nation is never superfluous:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Because half a dozen grasshoppers under a fern make the field ring with their important chink, whilst thousands of great cattle reposed beneath the shadow of the British oak chew the cud and are silent, pray do not imagine that those who make the noise are the only inhabitants of the field, &#8211; that, of course, they are many in number, &#8211; or that, after all, they are other than little, shrivelled, meagre, hopping, though loud and troublesome insects of the hour".<note xml:id="324" n="1"></note> </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Shortly before midnight Bishop Mercer arrived from Chester, having had a crowded, comfortless, &amp; tedious journey. He tells me that he is now acting as </hi><hi rend="underline">alter ego</hi><hi> for the Bishop of Chester, who he thinks has had a slight stroke of paralysis, and is in great apprehension of another. These are no days for invalidish rulers whether in Church or State: but certainly in the former we have a good many of them. They wind up by taking pensions, &amp; living indefinitely! </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
