<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">874</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A calm beautiful morning with enough snow on the ground to certify mid&#8211;winter. At breakfast we had an exasperating conversation, in which I maintained the tolerant thesis that the moral anachronism exhibited by Germany was capable of such an explanation from her history as allowed us to think charitably of her people. But M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="542">Gow</persName> and <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> will allow nothing in such an argument: Germans are just obscene vermin, and that closes discussion!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, and afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion. <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName> came in to lunch. I attended Evensong, when Gow preached from S. Paul's words: "Redeeming the time." He rejected the marginal rendering of R.V. ("buying up the opportunity"), and suggested that the sense of the original would be best conveyed by "redeeming the times." His blindness made the reading of his MS more difficult than it ought to have been. <persName xml:id="3553">Meade&#8211;Falkner</persName> and <persName xml:id="3554">his wife</persName> came in to tea: also the two boys &#8211; <persName xml:id="3571">George Nimmins</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName>. To them I gave copies of Scott's Novels: "The Abbot" to the first, &amp; "Old Mortality" to the last. </hi><hi rend="underline">The <orgName xml:id="107">Royal Society of Literature</orgName> having sent me some <ref xml:id="879">copies</ref> of my Lecture on <persName xml:id="3959">Warburton</persName>,</hi><hi> I sent off several by way of "Christmas Cards." After dinner I read to my family <persName xml:id="2916">Ronald Knox's</persName> witty but ribald satire on <ref xml:id="839">"Reunion all round"</ref>. It is really a venomous satire on the Church of England conceived in the interest of the Church of Rome. But it is extremely amusing, &amp; in a society, cursed with the humourless obsessions of a thousand cranks, everything is pardoned to the man who can &amp; will add something to the slendour stock of human amusement. As our Anglican "Fool" young Knox is well enough. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
