<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[120] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">879</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Beyond writing letters I have really done nothing. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> went with me to call on the officers of the troops now coming into the City, and afterwards walked with me for an hour and a half. The weather has become quite mild, &amp; the consequent melting of the snow in the moor is reflected in a turgid and rapidly flowing river.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1289">Reginald Smith</persName>, the publisher, is reported to have died unexpectedly</hi><hi>. I made his acquaintance in connexion with the little book on <ref xml:id="85">Robertson of Brighton</ref>, and liked him</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner, I read aloud for <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta's</persName> benefit, Burke's 'Reflections on the French Revolution'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Norman <persName xml:id="3542">Henderson</persName>, the young Shetlander whose acquaintance I made in the train (v. 258), sent me his photograph. He is advancing in his mastery of the Flying Art, and writes very intelligently about it. He uses one old&#8211;fashioned expression not often met with nowadays: "I </hi><hi rend="underline">presently</hi><hi> hold a 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Class Certificate".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The statement appears in the papers that an agitation is already on foot to abolish the independent Deanery of Exeter at the demise, (which cannot be long delayed,) of the Dean, &amp; making the Bishop ex officio Dean: transferring the income of the Deanery (&#x00A3;2000 per annum) to the projected new see of Plymouth. This is, of course, what our 'high&#8211;flying' reformers would desire to do with all the deaneries. The existence of dignitaries, who are independent of the diocesan system, is hateful to them. They think of nothing else than the multiplication of bishopricks &amp; parishes. Considerations of history are unintelligible to them. The old argument in favour of 'prizes' in the Church is no longer thought to merit regard. They are the Fanaticks of confiscation. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
