<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">853</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. The weather rapidly improved, and by the time Mattins was sung (i.e. 10 a.m.) the day was beautifully fine. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> preached briefly as is his wont, so that there was time enough for me to read over my address before going to the race&#8211;ground for the Inspection of National Volunteers. There were more than 3000 men on parade, and they had weapons enough to make a gleam of bayonets in the sun&#8211;light. An immense crowd gathered to witness the function. I robed in the ground&#8211;man's house, &amp; was there picked up by an officer, &amp; led to the platform which had been erected in the midst of a hollow square. There I said the Lord's Prayer &amp; two collects &#8211; that for Advent Sunday, and a War&#8211;prayer. I gave a short address on the words of Christ: "Be ye also ready, for in an hour that ye think not, the Son of Man cometh." After the Benediction, the National Anthem was played by the band. Lord French was rather late in arriving. On his </hi><hi rend="bold underline">arrival he immediately made a brief inspection of the Volunteers, &amp; then addressed them</hi><hi> from the platform. Then about a dozen 'notables' were presented to him, the men gave 'Three Cheers', &amp; he went away to York. On the whole the function was as successful as we could have wished. Col. <persName xml:id="1659">Burdon</persName>, Col. <persName xml:id="3833">Blackett</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3834">his wife</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3466">Lady Scarbrough</persName> came to lunch. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At Evensong <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> preached a very poor sermon, mentally on the level of the Sunday&#8211;School. Various people came in to see him at tea&#8211;time, for he has many friends. I completed and despatched the rather lengthy letter to the "Guardian", which in substance I had written yesterday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My post&#8211;bag contained two long letters, one from my godson, the other from Arthur <persName xml:id="336">Galton</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
