<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[328]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">795</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>High winds and high temperature with much rain. <persName xml:id="3842">Craster</persName> went off to Oxford after breakfast. I wrote cheques for the quarter's household accounts. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> called to see me, &amp; obtained my promise to preach to the Mayor and Corporation on Sunday afternoon, November 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. <persName xml:id="3747">Rushworth</persName> also called, &amp; ensnared me into buying the Cruci&#8211;fix, which he shewed me awhile since. I attended Evensong. <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> re&#8211;appeared after his holiday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner I read to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> the "Times", and also </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the proof of the 'Edinburgh' article</hi><hi><ref xml:id="779"></ref>, which will appear in a few days. It reads rather fiercely, but is, I think, sound in its substance. The real gravamen against my whole ecclesiastical position is that it is destitute of promise. I can see quite clearly that the direction in which Anglican policy is moving can lead to nothing but disestablishment, disendowment, and disruption. I can see that, so far as it is really successful, it sacerdotalizes Anglicanism, and facilitates the triumph of the older &amp; completer sacerdotalism of Rome. I can see that this kind of success implies an ever waxing alienation of the general mind. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But I have no alternative policy</hi><hi>. The mischief has gone too far for remedy. It is 'too late to save a falling Church'. If religious revival is to take place I suspect that it will come from outside the Church, not from inside. </hi><hi rend="italic">This much&#8211;trumpeted 'National Mission' appears to become more utterly conventional every day. Those who are running about the country exhorting little companies of puzzled women have no vision of any larger teaching than that which has passed on their lips for years past, and been admittedly powerless. A Dervish&#8211;like fervour cannot be maintained, and is not really illuminating or morally helpful.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
