<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[290]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">808</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received the following in reply to my letter about the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> "Life".</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Henson,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It will be a good deed, if you can carry this out. It will be very difficult. There is hardly anyone left who can tell about the early days &#8211; Eton &amp; so on &#8211; thought there is a fragment of autobiography which may do instead. Who now remembers the days of the Oxford Commission, &amp; the All Souls politics of that time? There was little more than a rumour of them left, when I came in &amp; found a Robarts not the same as his reputation in College meetings. What is to be said about <persName xml:id="228">Anson's</persName> law&#8211;work, as a teacher &amp; writer? And who knows his various ways of doing good works as Warden, &amp; who can speak properly about them? His political work, though hard to treat rightly, is not lost beyond recovery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>His own introduction to <persName xml:id="39">Doyle's</persName> Essays is one of the finest pieces of biographical writing I know anywhere. But <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName>, I know, wants something larger.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> undertook it, &amp; made a beginning &#8211; he had the right sort of skill, but he found he was not strong enough some time before his last illness. (This sound funereal, but you know what I mean. I saw him on Sunday, &amp; he is hopeful.)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I hope you will accept, in spite of all the difficulties. You understand how to write history, &amp; with the XVIIth century scale you could do everything possible, in the best way.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[288] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I will help, all I can. I know that I </hi><hi rend="underline">never</hi><hi> could have written the Life, &amp; now I have very little time to spare. But I promised Miss Anson to do what I could &#8211; and it is little enough.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have spent a good deal of the summer reading Swedish newspapers, &amp; I have not been further North than Lichfield (where in Stowe Ho: you are remembered). It is very remarkable, but I do not remember a summer with happier days in it, &amp; none more sorrowful. With all good wishes, I am always yours truly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>W. P. <persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I went to <persName xml:id="3747">Rushworth</persName>, and bought a present for <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to mark the 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of our wedding, which falls tomorrow. Also, I attended Evensong, and afterwards went to the Masonic Hall, and did my duty at the meeting of the Lodge. I was admitted to be Junior Warden for the year. On my return </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I found a letter from <persName xml:id="2868">Cyril Still</persName>, saying that news had been received that <persName xml:id="1259">Reggie</persName> was "missing", probably killed.</hi> <hi rend="italic">My last letter from him was dated but two days before the offensive in which he was lost. He wrote: "It is perfectly amazing how any human being can live under these circumstances. You at home cannot conceive how awful they are. I pray to God that I come out of the business alive, &amp; if we go into battle, I shall go full of confidence in Him &amp; myself. Good Bye! for now." The words disclose no unworthy mood in which a young soldier girds himself to meet his fate. I had come to care for the lad almost as if he had been my own son.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
