<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> , 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">866</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, and presided at a meeting of the chapter. No business of importance was transacted. The <persName xml:id="552">Headlams</persName><persName xml:id="553"></persName> arrived shortly after 11 a.m. I took him for a walk. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir <persName xml:id="3138">Frank Brown</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> lunched, &amp; was somewhat startled at the opinions, crude and crudely expressed, of my learned guest, after whom (as I learned afterwards) he had regard as the author of letter in the 'Times' on educational questions, but who now impressed him most by his evident ignorance of the social questions on which he dogmatised so freely! </hi><hi>Sir Frank &amp; I went to the meeting of the "War Savings C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>", and on the way he told me that he would himself be Chairman only on condition that he had a Vice&#8211;Chairman who w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> do the work, and that he did not think I could be asked to accept that position.<note xml:id="321" n="1"></note> Of course I assented. In due course, the meeting (which had quite evidently been primed in advance) elected <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> to be Vice&#8211;President. This is well&#8211;enough, but I felt somewhat chilled at the attitude of the Committee, which gave me a novel impression of personal unfriendliness. My discontent was not relieved by discovering that the Chapel was wholly unprepared for the Bishop's use. Then, the sudden &amp; vehement heating caused most alarming sounds in the pipes, so that I caused the fire to be raked out again! This did not, however, disturb those in the Chapel. There came to dinner <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> and <persName xml:id="3263">his wife</persName>: &amp; afterwards <persName xml:id="2800">Culley</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3448">his wife</persName>, <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3805">Fearne</persName>, and <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>. After the other guests had gone away or gone to bed, Headlam &amp; I sate for an hour, and talked together on ecclesiastical affairs. He is less truculent at close quarters!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
