<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[314]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">801</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. Intercessions for the Boys become more real when their letters from the Front are fresh in one's mind. It is all that one can do for them now. The <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> seems to have risen to his full height in his speech to the Commons last night: and the circumstance of his recent bereavement added a pathetic dignity to his language, which was elevated &amp; moving. The House evidently was impressed in no ordinary degree.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Major <persName xml:id="2808">Rowlandson</persName></hi><hi> came to lunch. He has now got a temporary appointment in these parts. Last week the War Office sent a demand for 60 officers, and there were but 4 available. If this be at all representative, the military situation will become speedily serious. I attended Evensong, and afterwards walked with Logic. On my return I wrote two condolence&#8211;letters, one to <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> on the death of his mother, and one to <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> on the death of her nephew.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling</persName></hi><hi> arrived. He says he will follow my advice in the matter of Angel <persName xml:id="1812">Colenso</persName> (v. p. 334).</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have told the minor canons that, provided always their duties in the cathedral are duly provided for, I have no objection to their giving assistance in connection with the "National Mission". My own disapproval of the Mission is well&#8211;known, but I have no desire to make my own decision a law for others in such a matter. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> says that <persName xml:id="3674">Bardsley</persName>, the Secretary of the N.M. addressed her students, and was a hopeless failure. The truth is that such high expectations as to the Mission are raised that disappointment is inevitable. For nothing short of a miracle could avert it; and miracles do not happen.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
