<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]		</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">876</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The paper announces the death of the <persName xml:id="2429">Dean of York</persName>. It will be very interesting to note how <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd–George</persName> exercises his patronage, for it will indicate how far he will defer to the <persName xml:id="130">s</persName>, who will naturally desire to secure the appointment agreeable to himself. <persName xml:id="3584">Lyttleton</persName> lately of Eton, <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName>, <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>, <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>, &amp; the ever hopeful <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> will be dreaming dreams! <persName xml:id="243">Rawnsley</persName> will also cherish hopes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After attending Mattins, I walked with <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> for an hour, taking him to see the new House at the School. The roads were so dangerous with the ice that I was thankful to get home with whole limbs. Meanwhile <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> had a prayer–meeting in the drawing room at which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="542">Gow</persName> "preached".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong and afterwards read in my study. After dinner I read to my family &amp; so to bed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Gow presented me with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Buchan's</hi><hi> volume of Essays – "</hi><hi rend="underline">Some Eighteenth Century Byways</hi><hi>". It is amazingly interesting, &amp; deals with topics in which I am interested. It contains some good things e.g.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The development of the Scottish Kirk from the days of <persName xml:id="2239">Knox</persName> to the Revolution Settlement is one of the ironies of history. In theory with its General Assembly &amp; its insistence upon spiritual liberty, it was a noble democracy: in practice, unhappily, it thought it its duty to allow liberty of conscience to none but itself. With the meek sentences of the Gospel on its lips it showed an unscrupulous fierceness, a patient malice, &amp; an intolerant selfishness which cast mere secular misdeeds far into the shade".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p> 
<hi>There is much in this which reminds one but too clearly of the so called "Catholic" faction in the Church of England. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
