<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">838</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided over an amicable meeting of chapter. We agreed to ask <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> to report on the Bishop's Throne with a view to replacing or renewing the woodwork. Also, we appointed the Treasurer, <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, and Car&#x00F6;e a committee to consider &amp; report on the wood&#8211;work now in the Library, with a view to its exhibition.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather which was bitterly cold became as the day passed very tempestuous &amp; wet. Beyond going to the Cathedral for Mattins and Evensong, and to the Chapter house for the meeting, I did not venture out of doors. Old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3845">Fleming</persName>, the Vicar of Coxhoe, who is to be installed as an honorary canon tomorrow, arrived to stay the week&#8211;end. He has been 49 years in his depressing parish. While <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was reading to me in my study before going to bed, a formidable down&#8211;blow of soot filled the room with smoke and dirt, and covered everything with black. The chimney must have been very foul. This will put my study out of use for some days, a circumstance which is the more annoying as I wanted to write a careful letter to the "Guardian" on <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> little book. He has a rather indignant protest in this week's issue against what he call "misrepresentation".</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
