<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[246]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">828</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName></hi><hi> went off to Newark by the 8.20 a.m. express. We breakfasted together before he left. The Newcastle paper announces the important (!) fact that this is my Birthday, adding the fact that I complete 53 years today. I completed the sermon for Assize Sunday; attended Mattins and Evensong; walked with Logic; sent a birthday cake with an adequate supply of sixpences to the schoolhouse; and received the good wishes of the boys from </hi><persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi></persName><hi>. From the good ladies at Birchington came very kind letters, &amp; a beautifully worked shield with the Cathedral arms. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi> sent me a volume of verse with a Greek inscription. <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> sent me an affectionate letter. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2658">Kathleen</persName></hi><hi> did the same. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="369">Miss Graham</persName></hi><hi> sent a card with a message of goodwill. Old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName></hi><hi> wrote me a characteristic letter. It is rather an odd collection of well&#8211;wishers. </hi><hi rend="italic">I received from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1592">Lord Cromer</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> a copy of a letter, which the <orgName xml:id="263">Anti&#8211;Suffrage Society</orgName> proposes to send to the Press, together with a request for permission to append my signature. This I graciously conceded, only regretting that the letter was so mildly expressed.</hi><hi> The </hi><hi rend="underline">Medical Association</hi><hi> sent me a long screed about the proposed arrangements for facilitating maternity. I gather that the general practitioner is alarmed lest his practice shall be curtailed by the transference of maternity cases to a new brood of State Officials. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> E. S. <persName xml:id="3639">Buchanan</persName></hi><hi>, who appears to have worked with the late Bishop John <persName xml:id="1554">Wordsworth</persName>, &amp; to be a recognised authority on textual questions, sends me three pamphlets, which contain a formidable attack on the textual methods of <persName xml:id="1047">Westcott</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1965" display="no">Hort</persName>, and on the Revised Version. He claims that a sound criticism annihilates the contention that our Lord asserted the absolute indissolubility of marriage. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
