<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[312]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">802</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A letter came from a Leeds parson asking me privately to suggest names for the Vicarage of that city. It appears that the patronage is vested in 25 trustees, &amp; that these gentlemen are at their wits' end to discover a suitable clergymen, and meditate handing over the matter to the <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Winchester</persName>! Thus the world goes with us! I wrote to <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> inquiring whether </hi><hi rend="underline">he</hi><hi> could suggest anybody. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">I</hi><hi> can't. The clergy are all of the same colour now, and that the wrong one.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Bank, and directed M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3901">Moult</persName>, the Manager, to hold my "War Savings Certificate" in his strong&#8211;box.<note xml:id="321" n="1"></note> The serial number of this document is </hi><hi rend="bold">D 27,493, </hi><hi>and it falls due on September 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1921. If the said document were lost, a duplicate could be obtained on production of the serial number.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That strange lad, Charlie Fairlie <persName xml:id="2118" display="no">Cunningham</persName>, now a Papist formerly a chorister at Westminster Abbey, writes to me a rather rhapsodical letter on the religious state of England. I was so far interested, however, that I sent him a careful reply.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We spent the afternoon in going over the great munitions works which the Government have established at Birtley. <persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName> and Capt</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> Algrain were our guides. We first visited the cartridge factory ^which is^ under the direction of Armstrongs, and mostly 'manned' with women &amp; girls: and then we went to the shell&#8211;factory which is entirely worked by Belgians, largely invalided &amp; wounded soldiers. From the Factory we went on to the village &#8211; Elizabethville &#8211; which now contains 4500 Belgians, of whom about 400 are married. It is completely organised as a civil community under a governor (Capt. Algrain). We visited Church, Hospital, Schools, Market, &amp; private houses.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
