<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[336]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">791</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" reports in full the sermon with which the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> "opens" the "National Mission"</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is an impressive and eloquent deliverance, but vague and even perplexing. Certainly the inquirer will find as ambiguous response therein as ever was returned by the Delphian oracle. I wrote to <persName xml:id="389">Lord Bryce</persName> thanking him for his "Inaugural Address to the British Academy".</hi><hi><note xml:id="274" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> Then I weeded the gravel walk, &amp; otherwise busied myself in the garden. <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> arrived about 6 p.m., and I had much talk with him. He made himself very agreeable to Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName>. The Evening papers report but petty damage done in last night's raid, in which another Zeppelin was destroyed. This makes four Zeppelins destroyed in as many weeks. It would seem that this particular method of taming England is not without some disadvantages of its own. Hadow is as talkative and cheerful as ever. He certainly seems to have found the place which matches his powers and inclinations. He is thoroughly successful, and has the vivacious charm which belongs to the successful man. His many&#8211;sidedness of interest and knowledge gives him access to many avenues of personal influence: and his natural good temper enables him to make the most of whatever opportunities he has. His subject &#8211; education &#8211; is one that commends the approval of all the best people: and thus it makes him everywhere intelligible and welcome. How far otherwise is the clergyman's lot! Save in the narrow pinched grooves of what is called 'the religious world', </hi><hi rend="italic underline">his</hi><hi rend="italic"> subject is unwelcome, barren of interest, almost unintelligible. He may be tolerated in spite of it; he will never be welcomed on account of it. Men suspect, or pity, or despise the official representative of Religion.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
