<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[236]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">835</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The post brought me a letter from M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Arthur <persName xml:id="3738">Elliot</persName>, writing as as 'an old Editor of the "Edinburgh Review" to thank me for what he calls 'the <ref xml:id="779">excellent article</ref> in the current number on the <ref xml:id="817">Report of the Archbishops' Committee'</ref>. He says that it recalls to his mind 'the views expressed in the same Journal by Dean Stanley and other eminent contributors in the past'. I fear that may be true, and that I and my opinions are obsolete by half a century at the least! But not the less true both morally and historically. I wasted the morning in trying to prepare materials for a sermon on 'corporate penitence', a hazy &amp; misleading phrase much used by the new race of missioners! It occurred to me to take my text from that strange &amp; moving story of the 'hanging up before the Lord' of Saul's sons to end a famine. The narrative illustrates vividly enough the primitive notion of corporate guilt. "After that the Lord was entreated for the land" is a suggestive sentence, disclosing a savage conception of God. I attended Mattins and Evensong, &amp; then 'did my duty' by putting in an appearance at the <persName xml:id="3897">new Mayor's</persName> reception. The city fathers are, I think, somewhat perturbed by my brutal lucidity on Sunday! We lunched with the <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshanks</persName><persName xml:id="2663"></persName> to meet the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> and <persName xml:id="1981">his wife</persName>. I had some talk with the Bishop about the very important appointment to Newcastle from which the <persName xml:id="1874">prating G.</persName> has now retired. I gave him <persName xml:id="636">Pearce's</persName> three names, which he suggested for Leeds. He is evidently rather attracted by the notion of appointing the amiable but muddle&#8211;headed <persName xml:id="923">Newsom</persName>, who would cause no friction but strengthen no cause. He is, however, a good fellow in himself, &amp; certainly the Bishop might do worse.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
