<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">856</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName> and <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd George</persName> have resigned</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The King has sent for <persName xml:id="2278">Bonar Law</persName>.<note xml:id="328" n="1"></note> Meanwhile, the d&#x00E9;bacle in Roumania proceeds apace, and the ignoble paralysis in Greece shows no sign of improvement. I attended Mattins, and then spent half an hour in sawing up logs</hi><hi rend="italic">. <persName xml:id="4019">Locksley</persName> [Loxley] &amp; <persName xml:id="3854">Bothamly</persName> [Bothamley] waited on me as a deputation from the Chapter of the Rural Deanery to indicate the desire of the parochial clergy that, if soldiers were stationed at Durham, there should be no Church Parade for them in the Cathedral, but that separate parades should be arranged for them in the parish churches. I bit their heads off!</hi><hi> The newly appointed incumbents of Bearpark &amp; Edlingham, <persName xml:id="3726">Hawke</persName> and <persName xml:id="3727">McCracken</persName>, came to lunch. Also the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>. They seemed decent &amp; intelligent clergymen. I attended Evensong &amp; then walked with Logic.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started to read </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Matheison's</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; Reform in Scotland 1791&#8211;1843</hi><hi>" which forms the concluding volume of his considerable work. It compares the Evangelicalism of Scotland with that of England in a very interesting way. Both were intellectually squalid, and socially repulsive, disfigured by tuft&#8211;hunting parsons &amp; corybantic fanaticks to an intolerable degree. The strength of both lay in the general horror produced by the excesses of the French Revolution, and in the extreme &amp; universal abstinence from spiritual interest &amp; evangelistic effort which marked the reigning 'Moderates'. The situation at the present time is quite startlingly similar. I am a "Moderate", and only by violent efforts can I bring myself to simulate interest in foreign missions, or in "Home Missions", or in "Temperance", or in any "Social Reform"!!! Oh dear!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
