<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[278]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
           </p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">814</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The second lesson this morning includes the verse. l. Tim. ii. 15. 'She shall be saved through the [mayin: her] childbearing.' (&#x3B4;&#x3B9;&#x3B1; &#x3C4;&#x3B7;&#x3C3; taugree&#x3BA;&#x3B5;&#x3BA;&#x3BD;&#x3BF;&#x3B3;&#x3BF;&#x3BD;&#x3B9;&#x3B1;&#x3C3;). The <persName xml:id="532">Bishop of Ely</persName> quoted these words in conversation on Sunday. "S. Paul said the truest thing about Woman that has ever been said in those words", he observed. "I see that you set aside the notion that the reference is to the childbearing of S. Mary", I said, &amp; he rejoined: "Yes: on every ground, both linguistic &amp; exegetic that sense is inadmissible. S. Paul mentioned childbearing as woman's supreme &amp; distinctive function."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3571">George Nimmins</persName> came &amp; finished the re&#8211;arrangement of my books. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName> has come out of hospital, and is again in the choir house. I went to see him. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, whose zeal in these matters is apt to outrun his discretion, writes to ask my opinion about starting a branch of the <orgName xml:id="38">Churchmen's Union</orgName> in Durham. </hi><hi rend="italic">My own feeling about that society is one of grave and deepening misgiving. It represents a blend of the old liberal Anglicanism, which was mainly Radical &amp; undenominational; and the new liberal Catholicism, which is mainly heretical &amp; sacerdotalist. The first advocates disestablishment &amp; female suffrage: the last Biblical Criticism and Episcopacy! Neither commands my confidence. I would move cautiously forward, maintaining &amp; making the most of the Establishment: relaxing clerical subscription, &amp; reconciling Non&#8211;episcopalians. I would raise the standard of clerical education, &amp; reduce the number of the clergy by uniting the smaller livings. To this end I would abrogate the Pluralities Acts. Throughout, my aim would be to strengthen &amp; broaden the National Church. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
