<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">851</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brings me a letter from the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName>, which confirms the evidence of the <persName xml:id="602">Bishop of Southwark</persName>. It runs thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Dean,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My attention has been called to your most important letter about the Papalizing of our Church. It is becoming quite serious. We were practically </hi><hi rend="underline">ordered</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>to launch into the present Finance scheme.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>to run the National Mission.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>To submit to a Continuation C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> of the Mission.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>This Diocese was </hi><hi rend="underline">ordered</hi><hi> by the National Council Mission to pay &#x00A3;162. for its extravagances. There is probably another bill to follow. All this is quite apart from the matters </hi><hi rend="underline">voted</hi><hi> at the Bishops' meetings, although in these respect for the Abps., &amp; especially for the <persName xml:id="128">Abp.</persName> in whose room we meet, makes free discussion on </hi><hi rend="underline">any matter of importance</hi><hi> difficult. We may talk as much as we please about trumpery affairs. In the Bishops' meeting the Council re. Ordination was carried, which issues all kinds of orders about conditions of ordination. The C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tees</hi><hi> on Church &amp; State, and Expert C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> on Rubrics were appointed over our heads. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">All this has come in with the present <persName xml:id="130">Abp. of York</persName></hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I often speak in a minority of one, and am afterwards thanked secretly for having spoken.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The whole arrangement is a serious menace to the liberty of the Church, &amp; I am glad that you have called attention to it. There are a few laity behind it all, &amp; not least M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="740">Creighton</persName> </hi><hi rend="bold">[194] </hi><hi>&amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi><persName xml:id="283">Montgomery</persName>. They are out now for autonomy, &amp; will get disestablishment, and deserve it. I hope that you may have some opportunity of returning to the fray. Your Church &amp; State article will do a lot of good. The Church Papers are muzzled to a great extent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very sincerely</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>E. A. Manchester.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>This letter gives a suggestive glimpse into the working of the Church of England. The <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> confessed to me very similar sentiments a few days ago. The <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol</persName> is also extremely discontented. Why do they not combine, &amp; break up the hypocritical pretence of agreement? <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName>, <persName xml:id="2533">Nickson</persName>, <persName xml:id="3933">Woods</persName>, <persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName>, <persName xml:id="475">Perceval</persName> [Perival], <persName xml:id="242">Knox</persName>, <persName xml:id="1980">Wild</persName>, <persName xml:id="720">Diggle</persName>, <persName xml:id="477">Chavasse</persName>, <persName xml:id="1727">Jayne</persName> &#8211; there are 10 bishops who might be brought to act together if there were anyone to lead them. But there is no one, and every day makes the position worse.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My residence having ended, I took the opportunity of walking to the race&#8211;course to see what preparations had been made for Sunday's event, and then walked over 'Nine tree Hill' with Logic. The weather was still, foggy, and very cold.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
