<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">839</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The stormy weather continues. Rain, wind, and bitter cold. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is clear to me that on <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> 'principles' the English Reformation could nowise be justified: while they serve very well as the premisses </hi><hi>[sic]</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of the Roman conclusion.</hi> <hi>Even where he refuses to sanction Roman practices he does so on no principle save that the law at present forbids. Sometimes he expresses his desire for the very practices he owns himself compelled to prohibit: &amp; he indicates popular agitation &amp; insistence as a sure method for securing a change of the law. I would test Gore's churchmanship in the following points:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>Reservation of the Sacrament for the purpose of worship.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Compulsory confession.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The doctrine of ecclesiastical authority.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>I preached at Mattins, and celebrated the Holy Communion afterwards. Before the service I installed Canon <persName xml:id="3845">Fleming</persName>, who read the lessons. Though so ancient in aspect, and physically frail, he read clearly, &amp; with a loud voice. I attended Evensong, when the Anthem was Wesley's 'Wilderness'. Afterwards I wrote a letter to the "Guardian" on the subject of Gore's <ref xml:id="828">"Manual"</ref>. It did not please me, or fulfil my real intention, but I sent it off, as I shall have no time to write anything better. Also I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, from whom also I received a letter. After dinner we sate in the back study, and talked together until our guest retired to bed. The weather was boisterous &amp; wet throughout the day. Our only comfort under its discomfort is the hope that it operates on the side of our Roumanian allies, who are hardly pressed by the Germans. It will be a first&#8211;class disaster if Roumania is crushed, and pillaged, but it does not seem very improbable.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
