<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[332]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">793</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brings me the following from the <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol</persName>:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"I may say for your private information that sometime ago I wrote to the <persName xml:id="215">P.M.</persName> urging him </hi><hi rend="bold underline">strongly to consider you for one of the vacant sees, &amp; I know Lord <persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> did the same</hi><hi>. It is becoming really vital to us that we should have in <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> &amp; in the direction of ecclesiastical affairs those who can voice with logical clearness a more central &amp; historical Anglican position."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>But even if the P.M. were disposed to take this course, which does not appear to be probable, how could I possibly afford to accept the Bishoprick of Exeter saddled as it is with a pension of &#x00A3;1600 to the outgoing bishop. I have reason to know that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the Bishops of <persName xml:id="475">Hereford</persName>, <persName xml:id="602">Southwark</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1980">Newcastle</persName> also desire me to join the Bench</hi><hi>; but all of them together cannot increase the income of the see! It is, however, rather disconcerting that money should play so large a part in these things.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I revised a sermon for tonight, and wrote to </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling</persName></hi><hi>. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> lunched here to meet <persName xml:id="3842">Craster</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Crook, and preached in the Parish Church, where the Harvest Thanksgiving was in progress. The wet weather was unfavourable to church&#8211;going, but notwithstanding there was a considerable congregation. The church is a mean building, and can accommodate about 500 persons. This, with a mission&#8211;room holding perhaps half as many, provides for a population of about 11,000 people. The Vicar, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3576">Barker</persName>, told me that there were 13 dissenting chapels in the parish, including what was said to be the only Moravian congregation in the country. There are a good many Roman Catholicks.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
