<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">848</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a Zeppelin raid on the coast last night. We slept through it, though the attacks were said to have been made at Hartlepool. The London post had not come in at breakfast time. Later in the day we learned that two Zeppelins had been brought down, one off Hartlepool, and another off the coast of Norfolk. Many persons in Durham witnessed the downfall of the first. The evening paper reports that no considerable damage was done by the airships. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. At the latter </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3510">Walter Jackson</persName></hi><hi> made his thanksgiving for recovery from illness. I started making preparation for the <orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName> Lecture.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="636">Ernest</persName> wrote from Westminster to express approval of my letters to the "Guardian" and the "Times". He is doubtful of my wisdom in mentioning W. <persName xml:id="1173">Temple</persName> by name. He thinks that doing so might 'tend to give an undue estimate of his importance, and to drive a wedge that need not be driven, between him and us'. But I think it </hi><hi rend="bold underline">important that Temple should be forced to come into the open, &amp; be understood to be what he really is viz. an aggressive Episcopalian.</hi><hi> Ernest evidently shares the general estimate of <persName xml:id="552">Headlam's</persName> amiability:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Headlam has evidently reverted to his earlier manner or want of manner, &amp; has amply justified the opposition recently raised against his being promoted, on the ground that the clergy simply would not be able to stand him personally.'</hi></p></div><p><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="600">Ernest Rudling</persName></hi><hi> sent me a grateful letter in acknowledgment of the cheque. He hopes to be sent to France almost immediately, where his chances of survival are, I suppose, not considerable. But of this he appears to be comfortably unconscious!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
