<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916. Liverpool.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">863</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3655">Holt</persName> &amp; I walked into the city, having much interesting conversation on the way. He is himself an Unitarian, much given to good works. His <persName xml:id="3658">father</persName> was the first Lord Mayor of Liverpool. When Gladstone offered him a baronetcy, he declined it, and suggested that some distinction should be bestowed on the Mayor of the greater cities. The G.O.M. jumped at the idea, and forthwith acted on it. After having my hair cut at the barber's; I was taken to the Liverpool Institute, where M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3661">Weisse</persName> had collected the boys into their hall or theatre. I made them a short speech, and was then shown over the school. The equipment is admirable, the teaching efficient, and the general impression conveyed by the boys thoroughly good. There are about 500 boys in the school, ranging in age from 11 to 18. The Head&#8211;master (of German stock though born in Edinburgh) is evidently an enthusiast. From this school I was led by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Holt to the Liverpool Cathedral, &amp; handed over to Canon H. G. <persName xml:id="3669">Smith</persName>, who showed me so much of this vast structure as already exists.<note xml:id="329" n="1"></note> The height of the nave vaulting is 116 feet. Then Canon Smith walked with me to the Municipal Buildings, where the <persName xml:id="3667">Lord Mayor</persName> entertained me at lunch. </hi><hi rend="italic">In proposing my health he described me as 'a national figure'!! I made a brief speech in reply, and then we all went to the smaller S. George's Hall, and I distributed prizes and certificates, + made a speech on education:</hi><hi> I spoke more haltingly than usual, + sate down in much self&#8211;discontentment. Then I was given tea by the Lady Mayoress, &amp; sent off to the station. I took 8 hours to get to Durham, and arrived about 2 a.m.</hi>
 </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
