<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[258]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">823</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Oxford by the 10.25 a.m. train, and travelled to Durham, changing at Woodford, Sheffield, &amp; York, and arriving fairly to time about 5 p.m. My journey was sensibly relieved by the conversation of a young Shetlander, 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> Lieut. Norman Percy <persName xml:id="3542">Henderson</persName>, who returned from the front in order to learn flying, and is now stationed at B.N.C.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Before going to bed I wrote to <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName> informing her that after consulting my friends in College, I was 'prepared to undertake the task which she was good enough to propose to me'.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"It is not, of course, possible to decide what form it would be desirable to adopt for a "Life" of the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> until one knows the extent &amp; nature of the materials that he has left behind; &amp; therefore, I apprehend that my first duty must be to ascertain this point. Until the end of the year it will not be possible for me to do anything, but I should like to work steadily at it with the New Year. You will, I know, yourself give me the necessary information about the earliest years, &amp; help me with advice &amp; criticism throughout."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I add the suggestion that, if she is still at <orgName xml:id="225">Pusey</orgName> in February 1917, when </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I must come up to London for the Lecture at the <orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName></hi><hi>, I might manage to come up to Oxford to see her.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The 'Church Times' has a hostile leader on my <ref xml:id="779">Edinburgh article</ref>. Lord <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> expounded the Report to the House of Laymen, avoiding any specific reference to his critics. The <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> was present to hear his exposition, &amp; perhaps also to indicate his own approbation of the Report.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
