<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[308]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">804</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The violent wind of last night has broken a considerable branch from my principal tree, and hurled it into my neighbour's garden. There is still enough foliage on the trees to render them rather helpless under a gale: and the gales of the last week have robbed us of our autumnal glories. This morning the wind is moderating, though still high, and there is a brilliant sun. Reviewing the four changes in the Episcopate since I became Dean, one notices that there is a steady decline in intellectual distinction. At Bristol </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2533">Nickson</persName></hi><hi> succeeds <persName xml:id="172">Browne</persName>: and at Exeter, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="31">Cecil</persName></hi><hi> follows <persName xml:id="358">Robertson</persName>. In both cases the out&#8211;going bishop had some academic and literary pretentions; the incoming bishops are wholly destitute of these. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1980">Wild</persName></hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3933">Woods</persName></hi><hi> replace <persName xml:id="1132">Straton</persName> and <persName xml:id="176">Carr&#8211;Glyn</persName> [Carr Glyn]: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">in no case is there any pretence of intellectual distinction, but some improvement in personal quality</hi><hi>. What possible weight on any theological issue could the four new bishops carry?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle, and there I preached in S. George's, where a dedication Festival was being observed. It is a fine new church, richly, even sumptuously, adorned. The Vicar, <persName xml:id="3590">Canon Boot</persName>, is evidently a "moderate High Churchman", and a member of the "great central body" of Anglicans, of which Bishops are wont to speak on platforms! I repeated the sermon on 2.Samuel xxiii. 14&#8211;17, which has already been delivered in Durham, and in South Moor: and I added some vigourous expressions proper to Newcastle, and to a congregation of well&#8211;to&#8211;do folk, respecting "war&#8211;profits". I saw no reporter in the congregation, and none came to beg for my MS. afterwards. We lunched with the Vicar &amp; his family, &amp; had tea with <persName xml:id="3722">Lady Ravensworth</persName> on our return journey.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
