<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[292]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">807</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It being S. Luke's day, I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Sacrament. <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName> celebrated, 4 canons &amp; 2 minor canons attended. I received from <persName xml:id="1330">George Macmillan</persName> the draft of a petition to the <persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> asking him to grant a Civil List pension to <persName xml:id="1019">Addis</persName>, the out&#8211;going Vicar of All Saints, Ennismore Gardens, and I signed &amp; returned it. I revised the Sermon for next Sunday: and attended Evensong. Before the service I invested Edgar <persName xml:id="3572">Dobbie</persName> with the S. Cuthbert's Cross, as a badge for good conduct. This is a device by which we seek to enlist vanity in the service of discipline! After service I walked with <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>. He told me privately that <persName xml:id="1028">Lord Wolmer</persName>, who is evidently the aggressive agent in this "autonomy" agitation, has written to him suggesting that a meeting should be convened for considering the <ref xml:id="817">Report of the Archbishops' Committee</ref>, &amp; offering to provide a speaker. [symbol] </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Gee is one of the "Archbishops' Messengers", and has received a printed commission from their Graces</hi><hi>. This is another appeal to vanity, this time in the interest of a project, which has been launched with precipitation, conducted with vast parade of advertisement, &amp; now is on the look&#8211;out for a justifying </hi><hi rend="underline">raison d'être</hi><hi>. <persName xml:id="3828">Stock</persName> [Stocks], the University Librarian, came to see me with respect to the Cock Library at S. Oswald's Vicarage. It appears that Cock was a learned non&#8211;juror, who died in 1702, and bequeathed about 1500 volumes, mainly controversial, to the Vicars of St. Oswald's together with &#x00A3;20 to provide for their suitable accommodation in the Vicarage of that parish: that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4019">Loxley</persName> the present Vicar would like to transfer them to the Chapter Library: that there was some question as to his legal competence to do this. I promised to bring the matter before the Chapter.<note xml:id="326" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
