<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[340]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">790</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>O Lord, give me the light of Thy Holy Spirit to guide me through this darkness along these tangled ways, for truly without Thy help I must needs go aside from the path, and be lost. Show Thou me the Way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee.	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Amen.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated at 8 a.m. Four wounded soldiers were among the comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi>, and three of them, who were quite able to walk, were too shy to come up to the rails, so I carried the sacrament to them. The other was too crippled to come up, &amp; was entitled to receive in his seat. I spoke kindly to them afterwards, in the Cloisters. They bring a sacrifice to the Lord, which exceeds in spiritual worth anything that the rest of us can offer. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, and preached on behalf of the <orgName xml:id="297">"<hi rend="underline">Lord Kitchener Memorial Fund</hi>"</orgName>. The Church was fairly filled, but the congregation did not contain more than 20 grown men, even counting those in the choir. Four&#8211;fifths of the congregation were composed of school&#8211;girls, &amp; young women. The remainder were mostly old women. Yet this is the parish church for a population of more than 6000 people. Making all allowance for the absence of men on account of the war, it yet remains painfully suggestive that such a handfull should attend Divine Service. There cannot be fewer than 1000 households in the parish. I doubt whether (on the most liberal estimate) 100 of them were represented in the Parish Church this morning. The occasion was special: there was a special preacher: there has been a vast amount of special religious activity connected with the "National Mission": there are three young (relatively) and active clergy: and this is the poor result. '<hi rend="underline">Parturiunt montes et nascitur ridiculus mus</hi>'.<note xml:id="323" n="1"></note>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[338] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Russell Ellice</hi><hi>, the new boy at the school whom Brand commended to me, came to lunch. He is neither an Adonis, nor a genius, but a prosaically normal lad of 14 with little to say. But he may have all the more in him for his economy of words.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Evensong, and afterwards motored to Willington, where I preached to a crowded congregation. It was, of course, the Harvest Festival. I repeated for the fourth time in succession the sermon on Galatians VI.7.9. It gradually attains a more perfected form, and, as I get to know it more completely, my delivery certainly becomes easier, &amp; I begin to understand how the legend of Whitfield working through his ministry on 7 sermons, which by constant iteration had attained homiletic perfection, may contain a measure of truth. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3571">George Nimmons</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> went with me, and we had a good deal of talk. He is a good lad, &amp; aspires to be a sailor. </hi><hi>We got back to the Deanery about 8.30 p.m. Then after supper I read some poetry to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. Miss M. came to us yesterday from Scotland where she has been staying for some time with the <persName xml:id="956">Haldanes</persName><persName xml:id="1386"></persName>. She says that Lord H. was deeply moved by the death of Raymond <persName xml:id="305">Asquith</persName>, and that his prayer at the family devotions on Sunday night was most beautiful &amp; moving. It would appear to be the practice of that eminent man to pray extemporaneously in his own household. This is a very interesting fact, hardly to be paralleled in England, though I should suppose that a generation or two ago it was not uncommon. Scotland is still at least so much behind its southern neighbour. The Tractarian movement did much to destroy extemporaneous prayer in homes, &amp; to substitute some form of set words, or attendance at Mattins. These are now in turn disappearing.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
