<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1916.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">852</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of Chapter. Our principal business was the appointment of incumbents to Bearpark and Edlingham. We appointed <persName xml:id="3727">McCracken</persName> to the latter, an Irishman very highly recommended, but said to be a Christian socialist of an ardent type. To Bearpark we appointed <persName xml:id="3726">Hawke</persName>, also highly spoken of, and a 'Socialist'. Both these men were said to be of the humblest origin, and both had been nearly 20 years as curates in the diocese. I would not allow my dislike of Socialism to affect my vote, &amp; so I told the Chapter. The consequence is that two more parishes go into the hands of that poisonous faction! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote another letter to the "Guardian" replying to </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="3912">Whitney's</persName> rudely&#8211;expressed letter</hi><hi rend="italic">. But of such correspondence there is no tolerable end: &amp; probably one were wiser never to embark on it. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I attended Mattins and Evensong. Also I walked with Bp. <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName>.</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName> arrived in their motor from Darlington.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName> arrived, not at 6.23 p.m. as he had arranged, but about 9.30 p.m. bringing a copious story of missed connexions and lingering trains. The Bishop of Jarrow &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName> came to dinner, also M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3518">Hodgson Fowler</persName>. <persName xml:id="2800">Culley</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3448">his wife</persName> came in afterwards. There was cheerful talk enough, but it left no impression on my mind, so that I judge that its quality could not have been high. A book arrived from the publishers 'with the author's compliments'. It was <persName xml:id="3566">Foakes Jackson's</persName> "Lowell Lectures" recently delivered at Harvard. The subject, "Social Life in England 1750&#8211;1850"<ref xml:id="834"></ref>, gave opportunity for much gossip about disreputable Royalties, which is so dear to the American public. But whether we should give it them is another 'proposition'!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
