<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">906</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'The grossest errors are but abuses of some noble truths.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Whichcote</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>It is not less true that the grossest vices are but perversions of the best faculties, as Tacitus said, 'Corruptis optimi pessima.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>O God, give me a portion of the spirit of St Paul, something of his courage, of his sympathy, of his willingness to labour &amp; suffer in the cause of Truth, of his large vision, of his readiness to abandon error, above all of his devotion to thy Blessed Son. Cleanse my conscience, illumine my understanding, kindle my heart, direct my life in the way of Thy service, through the same Thy Son, Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. Then I set to work on the Commemoration Sermon, &amp; mainly finished it. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="3528">Salvin</persName></hi><hi> came to lunch. I attended Evensong. When I came out of service </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Hale</hi><hi> from Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street came to see me in order to induce me to attend a "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">War Savings' Meeting on Feb 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline">.<note xml:id="321" n="1"></note> I consented on condition that he w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> fetch &amp; return me</hi><hi>. Several letters arrived by the afternoon post but nothing of any real value. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> took me down to the recreation rooms used by the troops. They were not crowded but apparently appreciated. After dinner I read my sermon aloud to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>. It did not please me at all.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There seems to be a general impression that the congregation on Saturday will be extremely small. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> &amp; the <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> announce their intention of coming &amp; there will presumably be a few honorary canons!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
