<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[78]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">897</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName> on F. W. <persName xml:id="3776">Robertson</persName></hi><hi> (v. 'Spirit, Matter, &amp; Miracle' p. 66.)</hi>
</p><div type="quote"><p><hi rend="italic">"In regard to the New Testament, there is one name that is apt to be overlooked, F. W. Robertson (1816–53) of Brighton. The reason for this comparative neglect is probably because he was a simple parish clergyman, and not a technical scholar or theologian: he comes more into the history of thought and action than into the history of exegesis. But I imagine </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that his was the first clear example of what may be called the realistic study of the Bible, envisaging the Biblical characters, not as saints upon a pedestal, but as living men and women in the circumstances of their time. And this with him was a genuine British product, independent of foreign influences</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The morning post brought me an invitation to preach in the "<orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName>", from the Church Committee of that institution.<note xml:id="418" n="1"></note> It occurred to me that it might be both wise and bold to accept, &amp; I wrote a careful letter, well–adapted, if occasion arose, for publication<ref xml:id="919"></ref> proposing to do so on Sunday, March 25</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic">.<note xml:id="419" n="1"></note> </hi><hi>I received from the Life Assurance Office the cash bonus (£140.16.0) on the smaller of my policies, and paid it forthwith into my Bank, ordering the Manager to secure for me £500 of the new War Loan Stock.<note xml:id="284" n="1"></note> </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to Sanday, asking him to send me one of his 'privately printed' symposia</hi><hi>.<note xml:id="338" n="1"></note> Also I sent out, through <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>, the invitations to lunch on the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> inst.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was more snow at intervals during the day, &amp; no sign of any change of weather. After dinner I read aloud some of "Pickwick", and actually succeeded in keeping <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> awake!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
