<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[64]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">905</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Divide with reason between self&#8211;love &amp; society; &amp; be so true to thyself as thou be not false to others, especially thy king &amp; country. It is a poor centre of a man's actions, himself. It is right earth; for that only stands fast upon his own centre; whereas all things that have affinity with the heavens move upon the centre of another, which they benefit.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bacon Essay xxiii 'Of Wisdom for a man's Self'.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Babington's</hi><hi> Preface to the 'Rolls Series' edition of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop <persName xml:id="3632">Pecock's</persName></hi><hi> book "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Repressor of over much blaming of the Clergy</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="859"></ref> is very good reading. It contains a fairly good account of his trial &amp; condemnation by Archbishop Bourchier in 1457. He was offered by his Grace the pleasant alternative of recantation or burning at the stake, &amp; he chose the former. The modern admirer of the medieval church may well consider this aspect of it.<note xml:id="340" n="1"></note>	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The "Newcastle Daily Journal", the "Yorkshire Post", and the "Times"<ref xml:id="916"></ref> have my letter to the '<orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName>' secretary announcing my acceptance of the invitation to preach there on March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. So </hi><hi rend="underline">that</hi><hi> fat is in the fire, &amp; we must see what kind of a blaze will come! I chose the text for the Commemoration Sermon, and made a start at the discourse. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, having developed a cough, stayed in bed, and was visited by D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3099">Stuart</persName>. Scarcely had that loquatious leech taken his departure before a telegram from the adjutant at Gravesend ordered Ernest to report himself tomorrow! This seemed too rash, so I telephoned to the doctor, who undertook to communicate with the adjutant. Ernest himself wrote a propitiatory letter explaining his situation.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
