<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi> 
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">889</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I attended Mattins and Evensong. There was no choir at either, the boys being away for the next fortnight. I wrote a short address for tomorrow's function, and then went through the Dedications of Jeremy <persName xml:id="1439">Taylor's</persName> <ref xml:id="310">'Works'</ref>. Colonel <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName>, <persName xml:id="3630">Major Craven</persName>, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> came to lunch, and afterwards I went round the Cathedral with Colonel Herne. He told me incidentally that he was of the High Church persuasion! The weather throughout the day was most unpleasant &#8211; high wind with floods of rain. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I started to walk with Logic after Evensong, but were turned back by a deluge almost immediately. <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> kept indoors all day, feeling rather sorry for himself. It was no suitable day for a man to travel in after an attack of influenza. The 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> truck&#8211;load of coal was brought in this morning. By packing the coal into the cellar carefully it is hoped that as much as 18 tons will be placed in it: and the remaining 7 tons may be stacked in the smaller cellar by the kitchen.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
