<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">914</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins: celebrated the Holy Communion at 11.15 a.m.: and afterwards presided over the annual meeting of the St. Catherine's Home Committee in Bishop <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin's</persName> Library. After lunch, I attended a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Hospital Governors</orgName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Mayor called on me to show me the plan for the new allotments on Dean &amp; Chapter land. He says that about 100 additional allotments will be taken up in the City, making a total of nearly 600</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a letter from the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName></hi><hi> marked "private and confidential". He is evidently much exercised by the progress of the Archiepiscopal scheme for securing "autonomy".</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"I take the earliest opportunity of letting you know that the </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C.</persName>, urged by the <persName xml:id="49">Bp. of O.</persName>, is pushing forward the <ref xml:id="817">Church &amp; State Report</ref> with great energy</hi><hi>. He wished to have a meeting of all the Bps. And all the Bps. Suffragan holding sees in the month of May, to discuss the <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> report…..Fortunately the Bps. resolved not to have the Suffragans summoned, but to discuss the matter among themselves…..My object in writing to you is to ask you what you think ought to be done under the existing circumstances. The position seems to be full of peril."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2074">Bishop of Ripon</persName></hi><hi rend="bold underline"> has asked me to address the meeting of men in Leeds on Good Friday which Bp. <persName xml:id="280">Boyd Carpenter</persName> originally started.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I observe a significant reticence in the Church newspapers about my projected visit to the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName>. The "Challenge" professes to have no objection to my preaching there, but only to the wide publicity given to the fact, and to the absence of episcopal authority! But I suspect they are a little abashed by the generally favourable attitude of the secular press. They will speak their minds more boldly before long!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
