<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> to February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">920–929</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"In looking back, with our present experience, we are driven to the melancholy conclusion that, instead of diminishing the number of wars, ecclesiastical influence has actually &amp; very seriously increased it".– <persName xml:id="3601">Lecky</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"But although theological influences cannot reasonably be said to have diminished the number of wars, they have had a very real &amp; beneficial effect in diminishing their atrocity." – Ibid.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I stayed at the Station Hotel, York, during my visit to the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>. <persName xml:id="3800">Canon Scott</persName> and Bishop <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> were my main comrades, but I saw a good many other clerics, and was on civil terms with them all. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The <persName xml:id="130">Abp. of York</persName>, whom I now saw for the first time since he lost his hair, is unrecognizable. He has the aspect, and even the carriage, of an aged man. Only his voice attests his identity with the youthful prelate of a few months since. He was civil enough to me, &amp; asked me to lunch with him, but both on his side and on mine there is a clear perception of definite &amp; irremoveable antagonism. We are pursuing different ideals, and our methods correspond to our ideals.</hi> <hi>I moved as an amendment to <persName xml:id="2021">Frere's</persName> motion the resolution which I had announced: &amp; I made a speech which impressed &amp; stirred the House. But I was myself very discontented with it, for much that I had planned to say was left unsaid, &amp; much that I did succeed in saying was very ill–said.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Welldon seconded me, but to little purpose. Finally, having got all the advantage I could out of the debate, I withdrew the amendment on condition that Frere admitted into the motion a sentence which made it colourless. ("without expressing at this stage any opinion on the merits of the scheme put forward in the <ref xml:id="817">Report on the Ch. &amp; State</ref>").</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Friday (Feb 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) I travelled from York to Oxford, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">where I put up with the <persName xml:id="66">Warden</persName> of All Souls</hi><hi>. On Saturday (Feb. 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) I called on the <persName xml:id="2141">Omans</persName><persName xml:id="2142"></persName> and on <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, who now lives in his own hired house, 31, Holywell. He is distinctly ^better^ than he was in the autumn, but still far indeed from health. <persName xml:id="302">Miss Anson</persName> sent the car to fetch me to <orgName xml:id="225">Pusey</orgName>, where I spent the week–end in order to see the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> papers. There is not much biographical material of any value. However we put aside such as seemed quite useless, and she undertook to send me the rest. The Vicar of Pusey is <persName xml:id="3592">Maude</persName>, whom I once knew as a fellow of Hertford. He has shaved his beard, &amp; looks very different from my recollections of him. I went to the Holy Communion at 8.30 a.m. The service was choral, both Maude &amp; his wife possessing fine voices, but what happens when one or the other has a cold is dreadful to reflect upon! Also I went to Mattins, &amp; heard a quaint little extemporaneous talk from Maude, who laboured to persuade his rustics that our Saviour's stern rebukes of the "Scribes &amp; Pharisees hypocrites" had no proper reference to formalism or ceremonialism in religion! It was a hopeless thesis, &amp; a feeble plea. Later he &amp; his wife came to tea, &amp; we had some civil talk, never rising out of the severest commonplace.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Monday (Feb. 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I proceeded to London, &amp; on arrival went to 19 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, where I lunched with the <persName xml:id="216">Gows</persName><persName xml:id="542"></persName>, &amp; joined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. Later we went together to 16 Elvaston Place, where we were the guests of Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName> for the remainder of our visit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Wednesday (Feb 14</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">) we dined with <persName xml:id="2069">Sir John</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Lady Barran</persName>, and there met </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the <persName xml:id="3600">American Ambassador</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Page</hi><hi rend="italic">. I had much very interesting conversation with his Excellency, who does not scruple to express his personal desire that America will come into the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[38] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We had previously lunched with the <persName xml:id="990">Runcimans</persName>, &amp; met <persName xml:id="3599">Gardner</persName> [Gardiner], the Editor of the Daily News. It was curious to note the tone of disparagement which ran through all their political comments. Party feeling is certainly as bitter as ever, though it does not express itself so openly. On Thursday (Feb. 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) we lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="977">Buchanan</persName>. Professor &amp; Miss Ramsay were there, &amp; another whose name escapes me. We had much pleasant conversation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">At 8 p.m. we dined at Lambeth. The dinner was worthy of the saintliest of his <persName xml:id="128">Grace's</persName> monastic predecessors. <persName xml:id="2253">Bishop Brent</persName> of the Philippines was there, &amp; the Archbishop's <persName xml:id="239">brother</persName> &amp; his wife.</hi><hi rend="italic"> After dinner the <persName xml:id="128">Abp.</persName> carried me off into his sanctum, &amp; for more than an hour we talked. He began by complaining of my purely critical attitude, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">referring to the <ref xml:id="779">"Edinburgh" article</ref>, (which has evidently had considerable effect</hi><hi rend="italic">). "What is your policy?" I replied that it was not my place to formulate a constructive policy, and, if it were, I was disposed to think matters had gone too far, &amp; that disruption was now only a matter of time. He seemed to agree. I pointed out the unrepresentative character of his "Church &amp; State" C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">tee</hi><hi rend="italic"> . This seemed to move him, for he pulled the Report from his bookshelf, &amp; proceeded to go thro' the names: but gave it up when I defended my thesis in detail. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop repeatedly affirmed his substantial agreement with me, &amp; seemed hurt at my not perceiving, or, at least, not recognizing the fact. I told him that the control of the Church seemed now to have passed into other hands, that I did not trust his fellow–Primate, or the episcopal majority, &amp; that, in short, the direction which Church affairs were taking seemed to me to be perilously mistaken. He expressed no dissent, &amp; we parted in a melancholy but amicable mood.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[36] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">On Friday (Feb 16</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">) I stayed indoors most of the morning, in order to see </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> who had wired overnight that he was ordered to Salonika.</hi><hi> I had to go before his arrival, in order to lunch with </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName></hi><hi>, who had promised to look out what letters from or about the Warden he could lay his hands on. However Ernest came to me at the <orgName xml:id="89">Athanaeum</orgName>, and we bade one another farewell. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Shall we ever meet again? Has the close friendship of the past year reached its term? God knows. I felt depressed at losing the Boy</hi><hi>. Returning to the Club, I found </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Bishop Brent there, &amp; we had some more talk.</hi> <hi>He is over here in order to organize, or assist in organizing, the better information of his countrymen with a view to bring them, though so late, into the War. I saw </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3946">Newbolt</persName></hi><hi>, who is most cheerful about the submarines. He says that <persName xml:id="2052">Carson</persName>, though he 'pulls a long face' in public, expresses himself most cheerfully in private: that already 30 submarines have been destroyed or captured: that in 6 weeks the much vaunted campaign will be over. This is good to hear, but time alone can show whether it be true. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">At 5.30 I went to the <orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName> in Albermarle Street, &amp; gave my lecture on "Authors' dedications in the XVII</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> century". There seemed to be a good audience: &amp; to my surprise, I was given a cheque for £10.</hi> <hi>afterwards. Miss Mundella gave a dinner–party. (<persName xml:id="602">Bp. of Southwark</persName>, <persName xml:id="3597">Frank Dicksee</persName>, Justice <persName xml:id="4071">Younger</persName>, <persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName>, <persName xml:id="2768">Lady Charnwood</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3598">Geo. Trevelyan</persName>, &amp; ourselves.) We had much pleasant conversation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On Saturday (Feb 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) I returned to Durham by the 10 a.m. from King's Cross. After a very exhausting journey I got to the Deanery about 4.30 p.m. &amp; went speedily to bed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
