<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ash Wednesday, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">933</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went together to the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. The Celebrant was <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>, as Canon in Residence. There were fewer Communicants than in former years, and (with the exception of the clergy &amp; one student) all were females. The solitary male was Philip. I suspect that boy is traversing a difficult stage of </hi><hi rend="underline">his</hi><hi> pilgrimage just now. At his age (22) spiritual issues, if realized at all, are realized with intensity. There is an utter sincerity about one's religious procedures which in later life is not found, perhaps cannot be found. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins at 10 a.m., and read the Commination Service from the pulpit. Also I attended Evensong, and listened a little simple sermon from the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> jerkily delivered. There was the tiniest congregation I have yet seen for this occasion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3813">Darwin</persName> sent me a little book which she has written, called "My German Professor, A True Story of Yesterday &amp; Today". It is pleasant, womanly, and wholesome. I wrote her a sincerely flatterous letter of acknowledgement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> arrived about 11 p.m. He had come from Holy Island, where he had been hearing more comfortable stories about the submarines. We have a device for turning them upside down, and (so it is stated) the wretched things are done for in that situation. He reports that the </hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> expresses himself very ardently about the Commemoration of Founders &amp; Benefactors which he attended in Durham Cathedral.</hi><hi><note xml:id="240" n="1"></note></hi><hi rend="italic"> He admired particularly the completeness of the service, &amp; the facility with which every part of it was carries through. It is so difficult to judge any work of one's own that an outside opinion if (as may be assumed in this case) honest is worth noting.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
