<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[66]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">904</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="556">Jim</persName> and <persName xml:id="2801">Clara</persName> terminated their visit which began on December 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> &amp; was broken by a visit to Scotland from Dec 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> to Jan 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. They started to motor to London. I went to Newcastle, and spent a melancholy hour with the dentist. On my return I wrote a large number of letters.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The Bishop of London (<persName xml:id="2784">Blomfield</persName>) is a man of very great ability, humane, placable, generous, munificent, very agreeable, but not to be trusted with great interests where calmness and judgement are required".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Substitute 'Oxford' for 'London' and the description will serve for 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sydney <persName xml:id="3896">Smith</persName></hi><hi> was brutally frank about the motives of clergymen:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"the truth is, the greater number of clergymen go into the Church </hi><hi rend="underline">in order that they may derive a comfortable income from the church</hi><hi>. Such men intend to do their duty, and they do it, but the duty is, however, not the motive but the adjunct. If I was writing in gala and parade, I would not hold this language; but as we are in earnest &amp; on business, and as very rash &amp; hasty changes founded upon contrary suppositions of the pure disinterestedness &amp; perfect inattention to temporals in the clergy, we must get down at once to the solid rock without heeding how we disturb the turf &amp; the flowers above."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Has he really been as good as his word, and reached the 'solid rock'? At least he has laid his finger on some stern and governing factors in the practical problem of an endowed professional ministry, which may not wisely or rightly be ignored.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
