<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[20]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">940</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another glorious morning, bright with the sun &amp; musical with the birds, only the leafless trees &amp; flowerless borders attesting to winter's reign. I attended the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in <placeName xml:id="77">S. Gregory's</placeName> &amp; received the Sacrament. I attended Mattins, &amp; worked all morning at the C.T. Sermon. After lunch I walked round Houghall Wood with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>; &amp; afterwards shewed the Cuthbert Relics to <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> and <persName xml:id="2763" display="no">Alice</persName>. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> was present in order to witness to the condition of the relics.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The afternoon post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, in which he sends me the record of De Laune's institution to the Parish of Redenhall. It runs thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Petrus de Laune sacroe Theol: professor. Rector ordinatus presbiter per doctores et professores Collegii de Layden 26 Junii 1599</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Per Franciscum epum Norwic: 12 Nov. 1629 institutus.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Beeching comments: </hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"So <persName xml:id="2820">Cosin</persName> was right in his recollection that De Laune had his orders at Leyden. Overall had been away from Norwich some years before the appointment to Redenhall, which took place in the first year of the episcopate of Francis White. Being the </hi><hi rend="underline">first</hi><hi> year, the Archbishop seems to have had a claim on certain presentations: he is said to have made a choice of Redenhall, &amp; appointed de Laune. The Archbp. was Abbot".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Gilbert went with me to the <orgName xml:id="239">Y.M.C.A.</orgName>, where I presided over the annual meeting. Colonel <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName> had prohibited the soldiers from taking part in a concert, which had been arranged, because his permission had not been first obtained! This damped the proceedings, which were sufficiently dull.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
