<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]		</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">916</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. There was but a small number of communicants, a fact easily explained by the continuance of the severe weather, and the resulting epidemic of influenza. I preached to the troops at 10 a.m. There was a formidable accompaniment of coughing to my speech, but I think they listened as well as they could. I attended Mattins, and heard an excellent discourse from <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> in which he related the legend of <persName xml:id="3603" display="no">Dorothea</persName>, &amp; quoted <persName xml:id="3605" display="no">Massinger's</persName> play.<note xml:id="327" n="1"></note> Accompanied by <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, I motored to Sunderland and preached in St. Ignatius's church. Before the service I had some conversation with <persName xml:id="3470">Sykes</persName>. His son, erstwhile a schoolmaster, now a British Officer invalided from the front, was there, silent &amp; awkward but neither unintelligent nor deliberately uncivil. We were back in the Deanery about 9 p.m. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the streets of Sunderland I bought a paper, and learned the very important </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">fact that America had broken off diplomatic relations with Germany. </hi><hi rend="italic">The President told the Senate that he would wait for an "overt act" before going the final stage &amp; declaring war. It would appear that he had not long to wait, for the sinking of an American vessel is already reported. The other neutrals have been invited to follow America's example. Thus at last the true character of this amazing conflict is being made perfectly clear. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is a fight between civilization &#8211; the civilization of Christendom &#8211; and the resuscitated Paganism of Germany. How long will it continue? </hi><hi rend="italic">What fresh abominations must the groaning world witness? What are the real potencies of modern war when frankly dissociated from all restraining influences of chivalry &amp; morals? The next few weeks will give us the answers to these questions.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
