<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">903</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="2069">Barrans</persName><persName xml:id="2070" display="no"></persName> went off after breakfast in the hotel omnibus, for no cab was obtainable. I read through Sydney <persName xml:id="3896">Smith's</persName> letters to Archdeacon <persName xml:id="3913">Singleton</persName>. They contain much sound wisdom disguised under a masque of humour. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">His references to <persName xml:id="2784">Blomfield</persName>, <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>, are admirably suitable to <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>, Bishop of Oxford.</hi> <hi>Also I finished Stuart Reid's Life of the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3606">Earl of Durham</persName><ref xml:id="846"></ref>. It is very interesting. There was a kind of fatality which pursued that vivacious nobleman. Even the authorship of his famous "Report" was questioned, but apparently with no better justification than a venomous dictum of Brougham. Old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3822">Ritson</persName> sent me a silver&#8211;gilt sugar box for the table as a memento of the function at Muggleswick. I attended Evensong, when a treble solo was very well sung by Kay. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> came to see me for no apparent purpose except to disclose his hunger for preferment. He has set his heart on getting the Deanery of York, and is evidently pulling every string he can get hold of. It is rather a disgusting spectacle, &amp; probably as futile as it is disgusting. For I have no doubt whatever that Lang has arranged for the man of his own choice to be appointed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
