<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">915</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName></hi><hi> writes to me this morning:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"With extreme interest I read the "<orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName>" correspondence. I think you have done rightly as well as generously in saying, Yes. This is a time when unprecedented conditions </hi><hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> affect the handling by a great Churchman of such a request".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, and then presided at a meeting of Chapter. We talked over the question of National Service as it would affect the Minor Canons: &amp; I told May that we sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> expect him to volunteer. I attended Evensong: and then revised the proofs of the "interview" which the representative of the <ref xml:id="848">"Christian Commonwealth"</ref> had with me last week. The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> came to tea, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I gave him a type&#8211;written copy of my letter to the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>. </hi><hi><persName xml:id="2798">Dolphin</persName> brought two Belgian officers to tea. I showed them over the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening papers announce that America has broken off diplomatic relations with Germany. Will this step mature into open conflict?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><persName xml:id="3654"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> A. F. Robson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> writes to me from West Malvern, enclosing a long &amp; elaborate paper of directions for teaching during Lent, issued to the clergy of the diocese by the <persName xml:id="2047">Bishop of Worcester</persName>. He would have me advise him what he should do. The Bishop's programme is sufficiently ambitious. The conflicting claims of the employer &amp; employed, the relation of one sex to the other, the procuring for all classes a Christian Sunday, purifying public life, improving the morals of places of entertainment &#8211; these are to be dealt with in successive weeks of Lent. It is a "large order" for our poor little half&#8211;educated country parsons to work through. And the Bishop himself is hardly the wisest or most learned of men.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
