<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">932</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in writing some important letters 1) to the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> about the National Service Scheme as it bears on this Foundation. 2) to <persName xml:id="3734">Ernest Myers</persName>, <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName><note xml:id="339" n="1"></note>, and the <persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> beseeching their assistance in providing materials for the <persName xml:id="228">Warden's</persName> Life. I attended Mattins and Evensong, &amp; arranged a cycle of celebrants for the week&#8211;days in Lent. </hi>
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Monday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>the Dean</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Tuesday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName></hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Wednesday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Thursday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>A minor Canon</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Friday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName></hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi>Saturday:</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rend="Normal">
<hi><persName xml:id="2785">Bp. of Jarrow</persName></hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon, service over, I walked to the headquarters of the Y. &amp; L. Transporters, &amp;, finding no one at home, continued to the Officers Mess, &amp; there had tea with such	officers as turned up. I left a letter for Colonel <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName>, suggesting that be the number of men what it may, they sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> always come to the Cathedral while the cadets from the School are available.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It being Shrove Tuesday the children of Durham followed their immemorial custom of visiting the Cathedral, led by some legendary hope of blessing, but the wetness of the day, &amp; the general dislocation of life made their numbers less than usual, and their mirth more chastened.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">By one of those absurd coincidences which fill my life I am pledged to write an article against "Prohibition" just at the precise moment when the Sectaries to whom "Prohibition" is the summary of all Religion, are minded to take me to their hearts! My devotion to the Establishment and my dislike of Total Abstinence are two faults in the Dean of Durham hard to be condoned by any faithful Nonconformist</hi><hi rend="italic">. <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> may hold them to be schismaticks, but he is willing to profess himself a Teetotaller, and to vote for Disestablishment. For too many Dissenters these are really 'the weightier matters of the Law'. </hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
