<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">901</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
I presided at a Chapter meeting. We elected M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <persName xml:id="3575">Hudson Barker</persName>, the Vicar of Consett, to be Vicar of South Shields, in succession to Canon <persName xml:id="4031">Roberson</persName>, now Vicar of Norham on Tweed. Also, we voted a second donation of &#x00A3;10 to the fund for financing the Dictionary of Patristic Greek, which <persName xml:id="2950">Turner</persName> is running. <hi rend="bold underline">Also we decided to 'meadow' the grass in the College, and to employ the gardeners in growing vegetables in the land bordering the choirboy's playing field</hi>. We held the audit of the College accounts immediately after the Chapter Meeting. <persName xml:id="2069">Sir John</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Lady Barran</persName> arrived at tea&#8211;time and we had much talk. There came to dinner Colonel <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName>, <persName xml:id="3651">Captain Slade</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="3679">Miss Christopher</persName>. The <persName xml:id="2800">Culleys</persName><persName xml:id="3448"></persName> and the <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> came in afterwards, and 'discoursed sweet musick'.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent in notice to the Prolocutor of the following resolution:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"That this House regrets that the large and most important subject of the Relations of Church and State should have been brought before the public during the War, when adequate consideration of it is wholly impossible, and could not accept without grave modification the proposals contained in the <ref xml:id="817">Report of the Archbishop's Committee on Church &amp; State</ref> as forming a satisfactory basis for the future relation of Church and State in England."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Proposed by the Dean of Durham</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Seconded " " Dean of Manchester </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The form of this Resolution included some suggestions from Bishop <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>, which had the effect of mitigating the censure on the Report which I had desired to express.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
