<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3rd Sunday in Lent, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">951</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Tho' truths in manhood darkly join,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Deep&#8211;seated in our mystic frame,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We yield all blessing to the name</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Of Him that made them current coin.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>For Wisdom dealt with mortal powers,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Where truth in closest words shall fail,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>When truth embodied in a tale</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Shall enter in at lowly doors.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And so the Word had breath, and wrought</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>With human hands the creed of creeds</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In loveliness of perfect deeds,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>More strong than all poetic thought;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Which he may read that binds the sheaf,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Or builds the house, or digs the grave,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And those wild eyes that watch the wave</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In roarings round the coral reef.<note xml:id="333" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]		</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'As to war, if it be the means of wrong &amp; violence, it is the sole means of justice among nations. Nothing can banish it from the world. They who say otherwise, intending to impose upon us, do not impose on themselves. But it is one of the greatest objects of human wisdom to mitigate those evils which we are unable to remove.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Burke</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The snow had nearly disappeared during the night, a rapid thaw having set in. It was damp &amp; dismal enough when I went to church at 8 a.m., but as we left the Cathedral, the sun was shining pleasantly. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1097">Harold</persName> were among the communicants. I celebrated. After breakfast we all three motored to Newcastle, where I preached to a large congregation in S. George's. We lunched with the Vicar (<persName xml:id="3590">Canon Boot</persName>): and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">then visited the new Vicar of Newcastle (<persName xml:id="923">Newsom</persName>)</hi><hi>. He &amp; his wife appear to be taking to their new field of work very cheerfully. We called at <placeName xml:id="63">Ravensworth Castle</placeName> on our way home, &amp; had tea with the family there. We reached home about 6.30 p.m. After dinner I showed the Raemaker pictures to Harold, to whom most of them were new.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
