<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
   <hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
           </p>
         <p>         
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">908</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A cheerless icy morning with occasional essays in snow!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The choral celebration at 11 a.m. was very scantily attended, but the procession was long, and the singing sounded very beautiful under the great vault. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Just 30 people came to lunch</hi><hi rend="italic">, for several failed at the last moment for various reasons. The <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> was among my guests; and <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName>. The procession at the special service was made more varied and pompous by the presence of the University magnates in their gaudy robes. <persName xml:id="3462">Lord Durham</persName> was there with a party. The congregation was not large, but larger than I had expected. I preached<ref xml:id="917"></ref> from Heb: x.39 "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">But we are not of them that shrink back unto perdition: but of them that have faith unto the saving of the soul</hi><hi rend="italic">". After the service there came many into the Deanery for tea, including the Lambton party. When at last everybody had gone away, I felt extremely fatigued. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="1780">Gouldsmith</persName> and <persName xml:id="3161">Dawson Walker</persName> expressed warm approval of my decision to preach at the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Capt. <persName xml:id="3524" display="no">Lewis</persName> brought a young officer named Brook to the service, and afterwards to tea. Radcliffe sent a cheque for &#x00A3;402: being the amount of insurance bonus.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
