<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
       </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">931</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have done nothing all day but write letters and attend services, save of course, to read the papers. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The "Church Quarterly Review" has an article by the Editor on "Catholicism" which says many sound &amp; accurate things, but succeeds in being monstrously offensive to many individuals. The same hand is but too plainly discernible in another article on the <ref xml:id="817">"Church &amp; State Report"</ref>, and here I myself am subjected to some rude handling</hi><hi>.<ref xml:id="920"></ref></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I consented to write an article on "</hi><ref xml:id="915"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Prohibition"</hi></ref><hi rend="italic"> for a volume which has been projected as a counterblast to the agitation of the Fanaticks. The question of principle seems clear enough. It cannot be reasonable to prohibit legitimate use in the interest of Liberty. Religiously, this proscription of all alcoholic liquors appears to be heretical. But the matter is curiously complicated by the pertinacious &amp; (more or less) authoritative declarations of scientific folks as to the mischievousness of alcohol e.g. the Report drawn up by a Committee of the <orgName xml:id="166">Royal Society</orgName> in 1917, which <persName xml:id="990">Runciman</persName> has sent me, speaks dogmatically on "the results observed in practice, &amp; on large numbers of individuals, as to the effect of alcohol on the accomplishment of physical work". Troops march further without than with alcohol, &amp; are in better condition. It is all very puzzling. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "British Weekly" has an article on "Prohibition" by <persName xml:id="2155">Denny</persName>, which is very fanatically expressed</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is humiliating that a man of his ability, knowledge, and experience of life should be able to take such a tone with respect to a policy which he knows to be condemned by many, probably by most, of his fellow&#8211;countrymen. But "Temperance" is a matter which has become the victim of fanaticism, &amp; where that can be said, there is no place for charity, or reason, or modesty. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived by the late train, having travelled without inconvenience, and with fair punctuality.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
