<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[14]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">948</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Instead of going to church at 8 a.m. I worked at the C.T. sermon, &amp; finished it by lunch&#8211;time. <persName xml:id="3470">Sykes</persName> came to lunch, &amp; we went together to a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="96">Ch. Def. Society</orgName> C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi><persName xml:id="1237">Priestman</persName> arrived late, but S. brought him on to the Deanery, where we finished the business, &amp; had tea. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Col. <persName xml:id="3608">Maclean</persName> called to thank me for my kindness to the Troops! <persName xml:id="1097">Harold Henson</persName>, now a Captain in the battalion of Colonials, arrived before dinner. He is a silent youth.</hi> <hi><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> also came to see me. Much snow fell today.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]		</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>'Whoever teaches civilians to love their self above all things, or military men to believe that they have no vocation but a murderous one, helps to make the one so weak that they must be ready to quail before any physical force, the other so wicked that they must be ready to exert it. And the loss of all national spirit will lead, as it has ever done, not to a golden age of Christian fraternization, but to military despotism.'			</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>F.D. <persName xml:id="687">Maurice</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'We are called to rise above the level of fighting pagans, not to fall below it. There is indeed, a lower depth than that of the military spirit &#8211; the depth of complacent mammon&#8211;worship.'	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3594">Miss Stephen</persName> <ref xml:id="847">'Quaker Strongholds'</ref>; p.133</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
