<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">918</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>It is the inevitable characteristic of a moderate or liberal section in Church or State to hold together with comparative laxity. The very fact of their liberality implies a regard to more than one side of any question – a certain impartiality which refuses to lend itself to mere blind partisanship, or to that species of irrational devotion which forms the rude strength of great parties.		</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3604">Tulloch</persName></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I frittered away my morning in writing letters &amp; making preparations for going away tomorrow. I called at the Bank, and instructed the Manager to apply for a further </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">£500</hi><hi>. of War Loan Stock. On my return to the Deanery, I presided at a meeting in the dining room at which a feeble–looking parson, <persName xml:id="3602">Archdeacon Rees</persName>, explained his experiences in East Africa, where he had been interned by the Germans, and treated with some roughness. I was struck by the emphasis he laid on the friendly intimacy which had grown up between the internal missionaries of the C.M.S and the Universities' Mission. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">They had actually reached the point of communicating together!</hi> <hi>It never seemed to occur to the speaker that this was a sufficiently absurd description of the members of one &amp; the same Church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I attended a meeting of the Marquis of Granby Lodge of Freemasons. This is an ancient Lodge, founded as long ago as 1739, and it has a numerous membership. The proceedings were half an hour behind time in beginning, and were so leisurely, that nearly 2 hours were expended in getting through the business. The frost is more severe than ever. As I walked home the great buildings looked very wonderful in the moonlight.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
