<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">885</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Geordie <persName xml:id="571">Gore</persName></hi><hi> went away after breakfast. I paid the household bills, which show a disconcerting increase. </hi><persName xml:id="3585"><hi rend="underline">Boutflower</hi></persName><hi> lunched here. He wanted to discuss with me the new scheme for <orgName xml:id="227">Sherburn Hospital</orgName>. </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName></hi><hi> and I walked for an hour in a fair sunshine which was a hypocritical masque of a bitter wind. The choirboys came and sang carols in the drawing room for an hour. We asked the residents in the College, and a few others to come in. I gave the boys severally sixpence, and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> added an orange, and a Christmas card.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="3650">Dean of Chester</persName></hi><hi> has a letter in the "Times" supporting me: and the </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1816">Bishop of Norwich</persName></hi><hi> sent me his "Charge" with a letter expressing agreement with me on the subject of multiplying bishopricks.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I find </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="512">Bishop Hall</persName></hi><hi> so interesting that I waste much time in reading what has no bearing on the purposes for which I am now concerned with him. His opinion of Russian Christians is notable:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">These are the basest dregs of all Christians…..These are as ignorant as Turks, as idolatrous as heathens, as obstinate as Jews, and more superstitious than papists". </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Perhaps this view was not more wide of the mark than the excessive laudation which now prevails.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
