<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">938</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"We are called to rise above the level of fighting pagans, not to fall below it. There is, indeed, a lower depth than that of the military spirit &#8211; the depth of complaisant mammon&#8211;worship. To our shame be it confessed that this spirit may clothe itself under the profession of "non&#8211;resistance". When the salt so loses its savour, it is truly fit for nothing but to be cast out &amp; trodden underfoot".	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3594">Miss Stephen</persName>. <ref xml:id="847">"Quaker Strongholds"</ref>, p.133 	</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>A most beautiful morning, soft air, bright sun, &amp; the birds singing as if well&#8211;assured (poor fools!) that the winter now lay behind them. I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and celebrated. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName>, enclosing a copy of his will! </hi><hi>This looks like business. I attended Mattins. The whole morning was spent in writing a short article against "Prohibition" to form a chapter of the small volume projected by Eveleigh Nash. In the afternoon I walked with Bp. <persName xml:id="2785">Quirk</persName>, &amp;, on my return, wrote to Ernest. At 6 p.m. I took <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> to the <orgName xml:id="270">Choir School</orgName>, where he talked about his experiences in France very interestingly to the boys for an hour &amp; a half on end.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
