<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[34]	</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
          </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">930</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol][symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I did not go to the early service, being exhausted by yesterday's travels, but I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. Also I received the Holy Communion after Mattins, when <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> celebrated. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Philip le <persName xml:id="3919">Mesurier</persName> lunched with me. He told me that he had acted on the advice which I gave him: (see p.58) that his father had given him </hi><hi rend="underline">carte blanche</hi><hi rend="bold underline">: that <persName xml:id="3159">Moulsdale</persName> had not taken his behaviour in good part, &amp; insisted on a letter from his father before transferring him to the Castle. This demand did not seem to me improper in itself, or unnatural in the circumstances; and so I told the youth. Philip is an unusual type of young man, with an old&#8211;world gravity &amp; politeness which are but too rarely found now. He may have, I am disposed to think that he has, a good intellect as well as a good heart. Certainly it were a pity to have him prematurely spoiled by a Ritualistic Seminary. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">But my circle of personal responsibility is widening perilously. <persName xml:id="3654">Robson</persName> of West Malvern protests to his Bishop against dictation, &amp; even sends a vigourous letter to the "Challenge", avowedly in deference to my leading. Young Philip is revolutionizing his life in yielding to my opinions. Several parsons have written to me to tell of action which my example has moved them to take. Even of the Bishops some write to ask for my "advice". The Archbishop spoke of the effect of my words and writings, &amp; even seemed to plead for my assistance. What does all this mean but the terrifying and distasteful proof that I am losing my personal liberty, becoming enmeshed in the net of responsibility for others, bound by my own precedents? It displeases &amp; alarms me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> came in about 6 p.m., &amp; sate talking for more than an hour. He is of course disappointed at the appointment to the Deanery of York, but he will be the better for being 'put out of his agony of futile hope!'</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
