<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">956</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">A revolution is reported from Russia. The Czar has abdicated, and his brother has been proclaimed Regent during the minority of the new Czar, a boy of 13</hi>. <persName xml:id="2278">Bonar Law's</persName> statement in the House last night was as optimistic as possible, but optimism is difficult in the circumstances. There is no account yet of the attitude of the Russian Church, a factor of cardinal importance, &amp; in the long run probably decisive. The "Times" has a continuous narrative of the Revolution. I observe that there are references to "drunken" mobs, which hardly suggests the prohibition of vodhka; and the gaol&#8211;birds, having been liberated, proceeded to make repeated efforts to burn down the Law&#8211;courts! This certainly <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> revolution.
         </p>
         <p>
I finished the sermon for All Fools' Day (!) taking as my subject "<hi rend="underline">The Failure of Lutheranism, not a disproof of the Reformation</hi>". It is designed as an appendix to the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName> Sermons: &amp; adds a measure of completeness to them. Then <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came, &amp; cleared up my room. I gave him "The Fair Maid of Perth": &amp; he stayed to lunch. I attended Evensong, and then went through Houghall Wood with <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName>. On our way, we stopped to talk to the Vergers who were getting to work on the meadow by the white gate.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Philip le <persName xml:id="3919">Mesurier</persName> came to say Goodbye. He thinks he has arranged his removal from S. Chad's</hi>. The afternoon post brought me a kind letter from old Prof. <persName xml:id="1862">Bonney</persName>, to whom I had sent a copy of my little correspondence with the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>. He approves my action. The 'Record' has a note commenting on my preaching in S. Sepulchre's on the Sunday following my appearance at the 'City Temple'. I shall be devoutly thankful when the whole performance is over. Anyway another fortnight will practically see me through it.
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
