<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
        </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">887</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"There needs no prophetical spirit to discern, by a small cloud, that there is a storm coming towards our church: such a one as shall not only drench our plumes, but shake our peace. Already de we see the sky thicken, and hear the winds whistle hollow afar off, and feel all the presages of a tempest, which the late example of our neighbours bids us fear".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="512">Bishop Hall's</persName> Dedication of Via Media (v. Works. IX. 489)</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and celebrated the Holy Communion. After breakfast I walked into the town &amp; bought Logic's dog licence. Then I presided at a Chapter&#8211;meeting. After lunch I distributed prizes to the choristers in the Chapter House, and then attended Evensong. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> brought to tea the dowager <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry</persName>, <persName xml:id="3735">Lady Palmer</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Palmer, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi><persName xml:id="2843"></persName> &amp; Miss <persName xml:id="2895">Pemberton</persName>, &amp; others. Also Colonel <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName> was of the party. Scarcely were they gone, than we went to the Choir&#8211;house for the Choristers' Entertainment. The boys acted the court&#8211;scene in </hi><hi rend="bold underline">"Richard III". </hi><hi>George was really very effective as the King, &amp; Harris as the Bishop of Carlisle. <persName xml:id="3572">Dobbie</persName> was Bolingbroke, &amp; Jackson, Aumerle. I had no expectation that the boys had so much dramatic ability. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName> has an effective letter in the "Times" headed "Episcopal Palaces"</hi><hi>. After dinner <persName xml:id="2841">Ernest</persName> read to us from "Martin Chuzzlewit". So ended a week of singular futility &#8211; the first week of the New Year, which was to be marked by so much energy and effort! The brief remainder of my working life is running out, and nothing done. This tiresome "<orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName>" Lecture had caused me to spend much time &amp; labour to no purpose, &amp; I have not yet succeeded in getting it into shape!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
