<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[84]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">891</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"A foreign ambassador, some 200 years since, coming to Durham, addressed himself first to the high &amp; sumptuous shrine of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Cuthbert, 'If thou beest a Saint, pray for me': then coming to the plain, low, and little Tomb of Bede, 'Because', said he, 'thou art a Saint, good Bede, pray for me'."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>(<persName xml:id="2095" display="no">Fuller</persName>, in 1655.) </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3453">Heylyn</persName></hi><hi> in his '</hi><hi rend="underline">Microcosmus</hi><hi>' (1625) has a violent denunciation of Tobacco.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"This unsavoury drug was first brought hither by the mariners of Sir Francis Drake Anno. 1585. It may be as an antidote for the immoderate use of drinking, which our Belgian soldiers brought with them 3 years before, from the Low Countries, before which time, of all Northern people, the English were deemed most free from that swinish vice; wherein, it is to be feared, they have now out&#8211;gone their teachers, the Dutch." [p. 799]</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins, &amp; worked at the Lecture. <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName> came in, &amp; arranged my new supply of note&#8211;paper &amp;c. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bp. of Jarrow</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2689">Quirk</persName>, <persName xml:id="2808">Rowlandson</persName>, <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName>, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Luxmoore came to lunch. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then the Mayor &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Waite called to see whether we w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> grant land for allotments. We were complaisant, &amp; conceded all we were asked</hi><hi>. Then we had the first meeting of the Patronage Committee. <persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName>, <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>, &amp; Quirk were there beside myself. We chose three names for submission to the Chapter as suitable for South Shields: and subsequently I wrote privately to the gentlemen inviting them to be candidates. The snow which lay thickly on the ground this morning maintained itself throughout the day. After dinner we sate in my study, talking &amp; reading aloud until bed&#8211;time. This tiresome lecture for the <orgName xml:id="287">Royal Institution</orgName> 'holds up' everything else, and is itself the most absolute waste of good time!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
