<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A most glorious day, everything rushing into flower &amp; blossom, &amp; the birds simply giddy with joy, singing &amp; domesticity!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lady Eden went off after breakfast, ending thus a visit which has continued intermittently for months.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Rev. John McLeod Campbell &amp; his sister came to lunch. I knew him when he was Chaplain of Hereford. He was a relation of Sir William Anson, &amp; used to be much in All Souls. Since 1924 he has been Principal of Trinity College, Kandy, where he presides over a college of boys &amp; youths of whom about half are non&#8211;Christians. There is a 'conscience&#8211;clause', but it is almost never claimed. The parents, however, object energetically when a boy changes his religion.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Jimmie came to see me. He looks rather 'played out', the results of (1) working for his exam</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">tn</hi><hi>: (2) ceasing to play football: &amp; (3) a bad cold. I shall be glad when his Ordination to the priesthood has been successfully accomplished, and he has settles in at Bishopwearmouth under Wynne&#8211;Wilson. The experiment of working for a degree while serving a curacy cannot in his case be said to have proved successful. I shall not repeat it.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
