<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[15] </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A warm &amp; brilliant day, though with a cold wind. I worked at my preparation for tomorrow both in the morning &amp; in the evening. This with my letters occupied about 7 hours.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and I walked to Binchester Farm, &amp; left cards on the Thompsons who were not at home: being in fact in Newcastle attending a great gathering of Conservatives, and listening to Winston Churchill. Lady Eden &amp; Fearne attended the same meeting.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Anne's Football Club</hi><hi> having won 'the Shield' desired to be photographed, and impudently sent to request me to join them. This, with characteristic deference to the impudence of adolescents, I did. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Birney</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Witton Park, was with the youth, &amp; I had a short talk with him.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Papist </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Blundell</hi><hi rend="italic">l asks that his correspondence with me might be published. It is difficult to refuse this request though, if I had contemplated publication, I should certainly have bestowed more pains on my share in the said correspondence. It is evident that my letters in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> made an impression on the lay Papists, and they are really anxious to separate themselves, so far as they decently can, from the position taken up by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi rend="italic">, who is not an able controversialist. I wrote to William.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
