<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My mind fastens on a Declaration by the Bishops, which should assert quite clearly the independence of the Church within the spiritual sphere: emphasize the obligation of the Bishops to maintain both the Catholic witness and the tolerant tradition of the Church of England: affirm the practical advantages of the Establishment, &amp; the duty not lightly to cast aside so valuable an auxiliary: and end by stating the necessity of such a revision of the present relations of Church &amp; State as would secure the spiritual franchise of the Church.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the course of the morning a telegram was brought to me. It ran thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Carless Davis</hi><hi> died this morning wife would like you conduct funeral at Oxford Saturday or Monday.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wired that I would do this, though it will be difficult to manage as I am week&#8211;ending at Winchester. It is indeed distressing that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Davis</hi><hi> should thus be taken away in the prime of his powers. I shall soon not have a friend left: and he was rather an intimate friend.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[109] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Wakefield</hi><hi> and I had speech with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi> on the difficult subject of the Archbishop's resignation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">We urged that his Grace should make a definite announcement that he would retire at the end of this year. This would provide a reasonable excuse for letting the issue between Church &amp; State remain undiscussed until the new Archbishop had time to get into his stride</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We talked a vast deal but not to much effect. Both the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Norwich</hi><hi> &amp; the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Birmingham</hi><hi> took part in the discussion, but very ineffectively.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">There has been a terrible railway accident at Darlington in which no less than 22 persons were killed mostly women</hi><hi>. They were holiday&#8211;makers returning from Scarbrough, &amp; seems to have come from Gateshead, Sunderland, and Hetton&#8211;le&#8211;Hole.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Archbishop was at the pains of going through the </hi><hi rend="italic">notes of his address yesterday, which I missed. He is astonishingly alert &amp; vigourous. His interventions in debate are almost always acute &amp; relevant: and his conduct in the chair leaves nothing to be desired. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Yet on reviewing the course of events during the last two years, can it be reasonably denied that they show many evidences of Senectitude at the helm?</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
