<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, July 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the day, (i.e. much of it,) in preparing my Sunday work, &amp; writing letters.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon I had an interview with an Ordination candidate named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lamb</hi><hi>, who is a student of S. Chad's. I was not ill&#8211;pleased with him. He seems to be reacting against the de&#8211;spiritualised ceremonialism which marks some of the students in that seminary of advanced "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism", &amp; he expressed a burning horror of the cunning sophistries by which pledges were emptied of meaning, &amp; even Ordination Vows made of none effect. I accepted him for Ordination at Advent on a tithe from S. Jude's, South Shields. Lionel &amp; I motored to Norton, where I consecrated an addition to the churchyard, &amp; gave an address to the considerable gathering of parishioners which witnessed the ceremony. Then I inspected the old church. Norton runs back to the 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. century. It was a collegiate church.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We dined luxuriously with an amiable octogenarian sybarite, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Keith</hi><hi>. After dinner, he gave me a list of names of persons whom he knows to be wealthy, &amp; who, he thinks, might respond to a direct appeal from me for the Castle. But I don't share his optimism, for these North&#8211;country magnates are as close&#8211;fisted as they are wealthy. We were back in the Castle in Auckland soon after 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
