<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A wet day with some delusive intervals of sunshine, and a conclusion in a violent thunderstorm.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to the Archbishop, thanking him for </hi><hi rend="italic">a copy of his tractate "The Prayer Book: our Hope &amp; Meaning". It is charming in tone &amp; temper, but very poor intellectually, &amp; strangely uninspiring. But can an aged Opportunist, even though he be popular &amp; saintly, inspire anybody? </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>An Ordination candidate, Usher, came to lunch &#8211; a ginger headed youth who has taken a 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> class Theological "Honours" at Durham, &amp; desires to be ordained in September.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Hurworth, where I consecrated an addition to the churchyard. After having tea with Miss Forster, we went to Wynyard, where I preached to a congregation of choir members, men, girls, &amp; boys, in the Chapel. It was the annual Festival of Country Choirs, &amp; astonishingly well arranged. My sermon, which had been carefully prepared, suffered from the absence of a pulpit. I had to preach from the conductor's music stand, a frail structure! After the service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>James Parker Smith sent a piece of silver as a belated offering on the occasion of our silver wedding, and old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Snaith sent some horns of an Auckland Park deer!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
