<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel came with me to Darlington, where I took the express to King's Cross. On arriving there I drove to the Athenaeum, &amp; deposited my bags. Then I went to the hairdresser, &amp; he did his duty on me. On returning to the Club, I had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Philip A. Inman, the Superintendent of Charing Cross Hospital. He told me that he desired to take Holy Orders: that he was 38 years old: had been making an income of £3000 to £4000 per annum, &amp; had saved enough to be independent: was married &amp; had no children. I asked him some questions which he answered with frankness &amp; modesty. I was favourably impressed with him, &amp; said that the Chaplain should send him the usual application form with references. When I had received this, I would consider it &amp; write to him what my decision would be.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Then I went to the House of Lords, &amp; had an interview with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Justice Roche</hi><hi rend="italic"></hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="5462"></persName> about the Mansion House Meeting. He seems really keen about the Castle. Walking back to the Athenaeum, I fell in with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Talbot</hi><hi rend="italic">, and one of his grandsons. I dined by myself in the Club, and afterwards made my way to the S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul's Deanery, where I had arranged to put up.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[146] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Justice Roche expressed himself very keenly about the Castle. He has got into personal touch with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi rend="italic">, and is, perhaps, disposed to over–estimate the value of that nobleman's assistance. For Londonderry, though an able, ambitious &amp; even public–spirited man, is an Irishman and a man of the world. He is plausible &amp; promising, but lacks stability &amp; will make no personal sacrifices. Anyway, it is all to the good that his Lordship should come to the front, and, if his doing so, would make it easier for me to fall to the rear, I shall be the better pleased. The Mansion House Meeting may fairly mark the limit of my personal exertions in a matter which is not primarily an ecclesiastical concern. I have made it plain, by raising the question in the House of Lords, that there is no hope of help from public sources: and I have secured, through the good offices of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Banbury</hi><hi rend="italic"> a public meeting in the Mansion House. My friendship with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Editor of the Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> has certainly assisted in securing the more–than–benevolent attitude of that Journal: and 'Punch' has been very helpful. Add the letters public &amp; private that I have written, &amp; the speeches that I have made. On the whole I am now morally entitled to hand over the Appeal to the Academicks.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
