<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A bright day but very cold, the wind cutting.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> prints my letter on its front page under the heading '</hi><hi rend="underline">The faith of the Sovereign' Catholic Allegiance to Elizabeth. Reply to Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi>.' It reads better than I expected, though whether it was worth while writing it I doubt.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Durham, where I instituted and licenced 8 clergymen in the Castle, and then lunched with Wilson. Then I had an interview in the Chapter Office with Probert from Winlaton. When he had gone, I was photographed by Edis. Then we motored to Deaf Hill, where I confirmed 60 candidates. We had tea with Wilkinson, the Vicar of Chilton: after which I confirmed a sick woman privately. Then we went to Lomax's largest church, an ex–skating rink, where I confirmed 175 persons in a stifling atmosphere. After the service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Prime Minister sends me a civilly expressed refusal of my request that he should speak for the Castle Fund at the Mansion House Meeting. I wrote to Lord Grey asking him to do so.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Dean of Worcester &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Moore Ede lunched at the Castle, in my absence.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
