<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A woefully wet day, dismal and chilly. Nevertheless, I motored to Wooler, taking Alexander with me. The Vicarage was less attractive and less commodious than I had expected, and than a rental of ten guineas a week might seem to suggest. But it will suffice, &amp; no doubt living in Auckland Castle spoils one for normal houses. The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Moran</hi><hi>, is a little round chatty man inclining to baldness. He said that he had met me in Oxford when I was secretary to the Laymen's League! From him I learned that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frazer</hi><hi>, the deacon whom I ordained last Advent, had died this morning. This is very regrettable, &amp; for his parents, whose only son he was, extremely distressing. On returning to the Castle, I wrote a letter of condolence to his father, but indeed, with the best will in the world, what can one say? "The economy of Heaven is dark".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Norman Sykes</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">wrote to me a very interesting letter. He is pursuing his study of XVIII</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> century Anglicanism</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hoadly</hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">a repulsive figure, was, he thinks, more respectable than is generally allowed: and</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Wesley</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">far less so. I think the exorbitant self&#8211;will of the Methodist "Apostle" was the real root of the schism</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
