<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A warm morning &amp; a heavy mist over the land, the birds all singing divinely, &amp; great peace everywhere.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and Lionel went with me to </hi><hi rend="underline">Chester–le–Street</hi><hi> where I dedicated an Altar, a Bishop's Throne, Readers and painted panels which had been presented as memorials of divers deceased worthies. I preached and celebrated the Holy Communion. There was a large congregation, and no less than 140 communicants. After service we all went to the Hermitage for lunch. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Wood</hi><hi> was very depressing about the future of the coal fields in Durham. We returned to Auckland after lunch.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the evening I motored to Sunderland and preached in S. Mark's Millfield, where the ''diamond jubilee'' of the parish was commemorated. In the course of my sermon I read out a letter which I had received from old Charles Green the first Vicar. He will be 98 years old this year. I returned to the Castle after the Service, &amp; though there were many cars on the road, arrived in less than an hour. The MSS. of both my sermons were carried off by reporters. I have an ill choice proposed to me by those gentlemen, either to be credited with their astonishing mis–reports of what I have said, or to suffer my MSS. to be soiled &amp; folded!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
