<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My speech this afternoon must begin with a brief reference to the Darlington tragedy: then state the assumption underlying my motion viz: that the preservation of our own historical monuments is a national concern: this would lead on to a short description of the Castle as one of the greatest &amp; most interesting of our historical monuments. Then I must describe the perilous state of the building, &amp; the inability of its present guardians to maintain it. Finally, I may enlarge on the public utility, educational and civil, of the Castle, on the considerable efforts of the local population to preserve it: on the obligation of the whole community; &amp; end by raising the point of possible State assistance. Incidentally, I must introduce (α) a reference to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi><hi> as Chancellor: (β) a reference to the contributions of their majesties: and (γ) a compliment to the Ancient Monuments Commission under </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Peers'</hi><hi>s direction. Perhaps I ought to meet in advance the obvious objection that if the State assists in the preservation of Durham Castle, it will create a precedent which might be applied to many other ancient buildings, which are becoming dilapidated, &amp; whose guardians cannot afford to maintain them. Also, I must somehow work in the allusion to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Curzon</hi><hi>'s zeal for preserving ancient monuments.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[121] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I walked to the Athenaeum after breakfast, &amp; prepared notes for my speech. Also, I wrote some letters including one to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fisher Ferguson</hi><hi>, who had informed me that he was leaving Collierley (Laus Deo!) and was going to Nottingham. Then I drove to Westminster, and deposited my robes in the Bishops' Room at the House of Lords. Then I "looked in" at the Assembly for half an hour: &amp; then lunched at the Westminster Deanery. [symbol] After a brief visit to the Assembly I went to the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">House of Lords</hi><hi>, where I "called attention to the grave state of Durham Castle, &amp; asked H.M. Government whether assistance from public funds could be given towards its preservation". I began by some reference to the Darlington disaster, &amp; then spoke for about 20 minutes. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi> spoke very well. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lords Phillimon</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi><hi> spoke as judges who had occupied the Castle: &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Gainford</hi><hi> also spoke. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Archbishop of York</hi><hi> spoke. In reply </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Peel</hi><hi> was negative but sympathetic. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Middleton</hi><hi> passed me a card on which he had written:</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"This House though cramped in legislative power is a great advertising medium under the stimulus of polished Episcopal oratory! I hope the response may be adequate."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[122] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I dined with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Macmillan</hi><hi> at 44 Grosvenor Road. Only his wife and another lady were present. I had a great talk with him, &amp; confirmed the favourable impression I had formed of him as a member of the Street Offences Committee. He is as scornful of the modern doctrine of sex–equality as I am, and as conscious of its practical absurdity when actually applied to life.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi> called to see me about 6 p.m. He appears to be keen about the Mansion House meeting on July 23</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Justice Roche</hi><hi><persName xml:id="5462"></persName> had written to him, and given him a list of names of persons to whom he should write. He wanted to know whether I approved of this. Of course I told him to do everything that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Roche</hi><hi> suggested. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fleming</hi><hi>, whom I saw in the Club this afternoon, said that he had written about the Castle in the forthcoming issue of S. Columba's Magazine. This is a friendly action, but whether it will have any appreciable </hi><hi rend="underline">effect</hi><hi> I doubt. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Di Darling</hi><hi> promises to exert herself to bring her friends to the Mansion House. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitty Inge</hi><hi> suggests luncheon parties on July 23</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi>: and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Struthers</hi><hi> approves. Add the exertions of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sidney Walton</hi><hi>, &amp; surely there must be some attendance in the Mansion House. It is our last chance!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
