<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A chilly uncomfortable day, tending to rain. I had a 'bad night', &amp; felt woefully inapt all day. However, I spent the morning in writing a sermon for the County Choirs Festival. In the afternoon I motored to Durham, and confirmed rather more than 200 persons in the Cathedral. Before the service I had an interview with Dawson about his acceptance of the Sunderland Rectory. He makes it turn on my allowing &#x00A3;100 per annum of the Sunderland money which I hold in trust for the parish, to be granted to him so long as the pension (&#x00A3;210) is payable to Pater out of the income of the benefice.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The 'Times' reports that Ernest Pearce has been elected an hon: Fellow of Worcester College, Oxford. Is that a personal, or a diocesan compliment? Has the Bishop of Worcester any official connexion with the College?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic underline">There is an important letter signed by the Master of Trinity, and 18 other Cambridge magnates in favour of the Revised Prayer Book</hi><hi rend="italic">. They say significantly:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"The rejection of the Measure by Parliament would in these circumstances gravely affect confidence in the spiritual independence of the Church as by law established."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This ought to set some people thinking.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
