<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This Mansion House Meeting haunts me. I wrote to Ralph, asking him to be one of the two speakers: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">to Lord Salisbury suggesting that I should raise the matter of the Castle in the House of Lords</hi><hi>: to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice Roche, invoking his assistance: &amp; to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Archibald Campbell, the Chairman of the London Stock Exchange, begging for Funds.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Newcastle, &amp; had my hair cut &amp;c, returning to Auckland immediately after the operation.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Merrefield</hi><hi>, the Rector of Etherley, died yesterday. He has been ill for months, during which his duty has mostly been done for him without charge. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> has officiated constantly, &amp; I myself have preached twice. He has held the benefice for 8 years. It is in the gift of the Bishop of Manchester, &amp; is only worth &#x00A3;283 net. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Baily</hi><hi> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Ignatius having rejected my suggestion of an exchange of livings with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bailey</hi><hi> of Heatherycleugh, I wrote to Bott of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John Baptist's, Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees proposing the same exchange to him. He is a hopeless failure where he is, but whether he could endure the isolation of a remote moorland parish is very doubtful indeed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The wonderful work of Methodism in Bristol has begun, Whitefield and Wesley being the instruments. With characteristic deference Wesley consults the bishop of the diocese. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Butler</hi><hi> said, '</hi><hi rend="underline">Well, sir, since you ask my advice, I will give it freely. You have no business here: you are not commissioned to preach in this diocese. Therefore I advise you to go hence'</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wesley</hi><hi> replied, "</hi><hi rend="underline">My lord, my business on earth is to do what good I can. Whenever, therefore, I think I can do most good, there must I stay, so long as I think so. At present I think I can do most good here: therefore here I stay</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>v. Letters of John Wesley p.70</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A Low Church pamphlet appeared in 1699 which insinuates that the clergy of the Church of England are divided into two camps: "one party were for finding out Means of Reconciliation with Rome, &amp; bringing the Pope to terms", and this, adds the pamphleteer is "the true Difference between the High Church &amp; Low Church (as they are called) to this Day.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>v. Wickham Legg's English Church Life, p. 411.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Are not these words substantially true at the present time? Rome still provides the test.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
