<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Religion's greatest obstacles today are the architecture, stained glass, ceremonial, and hymn tunes of yesterday</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dearmer</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Introduction to the 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">. ed</hi><hi>. of '</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Parson's Handbook</hi><hi>. p. 8.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The suggestions appears to be that if we could make a clean sweep of Victorian architecture, stained glass, ceremonial &amp; hymn tunes and replace them by those of an earlier time we should have removed 'Religion's greatest obstacles'! What then must Religion be if its acceptance can be determined by these things? </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Good taste</hi><hi> might conceivably be expressed or insulted by them, though the discovery of a satisfying definition of good taste is yet to be made, but </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Religion</hi><hi>? Surely that is primarily concerned with Conscience and Reason, and where these demand it, man will not lightly surrender it because its external expressions have come to be in their opinion unsatisfactory. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dearmer</hi><hi> is a typical example of the shallow &amp; lop&#8211;sided religionism which now runs riot in Anglican circles, notably those which affect a scrupulous regard for Laudian traditions as to ceremonial. They are mainly differentiated from the 'Anglo&#8211;Roman', whom they denounce, by a certain Pharisaism and insular narrowness.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 12 com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi>., including the four Brydens &amp; John. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi><hi> in answer to his request for advice on the difficult pastoral problem presented by a strong local custom of pre&#8211;nuptial unchastity. Also, I wrote to President </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Richmond</hi><hi> of Union College, Schenectady, inquiring about Judge </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ben B Lindsey</hi><hi> what his reputation in the Republic actually is, and what amount of truth there is in his account of American Society and of the Armenian method of "co&#8211;education".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The '</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Observer</hi><hi>' gives prominence to an opinion expressed by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arnold Bennett</hi><hi> in the current number of "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The World To&#8211;Day</hi><hi>", to the effect that "</hi><hi rend="underline">the sale of Bibles is steadily &amp; very seriously declining</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"I am informed by the highest authorities whom there can be no gain&#8211;saying, that the circulation of the Bible is now definitely on the wane, and to an extent extremely disconcerting both spiritually and economically".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Various religious authorities are quoted in contradiction of this statement which certainly coincides with my own observations, and agrees with the statement made to me by the Master of the Temple.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella went with me to Durham, where I preached at Evensong in S. Nicholas, Church. This is a very unpleasing modern church erected in the place of a medieval building which was ruthlessly demolished. For 24 year </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Bothamley</hi><hi>, profanely known as 'Steeplejack Bill' has held the benefice, &amp; continued the tradition of pronounced Evangelicalism which attaches to it. The patronage is held by some fanatical trust. I was surprised to find a surpliced choir, &amp; to hear the service intoned: but not even the citadels of Protestantism can wholly withstand the stream of ecclesiastical fashion. After service we returned to Auckland. The number of motors on the road suggested anything rather than Lord's Day observance. I could not but notice the recklessness of the driving in too many cases. No doubt the fineness of the day brought the 'owner&#8211;motor' on the road in unusual number.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My sermon, on which I had bestowed unusual pains was, I fear, a failure. It was "above the heads" of the congregation, and, being read, lay exposed to their suspicion! The church is acoustically bad, &amp; I had a bad throat!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After dinner I read through a little but suggestive book, "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Jewish Antecedents of the Christian Sacraments</hi><hi>" by an American Professor, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">F. Gavin</hi><hi>. It is published by S.P.C.K.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
