<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Lionel &amp; I went to Darlington, where I took train for London. I visited the hair–dresser, and the tailor: and then had tea in the Athenaeum. Then</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> I went to Lambeth, only to find that the meeting of Bishops had begun at 2.30 p. m: &amp; not, as I had stupidly assumed, at 10.30 a.m. tomorrow! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">So I had missed the Archbishop's statement, &amp; the general discussion</hi><hi rend="italic">. It appeared that the general sense was hostile to my plan of a declaration by the Church Assembly.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">"Well: I see that your vast and vacuous Brother has been at it again" – such was Lord Sumner's reference to the Bishop of Winchester's reported action in the matter of the Confirmation Service</hi><hi rend="italic">. It appeared from the Bishop's explanation that his action had been much exaggerated. Yet it was unfortunately timed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I received letters from Lord Hugh Cecil &amp; Lord Wolmer both deprecating a discussion in the Assembly, and urging an Episcopal declaration, which the Assembly would order to be entered on its record</hi><hi rend="italic">. This may, perhaps, be the best procedure, but I doubt if it will command general approval. The Bishops have quite plainly 'got the wind up', &amp; would</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> like</hi><hi rend="italic"> to do nothing.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[107] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I dined with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Grillions</hi><hi rend="italic"> at the Hotel Cecil. It was but a small party, but we had much interesting conversation. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">General Lyttelton</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Owen Seaman</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rudyard Kipling</hi><hi rend="italic">, and the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Durham</hi><hi rend="italic"> formed the company.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">We discussed India. R.K. said that '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Mother India</hi><hi rend="italic">' was absolutely true, &amp; that he could confirm all that it contained from his own experience. We discussed the United States. R.K. said that he had lived there for four years, &amp; had the meanest opinion of the population. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It was a case of 'the manured thistle' i.e. the rubbish of the Old World, strengthened &amp; developed by the conditions of life in America.</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">General Lyttelton</hi><hi rend="italic"> spoke of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gataker</hi><hi rend="italic"> [Gatacre] in no flattering terms, allowing him little more than animal courage, of which beyond question he had abundance. He admitted, however, that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gataker</hi><hi rend="italic"> had been harshly treated, and that he had carried himself with dignity and even with magnanimity after his disgrace. He said that he could remember seeing men play cricket and hunt in top hats. R.K. spoke of Durham Cathedral with enthusiasm, alleging that it was in his belief the finest cathedral in the world. I returned to Lambeth about 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
