<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I left Park Lane after breakfast, &amp; drove to the Athenaeum. There I left my luggage, and walked to Westminster </hi><hi rend="bold underline">where I obtained the Official Report of the Debate on the Prayer Book in the House of Commons on June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">.</hi><hi> Then I proceeded to King's Cross, &amp; took train for Darlington. On the journey I read the Commons Debate. Lionel met me with the car, &amp; we were at the Castle before 5 p.m. I found the Wynne–Willsons with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Bulmer &amp; her son from Hereford. They came to see the Castle, &amp; stayed for tea. When they had gone, Lionel and I went through the correspondence until nearly dinner–time. After dinner, I wrote a series of letters, including one in which I rejected the application of a Wesleyan Minister to be accepted as an Ordination candidate. I dislike 'rats' at all times: but this one could not, or at least did not, plead any </hi><hi rend="underline">conscientious</hi><hi> plea for his ratting! Also I paid the Household accounts, and a whole series of bills, which had come in during my absence.</hi> 
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">William writes to tell me that he is accepting a new position as Assistant Manager in the Bulawayo Branch of Baldwins Ltd. I do hope he is not making a mistake.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
