<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><hi> came to tea. Everybody was out except myself, so we had much talk together. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He was strongly of opinion that, even if the opportunity were given me, I ought not to exchange Durham for York</hi><hi>. An Archbishop, he said, must always be in the chair, &amp; is thus deprived of all chance of free self&#8211;expression, a situation which would be intolerable to a man of my temperament. He agreed that, in any case,</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">I could not honourably accept appointment without stipulating for 'a free hand in the matter of the Establishment'</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The money for the Castle dribbles in with a slowness which is extremely alarming. Today &#x00A3;9:9:0 has arrived. At this pace, we shall be in a position to begin in, perhaps, thirty years time!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The newspapers announce that the Primate has resigned &amp; that his resignation will take effect on November 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, which is his wedding day. The </hi><hi rend="underline">'Yorkshire Post'</hi><hi> not content with once more publishing his Grace's portrait, publishes also those of the 4 commissioners who were deputed to accept his resignation. A categorical denial of the Bishop of London's rumoured intention of accepting translation to a smaller see, is issued from Fulham.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
