<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">N. &amp; W., B. and E. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Combine in our glorious unity.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">White is black, &amp; black is white</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Always provided we write</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The hapless public to deceive</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">And our own incomes to receive.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">For are we not all "C. of E."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Bound in a glorious unity?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This doggerel which I scribbled yesterday afternoon indicates sufficiently what I think of our unanimous concurrence with the pronouncement read out to us by the Archbishop. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The unanimity robs it of all value either as a protest or as a declaration of principle</hi><hi rend="italic">. The Archbishop showed me the draught of the speech beforehand, &amp; I thought it not wholly inadequate, but it </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">never entered my head that the minority bishops would approve it</hi><hi rend="italic">. Unless they are wearing the white sheet, this can only mean that they do not find the language inconsistent with the course which they have pursued. I shall be greatly surprised if the impression produced will not be the very opposite of what we desire or intend. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Semper pavidi.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[113] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Almighty God, who in Thy good providence disposed the hearts of men to mutual charity, that here on earth in diverse brotherhoods they may prepare the coming of Thy heavenly Kingdom. We give Thee thanks for every human fellowship, but more especially that Thou hast prospered this our ancient House, and still dost guide the footsteps of her children, not weighing our merits nor measuring Thy fatherly affection. Send for Thy light upon those assembled here, and on our brethren dispersed throughout the world, that we and they being knit more closely in the bonds of friendship, may likewise grow in love of Thee, &amp; obtain together those eternal mansions, which Thou hast promised by the mouth of Jesus Christ, our Lord. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Prayer used in Balliol College Chapel, Oxford. Composed by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">H. Carless Davies</hi><hi rend="italic">, printed in "A. L. Smith, by his wife' p.319.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I had some talk with the Archbishop before leaving the Palace after breakfast, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; pressed on him again the inevitable consequence of the episcopal unanimity on which he sets such store</hi><hi rend="italic">. His much expected statement will be deprived of all point and value.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I went into the city, and had an interview with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hird</hi><hi>. We agreed to halve the loss on the '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Book &amp; the Vote</hi><hi>', of which 2000 copies were printed, and about 1000 have been sold. He said that the loss was £60.00: &amp; I suggested that we should halve it. Also I agreed to take 200 copies of "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; Parson in England</hi><hi>" at 1/– a copy. These may be given to the Ordination candidates. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>As usual </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hird</hi><hi> was communicative. He told me "in strict confidence (!)" </hi><hi rend="underline">that no more than 10,000 copies of the Archbishop's 'valedictory' had been sold, out of 50,000 printed: &amp; that the publishers had lost £500.00 on that arrangement</hi><hi>.</hi><hi rend="bold">] </hi><hi>I tried without success to get from him some explanation of the really curious fact that my latest book had not been advertised at all, so far as I could see. He seemed to think that the "fed up" condition of the public so far as the Prayer Book was is concerned, was answer enough.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I travelled to Winchester, &amp; arrived just as the match with Eton was ending. The Warden, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenyon</hi><hi>, &amp; his wife, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Chitty</hi><hi> &amp; his wife, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hardy</hi><hi>, &amp; I formed the party beside our hosts. Before going to bed, I had a good deal of intimate and interesting talk with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Williams</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
