<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Sir Reginald Blomfield sends me a copy of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Quarterly Review</hi><hi> which contains an article which he has written on "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Revolt of the Camisards. 1702&#8211;1704.</hi><hi>" He explains his action in a letter. "</hi><hi rend="underline">I read with very great interest your demolition of Cardinal Bourne as to the relative exploits in persecution by Roman Catholics &amp; Protestants, &amp; this is further evidence on the Protestant side</hi><hi>." I read the article with much interest &amp; advantage, for I have but a slight knowledge of the events recorded.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning in clearing off an accumulation of letters, </hi><hi rend="italic">and on writing the Article on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church &amp; State</hi><hi rend="italic">' for the new edition of the Encyclopaedia Britannica.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon I went in to Durham, &amp; discussed diocesan business with the Bishop of Jarrow.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Dibdin </hi><hi rend="italic">is reported to have made a speech yesterday on the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Revised Prayer Book</hi><hi rend="italic">. He magnifies the changes now proposed in the rubrick allowing continuous Reservation, and, indeed, does so so extravagantly as greatly to increase the probability that Anglo&#8211;Catholicks generally will vote against the Book. He may possibly make the Book more acceptable to the House of Commons by this exaggeration, and that consideration may be assumed to have determined him to speak. And probably Cantuar had approved beforehand of his doing so.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
