<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A heavily clouded sky with steadily falling rain gave ill promise for the day.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Master of the Temple left after breakfast. Ella and Fearne went off to fetch a puppy from Northumberland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>About 50 of the clergy whom I have ordained attended the reunion, of whom about 35 attended the Holy Communion at 11.30 a.m. After service followed lunch, &amp; then they went into the garden, &amp; walked in the Park until tea&#8211;time. The coldness of the weather made sauntering unpleasant, &amp; the sodden condition of the ground precluded games. After tea we had Evensong in the chapel, at which I gave an address, &amp; then they went away. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I gave everyone a copy of</hi><hi rend="underline"> 'The Book &amp; the Vote'</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Bishop of Jarrow &amp; I discussed appointments, and agreed upon a series of preferments.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Smith &amp; Miss Rait from Row arrived on a visit. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip Strong</hi><hi>, who is now Vicar of Christ Church, Leeds, stayed the night. I had some talk with him after dinner, and found him a good deal more reasonable in his opinions than I had expected. I wish we could have kept him in the diocese, &amp; I think he would probably have gained by a longer career as an assistant curate.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
