<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Although Gregory contributed but little to the Liturgy, and nothing at all to the sacred music and poetry of the Roman Church, there is yet one respect in which he greatly influenced the religious life of the city. He used the whole weight of his unrivalled authority to encourage popular veneration for the relics of the saints.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dudden</hi><hi> '</hi><hi rend="underline">Gregory the Great'</hi><hi>. Vol.1. p.276</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"Some thieves once broke into the garden of Isaac the Syrian, but found themselves compelled by a supernatural impulse to work hard at digging the whole of the night. In the morning the abbot came out, and, with a twinkle in his eye, said to the perspiring burglars: '</hi><hi rend="underline">Rejoice, my brothers: you have worked well: now take your rest</hi><hi>'. He then gave them some breakfast, &amp; sent them away with his blessing and a present of vegetables."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ibid. p.345.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This is a specimen good story from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">S. Gregory's</hi><hi> '</hi><hi rend="underline">Dialogues</hi><hi>'. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dudden</hi><hi> with good reason emphasises the paradox implicit in the fact that the author of this record of absurdities was also 'the highest ecclesiastical authority, and the keenest intellect of the age'.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.a.m. There were 9 communicants including John.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After breakfast I prepared an address, which I delivered to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Freemasons</hi><hi> at their service in the Chapel in the afternoon. There was a fair, but not large attendance. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ravensworth</hi><hi> read the lesson, &amp; afterwards had tea with some of the officers. I discussed the burning question, </hi><hi rend="underline">Is Freemasonary a Religion</hi><hi>?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> &amp; Miss Richards with the master of the Temple came to tea, &amp; the Master stayed the night. We walked in the Park, discussing this tiresome &amp; endless question of the Prayer book. He retailed the metropolitan gossip which was not particularly intelligent or well&#8211;informed. </hi><hi rend="italic">On the whole the gather that the general opinion inclines to take a favourable view of the parliamentary prospects of the Book. Mainly this is the result of a growing appreciation of the grave consequences which a second rejection must needs involve. The near approach of the General Election, which the most reluctant Government cannot avoid sometime in the course of next year, adds emphasis to the well&#8211;grounded fear, that the abhorred issue of Disestablishment would become a primary issue in the conflict.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
