<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major's</hi><hi> letter in the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Times</hi><hi> of yesterday under the heading "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; State. The ultimate authority</hi><hi>" is characteristic &amp; disconcerting. It is regrettable that he should be opposed by so inadequate a champion as Professor </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Goudge</hi><hi>. His last paragraph runs thus:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>["]Can we feel sure that the House of Commons possesses the Spirit in a less degree, or is less essentially Christian in character than the Church Assembly? The question I cannot answer with conviction, but I think we may rightly assume that the body which claims to have more of the Spirit almost certainly has less than the body which dare not make that claim".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Surely his thinking is confused. It is the old question of the validity of spiritual action by unworthy ministers appearing in another form. The validity of such action depends on Divine Commission not on human excellence. "</hi><hi rend="underline">We have the treasure in earthen vessels</hi><hi>". The House of Commons is not commissioned or qualified for the work of shaping Liturgies &amp; determining methods of Sacramental ministry. The Church Assembly, including Bishops, Clergy &amp; Laity in corporate action, is so commissioned &amp; qualified. The Spirit of God inspires right–thinking members of both for the performance of their several duties, but there are spheres delimited, &amp; functions which are incommunicable. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Norham</hi><hi>, and visited both the Castle and the Church, both most interesting. On the way we called on the Butlers, descendants of General [S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi>] Paul. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Butler</hi><hi> showed us divers portraits of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Josephine Butler, the patron–saint of all the Purity zealots. In Norham church we fell in with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Greens</hi><hi> from Hereford. They were staying with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Green's mother, the old lady, aged 92, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Askew Robertson</hi><hi>, concerning whom Lady Tankerville spoke to me. This ancient dame gave us tea, &amp; then showed us her pictures. The best thing she had was a little Velasquez. A billiard table made from the wood of the "Royal George" was curious. The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Greens</hi><hi> carried us to </hi><hi rend="underline">Ladykirk</hi><hi> in Scotland. This church was builded [sic] in 1500 by James IV of Scotland in fulfilment of a vow made when he crossed the flooded Tweed. It is a simple dignified building with transepts but no aisles. The Minister, a youngish–looking man more clerical in aspect than is common with the Presbyterian clergy, told me that he had heard me preach in S. Cuthbert's, Edinburgh, when </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Macgregor</hi><hi> held that charge, some 20 years ago, &amp; repeated the text of my sermon. This was creditable to him &amp; to me. I asked him how often the Holy Communion was administered in Ladykirk, &amp; he replied '</hi><hi rend="underline">Four times in the year. There is no desire for anything more</hi><hi>'. I noticed a curious iron frame, like a lamp–holder, attached to the body of the pulpit, &amp; was told that this served to hold the basin for Baptism.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[199] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>There was an elaborately carved chest with '</hi><hi rend="underline">S. Nicholas, Liverpool</hi><hi>' on the cover, &amp; many pious legends. Among them '</hi><hi rend="underline">God at his worst is better than the world at its best'</hi><hi>. It bore the date 1651. I inquired how it came to be there. I was told that it had been presented by a local laird. The extensive churchyard was planted with roses tc, and admirably kept. I noticed a few glass globes, &amp; was told that these horrors had now been prohibited, but the actually existing ones were irremovable, &amp; had to be left to the tender mercies of Time. The two churches on opposite banks of the Tweed, Norham &amp; Ladykirk, are of uncommon interest. The romantic beauty of their situation adds greatly to their singular attractiveness. We returned home through Coldstream and Cornhill, and arrived about 7.30 p. m. well–satisfied with our expedition.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I found a letter from </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Wynne–Willson</hi><hi> in which he says:– "</hi><hi rend="italic">I should like to express to you my feeling of devout thankfulness that the Diocese is to continue under your role, while at the same time I try to ne unselfish and regret that the Church is not to have your guidance as an Archbishop</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This is civilly expressed. Nevertheless, I anticipate a certain loss of prestige &amp; influence in the diocese.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
