<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Times </hi><hi>reported another aggressive pronouncement by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi><hi>. I was foolish enough to spend the morning in writing a letter to that journal in criticism of his Eminence.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I walked around the Park. Later, we motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Shotton</hi><hi> where I confirmed 100 persons. It was pleasant to see the males slightly preponderating over the females. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gadd</hi><hi>, the Rector of Burnmoor, offering him the living of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Thomas's, Bishopwearmouth, which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi><hi> is vacating in order to go to Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees. It is essential that the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Thomas's should be a preacher, for the congregation in that parish is gathered from a wide area by the attraction mainly of the pulpit. There are about 700 parishioners, mostly very poor people. Gadd is a popular windbag, but he has the reputation of being also a sympathetic visitor. The patron of Burnmoor is Lord Durham, &amp; the net value of the living is stated to be &#x00A3;500.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I sent copies of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi> to Canon Raven, Bishop Talbot, and Professor Davis.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather today has been pleasant, but tending to become cold as the day failed.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
