<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
<p><hi>The morning post brought a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Manchester</hi><hi> telling me that he had accepted appointment to the Archbishoprick of York. I wrote him a civil letter.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>So the chapter of "preferment" is definitely closed to me, and I must end my career, so far as the hierarchy goes, at my present position. The "Old Adam" in me would like to have had the chance of refusing a primacy, but obviously there is no substance in that "grievance". And I am startled at realizing that my contemporaries put me on one side as </hi><hi rend="underline">passé</hi><hi>. They may be right: I incline to think that they are: nevertheless it is alarming to have the fact so clearly affimed. But, indeed, apart from other considerations, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi>'s appointment to Canterbury at the age of 64, rendered it almost imperative that a younger man should be appointed to York. It would never do to have the two Sexagenarian primates doddering </hi><hi rend="underline">together</hi><hi> in a few years' time! </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><hi> have been very closely associated in the policy which carried the Enabling Act on to the Statute Book, &amp; they will work easily together.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>O Lord, my God, I humbly pray,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Give me Thy help throughout this day</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>To speak Thy Word, to know Thy will,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Thy sovereign purpose to fulfil.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>And bless, O Lord, my work to me,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>And those through whom I work for Thee.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Let not my fault Thy work betray,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Uphold my goings in Thy way;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>And when I have tried to do my best</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Give me Thy Light and welcome rest.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Bishop Stubbs. Written in 1897. (v. Letters ed. Hutton. p. 309)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We left the Castle at about 2.15 p. m., and motored to </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Wooler</hi><hi>, a distance of 72 miles, in about 3 hours. The maids, who preceded us yesterday, had prepared tea, &amp; we soon established ourselves in our temporary home. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is not without interest that this is the first occasion in the course of my life on which I have hired a house.</hi><hi> My holidays have all been taken abroad, or in visiting my friends. The first is too fatiguing, and the last too shackled for my years and 'cussedness'!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
