<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A glorious day in which it was really sinful to stay indoors. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi><hi> went off after breakfast, having found time to read &amp; vehemently to condemn the Report on Durham Castle!! He really is too, too aggravating. The truth is that he is constitutionally unable to approve any proposals which do not emanate from himself. It is a sad blot on an attractive character.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I completed the sermon for S. Nicholas, Durham. In the afternoon I walked round the Park, and had some talk with divers pit lads.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I had interviews with the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest Merryweather</hi><hi>, assistant curate of Brandon, who is to be licensed next week; and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">William Edmund Latimer</hi><hi>, who desired to be accepted as a candidate for Holy Orders. He is prepared to go to a Theological College for two years at his own charges, and he knows no Latin or Greek! Nevertheless I was well impressed by him &amp; consented to accept him as an Ordination Candidate. Indeed I agree with his complaint that the attempt to learn Latin &amp; Greek is no better than waste of time. At his age (31) and with two years at his disposal the time would certainly be used to better advantage.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
