<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Laws</hi><hi> came to say, Goodbye: and, like the fool that I am, I gave him &#x00A3;15, besides letting him have his wages to the end of the month. He has been in my service about 5 years, &amp; has certainly deteriorated. This deterioration I incline to attribute to two causes &#8211; his silly day&#8211;dreaming over his imaginary claim to Lauriston Castle, and his </hi><hi rend="bold underline">entire undoing by attendance at spiritualistic séances.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning on that tiresome Article for the B.E. After lunch </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi> came to see me, &amp; walked with me round the Park. He is an amiable &amp; good&#8211;looking youth, but whether he has brains adequate to a career, I am by no means assured. But he is not yet 18, and may develope.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> came back in good spirits: we went through the letters after dinner.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Modern Churchman</hi><hi rend="italic">" has a good many references to me, and all hostile. This sentence sets one thinking:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"To cite the institution of Christ, the practice of the Apostles, &amp; the tradition of the Catholic Church, as authoritative in the matter of admitting women to the ministry of the Church of England, seems to us to be quite reactionary." </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Well, well!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
