<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A doubtful morning, and much colder. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but five Communicants including John. Lionel was celebrating later at Stockton: so, though he was present and read the Epistle, he did not communicate.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I went to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spennymoor</hi><hi>, and preached at Mattins to a congregation largely composed of Freemasons. The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bates</hi><hi>, and his wife assured me that they were both healthy and happy in the parish. I pressed on him the vital importance of visiting the people in their homes. It is this part of parsonic duty which the modern parson so commonly neglects. He prefers to write in the Parish Magazine!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi>, addressing the letter to Winchester.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Sunderland, and had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi><hi>. His brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Plumptre</hi><hi>, from Toronto was there. Then I went to Southwick Parish Church, &amp; confirmed 83 persons. There was a large &amp; attentive congregation. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nigel Cornwall</hi><hi> acted as my Chaplain, &amp; carried the staff. There is much to be said for holding Confirmations on Sunday, but it is too inconvenient for every parish except the one in which the Confirmation takes place. After service I returned to Auckland, &amp; was comforted on the way by a rainbow.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
