<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Williams</hi><hi> of Jarrow Grange writes to accept nomination to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Thomas's, Sunderland. The patronage of Jarrow Grange is Lord Northbowere's.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi> contained a letter from the Bishop of Norwich on the Prayer Book Crisis, which induced me to waste the morning in a writing a reply.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Park was filled with crowds of people mostly young attracted by some kind of a "Temperance" demonstration. The fineness of the weather made it sufficiently delightful to move about in the open air, &amp; roll on the grass.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>'The decrees of the Council of Trent are written in a Latin which, for the purpose, could not wish improved. The theologians of the new scholasticism, such as Melchior, Cano, Canisius &amp; their successors, attached no small importance to a good Latin style. The surprising fact, therefore emerges that a tendency, which appeared for a long time to be given up to the worship of pagan ideals, &amp; which had not otherwise succeeded in creating any enduring works, now at last, in the service of the church, exercised an influence which has outlived the ages'</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Pastor. 'History of the Popes XVI, '29</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
