<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I received a letter from the Headmaster of Westminster thanking me for my "memorable &amp; most helpful Confirmation address". This pleases me because it comes from a man familiar with the conditions and problems of adolescence, &amp; I am always in doubt as to the worth &amp; suitableness of my addresses at confirmations. The particular address which I gave to the Westminster boys was substantially with that which I gave at Southwick on June 17</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi><hi rend="italic"> brought a party of 4 ladies to be confirmed in the chapel. After service they all had tea.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Leonard Wilson</hi><hi rend="italic">, the son of the Vicar of S. Edmund's in Gateshead, writes to me from Cairo, to sympathize with me over the rejection of the Revised Prayer Book. He goes on:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"I have read &amp; reread your book of Ordination Addresses &amp; find in them a stern incentive to self&#8211;discipline, &amp; a nobler interpretation of my Ordination vows than I had understood before. To read those changes is to be humbled &amp; to be shown how my own vows have been carelessly forsaken &amp; denied, to wish almost that I had never been ordained to so great a dignity &amp; such solemn service."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I think mainly I feel like that myself.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
