<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A brilliant morning, &amp; the air fresh, altogether beneficent to mind and body</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. I reflected that all my greatest predecessors died Bishops of Durham &#8211; Tunstall, Morton, Cosin, Butler, Lightfoot, Westcott. Why, then, should I wish to leave this great See? But do I wish it? I think, to be perfectly honest, that I desire the distinction of refusing a Primacy, and perhaps, I resent the loss of consequence which my being passed over must needs involve. The first is mere vanity: the last is probably slight &amp; transitory. It is humiliating that the unreal &amp; unwarranted chatter of newspapers &amp; ''Society'' should be able to affect one's mind. And when I turn my thoughts in another direction, &amp; consider not my possible ''preferment'', but my certain duty, how disgusting this concern about one shows against mu unconcern for the other! </hi><hi>'</hi><hi rend="underline">'Who can tell how of the offendeth? O cleanse Thou me from my secret faults. Keep thy servant also from presumptious sins lest they get the dominion over me: so shall I be undefiled &amp; innocent from the great offence. Let the words of my mouth, &amp; the meditation of my heart be always acceptable in thy sight, O Lord my strength &amp; my Redeemer</hi><hi>.''</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>There is nothing like the Psalms to put us right.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[162] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 14 communicants viz. our two guests, five of the household, the 4 Brydens, and ourselves. The Collect is wonderfully relevant to our actual situation, with its reference to God's "</hi><hi rend="underline">never&#8211;failing providence</hi><hi>" and its petition that God will "</hi><hi rend="underline">put away from us all hurtful things, &amp; give us those things which be profitable to us.</hi><hi>"</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">We discussed the American problems, Prohibition and Divorce, at breakfast with our American guests. They are opposed to both, but they do not perceive the gravity of either. The horrible mingle&#8211;mangle of family relationships which flows from the facility of divorce in America provides an endless series of comic &amp; "spicey" narratives, which relieve the dullness of American conversation, and disclose both the deadness of American conscience &amp; the poverty of American humour. Philistinism run to seed! Ella took the ladies to the morning service in the Cathedral, &amp; left me in peace.</hi><hi> I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>, &amp; sent him the Bishoprick, addressing my letter to Johannesburg. Also I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tony Chute</hi><hi>, who had sent me a very interesting letter, mentioning inter alia the astonishing &amp; perhaps unparalleled fact that in no less than 187 years, there had been only 3 Presidents of Magdalen. </hi> 
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[163] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"I think you will enjoy this gem which appeared in the Examination for 'Divvers', which I was put on to last term. We had asked the candidates to give examples of parables illustrating the growth of the Kingdom of God. One genius quoted amongst others, '</hi><hi rend="underline">the seed that grew secretly, and ended by covering the whole earth, thus illustrating the gradual contamination of all peoples by the persistent spreading o the word of God</hi><hi>'!"</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Rev: A. W. Chute. July 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and her American guests accompanied me when I motored to Wolsingham in order to preach at Evensong. There was a fair congregation considering the fineness of the weather, which made the country &amp; the open&#8211;air particularly alluring. I preached on the Apostolic Character of the Church, taking occasion to speak of the present crisis. The people listened with attention, but, I think, rather puzzled than edified. It is difficult to realize the slenderness of popular interest in ecclesiastical matters, &amp; the inability of most people to follow any kind of connected reasoning.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Page&#8211;Gourlay arrived during the afternoon, and stayed the night.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
