<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Warm, and rather sultry weather, &amp; the comfortless restlessness of a Bank holiday pervading everything.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I revised an old sermon for broadcasting from Newcastle on Trinity Sunday.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I wrote to Warr, the Minister of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Giles's, thanking him for his book on Principal Caird: and to William. </hi><hi rend="italic">Lomax arrived at 4 p.m., &amp; talked confusedly for more than an hour about the man M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Manners, whom he wants me to ordain with no better evidence for fitness than his own confident assurances. But I would not consent. He had tea, &amp; went away ruminating on the spiritual blindness of the Episcopate!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I wrote to Marsh bidding him call banns at the Holy Communion during the weeks that his Church, except the Chancel, is out of use for cleaning &amp; decorating.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Major Stafford, a Sapper from Catterick, came for the week&#8211;end &#8211; an inoffensive quiet little man who served right through the War in France, &amp; went unscathed through the Retreat to ??ions. He spoke with quiet contempt of the Americans.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather degenerated into rain as the night drew on, an ill promise for the holiday.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
