<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Rogation Sunday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Chancellor Smith</hi><hi> read the Epistle, &amp; ministered the Chalice. We numbered 9 communicants including our four guests.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning in writing a sermon for the evening.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi><hi> came to lunch. He was extremely pessimistic as to the prospects of the Prayer Book. The pressure of constituents on their members was, he thought, almost wholly against the Book.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Hamsteels</hi><hi>, and preached at Evensong. The little church was densely crowded, &amp; the atmosphere was deadly. There appeared to be no possibility of ventilation. The result was that I could not preach even tolerably, and my sermon, on which I had bestowed no inconsiderable pains, was a total failure. I called the attention of the parson &amp; churchwardens to the need for some system of ventilating the church, but they clearly thought I was making an unnecessary fuss! I returned to Auckland after the service, &amp; found that James Parker&#8211;Smith had retired to bed with a suspicion of bronchitis, and that D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Cecil M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Cullough was in attendance.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
