<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A most brilliant morning, though still cold. I packed my bags before descending to breakfast. We left Minehead at 9.25 a.m., and travelled to Darlington by way of Taunton, Bristol, Birmingham, Derby (where we changed) and York. We were met by Leng with the Nash car, &amp; so came home to Auckland Castle.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> I. Barwick, assistant&#8211;curate of S. Paul's, Hendon, has had a stroke, and died. I ordained him in 1924. He was one of three artisans, whom I accepted as candidates under special conditions. Another of the three, Crosby, has broken down, &amp; will be 'on the shelf' for an in definite period. This is certainly very discouraging. The loss of their service is bad enough: the bequest of penniless widows and orphans they almost always leave to the diocese, is perhaps worse. The strain of continuing responsibility seems to be greater that they can sustain. They come of an underfed ancestry &amp; have no physical stamina.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The pectoral crow presented to the diocese by Prebendary Clark Maxwell has arrived. I suppose I must wear it sometimes, though my natural task rejects these ornaments as trifling and, in the actual state of English opinion, probably also impolitic.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>George Nimmins writes from Port&#8211;Said where he has arrived on his homeward journey. He is beside himself with delight at the prospect of being at home again.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
