<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A warm heavy day, but threatening change. I frittered away the morning on writing letters. Molony, the assistant curate of Esh lunched here, &amp; afterwards talked with me. He is 38 years old, with rather a weak face, and talks much &amp; confidently. He declared that he was not an Anglo&#8211;Catholic, but that he went about his parish in a cassock which few reasonable clergymen would do. He is unmarried, and lives with his mother, who has a small income of her own. I told him that I would write to the Bishop of Manchester, who is the Patron of Esh, &amp; request that his name should be considered for appointment to the incumbency.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Later Lionel motored me to Ingleton, where I consecrated an addition to the parish churchyard. There was a small gathering of the parishioners, to whom I made a brief address.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and Fearne motored to Ripon, &amp; attended the Garden Party given by the Bishop of Ripon &amp; his sister.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I read through an extremely interesting little book, "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Russian Church since the Revolution</hi><hi>" by G. P. Fedoroff which was sent me by Athelstan Riley. It gives a painful impression of cunningly calculated hostility, which is having a considerable effect on the Russian People. I wrote to Riley.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
