<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel went with me to Darlington, where I took train for London. On arriving at King's Cross, I </hi><hi rend="bold underline">went to 21 Park Lane</hi><hi>, and, leaving my bags there, proceeded to the hair&#8211;dresser, &amp; was duly handled by him.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Then I had tea in the Athenaeum, where I fell in with the Archbishop of Canterbury, who seemed unusually vigourous and alert. He seemed resolute to carry the Revised Book again to Parliament. He says that the Bishop of Southwell asks leave to resign his bishoprick. His illness seems rather religious than physical, but very hopeless anyway. Then I walked to Westminster, &amp; made vain attempts to see </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Caröe</hi><hi rend="italic">. As I was crossing through S. Margaret's Churchyard I encountered </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was trembling all over, &amp; to my thinking looked woefully ill. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He thinks that the House of Commons will not reject the Prayer Book a second time.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I returned to the Athenaeum, and, after writing a few letters, dined there, having as my table&#8211;companion that old club&#8211;caterpillar, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Graves</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi> I walked back to Park Lane, and had a short conversation with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Scarbrough</hi><hi> before going to my room.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather has become quite mild, and, if the rain would hold off, would be pleasant enough. </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
