<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"After listening for some 14 hours to the debate in the House of Commons on the Prayer book Measure, the dominant impression left on my mood is the manifest incapacity of such an assembly to deal with the doctrinal issues involved"</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Father Woodlock</hi><hi> S.J. as reported in the Manchester Guardian. June 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi><hi> suggesting that the final business of the Church Assembly should be to pass resolutions repudiating the spiritual authority of the House of Commons, &amp; promising support to the Bishops. I do not suppose that his Grace will approve this course, nor am I at all confident that the Assembly </hi><hi rend="underline">would</hi><hi> pass such resolutions, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">for the clergy generally are getting frightened at the possibility of Disendowment, and the politicians are straining every nerve to hush up the tiresome business</hi><hi>! What I anticipate is the retirement of the Archbishop, &amp; a postponement of all action on the Prayer Book Crisis until his successor has had time to consider and formulate his policy. In effect, nothing at all will be done, and we shall drift on.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I motored to Sunderland, and, picking up </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi><hi> on the way, went to the Seamen's Institute where I dedicated the Church and preached the Sermon. Then followed a meeting in the Concert Hall presided over by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Luke Thompson</hi><hi>, one of the M.P.s for Sunderland. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He is himself a Wesleyan, but he voted for the Prayer Book, and expressed much disgust at the speeches against it. I had much talk with him afterwards. He is very anxious to discover some method of getting the Prayer Book out of the next Election</hi><hi>. He thinks that Lloyd George is but too eager to make a bid for Nonconformist support by including Disestablishment on the programme of the Liberal Party. I could not offer him much hope. A young Hercules, named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Capron</hi><hi>, 6 feet 3 inches in height, joined us. He aspires to be ordained in Advent to the assistant curacy of Ryhope.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We motored to West Rainton, where I collated the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Rodolphus Thomas Heselton</hi><hi> to the Rectory. I myself ordained him to the diaconate in 1924, and to the priesthood in 1925, so that he has been about three years in priest's orders. There was a large congregation, a very attentive congregation, and a reverent service. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
