<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A bright morning after the storm and rain of yesterday, but everything has a battered &amp; shipwrecked appearance.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but five communicants, including John.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel was taking the duty at Sacriston. I motored to Burnmoor, and preached at Mattins. The "Diamond Jubilee" of the parish church was being commemorated. There was a large congregation which nearly (but not quite) filled the building. Hugh Stobart read the first lesson, and a young man from the parish named Gray read the second. In the course of the service Lord Durham was prayed for by name, and I made an allusion to him in the sermon. Hugh Stobart told me that he had no adequate "will to live", and that this added much to the gravity of his illness. After the service, I returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Norman Sykes sent me a very interesting paper on Bishop Hoadly</hi><hi>. I wrote to thank him for his gift. Also I wrote to William.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The day, which had been doubtful, ended finely but became chilly, so that a fire was welcome.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
