<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I had a very interesting conversation in the Athenaeum yesterday afternoon with a very attractive &amp; rather distinguished looking Roman ecclesiastic, whose name (which I learned when we exchanged cards on parting) was the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> A. N. Gilbey, Mark Hall, Harlow. He told me that he was reading Theology in Rome. I asked what part of his work interested him most, &amp; he replied he was most concerned with doctrinal development. We talked of the present position of the Vatican. He said that the enormous sums contributed by America more than made up for the losses of the War through the impoverishment of Austria, Belgium, &amp; France. The single diocese of Chicago contributed greatly more than Great Britain in Peter's Pence. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi><hi> was friendly to the Church, but would tolerate no other associations than those of Fascisms. Thus the Boys' Scouts, which had been introduced generally into the Italian parishes, had been summarily dissolved. But the control of religious instruction in the schools had been restored to the Church. We parted with expressions of mutual esteem, &amp; the hope that we should extend our acquaintance in the future.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; received the Holy Communion in a side&#8211;chapel. The Celebrant was Canon Simpson, who though he read reverently, was so rapid that I could hardly keep pace with him.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Catherine went with me to the Temple, where we attended the morning service. The preacher was an American Bishop &#8211; an old man with a wonderful rush of words to the mouth, and so rapid an utterance that it was probably impossible for most of the congregation to understand what he said. He introduced all the trite things, quotes President Wilson and Rudyard Kipling, &amp; raced from China to Peru. It was the old&#8211;time extempore sermon belated and not first rate of its kind. The anthem was that moving composition of Wesley. "Thou shall keep him in perfect peace: whose mind is stayed on Thee". And before the sermon we sang the admirable hymn, "God moves in a mysterious way".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Blind unbelief is sure to err,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>And scan his work in vain,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>God is his own interpreter</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>And He will make it plain.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>There is an elemental strength in those times which is strangely convincing &amp; consoling. 'Verily, Thou are a God that hidest Thyself'.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[151] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The American bishop &#8211; lately of Chicago, &amp; now technically 'retired', though he told me that he had preached more than 200 sermons last year! &#8211; came to tea. He was full of stories &amp; personal gossip. He thought that Hoover was sure to get the Presidency. 'Al. Smith' was 'wet' in personal habit as well as political profession [being indeed a heavy drinker!] The Bishop himself had supported Prohibition, which, however, was a disaster. Beers &amp; light wines would have to be conceded. He said that New York which had been an Irish City, was now a Jewish City. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">An Irishman with 4 children informed his priest that he would never have a 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> child "What is this nonsense Pat,' said the priest sharply, 'have you will listening to that sinful talk about limiting families.' No, your Reverence,' replied the Irishman, 'but they tell me that 'ivry 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> child in New York is a Jew &amp; I'll have no Jews in my family'</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> After tea I walked to the Temple, &amp; talked with the Master. He is as futile and gossip&#8211;laden as usual. Then I attended the service in S. Paul's Cathedral, &amp; heard Ralph preach from the words, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Where two or three are gathered together, there am I in the midst of them</hi><hi>". There was a huge &amp; very attentive congregation.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
