<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The day has been completely wasted in writing letters. There was an exasperating, and very unfortunate error in the article on "Durham Castle" in the Times. A contribution of 1000 dollars appears as one of &#x00A3;10,000, unless, indeed (which I cannot think possible) the amount 'from the Dominions' came in after I had left London. In any case, the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi><hi> has helped me nobly.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I walked round the Park in the afternoon. There came to dine the Bishop of Gloucester and Miss Headlam, the Bishop of Gibraltar &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">re</hi><hi>. Hicks, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">a</hi><hi>Cullough &amp; the Vicar making, with the house party, a company of ten.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">My Ordination candidate, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Philip Innes</hi><hi rend="italic">, sends me the book which he has published. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Human Touch, Sunshine and Shadow in a Hospital</hi><hi rend="italic">." It is series of moving incidents which he has witnessed in the Hospital, &amp; which he records &amp; evidently "writes up". How much is fact, &amp; how much is commentary 'twere hard to say, but there is throughout the rather melodramatic sentimentalism of the popular press. These stories are the staple of Dissenting preaching, &amp; they provoke as much scepticism as interest. On the whole, I find them more disconcerting than helpful. They are so obviously designed to untie the purse&#8211;strings.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
