<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The post brought tidings of two deaths of parson's wives viz. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Lillingston &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Hayward. I wrote letters of condolence to both husbands, and also to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Bateman, the widow of my old butler, whose death was announced on Monday. One grave disadvantage of clerical matrimony is the necessity of taking account of the health of </hi><hi rend="underline">two</hi><hi> individuals in every parish. The range of possible disturbance extends with the emergence of the family. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lister</hi><hi>, Vicar of S. Stephen's, South Shields, writes to ask permission to seek an exchange, because his wife's health is "seriously affected by the strong sea air". He has only been 2 1/2 years in the place. How can any effective pastoral ministry be carried on thus? </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Heselton</hi><hi>, assistant curate of S. Mary's, Gateshead, writes to say that he will accept West Rainton.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fawkes,</hi><hi rend="italic"> who had told me that he was </hi><hi rend="italic underline">not</hi><hi rend="italic"> sending me his "Shall we disestablish?" because I shall not like it. He, as is natural in an ex&#8211;Papist, is a thorough going Erastian: he exults in the vote of the House of Commons: and regards Bishops with disgust mingled with fear.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After dinner </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur</hi><hi> (perhaps warmed into some semblance of civility by the assurance of our imminent departure) was even amiable, showing us his curios &amp; photographs, &amp; generally expanding. So we traversed the time until we retired to our rooms at 9.40 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
