<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Birmingham </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Women's Welfare Centre</hi><hi rend="italic"> states in its first annual report that the percentage of women known to be pregnant when married is no less than 33.3 per cent. This is an ugly side&#8211;light on British morals. Of course Birmingham may not be representative of the country as a whole. Probably it is representative of the industrial districts.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The newspapers announce the appointment of the Archbishop of York to the Archbishoprick of Canterbury</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> So yet another Scot sits on the chair of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Augustine. He is certainly an impressive primate to look at. The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic"> reproduces his last portrait, that by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir William Orpen</hi><hi rend="italic">, and of course the papers overflow with eulogies &amp; 'tributes'. What a bewildering thing we are looking at! Yesterday the proposals of the Archbishop were rejected with something like fervour. Today, their Graces are belauded as the best, the ablest, the wisest of men! '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Put not your trust in princes'</hi><hi rend="italic"> says the Psalmist. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Langs's</hi><hi rend="italic"> accession to the Primacy of All England has been so generally expected that it's actual announcement seems to matter little. How odd are the fortunes of men! He comes to his Throne in an evil time. Since </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cranmer's</hi><hi rend="italic"> accession was there ever a darker outlook for the Church of England?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote a brief letter of ''congratulations'' to the Archbishop, and then finished the sermon for tomorrow.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert Harding</hi><hi>, the rather emotional youth from Queen's Cambridge, who aspires in two years' time to be ordained in this diocese, came to lunch. He aspires to go at once to Mirfield, &amp; (as he is an applicant for a diocesan grant) desires me to approve that arrangement. I walked and talked with him for an hour. He is plausible, and almost sycophantic, &amp; certainly needs discipline. I doubt if he could be other than an 'Anglo&#8211;Catholick'. The only question is of the measure of his absurdities in that character. I reserved my decision, &amp; gave him a copy of '</hi><hi rend="underline">'Church &amp; Parson in England</hi><hi>''.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Two American ladies, the on a sister of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Toland and the other a 'flapper', came to spend the week&#8211;end. D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> McCullagh and his son, the Major, came to dinner, and we succeeded in passing the time amicably until the service in chapel, after which we dispersed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><hi rend="italic"> wrote to me suggesting that a list of contributors to the Durham Castle Fund should be sent to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> with their Majesties' names at the head of it. I forwarded the suggestion to the Hon. Treasurer in Newcastle.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
