<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[164]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The American ladies took their departure. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pearson</hi><hi>, assistant&#8211;curate of Felling, offering him nomination to the living of Firtree.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Also, I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tindal</hi><hi>, assistant curate of Monkwearmouth, offering him nomination to the parish of Stanley by Crook.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Also, I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Beaglehole</hi><hi>, assistant&#8211;curate of Consett, proposing that he should undertake the charge of the district which has been cut out of Dunston, &amp; suggesting that, if he were willing to do this, he should forthwith get into touch with the Vicar of Dunston.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> motored to Durham where I discussed diocesan business with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Jarrow</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">He has returned from the south where </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he finds the notion persistent that I am to be Archbishop of York:</hi><hi rend="italic"> but I convinced him that it was highly improbable that the offer of the Archbishoprick could be made to me, &amp; that, if it were, it was highly improbable that I should accept it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He thinks that only my attitude on the Establishment prevented my being considered for Canterbury:</hi><hi rend="italic"> but I cannot believe that there was ever any serious likelihood of that.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Page&#8211;Gourlay was selected as the Conservative Candidate for this division. He could hardly be an ideal candidate in any circumstances, but here, where the Labour majority is enormous, it matters little under what figure&#8211;head the Conservatives advance to annihilation. Sybil, Lady Eden, came to dine. I am not pleased at the association of Auckland Castle with the Conservative party in the popular mind.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>If a total lack of interest in one's books be an indication that it is time to leave them, and a disgust with all one's normal employments be an evidence of one's incompetence to perform them with normal efficiency, then I ought to leave my books and retire from my ordinary work. But I am hardly free to be frankly idle. The undertakings to which I am pledged in the autumn can only be carried through if I prepare myself in advance. There are especially the following.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>1. The Church Congress. Sermon and Paper. October 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>2. S. Chad's. Dedication. Sermon. Oct 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>3. Address Clerical Society at Saltburn. Oct. 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>4. Preach to Doctors at Manchester Cathedral. Oct. 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>5. Address Mass Meeting at Bristol. Oct. 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>6. Preach All Souls College. November 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>7. Preach at S. Mary's, Oxford, &amp; in New College. Nov. 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>8. Visitation Charge. Nov. 21</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> &amp; 22</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
