<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The rain continues, &amp; the country has a bedraggled, sodden look, infinitely depressing as if arranged for some great calamity.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The ceiling of that Citadel of Dissent, the Central Hall, Westminster, fell on a crowd dispersing from a meeting. One was killed, &amp; seven injured. This melancholy episode fits in admirably with the ominous suggestions of the time. The Prayer Book Debate was proceeding in the House of Commons when this disaster befell the sectaries.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After lunch Lionel and I motored to High Force. The waterfall was very impressive, but less so than I had expected. The great central rock stood out gauntly between the two falls. In a first&#8211;class exhibition this rock is said to be completely submerged. After having tea in the Hotel, we returned to the Castle. The journey took just under the hour.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to S. Helen's, West Auckland, and preached at the dedication of a Rood Beam &amp; a re&#8211;created Organ. There was a large congregation. Sir John Priestman presided at the Organ, &amp; gave a recital thereon after the dedication service had ended, but I did not think it necessary to stay for this, &amp; returned forthwith to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>What is the frantic frenzy, scorn'd so much,<lb/>And dreaded more than a contagious touch?<lb/>I grant it dangerous, and approve your fear,<lb/>That fire is catching, if you draw too near;<lb/>But sage observers oft mistake the flame,<lb/>And give true piety that odious name.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>&#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; &#8211; </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="underline">But that disease, when soberly defined</hi><hi>,</hi><hi rend="underline">
               <lb/>Is the false fire of an o'erheated mind</hi><hi>;<lb/>
            </hi><hi rend="underline">It views the truth with a distorted eye</hi><hi>,<lb/>
            </hi><hi rend="underline">And either warps or lays it useless by</hi><hi>;<lb/>
            </hi><hi rend="underline">'Tis narrow, selfish, arrogant, and draws</hi>
            <lb/>
<hi rend="underline">Its sordid nourishment from man's applause</hi><hi>;<lb/>
            </hi><hi rend="underline">And, while at heart sin unrelinquish'd lies</hi><hi>,<lb/>
            </hi><hi rend="underline">Presumes itself chief favourite of the skies</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cowper</hi><hi>. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Conversation</hi><hi>'</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">There is a 'fanatic frenzy' enough and to spare in the Protestant opposition to the Revised Prayer Book. Bands of zealots, whose ardour is kept at fever heat by suitable oratory, are employed in continuous prayer for the victory of their cause, while the debate proceeds in the House of Commons. In the XX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century we are witnessing an orgy of fanaticism which would have been natural in the XVIII.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
