<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The newspaper cartoon may well give me the subject of my sermon in Newcastle Cathedral on Trinity Sunday, a sermon which would serve as my answer to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Keith's</hi><hi rend="italic"> profession of unbelief. Humanity is blind–folded, that is, reduced by external action either her own or another's, to an incapacitating blindness. Deprived of her true organ of direction (i.e. the eye), she is solely dependent on what she can hear, &amp; that organ brings two voices, neither of which is satisfying, though neither when carefully considered is prohibitive of satisfaction. For their respective messages must be slightly expanded in order to convey their meaning. Instead of "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Science: we offer no hope</hi><hi rend="italic">", it should run, '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Science: on the line of our researches we offer no hope</hi><hi rend="italic">': and instead of '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Religion: we offer no proof</hi><hi rend="italic">', it should run: '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Religion: on the line of your researches we offer no proof</hi><hi rend="italic">', or, perhaps, '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">on the line of our researches we can give </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">you</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> no proof'</hi><hi rend="italic">. Meanwhile, the only ultimate authority, which can provide both hope &amp; proof, is left unheeded. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Spirit of man is the Candle of the Lord</hi><hi rend="italic">". "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">We know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we know him that is true, &amp; we are in him that is true, even in his Son, Jesus Christ</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 10 communicants including Harry Leng &amp; George N. The morning was occupied by preparing a sermon for use at Easington. These continuing 'preachments' destroy one's competence for all really good work. My work was interrupted by the arrival of the photographer who came to show me the pictures he had taken last week. They appear to be more successful than usual.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">The papers report the death of Sir Edmond Gosse,<persName xml:id="2083"></persName> a vain gossiping man &amp; an incorrigible tuft hunter, but endowed with a genuine gift for literature &amp; literary criticism.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>George Nimmins took his leave. He is a good type of young Englishmen, very true to the ultimate loyalties. Lionel motored me to Durham, where I attended a meeting of the Durham Castle Fund Committee: and then went on with me to Easington Colliery, where I preached in the temporary church, and then cut the first sod on the site of the new one. A considerable crowd of miners &amp; their families witnessed the ceremony with, as it seemed to me, more curiosity than understanding. After talking to scouts, girl–guides, &amp; being presented with a silver spade by the Churchwardens, I returned to the Castle, where we arrived at 9.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
