<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We left the Vicarage about 10 a.m., and motored to Longtown by way of Coldstream &amp; Hawick. On the way we were held up by sheep, &amp; by a puncture caused by the broken glass of one of the front&#8211;lamps, which fell off &amp; splintered under the car. We reached Longtown about 1.30 p.m., &amp; were there joined by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Murray, &amp; Eleanor with their party, Colonel &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Crawford, with their son &amp; daughter, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>D. Durie. We drove at once to </hi><hi rend="underline">Lanercost Priory</hi><hi>, &amp; there lunched from our baskets in the refectory. The nave of the Augustinian Church has been adapted or use as a parish church, &amp; the ruined chancel and transepts contain the tombs of the Dacres, who merged in the Howards. From Lanercost we went on to </hi><hi rend="underline">Naworth Castle</hi><hi>. The Carlisles were shooting, but the 'seneschal' (a courteous elderly gentleman who had a considerable interest in me!) showed us the Hall &amp; Dacre Tower. Naworth is truly a gem of feudal pride &amp; splendour. Here our party separated. We made our way via Gilsland to Bewcastle, over a bad &amp; winding road. We were rewarded by the spectacle of the famous </hi><hi rend="underline">Bewcastle Cross</hi><hi>, standing erect in the Churchyard. It is dated 680 A. D. Then we went home over the moors to Jedburgh, and finally arrived at the Vicarage a few minutes after 9 p.m., having travelled 187 miles. The weather, though sometimes doubtful, was generally fine.</hi>
         
      </body>
   </text></TEI>
