<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I worked at my article for the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi>", which I want to make important. Probably, if I were a wiser man with a more adequate concern for my own interests &amp; reputation, I should "leave well alone", but being the whimsical jackass that I am, I propose to write some candid words on the situation. So I worked at the foolish things until I had finished it. Before sending it off, however, I read it over to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi>, and at his suggestion (though against my own judgment) cut out a glittering phrase, which was not even original!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi> lunched with me, &amp; walked with me in the Park. He raised the question of Ordination, &amp; said that he had been thinking of it, though his mind (he is but 18) was not made up. I could not but say that it would please me greatly if he were ordained, 'though I wished him to come to a decision apart from any wish of mine. He is certainly being developed by Oxford, I hope wholesomely. He took off Coulton's 'Reformation and Art'. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather today has been quite detestable, chilly and gusty. I was chagrined to see clouds of red dust blown from the drive into the garden, thus disallowing my comfortable belief that the ash had bound into so firm a surface as to be proof against the winds.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
