<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I received pleasant letters from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi>. The latter writes enthusiastically of the delights of Oxford. He also encloses three small bills, which, he tells me, form his entire indebtedness! So far certainly he has shown no disposition to extravagance: but he is very young &amp; Oxford is very seductive. I sent him a cheque.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. D. R. Evans</hi><hi>, Vicar of Coxhoe, came to see me by my appointment. He is reported to have transgressed my rule about Lay readers preaching in parish churches when the clergy are present. He pleaded a tendency to quinsies!! I was nowise sympathetic, &amp; finally he "gave me his word" (a Welshman's) that the offence should not be repeated.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Morris Young</hi><hi>, Vicar of New Shildon, came to ask permission to employ Llewelyn as his assistant curate. I consented though the said L. will not complete two years since his Ordination before September, but I said he must give the legal notice to his present chief. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Morris Young</hi><hi> had tea.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Thornley, where I confirmed 120 persons, of whom no more than 25 were males. They came from Wingate, Wheatley Hill and Thornley. The service was reverent &amp; hearty, but the clergy are dismal, dejected and decrepit!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
