<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Birmingham</hi><hi rend="italic"> is reported to have made a vehement onslaught on the New Prayer Book, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">gone out of his way to attack the Bishop fo Durham</hi><hi rend="italic">! If it were worth while to reply, much pretty controversial play might be made out of an examination of the Episcopal Opposition &#8211; Norwich, Birmingham, Truro, Exeter, Worcester, &amp; Bishop Knox, no two of them are in agreement. But the less said the better, &amp; the spectacle of bishops in open conflict is not edifying.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I left the Castle at 10.30 a.m., and motored to York, where I lunched with Rotarians in the De Grey Rooms. After a very bad lunch I spoke to them for half an hour on Durham Castle. Then I returned to Auckland, arriving about 5 p.m. only to leave again at 6 p.m. in order to motor to Quarrington where I confirmed 69 persons from the 3 parishes of Coxhoe, Kelloe, &amp; Cassop cum Quarrington, with a combined population of nearly 10,000. These are all mining parishes: the pits are old, &amp; many have been closed. I inquired whether the pitmen were moving away, &amp; was told that they were beginning to do so. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Chancellor Smith &amp; James Parker Smith with his wife arrived.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
