<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Veneker, who has just returned from America, &amp; has strong views about cementation. He, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Peale, &amp; that infallible mischief–maker, Blackitt, have evidently formed a corner, &amp; may give trouble. Then I fell into conversation with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Blanesborough</hi><hi>, who expressed his hope &amp; expectation that I should go to York. I told him that rumour, which I believed to be well–grounded had already arranged otherwise, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; that in any case, I should not accept preferment without stipulating for a 'free hand' on the question of Establishment. He was evidently rather startled by this; &amp; entered on an energetic defence of what he understood to be the Constitutional relation of Church &amp; State under the Enabling Act</hi><hi>. But I pointed out to him some aspects which he had ignored, &amp; showed him how little prospect there really was of the Establishment lasting much longer. Would it not be better for the Church to insist on clearing up the principles of its Establishment here &amp; now, when clearly spiritual issues have been raised than to await the advent of a "Labour Government" when the conflict with the State would probably break out over intolerable abuse of the Crown Patronage.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[153] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">The meeting in the Mansion House was well–attended, and, so far, must be judged to have been successful</hi><hi>. The Lord Mayor read out, almost without alteration of a word, the "suggestions" which I had sent him for his opening speech! Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi><hi> spoke well, &amp; I followed. Probably I was better heard than anybody else, at least several persons assured me that it was so. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> spoke well, but less effectively than I had expected. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Goodenough</hi><hi>, a City magnate, proposed, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Nicholas Grattan–Doyle</hi><hi> M.P. seconded a vote of thanks to the Lord Mayor. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Justice Roche</hi><hi></hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="5462"></persName> gave an account of the finances. After tea with the Lord Mayor, I came away, picked up my bags as the Deanery, &amp; went to King's Cross, where I caught the 5.30 p.m. express. The journey was relieved by conversation with my compagnon de voyage, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lieut. Commander E. R. Micklam</hi><hi>, who told me that he had just been appointed manager of the armament works of Vickers–Armstrong L</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> in Newcastle, where he would have some 5000 men under him. He had received a house – Wylam Hall, Wylam–on–Tyne – where he &amp; his wife would live. I was very favourably impressed with him. At Darlington Lionel met me with his car, &amp; drove me home. We were back at the Castle shortly after 10.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
