<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote letters including a "Collins" to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi>. Then I prepared notes for the afternoon. After lunch I went into Durham, and admitted to their office a number of lay&#8211;readers in the Cathedral. I gave an address to the lay&#8211;readers, of whom more than a hundred were present. Then I went to S. Mary's College, where 170 under&#8211;graduates (mainly female) from Canada were having tea. The Secretary said that she remembered my addressing the Canadian Club in Winnipeg in 1912 &#8211; 15 years ago. After addressing this company, I returned to the lay&#8211;readers, and spoke to them for 45 minutes on the situation in the Church created by the rejection of the Revised Prayer Book. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I took the precaution of excluding reporters, &amp; then expressed myself with considerable freedom.</hi><hi> Then Lionel and I returned to Auckland, where I found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aubrey Pike</hi><hi>, an ordination candidate from Cuddesdon, had arrived. He seemed a pleasant youth, &amp; we walked in the grounds for an hour, before dinner. I presented him with a copy of "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; Parson in England</hi><hi>", as I thought he would there best learn the point of view from which I regard the Ministry, and how, if he should be ordained in this diocese, he would be expected to behave himself. </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
