<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I left Park Lane after breakfast, &amp; went to the Athenaeum, where I found Lord </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Northbourne</hi><hi rend="italic">, who spoke to me about the vacancy at Jarrow Grange. Then I went to King's Cross, &amp; took the Pullman express to Darlington, where I was met by Ella with the car. I relieved the tedium of the journey by reading "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Through the Looking Glass of Lambeth</hi><hi rend="italic">" by "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">An unknown Layman</hi><hi rend="italic">". The writer allows himself in all sorts of impertinences about individuals. Its references to me are particularly offensive for, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">inter alia</hi><hi rend="italic">, it attributes to me the description of the Evangelical Party as "an army of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">degenerates</hi><hi rend="italic"> generalled by octogenarians", whereas my word was '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">illiterates</hi><hi rend="italic">', &amp;, so far from adopting the description, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I said that it was only true if a sharp distinction were drawn between the Evangelical Party and the Evangelicals</hi><hi rend="italic">. The naming of possible successors to the Archbishop is extraordinarily annoying. The young Pullman Car attendant who put out my bags at Darlington, said to me. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"Are you going to succeed the Archbishop of Canterbury, my Lord?</hi><hi rend="italic">'! </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">James Parker&#8211;Smith</hi><hi rend="italic">, who ought to know better, writes to entreat me not to say anything which would hinder my appointment to Canterbury!! I feel disposed to do something really extravagant. </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
