<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Briggs</hi><hi>, the Vicar of Hunwick, came to tell me that the health of his wife &amp; youngest child suffered so much from the harshness of the climate &amp; the dampness of the Vicarage house, that he must have a change of benefice!! Another winter would be fatal! The clergy &amp; their wives appear to be strangely delicate creatures.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Meade Faulkner</hi><hi> came to see me in the afternoon, &amp; talked for an hour. He is certainly very ill, &amp; he told me that he was 70 years old. Our conversation took an unusually intimate tone, &amp; I asked him why, though a most regular attendant at the Cathedral services, he </hi><hi rend="underline">never</hi><hi> received the Holy Communion. He replied with a confession of a vague, almost pantheistic sacramentalism. He disclaimed any disposition to join the Roman Catholic Church, with which he acknowledges much sympathy. But the Pope is more than he can stand. I was impressed by the seriousness with which he spoke of himself and of his religious convictions, if indeed that word may be used of such nebulous opinions as he professed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> &amp; I motored to Sherburn where I confirmed 73 persons. The weather was cold &amp; stormy: our car was open, &amp; rain had started to fall before we regained the Castle after service.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
