<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <
<p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Another letter from Lady Scarbrough urged me to preach at Chester–le–Street next Sunday morning when the Duke &amp; Duchess of York were to attend the service in Chester–le–Street parish church. So I sent a telegram to the Rector asking if it would be convenient for me to do this, &amp; on receiving his affirmative reply, I wrote to Lady S. consenting to her request. I decided to repeat the sermon about Childhood which I preached in S. Gabriel's on Sunday night.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halsbury</hi><hi> thanking him for his novel, "1944", which describes very realistically the destruction of London by poison gas, discharged from aeroplanes. He raised a discussion on the subject in the House of Lords last night.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I walked round the Park during the afternoon. An American clergyman, the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Warren M. Way, Rector of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Mary's School, Raleigh, with his daughter, called on me with a letter of introduction from Bishop Cheshire. They stayed to lunch, &amp; were shown over the Castle. They were rushing through Europe in a few weeks &amp; will carry back a queer mingle–mangle of disconnected reminiscences. They had 'done' Oxford in two hours! and were on their way to Rome!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
