<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A dull wet day with a falling thermometer. I started on a sermon for S. Nicholas, Durham After lunch I motored to Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Lay Helpers' Association. The I returned to Auckland, whence a little later I went forth again taking Lionel with me, &amp; motored to Usworth, where I confirmed 130 persons, of whom no more than 30 at the most were males, presented from the two parishes of Usworth and Eighton Banks. Of which the first has 8300 and the last 4764 inhabitants. The two incumbents are among the least satisfactory in the diocese. Begg, who was ordained as long ago as 1888, has been 33 years in Usworth, and Bailey whom I myself appointed to Eighton Banks in 1824, is an eccentric &amp; decrepit though by no means aged person. Both are without interest in their work, or reasonable industry. I commented on the number of women who presented for Confirmation. 'Yes' said Begg,'they came of their own accord; a kind of wave passed over the parish.' I inquired if there was a 'Mothers' Union' or any association for their spiritual help. 'No', he replied, 'my wife hasn't the time for it!!' The truth being that both he and his wife prefer to make money by teaching in Newcastle. The wonder is that the people are so constant in their loyalty to the Church.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
