<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
<p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote an address to the Churchwardens of the Diocese, and then motored to Durham with the Chancellor, &amp; delivered it in the Galilee, to a considerable gathering.</hi><hi> We had previously lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi><hi> in the County Club. I spoke about the serious situation which could not but be created by the action of the House of Commons, &amp; emphasized their duty as Church officials to exhibit &amp; encourage loyalty to the Church of England in the matter of the Revised Prayer Book. A reporter carried away my M.S. Then I motored to Houghton&#8211;le Spring, &amp; left Lionel at the Rectory, myself returning to Auckland. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="underline">William</hi><hi>. It is nearly four years since he went to South Africa, and our fortnightly letters have been regularly exchanged.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We had a small dinner party _ Colonel &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Headlam</hi><hi>, Professor &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Masson, James &amp; Maimie, Lady Eden &amp; Colonel Headlam's secretary, the Chancellor&amp; Fearne, &amp; ourselves &#8211; 12 altogether.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Colonel Headlam is very pessimistic as to the prospects of the Prayer Book in the House of Commons. He says that he knows several members who voted for the Book last ime, and now declare their intention of voting against the Book.</hi><hi> If this is indeed the case, the the prospect of the vote of the House being reversed is slight.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
