<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A most glorious summer day, just such a a day as that on which I myself was ordained to the diaconate in Cuddesdon Parish Church on June 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1887. How little then I realized what ordination would involve! How unsuspected was the course which should bring me to this place and function! May God forgive me the faults, failures, and blunders of my ministry!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I thought it well to write to Lord Londonderry with reference to the suggested visit of the King to Durham Castle when he comes to Newcastle in October for the opening of the new Bridge. Last night Major Orr&#8211;Ewing &amp; Jones the architect waited on me in a state of considerable excitement with reference to this matter, &amp; I rashly (being in haste &amp; on the point of leaving for Durham) made some propositions, which on reflection I reckon to be temerarious. They had a telegram from the Marquis, which indicated that he was in communication with Lord Stamfordham on the subject, &amp; that the notion of a visit was being entertained. It would be a horrible nuisance, &amp; breed a thousand resentments: but it might help forward the Castle Preservation Fund, which now languishes woefully.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Durham, and was at the Cathedral in good time. The Ordination was carried through without any untoward incidents. Canon Richards was the preacher. His sermon was able &amp; well delivered, but perhaps too polemical for the occasion. He took up his parable against the Papists. There were more communicants than usual. After service I called on J. G. Wilson, and then lunched at the Deanery. I attended in the Cathedral at Evensong, &amp; pronounced the Benediction from the Throne: but I was woefully sleepy. After having tea with the Bishop of Jarrow, I motored to Newcastle, and preached to a large congregation at Evensong. After service I delivered a short sermon to be broadcast. Then I returned to Auckland, very tired.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Somebody sent me last week a newspaper cutting, containing a short letter signed "Surprised", &amp; headed 'Mowing the Lawns at Bishopthorpe. The writer says:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"The hum &amp; rattle of a lawn&#8211;mower at work attracted considerable attention from passsers&#8211;by at Bishopthorpe Palace this afternoon (Sunday). Through the trees a workman c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> plainly be seen pushing a lawn&#8211;mower, working most assiduously." The date is May 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1928, and the </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>writer was evidently shocked. If his eyes did not deceive him, I think he was justified.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
