<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lang spoke last night with extraordinary self–possession (possession), brilliancy, and wit. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I have never heard him to better advantage. Perhaps, (this is always his fault) he was a little too long, and, perhaps, his manner was a little too pompous: but it was none the less an amazingly able &amp; successful speech. I reflected sadly that it would be quite beyond my power to make a speech anything like as good. Some years ago, at Curzon's request, I did propose the scene toast, &amp; I remember how careful was my preparation, how dull &amp; stilted my performance, how slight my success. And Curzon <hi rend="bold">[</hi>had the dubious taste to<hi rend="bold">]</hi> described me to the company as the ecclesiastical counterpart of Lloyd George! After my speech in the House of Lords on December 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, I was freely likened to Lord Birkenhead as an orator!. Of course the common element in these comparisons is that I share with both those distinguished <hi rend="bold">[</hi>notorious<hi rend="bold">]</hi> politicians the quality of being a man <hi rend="bold">[</hi></hi><hi rend="underline">horus homo</hi><hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>, who comes on the public scene with no advantages of birth or fortune. But I have no such gifts as either the Welsh politician or the English lawyer: and, when I review my scanty powers &amp; scantier achievements, I marvel that they can so impress (impress) my contemporaries as to suggest such comparisons, &amp; secure for them such a measure of acceptance. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[13] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I lunched at the Windham Club in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> James's Square with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bunnell Burton</hi><hi>. He is a keen member of the Church Assembly (Assembly), &amp; one of those in charge of the revised P.B. Measure. I attended the meeting of the Assembly (Assembly). The Archbishop introduce the Measure in a neat little speech, &amp; then a series of members declaimed the most appalling drivel until 5.15 p.m. I seceded for tea at 4 p.m. with the Bishop of E. &amp; I. and then I had an interview with an Ordination candidate named Harding. Then I called on Caröe, who has just returned from Palestine &amp; Cyprus. Of the latter he speaks with enthusiasm. I asked him again to report on the dilapidations for Auckland Castle, which must be done again in October. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I had some talk with the Bishop of Liverpool, who expressed entire disapproval of Raven's agitation for the Ordination of Women. Then I walked to the Athenaeum, and dined there, having as my table–companions the Bishop of Gloucester and Portsmouth. After dinner I walked back to Park Lane. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather today has been almost oppressively (oppressively) hot. I was surprised to see that the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, whole reporting the Prime Minister's speech at the Mansion House in full, gave no report at all of the speech of the Archbishop of York. </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
