<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In England, where so many monasteries lived on as cathedrals, and the parish churches have been comparatively respected, we have still perhaps a quarter of what was standing in 1530, especially if we count the fragments: for instance a single bay of a cloister often enables us to judge of the rest. In France &amp; Italy, a larger proportion of medieval work has perished, &amp; more, perhaps, by rebuilding than by revolution.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Coulton</hi><hi> l.e. 480</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Miss Maude had an interview with me with respect to my decision that she must limit her public work as Organizing Secretary of the Preventive &amp; Rescue Association to her own sex. I was monstrously bland, but insisted that there must be no more meetings for Men &amp; Boys, &amp; she promised obedience: but she is obsessed in the usual way with "sex problems", &amp; can probably no more keep her tongue off them than I can avoid gibing at Feminism! I believe Christian Morality would gain if all these fantastical societies which champion it in fragments were done away.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[36] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>George Nimmins came with us to Sunderland, where I confirmed about 100 persons in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Stephen's, Ayre's Quay. The Vicar, (Rev. E. Yates Moore) is evidently 'making good' in a very difficult situation. He tells me that unemployment is again beginning to blight the parish. There was no real recovery of the ship&#8211;building industry, only a brief interlude of activity.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Jackson of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's brought candidates. He looked very tired. He has been fourteen years in his slum parish, &amp; has worked heroically. His strongly accentuated Anglo&#8211;Catholicism makes it difficult to transfer him, but I would gladly give him preferment if I could.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>When I arrived in the Castle, I found the old Chancellor in an ill state. His exertions combined with the cutting wind had been too much for him. He is 83 and as vigourous as a young man: but there is no cheating Time.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Evening paper has a rather suggestive picture suggested by Sir Arthur Keith's denial of the survival of the soul after death. It is called 'Humanity's Guide' &amp; represents a blindfolded woman groping along a wall marked by a Note of Interrogation, while a Professor &amp; a Parson severally proclaim that there is 'No hope', and 'No proof'.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
