<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[']Our English Churches, in spite of all ravages, contain probably twice as much medieval stained glass as there is in all the churches of Italy; &amp; I am told that Spain is not much better in that respect.[']</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Coulton</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="underline">Art &amp; the Reformation</hi><hi>. p450</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The chapter 'Renaissance &amp; Destruction' in Coulton's book contains much information which to me was both astonishing &amp; novel. I had not realized the shameless Vandalism of the Middle Ages, nor the extent of the destruction wrought by the Renaissance on classical and medieval monuments.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Jame &amp; Maimie left after breakfast. I frittered away the morning very uselessly: in the afternoon I walked round the Park with George Nimmins, &amp; later took him with me to Roker, where I confirmed 79 persons.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The newspapers publish a correspondence between the Bishop of London, &amp; 'Jix', in which, of course, the latter scores. Bishop Knox has a correspondence with the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Alban's, and makes him look very foolish. Certainly 'the stars in their courses' are fighting against us!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
