<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the review of Shadwell's<persName xml:id="30"></persName> book, and sent it to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>. Hardly had I done so before the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> arrived, and, somewhat to my surprise, included a long review of the same book by no less a person than <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord D'Abernon. </hi>It seems rather superfluous that another review, by an inferior authority, should appear. I suspect that there has been some change of plans since The Editor asked me to review the book.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park, and watched the splitting up of a great beech&#8211;tree.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and his wife arrived after dinner. They are apparently in great health and spirit. May they retain both in the formidable new sphere in which they are entering!</p>
         <p>The publishers inform me that they have sent copies of my book to all the members of the house of Laity, and no doubt the fact will have full expression on their account. But no word of thanks or criticism has reached me from anybody, &amp; this is hardly consistent with the copies having been received. No mention of the book is made in any of the publishing sheets, so that its appearance can hardly be known to anybody. If it were otherwise, I doubt if it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> make much difference so long as the public mind is filled with the squalid yet absorbing excitement of the General Election.</p></body></text></TEI>