<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Grant, we beseech thee, merciful Lord, to thy faithful people pardon and peace, that they may be cleansed from all their sins, &amp; serve thee with a quiet mind; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>We motored into Durham, and attended the morning service in the Cathedral. I had already celebrated in my chapel, &amp; all my party had communicated, so we did not wait for the late celebration. The Bishop of Carlisle preached in the interest of C.E.T.S.<orgName xml:id="188"></orgName> He has a good voice, but he does not manage it well. <hi rend="bold underline">His sermon was extemporaneous, &amp; exhibited the familiar defects of that kind of preaching, being verbose, incoherent, &amp; ill&#8211;arranged. But he said some true things, &amp; avoided some pitfalls into which Temperance orators commonly fall</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After service we lunched in the Deanery, &amp; then attended Evensong in the Cathedral. I returned to Auckland, and finished Pullan's Bampton Lectures. They are able, interesting, and sophistical. <hi rend="bold underline">Lord Astor arrived about 9 p.m.</hi> He is a well&#8211;set&#8211;up youngish man, with a frank manner and a ready tongue. He disclaimed advocacy of Prohibition, but ardently advocated State control of the trade in alcohol. I was distinctly pleased with him.</p></body></text></TEI>