<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I called at the famous house in Albemarle Street, and was shown the Byron MSS.</hi> They are extraordinarily full of interest. <hi rend="bold underline">Byron wrote freely, &amp; corrected incessantly.</hi> His proofs were always subjected to revision by Hobhouse &amp; Griffith: &amp; then sent to him. <hi rend="bold underline">The five successive revisions of the Giaour nearly trebled the size of the poem</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He was curiously careful to note the number of lines that he had written. I was much interested in the portraits of eminent literary men, in the room where they gathered so often for work and conviviality, on the fire&#8211;place in which the Memoir was consumed, in many personal relics which fill the cases. <hi rend="bold underline">The Byron MSS were lent to the Laipsic Exhibition just before the War, and were insured by the German authorities for &#x00A3;9000.</hi> For some years <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Murray</hi> heard nothing of their fate, &amp; had resigned himself to their loss. But they eventually were returned without injury.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Marriage of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hon: G. Phillimore </hi><hi rend="italic">with an "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">innocent divorcee</hi><hi rend="italic">" in S. John's Westminster.</hi></p>
         <p>I returned to Auckland Castle by the 5.30 p.m. express, and was met as usual by the car at Darlington. I beguiled the journey as far as York by reading Miss Macaulay’s novel, "Told by an Idiot": but from York to Darlington I had the company of Sir Arthur Pease<persName xml:id="5262"></persName>, who talked very eagerly about the political crisis.</p></body></text></TEI>