<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Durham after breakfast, and I presided over a meeting of the Barrington Trustees. Then we went on to Wynyard to take part in the celebration of Lord Castlereagh's<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> coming of age. There was a large gathering of "the County", and a number of deputations which had brought gifts and addresses to the young Heir. I was startled by learning that Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> had at the last moment failed to turn up, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; by being asked to take his place in proposing the health of Lord C. I dislike unpremeditated speaking extremely: however, I could but consent. My speech was, as usual, far too heavy for the occasion, but it was well&#8211;received. Lord C. spoke modestly and effectively in reply</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I sate at lunch between two beautiful and intelligent women<hi> –</hi> the Duchess of Sutherland and the Marchioness of Londonderry. On our way home, we turned aside to call on the Sykes family at Sedgefield. They all seemed happy and pleased with their new home. But, though the income of the benefice is large <hi>–</hi> &#x00A3;1794 net <hi>–</hi> Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> doubts whether he can afford a second curate, which the size of the parish seems to require. Two curates would cost &#x00A3;500 per annum, and he finds &#x00A3;1294 inadequate for the Rector of Sedgefield. He is a sincere man, whose word can be taken: but what a situation is disclosed! We are generally proclaiming that the adequate stipend for a parish clergyman is &#x00A3;400 per annum, and a house!</p></body></text></TEI>