<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Andrew's Day, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A hard frost, a clear sky, snow covering the land. I motored to Newcastle, and presided over a meeting of the Governors ^[of Barnard Castle School]^ in the Station Hotel. There were explosive materials enough, but no explosion! After lunching with my colleagues, I returned to the Castle. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop&#8211;designate of Winchester</hi> arrived in good time for the Festival service in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's. I went with him, and we presented a union of magnates, rarely if ever before presented to the public view. His sermon was mainly a missionary address, composed of episodes from his recent tour in India. He certainly has great fluency, &amp; the congregation was evidently interested: but I did not detect any signs of thought, and he speaks too fast. After service we returned to the Castle for dinner, &amp; were joined by the Vicar and his wife. Before going to bed, I had some talk with him about Farnham and Winchester. He is going into residence almost immediately <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; expresses himself very properly about the monstrous proposal to vacate the Castle &amp; break up the diocese.</hi> The Dean of W. had been known to him as one of his Archdeacons at Peterboro, where, on account of his valetudinarian habits, he was known as Miss Hutton.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The newspapers report the death of old M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Dicey in her 86</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> year</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>"Then is their life but labour &amp; sorrow". How fully did this poor lady illustrate the Psalmist's text!</p></body></text></TEI>