<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Protestants are not renouncers of tradition: for we allow all catholic traditions that can prove themselves to be such; but we finding little or nothing excepting this, that "The Bible is the word of God", and that "the Bible contains all the will of God for our salvation", all doctrines of faith and life, – little or nothing else, I say, descending to us by a universal tradition, therefore we have reason to adhere to scripture, and renounce all pretence of tradition of any matter of faith not plainly set down in the bible.</p>
         <p>Jeremy Taylor, Works VI 301</p>
         </div>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">In the church of Rome faith and Christianity increase like the moon"</hi> thus J. Taylor sums up the case against Papistry.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The truth, fulness, and sufficiency of scripture in all matters of faith and manners is the principle that I and all Protestants rely on".</p>
         </div>
         <p>Thus (VI.291) he states the ground of the Church of England.</p>
         <p>Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName> came to lunch, bringing with him the final changes for the dilapidations. These I paid making a total disbursement on this account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">£1454.8.0.</hi> It is a heavy charge.</p>
         <p>I went with Caröe to Kimblesworth, where he inspected the church. Lord<persName xml:id="1246"></persName> &amp; Lady Emmott arrived on a short visit. He was informing about Russia.</p></body></text></TEI>