<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>More snow fell during the night. The Archbishop's letter appears in the papers, where it is given great prominence, &amp; made the subject of flatterous leaders. His Grace has acted with great astuteness in choosing the time for disclosing these cryptic manoeuvres. For who can decently criticize efforts to make peace between Christians at Christmas time? In the temporary paralysis of reason &amp; orgy of sentiment any sugared folly can pass. But the unpalatable facts which underlie our divisions are not to be conjured away by the exchanges of compliments. Can any one who knows the men, &amp; knows the Churches pretend to think that Anglicanism is fairly represented by a distinguished medievalist (Armitage Robinson<persName xml:id="44"></persName>) and four Anglo&#8211;Catholic leaders (Frere<persName xml:id="2021"></persName>, Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, Kidd<persName xml:id="1733"></persName>, &amp; Lord Halifax)? Ought I to address a serious &amp; argued "remonstrance" to the "Times", which would break the spell? <hi rend="bold underline">My question was in a sense answered by a telegram from the Editor of the "Sunday Times" asking me to contribute an article of 1000 words to their next issue. I replied in the affirmative, &amp; wrote the promised article forthwith. It is difficult to avoid an appearance of disrespect to the Archbishop, and yet it is impossible to express approval of his behaviour. I am persuaded that he is influenced by very unwise counsellors, among whom I incline to think that</hi> Armitage Robinson is both the most influential and the most unwise.</p></body></text></TEI>