<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A bitter brilliant morning, with the land frost&#8211;whitened under the sun. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The birds, who appear to have established themselves in the roof, disturbed the service. It seems impossible to dislodge them. After breakfast, I set myself to the task of preparing a sermon for use in the afternoon, only interrupting my work in order to go to Mother's bedroom, and read prayers to her.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Burnopfield, carrying Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wynne&#8211;Willson as far as Durham, that they might attend Evensong in the Cathedral, and there I preached to a very crowded congregation on the occasion of the "Jubilee" of the parish church. The Vicar, the Rev. J. Madill, has held office since 1906, and has a faded disheartened appearance. His curate (unlicensed) is that hopeless creature Wolseley, who cannot speak intelligibly! The only good feature was the choir &amp; the Church Lads' Brigade; for there must be some attractive influence which has brought and kept together so many boys &amp; young men. The population, about 6000 in number, is wholly engaged in mining. There is at present little or no unemployment. The situation of the parish is bleak and beautiful, for it is nearly 1000 feet above the sea &amp; commands a wonderful prospect of moorland. From the Vicarage on a clear day an unimpeded view of the Cheviots may be obtained. I returned to the Castle about 6 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>