<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[104]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, December 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The last Sunday in the year is dark &amp; wet. Everywhere the snow, which yesterday crackled under the walker's foot, is dissolving into slush, and the state of the Castle's roofs is being put to the severest of tests. Fortunately, I have no preaching engagements today, and can indulge the mood of reminiscence without interruption.</p>
         <p>I celebrated Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. there were six communicants among whom was Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> who yesterday expressed his desire to be ordained. <hi rend="bold underline">At 11 a.m. I read the Morning Prayers in Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> bedroom</hi>, and that was the extent of my religious observance.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Sunday Times" published the little article I wrote under the heading "Reunion with Rome", &amp; added a brief leader. In yesterday's "Daily Mail" there is a list of telegraphed comments headed by my own</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>As might have been expected, the most effusive in approval are from Evangelical bishops! They "live &amp; move &amp; have their being" in a world of platform platitudes &amp; pietistic phrases, &amp; they have now exchanged the cant of "No Popery" for the cant of "Reunion"! Apart from them, the prevailing note is of disapproval harassed in its expression by a desire to "save the face" of the Primate. The more I think of it, the more I am convinced that his Grace has been wheedled and hustled into a considerable blunder.</p></body></text></TEI>