<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edwards Everett Hale</hi> once told me that churches should make new creeds every year as birds build their nests.</p>
         <p>Bishop Lawrence "Fifty Years" p. 51</p>
         </div>
         <p>Six years ago, on December 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1917, I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lloyd George accepting nomination to the bishoprick of Hereford. Was it well done?</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" advises M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> resignation, &amp; the formation of a Labour Government under <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Ramsay Macdonald</hi><persName xml:id="891"></persName>! Thus the fatuity of the "Die Hards" has brought the country within sight of the truly formidable contingency of Revolution: for unless the leopard can change its spots, a Labour Government could mean nothing less. How would it fare with the Church in these novel circumstances? Is there any reason for doubting that the Crown patronage would be as honestly administered as in the past? I suspect that Socialism gains quite as much from the fears of its opponents as from the zeal of its supporters.</p>
         <p>Beyond writing a number of letters, reading, &amp; walking in the Park, I did nothing.</p>
         <p>The weather has become suddenly milder: &amp; the roads, which yesterday, were of a flinty hardness, are today like sponges. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Faith Pease, Lord Gainford's<persName xml:id="2216"></persName> younger daughter, writes to ask whether I will baptize and confirm her by way of preparation for her marriage.<note xml:id="543" n="1"></note></hi></p></body></text></TEI>