<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The Bishop of Carlisle kept his bed with some kind of an indisposition. Accordingly the engagements at Sunderland had to be cancelled. After an early lunch I went with Lord Astor as far as Durham, and then sent him on in the car to Sunderland. I had an interview with Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> about the protest against the Stockton Report. Then I presided at a meeting of the Church Building Board. Then, I went to my room in the Castle, and had interviews successively with the Vicar of Chilton Moor and Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName>. As a result of the last I felt myself able to write to the Bishop of Exeter asking him wholly to cancel &amp; banish from mind the evil report of S.<persName xml:id="5358"></persName> sent to him by some strange &amp; unaccountable confusion.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury sent me a rather torturous epistle about his ill&#8211;advised speech</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Also I received a long letter from that crafty old "clawback" D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harris of Colwell, who, for some unimaginable reason thought it worth his while to inform me of the inner conflicts of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic faction. It appears that the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> Prayer Book represents the triumph of the moderates. He mentioned the curious fact that one Anglo&#8211;Catholic stated that he had used the Latin Mass for 13 years!</p>
         <p>The newspapers report that Germany is breaking up. This is probably the aim of French policy. The plea of reparations has been no more than a "smoke screen"!</p></body></text></TEI>