<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The snow lay heavy on the ground. But the chauffeur having ruled that the roads were passable, I returned to Auckland after breakfast being met by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> not far from Sedgefield. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to lunch, and afterwards walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and me in the Park. He is an affectionate lad or rather man, for he was 21 last May, and it is a sad pity his boyish desire to take Holy Orders never gained fulfilment. He is, I think, sincerely religious, &amp; devoted to his Vicar, Canon Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName>, a clergyman of whom I think highly.</p>
         <p>I read Winston's Book for several hours. It is absorbingly and painfully interesting.</p>
         <p>There was no post today, and no newspapers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury acknowledging the advance copy of his letter to the Anglican Metropolitans,</hi> &amp; made a copy of my own letter, which I entered in my private "Register". I cannot see my way to mitigate, still less to withdraw, the disapproval of his Grace's action which I expressed at the Bishop's meeting. The Primate ought not to have given his approval to "conversations" in which the Church of England has for its representatives none but Anglo&#8211;Catholics. It is certain that the impression of Anglicanism which they could give to the Papists would be gravely misleading.</p></body></text></TEI>