<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>A white frost, redeemed by the stillness of the morning and the brightness of the sun. Davison, whom I instituted last Sunday to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's Auckland, is hors de combat with an attack of erysipelas. With much difficulty provision has been made for the services in his church. I myself have undertaken the early celebration, and Petitjean, who is but in deacon's Orders, will do all the rest. The shortage of clergy in the diocese is brought home sharply whenever any sudden point of need emerges.</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I motored to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, where I celebrated the Holy Communion in the little old church, which was decorated for the Harvest Thanksgiving. There were 24 communicants, all women save four, of whom my William was one.</p>
         <p>We (i.e. William &amp; I) left the Castle at 9.40 a.m. &amp; motored 20 miles to Stockton, where I dedicated a Window, Tablet &amp; Pateu to the memory of Eric Purvis, the vicar's son, who was drowned at sea. There was a very long congregation. I preached from S. John x.10 "I came that they may have life". After service, I presented the MS. of my sermon to the Vicar. We returned to Auckland in time for lunch. The brilliant colouring of the trees seen to perfection in the sunlight made our journey a continuing feast of beauty.</p></body></text></TEI>