<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. There were no less than 18 communicants including myself, for Ashton, his wife and daughter, George Laws, &amp; old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith joined the household. After breakfast I motored to Crook, and there celebrated the Holy Communion, &amp; preached the sermon. The communicants numbered 128, of whom half were men. I noticed that the hands out–stretched to receive the Blessed Sacrament were almost without exception toil–hardened and toil–stained. I returned to Auckland for lunch. We all motored into Durham, where I gave Christmas Boxes to the Vergers &amp; Reeve. Leaving <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> in the Cathedral, <hi rend="bold underline">I went on to Wynyard, where I baptized Catherine Edith Helen, the daughter of Lady Maureen Stanley,<persName xml:id="5270"></persName> in the private chapel. I preached at Evensong, &amp; stayed to dinner.</hi> It had been arranged that Ella sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Join me at dinner, &amp; that we should return to Auckland the same evening, but a considerable snowstorm made the roads dangerous. Ella telephoned that she could not come, &amp; that I must stay the night. There was an old–time Christmas party at Wynyard. <hi rend="bold underline">The guests included Princess Marie Louise<persName xml:id="5406"></persName>, the Duchess of Sutherland<persName xml:id="5407"></persName>, Lord &amp; Lady Chester, Lord<persName xml:id="5401"></persName> &amp; Lady Dufferin, Lord &amp; Lady Plunkett, Lords Castlereagh<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> &amp; Staindale,</hi> &amp; many appendant children. Dancing was maintained with much vigour until midnight, &amp; then we all went to bed. The snow was some inches thick.</p></body></text></TEI>