<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shadwell's</hi><persName xml:id="30"></persName> book "<hi rend="underline">Drink in 1914&#8211;1922, a Lesson in Control</hi>" which, at his request, I foolishly promised to review for the "Times Literary Supplement".</p>
         <p>The sorely aggrieved curate, Macready, from the Oxbridge Mission came to lunch. I spoke to him soothingly, but, plainly, the situation is not easy. Probably I had better let a deputation come here, &amp; blow off steam.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">An impudent letter from the Mayor of Sunderland surprised and annoyed me. I had invited him to attend the institution of Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> on December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, and he takes occasion to lecture me on appointing an outsider! At first I meditated an angry answer, but eventually I replied quite mildly!</hi> It is probably that there is a good deal of clerical grumbling under the surface, and a base fellow like this Mayor would greedily garner such squalid advantage as may accrue from expressing it! I have a certain anxiety for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson's</hi> sake. The late Mayor, Raine<persName xml:id="5371"></persName>, who now represents Sunderland in Parliament was a far superior person: <hi rend="bold underline">but his wife has just been converted to Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, and probably regards the Bishop of Durham with a growing aversion!</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury consenting to act as Convenor of the little Committee of Bishops charged with revising the Thirty&#8211;nine Articles.</p></body></text></TEI>