<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead's</hi><persName xml:id="2508"></persName> Rectorial Address on "<hi rend="underline">Idealism in Inter&#8211;nationalism Politics</hi>" delivered last Wednesday to the students of Glasgow was rather a brazen performance. There is a suggestion of the late Kaiser's flamboyant style in the following:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The world continues to offer glittering prizes to those who have stout arms &amp; sharp swords, &amp; it is, therefore, extremely improbable that the experience of future nations will differ in any material respect from that which has happened since the twilight of the human race. It is for us therefore to prove in our history a martial rather than a military people, to abstain, as has been our habit, from provocations, but to maintain in our own hands adequate means for our own protection, and, so equipped, to march with head erect and bright eyes along the road to our own imperial destiny".</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is quite in the old pre&#8211;War style. Of course his Lordship has a fling at the League of Nations. Two correspondents write to beg me to answer this Address, but I declined, having no time to do it thoroughly, &amp; being in no mood to do it otherwise.</p>
         <p>I paid 2.A.B. the final instalment [&#x00A3;123:3:5] on the loan of &#x00A3;2500 contracted by Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName> in order to reform the drainage. Also, I sent <hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;20</hi> to the Emmet Memorial Fund.</p>
         <p>Lloyd&#8211;George has made no delay in declaring himself opposed to the Protective policy of the Government. The "Glasgow Herald" also repudiates Protection.</p></body></text></TEI>