<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked all the morning at the "Introduction" of my pamphlet "In defence of the English Church" but my progress was very slow. My right hand seems to have lost its cunning.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I took the Johnsons into Durham</hi><hi rend="bold">, </hi>and showed them the Castle and the Cathedral. We had tea with the Dawson Walkers<persName xml:id="3161"></persName>, and then I took Johnson into the Chapter Library and the Deanery. We fell in with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, with whom was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rendall Harris</hi>. He had come to Durham to look at an Ms. in the Library. We got back to Auckland about 6.30pm.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"With a few courageous exceptions the authorities of the Church, owing largely to the method of their appointment, held aloof from the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Movement"</p>
         </div>
         <p>This modest &amp; suggestive sentence is taken from the little green covered tract entitled "Anglo&#8211;Catholic Aims" which was issued by the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Congress Committee last summer. It indicates what indeed is becoming apparent by many signs that <hi rend="italic bold underline">a dead set is to be made against the Crown nomination of the Bishops</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Yet, even if their object were gained, &amp; Anglo&#8211;Catholics reigned on the Bench, could they acquiesce in the position which is assigned to Bishops in the procedure of the Movement? Would not the logic of their position compel them to assert some small measure of authority over the clergy?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>