<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923. Guy Fawkes Day.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The great thing to know is whether, after all, the imbecilities that time has consecrated do not form the best investment a man can make of his stupidity. Far from feeling glad when I seem some time&#8211;honoured fallacy exploded, I think of the new one that will come and take its place, &amp; I ask myself the anxious question – will it not perhaps be more inconvenient and dangerous than the other? On full &amp; sufficient consideration, the old prejudices are less baneful than the new; time, by long usage, has given them a polish &amp; made them almost innocent.</p>
         <p>Anatole France</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I lost my umbrella yesterday. The butler vainly communicated with the Palace. I must have left it in the taxi</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I caught the 10 a.m. express at King's Cross, &amp; was met by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> at Darlington. The responses to my appeal for the Diocesan Finance Board are sufficiently discouraging. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Gainford<persName xml:id="2216"></persName> excuses himself that he is a Quaker, &amp; that times are bad. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hiram Craven contents himself with pleading poverty: &amp; Miss Baker sends three guineas! It is difficult to dispute the argument that trade is prostrate: but the demands on the Fund increase steadily, and its income is evidently shrinking. Moreover there is no longer any social obligation to support the National Church.</p></body></text></TEI>