<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Snow fell briskly at intervals throughout the day. I did not leave my room, but after dealing with the correspondence, fell to reading a book which was sent me by John Murray, with a request for my opinion on it. <hi rend="underline">"The causes of the present conflict of Ideals in the Church of England</hi>" by R. D. Richardson B.A. is a "Modern Churchman's" publication, &amp; discloses but too fully the muddleheadedness of that type. <hi rend="bold underline">Still there is both promise and ingenuity in the volume, &amp; I think the Author will be heard of again.</hi></p>
         <p>An old gentleman named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stokoe</hi> writes from Sunderland to tell me that he desires to contribute something towards establishing the Chaplain in the Gatehouse, &amp; that he has bequeathed &#x00A3;1000 to the Bishop of Durham for the good of the diocese. If this actually matures, the money &#8211; &#x00A3;50 yearly – will be very useful for the clergy. </p>
         <p>The general impression of the progress of the General Election seems to be increasingly favourable to the Government. Most of the forecasts give Protectionism a majority, though perhaps hardly large enough for its programme. It would almost appear to be the case that Free Trade is sharing the fate of all Victorian ideals &amp; institutions. Protestantism, law &amp; order, the middle classes, free trade – all that was great in the eyes of our fathers seems to have lost hold on our minds, &amp; no longer wakes the smallest enthusiasm in any quarter. </p></body></text></TEI>