<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>You were all brutally mistaken about Shelley, who was, without exception, the <hi rend="underline">best </hi>and least selfish man I ever knew. I never knew one who was not a beast in comparison.</p>
         <p>Byron to Murray. Aug: 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1822 (vi.99)</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote to Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> consenting to contribute &#x00A3;50 towards a second "loan" to G.<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> It is a hopeless business, but there is nothing else to be done. </p>
         <p>I wrote letters, &amp; worked at the charge for the <hi rend="underline">Ordinandi</hi> all the morning. After lunch I walked in the Park with the dogs: and then, after an early dinner, accompanied <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> to the Theatre to see Sir Frank Benson's company perform "The Rivals". After the performance, we went behind the curtain, &amp; talked with Sir Frank Benson. He is a taller and more impressive man that his brother L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>, but was too much disfigured by his "make&#8211;up" to permit of a positive judgement on his appearance. I asked him how he liked North Country audiences, and whether he preferred them to Southerners. He answered that he preferred them, &amp; spoke rather contemptuously of London. During the afternoon some of his company were shown over the Castle by Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName>, on whom they left a very favourable impression.</p>
         <p>That worthless wastrel <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Alfred Douglas</hi> has been sentenced to six months imprisonment for his impudent libels on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winston Churchill</hi><persName xml:id="2441"></persName>, &amp; obstinate persistence in them.</p></body></text></TEI>