<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The post brought me a characteristic letter from Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>. His heart is golden, but his head is perverse! My letter on the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> appears on the front page of the "Times", &amp; reads severely, but not, I think, excessively so. Later I received telegram from Gilbert Murray:</hi></p>
         <p>"Would you join deputation to Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> next Thursday 3 p.m. Downing Street to support Government's action against disrupting Germany. Your presence would be immensely valuable".</p>
         <p>This telegram shows that the League of Nation itself welcomed my epistle.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 5.15 p.m., &amp;, after picking up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in Darlington, went to Haughton&#8211;le&#8211;Skerne, where I instituted Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> to the Rectory. The church was well&#8211;filled, and I think the congregation was impressed. After the service we went in to a new parishioner, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Williams, who has established himself nicely in Haughton Hall. We got back to the Castle about 9 p.m.</p>
         <p>I must have taken a chill yesterday for today I am in an ill state; everything is a burden to me. What poor creatures we are at best!</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A certain M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> E. Blackwood Wright, Barrister&#8211;at&#8211;Law, sends me a type&#8211;written letter which he sent to the "Times", but which the "Times" did not publish. He points out that the Archbishop of Canterbury has no ground in law for claiming that the Bishop is the "lawful authority" mentioned in the formula of Clerical Subscription provided by the Clerical Subscription Act. "If the Abp's view were correct, the Bp of Lincoln c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> never have been proceeded against for as Bishop he w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have been a lawful authority".</hi></p></body></text></TEI>