<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> seemed to think there was something subtle and even sinister about the Archbishop's suggesting that I should address to him a request for explanation. To me, on the contrary, it appeared the most simple and indeed obvious of arrangements, when once I had told him that in my judgement explanation was required, &amp; he had admitted the fact.</p>
         <p>The lady, I think her name was Murray, who attacked me after dinner on the subject of "Birth control" appears to be a fanatical missionary of <hi rend="underline">that</hi> Gospel. I was not very responsive to her ardour, for the subject is hateful, and these enthusiasts ignore altogether every aspect but the physical &amp; social. That morality itself is concerned does not enter their heads.</p>
         <p>Lord S.<persName xml:id="3465"></persName> drove me to King's Cross where I caught the 10 o'clock train for Darlington, where William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car. I found the proofs of my booklet "In defence of the English Church" had arrived. These I corrected &amp; returned.</p>
         <p>The Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> himself announced in clear terms his belief in protection, and his intention to make that his policy. America will join a Conference if requested to do so by all the allies. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin makes an earnest appeal to M. Poincar&#x00E9; not to refuse to come into line.</p></body></text></TEI>