<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I felt woefully unequal to my task of preaching, but, when it came to the actual performance, my voice served me much better than I had dared to expect. <hi rend="bold underline">The Royal Exchange was filled with an audience almost entirely composed of young &amp; middle&#8211;aged men. A pulpit (without any desk whereon papers c</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be placed) was provided, &amp; I made shift with my mortar&#8211;board as a screen for my MS. The attention of the assembly suggested that they were able to hear what I said, and I was assured by many, that this was the case</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> A considerable choir led the singing which was "conducted" by a leader in surplice and hood. The <hi rend="bold underline">Lord Mayor &amp; Sheriffs attended in State: and afterwards I lunched with them at the Mansion House</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>This function ended, I called upon Hodder &amp; Stoughton in Warwick Square, &amp; found an early copy of my booklet lying on the publishers' table. This I took away with me. Then I went to the hair&#8211;dressers, &amp; had my hair cut. <hi rend="bold underline">I dined with Dunbar&#8211; Buller at 15 Upper Grosvenor St: He is 75 years old, &amp; visibly failing: but he was very insistent that he had never had, &amp; that he was never likely to have a stroke</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> We dined t&#x00EA;t&#x00E9;&#8211;a&#8211;t&#x00EA;t&#x00E9;: &amp; I think he was really glad to see me again. But we grow old &amp; the savour of life is gone.</p></body></text></TEI>