<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Colder than ever. My morning was much broken up. First, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burkitt came to see me about the appointment of a new Headmaster for the N.E. Counties School. Next, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hurrell, came about the consecration of the new Burial Ground in his parish. He wants to get the sectaries to take part in the function. I approve, but one must walk "delicately" to avoid legal pitfalls. Then, the Vicar called about the "ordination" of his deaconess. It appears that the communities are fluttered at the notion of her being "ordained" without a preliminary period of devotional preparation. I advised in the interest of her professional career, that she should "toe the line"!</p>
         <p>Miss Ramsey &amp; George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> arrived at the Castle. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Newcastle, and attended a lecture by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rosita Forbes</hi><persName xml:id="5372"></persName> in the Town Hall. The lecture was illustrated by slides, &amp; was exceedingly well delivered. The lecturer described her journey in Arabia with much vivacity &amp; humour. I proposed a vote of thanks to her at the end. After the lecture, we went to Sir J. Oliver's house, &amp; dined with a numerous company. I sat next to the Lecturer, &amp; had much talk with her. She told me that she was the daughter of Herbert Torr, whom I used to meet at the Representative Ch. Council. I was certainly pleased with her, better pleased than I had expected to be. We returned to Auckland, arriving at 11.45 p.m. there was a heavy snow&#8211;fall at Newcastle.</p></body></text></TEI>