<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I went into Durham after breakfast, &amp; had an interview with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>. He showed me the letters which had been intercepted between the nefarious Jamaican &amp; the choirboys. They certainly make it most desirable that the Darkie should be got out of Durham. Then I licensed a curate in the Castle. After buying some Christmas presents at Andrew's book&#8211;shop, I went back to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> sent four pheasants.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mess</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi> sent me their account for the copies they have issued "with the Author's compliments" to the Bishops &amp; the members of the House of Laity, and also those sent to myself. With the postage it reaches the formidable sum <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;46:12:10</hi>. Is this money well spent? It is certain that it can ill be afforded. Yet I could not but feel that it was worth while to make an effort in order to bring the moral implications of clerical subscription into due prominence. The curious impudence with which the latest generation of Anglo&#8211;Catholics express themselves has driven the fact that they are all subscribers to the Declaration of Assent out of view. <hi rend="underline">None the Less, that fact is central to the whole controversy about Prayer&#8211;Book Revision</hi>. For if these gentlemen allow no binding force in the promises they make, it is obviously useless to waste time in trying to meet their objections to their existing obligations. Only on the basis of good faith is it worth while to go on.</p></body></text></TEI>