<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I had but time for some unavoidable correspondence &amp; the preparation of an address on "Educators" before William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> was at the door with the car to carry me to Durham. There I licensed half a dozen curates among them that queer creature Palgrave, who was with me at the Oxford House when first I was ordained. He has had a roving career, mostly of hard &amp; obscure service, &amp; he winds up as an assistant curate. Yet what honest man w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not set his life above mine in the scale of spiritual values? I lunched pleasantly with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, &amp; then presided over the <hi rend="bold underline">Diocesan Conference</hi> Committee, where that tiresome "saint" from Ferryhill, Lomax, made himself a considerable nuisance. When this was over, I motored through a deluge of rain to West Hartlepool. Here I went to Christ Church Vicarage &amp; had an interview with Captain Hare, the son of the old Vicar of Greatham, who has resigned his benefice under coercion of the doctors. After tea with the Macdonalds, I went to the Town Hall, &amp; distributed prizes to the Secondary School. In spite of the rain, and three electioneering meetings, there was a large attendance of the public. My speech, which took 45 minutes to deliver, was listened to with attention, and much applauded. We motored back to Auckland through heavy rain, &amp; arrived about 9.45 p.m. Thus I frittered away another day.</p></body></text></TEI>