<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I say that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter Scott</hi> is as nearly a thorough good man as man can be, because I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> it by experience to be the case.</p>
         <p>Byron to Henry Beyle 1823 (vi, 221)</p>
         </div>
         <p>Byron's earnest and emphatic remonstrance against the statements that Scott's character was "little worthy of enthusiasm" has the ring of sincerity. It is, indeed, evident enough that Byron made regard &amp; admiration for himself the very criterion of greatness &amp; goodness in others. Nevertheless, his references to Scott are invariably more respectful than those he makes to other contemporaries whom he favoured, &amp; this is the more noteworthy since he abhorred Scott's politics. The enthusiasm for the Waverley novels finds frequent expression and the charm of Scott's personality – which exhales from the romances – held him.</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 9.15 a.m., &amp; motored to South Shields, picking up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in Durham on the way. I instituted Lane–Davies to the Vicarage of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Michael's, South Westoe, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. The congregation may have numbered nearly 500 persons, &amp; the population of the parish is stated to be 23,000! There were many communicants, &amp; the service was interrupted by an awkward interval during which the Curate fetched more bread from the vestry for a second consecration! Leaving Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> in South Shields, <hi rend="bold">[91] </hi>Wilson and I motored over an execrable road to Gateshead, where we lunched at the Rectory. After lunch I went to S. Columba's and preached to a congregation of men. While this service was proceeding William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> carried Wilson back to Durham, &amp; returned for me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Suthrien</hi><persName xml:id="5364"></persName> asked me whether my "charges" to Ordinandi had been published, &amp; said <hi rend="bold underline">that the men whom I had ordained greatly desired to have them</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>This request pleased me. On the way back to Auckland I turned aside to call on Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, whom the papers reported to be on the sick list. I found him in the company of his relations – the Lambtons are a numerous race. One of the ladies had just returned from Newcastle, where she had had a broken collar bone set. There had been a motor car accident in which the damage had been done. Everybody was, of course, full of the General Election. The older members of the family are Freetraders: the younger Protectionists. I threw my weight into the scale of the seniors! Everybody expressed horror at the prospect of a Labour government, &amp;, indeed, it <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> difficult to avoid anxiety as to the behaviour of such ignorant amateurs as the Labour men certainly are. Before leaving Lambton I had another look at the fascinating "Master Lambton" by Lawrence. It is certainly a delightful picture. I got back to Auckland at 6.30 p.m. </p>
         <p>The weather became curiously warm as the day advanced and it blew a hurricane, so strong that the car staggered with the violence of the wind.</p></body></text></TEI>