<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A telegram from the Editor of the "Daily Mail" asked for a pronouncement on the "Malines reunion conferences". I filled up the prepaid form thus:&#8211; "<hi rend="underline">Reunion with Rome cannot usefully be discussed until the present claims of the Papacy have been abandoned, and the Church of England has been frankly recognized. No authority from the Bishops or Convocations has been given to the conferences at Malines". </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the morning in writing to the "Times" a letter headed "</hi><hi rend="underline">Rome and England</hi><hi rend="bold underline">". It will not please his Grace, but will define my position sufficiently.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather changed during the night, rain fell in some quantity, and the snow began to disappear as quickly as it had come. The Park was in a very soppy state when I walked in it with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> during the afternoon.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The comments on the Archbishop's Letter are marked by a certain perplexity. Reluctance to show disrespect to his Grace, who now adds the authority of age to that of office, and a certain curiosity as to the extent of the Pope's concern with the conferences at Malines are combined with a clear perception of the preposterous unreality of the whole proceeding. The Romans fasten on the Archbishop's declaration that the traditional Anglican position will not be weakened or altered: the Protestants point naturally to the unsuitable character of the English delegates.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>