<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>. Then I tried to draft something for the clergy about the Parochial Rolls. Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName> lunched, &amp; afterwards accompanied me to Hunwick where I consecrated a Burial Ground i.e., a portion of one. The incumbent M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hurrell, had asked me to invite the local sectaries to take part in the function. Accordingly, after the Consecration had been duly completed, three of them conducted a short ancillary service of Scripture, an address, and prayers, ending with the Benediction which I pronounced. The Burial Board was well represented, but the people were conspicuous by their absence. Their absence was perhaps explicable by the weather, but not I suspect wholly so. I incline rather to the supposition that they disapproved of their ministers being mixed up with such superstition!</p>
         <p>On returning to the castle, I received a deputation of three men from the vacant parish of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Jude, South Shields, the patronage of which is for this turn in the hands of the Crown. I heard what they had to say, asked them some questions, &amp; gave them tea. It is pitiful to know that one's power to satisfy their perfectly legitimate demands is almost nil. When the deputation had taken its departure, I was at last able to make some preparation for tomorrow! It is this <hi rend="bold underline">"hand&#8211;to&#8211;mouth" manner of working</hi> that makes episcopal life at once so busy and so futile. it is difficult to see how anything permanent can be done by bishops!</p></body></text></TEI>