<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S. Thomas's Day, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ordination</hi> passed off without serious episodes, at least nothing more serious than the omission to light the altar candles &amp; set out the linen, and the absence announced at the last moment of several volunteer chairmen. These small mishaps were the "last straws" in the process of breaking the camel's back of Clayton's<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> nerves, so that he was too fluttered to communicate! Sykes from Middlesborough preached an extemporaneous discourse, which at least had the merit of being brief. The candidates pleased me by their earnestness &amp; reverence of demeanour. Two Nonconformist ministers from Bishop Auckland were present, and (with my consent) communicated. After the Ordination, so soon as the congregation had dispersed, I confirmed M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Raine in the presence of her husband, Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, and Clayton. Then everybody stayed to lunch to the number of more than 40: and, when they had departed, I lay down on the sofa to nurse a headache!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Frere<persName xml:id="2021"></persName>, now Bishop of Truro, acknowledges his copy of "In defence of the English Church"</hi> in a very characteristic letter, in which he says that after reading it "with exceptional care &amp; reflection", he is "puzzled by a good many things in the book, and the way in which they are related to other parts". He can't be more puzzled about "what is really my position" than I am myself!</p></body></text></TEI>