<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>Sixty years of my life have passed. There cannot be many more to come. On the most optimistic view, a decade of active life remains to me. It is not a comfortable reflexion. Substantially my life has disclosed its content. I can see quite clearly that my place will be a humble one in the general record. <hi rend="underline">"I am not better than my fathers".</hi> I received gifts or letters from the little faithful group – George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, Alfred Spelling<persName xml:id="7"></persName>, Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Olive<persName xml:id="1686"></persName>, and of course <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Birkenhead<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> is reported to have denounced "sentimentality" at Glasgow; but there is a vast amount of sentiment in us all. Being on the sick list, I remained in my study, and did nothing more serviceable than writing letters of thanks to my Birthday correspondents, save that I had interviews with two of my clergy. I succeeded in passing on my engagement to dedicate a War&#8211;Memorial at Lyons to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I read through the Report of the Lambeth Conference Committee on "The Ministry of Healing", and was much distressed at its character.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I cannot accept its "fundamental principle" viz "that the power to exercise spiritual healing [of the body] is taught by Christ to be the natural heritage of Christian people who are living in fellowship with God, &amp; is part of the ministry of Christ through His Body the Church". The Committee is mostly composed of the least authoritative Bishops.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>