<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote the Address for the Royal Exchange on Monday, and made a copy of it which I sent to Albert Saxton<persName xml:id="222"></persName>, who had asked for it that he might send a translation to the Dutch newspapers. In the afternoon the State&#8211;room was crowded with subscribers to the "Women's Offering", which was formally presented to me, or rather to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, who acted for me.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> has a long letter in the "Times" conceived in a tone which might fairly be called impudent</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>This fact seemed sufficient to exonerate me from any obligation to answer him. His Grace and Lord Birkenhead<persName xml:id="2508"></persName>, who has "taken up his parable" in his Rectorial address in Glasgow against Idealism, are joining hands against the "League of Nations". The attitude of America gives a kind of respectability to their cynical contempt of the League. How perverse is human nature! Who could have imagined that the one considerable triumph of American "Idealism" – the establishment of the League of Nations – should find the principal obstacle to its successful working in American "Politics"? But America embodies this Mezentian Union of impracticable altruism, and a cynical partisanship. Even the policy of "feeding Germany" has its strongest support in the political value of spreading a great sum of money in purchasing food stuffs from the Western farmers! It might gain Coolidge the Presidential election!</p></body></text></TEI>