<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>The bitter weather continues, &amp; the sky is cloudless. After breakfast the Wynne&#8211;Willsons<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> went off to Sunderland. I celebrated the Holy Communion in Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> room. It being William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> Birthdays, I gave him "Martin Chuzzlewit". I ran through the latest statistics of clerical incomes in my diocese, and found that of the 265 benefices</p>
         <p>11 were above &#x00A3;1000 net</p>
         <p>49 were above 500 net</p>
         <p>114 were above 400 net</p>
         <p>185 were above 350 net</p>
         <p>245 were above 300 net</p>
         <p>20 were under 300 net</p>
         <p>Do these figures really bear out the tragical statements as to clerical poverty so often made in Church Assemblies? How far is Durham better endowed than the rest?</p>
         <p>If the endowments were equally divided every incumbent would receive a net income of &#x00A3;444. If the episcopal income were added there would be about &#x00A3;17 added.</p>
         <p>Beyond walking in the Park with the dogs during the afternoon, I stayed in my study, &amp; muddled away the time in letter&#8211;writing and reading Byron's Letters. It is always difficult to determine the evidential value of private letters, &amp; in the case of so morbidly egotistic a poseur as Byron the difficulty is particularly great. He was posing to others, and, which was still worse, he was posing to himself. Hence the saving factors in his experience &amp; in his own nature were never able to come into play.</p></body></text></TEI>