<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Williamson motored me to Darlington where I took train to London in order to attend the meeting of the Committee on Ecclesiastical Courts. <hi rend="bold underline">The little correspondence between me &amp; the Archbishop of Canterbury appeared in the morning papers. In the "Times" and the Yorkshire Post it has a prominent position on the front page.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Harold Knowling<persName xml:id="113"></persName> came to see me at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. He gave me a rambling incoherent account of his domestic affairs which was probably more plausible than true, and assured me that peace at home had been restored.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Findlay</hi> told me that he had supported the Enabling Act, but had grown to doubt his wisdom in doing so, as the Act had not worked as he expected.</p>
         <p>No man of honour ever talks over his difficulties with his wife with another woman. So called "platonic friendships" are always imprudent and rarely innocent. Extravagance &amp; self&#8211;indulgence leading to financial embarrassments lie at the root of many, perhaps most, domestic bickerings. The desire to make money quickly without honestly earning it is the curse of our post&#8211;war youth.</p>
         <p>I dined with mine host &amp; hostess in 21 Park Lane. The IngesInge<persName xml:id="427"></persName><persName xml:id="1209"></persName> came to dinner.</p></body></text></TEI>