<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>There was a rapid thaw during the night, &amp; deluges of rain. Accordingly, the snow had all disappeared, and sodden landscapes met the eye. It is just 35 years since I was instituted publicly in Barking Church as Vicar of Barking. I think all who took part in the service except myself are now dead, and I myself in mind &amp; purpose am now unrecognizable. </p>
         <p>I motored to Gateshead, picking up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in Durham, and there I admitted Philps to the perpetual curacy of Christ Church, in succession to Davison. It was a well&#8211;arranged &amp; reverent service, and my sermon was listened to with attention. I was particularly pleased to see, &amp; receive good accounts of, three of the young men whom I have ordained – Suthrien, Trotman, &amp; Bamlett. After lunching with the Rural Dean, I returned to Durham, &amp; attended Evensong in the Cathedral. After having tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mead Faulkner</hi><persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, who has just returned from Spain, (<hi rend="underline">where, he says, the people are delighted to be rid of Parliamentary government</hi>) I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, there I preached in the Parish Church, and afterwards had supper in the Rectory. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> gives an excellent report of his two deacons, Booth &amp; Brewer. It is evident enough that he is getting hold of the parish. I picked up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> in Durham, whereto they had come to listen to the Advent music in the Cathedral, and then I returned to the Castle where we arrived at 10.30 p.m. The weather throughout the day was mild &amp; occasionally fine. </p></body></text></TEI>