<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the day at the Bishop's Meeting in Lambeth. The principal subject of discussion was the Report of the Lambeth Committee on <hi rend="bold underline">"The Ministry of Healing",</hi> which was introduced by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge</hi><persName xml:id="602"></persName>, the Chairman of the Committee. I subjected it to some rather hostile criticism, &amp; I think there was a good deal of apprehension in the minds of the bishops. The Bishop of Ripon spoke sensibly, &amp; so did the Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName>: but there is so much reluctance to stand up against any stream of opinion that it is hopeless to look for anything decisive from the bishops. We had some interesting information about Hickson's Healing Missions in Australia and South Africa. The first glowing reports are giving place to misgivings &amp; doubts. There is also some restiveness about Hickson's financial methods.</p>
         <p>In Parliament M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> announced an immediate dissolution, and a General Election in the first week of December. It is reported that the Liberal Party will go to the Polls as an united Party under M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Asquith. Birkenhead<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> &amp; Austen Chamberlain<persName xml:id="343"></persName> are joining forces with the Government. It is difficult to imagine that any good can come to the country form these precipitate tactics. If the Labour Party had not tied itself to the Capital Levy, I see no reason why it sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not gain a majority.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">My letter to the "Times" in rebuke of the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> seems to have pleased many people. The Archbishop of York, &amp; the Bishops of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> &amp; Salisbury were particularly effusive. Lady Frances Balfour wrote at some length to thank me for what she calls my "dignified protest", &amp; to beg me not to answer her nephew's "somewhat rude" letter. Her description of his Grace's upbringing is amusing.</hi></p>
         <p>I dined with Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers. The Swedish ambassador &amp; his wife were there: Edmund Gosse &amp; his wife: Sir Bernard &amp; Lady Malet: &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Carlisle (?): also the pretty American whom we met originally with the Ramsays in Stockholm. It was a moderately amusing evening, no more: for I was listless &amp; tired. The rain fell heavily, &amp; that circumstance added to the general depression.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitty Inge</hi><persName xml:id="1209"></persName> writes to me from Oxford. She was in the Abbey on November 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, &amp; heard my sermon, which much have impressed her, for she writes flatterously. Also, her father, the quondam Archdeacon<persName xml:id="383"></persName>, writes me a somewhat belated Birthday letter. "You cannot expect me who am in my 78<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year, to condole with you in reaching 60 which seems to me a stage now far back in the distant past, but I should like to repeat that there is no one among my friends for whom I have a greater affection than yourself. You have always been so kind &amp; welcoming to me ever since I had the pleasure of being introduced to you". Albert Saxton<persName xml:id="222"></persName> also wrote to me.</p></body></text></TEI>