<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, who orderest all things according to Thy Will, and dost not disdain to guide the way of the least of Thy servants, have mercy on me, and cause me ever to walk in the path of Thy commandments, and to seek Thy glory in all that I attempt &amp; do, through Jesus Christ, Thy son our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>A brilliant morning, calm and mild, like the face of a Saint. Before getting up I read Berguer's account &amp; psycho&#8211;analytical interpretation of the Birth of Jesus. It does not attract me.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I drove to Buckingham Palace where everybody was somewhat "fluttered" by the departure of the King of Sweden.</hi> It was explained to me with what seemed rather superfluous emphasis that H.M. was so pressed for time that he c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not receive me after the service. The service began at 9.50a.m., and ended at 10.20 a.m.; my sermon occupied exactly 13 minutes! I walked away immediately to the Chapel Royal for the next function. As I passed out of the Palace Gates I noticed a considerable gathering of people waiting for the King of Sweden's appearance. Probably some of them were Swedes. The "Children of the Chapel Royal" looked very brilliant, their tunics being new.</p>
         <p>The Chapel Royal appeared to be well&#8211;filled, but I recognized nobody except L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>. Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> &amp; Lady Struthers, Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> <hi rend="bold">[44]</hi> [symbol] and his son, and Angela Thelwall<persName xml:id="1812"></persName>. The altar looked very splendid being <hi rend="bold underline">still arranged as it had been yesterday for the marriage of the Crown Prince of Sweden</hi>. I preached from my stall, repeating the sermon on the League of Nations which I preached to the Freemasons of Jarrow a few weeks ago. I suspect that Sir Henry Craik was deeply resentful! Angela Thelwall came in to the Vestry after the service.</p>
         <p>After lunch, as I took my coffee, an old gentleman started talking about D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett's<persName xml:id="1725"></persName> successor, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hutton<persName xml:id="5369"></persName> from Glasgow, of whom he spoke enthusiastically. Then he went on to describe his own relations with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Parker of the City Temple, whom he greatly admired. <hi rend="bold underline">He had a mean opinion of Campbell, "a frisking Italian greyhound replacing an old lion".</hi> He said Campbell attributed his own extraordinary popularity to his picturesque combination of a boyish countenance &amp; an abundant frame of grey hair! Then he proceeded to speak of his wife who is mentally deranged though not "certified". Did I believe in spiritual healing? I was not favourable. He seemed a little disappointed. This good man hailed from the North, &amp; knew L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>, of whom he spoke with sympathy &amp; regard. I cannot imagine who he is, and I dared not ask him! Then I walked to 39 Grosvenor Square in order to call on L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Durham but found that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not return from Newmarket until tomorrow.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Returning to the Club, I committed an indiscretion – <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the "Times" rebuking the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> for his attack on the League of Nations, &amp; on the Bishops for supporting it.</hi></p>
         <p>"The Duke of N. is a man of great name and high promise but his position in politics is not yet so assured that he can afford to offend the conscience of the people, &amp; to affront their intelligence". I wonder whether the "Times" will publish it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Sir Henry Craik came into the Club, &amp; (as I expected) attacked me with characteristic vehemence on my sermon! It was outrageous, made his blood boil! I returned the "soft answer", and we parted amicably</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There was a great congregation in the Abbey at 6.30 p.m., many standing throughout the service. My sermon took exactly 32 minutes to deliver, &amp; was closely listened to throughout. My text was Micach vi. 8 and Romans iii.7.8, and my subject was really </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"The Meaning &amp; permanent worth of the Protestant version of Christianity". </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName><hi rend="italic"> were in the Abbey, &amp; both thanked me afterwards. The Dean also thanked me, but, I think rather ruefully!</hi> I had supper in the Deanery after the service. Whittuck was there. He kindly offered to put me up if I wanted hospitality. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Mountgarret</hi> was there also, &amp; some others whom I did not identify. I got back to my prophet's chamber shortly after 9 p.m., very tired.</p></body></text></TEI>