<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> sends me a kindly acknowledgement of my little book ("In defence of the English Church") which he is reading "with great avidity &amp; delight". He adds: "You have a wonderfully clear way of putting things &amp; I envy you your style. We have few stylists now". <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Knox</hi> also acknowledges a copy "in no formal manner, but with sincere appreciation of its brilliancy &amp; power". I must set these flatterous letters against the fact that for the most part the bishops do not think it necessary even to say "Thank you!".</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aglionby</hi> writes to say that the Abp. of C. has asked him to be Bishop of Accra, and to ask whether he ought to accept the offer. I reply that probably he ought to do so. </p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Shildon, and confirmed a poor girl who was said to be dying, or nearly so. Her brother, a pleasant&#8211;faced youth of 21, was changing his clothes in preparation for his work in the mine, where he filled the pony's lorries. I noticed the cuts &amp; scars on his legs, which, he said were caused by the coal. His names was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas William Johnson.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to the Bishop of Norwich enclosing Bp. Knox's letter, &amp; asking his opinion thereupon. Knox advises the convening of a Conference of the followers of Paige&#8211;Cox and Inskip<persName xml:id="4783"></persName> to agree upon a policy of P.B. Revision, and suggests that such a Conference might be convened by the Bishops of Norwich, Durham, &amp; Gloucester. But I doubt if even these three could agree on anything!</p></body></text></TEI>