<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfasting with Lord S. I walked to the Club, and then to the watch&#8211;makers, Bennett, 105 Regent Street, where I left my watch to be repaired. Then I went to Hugh Rees, &amp; ordered some books. I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended the meeting of the Commission. I lunched at the Deanery, and then returned to the Commission. A general approval was given to my scheme for revising the constitution of Durham Cathedral.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury was evidently perturbed by what I said to him last night, for he sent me a telephone message asking me to meet him at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> at 6 p.m. He also sent me a note suggesting that I sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> write a letter to him asking for an explanation of his speech to the Canterbury Diocesan Conference. He w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> take occasion in answering it to remove any misunderstanding. I met his Grace as appointed and we had a very interesting talk over the whole situation.</hi><hi rend="italic">Finally I wrote a letter (copy appended) and handed it to him, adding that whatever he wrote to me in reply, I should certainly publish. So the plot thickens.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1923</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Archbishop,</p>
         <p>The report of the Canterbury Diocesan Magazine for last August attributes to your Grace some language respecting the Bishop's power to authorize disobedience to the rubricks of the Prayer Book, which is certainly capable of being misunderstood, and which I find it hard to reconcile with the known views of your Grace often expressed in the past.</p>
         <p>The subject is important in itself, and at this time so urgent that I take leave to beg your Grace to explain your words. I have reason to know that an explanation would be welcomed by many besides myself.</p>
         <p>With apologies for placing this burden on your Grace at a time when so much anxiety is coming upon you.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Most sincerely &amp; dutifully yours</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The most Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> &amp; Right Hon<hi rend="superscript underline">ble</hi></p>
         <p>The Lord Archbishop of Canterbury</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Archbishop said that he had read my article in the "Spectator", and, when he put it down, he said to himself, What would Henson do if he had a free hand? I replied that my policy was as clear as it was simple. In view of the general disobedience of the clergy, I would revise the formularies, Prayer Book and Articles both, and I would simplify the legal procedure so as to make possible the enforcement of the revised books, &amp; then I w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> enforce them inexorably. But that would mean disruption, he said, "I assumed that it would, and disruption seems to me unavoidable if the Church of England is to exist in anything more than name". But, said his Grace, I will never be the Abp. to force a disruption. I must be out of the way first. We spoke of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Frere's</hi><persName xml:id="2021"></persName><hi rend="italic"> elevation to the Bench. I said that it was in my judgement defensible only on the assumption that the Reformation Settlement was dead. He said that he was anxious about the negotiations at Malines,<note xml:id="539" n="1"></note> &amp; had adapted some instructions for the guidance of the Anglican representatives. He had showed these to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Frere</hi><hi rend="italic">, who professed to agree with them heartily. The Archbishop is certainly being very hard driven, and, I think, in directions which he does not like, and towards ends which in his heart of hearts he does not approve.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>