<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>I started work on the Westminster Sermon. My intention is to utilize the associations of November 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> in order to point to the real issue of Prayer Book Revision viz. whether the Church of England should, or should not, continue to be Protestant.</p>
         <p>The Rev. Charles J. Lockyer, curate of Leadgate, came to see me. He has a long list of grievances against his Vicar, which may, or may not be substantial. On the principle "Audi alteram partem"<note xml:id="540" n="1"></note>, I would not discuss them, but said that they disclosed a measure of friction which must be prohibitive of useful cooperation. I bade him therefore hand in his three months notice, &amp; seek another curacy, &amp; I suggested Beamish or South Westoe.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I walked with Jack in the Park, &amp; asked him to be executor to my will. I said I sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> leave to him Stanley's Clock &amp; table.</hi></p>
         <p>This is the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> anniversary of my Enthronement in Durham Cathedral. These 3 years have been laborious &amp; inconclusive. I feel farther from solving the personal problem than ever. Ought I to have taken episcopal office? Ought I to have accepted the bishoprick of Durham? The development of the system created by the Enabling Act has more than confirmed my worst fears. It has become increasingly doubtful whether the conditions of episcopal office in the Church of England will continue to be tolerable to a self&#8211;respecting man.</p></body></text></TEI>