<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The Church of England receives the first four general councils as of highest regard, not that they are infallible, but that they have determined wisely and holily.</p>
         <p>Jeremy Taylor VI. 360</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote again to Ernest respecting the woeful business of S. Then I settled down to my Address for the Diocesan Conference, until I was interrupted by Turner, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's, West Hartlepool, who came to talk over the questions of making a "conventional district" out of his parish. After him came the new curate from Stockton, Thompson: he in turn was followed by the Appletons, father &amp; son.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> took the Emmotts<persName xml:id="1246"><persName xml:id="2228"></persName></persName> for a motor drive after lunch, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me on a walk round the Park with the dogs. On returning to the Castle, I resumed work on the Address.</p>
         <p>Sir Arthur<persName xml:id="5262"></persName> &amp; Lady Pease, &amp; Colonel M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dowell came to dinner and we were sufficiently cheerful.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Lord Grey of Falloden has a long letter in the "Times" headed "Europe at the Cross Roads". It is expressed in melancholy, almost minatory language: describes the conduct of Italy in severe terms: declares the union of England &amp; France to be indispensable: and exalts the League as the one hope of the world</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p></body></text></TEI>