<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Amongst so many so huge volumes as the infinite pains of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Augustine have brought forth, what one hath gotten him greater love, commendation &amp; honour than the book wherein he carefully collecteth his own oversights, and sincerely condemneth them?</p>
         <p>Richard Hooker. Pref. to E.P.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I meditate a charge to the Ordinandi which shall deal with their duty in respect of controversy, since it is certain that at least the first years of their ministry will be passed in a controversy&#8211;distracted church. But it is not easy to speak sincerely, or wisely, or usefully on that subject.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> writes to ask me to write one of his series of Tracts viz: the one on "The Sacramental Presence". But, though I would very willingly associate myself with him in his effort, I did not think it advisable for a Bishop to be a tractarian! I suggested that he might invite the cooperation of Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, the Rector of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring.</p>
         <p>Several acknowledgements of copies of "In Defence" arrived, proving that the publishers had at least carried out my instructions.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed 116 persons in S. Luke's church. These were presented from the two parishes – S Luke's and Holy Trinity. I was pleased with the demeanour both of the candidates and the congregation. Also I saw with satisfaction that Warth gave to his candidates so comparatively harmless a Communion book as Walsham How's<persName xml:id="5374"></persName>.</p></body></text></TEI>