<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1923.</hi></p>
         <p>It is not without a melancholy significance that the consecration of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's, Boldon, yesterday was the first function of the kind that I have been called upon to perform during an episcopate of nearly six years. In Bishop Lightfoot's<persName xml:id="1817"></persName> time the consecrations of new churches happened every year. But then the men and the money were available. Now &#8211;!</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 9.10 a.m. and motored to Sunderland, picking up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in Durham on the way. In the parish church I collated Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> to the Rectory, preached, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. Save for the coughing of the school children, who ought not to have been present, I was pleased with the service. Both the newly elected members for Sunderland were present. I lunched at the Rectory, and then motored to Seaham Harbour where I preached to a congregation of Freemasons in the parish church, and afterwards had tea with the Vicar. Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName>, Lord Londonderry's<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> agent, was there with his wife &amp; daughter, all mightily chagrined at the result of the election in their division, for which Sydney Webbe has been again returned. Then I motored back to Auckland going by way of Eppleton, in order to leave Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> there as he had undertaken to preach in the parish church. I reached the castle at twenty minutes before seven o'clock. The weather was bright but bitterly cold.</p></body></text></TEI>