<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[213]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>An Ordination candidate, Arthur Norris, came to see me. He is the son of a foreman&#8211;engineer at Jarrow, has been educated in a secondary school, &amp; has taken his degree at Durham with honours. I was generally impressed with him.</p>
         <p>Christopher Birney, a lad of 15, the son of the new Vicar of Witton Park<persName xml:id="5383"></persName>, came to see me. He too aspires to be ordained. I said that if he passed matriculation to Durham, I would consider his application.</p>
         <p>Chute, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's, West Hartlepool, came to dine and sleep. A very attractive, honest, hard&#8211;working man. If only we had more of his type and training!</p>
         <p>During the afternoon I motored to Durham, &amp; saw Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> about divers items of business. The Chapel Committee of the School are disposed to take up an attitude of unreasoning opposition to the proposed new road: and set aside my suggestion of a conference with the Surveyor with a promptitude which argued, perhaps, a lack of the respect due to their Diocesan. But one must make allowances for disappointment, &amp; chagrin. It is <hi rend="underline">never</hi> worth while to indulge the sentiment of personal injury: and I shall not allow myself to do so now. But I make a note of the incident.</p></body></text></TEI>