<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I can only consider Gothic art as a part of the medieval revival which distinguishes our age and seems to me as important as the revival of pagan learning in the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. It is the culminating point of my reactionary and contracted opinions that a Grecian building, especially a church, seems to me as great an anachronism now as an invocation of Apollo and the muses in a poem. <hi rend="underline">Quid plura</hi>? I have condemned myself.</p>
         <p>Lord Acton. Feb 1859.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I gave a final revision to the Article, and sent it off to the Editor of the "<hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century and After</hi>". An ordination candidate named Cole was brought to me by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> – another Knutsford man, now at King's College, London. He stayed to lunch, and afterwards went with me to Durham. I presided at a meeting of the Sons of the Clergy, where we voted &#x00A3;52 to the widow of poor Brewer, and &#x00A3;37:10:0 to that woeful M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rooker. On returning to Auckland, I wrote to the Bishop of Bradford asking him whether he could find a place for the woeful curate. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> thinks, as I do, that it is not possible for him to find a place in the diocese. The curate at Hartlepool wrote to say that he was leaving the diocese because there was no prospect of "promotion"!</p></body></text></TEI>