<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The bitter weather continues, and lowers everybody's vitality with the result that this cursed Influenza kills many. Geeson, the Vicar of Witton Park died this morning. He was tackling that woeful parish with much energy, &amp; beginning to make an impression on it.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Kimbleworth, where I took part in the future [funeral] of Elder, the Incumbent. Both these clergymen were comparatively young, 45 &amp; 57, and both were working well. How are they to be replaced?</p>
         <p>We went on to Sunderland, and had tea with Wynne&#8211;Wilson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>. Both he and his wife seem well and cheerful. I begin to allow myself to believe that this appointment will justify itself. Then we went on to Jarrow Grange, where I confirmed 109 candidates. There had been an epidemic of influenza in this district, and the effect was disclosed in an avalanche of coughing! Apart from this very trying circumstance, the service pleased me, for the candidates were of a reasonable age, and carried themselves with earnestness and devotion. We returned to Auckland by way of Gateshead, arriving about 9. 45 p.m. The Conformations so far are:&#8211; </p>
         <p>1. Jarrow, S Peter 83</p>
         <p>2. Hetton&#8211;le&#8211;hole 110</p>
         <p>3. Jarrow Grange 109</p>
         <p>=302 candiates</p></body></text></TEI>