<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. After breakfast I wrote a letter of condolence to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Geeson. Also, I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, who appears to be very solitary in Batavia. <hi rend="bold underline">Also, I accepted the invitation of the Gray's Inn Benchers to preach on July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> when representatives of the American Bar will visit this country.</hi> Also, I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Coley, the doctor in Newcastle, who had criticised with discrimination &amp; civility my speech in the H. of Lords.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with the dogs. Neck distinguished himself by taking feathers out of one of Bryden's hens. There are also rumours that she has been observed to chase the sheep in the outer Park. These are disquieting circumstances, and portend a tragedy!</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to Croxdale, where I preached at Evensong. The population of the parish exceeds 1700, but the congregation could hardly have been more than 100. And the parson did not appear to be discontented with this situation. The squire, Salvin<persName xml:id="3528"></persName>, is a Roman Catholic, and there are some 30 families of his co&#8211;religionists. We may deduct 200 on this account. One third of the men &amp; lads might be working on their shift in the pits, and half of the people would perhaps describe themselves as Nonconformists of one description or another. Then there would be the sick, young, aged, who could not attend service in Church. I suppose 100 represents about one third of the available folk.</p></body></text></TEI>