<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[134]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The Greeks told no fewer lies than other races, but they had the desire and the power to see the world as it is. So they came to give Europe the conceptions of philosophy and science. There we inherit from them alone; Palestine and our German ancestors neither created them, not show any signs of the temper which creates them, and Rome received her share from Greece.</p>
         <p>R. W. Livingstone, "The Pageant of Greece" p. 10</p>
         </div>
         <p>The strike of engine&#8211;drivers and firemen began at midnight yesterday. Whereto will this grow? is the inevitable question. In a diseased state of the body politic, as in that of the body physical, a scratch may have fatal results.</p>
         <p>I finished the Stockton sermon – a thin yet stilted composition! The inconveniences of the strike were immediately apparent. Neither the "Manchester Guardian" nor the "Times" arrived at all, &amp; the other papers with the letters arrived late.</p>
         <p>I have to speak in Stockton on the theme "What we owe to the Reformation", and I meditate whether it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be wise to refer to Malines, and if so what reference it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be judicious to make, the Abp's supporters, and among them must be reckoned nearly all the bishops, are striving to belittle the whole episode, which they were equally prepared to magnify a month ago!</p></body></text></TEI>