<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The new Dean of Carlisle is the socialist Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Philips Newcastle! It is a great fall to pass from Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> to Moll</hi><persName xml:id="5379"></persName><hi rend="bold">!</hi> There can be no concealing the decline in learning &amp; consequence which recent appointments disclose. Chase, Wace, and Rashdall give place to White Thompson<persName xml:id="5378"></persName>, Bell, and Moll.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and lunched in S. Chad's College on the occasion of the annual festival. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName> proposed the toast of "Church and King" coupling my name with it. I responded, &amp; took the occasion to speak about the shortage of clergy. After lunch we all descended to the chapel by 34 steps, and there I dedicated a reredos erected to the memory of the 16 members of the college who had fallen during the War. The service was extremely well&#8211;arranged. Then we motored to Jarrow where I had tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilburne</hi>, &amp; afterwards interviewed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Woods</hi>, the curate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Jude's Tynedock in his study. I dissuaded him from leaving the diocese, and recommended him to another curacy. Then we went to S. Peter's, and there I confirmed more than 30 candidates. We returned to Auckland immediately after the service.</p>
         <p>The Church is very weak in the Rural Deanery of Jarrow. A considerable proportion of the people is composed of Irish Papists, and there are many Nonconformists, not perhaps of the best type. The district has "developed" very rapidly, &amp; there are no traditions, and but few educated residents.</p></body></text></TEI>