<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We may, upon the evidence before us, take it for certain that Byron only admired two of his contemporaries – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Scott</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shelley</hi>. He liked <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hobhouse</hi>, &amp; they had travelled together without a serious quarrel, which is a proof of friendship; but he felt that Hobhouse undervalued him, and, as Byron had a good deal of the spoiled child about him, he resented the friendly admonitions which, it seems, Hobhouse unsparingly administered whenever they were together. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tom Moore</hi> was a "croney" – a man to laugh &amp; sit through the night with – but there was nothing, either in his genius or his conduct, which Byron could fall down &amp; worship, as he seemed capable of doing in the case of Shelley and Scott.</p>
         <p>Edgcumbe "Byron, the last Phase" p. 35</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to South Shields via Sunderland, as the direct road was reported bad. After having tea with Pryke at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's Vicarage, I attended a meeting in aid of the League of Nations Union held in a Wesleyan chapel &amp; presided over by the Mayor. The audience was mostly old or middle&#8211;aged, and evidently gathered from the congregations of the churches &amp; chapels. I spoke for 45 minutes.</p></body></text></TEI>