<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[179]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I travelled to London by the early train, and, after leaving my bags in Park Lane, went on to Westminster, where I attended the meeting of the Patronage Commission. I lunched at the House of Lords, &amp; then wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. After attending the Commission until 4 p.m., I returned to the H. of Lords, where I took the oath and attended the House. Lord Olivier,<persName xml:id="5839"></persName> the new Secretary for India, made a long speech (1 hour &amp; 20 minutes) which I found difficulty in hearing. Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> spoke admirably for 50 minutes. I hastened to Park Lane, &amp; changed. I dined with the Club. There were but five members present viz Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, Lord Crawford<persName xml:id="5377"></persName>, Lord Dunedin<persName xml:id="5405"></persName>, Sir H. Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName> &amp; myself. We talked a great deal, but not very fruitfully! Lord S. asked me about Walters, who was once a curate of mine. He seemed to have impressed him as a preacher. <hi rend="bold underline">Lord S. said that he would be glad if I could recommend to him any of my clergy who, in my opinion, might fairly be asked to preach to H.M. I am afraid there is not much use in suggesting men who read &amp; think. They would "preach over the King's head", as Lord S. phrases it! Rank and jocosity are the requisites</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>