<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[186]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Shrove Tuesday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Duncan of Willington and Nairne Clark of Hunstanworth came to see me, and had lunch. The first wished to talk over the case of the unhappy Burgess who he would like to have as a curate in spite of his record: the last wanted to consult me about divers parochial embarrassments. <hi rend="bold underline">The local Dissenter desired to have his young men confirmed with the clear understanding that, after confirmation, they would remain sectaries! This appears to have been the custom under the former incumbent! I ruled that confirmation implied the intention of churchmanship</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>"Close dances" are demoralizing his parish. He had taken a strong line against them, thereby alienating the youth. Was he right? I recommended a middle way: let him attempt to reform the dancing, &amp; not to be carried into a Puritanic severity which could not really be justified. </p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with the dogs, and then set out for Hetton&#8211;le&#8211;Hole, where I confirmed 109 persons. The parson, Smith, is a rough&#8211;looking little man, but he seems to have influence with his people, and I was certainly pleased with the Confirmation. After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The weather continues bitterly cold, and there seems prospect of more snow.</p></body></text></TEI>