<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Peace hath her victories</p>
         <p>No less renown'd than War; new foes arise,</p>
         <p>Threatening to bind our souls with secular chains</p>
         <p>Help us to save free conscience from the paw</p>
         <p>Of hireling wolves, whose gospel is their maw.</p>
         <p>Milton, 1652</p>
         </div>
         <p>The warmth of the weather last night was uncomfortable. I could not sleep, and felt the fact throughout the day. I wrote letters, &amp; worked at a sermon for next Sunday. I received letters from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Carson</hi> and the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dean of Westminster</hi> thanking me for my letter in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>": also, the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Editor of the "Nineteenth Century and After</hi>" asked me to write an article on "Reunion". The "Times" publishes a statement from its correspondent in Rome, which must needs be annoying to the Archbishop since it categorically denies that the Pope had any official "cognisance" of the conferences at Malines. <hi rend="bold underline">It was specifically on the understanding that the Pope did so far countenance the venture that his Grace went into it.</hi> Cardinal Mercier<persName xml:id="3626"></persName> must be called upon for an explanation, for he was responsible for misleading the Archbishop.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> went to a dance at Rokeby, leaving me to entertain the Smiths! </p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi>" has a leading article filled with sycophantic adulation of the Archbishop.</p></body></text></TEI>