<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[218]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished Byron, and sent the M.S. registered to the Cambridge Press.</hi></p>
         <p>Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName> came to lunch bringing with him an Eton master named Martin, and his two boys. I showed them the castle, and had some talk about the failure of the public schools to supply Ordination candidates.</p>
         <p>The weather reverted to winter. We drove to Southwick in sleet and rain, through a snow&#8211;whitened country. At S. Columba's, Southwick, I confirmed 102 persons. This is a parish, half of the inhabitants of which are said to be miners, and the rest mostly shipyard workers. The population is 8000: the income &#x00A3;380 net: &amp; the patronage belongs to the Bishop. The Vicar – H. F. MacMunn – has held office for 7 years. He is an Anglo&#8211;Catholic, though not of the wildest type. He has two insignificant looking curates, whom I myself ordained. They would seem better cut out for office boys than clergymen! Yet they will in due course be set in charge of populous parishes.</p>
         <p>Lomax of Ferryhill came to see me. He says that the fanatical socialist, Macmanus, whose aspect &amp; vehement speech in the Diocesan Conference arrested attention, is a saint, works as one of his staff, and aspires to Ordination! I said he might come and see me. What people like Lomax will not consider is the <hi rend="underline">future</hi> of these ardent illiterates whom they encourage to seek Orders. How could they ever be appointed to incumbencies?</p></body></text></TEI>