<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName> spoke hopefully of the liberal Evangelical campaign which he and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> are leading. He says that they are organizing a counter&#8211;crusade against the crusade of the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics". Thus at Nottingham where an "A.C." mission has just be concluded, they have arranged a series of public lectures in answer. He himself is going to speak on "Reservation". The town&#8211;hall is crowded for these occasions. The spectacle of such open conflict between members of the same church can hardly be edifying, &amp; may well give occasion to the Lord's enemies to blaspheme, but it is difficult to resist the belief that even this scandal may in the long run be less hurtful to Religion than to suffer this sacerdotalist corruption to prevail unrebuked. At least it is a new force that is entering the arena, &amp; may, even at the eleventh hour, change the fortunes of the day. <hi rend="bold underline">The tub&#8211;thumping "No Popery" type of Protestantism has had it day, and commands no following except among the illiterate</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It is, however, hard to discover any adequate alternative to the aesthetic attractions of the "Anglo&#8211;Catholics". The "shop&#8211;boy" ritualist represents a numerous type. He cannot think, and he cares little for truth, but he feels, and he is avid for excitement and amusement. Morally, he is not of a strong type, and the confessional, if it does not always or often reform his habits, does certainly propitiate his conscience and relieve his mind. How is <hi rend="underline">he</hi> to be dealt with?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to Westminster, and had an interview with Downing at the Ecclesiastical Commission about the proposed new road into Bishop Auckland. He had heard nothing about it, but promised to keep me informed of any action which the Commissioner would take. He said that he thought the local authority could exercise compulsion if necessary in acquiring the land. Then I called on Barnes, who was absent from home: &amp; De Candole, with whom I had half an hour's talk. After lunching in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I had an interview with an Ordination Candidate, Hill, another Knutsford man of the usual rough type. He would come forward in September. I left King's Cross at 5.30 p.m., &amp; travelled to Darlington, where William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> met me with the car. Before going to bed, I went through the correspondence. Another incumbent writes to say that the doctor insists on his resigning his parish forthwith. Of course he is penniless, married, and the father of three young children! What with the preferment of assistant curates to livings in other dioceses, and the failure of health before the severity of the Durham climate &amp; the size of the Durham parishes, there will soon be no incumbents left! The two normal causes of "wastage" viz. death and retirement, are as operative in Durham as elsewhere. The shortage of candidates for Ordination grows worse. Indeed the prospects for this year are very black. I have so far heard of no candidates for Trinity at all, i.e. no deacons. This must be unprecedented.</p></body></text></TEI>