<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[210]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Church&#8211;ladders are not always mounted best</p>
         <p>By learned clerks and Latinists profess'd.</p>
         <p>The exalted prize demands an upward look,</p>
         <p>Not to be found by poring on a book.</p>
         <p>Small skill in Latin, and less in Greek,</p>
         <p>Is more than adequate to all I seek.</p>
         <p>Cowper "Tirocinium" 1784</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communions in the Castle Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I wrote a series of letters including one to the new Headmaster suggesting that he should be ordained. Also, I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> and Jimmie Dobbie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>, to Ernest, &amp; to the two girls, Penelope &amp; Blanche, who are to be confirmed on Palm Sunday. In the afternoon I prepared notes for the sermon which I preached at Evensong in Trimdon Church. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to this service. Pestle<persName xml:id="5238"></persName> came in to supper, &amp; I had some talk with him about his future. I offered to recommend him to Parry Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName> in the event of Hunwick becoming vacant. He rather jumped at the notion. I took occasion to utter some cautions on the subject of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism". He disclaimed any sympathy with the extremists; but, of course, there is no logical halting&#8211;point between moderate &amp; extreme victims of the same fallacy. It is more a matter of temperament than of reason in both cases. The moderates always are beaten when the issues of conduct are brought into debate.</p></body></text></TEI>