<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Besides, my Muse, by no means deals in fiction:</p>
         <p>She gathers a repertory of facts,</p>
         <p>Of course with some reserve and slight restriction,</p>
         <p>But mostly sings of human kings and acts – </p>
         <p>And that's one cause she meets with contradiction;</p>
         <p>For too much truth, at first sight, ne'er attracts;</p>
         <p>And were her object only what's called Glory,</p>
         <p>With more ease too she'd tell a different story.</p>
         <p>"Don Juan" Canto XIV s. xiii</p>
         </div>
         <p>After writing of the necessary letters, I fell to working at this woeful "Rede" lecture on Byron, which grows more formidable daily. <hi rend="doubleunderline">How</hi> from Durham came to lunch, and stayed the afternoon. We walked in the Park together. He wanted to sound me about the project of handing over the Castle at Durham to the Board of Works. I don't like it, but I can see that it may be necessary. Also, he told me that Pestle's<persName xml:id="5238"></persName> fellowship would not be renewed. Would it be possible to place him in the diocese? I was vaguely encouraging.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Old Canon Fowler's death is reported. He is the last of the great trinity of Durham antiquaries – Greenwell, Hodgson &amp; Fowler, who died at the ages of 96, 90 &amp; 91. There must be something particularly healthful about the study &amp; habit of antiquarians</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p></body></text></TEI>