<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[180]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather was bitterly cold. I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and spent the morning there, save that I went out &amp; had my hair cut. After lunching in the Club, I walked to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and attended a meeting of the Ecclesiastical Court Commission. Justice Sankey<persName xml:id="3403"></persName> was on my left, &amp; D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Darwell Stone<persName xml:id="4414"></persName> on my right. We had some rather illuminating discussion on the question, Whether a final court could be created which should satisfy Anglo&#8211;Catholic principles. The question was left undecided, but 'twas clear enough that <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi> could satisfy Darwell Stone &amp; his following. I went over to the House of Lords, where L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Buxton asked a question about the threatened Coal Strike. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Gainford<persName xml:id="2216"></persName> made a speech, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">then I was fool enough to make a speech myself. I spoke without preparation, &amp; to no good end</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I dined in the Athenaeum, having "Fish" Cecil<persName xml:id="31"></persName> as my table&#8211;mate. He told me that not only had he <hi rend="underline">not</hi> authorized Bishop Masterman to make a pronouncement on the subject of dividing the Exeter diocese, but Bishop Masterman had himself promised not to do so! The snow was falling fast, &amp; there was a substantial covering of snow on the street, when I returned from the Club to Park Lane.</p></body></text></TEI>