<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Headlam died yesterday in a nursing home at Gloucester. The Bishop of Gloucester telegraphed the news, &amp; added a request that I would officiate at Whorlton, where the funeral will take place on Friday</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>The gardener picked up a large brown owl in the garden. It was living, but injured probably by rooks, &amp; died during the night.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I succeeded in finishing the Edinburgh Article, &amp; sent it off to the Editor. It doesn't please me, but I can do nothing better</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>We motored into Durham, where I licensed two curates, &amp; lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Then we went to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, where I confirmed 96 candidates. After tea with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, we went on to S. Aidan's, South Shields, where I confirmed 135 candidates. In all the confirmations in this town, the fewness of males is very marked. Why is this? We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Sir Fredrick Bridge died yesterday</hi>. He was 80 years old, a kindly old man enough, amusingly vain &amp; egotistical. More popular, perhaps with the unmusical multitude, than with the musical few. He tried us too much at Westminster by his incapacity to train the choir, by his ill choice of music, by the frequency with which he caused his own compositions to be sung in the Abbey&#8211;church, so that the profane spoke of our "Bridge parties", and, most of all by his incorrigible and untimely jocosity. But he had many loveable traits, and on the whole we liked him well enough.</p></body></text></TEI>