<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Between two worlds Life hovers like a star, </p>
         <p>'Twixt Night and Morn, upon the horizon's verge,</p>
         <p>How little do we know that which we are!</p>
         <p>How less what we may be! The eternal surge</p>
         <p>Of Time and Tide rolls on and bears afar</p>
         <p>Our bubbles; as the old burst, new emerge,</p>
         <p>Lashed from the foam of ages; while the graves </p>
         <p>Of Empires heave but like some passing waves.</p>
         <p>"Don Juan" canto XV, stanza xcix.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote letters, and squandered time on "Byron". Then I walked in the Park. At 5 p.m. I motored to South Shields, and confirmed 113 persons in S. Mary's Tyne dock. This confirmation pleased me well. The sexes were not very unevenly divided. 48 males to 65 females: the candidates were of a good age, &amp; gave me the impression of great earnestness and resolution. There was a considerable, and well&#8211;behaved congregation. This is an "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" church but of a comparatively moderate type. Both Vicar and curate are unmarried men, who get on well together, &amp; are keen about their work. The curate, Strong<persName xml:id="5382"></persName>, is one of the best of the men whom I have myself ordained: but then he is a parson's son, his father being an incumbent in the Midlands. That type has now become almost extinct. After service we returned to Auckland arriving about 10 pm.</p></body></text></TEI>