<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is too true, indeed, that there is a miserable rent in the church, and I make no questions but the best men do most bemoan it, nor is he a Christian, that would not have unity, might he have it with truth. But I never said, nor thought, "that the Protestants made this rent". The cause of the schism is yours: for you thrust us from you, because we called for truth and redress of abuses. For a schism must needs be theirs, whose the cause of it is.</p>
         <p>Laud<persName xml:id="3468"></persName>. Conference with Fisher. P. 150</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wasted the whole day in writing letters, in making notes for a Convocation speech, &amp; in walking &amp; talking with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName>. He is a puzzling mixture of independence &amp; bigotry. His attitude towards the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" movement is far more sympathetic than I should have thought possible. Indeed, he seems to be quite indifferent to the moral turpitude of the casuistry which explains away the most solemn undertakings and justifies the most shameless disobedience. <hi rend="bold underline">He expressed his cordial appreciation &amp; approval of the proceedings at Malines.</hi></p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> sent me Miss Burrell's contribution of &#x00A3;100 towards the purchase of the hoardings sites in Durham. This is a welcome and unexpected assistance.</p></body></text></TEI>