<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[222]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant morning with a white frost. The change to summer time brought us all out of bed an hour earlier than usual. We were rewarded by the lights in the Chapel which looked beautiful when we gathered for the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and Frank Berry communicated.</p>
         <p>After breakfast I wrote letters, and prepared notes for my Confirmation Addresses. <hi rend="bold underline">I sent an amended form of the resolution, which I propose to move at the next meeting of Convocation</hi>, to the Abp of York. It now runs thus:&#8211; </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>That, in order to facilitate the Ordination of Candidates whose poverty renders it necessary that they should maintain themselves at a relatively early age, it is expedient that Ordination to the Diaconate should at the Bishop's discretion take place at the age of twenty&#8211;one years, and that in the case of men so ordained the Diaconate should continue for a period of not less than three years.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote to the Bishop of Ripon asking him to second the resolution. <hi rend="bold underline">Also I wrote to Murray explaining exactly how my arrangements stood, and saying that if he persisted in making me come to the Byron luncheon, I would do so in spite of the inconvenience.</hi></p>
         <p>In the afternoon I confirmed 204 persons in South Church. Among them were Penelope Webbe<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> and Blanche Lawrie. In the evening I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's and confirmed 69 candidates from that parish. A very pleasing service.</p></body></text></TEI>