<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The most serious danger of modern society is not, as some short&#8211;sighted critics imagine, the tendency to anarchy, but the desire to find some absolute and final authority. It is the doctrine of absolute authority which is the greatest danger of our time, and it is not less dangerous when it masquerades under the form of democracy.</p>
         <p>A.J. Carlyle v. "The Return to Christendom" p. 118</p>
         </div>
         <p>The first "Labour" or "Socialist" ministry is announced in the papers. It includes three peers! Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName> goes to the woolsack: Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parmoor</hi><persName xml:id="1736"></persName> is President of the Council: and Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chelmsford</hi><persName xml:id="65"></persName> is Secretary of the Admiralty. The last is surprising enough. His Lordship was ever thought to be a Tory. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lenin's</hi> death is reported, and this time the report seems to be true. He was not yet 54 years old, and he has wrecked a world!</p>
         <p>I motored with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> to Barnard Castle. There I called on the Headmaster of the N.E. Counties' School, &amp; learned his reasons for refusing to lend the School Building for a Ball. We looked at the ruins of the Castle, &amp; visited the quaint medieval house in which Oliver Cromwell is said to have passed a night. Then we had tea in the King's Head, and parted, he remaining in the Hotel in order to return to Sedburgh by the early train tomorrow, I motoring back to Auckland. The fog was so thick that William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> found it difficult to keep the road, &amp; our journey took over an hour to accomplish.</p></body></text></TEI>