<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>By this (i.e. the inability of the ancient church to determine the Christian's duty in the matter of Easter observance) you may plainly see the danger of our appeal to antiquity, for resolution in controverted points of faith, and how small relief we are to expect from thence; for if the discretion of the chiefest guides and directors of the church, did in a point so trivial, so inconsiderable, so mainly fail them, as not to see the truth in a subject; wherein it is the greatest marvel how they could avoid the sight of it: can we, without imputation of extreme grossness and folly, think so poor&#8211;spirited persons competent judges of the questions now on foot betwixt the churches?</p>
         <p>John Hales<persName xml:id="2184"></persName> of Eton "Concerning Schism"</p>
         </div>
         <p>The tract on "<hi rend="underline">Schism and Schismaticks</hi>" appears to have been written about 1636, probably for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chillingworth</hi><persName xml:id="551"></persName>, who was then engaged on his "<hi rend="underline">Religion of Protestants</hi>" (1637). It was circulated in manuscript, &amp; a copy fell into the hands of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Laud</hi><persName xml:id="3468"></persName>, who sent for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hales</hi>, &amp; satisfied himself sufficiently to make him a chaplain. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hales's</hi> letter to the Archbishop vindicating himself is "a model of firmness &amp; good humour". He is said to have assisted Laud in the second edition (1639) of his "<hi rend="underline">Conference</hi>" with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fisher</hi>. The tract of "<hi rend="underline">Schism</hi>" was not printed till 1642.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName>, enclosing one from his friend, the French Modernist, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Houtin</hi><persName xml:id="1876"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">It appears that in France the conversations at Malines are connected with the King's visit to the Pope, during his stay in Rome a few months ago, and that both are suppose to be inspired by the British government!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Little</hi> wrote again expressing his belief that the woeful cleric could and would repay the money that he had stolen, &amp; begging that, if he did so, he should be given a <hi rend="underline">locus poenitentiae</hi> [a place for repentence]. Also, the poor wretch himself wrote, promising to repay all, expressing repentance, and praying for mercy. After lunch I motored to Walworth Castle, and had an interview with <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Sir Alfred Palmer</hi><hi rend="bold underline">who agreed that, if the money were refunded this week, there should be no persecution. On my return home, I wrote to Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, sending him all the letters, &amp; suggesting that if he were really prepared to take the unhappy man on to his staff, the way was open for him to do so. I wrote also to Little, and the unhappy man himself. So that matter stands.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to Foakes&#8211;Jackson<persName xml:id="3566"></persName>, inviting him to continue the good practice of writing to me from America.</p>
         <p>I wasted some time in attempting the little article on "<hi rend="underline">Reunion</hi>" for the "<hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century, &amp; After</hi>", but I made no progress. This woeful and humiliating case of discipline so fills my mind that it seems impossible to think steadily of anything else.</p></body></text></TEI>