<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I motored to Barnard Castle, and presided over a meeting of the Governors of the N.E. Counties School. The business was of exceptional importance, &amp; no less than 17 governors attended. We had to co&#8211;opt 3 governors, and there were 5 candidates. <hi rend="bold underline">I could not but feel a certain satisfaction at the fact that Bircham<persName xml:id="5380"></persName>, the Vicar of Barnard Castle, was not re&#8211;elected. This rebuff was a reply to his recent rudeness to his bishop</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>But, though pleased, I could not avoid a certain sympathy for the man as he sate, at the council&#8211;board, from which his absence was so plainly desired by his colleagues. Then we went to the election of a new headmaster, and to my great surprise, a man named Coombes was elected. He was far from being the best candidate, but he let it be known that he was a dissenter, and that settled the election. The majority of the governors are also dissenters! I had not thought he was in the running, so plainly superior were at least three others. Two thirds of the boys are Church boys.</p>
         <p>After the business was concluded, I returned to Auckland by way of Darlington in order to give Knowlden<persName xml:id="5439"></persName> a lift homewards. He is so changed in appearance since his illness when he allowed his beard to grow, that I find it difficult to recognize him.</p></body></text></TEI>