<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[221]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Heresy, it must be remembered, is a product of the Church, and, ere it could be excommunicated, has been in communion often with such tenacity, as to leave it doubtful for a whole generation what hand would carry off the banner of orthodoxy: The great ecclesiastical heroes won all their victories over fellow&#8211;disciples.</p>
         <p>Martineau p. 164</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Murray writes to invite me to the Byron Centenary Celebration Luncheon on April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, &amp; asks that I </hi><hi rend="bold">w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> speak on the Toast of Byron and Mankind along with the late Prime Minister. The date is most convenient [sic], but the invitation is hard to decline.</hi></p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> and Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName> came to lunch, and afterwards went with me to Stillington, where I instituted Morris Young to the Vicarage. There was a fair congregation, and an atmosphere of goodwill, which allowed me to indulge the hope that the new ministry would be harmonious. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went to Hartlepool, and as my representative attended the funeral of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Morrison. He joined me at Stillington in the course of the service.</p>
         <p>The pastures have an avid aspect more suitable for the late summer than to the early spring. Indeed the absence of rain combined with the severity of the frost has brought the stock&#8211;farmer into no slight difficulty. There is no grass in the fields, &amp; their supplies of fodder are running out. We returned to Auckland after the institution, &amp; William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> carried Wilson into Durham.</p></body></text></TEI>