<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The motif of Manfred is remorse – eternal suffering for inexplicable crime…. Manfred is no echo of another's questioning, no expression of a general world&#8211;weariness on the part of the time&#8211;spirit, <hi rend="underline">but a personal outcry</hi>: "De profundis clamavi!"</p>
         <p>Introduction to Manfred. vol. iv. P. 82</p>
         </div>
         <p>I can put no other meaning on these words than one which assumes that Byron was guilty of an incestuous love for his half&#8211;sister: but in that case, all his other poetry must be read in the light of this astounding fact. The tender &amp; beautiful "Epistle to Augusta" is then seen to be charged with an intolerable eroticism.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">This Byron lecture wastes much time.</hi> The mere necessary task of going through the poetry &amp; letters consumes hours that could be better applied in my proper tasks. Nor can I cheat myself into thinking that I gain much from soaking my mind with so much venom &amp; vice!</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Mainsforth, and had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Surtees. Some bedrooms have been added to the house, but mostly it remains as it was in the time when Sir Walter Scott was entertained under its roof. But the collieries have crept up very close to the house, &amp; the general aspect of the neighbourhood is sufficiently squalid.</p>
         <p>The day was calm &amp; comparatively mild.</p></body></text></TEI>