<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">Wordsworth</hi> &amp; <hi rend="underline">Coleridge</hi> had found inspiration in the large faiths and regenerating principles which called into being the French revolution; <hi rend="underline">Byron</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Shelley</hi> on the other hand, produced their most characteristic works in the days of the reactionary Holy Alliance. And in the space between the era of faith and the era of reaction loomed the colossal form of Napoleon astride a blood&#8211;stained Europe.</p>
         <p>Cambridge. History of Eng: Lit: XII. 39</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Committee of Governors of the N.E. Counties School. We had lunch in the Common Room, and then I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Afterwards I returned to the Castle, &amp; walked in the Park with the dogs.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" publishes under the heading "Bishops on the Malines Conversations" the opinions of the Bishops of Lichfield &amp; Durham</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The one bishop has expressed his mind in his diocesan magazine: the other has made a speech at Stockton. The first holds that it is "quite grotesquely untrue" to represent the English delegation at Malines as men "who regard the Reformation as a complete mistake"; the last says that these distinguished men held opinions which "could not possibly be reconciled with the teaching" of the great Anglican divines of the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> &amp; 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries.</p></body></text></TEI>