<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[223]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Stagnation, not change, is Christianity's most deadly enemy, for this is a progressive world, and in a progressive world no doom is more certain than that which awaits whatever is belated, obscurantist, and reactionary.</p>
         <p>Fosdick Christianity &amp; Progress. P. 165</p>
         </div>
         <p>"The world passeth away and the lust therefor, but he that doeth the Will of God abideth for ever". It is an escape from this bondage to never&#8211;ceasing change that we seek to find in Religion.</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>"Change and decay in all around I see</p>
         <p>O Thou Who changest not abide with me".</p>
         </div>
         <p>What is "stagnation", but a process of dying, a mortal acquiescence in a drying up, or cutting off of the springs of life? It is not the proper antithesis to change, which ought to mean an invigoration of life by fresh resources.</p>
         <p>I attended the funeral of the late Vicar of Eldon, Gray. There was a considerable concourse of parishioners, and more than a dozen of the clergy from the Rural Deanery. The lad who was managing everything in the vestry was evidently much distressed. He gave a simple and affecting account of the Vicar's sudden collapse. He assisted him to the Vicarage, &amp; when they parted Gray took the lad's hand, and kissed it. This boy also is an aspirant to something more than his present job.</p></body></text></TEI>