<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">A smart but superficial writer</hi>" – that is Newman's description of Chillingworth<persName xml:id="551"></persName> (v. Development p.6) "<hi rend="underline">To be deep in history is to cease to be a Protestant</hi>" is another <hi rend="underline">obiter dictum</hi> of the same subtle dogmatist and its truth turns on the sense given to the words "deep" &amp; "Protestant". <hi rend="bold underline">The Abp. of York acknowledges receipt of my proposed resolution for the next meeting of Convocation, and adds an expression of his own regret that I should "feel obliged to raise this matter in this particular way". At the same time he allows that the motion is "quite in order", &amp; undertakes to put it on the agenda. On the whole, I think it would be the wisest course to move the resolution</hi>, for 1. That is the constitutional method of venting a grievance. And 2. The enemy has blundered into a strategically impossible position, in which he may be attacked at advantage. If it be really worth while to oppose the Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement at all, it cannot be wise to ignore times and occasions.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Board for Religious Education.</p>
         <p>In the evening, to my surprise &amp; annoyance, a "deputation" from S.P.G.<orgName xml:id="23"></orgName> who had been invited to address the clergy of the Rural Deanery, was simply "planted" on us without notice. The Vicar and his family went to the play! On the whole, if I must practice hospitality, I prefer to invite the guests.</p></body></text></TEI>