<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>One road only has in the Past led into democracy, viz. the wish to be rid of tangible evils, but the roads that have led or may lead out of democracy are many.</p>
         <p>Lord Bryce, Modern Democracy, ii, 661</p>
         </div>
         <p>I worked at the Stockton sermon all the morning. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to tea, and I paid him &#x00A3;500, the purchase money of the hoarding sites in Durham. I can ill afford the money, but I think it judicious to terminate the annual payment.</p>
         <p>The Metropolitan Free Church Federation has held a meeting in the City Temple yesterday in support of Protestant principles "as understood and enjoyed by the Free Churches". D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Carnegie Simpson</hi><persName xml:id="2015"></persName> "speaking as one of the Free Church Federal Council in the Conferences on Union being carried on at Lambeth Palace" referred to the "Conversations" at Malines. He was, of course, very polite to the Archbishop, but said some rather significant things. "Free Churchmen had the right to say that they assumed that positions agreed on with them at Lambeth w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be given away at Malines. Free Churchmen c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not carry on conference if what was gained on their swings was to be lost on the Roman roundabout. He asked that there sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be the same publicity about Malines, &amp; anything agreed on there, as there had been at Lambeth, &amp; their findings there. Then they would all know where they were… the issues involved were not merely ecclesiastical points such as the Papal claim".</p></body></text></TEI>