<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A bright bitter day. In the course of the morning I called at 10 Downing Street, and had an interview about Egglestone, which I advised the Patronage Secretary M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Duff, to fill up. Then I walked to the Abbey, &amp; spent an hour with Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">I lunched at the House of Lords, and had some talk with </hi><hi rend="bold">L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Buckmaster about Carnegie's reported refusal to allow a Presbyterian minister to baptize a member's child in the Crypt chapel. This seems to me great folly, &amp; very surprising for I know that the Archbishop was consulted</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I went back to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; there remained until I returned to Park Lane to dine alone with Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName>. Buckle<persName xml:id="322"></persName> was in the Club, and with him I had some talk. Also, with Hicks, who has just been appointed to the Vicarage of Brighton.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The newspapers report little of my speech, and what they report is comparatively harmless. But one never knows when &amp; where the echoes of one's indiscretion will assail one. One person familiar to me by face but not by name came to me in the Club, and expressed approval of my speech, but I know not what report of it he had seen</hi>. A letter from <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> assured me that her function yesterday had gone off without hitch. The Princess seems to have been amiable!</p></body></text></TEI>