<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[215]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Passion Sunday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We beseech thee, Almighty God, mercifully to look upon thy people; that by thy great goodness they may be governed and preserved evermore, both in body and soul; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. there were but five communicants, though it was the first Sunday in the month.</p>
         <p>I motored to Whickham, and discussed several matters of business with Little, whom I have just made an hon&#8211;canon in succession to old Fowler. Then I went to Marley Hill, and preached at Evensong in the parish church which was crowded and asphyxiating. The vicar, Arbuckle, is an old man, afflicted with a bad heart – physically bad, not, I trust, otherwise. There were many young men in the congregation, which, he assured me, was the general fact &amp; not a special turn&#8211;out for my benefit! There are 4000 people in the parish, and the income is set down as &#x00A3;336 net. The patronage is in the Crown and Bishop alternately. </p>
         <p>Cass, the curate at Coundon, has just, at my suggestion, consented to transfer himself to Marley Hill, where he will replace that queer creature Burgess who is now at Willington.</p>
         <p>I was rather distressed to hear that the physical weakness of the incumbent &amp; the moral collapse of the curate have prevented any preparation of confirmation candidates this year.</p></body></text></TEI>