<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The morning post brought ill news. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bertram Jones</hi>, the Rector of Hartlepool, wrote to say that his health can no longer endure the rigour of the climate. Prideaux<persName xml:id="3181"></persName> wrote to say that his curate, Mason, whom I ordained last year had broken down in health. Old Canon Scoot wrote to announce his resignation of Norton.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="4092"></persName> of Ryhope came to lunch. <hi rend="bold underline">We all motored to Whorlton for the funeral of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Headlam. The Bishop of Carlisle read the lesson, and I did everything at the graveside. There was a considerable gathering of neighbours</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then I went to the N.E. Counties' School in Barnard Castle, and confirmed 50 boys in the chapel. Then we all returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> writes to thank me for my "delightful article", and says that he has "thoroughly enjoyed reading it"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Macready</hi> writes to accept Kimblesworth. He is an eager, conceited, ill&#8211;bred fellow, of course, but he is also comparatively young, energetic, and, in his way, religious. He is at his wits' end to make both ends meet where he is, and even the squalid income of the new parish will improve his finances. He will be hard to replace in Stockton. His removal will probably involve the collapse of his mission. And this will be very hard on the congregation which has been drawn together, and encouraged to collect money for a new building to replace the dilapidated Army Hut.</p></body></text></TEI>