<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>From the beginning of the world to this day, there was never any great villainy acted by men, but it was in the strength of some great fallacy put upon their minds by a false representation of evil for good, or good for evil.</p>
         <p>South. vol i. p. 441</p>
         </div>
         <p>South's sermon on "<hi rend="underline">The fatal Imposture and Force of Words</hi>" (1686) from the text Isaiah v.20 "Woe unto them that call evil good, and good evil", is not irrelevant to the case of these sacerdotalist&#8211;socialists who defame the Reformation, and brand Industrialism as a condition of utter degradation.</p>
         <p>We motored into Durham, lunched at the Deanery, &amp; attended the service of Commemoration of Founders &amp; Benefactors in the Cathedral. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> preached an interesting sermon on Tunstall. After tea in the Deanery, I interviewed two candidates for Ordination. Both were poor creatures to look at. Headlam and his wife came with me to Auckland. He is certainly enjoying the episcopate, and, save for an odd twitching of the countenance, seems to be in good health. He intends to deliver a "charge" on the Church of England early this summer. I may expect to have the reading of it before I compose my own Charge, which is due in the autumn.</p>
         <p>The weather was again spring&#8211;like.</p></body></text></TEI>