<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[182]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>"Don Juan" is, perhaps, the most permanently interesting as it certainly is the most considerable of Byron's writings. The satire never grows obsolete, for it is directed against crimes &amp; follies which never fail from civilised society. In Christendom both are emphasized and rendered more repulsive, for the discord between profession &amp; practice is there most evident, most extreme, &amp; most offensive. The society which Byron satirized was not only abnormally selfish &amp; corrupt, but the form of Christianity which was fashionable among its members was peculiarly exposed to the scandal of hypocrisy. "Corruptio optimi pessims" [the corruption of the best is the worst (of all corruptions)]. The exalted spirituality of Evangelical Christianity is more easily approved in theory than given any expression in practice.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I officiated at the marriage of Faith Pease &amp; Michael Beaumont</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Both were very young, only twenty one. The Guards Chapel was filled with a fashionable throng, &amp; all the marks of a "fashionable wedding" were prominent. I excused myself from going to the reception, &amp; returned to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I found Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>. He is in considerable trouble on account of his wife, who has been operated on for cancer. Then I got away to King's Cross in time for the fast train. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me at Darlington. The weather continues to be bitterly cold.</p></body></text></TEI>