<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Herein lay the secret of Byron's potency, that he could remint and issue in fresh splendour the familiar coinage of the world's wit. Moreover he lived in a great age, when great truths are born again, and appear in a new light.</p>
         <p>Byron's Works vol. II. P 239 note</p>
         </div>
         <p>I worked at the sermon to undergraduates. Nicholson, who has resigned the curacy of Bishop Auckland, came to lunch. He aspires to become Vicar of Forest and Frith.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to South Hill, where we had tea with the Storys. Old M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Story [Storey] talked very interestingly</hi><hi rend="italic">. He is an ardent tariff&#8211;reformer, a great admirer of Disraeli, very scornful of the Liberal party, and very fearful of Socialism. I asked him whether he had kept a journal, and he replied in the negative, adding that, of all the numerous letters from well&#8211;known men he had received in the course of his life, he had not preserved more than half a dozen. He confessed regret at this action which, at the time, had seemed required by the pressure of his life.</hi></p>
         <p>On my return to Auckland, I wrote to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hugh, Vicar of Winston, asking him to become the first rural dean of the newly constituted Rural Deanery of Barnard Castle.</p>
         <p>The weather today has been fine and sunny, but extremely cold.</p></body></text></TEI>