<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[226]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Lord, what a change within us one short hour</p>
         <p>Spent in thy presence will prevail to make,</p>
         <p>What heavy burdens from our bosoms take,</p>
         <p>What parch&euml;d grounds refresh, as with a shower!</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">We kneel, and all around us seems to lower:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">We rise, and all, the distant and the near,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Stands forth in sunny outline, brave and clear:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">We kneel how weak, we rise how full of power,</hi></p>
         <p>Why therefore should we do ourselves this wrong</p>
         <p>Or others – that we are not always strong,</p>
         <p>That we are ever overborne with care,</p>
         <p>That we should ever weak or heartless be,</p>
         <p>Anxious or troubled, when with us is prayer,</p>
         <p>And joy and strength and courage are with Thee?</p>
         <p>Archbishop Trench</p>
         </div>
         <p>I suppose the experience described in these lines is integral to a sincere profession of Christianity. It is certain that the assurance of Divine guidance which it expresses has often been connected with the most woefully mistaken action.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I worked at the Cambridge sermon:</hi> walked in the Park with Hugh Lyon after lunch: wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, from whom I had received yesterday a long and very interesting letter, and wasted the evening in my "family".</p></body></text></TEI>