<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[230]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, who through thy only&#8211;begotten Son Jesus Christ has overcome death, and opened unto us the gate of everlasting life; We humbly beseech thee, that, as by thy special grace preventing us thou dost put into our minds good desires, so by thy continual help we may bring the same to good effect; through Jesus Christ our Lord, who liveth and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghost, ever one God, world without end.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>"The gate of death" in the collect for Easter Ever becomes "the gate of everlasting life" in the collect for Easter Day. The victory of Christ could not be more impressively shown.</p>
         <p>I motored to Sunnybrow, and celebrated the Holy Communion in the parish church at 7.45 a.m., the parson Slim, being absent through sickness. There were 44 communicants, among them about a dozen of the newly confirmed boys, whom Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> has been shepherding. I followed the practice of the church by adopting the "north end", but it made me feel curiously awkward. Also, I called for prayer for the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Meanwhile the newly&#8211;confirmed members of my family – Penelope and three maids – made their first communion in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's Church, where the Vicar, single&#8211;handed, had to wrestle with a crowd of communicants, as many as 200 I was assured.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[231]</hi></p>
         <p>Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName> accompanied me to Pittington, where I celebrated and preached. I was particularly pleased with the number of young men who received the Holy Communion. It appears evident that the parishioners like old Boddy, and are being drawn to church by him. We lunched with him. He spoke of Birney<persName xml:id="5383"></persName>, the new Vicar of Witton Park, whom he had known as a boy. He thought that he would probably justify appointment to the charge of a parish. </p>
         <p>We motored to Durham, and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. The singing was admirable. After tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Webbe, &amp; Penelope<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> went with me to Willington, where I read the lessons from the Revised Version, (of which I have myself presented a lectern copy to the church) and preached the sermon. Before service I called at the Vicarage, &amp; saw Duncan in bed. He is happily recovering, though still very feeble. The church was crowded, and the atmosphere was asphyxiating! But I was pleased by the heartiness of the service, &amp; the attention of the people. We retuned to Auckland, when the service was finished.</p>
         <p>Even if (which may Heaven grant!) the Bishop of Jarrow recovers from his illness, it will be plainly impossible to hold him to the confirmations for which he has made himself responsible. Of these there are nine noted in my calendar, and these mostly at times when either I am myself engaged in confirming, or I am absent from the diocese! </p></body></text></TEI>