<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[150]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>My conversation with the Archbishop last night is much in my mind. As I found myself once more alone with him in that familiar room, inevitably my mind went back to my interviews with his Grace just before my consecration. The position seemed to be reversed. Then I was justifying myself to him: now he was justifying himself to me. And in both cases the plea of conscience was being urged on the one side, and that of general ecclesiastical and religious interests on the other. <hi rend="bold underline">I told him that in my deliberate judgement, he had made a grave mistake</hi>. He admitted that he had been deceived, and was plainly perturbed by the resentment which his action has provoked: but he said <hi rend="bold underline">that he could not have faced his conscience if he had "stamped upon" an effort to advance the cause of unity in the Church. I said that we were in real danger of pursuing a false ideal of unity, and that it was high time that we cleared our minds</hi> on the point. He said that the Nonconformist leaders approved his action: that they had assured him of as much there in his house. I could but reply that <hi rend="bold underline">perhaps he had under&#8211;estimated the extent of his own personal influence, and that it was rather more than could be expected of Nonconformist ministers that they should rebuke the Archbishop to his face! But indeed his evident distress seemed to belie his speech.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>When the communication from the "Times" correspondent, denying that the Pope had given "official cognizance" to the "conversations" at Malines, and thus "giving the lie" to the Archbishop appeared, his Grace had betaken himself to the Editor of the Times in order to ascertain what measure of authority attached to the correspondent's statement. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Geoffrey Dawson</hi><persName xml:id="2709"></persName> made inquiry, &amp; was informed that the authority was none other than that of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gasparri</hi> himself<hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop feels compelled to "take it lying down" lest, if he makes</hi> any public protest, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Mercier</hi><persName xml:id="3626"></persName> shall come under official censure. <hi rend="bold underline">As it is, his Grace doubts not that the French ecclesiastics concerned are "having a bad time"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p>
         <p>I preached in S. Mary's, Bryanston Square, and celebrated Holy Communion. It is a vast church, built just 100 years ago, and equipped with galleries. The floor was, perhaps, two&#8211;thirds full: only a few school children were in the gallery. I was interested, and distressed, to see hardly any young men in the congregation which included a fair proportion of grey, &amp; white, &amp; bald heads. Of nearly 50 communicants, the male sex was represented by two elderly individuals, of whom one was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Ballance</hi>, whom I had met in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> overnight. This church provides an "old fashioned" Anglican service, i.e. choral Mattins with a plain celebration. The population of the parish numbers about 10,000, and beside the Rector (L. Percival) there are two assistant curates.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I lunched with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. A young lady dressed as the Duke of Monmouth was present. She was a friend of little Paula<persName xml:id="2067"></persName>, and looked remarkably pretty in her graceful costume. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph </hi>told me that the circulation of the "<hi rend="underline">Church of England Gazette</hi>" has now reached 40,000 weekly.</p>
         <p>I had tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3466"></persName>, &amp; then walked to Westminster, where I had an hour's talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. Then I returned to the Athenaeum, and dined there, having as my table&#8211;companion that inveterate &amp; shameless gossip, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Graves</hi>. I walked back to Park Lane, &amp; was in my room by 9.30 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There can be little doubt that the Archbishop's object in getting me to Lambeth last night was to persuade me to withdraw my motion in Convocation.</hi> But I was careful to avoid giving him any grounds for thinking that I should do this. None the less, I am not wholly certain whether it were not the wisest course. For I don't like being seen in open opposition to Cantuar: <hi rend="bold underline">I detest being seen to stand with Joynson&#8211;Hicks<persName xml:id="4295"></persName> &amp; his following of fanatics</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Yet, these repugnances are personal sentiments, which cannot be reasonably allowed to determine my action. One cannot choose the times and occasions of conflict: and it may well be the case that the "conversations" at Malines are providing an excellent opportunity for serving the main Interest.</p></body></text></TEI>