<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>In my opinion the Edinburgh Review is as well qualified to judge of the merits of a poet, as Homer would have been to write a commentary on the Newtonian System.</p>
         <p>Shelley to Byron, Nov: 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. 1816</p>
         </div>
         <p>I distributed prizes to the boys of Tonstall School, Sunderland. This is a preparatory school for the public schools of the second rank, and contains about 100 little fellows mainly from the local aristocracy. The headmaster is a little vainglorious talkative parson called Blenkinsopp. As the building in which the function took place was low&#8211;pitched, its windows hermetically sealed, &amp; every seat occupied, the atmosphere was deadly, and I felt asphyxiated. I went to the Rectory for tea and [had] some talk about church&#8211;extension in the Cleadon Estate. In the house was Scott, the Vicar of S. Gabriel's whose wife died quite suddenly yesterday. I had some talk with him about his arrangements which are not easy since he has two small children, &amp; so small a house that providing suitability for a housekeeper will be difficult. On the balance of risks and inconveniences I am not sure whether the celibacy of the clergy won't win finally on its practical merits! I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Gabriel's, and there confirmed 124 candidates, more males than females, which is a gratifying novelty!</p>
         <p>After the service we motored back to Auckland, where we arrived a few minutes before 10 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>