<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at the Byron Lecture all the morning. In the afternoon, I motored to Staindrop, and confirmed 76 persons in the glorious parish church. Then, after returning to the castle for tea, I motored to Monkwearmouth, and confirmed 165 persons. Before the service I examined in the vestry two small girls who were only 13 years old. Of course, I allowed them to be confirmed, but I thought it worth while to make a little fuss about a quite unnecessary breach of the diocesan rule.</p>
         <p>After service a young man desiring to be ordained came to me in the vestry. He was converted to Romanism when 14, and had been in a seminary. Thence he had emerged with a horror of Papistry. He was an assistant master at the Tonstall school, and desired to become a clergyman. I asked him whether he thought he would be settled and happy in the Anglican ministry, and he replied that at least it would be less of a torture than the Roman. This did not appear to me very encouraging, so I would give him no answer there and then, but arranged to have an interview with him later. After this, we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I have now confirmed, since the beginning of Lent, 2913 candidates, distributed over 26 confirmations, an average of 112: This number is probably as many as it is edifying to take at one time. More than 200 at one time is apt to be wearying and less than 100 is bad economy of episcopal vigour!</p></body></text></TEI>