<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I went to the Clarendon Press Depository, and ordered a R.V. Bible of the largest size for the lectern of Willington Church. It costs nearly &#x00A3;10. Then I went to Blackwell's, and ordered some Byron&#8211;books. Mercier's<persName xml:id="3626"></persName> Letter to his diocese was on sale in the shop. Then I walked to Marston Ferry Road, and lunched with Mary Radford<persName xml:id="1204"></persName>. My godson, John<persName xml:id="3886"></persName>, is growing taller, and is evidently improved by the discipline of the school. Freddie Macdonald called for me at All Souls, &amp; carried me to Oriel, where he had brought together a dozen of his friends to meet me at the tea. We spent the best part of two hours in "talking large" to the youth. The depression of my failure last night hung over me, &amp; I was very dull &amp; futile. I dined in College. The small party of fellows included Edgeworth, Cruttwell, Summer, Jacob, &amp; Hancock. We had some interesting talk in the common room afterwards.</p>
         <p>W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> left &#x00A3;2000 and his fine collection of books on Iceland to the Codrington Library. His bust in bronze adorns the common room. It is a fine piece of work &amp; amazingly like the original. His loss to the College is irreparable.</p></body></text></TEI>