<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty and everlasting God, who dost govern all things in heaven and earth; Mercifully hear the supplications of thy people, and grant us thy peace all the days of our life; through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         </div>
         <p>The collect appears to have no reference either to the Epistle (Romans xii. 6f) or to the Gospel (S. John ii. 1f) I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. 6 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing notes for my evening's sermon, and in writing to <hi rend="bold underline">Carnegie Simpson</hi>. After lunch I walked in the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to tea, and then went with me to S. Andrew's, Tadhoe Grange, where I preached, and he read the lessons. He read well, because naturally &amp; without effort or effect. A lay&#8211;reader read all the service except absolution &amp; Benediction, and, save that he dropped <hi rend="underline">all</hi> his aspirates, he did well enough. Before service I called on the Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Wykes</hi><persName xml:id="4460"></persName>, who is recovering from influenza. This parish, altogether inhabited by miners, is more hopeful from a religious point of view than most. Especially the number of young men in the congregation pleased me. There were no less than 22 of them in the choir, beside 24 boys. <hi rend="bold underline">Wykes is an "old&#8211;fashioned High Churchman", who dislikes "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" and is a diligent visitor.</hi> He represents the best, &amp; most effective type of Anglicanism, but the type that is vanishing away.</p></body></text></TEI>