<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[229]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> room, using the Easter collect &amp; proper Preface. Then I wrote the following letters:–</p>
         <p>1. To the Bishop of Chester, recommending Wilton, the curate of Ryhope, for appointment to Thornley.</p>
         <p>2. To Canon Cosgrave<persName xml:id="5313"></persName> with reference to his report on his deacon, Hill.</p>
         <p>3. To Wardle, declining to entertain his application as an Ordination Candidate.</p>
         <p>4. To the Patronage Secretary with reference to the parish of Eldon.</p>
         <p>5. To Hilken about the ecclesiastical situation generally.</p>
         <p>6. To Salter, practically offering him the Rectory of Hartlepool.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Bishop Lasbrey came to see me, and I gave him a copy of "The value of the Bible &amp; Other Sermons". He expressed a strongly favourable opinion on Salter, who was his colleague at S. Gabriel's</hi>, Sunderland, for more than three years: and, on the strength of this, I took the serious step of offering Salter the Hartlepool Rectory.</p>
         <p>I revised the proof of the Byron lecture, and sent it to the Press. A telegram from M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quick sent from Lugano brought the grave tidings that the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> was "seriously ill". He is 74 years old, and has endured the strain of a formidable operation. It is impossible not the fear the worst. His death will be a heavy loss to the dioceses.</p>
         <p>Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName> walked round the Park with me. She is 26 years old. It is difficult to realize that the small child of my marriage day is now a grown woman.</p></body></text></TEI>