<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The Church of Rome kept the rule of faith entire, until that rule was changed and altered by the Council of Trent; and from that time it seemed to him a matter of necessity to come out of the Church of Rome, that so that Church which is true &amp; called out from thence might follow the word of God.</p>
         <p>Bernard Gilpin</p>
         </div>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" has a long obituary of old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dean Wace</hi><persName xml:id="212"></persName>, who died yesterday at the great age of 87. Thus the Labour Government will have the appointment to two important places – the Bishoprick of Ely, and the Deanery of Canterbury.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham, and presided over a meeting of the Maintenance and Training of the Ministry Board. <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> found it necessary to use chains on the motor&#8211;wheels, as there was much snow on the roads, and they were extremely treacherous. The school children, absorbed in sliding on the frozen spaces, seemed to invite destruction, &amp; a more than common passion for suicide possessed the dogs!</p>
         <p>The Appeal for the starving folk in Germany appeared in the papers &#8211; conspicuously in the "<hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>", obscurely in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>". It was altogether absent from the columns of the "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>"!</p></body></text></TEI>