<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, picked up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> at the Chapter Office, and went with him to the Shire Hall, where I had an interview with Brookers, the County Surveyor, on the subject of the proposed new road, which Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName> vehemently opposes as most injurious to the School. I must confess that the case for the road is much stronger than I had thought, &amp; I could not do more than stipulate for a personal conference between Brookes and the Dean &amp; Chapter so soon as the Dean returns from South America. I lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and then motored to Sunderland, where I confirmed 127 persons at Silksworth, and then (after food with Canon McCullagh) I went to Christ Church, &amp; confirmed 139 persons. Here again the males exceeded the females to my great comfort. After service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I took occasion to consult McCullagh about the forthcoming vacancy of the Rectory at Hartlepool; where for some while the was himself assistant curate. I suggested Prideaux<persName xml:id="3181"></persName> as a possible incumbent, and he agreed that he was in some respects very well qualified. But then, there are 2 objections. He is unmarried, and in view of the fact that M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cobb, the other Hartlepool incumbent's wife is a Papist, a clerical wife is rather desirable: and he is reported to be an Anglo&#8211;Catholic, which since the Hartlepool folk are said to be Protestant is unfortunate.</p></body></text></TEI>