<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Christianity is no theory of the study or the cloister. It has long since passed beyond the letter of documents &amp; the reasonings of individual minds, &amp; has become public property. Its "sound has gone out into all lands", and its "words unto the end of the world". It has from the first had an objective existence, and has thrown itself upon the great concourse of men. Its home is in the world: &amp; to know what it is, we must seek it in the world, &amp; hear the world's witness of it.</p>
         <p>Newman "Development" p. 3</p>
         </div>
         <p>I occupied the morning with preparing my Stockton sermon. After lunch I went in to Durham, and did some business with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. After having tea with him, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> R. J. Campbell</hi> wrote from Brighton asking me to preach in Robertson's church in Holy Week, but I declined. Also, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Lunn</hi> asked me to write something for the Religious Review of Reviews on a volume of Christian Socialist Essays to which Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> has written an Introduction. I weakly consented. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. D. Richardson sent me his book "The Causes of the Present Conflict of Ideals in the Church of England", of which the publisher, Murray, had already sent me a copy.</p>
         <p>There was a slight fall of snow during the day.</p></body></text></TEI>