<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I saw an amusing description of him (Bp. Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>) the other day. "<hi rend="bold underline">Oh how much he prays! But it is always after one of these fits of devotion that he does something peculiarly uncharitable &amp; unjust".</hi></p>
         <p>Extract from Fawkes'<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> Letter Feb. 20, 1924.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I think that herein Bishop Gore does but exhibit the working of some strange law of moral (or immoral) compensations which most of us have been humiliated &amp; dismayed at discovering to be operative in ourselves.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Macmillans write to say that "as the demand for" five books of mine which they have published between the yeas 1903 and 1918 has "practically ceased", they propose "if possible to sell off the stocks, but failing this to have them destroyed"! This is surely the "last straw" that break the back of my literary ambition!!</hi></p>
         <p>After writing my letters, I wasted the morning in clearing up my study in preparation for my departure tomorrow.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I walked round the Park with the dogs. The wind was bitterly cold.</p>
         <p>The more I think over Byron, the more impossible it appears to me to come to a decision upon him. The last few months of his life discloses a new &amp; greater man.</p>
</body></text></TEI>