<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We may talk about <hi rend="underline">the right</hi> of private judgement, or <hi rend="underline">the duty</hi> of private judgement, but a more important thing to insist on is <hi rend="underline">the necessity </hi>of private judgement.</p>
         <p>Salmon</p>
         </div>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Durham, and attended the meeting of the Council of Preventive &amp; Rescue Association in the Cosin Library. We returned to Auckland for lunch, and immediately after Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; I set out for Stockton. On the way I stopped at Norton Vicarage in order to see old Canon Scott, who had asked for an interview. His only object was to tell me that he didn't intend to resign the benefice! Then we went on to the Parish Church, where a mixed company of clergy and dissenting ministers had gathered in the vestry to receive me. They constitute what is called a "Fraternal" and the object of their assembling together was to attest the fact with all publicity. I preached to a considerable congregation on "The Message of the Church to the age". Then followed tea in an Institute and more speeches! Finally we went to the Vicarage, &amp; after tea attended a public meeting in the Baptist Tabernacle presided over by the Mayor. A former minister, Carey, spoke for half an hour: &amp; then I spoke for 45 minutes on "What we owe to the Reformation". I took occasion to say what I thought about Malines. Then we returned to Auckland. </p></body></text></TEI>