<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>If there is one thing absolutely certain it is this, that there <hi rend="bold underline">will be no reunion of Christendom until every man is left in undisturbed possession of that liberty which the New Testament guarantees to him</hi>. There will be different ideas as to what that liberty comprises: but it is certainly very wide, &amp; in doubtful cases the presumption is always in favour of freedom, not against it. <hi rend="bold underline">Because, though freedom is not a good thing in itself and absolutely, it is yet the indispensable condition of all human excellence.</hi></p>
         <p>Bigg, "Wayside Sketches" p. 179</p>
         </div>
         <p>A most depressing day, dark and dull with intermittent rain.</p>
         <p>I read much of the volume sent me by Lunn "<hi rend="bold underline">The Return of Christendom</hi>" by a group of Churchmen, with an introduction by Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> &amp; an epilogue by G. K. Chesterton<persName xml:id="5455"></persName> . It gives one much food for thought. The almost maniacal fervour with which the existing system of society is denounced: the confidence with which the "Socialism" and Christianity are identified, and the touching belief in the Middle Ages are all very suggestive. Two of the writers are "Priests of the Community of the Resurrection, Mirfield" – Thornton &amp; Bull. One is an American, the Rev. Niles Carpenter. That goose, A. J. Carlyle, writes a short paper, while disavowing agreement with the others.</p>
         <p>Baldwin's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> Government was defeated last night by 72 votes.</p></body></text></TEI>