<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 9.30 a.m., and motored to Norton where I preached and celebrated the Holy Communion. After lunching with the Vicar, Canon Scott, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I motored to Hunwick, and preached at Evensong to a congregation which did not fill the little parish church. It was explained to me that a "Mission" in one of the local chapels had drawn the people away from the parish church! <hi rend="bold underline">These incessant "missions" will be the destruction of all serious religion in the diocese</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>But what a revelation this is of the actual situation into which we have come! The time was when the advent of the Bishop into a parish would have been an event of great &amp; general concern. It would have emptied the chapels. But, perhaps, this was never the case in these mining districts where the Church is a late arrival and the established religion is Nonconformist. The very aspect of the fabrics attests the fact. For while the parish churches are very often mean &amp; pinched the Nonconformist chapels are substantial and commodious. We must add that the social &amp; educational quality of the Anglican clergy is hardly superior to the buildings in which they minister. The Nonconformist ministers are often better educated, and of a stronger type. Yet Nonconformity itself is religiously stricken, and, if the Church <hi rend="underline">could</hi> seize its opportunity, it might win the people.</p></body></text></TEI>