<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and caught the express to King's Cross, where I arrived a few minutes before 2 p.m. After leaving my bags in Park Lane, I went to the hair–dresser, &amp; had my hair cut &amp;c. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I found divers of my acquaintance. <hi rend="bold underline">Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> told me that Carola's<persName xml:id="5362"></persName> first novel, a historical romance about Mary, Queen of Scots, has been published, &amp; is favourably noticed in this week's "Literary Supplement".</hi> Lord Muir Mackenzie told me that he had joined the Labour Party, and undertaken to take charge of their business in the House of Lords. He said that Chelmsford<persName xml:id="65"></persName> had made acquaintance with Ramsay Macdonald<persName xml:id="891"></persName>, when the latter came to India on a Commission during his (Chelmsford's) Vice–royalty. <hi rend="bold underline">Ellison said that the Archbishop of Canterbury had received from Joynson Hicks<persName xml:id="4295"></persName> a rather truculent letter about the proceedings at Malines, &amp; that he had returned an answer which was intended for publication</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> gave an ill account of Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> health.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> before leaving the Club. I dined at 21 Park Lane. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName> was the only guest beside myself. We had much talk about the political situation. Two things about himself are, perhaps, worth recording. First, he voluntarily surrendered "as a personal  arrangement" £4000 of his official income: Next, <hi rend="bold">[147] </hi><hi rend="bold underline">he covenanted, as a condition of his taking office, that he should be made Minister of Defence as well as Lord Chancellor</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He said that the Lord Chancellor's pension was secured to him absolutely, and that he was under no legal obligation to undertake judicial work, but that <hi rend="underline">practically</hi> he had to do so, as the expectation was so strong. I asked him what he thought was the future of<hi rend="doubleunderline"> Sir John Simon</hi><persName xml:id="1008"></persName>. He replied that though Simon was a very able man, and organized his own press (e.g. the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>) with much skill, he could not succeed in making himself interesting. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead</hi><persName xml:id="2508"></persName> was, in his opinion, an able but not a great lawyer. He could not return to the Bar, even if he wished to do so as, being an ex–Lord Chancellor, he was a judge. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane </hi>ridiculed the statement that Sir John Simon was making <hi rend="underline">£70,000</hi> per annum. He said that the sum could not exceed £30,000. Lady S.<persName xml:id="3466"></persName> mentioned the gossip that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ramsay Macdonald</hi><persName xml:id="891"></persName> was the illegitimate son of a Scottish peer. Lord H replied that R. M. was certainly illegitimate, &amp; his father may have been a peer! It is sufficiently evident that fashionable London is in the mood to embrace the Labour Ministers, and discover that they are all disguised aristocrats! Lord H. went off in time to catch the night train to Scotland. He goes to see his wonderful old Mother, aged 99.</p></body></text></TEI>