<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[194]</hi> ^[Pages mis&#8211;numbered. There is no page 193.]^</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Certainly it remains true that nothing in the ancient or undivided Church has ever been made an article of faith (as distinct from a pious opinion or a religious practice) which is not to be found plainly in Scripture.</p>
         <p>Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>. "The Holy Spirit &amp; the Church" p. 281</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Committee of Selection appointed to choose a "short leet" of candidates for the final judgement of the Barnard Castle School Governors met here at 11.15 a.m., and out of 99 candidates chose seven. Then they had lunch, &amp; afterwards went over the Castle. There were only 8 clergymen among the applicants, and none of them was included in the chosen seven.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">As I feared the miners are in an intractable mood: and seem determined to force a contest.</hi><hi rend="italic"> So far as an outsider can judge of this very complicated business, the employers made offers which were just &amp; were generous: but the men are scornful &amp; hostile. There appears, indeed, to be a measure of ambiguity in their decision, &amp; it may be, as the "Times" suggests, that they have not definitely refused acceptance, but they disclose an unpleasant temper, &amp; the outlook is certainly gloomy.</hi></p>
         <p>Dame Meriel Talbot<persName xml:id="5381"></persName> telegraphed a request that she might pass the week&#8211;end at the Castle, &amp; arrived in the course of the afternoon. She is engaged in preaching Emancipation.</p></body></text></TEI>