<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[224]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>There may be therefore members of the Catholic church both among heathens, Turks, Jews, and all the several sorts of Christians, men &amp; women of integrity and simplicity of heart, who though blinded in some things in their understanding, and perhaps burthened with the superstitions &amp; formality of the several sects in which they are engrossed, yet being upright in their hearts before the Lord, chiefly aiming &amp; labouring to be delivered from iniquity, and loving to follow righteousness, are by the secret touches of this <hi rend="underline">holy light</hi> in their souls enlivened and quickened, thereby secretly united to God, and there–through become true members of this Catholic church.</p>
         <p>Barclay's Apology. Prop. X. (p. 258)</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Is there in all the works of the far–famed Caroline divines a description of the Catholic Church so just, so generous, so satisfying, &amp; so congruous with the Spirit of Jesus as this of the Quaker Apologist</hi><hi rend="bold">? </hi>It contrasts well with Article XVIII, though the latter is not <hi rend="underline">necessarily </hi>inconsistent with it: </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"They also are to be had accursed that presume to say, That every man shall be saved by the Law or Sect which he professeth, so that he be diligent to frame his life according to that Law, and the light of Nature. For holy Scripture doth set out unto us only the Name of Jesus Christ, whereby men must be saved".</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[225]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked at the Cambridge Sermon all the morning. Sir Henry Havelock–Allan<persName xml:id="5796"></persName>  and <hi rend="bold underline">his cousin, the Warden of New College</hi><persName xml:id="2107"></persName> , came to lunch. Neither of them had seen Auckland Castle before. Hugh Lyon also arrived at lunch–time on a short visit.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Sockburn, a parish on both sides of the Tees. The church, a mean little building, is in Yorkshire. Here I confirmed 23 persons, and then had tea with the Vicar, an old man named Clegg, who has held the incumbency for no less than 48 years, during which it is said that he has never been absent for so much as a single Sunday!</p>
         <p>We motored next to Darlington, where I confirmed 117 persons in S. Cuthbert's. After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The Lenten confirmations are now ended: I have confirmed in all 3995 persons: and the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> perhaps about half that number.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">John Murray writes to say that his Committee attach importance to my attending the Byron luncheon on the 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, and speaking to the toast of "Byron as the friend of mankind". So there is no help for it. I must desert <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at Stroud, catch the express to London, attend the function, and get back to Auckland by the late train. Then there is the bother of preparing a speech!</hi> It will be a very short one: and probably will be none the less welcome on that score!</p></body></text></TEI>