<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[217]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>Byron again all the morning. After lunch we motored to Tanfield, where I confirmed 170 persons. Old Canon Archdale is very feeble and foolish. He said that he had had a second stroke. I noticed that the rather disconcerting curate, Lister, had done all the work for some while past. After tea at the vicarage, I went on to Whickham, where I confirmed 180 persons in the parish church: and afterwards had supper with the Rector.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Little</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> said that when he was working as a clergyman at Arbroath he had discovered that copies of "Lux Mundi" were let out to the artisans for a charge of threepence per night. This discloses an interest in theological literature which would hardly be found south of the Tweed</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He also described the solitary occasion on which he had met the late </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Morley</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was about the time that the statesman, then known as "Honest John", had been turned out from Newcastle. Morley suggested, as they stood together on the Scottish railway&#8211;platform, that they should travel southwards together. Where do you get out? he asked, to which Little replied rashly "Where you got out – Newcastle</hi><hi rend="i bold">". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Morley turned on his heel, &amp; walked wrathfully away</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> That is an exhibition of petty resentiment </hi>[sic]<hi rend="italic"> which is rather surprising in a man of his stature in public life. But one never knows 'where the shoe pinches', &amp; the defeat at Newcastle wounded his vanity.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>
