<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[170]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Dock Strike</hi> has begun. These recurrent outbreaks of economic strike are most disquieting. What may they portend, or lead on to? Like a petty scratch on an unhealthy body, a silly trade quarrel may precipitate blood poisoning and result in death.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Bell</hi><hi rend="bold underline">is to be Dean of Canterbury. These "kindly Scots" can be counted upon to do one another's business! He was only ordained in 1907, just 20 years after me. He can hardly be much more than 40 years old. When I went to Westminster Abbey, I was 37. He is a good fellow enough, and my letter of congratulation was sufficiently sincere.<note xml:id="548" n="1"></note></hi></p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, and had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> about the possibility of organizing some training of Ordination candidates under the direction of a second chaplain to live at the Gate House. He seemed to be attracted by the notion, &amp; thought that possibly <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pestle</hi><persName xml:id="5238"></persName> might be serviceable for the purpose. I asked him to get into communication with P., and find out how far he would be disposed to cooperate. I returned to Auckland in time to join a half&#8211;a&#8211;dozen students from Durham whom P had brought over to see the Castle &amp; Escomb, and whom <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was entertaining at tea. I took the opportunity of warning P that Knight would be approaching him on my behalf.</p>
         <p>The weather, which was fine during the earlier part of the day, became boisterous in the afternoon.</p></body></text></TEI>