<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[214]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I completed in rough form this intolerable lecture on Byron. It needs revision, elaboration, &amp; extension before it will serve: but it is at least in being.</hi></p>
         <p>Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came to lunch with his wife &amp; boys, and they all stayed to tea in order to meet the renowned Miss Ishbell Macdonald<persName xml:id="5384"></persName>, the Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="891"></persName> daughter, who is visiting Bishop Auckland, &amp; wished to see the Castle. She appeared a modest, unspoiled, natural girl, who shewed an adequate interest in what she was shown. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ben Spoon and his wife, Watts the little foolish Socialist parson of Shildon with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watts, and the bank&#8211;manager who seemed to be organizing the party came with her. I always feel, when folk of this kind come to the Castle, that I am as the foolishly vainglorious Hezekiah when he displayed his treasures to the envoys of Babylon! The only inference they draw from what they see is, probably, that which stimulates cupidity &amp; confirms prejudice!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After dinner I read the Byron lecture to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>.</hi> It certainly does not please me. The parts are not connected obviously &amp; easily enough: there is no adequate grasp of the life as a whole, nor is the poetry brought into any relation with the general scheme of English literature. Altogether, it is too crude, too thin, too incoherent.</p></body></text></TEI>