<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I attended service in the College Chapel. Johnson is getting more bowed in figure, and slower in his speech, but he reads beautifully still, &amp; is very vigorous for a man of four score. I went to S. Mary's and heard the Bampton Lecture. The preacher was one of the ablest of the resident Anglo&#8211;Catholics – N. P. Williams. His sermon was clever, interesting &amp; learned. He allowed himself in some humorous versions of the Biblical Fall&#8211;legends, which made the gallery titter. I was struck by the size of the congregation. I lunched with the Spooners<persName xml:id="383"></persName>, and then returned to All Souls, where I dined quietly with mine hostess. After dinner, I went to S. Mary's, and delivered the sermon on which I had bestowed so much labour. So far as I could judge it was a total failure. The congregation was not as large as I had expected, a circumstance which may be partly explained by the chill &amp; cheerless weather. The Church was cold: the undergraduates were bored: I was myself consciously dull! It is humiliating that one should be so dependent on moods or conditions.</p>
         <p>Katherine<persName xml:id="4356"></persName>, now a fine young woman of 23, resides in London, where she is studying astronomy at the University. She week&#8211;ends at Oxford regularly, &amp; retuns to London after dinner.</p></body></text></TEI>