<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Let me advise you in reading, to have a care of those discourses which express domestic &amp; private actions, especially if they be such, wherein yourself purposes to venture your fortunes. For if you rectify a little your conceit, <hi rend="underline">you shall see that it is the same wisdom, which manages private business, &amp; state affairs, &amp; that the one is acted with as much folly, &amp; ease, as the other</hi>. If you will not believe me, then look into our colleges, where you shall see, that I say not the plotting for an headship, for that is now become a court&#8211;business, but the contriving of a bursarship of twenty nobles a year, is many times done with as great a portion of suing, siding, supplementing, &amp; of other court&#8211;like arts, as the gaining of the secretary's place; <hi rend="underline">only the difference of the person it is, which makes the one comical, the other tragical.</hi></p>
         <p>John Hales<persName xml:id="2184"></persName> i. 173</p>
         </div>
         <p>Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> went back to Gloucester after breakfast. His wife remains here for a few days. I prepared notes for the speech which I propose to make in convocation on the subject of Malines, and walked in the Park after lunch. Alas, I accepted a tender for J. Wilton &amp; Sons for the installing of a bath &amp;c in the Gate&#8211;house. It is to cost &#x00A3;46:10:0. Then the two sets of rooms must be furnished.</p>
         <p>The weather was mild and spring&#8211;like.</p></body></text></TEI>