<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Festival of the Epiphany, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1924.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Could we by a wish</p>
         <p>Have what we will and get the future now,</p>
         <p>Would we wish aught done undone in the past?</p>
         <p>So let him wait God's instant men call years;</p>
         <p>Meantime hold him hard by truth and his great soul,</p>
         <p>Do out the duty! Through such souls alone</p>
         <p>God stooping shows sufficient of His light</p>
         <p>For us i' the dark to rise by. And I rise.</p>
         <p>Browning. "Pompilia"</p>
         </div>
         <p>We all motored into Durham for the morning service in the cathedral. I preached and celebrated the Holy Communion. There was a very small congregation, smaller perhaps than I had a right to expect, but it is vacation time, many residents are away from home, and many have bad colds. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and I lunched in the Deanery. After lunch I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and discussed with him this woeful business at Marley Hill. Then I attended Evensong in the cathedral, and sate in the Throne, from which I pronounced the Benediction upon a strangely meagre congregation. The singing was wonderful. It does seem strangely perplexing that this exquisite &amp; costly service should be so little valued. After Evensong I had some talk with Meade Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, and then went to Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> for tea. Recovering the ladies from the Bishop's house, we all returned to Auckland.</p></body></text></TEI>