<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The heat last night made sleep impossible. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith &amp; Walter Smith left for Wales. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to Croft Castle, &amp; lunched with Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Atherley, very pleasant people. After lunch we were shown the Castle, a large square building with a considerable annex erected by the first purchaser of the present family, Kevill–Davies. Hard by the house is the little parish church which is distinguished by fine recumbent effigies of a medieval Croft &amp; his wife, and by a number of fine medieval tiles. In the grounds is a fine chestnut avenue, grown from the nuts brought from Spain by the Croft<persName xml:id="5243"></persName> who flourished under Queen Elizabeth. We motored to Yarpole, &amp; there I dedicated a Memorial Cross in the presence of a numerous assembly. Little Billy Kevill–Davies<persName xml:id="5205"></persName> unveiled the monument, on which his father's<persName xml:id="5206"></persName> name is inscribed at the head of the fallen soldiers. After the dedication I administered their pledge to 11 boy–scouts. Then we motored to Hereford.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I received a frigid and ambiguous letter from the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi><persName xml:id="128"></persName><hi rend="italic"> returning the letter from Abp. Söderblom<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His Grace is evidently alarmed at the prospect of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> declining to recognize Swedish Orders! Probably he has consulted his privy pundits, &amp; they have warned him. I wrote a short letter indicating my surprise at his suggestion of difficulty with the Lambeth Conference, &amp; stating that I would not acknowledge any authority in a body, avowedly gathered for purely consultative purposes, to control me in the exercise of my undoubted liberty</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>