<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The discussion at the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> turned on the Place of women in the Ministrations of the Church, and <hi rend="underline">it was evident enough that there was a strong feminist sentiment among the Bishops</hi>. At first it seemed likely that the subject would 'peter out' in the morning: but after lunch interest revived. <hi rend="bold underline">I made a speech criticising the assumptions &amp; pleas of the feminists, &amp; this had the effect of continuing the discussion till the end of the day</hi>. <hi rend="underline">I find myself in rather an odd position. The bishops who are ready to stand with me on Reunion are almost all feminists and Christian Socialists, &amp; they cannot understand how I can oppose both. In that opposition, moreover, I find myself in the same camp with ancient obscurantists &amp; "Catholick" bigots! Of course my ground of opposition is neither obscurantist nor "Catholick", but I find myself in the same lobby none the less.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>I joined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Davidson's<persName xml:id="404"></persName> "At Home". Among the company were Lady Helmsley<persName xml:id="4220"></persName> (whom I failed to recognize), &amp; Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName>, who was very affectionate. After tea, we called on the Speaker<persName xml:id="784"></persName>, &amp; then returned to the Deanery. There was a pleasant dinner party. Clutton Brock<persName xml:id="4169"></persName> &amp; his wife are staying in the house. He is curiously different to what I had expected. Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> turned up, &amp; discoursed sweet musick to the company. Meicklejohn<persName xml:id="2772"></persName>, once one of Asquith's<persName xml:id="215"></persName> private secretaries, was at dinner, &amp; Sir Something &amp; Lady Boyle. Also Stanley Leathes<persName xml:id="5245"></persName>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>