<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi> [sic]<hi rend="bold"> [96]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at the Swedish lectures. There came to lunch from Malvern George Dennistoun<persName xml:id="3560"></persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="3301"></persName>. Afterwards I walked to Belmont with Alan Radford<persName xml:id="3885"></persName>, &amp; then resumed work at the lectures. <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the Revd John F. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> (Wyelands, nr. Ross) formally accepting him as domestic chaplain</hi>, stipulating that he sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> enter on his duties at the beginning of January 1921:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"There is a certain solemnity as of a religious covenant when men become colleagues in the work of the Christian Ministry, &amp; when their union is intimate &amp; confidential as must be ours, that solemnity is deepened. We must be true to salt."</p>
         </div>
         <p>I thought that might properly be said.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi> [sic]<hi rend="bold"> [97]</hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>August 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Rust<hi rend="bold"><persName xml:id="5224"></persName>,]</hi></p>
         <p>I should have been better pleased if you had asked my permission <hi rend="underline">before</hi> inviting M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Holmes to preach in Hamsteels Parish Church, instead of taking that permission for granted, &amp; informing me <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the invitation had been sent, &amp; accepted. If you study the Report of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>, you will find that there is great regard paid to the principle of ecclesiastical order. Mere individualism, however well&#8211;intentioned, is discouraged.</p>
         <p>I desire to assist to the best of my power in clearing away the prejudices &amp; misunderstandings which now separate Anglicans &amp; Nonconformists, but I am not disposed to have my hand forced by hasty action in the parishes.</p>
         <p>And in any case, I think the request for my permission should be sent from the churchwardens as well as from the Incumbent. The congregation must not be ignored in matters of this kind.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The above was written to the Vicar of <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Hamsteels<hi rend="bold">]</hi>, &amp; sufficiently explains itself. I suspect there will be more cases of incumbents professing an ardent zeal to fraternize with the sectaries, and claiming my approbation for their disorderly proceedings. They mistake their Bishop rather wonderfully!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi> [sic]<hi rend="bold"> [98]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>August 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1920.</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>,</p>
         <p>We have taken passages in the steamer which leaves Newcastle for Gothenburg on Saturday the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of September: &amp; shall proceed to Upsala leisurely so as to arrive either on Thursday 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, or on Friday the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>The Lectures, I fear, will reflect the haste &amp; pressure under which they have been composed: but, such as they are, they may, perhaps, help to give a truer understanding of the phenomenon, Anglicanism.</p>
         <p>You will have read the Report of the Lambeth Conference, and noted the Resolutions which affect the relations of the two Churches, yours &amp; mine. I understood before I left London that the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> would correspond with you on the subject of sending the Bishop of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> to attend the Consecration in Upsala on September 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, so that a formal character might be given to the presence of English Bishops as desired by the Conference.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I told his Grace that this arrangement must depend, so far as I was concerned, on your wishes. Your courteous invitation to me had nothing formal in it: &amp; my acceptance of it was purely personal. In this matter I shall conform entirely to your wishes</hi>. My own sentiments as to the Church of Sweden are sufficiently well known.</p>
         <p>The threatened strike of miners, if it takes place, may compel my return to England as speedily as possible. It will not be fitting that the Bishop of Durham should be absent if his diocese, which is one of the greatest mining centres, is in confusion. I trust, however, that, even at the eleventh hour, the strike may be averted.</p>
         <p>Looking forward to meeting you in a few weeks,</p>
         <p>I am, my dear Archbishop,</p>
         <p>Yours v. sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Most Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> the Lord Abp. of Upsala.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi> [sic] <hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">[I finished the 6th lecture. It dealt with the Establishment</hi>. Elizabeth<persName xml:id="3077" display="no"></persName> arrived in the forenoon. The Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and Miss Pearce came to lunch, and at tea time M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burkitt<persName xml:id="573"></persName> &amp; Miles<persName xml:id="1863"></persName> appeared. <hi rend="underline">Per contra</hi>, Ernest left. We are certainly "dying game"! Miles Burkitt talked very interestingly of pre&#8211;historic wall&#8211;paintings in Spain, on which he appears to be an authority. He talked well, &amp; so relieved the taciturnity of Alan Radford<persName xml:id="3885"></persName>. </p>
         <p>Pearce is confronted with the Super&#8211;tax for the first time, and he exhibits evident signs of a not unnatural perturbation. Add the menacing &amp; indefinite burden of dilapidations, and the situation of a bishop without private resources, and living in a noble medieval castle, is not enviable.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>