<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">Yesterday, August 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> 1920, the English Revolution began</hi>."<note xml:id="513" n="1"></note> ‒ that was my observation after reading the newspaper this morning. A power has arisen outside of Parliament which openly claims to direct the policy of the nation, &amp; is avowedly acting in concert with a foreign power against the constitutional government of the country. <hi rend="bold underline">Organised labour representing a minority of the nation claims to dictate the foreign policy of the Empire: &amp; threatens "direct action" to enforce its claim</hi><note xml:id="513" n="1"></note>. The loathing of War, which has been created in the public mind during the last five years, predisposes many to condone any action which averts War, who naturally would have no part in movements of revolution. But no considering man can mistake the nature of last night's proceedings. England has ceased to be a constitutional monarchy, &amp; is making its first advance towards "the dictatorship of the proletariat".</p>
         <p>This day being the birthday both of Archdeacon Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> and of his eldest daughter, we were invited to join in a picnic on the river. We spent a pleasant afternoon.</p>
         <p>Creed<persName xml:id="5255"></persName> writes to decline my offer of the examining chaplaincy on the ground that he is already one of the Bishop of Wakefield's<persName xml:id="2980"></persName> chaplains. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>My mind swings back to the perilous notion of appointing the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" Moulsdale<persName xml:id="3159"></persName>, though I have misgivings as to the prudence of introducing the enemy into my very citadel! However, I have him there in Durham in any case, &amp; office <hi rend="underline">might</hi> clip his claws!<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>