<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast I wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> giving him an account of yesterday's functions.</p>
         <p>Then our host showed us over the chapter house, and University Buildings. <hi rend="bold underline">In the latter we were particularly impressed by the beautiful inlaid cabinet presented by the citizens of Augsburgh to Gustavus Adolphus. This is an astonishing piece of work</hi>. At 1 p.m. we lunched with the newly consecrated bishop of Westerås, and were photographed in the court&#8211;yard. After lunch we all walked to the cemetery in order to pay our respects to the tomb of the late bishop, (Fancy being carried off to Kensal Green to salute the host's father!) I noticed the huge stone slabs belonging to the "Nations" of the University, of which there are 13. On these slabs are inscribed the names of students who die during their residence in the University. After this we had tea with the Governor in the Castle. <hi rend="bold underline">In this famous building Queen Christina abdicated the throne</hi>. The local "diet", which seems to resemble our 'County Council' was in session. The Governor's wife is a most friendly lady who had been in England as a girl of seventeen, &amp; had there attended the preaching of Webb Peploe<persName xml:id="561"></persName> in S. Paul's, Onslow Square. She was very earnest in charging me to tell him that his sermons had impressed her permanently. I promised to send her a volume of my sermons. After tea there was little more than time to collect my papers before going to the University building to <hi rend="bold underline">deliver my lecture on "Puritanism". There was a smaller audience than I had expected, and among the absentees was my brother of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName></hi>. Then another long Swedish dinner!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>