<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished the Lectures after a fashion! They are woefully poor stuff, but put out some things of no slight importance, which yet are commonly concealed. What the Swedes will make of them I can't imagine!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>An ordination candidate ‒ the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> W. Rowland&#8211;Jones ‒ an ex&#8211;Wesleyan minister, who had been accepted for Ordination by Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, lunched here. I allowed the acceptance to stand, but he impressed me as very inadequate.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hereford Diocesan Messenger</hi> is humiliating to read, for it is full of amazingly exaggerated eulogies of the late Bishop. As descriptions of me they are absolutely grotesque, but they are evidently sincere, &amp; raise the question what is there in me which can carry to anybody the impression which is indicated.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> writes to inform me that the Swedish Primate will welcome a second bishop at the Consecration on the 19th: and that he had asked the Bishop of Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> to go. I wrote both to his Grace, &amp; to my prospective companion</hi>. I spent some time in the miserable task of tearing up letters and packing up my more private papers. There are few experiences more profoundly depressing than those which accompany one's departure from one scene of residence &amp; work to another. It becomes increasingly difficult to fit one's self in to new surroundings as one grows older, &amp; one's illusions are fewer.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>