<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[104]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished, with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne's</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName> assistance, preparing these abominable lectures, &amp; then set to work to clear up my room, &amp; make my preparations for departure. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>William helped in tying up the letters, papers, &amp;c, and in replacing the books which had been accumulated for the lectures ‒ a melancholy and dusty performance. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><persName xml:id="3230"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilley</hi><persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came in to say Goodbye, and we ended the day by dining at the Deanery, where the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Waterfield<persName xml:id="5129"></persName> were very pleasant.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">So ends my brief episcopate in Hereford, begun in a tempest of abuse, concluded in a stream of eulogy ‒ both equally undeserved</hi>. I am really sorry to go, partly, because I was beginning to get hold of this diocese, partly because I am dismayed at the task which lies before me in Durham. Certainly, when I came here, nothing seemed more evident than that I had reached the last stage of my career. Yet, here, after 2 1/2 years, I am called to a new, and vast enterprise. My personal unworthiness is more apparent than ever, and I at least cannot be deceived by the enthusiasm of my friends. For, indeed, </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>"Best friends would loathe us, if what things perverse</p>
         <p>We know of our own selves, they also knew:</p>
         <p>But what, O Lord, if Thou who knowest worse,</p>
         <p>Shoulds't loathe us too."</p>
         </div>
         <p>So I am turned to penitence by the humiliating plaudits of my friends. "There is mercy with Thee: therefore, Thou shalt be feared."</p>
         </body></text></TEI>