<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Today the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> dealt with the burning question of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Reunion</hi>. The morning was Idevoted to the Episcopal Churches, and we had an abundance of the meticulous &amp; unreal eloquence which seeks to prove that the miserable relics of ancient churches are really free from the heresies they have perpetuated! In the afternoon we came to the real matter in debate, when we discussed our relations with non&#8211;episcopal churches. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burrows</hi><persName xml:id="301"></persName> of Chichester made a woeful speech, bad in form &amp; substance, intensely narrow &amp; embittered in tone. <hi rend="bold underline">I followed him. My speech was closely listened to, and applauded at the close. At least I spoke with lucidity &amp; decision. My demand was that we should acknowledge frankly the validity of Prebyterian Orders &amp; Sacraments. I said some things which needed saying, &amp; which went home. A good many bishops came to thank me afterwards</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>We left Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>, &amp; transferred ourselves to the Deanery at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clutton&#8211;Brock</hi><persName xml:id="4169"></persName> &amp; his wife were staying at the Deanery, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName> also. C.B. said that he had been at Canterbury, &amp; met Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Northcliffe</hi><persName xml:id="4024"></persName> there. He said that he was much struck by the deteriorated appearance of the Napoleon of Journalism. A self&#8211;dedication to a personal vendetta can hardly have any but a debasing effect on character.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>