<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I received the Holy Communion together in the Abbey Church at 8 a.m. I did not attend matins, but gave myself to the indispensable task of preparing a sermon for next Sunday, when I am pledged to preach at the Temple. I attended Evensong, and heard an admirable sermon from W. Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>. He has an excellent voice, which he manages excellently. His thesis was familiar, and in his development of it, I suspect that we should disagree: but, as far as he went in his sermon, I had no reason to quarrel with him. The Bishops of Sacramento &amp; S. Florida came to tea in the Deanery. I preached to a great congregation in the nave at the evening service. The sermon was wholly uncontroversial, &amp; no doubt did for that reason disappoint many. But there was very close attention throughout, &amp; I hope some people were edified. Fedarb<persName xml:id="156"></persName> came into the Jerusalem Chamber to shake hands with me before going to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's where he now adds the practice of reading to his duties as churchwarden. I cannot see any adequate reason for this, since there are always two clergymen at the service, but Fedarb is so good a man that everybody is probably pleased with an arrangement which brings him into prominence.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>