<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>My letters included a cryptic message from Charles, who has been letting his tongue wag about the Chair of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert, &amp; is quite persuaded that he has filled it. "The announcement will be made on Saturday if not before." In that case it does not concern me in the least. Later a reporter came with a newspaper cutting which settled the question in the usual oracular style, and I had to deny that there was any truth etc. It appears that some penny&#8211;a&#8211;liner in the Globe declared it was probable: &amp; a Durham newspaper announced it was imminent! It is all very humiliating.</p>
         <p>I presided at a meeting of the Women's Political Association, at which the subject of State Purchase was introduced by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rankin, a humourless orator, and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nield<persName xml:id="5000"></persName>, the Quaker from Leominster who was inclined to be fanatical. The motion in favour of State Purchase was opposed by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dymond<persName xml:id="4212"></persName>, the ex&#8211;Mayor. I amended the resolution into an innocuous form, &amp; enunciated some platitudes. The meeting seemed to me very dull &amp; futile.</p>
         <p>The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> reports that about 75 people attended the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" meeting last night: Marcus Atlay<persName xml:id="5138"></persName> explained that the real purpose of the Conference in London was, not to intimidate the Lambeth Fathers, but to demonstrate against "Modernism" in the Church!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>