<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>After prayers the Secretary read out a type&#8211;written series of resolutions embodying the points which had emerged during yesterday's discussions. Immediately Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> produced a draft which he had prepared, &amp; which he had persuaded the Bishop&#8211;designate of Hereford (<hi rend="b strikethrough">an easily&#8211;gulled fellow</hi>) to approve. This draft was introduced with a highly truculent declaration of "Catholick" principles, but contained a series of proposals not excessively remote from those of the Secretary's. <hi rend="bold underline">I adopted the course of attacking the introduction, and recasting the resolutions. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This policy was accepted by Zanzibar with a fair grace</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, &amp; and much progress was made, for which <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> (rather prematurely, I suspect) bade us give thanks to God, but there is an evident division on fundamental principle, &amp; I doubt the wisdom of pretending that we are at bottom agreed.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>We dined with the <persName xml:id="2244">Strutherses</persName><persName xml:id="2708"></persName>. There were also there Lord<persName xml:id="1394"></persName> &amp; Lady Ernle, Sir George<persName xml:id="4464"></persName> &amp; Lady Younger, Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, Lady Corrie, and the Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. After dinner, Lady Younger motored us to Burdett Coutt's<persName xml:id="1064"></persName> reception. There we found Lord Milner<persName xml:id="839"></persName>. Our host with elaborate civility showed us the treasures of his house, which are amazing. I was amused to hear his debate on the Baroness's sense of humour. Marriott<persName xml:id="4624"></persName> was there, &amp; old Granville Smith<persName xml:id="5246"></persName>. We got a taxi, &amp; returned to our friends about midnight. This hardly appears a helpful manner of filling in the leisure of a Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>!<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>