<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> July, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I preached to a large congregation in the Temple Church</hi> from S. Matthew xx 25&#8211;8, which was part of the Gospel for S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's Day. My subject was <hi rend="bold underline">Reunion</hi> as affected by our theory of Christian Ministry; &amp; my sermon was confessedly related to the discussions on Reunion in the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. I noticed a black bishop in the congregation, and Bishop Mann<persName xml:id="1608"></persName> of South Florida. The last would not have approved of my discourse, which, indeed, was not lacking in decisiveness. <hi rend="bold underline">I took occasion warmly to recommend Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> Bampton Lectures to the study of churchmen</hi>. After service <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I lunched with the Benchers in the Middle Temple. Lord Finlay<persName xml:id="339"></persName>, Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>, &amp; several other Scots were present, &amp; <hi rend="underline">they</hi> of course approved the sermon. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Janey Fleet<persName xml:id="1243"></persName> was in the congregation, &amp; came in to shake hands after the service. Also the great Dorothea<persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, more effusive than ever. <hi rend="underline">After lunch Ella went off to pay calls, &amp; I lay down to rest.</hi><hi rend="bold underline">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">[Arthur Shadwell<persName xml:id="30"></persName> came in to tea, &amp; took off the MS. of my sermon </hi>to the "Times" office, promising to return it to me at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. <hi rend="bold underline">Then mine host<persName xml:id="956"></persName> &amp; I walked for a while in the Temple Garden. He, too, talks about the succession to Canterbury, &amp; says that my name is freely spoken of. The whole business is indecent &amp; preposterous, but it may explain the quite evident chagrin of the Archbishop</hi><persName xml:id="128"></persName>, for nothing more exasperates the Man in Power than the suggestion that he nears the end of his tenure, &amp; the indication of a possible successor! However, it can't be helped, &amp; must be endured.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>