<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant day, ideal for the concluding function of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I drove to the Cathedral in good time. The Bishops of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName>, Durham, &amp; Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> robed in the Chapel of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Michael, with the two English Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName>. The procession of the bishops was really an impressive sight, but there was nobody to witness it. I was surprised that, even in August, the spectacle did not attract a crowd. Inside the Cathedral there was a great congregation. The Archbishop's strongly&#8211;expressed desire that there should be a real "corporate communion", i.e. one at which the members of the corpus did actually communicate, bore fruit, for the whole body of the bishops, exceeding 230 persons, received the Sacrament. The Bishop of Tennessee<persName xml:id="5216"></persName> preached the sermon, which began well but tailed off woefully. It was rather too long for its quality. Before giving the Benediction, the Archbishop bade farewell to the Bishops in a few simple but moving words. The singing of the final hymn was very impressive. As I was leaving the Cathedral, Gilbert Box<persName xml:id="1208"></persName>, with his wife and infant, introduced themselves. Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName> drove us both to Garland's Hotel, &amp; then we went off to lunch with the Gows<persName xml:id="216"><persName xml:id="542"></persName></persName> in their new house at Hampstead. He is woefully blind. I asked him whether he would care to be one of my chaplains, &amp; he seemed pleased. After lunch we went to Lambeth, where the Archbishop awaited me. Between us we drafted a letter which <hi rend="bold">[77]</hi> <hi rend="italic">should be sent to the Press, to prepare the way for the Reports &amp;c. of the Conference. It invokes the sympathetic interest of all men of goodwill. Then we had tea in the garden, where we found several bishops. The Archbishop told me that a dozen of the High Church Bishops had sent him a "round&#8211;robin" just before the Conference urging that some doctrinal declaration should be put forth: &amp; that he had categorically declined to include it in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">agenda</hi><hi rend="italic">. They had (at the instance of the Bishop of Winchester) acquiesced in this, but he had felt doubtful up to the end whether something might not be attempted. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It is sufficiently evident that the Archbishop is immensely relieved at having got the conference successfully over</hi><hi rend="italic">. We walked back to the Hotel, stopping on the way to look at the statute of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Abraham Lincoln</hi><hi rend="italic">, opposite the Abbey. It is a fine sculpture &amp; compares well with the other statues in Parliament Square, but they have had the smoke of London to blunt their line, and give them an aspect of squalor. We dined in the Hotel, and then I walked to the Deanery of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul's, and had some talk with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. I shewed him </hi><hi rend="italic underline">sub sigillo</hi><hi rend="italic"> the resolutions of the Congress. He thought them disappointing, &amp; on some points reactionary but agreed that they must be made the most of. I was interested to observe the generally unfavourable view which he took of our performance, for which the members of the Conference are for ever thanking God, as if it were a marvel. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Perhaps the ardour of the gratitude discloses the measure of the fear</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Looking back on the Conference, &amp; summing up my impressions, I note the following. The Bishops themselves impressed me as a body of men intensely in earnest, not (with few exceptions) either learned or men of marked intellectual power, but devoted to their work. They represented an immense variety of experience, endeavour, and circumstance. It is no exaggeration to say that the Conference had something of the range &amp; largeness of spirit of a genuinely Catholic assembly. Some of the missionary bishops are ecclesiastical statesmen of no mean quality </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">e.g. the Bishops of Hankow (Roots<persName xml:id="2430"></persName>) and Tinnivelly (…<persName xml:id="5221"></persName>).</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> Several men struck me as genuinely apostles e.g. Brent<persName xml:id="2253"></persName> now Bishop of Western New York. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The prevailing spirit of the Conference was neo&#8211;Tractarian, though there were a good many bishops who would call themselves Evangelical. Mainly the latter were the senior bishops. The younger &amp; abler men have "no use for" either Protestantism or Anglicanism. There is a real desire for union with non&#8211;episcopalians, but no adequate perception of the difficulty. Episcopacy is exalted far beyond what its history or its present influence justifies</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is not perceived that this lofty claim for Episcopacy cannot &amp; in fact does not stand alone. The type of Christianity, of which the fact &amp; doctrine of Episcopacy form an integral factor, is not really possible for modernly educated Christians. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The choice for them lies between Rome &amp; some form of Protestantism</hi><hi rend="italic">. i.e. between authority and private judgments.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>