<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The outlook in the Committee <hi rend="underline">seems</hi> to be improving. We had some more experts. Tissington&#8211;Tatlow<persName xml:id="5260"></persName> explained the general attitude of the students movement. They have little respect for "the churches", &amp; are particularly alienated by the exclusiveness of the High Church Anglicans. This fact is an impressive commentary on the actual measure of success which has been achieved by the Tractarian movements. Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>, Lacey<persName xml:id="1936"></persName>, &amp; Oliver Quick<persName xml:id="5016"></persName> gave evidence, mainly on the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Mansfield Conference which they had attended.<note xml:id="522" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">I cross&#8211;examined Lacey, who cut a poor figure. His super&#8211;subtlety and lack of straightforwardness made a considerable impression.</hi> <hi rend="bold">[</hi>When the excellent Bishop of Uganda<persName xml:id="2174"></persName> started to expound his scheme for "Alliance" I became so bored that I gave it up, &amp; went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> for tea. There I wrote to Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, from whom I have received two long &amp; kind letters.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>The Archbishop of Armagh (d'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName>), the Bishops of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, Durham, Down<persName xml:id="3018"></persName>, &amp; Warrington<persName xml:id="4851"></persName> had conference together on Friday night, &amp; agreed to a procedure in the matter of the South Indian scheme of a United Church.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Lacey stated that it was his custom to receive the Holy Communion in the Roman Church, &amp; that a high Canonist in that church had assured him that he was right in doing so.</hi></p>
         <p>We transferred ourselves to the Deanery at Westminster. There was a pleasant dinner party ‒ Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> &amp; Dorothea Charnwood<persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, Lady Burghclere<persName xml:id="3273"></persName>, Archbishop of Armagh<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> &amp; Mrs D'Arcy, &amp; ourselves. The conversation was more sprightly than interesting. Dorothea never ranges far outside <hi rend="underline">personalia</hi>, &amp; these tend to bore me. <hi rend="bold underline">Unlike the great Dizzy, I do not find female society indispensable</hi>! Haldane spoke about Buckle's<persName xml:id="322"></persName> Life, &amp; told some anecdotes about the Berlin conference, which, however, I had heard before. He was severe on the Queen<persName xml:id="2728" display="no"></persName>, &amp; rather unfair. The burden she inflicted on the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName> was, he thought, excessive: &amp;, of course, her behaviour was grossly unconstitutional.<note xml:id="524" n="1"></note> But I pointed out how easy it is to carry back our present standards for the judgment of an earlier generation which had standards of its own, different from ours. The British Constitution in 1874‒1880 was far other than in 1920: and, perhaps, nowhere so different as in the part played by the Sovereign in the process of Government.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>