<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I went into the City, and changed a cheque. </hi>The cashier, whose attention I had called to my new signature, said "<hi rend="underline">That's a proud signature, my Lord. I have followed your course, so far as the papers have made it possible for me to do so, for many years."</hi> I thanked him for his goodwill: &amp; walked to Lambeth.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Here we resumed the discussion on the "marriage problems" Resolutions. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The dreadful question of "contraceptives" was raised</hi><hi rend="italic">. Of course, the official resolution condemned them utterly, and there seemed every likelihood that this would slip through unchallenged. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">So I rose, and moved an amendment. My speech must have impressed the assembly, for it opened an active discussion, which resulted in considerable modification of the resolution, &amp; the postponement of the general debate. The speech itself as a speech seems to have been a success, for I received many compliments on it</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>, with every appearance of sincerity, said </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I had thought that the art of oratory was dead until I heard your speech</hi><hi rend="italic">." The Abp. of Wales<persName xml:id="1454"></persName> (a flatterous Celt) said, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">It was the finest speech I have ever heard</hi><hi rend="italic">." The Bp. Of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName>, who spoke later, complimented me on the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">brilliance</hi><hi rend="italic">" of my speech; &amp; I bowed my acknowledgments. Many of the bishops came &amp; thanked me for what I said: &amp; there was general applause when I sate down. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p>Perhaps more weighty than such compliments from comparative strangers was the fact that my friends, the Bishops of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> &amp; Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> assured me that I had done well.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Uganda (Willis<persName xml:id="2174"></persName>) told me that he had asked the Indian Bishop of Dornakal (Azariah<persName xml:id="5220"></persName>) how he liked the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>: &amp; he replied that he had enjoyed it all until today, when, for the first time in his life, he had learned of the existence of "contraceptives". Both idea and practice were unknown to the Indians.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I intervened again, and successfully, on a resolution urging the instruction for boys and girls on sex questions. I moved an amendment which changed the resolution into an admonition to parents to give the requisite teaching to their children, and to prepare themselves for the difficult task. My amendment was withdrawn in favour of another moved by the Bishop of Ely<persName xml:id="532"></persName>, which had substantially the same effect.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>The Bishop of Manchester, at tea&#8211;time, introduced me to his sister, whom we met at Toronto, and who is about to return to Canada. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> makes no figure in the Conference. His conduct of the business today was feeble, and he gave the impression of inadequacy.]</hi> Bishop Brent<persName xml:id="2253"></persName> made an excellent speech: and Archbishop D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> also spoke effectively.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>