<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I received a long and kind letter from the Archbishop of Canterbury</hi><persName xml:id="128"></persName>.<note xml:id="511" n="1"></note> Then as the morning advanced came telegrams of welcome from the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; Canon Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>. Also a telegram of congratulation from the Bishop of Rochester<persName xml:id="929"></persName>: &amp; a letter to the same effect from Prebendary Morgan<persName xml:id="4819"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon I received a "round&#8211;robin" of congratulation signed by the Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName>, Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>, Dorothea<persName xml:id="2768"></persName> &amp; the two girls</hi>. All this is alarming enough. The "Times" had a paragraph to the effect that I had been interviewed, &amp; had categorically denied that anything had been settled. So I shall emerge from this torturing interval with the reputation of a liar! Beatty<persName xml:id="4506"></persName> came to see me, &amp; of course began on the same subject. Hence more lies! Knight<persName xml:id="4299"></persName> of Holmer lunched here (still more lies!), and afterwards motored with me round the confines of his immense parish in order that I might be able to form a judgement on his plans for church&#8211;buildings. But I felt it was indeed a futile task now.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam's</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> <hi rend="underline">Bampton Lectures</hi> arrived. This is a smart piece of publishing. I notice that, in the Introduction, he explains that he has incorporated a good deal that has already seen the light in the "Church Quarterly". I read the first Lecture. It contains much good stuff, but it is disfigured by a note of rudeness to opponents, some of whom at least are too eminent to be thus treated. His criticism of the New Testament gave me the impression of being very thin and dogmatic.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>