<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We packed our bags before going out with the Professor to visit S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas Church. <hi rend="bold underline">Here we did our homage at the grave of the Crown Princess</hi>, and then were conducted over the Church by the Vicar, <hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">(a very bibulous&#8211;looking ecclesiastic)</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> It contains a famous figure of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George &amp; the Dragon set up in the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. We saw also a number of fine vestments &amp; much communion plate. This church which is the "Town church" is the coronation place of the Swedish monarchs since the time of Gustavus Vasa<persName xml:id="5122"></persName>. It is a brick&#8211;built Gothic church, rather gaudily restored. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Olaus Petri</hi><persName xml:id="5111"></persName> ministered here, &amp; his tomb&#8211;stone is shown underneath the pulpit. Next we went to the old Meeting House of the Nobles, which is a fine rectangular chamber adorned with the shields of the Swedish nobility. <hi rend="bold underline">We walked back to the Hotel</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">[</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; </hi><hi rend="bold underline">"brushed up"] before proceeding to the Royal Palace to lunch with the Crown Prince.</hi> This was a very agreeable experience. The Prince was affable &amp; intelligent. Two of his children were present. After lunch H.R.H. showed us the Riddarholm Church which is undergoing restoration, &amp; then sent us to the station in his motor. We travelled by a slow train (47 m. in 2 hrs) to Upsala, &amp; were met at the station by the Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">He has staying here one of these inevitable Greek prelates, who have the same fascination for modern Scandinavians as the wives of the South for their barbarous ancestors! After dinner this potentate lectured to a numerous company in ^modern^ Greek, being translated into Swedish</hi>. I was edified by neither version, being ignorant of both tongues.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop took us (Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> &amp; me) into the cathedral, &amp; expounded the arrangements for Sunday's function</hi>. What vestments would we wear? I replied that we w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> appear <hi rend="bold">[</hi>in red<hi rend="bold">]</hi> ^our Convocation robes^ after the English manner. Were those robes the proper consecrating vestments? Here P. replied that the English bishops wore cape &amp; mitre; but I pointed out that this practice was a modern innovation, &amp; that no such vestments were generally worne in England. The Abp. of C.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> always wore the red Convocation habit at consecrations. This appeared to satisfy <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Abp. S&#x00F6;derblom</hi>, &amp; he said that we must act as officiating prelates, and take our stand beside him on either side of the altar. Also, we must read one of the Scriptural passages, either in Swedish or in Greek. <hi rend="bold underline">We elected to read Swedish! and were subsequently "coached" in the pronunciation</hi>! The Archbishop kept us up talking until a few minutes before midnight. He is an extremely clever &amp; versatile man, &amp; watches very closely the signs of their preferences which his hearers betray. Then he matches his words, with quite amazing adroitness, to those preferences. He is somewhat embarrassed by having to deal at one &amp; the same time with two, and they conflicting, exponents of Anglicanism. <hi rend="bold underline">When he placates Peterborough, he alienates Durham: when Durham smiles approval: Peterborough frowns discontent!</hi> Mainly, he is obsessed by the conventional forms of what is called ecclesiastical liberalism. He plays with Socialism: affects a mighty&#8211;zeal for democracy: &amp; proclaims his scorn for clericalism. But he is ambitious, &amp; fond of power. He likes to play the part of a great prelate, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; has many of the qualities which mark the character of our own Archbishop! The two men are in fact very similar</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>