<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I read the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> luxuriously in bed before getting up, &amp; also re&#8211;read a lecture of Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName>. Then I breakfasted in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote my letters before going to the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. The whole morning was wasted over a silly report on organizing Provinces &amp;c. This "bored me stark". <hi rend="bold underline">After lunch, Lang<persName xml:id="130"></persName> introduced the Reunion Committee's Report in a windy &amp; rather canty speech</hi>. Then the American bishops went off to attend the function of presenting Lincoln's statue;<note xml:id="518" n="1"></note> and the rest of us settled down to consider the Report on Women's Work. The Resolutions proposed were of a revolutionary character. <hi rend="bold underline">I made such opposition as I could, but with small success</hi>. The feminist tide runs strongly among the Bishops, but the proposal frankly to transfer women from the laity to the clergy startles and displeases the High Churchmen. Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> gave expression to this feeling. The "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot"<persName xml:id="105"></persName> set</hi>, however, are vehemently feminist, &amp; the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> himself is clearly in that camp. I dined in the Athenaeum with Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName>. George Adam Smith<persName xml:id="244"></persName> was there, and W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>. The latter promised to attend my enthronement on October 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. After dinner I wrote my diary, and spent the time in the Club until I returned to Garland's. I count the days until this precious conference is over!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>