<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from Linton Smith<persName xml:id="4851"></persName>, the Suffragan Bishop of Warrington, informing me that Hereford had been offered to him, &amp; making a series of inquiries. I replied to this letter without delay. Also, a letter from Ernest came with some characteristic reflections. He adds: "You will get a warm welcome from the laity; and if ever you feel inclined to vilipend Ll.G., remember that now (as before) he held out like a man." This means, I presume, that their Graces were hostile.</p>
         <p>The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came in, and I had to tell him of my approaching departure. He professed considerable regret. After lunch I walked with the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Withington, where I dedicated a Memorial Cross, and gave an address to the parishioners. The fineness of the weather, &amp; the beauty of the village, with its fine tower &amp; spire showing above the trees, made the scene very beautiful. We gave old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi> Lea &amp; his bicycle a lift home to Lugwardine, where we walked round the Vicarage garden, &amp; were laden with flowers. We were back in the Palace in good time for dinner. These functions have a rather hollow feeling now that I know myself to be as it were coming before the people under false pretences! However I must reconcile myself to this state of involuntary hypocrisy for some days yet, possibly for some weeks!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>