<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; I drove to the Abbey for the opening service of the Lambeth Conference</hi><orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. The bishops robed in the Great School. I walked as Bishop of Durham immediately in front of the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName>. The service was most impressive. <hi rend="italic">I could not but be moved at finding myself placed in the very same stall which I occupied when I came to the Abbey as Canon 20 years ago. As the Bp of London did not communicate, I </hi><hi rend="italic underline">led</hi><hi rend="italic"> the Bishops to the Altar.</hi> Ryle's<persName xml:id="325"></persName> sermon started well, but ended rather in a pathos. He made a long &amp; earnest appeal to the Bishops to restore the word 'holy' to the Nicene Creed, from which it had been inadvertently dropped out at the Reformation! I thought that at least he would advocate the omission of the 'filioque'! Then I rested for 1 1/2 hours, <hi rend="bold underline">when I went to Lambeth, &amp; had an hour's private conversation with the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>. He appealed to me to help him in drafting the Encyclical Letter, saying many flatterous things about my power</hi> of expressing myself in lucid &amp; dignified English &amp;c, &amp;c. I told him that I w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> do what I c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi>; &amp; insisted that the essential thing was that, in the matter of Reunion, the Conference sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> go forward, &amp; not again abide in platitudes. He agreed, &amp; seemed rather relieved when I drew a distinction between the presbyterians &amp; other non&#8211;episcopalians. He has evidently agreed to get Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, Bernard<persName xml:id="225"></persName>, Ryle, Copleston<persName xml:id="1690"></persName> &amp; King brought back into the Conference.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p>The Abp. is evidently apprehensive of something like a dead&#8211;lock. He points out that for the first time all the subjects on the agenda are both pressing &amp; highly controversial. I said that there was<hi rend="italic"> no use blinking the fact that the conflict on first principles was reaching a point within the Anglican Communion which threatened disruption, &amp; that, perhaps, disruption w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> not be the worst thing. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I could not be the Abp. in whose time the High Church party was driven out of the Church of England</hi><hi rend="italic">", he said. He will probably give in to a threat of secession, whereas my firm belief is that any such threat w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> certainly not mature in action. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>