<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>A fine morning. I reflected sadly as I looked out over the garden from my dressing&#8211;room, that in a few weeks, perhaps four at the most, I must leave this house for ever. It will not be without a very genuine regret. There is a strange sense of unreality, almost of insincerity, about everything that I do or say while the secret of my impending departure remains locked in my breast. This afternoon I felt a woeful imposter in pressing on the gathering of farmers their duty to support the Hospital. The notion of giving a garden&#8211;party to the farmers &amp; their wives was suggested by the Hospital authorities, and was on the whole well taken up. Sixty or seventy farmers accepted the invitation, &amp; I harangued them in the garden.</p>
         <p>Then I took <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> in the motor, &amp; we went as far as Bridstow just in order to see more of the glorious beauty of the country, which stretches in a grand panorama from the road to Ross. K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> was out in the parish, but we saw his wife. I did not think it well to reveal my secret to her, though to him I was prepared to make it known. <hi rend="bold underline">These waiting days between the decision and its official announcement are enormously trying</hi>. For one is bound to silence, &amp; yet the course of one's life is continually raising questions which cannot really be answered on the supposition which one's silence suggests. How can I make arrangements, appoint to livings, determine this or that issue in the diocese, when I know that I have no real title to do any of these things? My successor<persName xml:id="4851"></persName> will hardly thank me for anticipating decisions which he ought to take, since he must face their consequences! </p>
         </body></text></TEI>