<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I arranged that the Archdeacons<persName xml:id="3618"><persName xml:id="4450"></persName></persName> sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have the use of my motor during my absence on 4 days in the week, &amp; that on the remaining two William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> should assist Jones in cutting the lawn. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I put together papers &amp; books for the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>, &amp; bound up the congratulations in bundles. I wrote a short letter to the "Times", thanking my correspondents. Then we left Hereford, &amp; travelled easily to Paddington, where we obtained a taxi with little difficulty, &amp; were driven to 16 Elvaston Place, where Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName> awaited us.</hi></p>
         <p>A dinner party. Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName>, Lord Justice Younger<persName xml:id="4071"></persName>, the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ryle<persName xml:id="326"></persName>, Sir Henry Howard<persName xml:id="5244"></persName> &amp; his daughter, Lady Cromer<persName xml:id="1144"></persName>, &amp; several others. It was pleasant enough, though, perhaps the chaff about "prince&#8211;bishops" grows rather tiresome when one allows oneself to remember the actual situation. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Buchanan<persName xml:id="977"></persName> sate beside me at dinner, &amp; talked about the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> "Memoir"<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, with which she expressed herself greatly pleased. The references to her husband<persName xml:id="115"></persName> were happily favourable, &amp; <hi rend="underline">they</hi> no doubt determined her attitude towards the book. It is amazing how self&#8211;centred we all are, &amp; how we judge everything in its bearing on ourselves!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p>The National Assembly: (June 30&#8211;July 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>)</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I attended the first sessions of the National Assembly, and (with the exception of an hour at Q.A.B.<orgName xml:id="296"></orgName>) sate through them. It was sufficiently evident that the Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"></persName><persName xml:id="130"></persName> had arranged everything in collusion with the Palmer&#8211;Cecil&#8211;Wood combination, which has prevailed throughout</hi><hi rend="italic">. The main business was that of appointing various Committees, &amp; it became at once apparent that what I ever foretold is already happening, viz. that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the whole business will fall automatically into the hands of the metropolitan clique</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I spoke briefly<ref xml:id="1100"></ref> on the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> day </hi><hi rend="i bold">[July 1</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> emphasising the necessity of a more deliberate &amp; careful handling of the question of the endowments than the Assembly seemed disposed to contemplate. There was an evident desire to be rigorously "business&#8211;like". </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Athelstan Riley</hi><persName xml:id="213"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who made a dilatory speech, was summarily disposed of</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; there was a certain impatience of time&#8211;consuming rhetoric. The Archbishop was bent on getting through the business, &amp; succeeded to admiration. But the Assembly is an unwieldy thing, &amp; hard to fashion into a legislative instrument. </hi></p>
         <p>On Wednesday, we dined with the Charnwoods<persName xml:id="2685"></persName><persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, and on Thursday <hi rend="bold">[July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> we dined quietly with Miss Mundella.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On the whole I was received with kindness in the Assembly &amp; received many congratulations. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Edward Clarke</hi><persName xml:id="4002"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was particularly ardent in his words. I suppose my rapid advance is rather dramatic.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Friday July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1920, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I travelled to Canterbury, where we stayed with the <persName xml:id="383">Spooners</persName><persName xml:id="2162"></persName>. The Abp. of Rupertsland<persName xml:id="2933"></persName> was also their guest</hi>. On Saturday there were two functions  ̶  a lunch at S. Augustine's, and a service in the Cathedral <hi rend="bold underline">at which the Archbishop sitting in S. Augustine's Chair formally welcomed the Bishops. I walked with the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> as the elect of Durham. <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName> came over from Birchington, &amp; witnessed the</hi> function with Ella &amp; the Spooners. Afterwards there was a numerously attended garden party in the Chapter grounds. Then we all returned to London, &amp; were back in 16 Elvaston Place in time for dinner.</p>
         <p>I had some conversation with the Abp. of Rupertsland on the prospect of "Reunion" in the Conference. He said that he was not hopeful: <hi rend="bold underline">that he found a change for the worse in the feeling of the bishops: that he had been much impressed by Armitage Robinson's<persName xml:id="44"></persName> sermon at the recent consecration of bishops, which was glaringly in contrast with the sermon which he preached before the Conference of 1912, being, indeed, a plea for the rigidest view of Apostolical succession</hi>. He agreed that <hi rend="underline">either</hi> we must go forward by frankly recognizing the validity of presbyterian orders, <hi rend="underline">or</hi> we must drop the subject altogether. He said that the Abp. of Melbourne<persName xml:id="5215"></persName> was as depressed at the prospect as himself. I had a few words with D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName>, now Abp of Armagh, &amp; he also seemed rather disheartened. <hi rend="bold underline">On all of them I pressed the importance of keeping a stiff back, &amp; insisting on taking some forward step. Clearly, there has been a considerable "Catholick" reaction, &amp; the bishops are, for the most part, timorous creatures</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>