<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to see me at 9.45 a.m. with a sheaf of small affairs to settle. I signed the Commission for Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> to act as suffragan, &amp; promised to have the seal sent to Durham for its due sealing. He suggested that I should ask Pattison<persName xml:id="3773"></persName> to accompany me at Bishop Auckland when I go through the furniture. Incidentally, he said that, so far as he c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> remember, the great carpet was valued at no more than &#x00A3;30. <hi rend="bold underline">He said that the late Bishop's books were left to the Castle. I inquired whether I sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be bound to preserve the rubbish, &amp; he said that he thought I had a perfectly free hand. Then I ordered a dress suit of purple cloth at Wippell's: and went to the hair&#8211;dresser to have my hair trimmed</hi>. Then I walked to Lambeth, where the <hi rend="bold underline">tiresome business of the marriage&#8211;problems report was resumed. We had a series of frantically fanatical speeches, from Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName></hi>, S<hi rend="superscript">t </hi>Alban's<persName xml:id="1602"></persName>, &amp; others. I went off about 6.30 p.m., leaving the conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> in session. I dined at 16 Elvaston Place. The company consisted of Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>, the Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName>, Luigi Villari<persName xml:id="5253"></persName> (the son of the historian of Florence), M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Andrew Lang<persName xml:id="4068"></persName>, another lady, &amp; myself. It was quite a pleasant party. I returned to the Hotel about 11 p.m. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The discussion was continued at Lambeth until nearly 8 p.m., &amp; then </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Zanzibar</hi><hi rend="italic">, finding the bishops disposed to vote a very modest amendment, struck an attitude, &amp; threatened to secede from the Conference. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The menace had an immediate effect: the amendment was not put to the vote: &amp; the whole matter was adjourned until the following day! It is difficult adequately to describe such pusillanimous conduct. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>