<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I began my day by finishing Bury's book. It leaves on me the impression of the utter bankruptcy of rationalistic optimism. There is <hi rend="underline">that</hi> in man himself which baffles &amp; spoils everything. The Cambridge Sermon proves very troublesome. I want to preach about the "Via Media", and probably it is not prudent to do so.</p>
         <p>After lunch I had an interview with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Butt, the curate from Coddington, to whom I explained why I could not grant him a licence.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Then I motored to Bridstow, &amp; had some talk with K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> He says that the probability of my going to Durham is being talked about in London. He seemed rather startled at the notion of my joining in the actual laying on of hands in the Swedish ordination</hi><hi rend="bold">:</hi> yet surely there can be no real distinction between such an act of fraternal recognition, and receiving the Holy Communion at the hands of the Swedish clergy, the validity of whose ministry would thereby be conceded. Would any objection be taken against my accepting a Greek, Russian, or Armenian invitation to assist at a Consecration? If not, then it would seem to be evident that the objection to the same proceeding in Sweden arises from a refusal to acknowledge the genuineness of the Swedish episcopate, &amp; it would involve me in an endorsement of the whole Tractarian thesis. A vote of the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> could not be allowed any direct authority over my action, though it would be unreasonable not to take it into the most careful consideration. The Archbishop's<persName xml:id="128"></persName> personal opinion would weigh much with me if I could persuade myself that it would not be merely the echo of Bishop Talbot<persName xml:id="105"></persName> or Canon Mason<persName xml:id="3520"></persName>, or some other Tractarian.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>