<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[147]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Before getting up I wrote to Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName>, Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>, and Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>. Then we breakfasted, &amp; made some progress with the packing. We succeeded in getting our tickets at the Tourist Agency, &amp; returned to the Hotel in time for the motor car, which <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bildt</hi> sent to bring us out for lunch. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ramsays</hi> were also of the party. We drove about 24 miles over bad roads, &amp; through beautiful country. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> B's house is fine, &amp; finely placed on the shore of a wide lake. After a pleasant lunch we were motored back to our hotel, bursting a tyre on the way. I admired the expedition with which the chauffeur remedied the mischief, &amp; the convenient device he had for raising the car. We had tea, &amp; I walked round to the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Clara Church house, &amp; left the MS. of my sermon. The Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> was there, &amp; we again exchanged affectionate farewells.</p>
         <p>Getting away from Stockholm was both a complicated &amp; a costly business, &amp; would <hi rend="bold underline">never have been achieved at all but for the help of the messenger from the British Legation, who richly merited the 20 kr. with which I rewarded his attentions</hi>. The train was crowded: &amp; we only secured sleeping berths at the last moment. Numbers of people came to say Goodbye to their friends, &amp; the train moved out of the station amid much popular interest. As we passed over the bridge, we saw the last of Stockholm, bathed in the mild glory of a full moon, which traced its <hi rend="underline">Via sacra</hi> of brilliance on the rippling waters of Lake M&#x00E4;lar. We can hardly see a fairer city.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>