<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the day at Lambeth in Committee on Reunion</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The Bishops of Pennsylvania (Rheinlander<persName xml:id="3067"></persName>) &amp; Winchester (Talbot<persName xml:id="105"></persName>) led off with lengthy speeches on the Ideal of Reunion, which was, of course, so stated as to make Episcopacy essential, &amp; to disallow any recognition of non&#8211;episcopal orders. They were followed by <hi rend="bold">[</hi>the egregious<hi rend="bold">]</hi> Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">There was a sharp passage of arms between the Bishop of Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName> &amp; myself over the historical point whether the English Church had recognized presbyterian orders: &amp; I was treated with some rudeness by one of the Scottish bishops</hi><hi rend="bold"> (</hi><hi rend="b strikethrough">Maclean</hi><persName xml:id="2394"></persName><hi rend="bold">).</hi> In the afternoon the Bishop of Madras<persName xml:id="5157"></persName> expounded the situation in South India, &amp; expressed himself with some warmth, indicating that he would reconsider his position as an Anglican bishop if he were required by the Conference to refuse recognition of their ministry to the non&#8211;episcopal ministers concerned in the scheme for a South Indian Church. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>I met Fearon<persName xml:id="691"></persName>, lately Archdeacon of Winchester, in the club, and Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName>. Both were most friendly. <hi rend="italic">We transferred ourselves from the Deanery of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Paul's to 20 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, where we became the guests of Canon<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="italic">Temple</hi>. There was a pleasant dinner party. Sir Henry<persName xml:id="344"></persName> &amp; Lady Craik<persName xml:id="793"></persName> with Col: &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hill were also guests. I had some talk with Temple before going to bed. He expresses himself very fairly<hi rend="bold">.]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>