<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; there wrote letters. Then I went to Lambeth, &amp; sate continuously on the Reunion Committee from 11.a.m. to 6.15 p.m. with brief intervals for lunch and tea. <hi rend="bold underline">Things went badly on the whole. The return of the episcopal churches section of the Committee strengthened greatly the "Catholick" faction. [On the division to exclude the "reciprocity" paragraph from the projected appeal, the numbers were 33 against to 11 from exclusion. But the Liberal forces were as usual divided. The Bishops of Massachusetts<persName xml:id="931"></persName> and Uganda<persName xml:id="2174"></persName> voted on the wrong side</hi>. We got to work on the draft of the Report after tea.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>We dined with the Bishop of Madras<persName xml:id="5157"></persName> in his hotel. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Whitehead<persName xml:id="5249"></persName>, her mother, &amp; a young clergyman, her brother, (who was once one of Armitage Robinson's<persName xml:id="44"></persName> young men at Westminster). We talked "shop" for two hours, not very usefully, &amp; so returned home. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> W. is rather a formidable lady, and suggests M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Proudie. Her husband is evidently well under control, &amp; it is no extravagant surmise that she has been an important factor in shaping his ecclesiastical policy. <hi rend="bold underline">She told me that she herself had preached in the Cathedral in Madras &amp; that, not merely on special occasions to a congregation of her own sex,</hi> but to the general body of the faithful at the regular services. This argues a considerable audacity of innovation in the Church, and much marital complaisance in the Bishop. She spoke also with disconcerting frankness on the subject of parity.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>