<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Two press&#8211;cutting agencies send me cuttings from yesterday's newspapers. The <hi rend="underline">Daily Telegraph</hi> and the The <hi rend="underline">Daily Graphic</hi> stated my appointment to Durham as an accomplished fact, though they do not claim to speak officially. It is not altogether surprising, therefore, that I am receiving letters of congratulation, but it is enormously annoying from every point of view. How little these papers really know is shown by their confident expectation that Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> will succeed me here.</p>
         <p>Letters of congratulation, very kindly expressed, from Burdon<persName xml:id="1659"></persName> &amp; Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName>. The latter reminds me that I have often told him in the past 'that you do not think very much of the "Evangelical" body in the Church of England as a living &amp; effective force in Church life'. He goes on:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Still you will probably be disposed to tolerate variety in those who are proud to call themselves your friends; &amp; speaking as one who, both by tradition &amp; conviction, has been associated with that school of thought, I should like to assure you of loyal friendship &amp; glad support." This is handsomely expressed.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Lilley<persName xml:id="3618"></persName> came in, and had to be told the fatal news. He seemed very sorry.</p>
         <p>My designate successor in this see, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Linton Smith</hi><persName xml:id="4851"></persName>, Bishop of Warrington, &amp; his wife, came to learn all we could tell them about Hereford. After lunch I took them in the motor to Kilpeck, Abbey Dore, Peterchurch, and Madley. He seems a frank, pleasant man, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">told me that he had accepted the Bishoprick against the advice of both the Archbishops</hi><persName xml:id="128"></persName><persName xml:id="130"></persName>. Both he and his wife are evidently well&#8211;pleased with their approaching change of status &amp; locality.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>