<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[61]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The whole day was occupied with the discussion of the Resolutions on Women's place in the Church. <hi rend="bold">I</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">moved an amendment in order to raise directly the question whether Deaconesses were, or were not, to be admitted to Holy Orders</hi>. The voting went against me, but in the course of the day, the general conclusions went to meet my views. <hi rend="italic bold underline">There can be no doubt, however, as the feminist ardour of the Bishops</hi><hi rend="bold">. [</hi>In luncheon interval I had some talk with M<hi rend="bold">c</hi>Innes<persName xml:id="5251"></persName>, the Bishop in Jerusalem, an intelligent man. He gave me rather a startling account of the effect of the Zionist policy in Palestine. The local Jews, who get on well with their neighbours, are opposed to it. It is supported, advertized, &amp; pressed forward in a very unscrupulous way by the Zionist associations of England &amp; America, who are importing numbers of Bolshevistic Jews from Russia &amp; elsewhere, to the scandal &amp; terror of the Palestinian population. Samuel's appointment as British administrator gave a cruel shock to public belief in British good faith: but he was carrying himself with fairness &amp; independence so that he was now more popular with the Moslems than with his own compatriots.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>I lunched with the <persName xml:id="227">Murrays</persName><persName xml:id="666"></persName> (at 98 Park Street, Mayfair, W.1). Buff<persName xml:id="836" display="no"></persName> was there looking radiant. She retains the curiously attractive "Beatrice Cenci" look which she had as a child. Murray motored me back to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> after dinner. There I found Harold Boulton<persName xml:id="5254"></persName> &amp; Joseph Shaw<persName xml:id="5028"></persName> in the smoking room, &amp; had some talk with them before turning in.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
</body></text></TEI>