<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>I read aloud the lecture on "<hi rend="underline">Puritanism</hi>", &amp; corrected it. Then we walked to the British Legation, and inquired about the passport into Germany. A pleasant youth named Bennett (I think) one of the secretaries, retained our passports.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> We went to the <hi rend="underline">Skansen</hi>, &amp; viewed with interest the collections, living and life&#8211;less, which are there preserved. After lunching in the island, we visited the Scandinavian museum, where <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> "enthused" over the furniture &amp; <hi rend="underline">I gazed with profound interest &amp; a religious veneration on the relics of</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gustavus Adolphus</hi>. After tea we returned to the hotel, &amp; there I found messages from Abp. S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">including an invitation to lunch on Friday with the Crown Prince</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote 1) to Mr Baldwin at Gothenburg, 2) to Balfour Wilson at Broadstairs, and 3) to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. Then I revised the lecture on "<hi rend="underline">The Roman Controversy</hi>".</p>
         <p>There is a brief account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Henrik Schartau</hi><persName xml:id="5227"></persName> (1757&#8211;1825) in Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wordsworth's</hi><persName xml:id="1554"></persName> "<hi rend="underline">The National Church of Sweden</hi>"<ref xml:id="1089"></ref> p.364f., but it is too vaguely expressed to assist to an understanding of modern "Schartauists". He appears to have been a considerable "director" of individuals, and <hi rend="italic">an ardent preacher &amp; catechist. Thus he combined the characteristic qualities &amp; distinctive influence of Pusey<persName xml:id="4373"></persName> and Simeon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">"His fault, which was exaggerated by his followers, was a certain constant reference to the forms &amp; divisions of logic and to inward state of the soul  ̶  in other words to psychology. This led to a curious &amp; anxious introspection, to a balancing of motives &amp; convictions, and to the requirement of a conscious ascent through certain stages of progress, which was not altogether healthy. In his followers these characteristics have produced a certain dryness &amp; tediousness, and, it is said, too great a dependence on the "direction" of the chosen spiritual guide." All this leaves no clear impression on my mind.</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Wordsworth</hi><hi rend="italic"> adds that "popular favour is no longer strong for the system which he inaugurated."</hi> <hi rend="i bold">I suppose Schantauism is but a variety of Evangelicalism &#8211; an affair of emotions labelled by </hi><hi rend="i bold strikethrough">cant</hi><hi rend="i bold"> ^ traditional phrases ^. The emotions have generally disappeared, the phrases which were coined to describe them have continued in use, &amp; are now the veriest cant. Hence the whole system has sunk into a very nauseous kind of artificial pietism.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>