<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[148]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I got out of our 'sleeper' in time to see the sunrise of another brilliant autumm day. The country was rather monotonous, though there were interludes of beauty when we skirted one of the charming wooded lakes which are so characteristic of Sweden. <hi rend="bold underline">At 7.30 a.m. we reached Lund, &amp; were met at the station by Prof. Ahlen</hi>. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>After disclosing our tickets at the office, &amp; paying 3 kronor for the privilege of "stopping off", we went to the Grand Hotel, and breakfasted. Then I went into the city and got shaved. Returning to the Hotel, I wrote to Lord Durham thanking him for a gift of venison.<hi rend="bold">] </hi>The day was spent in sight&#8211;seeing &amp; hospitality. We had the great advantage of being shown over the cathedral by the son of the cathedral architect, (Hans W&#x00E4;hlin) who evidently had made a loving study of it. The wonderful crypt &amp; choir stalls are unforgettable. Then I attended an academic function, in which a new professor delivered an inaugural address. I wore my red gown, &amp; was thereby rendered very conspicuous, for everybody else was in evening dress. Next we lunched with Proffesor Ahlen: &amp; then M. W&#x00E4;hlin showed me a most interesting collection of medieval crucifixes, reredoses, &amp;c &amp;c. Then we had tea with Professor Rohde, the Bishop's son&#8211;in&#8211;law. Finally, we dined with old Bishop Billing at his palace. As we walked back to the Hotel, we stopped to admire the cathedral as it stood out in the strong light of a full moon. The splendid apse was particularly impressive. Then more packing, and bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>