<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[34]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the day at Lambeth where we discussed Foreign Mission Problems. On the whole 'twas a very dull day. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>I was most interested by a speech which was made by the Bishop in Jerusalem<persName xml:id="5251"></persName>. He denounced Zionism with much vigour: said that the whole country was longing for a restoration of Turkish rule: &amp; that the appointment of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Herbert Samuel</hi><persName xml:id="1480"></persName> had given the <hi rend="underline">coup de grace</hi> to British credit.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> The Bp. of Calcutta (Westcott<persName xml:id="5090" display="no"></persName>) described the difficulties which had arisen between missionaries &amp; the Government. He acquitted the German missionaries and the Government. He acquitted the German missionaries of any active agitation against British rul, but said that of necessity they carried their national feeling &amp; sympathies with them. Some of them objected to taking the pledge wh. the Govern<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> of India exacts from alien missionaries, viz: that they will make their converts good citizens of the British Empire. Azariah<persName xml:id="5220"></persName>, the Tamil bishop of Dornakal, made a striking speech about nationalism in India. <hi rend="underline">There was a general expression of disgust &amp; contempt for everything specifically Anglican (Prayer Book, 39 Articles, etc.). We must be "Catholick" or nothing</hi>! Bishop Root<persName xml:id="2430"></persName> of Hankow pointed out that the position of the English &amp; American missionaries in Corea with respect to the Japanese Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> was precisely identical with that of the alien missionaries in India with respect to the Government of India.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi></p>
         <p>The speeches of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Zanzibar</hi><persName xml:id="3469"></persName> are somewhat perplexing. He speaks contemptuously of the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>, &amp; all its ways: tells the Bishops to live among the poor in the slums, &amp; ask them to dinner: describes the episcopal character very grotesquely, &amp; is treated as "a chartered libertine". He is elaborately polite to me. I doubt whether he is taken seriously by anybody, though he is generally popular.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Palmer</hi><persName xml:id="2498"></persName> (Bombay) seems to regard himself, and to be regarded, as a highly important member of the Conference. His stutter obstructs his eloquence, but he speaks often. I find it difficult to understand his drift, but <hi rend="underline">he is bitterly contemptuous of everything distinctively English, &amp; evidently an ardent advocate of disestablishment in India &amp; in England</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">The American bishops so far have made no figure. Even Brent<persName xml:id="2253"></persName> was disappointing. Bp. Roots of Hankow is the best of them</hi>.</p>
         <p>I dined at the Mansion House. Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> went with me. There were no ladies. I sat between the Bishops of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName> &amp; Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">The American Bishops, so far as I could perceive, were all drinking wine freely, in spite of Prohibition</hi>. Their oratory after dinner was characteristically bombastic, &amp; the Bishop of Tennessee (Gailor<persName xml:id="5216"></persName>), who acts as their leader, ascribed to Lanfranc Langton's performance in the matter of Magna Carta.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>