<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[14]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920</hi>.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Qui confidunt in Domino sicut mons Sion: non commovebitur in aeternum, qui habitat in Jerusalem. Montes in circuitu ejus: et Dominus in circuitu populi sui, ex hoc nunc et usque in saeculum.<note xml:id="510" n="1"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>Durham was the 'the English Sion'. I copied the words from an illuminated text in my bed&#8211;room, and embraced the omen.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I preached<ref xml:id="1099"></ref> at 11 a.m. in Trinity College Chapel, &amp; received the Holy Communion</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was a singular coincidence that the first sermon I delivered after undertaking to sit in the chair of Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName>, Westcott<persName xml:id="1047"></persName>, &amp; Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, all Fellows of Trinity, should be delivered in that place.</hi> I preached on 'Privilege'  ̶ the subject was curiously relevant to my own situation  ̶  though the sermon was not a new one. </p>
         <p>The Holy Communion was wonderfully comforting. I lunched at Emmanuel with the Master<persName xml:id="5208"></persName>, who is Vice&#8211;Chancellor. Here I was delighted with the gallery &amp; its pictures. Sancroft<persName xml:id="5209"></persName>, Whichcote<persName xml:id="5052"></persName>, &amp; Cudworth<persName xml:id="4950"></persName> were among these. I walked in procession to the Senate&#8211;house, whence we passed in due state to Great S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's. <hi rend="bold underline">There was a very large congregation especially of dons. The Vice&#8211;Chancellor told me that he had not seen the Church so full at an University Sermon for 10 years past. My sermon was very closely listened to</hi>. I went in to old Prof. Bonney<persName xml:id="1862"></persName>, who was almost affectionate. I told him that I was going to Durham, &amp; he expressed the utmost satisfaction. This also gratified me quite inordinately.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>As I left the Senate house, a little lady accosted me. She was Miss Perry of Barking, now living in Cambridge. Gilbert Darwin<persName xml:id="3981"></persName> hailed me after the sermon at Trinity: &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">Cecil Ferens<persName xml:id="4218"></persName> was lunching at Emmanuel to meet me</hi>. I had tea in Clough Hall with Elizabeth<persName xml:id="3077" display="no"></persName>. Her "best friend" Miss Kennedy from West Ham was there  ̶  a very charming, bright girl. Elizabeth walked with me into the town, in order that I might renew my memory of the colleges.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Burkitt<persName xml:id="574"></persName> &amp; I dined in Trinity as the Master's<persName xml:id="4082"></persName> guests</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> It was a very pleasant evening. In the Combination room <hi rend="bold underline">I sat beside M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Taggart<persName xml:id="4083"></persName>, who was most civil</hi>. Then we went to the Master's Lodge, &amp; smoked (i.e. <hi rend="underline">they</hi> smoked) for an hour. The conversation was most interesting. <hi rend="bold underline">The Master spoke with much freedom of his experiences in efforts to get at the bottom of spiritualism. He thinks it is mainly, if not wholly, fraudulent</hi>. At 11 p.m. we left Trinity, &amp; walked home. The night was fine &amp; still. From a cloudless sky, one brilliant star shone, &amp; was reflected in the glassy surface of the river. Nothing could be more beautiful. So I ended an entirely pleasant day. I confessed to Burkitt the sentiment which had swept over me this morning in Trinity, &amp; he said that it established a link with the College. I replied that it would be very acceptable to me if Trinity would approve my going to the great See, which had almost become a Cambridge foundation.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>