<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920</hi></p>
         <p>The Reunion Report went through with little difficulty, almost without alteration, to the manifest relief of the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>. <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> was in charge of the resolutions, &amp; on the whole, did his part well. There were two dangerous moments. First, when the Bishop of Vermont (Hall<persName xml:id="5252"></persName>) denounced the whole Report as inherently inconsistent with Catholic principles: and, next, when the Bishops of Ely<persName xml:id="532"></persName> &amp; Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName> made an attempt to alter the resolution. The Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>, however, was in no mood for controversy, &amp; had plainly set its heart on getting something done. The Bishops of Western New York (Brent<persName xml:id="2253"></persName>), and Pennsylvania (Rheinlander<persName xml:id="3067"></persName>) refused to follow the lead of the Bishop of Vermont, <hi rend="bold underline">who could only carry 3 bishops with him when the vote on the Address was taken</hi>. Somebody suggested the singing of the Doxology when the Address was adopted, &amp; this was done with much fervour. <hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> was much applauded when he refused to follow the Catholick minority. It is almost amusing to notice the compliments which are poured out on this odd prelate, who only a few months since was hurling anathemas against all the bishops for their refusal to excommunicate me as a heretick! The Evangelical bishops appeared to be greatly pleased with the day's work, and, perhaps, the painful efforts at self&#8211;justification, which the Catholicks made, may be taken as some evidence that they feel themselves beaten</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>