<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>The Town&#8211;clerk of Darlington wants "a copy of my private arms" to copy into the "Jubilee Record Book" which I must sign when I enter the Diocese formally. I wrote to him in these terms:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I come of a race of West Country farmers &amp; small landowners who have never, so far as I know, borne arms, &amp; it is rather a point of honour with me not to begin doing so now. So you will, please, print the Arms of the See alone, &amp; a blank shield where the private arms would ordinarily come."</p>
         </div>
         <p>It's a nuisance to have to enter into these explanations, but there's nothing else to be done.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>We discussed the Church's duty in the matter of Industrial Matters. <hi rend="bold underline">The speeches were so uniformly Socialistic in tone &amp; effect that I was moved to speak in the contrary sense. My speech had a tonic effect on the discussion</hi>. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>In the interval before lunch we were all photographed. I attended M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Davidson's<persName xml:id="404"></persName> "At Home", &amp; had some talk with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Lowther<persName xml:id="1731"></persName>, who was very eager in defence of General Dyer<persName xml:id="5259"></persName>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">One of the American bishops expressed to me his wonder at the attentive hearing which I obtained in the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. I suppose he expected that I should be howled down</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> The Bishop of New York<persName xml:id="5218"></persName> introduced himself to me, &amp; said that his wife still spoke of my "unforgettable" sermon on President Garfield's<persName xml:id="2888"></persName> death. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>I dined at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>