<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>A sheaf of congratulatory letters! The Press&#8211;cutting Agency <hi rend="underline">proprio motu</hi> sends an article from the Yorkshire Post, with a column of biography!!</p>
         <p>My successor&#8211;elect<persName xml:id="4851"></persName>, having set Bateman's<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> mind at rest, went off in the course of the morning. I motored to Yockton, &amp; there instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chitty</hi>, the new Rector. The church was filled with people from Hanwood, the parish he had left, &amp; the new parish in which he was starting. The whole company were entertained at tea afterwards. <hi rend="doubleunderline">General Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="5210"></persName> &amp; his wife (n&#x00E9;e Wilkinson) were there. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip James</hi> acted as Registrar for his father<persName xml:id="4292"></persName>. After taking him &amp; young Chitty (who was returning to Oxford) in [to] Shrewsbury, I motored to Cound Hall, <hi rend="bold underline">where I had accepted the hospitality of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="5211"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Corquodale</hi>. The house bears the date 1704, and is an excellent example of the Queen Anne style. We walked for an hour in the gardens, which are extensive &amp; well&#8211;kept. On every hand there are tokens of opulence. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Corquodale, I gathered from his conversation, is a large paper manufacturer, &amp; bought Cound Hall some years ago. <hi rend="bold underline">He &amp; Fielden<persName xml:id="4560"></persName> (who in like manner bought Condover) are locally known, he told me, as the two fools of Shropshire</hi>, land&#8211;purchase being accounted in the present state of the world the height of folly! The Vicar of Cound, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lombard</hi><persName xml:id="5103"></persName> &amp; his wife, came to dinner, &amp; some neighbours, Colonel <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ramsden</hi> (?) &amp; his wife. The son &amp; heir arrived on a motor&#8211;bicycle from Liverpool. His conversation was, perhaps, more dogmatic than became his years, for he is not yet 23 years old, if I understood his father rightly.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>