<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi> [sic] <hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>A chilly day. Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith, Gabrielsson<persName xml:id="1314" display="no"></persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> motored to Wigmore in the morning, and I worked at the Lectures. After lunch our guests saw the Cathedral. After tea, the Smiths departed, and Baddeley<persName xml:id="206"></persName> arrived. I took him &amp; the Swede for a walk. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Baddeley, and I dined with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Percy Clive<persName xml:id="5223"></persName>. There was a small dance afterwards, during which Colonel Jeffreys &amp; I had a long &amp; interesting talk about the threatened coal strike. He appeared to speak with considerable knowledge of the situation, of which he evidently takes a very serious view. The worst difficulty just now is the circumstances that most of the troops are in Ireland, and of the 29 battalions left in England, a substantial proportion are Irish, who cannot be relied upon. He spoke with unusual decision of the essential superiority of English over all other troops: &amp; the real inferiority of the Irish. We returned home about midnight.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Gabrielsson<persName xml:id="1314" display="no"></persName> tells me that few of the students at Upsala will understand any English, so that they will depend altogether on the interpreter</hi><hi rend="italic">! It appears that they are mainly taught German in the schools as a second language. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In Sweden the use of the word "Mass" has survived the Reformation</hi><hi rend="italic">, but apparently forfeited most of its original meaning. It has no necessary connection with the Holy Communion, but describes the ordinary service on Sunday mornings which, more often than not, does not include a Celebration of Holy Communion. Among the country people any religious service, e.g. a cottage&#8211;lecture, would be described as "the Mass". It is clear enough that the medieval tradition of doctrine and worship was quite effectually destroyed in Sweden. [But cf. p. 135.]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>