<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918 [sic] ^1920^.</hi></p>
         <p>How hard it is to realize the greater factors of life! The trivial arrangements for my Swedish tour loom far more largely in my view, occupy a far larger part of my thought, and interest me <hi rend="doubleunderline">far more than the tremendous news of yesterday</hi>. And is the same with respect to the things of the spirit. The bothering questions of getting into Durham, the squalid anxieties as to ways &amp; means, even the details of ceremonial crowd out the really solemn facts of immense new responsibilities, of the terrific chasm between my personal inadequacy and the position to which I have been called, of the continuing paradox of my inner life. These things, on any reasonable valuation of intrinsic important, ought to absorb me, not those other trifles. "<hi rend="underline">Seek ye first His Kingdom &amp; His righteousness, &amp; all these things shall be added unto you</hi>." If one could really take that measurement of one's life, and live in the power of that assurance, how different would one be!</p>
         <p>I went to S. Nicholas, and celebrated the Holy Communion. Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> had evidently issued a whip to the recently confirmed communicants, for there was a considerable muster. Everything was very devout and moving. The Epistle ‒ 1. Cor: xv. 1ff ‒ was curiously accordant with my mood — at once self&#8211;defending &amp; self&#8211;accused. "<hi rend="underline">For I am the least of the Apostles, that am not meet to be called an Apostle, because I persecuted the Church of God. But by the Grace of God I am what I am: &amp; His grace which was bestowed upon me was not in vain: but I laboured more abundantly than they all; yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me</hi>." How far can I rightly make such language my own?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>After breakfast D. Patterson with his two boys Lloyd &amp; Adrian came to see me. I gave him a signed photograph. Then I wrote some purely personal letters. 1) to my brother Aubrey<persName xml:id="1095"></persName>, 2) to Olive Pollok&#8211;Morris<persName xml:id="1696"></persName>, 3) to Gilbert Simpson<persName xml:id="554"></persName>, 4) to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>.<note xml:id="514" n="1"></note></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I read "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Problem of Reunion</hi><hi rend="italic">" by Leslie J. Walker S.J., M.A. late senior chaplain to the 19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> division, B.E.F, sometime Professor of Philosophy at Stonyhurst College. The author, as a Papist, conceives of ultimate reunion as an acceptance of the Papal claim, but, as serviceable to that end, he urges the union of English&#8211;speaking Christianity. His description of the Anglican position is acute, &amp; mainly sound. The truth is that that position can only be maintained in the teeth of history &amp; the Anglican standards. The puzzling thing is that it is thus maintained, &amp; by an increasing number of Anglicans.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>