<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Bartholomew ‒ what terrific &amp; dismaying associations have gathered about this Apostle's name! The massacre of the Huguenots, and the eviction of the Nonconformists ‒ the one the most outstanding &amp; most illuminating fact of ecclesiastical history in France in the XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century: and the other the most characteristic fact of English Church History in the XVII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> ‒ both decorate with sinister significance the Festival of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Bartholomew. The difference between the two acts ‒ the spontaneous ferocity of the one, and the celebrated legality of the other ‒ disclose the difference of the creative age of the Reformation from the controversial, &amp; reflect the distinction of the French and the English temperaments. The Revocation of the Edict of Nantes (1685) is a closer parallel both in time, circumstance, and effect to the Act of Uniformity (1662). <hi rend="bold underline">There is a coldness &amp; a deliberateness about the intolerance of the 17th century which are more offensive than the brisk violence of the 16th. In the latter the respectable plea of conviction suggests itself, but in the former there is obviously nothing more than a cynical policy. </hi>The Churchmen had degenerated into politicians. An episcopal consecration in the Church of England on S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Bartholomew's Day must need wake these memories in a considering mind, especially in the mind of an English bishop designing himself to take part in the consecration. How far has the old spirit of intolerance disappeared form the Episcopate of England? We are powerless now, save for the putative oppression of latitudinarian curates, but had we power again, should we not use it, &amp; in the old way?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p>The consecration in the Cathedral at 10.30 a.m. was a very noble function. There were, I think, about 15 consecrating bishops besides the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, all from the Province except the Bishop in [sic] Jerusalem<persName xml:id="5251"></persName>. I was Gospeller, and the Bishop of Liverpool<persName xml:id="477"></persName> Epistler: <hi rend="bold underline">and I joined with the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> in presenting Strong<persName xml:id="120"></persName> for consecration as Bishop of Ripon</hi>. Williams<persName xml:id="4879"></persName> was presented by the Bishops of Liverpool and Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, who performed the same office for Kempson<persName xml:id="3184"></persName> as Suffragan of Warrington. The sermon was preached by Savage<persName xml:id="1815"></persName>, the Dean of Lichfield. It was a disappointing performance: exalting the development of diocesan machinery during the last half century, and making the usual conventional appeals to save the Bishops from secular business. I was surprised that there were some of the usual personal tributes to the men about to be consecrated. The preacher did, indeed, dilate on the personal sacrifices involved in their leaving Oxford, but that manner of speaking is unimpressive, esp. when it is perfectly well known that at least <hi rend="underline">one</hi> of the two academics is greatly pleased at his preferment, as he is perfectly entitled to be: and that when <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi> had deliberately decided against living out his life in Oxford. I thought the sermon was the wasting of a rare opportunity. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">[</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dolphin</hi><persName xml:id="2798"></persName> came to see me after lunch. He had not much to tell me: but he re&#8211;assured me on the subject of the Lodge, which, he says, contains about 12 rooms. He says that Ellis, the existing tenant, has declared his willingness to take over the whole of the garden, &amp; suggests that the rent be decided by a valuer. There may be something in this. But I incline to ask the Commissioner to take the Gardens.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi> [sic]<hi rend="bold"> [94]</hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Liverpool told me that the spiritualist parson, Vale Owen<persName xml:id="5177"></persName>, is an incumbent in his diocese: that he is a High Churchman &amp; believes that he is Divinely commissioned to "spiritualize" the Church of England: that he refuses to cease from his "mission", but has undertaken not to bring his spiritualist opinions into his sermons or into his confirmation instructions. He has been in the past a journalist, and his well&#8211;marked style is quite obvious in his communications. "How", inquired the Bishop shrewdly, "has your mother, from whom you allege these messages to come, acquired so perfectly your manner of expressing yourself?" To this question he could make no answer, but was disposed to be indignant! The Bishop thought that the influence which has led him into these follies is that of his wife.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><persName xml:id="130"></persName> took me for a stroll to the race&#8211;course, where we were so fortunate to witness a race. Motion and strife are stirring spectacles. He says that the business of the House of Lords is managed by the small body of regular attendants, mostly resident in London, mainly in the interest of their own convenience. It is almost impossible for a bishop residing at a distance to take any continuous part in the debates, &amp;, if he speak but rarely, he is apt to be oratorical, and thus disgust the House, which has grown discontented with rhetoric. I doubt if it will be possible for me to make any figure in the House, yet I shall resign with some regret the intention of making the diocese of Durham audible in the Senate. The cost of travelling &amp; hotels may well settle the matter on the squalid ground of expense.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi> [sic]<hi rend="bold"> [95]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">[</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> told a curious story about the large picture of George III in his regalia, accompanied by two persons in the back&#8211;ground, of whom one was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baron Harcourt</hi>, who carried the cap of maintenance at the King's coronation. "Lulu" Harcourt<persName xml:id="1590"></persName> wrote to request that the picture might be given to him to be added to the collection of family portraits at Nuneham, offering to send in exchange a picture of George III. The Archbishop properly declined the proposal, and, in order to disprove the suggestion that the picture (so obviously painted for family reasons) c<hi rend="superscript underline">ld</hi> not have been intended to be one of the Bishopthorpe heirlooms, quoted the letter of the artist, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Benjamin West</hi>, which happens to be preserved at the palace. In this letter the picture is described as "a deposit" for Bishopthorpe. This, however, failed to satisfy "Lulu". The intention, with wh. the picture had been purchased, was, however, made quite clear by the Archbishop's discovery (in a collection of autographs of English Archbishops &amp; Bishops, which he had seen in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pierrepont Morgan's</hi> house, where he had stayed during his visit to America) of Archbishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Harcourt's</hi> letter written in reply to the above&#8211;mentioned letter of Sir B. West. In this letter the Archbishop expressed the hope that the picture would be valued &amp; enjoyed by his successors. <hi rend="bold underline">A photograph of this letter is now in Bishopthorpe. This is certainly rather a curious coincidence; and justly is thought, by the present Archbishop, to add a new interest to a picture which, though a fair enough example of the artist's style &amp; manner, is not otherwise very remarkable</hi>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>