<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> re&#8211;assembled as a whole, to begin the consideration of the Reports of the various committees. We began with that on industrial relations. The Report, &amp; resolutions were, of course, strongly "Labourist", &amp; the latter were crudely expressed. "Fish" Cecil<persName xml:id="31"></persName> moved the rejection of the most objectionable resolution, &amp; was seconded by the Bp. of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>: <hi rend="bold underline">I followed on the same side, but my speech was ineffective</hi>. On the motion of the Abp. of York<persName xml:id="130"></persName>, the resolution was drastically amended, &amp; so passed. Another Resolution referred in too flatterous terms to American Prohibition, &amp; I moved the omission of the reference. In the course of my speech (which was dreadfully inadequate to the occasion) I twitted the American Bishops on their personal consumption of wine at the Lord Mayor's Banquet. This made the assembly laugh heartily, but the transatlanticks didn't like it. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">[I dined at 9 Vale Avenue. The Ulsterman, MacNeil came to dinner with his wife</hi>. It certainly startled me to hear him speak of the Government's accepting the Sinn Fein Republic, as if it were an inevitable &amp; possible procedure. The Irish Unionists are themselves yielding to the pressure of facts, e.g. Lord Iveagh<persName xml:id="5250"></persName> has accepted "protection" for his property from the Sinn Fein authorities. They argue that, since the British Government is plainly unable to fulfil the first duty of giving protection to the citizens, there is no other course open to them save to make the best terms for themselves with the actually governing power.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>