<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>This is <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">S&#x00F6;derblom's</hi><persName xml:id="2203"></persName> birthday, and it is celebrated with much circumstance. <hi rend="underline">Nine</hi> of her ten children have rallied to the parental hearth: gifts &amp; congratulations pour in from every side, and sentiment is in flood&#8211;tide. We were convemiently taken off for lunch at a Deaconesses' Training Institution, over which we were shown. It appeared to be a very well&#8211;organized foundation. The probationers were set to sing in the chapel, &amp; the effect was very devotional. I was reminded of the singing of the <hi rend="underline">Trinita</hi> nuns in Rome, which impressed me as much in 1886. <hi rend="bold underline">The atmosphere of these Lutheran churches is medieval. There has been a continuity of religious life, which in the Calvinistically reformed countries has been lost</hi>. England in this respect must be reckoned Calvinistic. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gabrielsson</hi><persName xml:id="1314" display="no"></persName> was at lunch, &amp; I had some talk with him. He says that <hi rend="bold underline">the present Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> is in some quarters suspected of inclining to Catholicism because of his ecclesiastical flirtation with England, and that the comparative simplicity of the appearance of the English bishops at last Sunday's consecration will be useful as correcting this suspicion!</hi> This may be commended to the "<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>"! Brilioth's<persName xml:id="5198"></persName> baby, a girl, is to be baptized this afternoon. It is the first grand&#8211;child, and this is the anniversary of its parents' marriage. Everybody is bubbling over with domestic sentiment. In due course the ceremony took place in the old church hardly the Palace. It was in its way a pretty function enough. The Archbishop vested in a long black robe officiated, the baby squalled becomingly, &amp; the small boy played the harmonium very admirably. Afterwards we <hi rend="bold">[136]</hi> all went to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brilioth's</hi> flat, &amp; drank the newly baptized infant's health in sherry. I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brilioth</hi>, who was at the recent conferences in Geneva.<note xml:id="515" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">He says that the bishops from the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> came to the "Faith &amp; Order" Conference, &amp; did not make a very good impression. </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Gore</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> had been present, &amp; was naturally the most interesting figure there. The Bishop of Bombay<persName xml:id="2498"></persName> had presided, &amp; much had been said of the Lamberth Appeal for Unity. But no progress had been made, &amp; </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Brilioth</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> himself came away with the conviction that the "Appeal" would be barren of results.</hi></p>
         <p>We dined at 6.30 p.m. The meal had a festive character. <hi rend="underline">Eight</hi> of the 10 children were present, &amp; sate on each side of their mother. The eldest of them made a speech in proposing her health, &amp; then one of the younger boys read out a long series of telegrams of congratulation, which had been received. A number of presents were displayed. The outer room reminded me of an English wedding reception when the presents are exhibited. On the whole, this was a curious disclosure of the intensely domestic life of the religious Swedes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I gave the Archbishop a cheque for &#x00A3;10. as a contribution toward his fund for the Austrian children.I think he was pleased</hi>. Mr &AUML;ckstr&#x00F6;m (?) who was God&#8211;father to the infant at the Baptism offers to take us to Stockholm tomorrow with our baggage in his motor boat; and we have accepted his invitation if the weather be fair. This will necessitate our starting about 10.45 a.m; &amp; will give me no time to finish my sermon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>