<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>After writing some letters in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I walked to Lambeth. <hi rend="bold underline">The amended resolution, being found unacceptable to the Pope of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName>, it was again postponed: and </hi>we settled down to the missionary problems Report. This was finished without much trouble by lunch&#8211;time: and then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge</hi><persName xml:id="602"></persName> introduced the Report on Spiritualism, Christian Science, &amp; Theosophy. He played his part excellently, &amp; made a great impression on the Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. <hi rend="bold underline">I offered a strenuous opposition to a Resolution urging the recognition &amp; regulation of Healing in the Church. There was a brisk discussion, &amp; in the end an amendment moved by the Bishop of Massachusetts</hi> (Lawrence<persName xml:id="931"></persName>) was passed <hi rend="bold">[</hi>by 64 to 60<hi rend="bold">]</hi> cutting out most part of the Resolution. The Bishop of Chester (Luke Paget<persName xml:id="2409"></persName>) made an excellent speech. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>The Bishop of St Alban's (Furse<persName xml:id="1602"></persName>) again spoke very fanatically.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>In the luncheon interval a photograph of the bishops who had worked in the Diocese of Durham was taken. I think the number was 25, including the following English diocesans ‒ Durham, Rochester<persName xml:id="929"></persName>, Lichfield<persName xml:id="3831"></persName>, Peterborough<persName xml:id="3933"></persName>, &amp; Wakefield<persName xml:id="2980"></persName>.</p>
         <p>I bought for &#x00A3;1. the chair on which I have sate during the Conference, &amp; the bag thereunto annexed. I dined in the Club, at the same table with McArthur<persName xml:id="1123"></persName>, the Bishop of Southampton. <hi rend="bold underline">He was at the Conference of 1908, and thinks that the level of intelligence in the bishops is higher in the present conference than it was then. The speaking, also, is in his judgment superior. I find it difficult to accept this view, for neither intelligence nor oratory has been </hi><hi rend="bold underline">ꓥ</hi><hi rend="bold underline">me judice</hi><hi rend="bold underline">ꓥ</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> impressive in this assembly</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>