<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[134]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>We went to Stockholm, &amp; there bade farewell to the Greek metropolitan who was setting out on his return journey to Constantinople. Then we went to the church of S. Clara in which I am to preach on Sunday next. <hi rend="bold underline">One of the clergy of the church has undertaken to translate my sermon as I deliver it</hi>. He appears, however, to be almost totally ignorant of the English Language! In the "church house" adjoining this church, the incumbent lives, there is a parish room, and the archbishop has his office. The parish of S. Clara is reckon to be unusually small, yet its population exceeds 12.000 souls. Here we left the archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> to do his business, and proceeded ourselves to the Grand Hotel, and lunched. </p>
         <p>Then we went to the British Legation, and recover our pass&#8211;ports, duly <hi rend="underline">visaed</hi> for Germany. After this, we went to the Skansen, where we were specially interested in the performances of the beaver, and in the majestic aspect of the great owls. We went back to the Grand Hotel for tea, stopping on the way to purchase a box of sweet meats as a Birthday offering to our hostess, and there continued until it was time to return to S. Clara for the lecture. There was a fair gathering, mostly British, in the hall of the Swedish Medical Society, where I lectured on "The Lambeth Conference"<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName>. It was an extemporaneous address eked out by quitations from the official Report. I was assured that everybody was interested. Then we had supper with the parson of S. Clara, &amp; went back to Upsala by a slow train, which brought us to our destination after midnight.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>