<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A woefully wet day, and very cold. Baddely<persName xml:id="206"></persName> went off by the early train, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; Gabrielsson<persName xml:id="1314" display="no"></persName> left after breakfast</hi>. Then I wrote letters, and got away by the 11.27 a.m. to York, where I arrived at 6 p.m. after changing four times <hi rend="bold">[</hi>viz. Stockport, Stalybridge, Huddersfield, Leeds.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> The motor met me &amp; other bishops, &amp; drove us out to Bishopthorpe. Here were the bishops who will take part in tomorrow's service, and the 3 episcopal candidates ‒ Strong<persName xml:id="120"></persName>, Williams<persName xml:id="4879"></persName>, and Kempson<persName xml:id="3184"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">I noticed that <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> has banished wine from his table. Nothing but cold water was provided at dinner. It looks likely that against my will, by the sheer necessity of the case, I shall be driven to this course. [That economy will be distasteful &amp; humiliating, but it will be easier to make than to travel third class, which, I fear will also be forced on me. When I watched the squalid over&#8211;crowding of the 3rd class carriages today, I felt that to be compelled to travel thus would be a very repulsive thing. </hi>Yet the cost of the tickets (&#x00A3;4.8.6. for my return ticket to &amp; from York) is really becoming prohibitive.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> The newspapers are full of the impending strike of the miners. If that strike takes place, and is persisted in for a few weeks, the loss to the country will be immense. The existing taxation will be quite insufficient to meet the national expenditure: and fresh taxes will have to be imposed. It is fairly certain that the burden on episcopal incomes will be again increased. <hi rend="bold underline">In these circumstances is it wise for me even to attempt to live at Auckland Castle? </hi>Yet, how can I avoid doing so?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>