<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">The conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> exhibited some signs of reaction from the tension of yesterday. No one could get up much enthusiasm for the Eastern churches, whether orthodox or heretical, and the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Gloucester</hi><persName xml:id="3536"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who had charge of the resolutions, would have extinguished the fiercest zeal! In the afternoon there was a flicker of excitement over the Swedish church, but it didn't prevent the adoption of the resolutions. The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> is evidently well&#8211;pleased at the ease with which the business was got through yesterday. He affects to think that the resolutions we adopted were really valuable &amp; significant. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> thanked me warmly for the self&#8211;restraint which kept me silent. If I had opposed, the resolutions would have failed! It appears that my silence is more welcome than my speech! I raised a laugh be explaining that I didn't intend consulting my metropolitan with respect to carrying out my promise to assist in the consecration of Swedish bishops</hi><hi rend="italic">. Afterwards, the Archbishop came to me in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; I took occasion to ask him whether he designed commissioning another bishop to join me at Upsala on Sept: 19</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">. He disclaimed the intention. He professes to be greatly impressed by the Bishop of Zanzibar's<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> speeches, &amp; general behaviour, which contrast rather amazingly with his letters at the time of the Kikuyu incident. I told him not to be too confident. Zanzibar was capable of any sudden &amp; surprising turn.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>