<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">This is the last Sunday of our residence in Hereford</hi>. We went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; received the Holy Communion together. Both of us felt a certain melancholy as we reflected that we had reached the end of a chapter of our lives which had begun in clouds, and ended (so far as the external appearance of things goes) in sunshine. I was consecrated in Westminster Abbey on February 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1918, and I vacated the see of Hereford at my confirmation as Bishop of Durham in York Minster on July 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920. It is scarcely 2⅟<hi rend="subscript">2 </hi>years, a brief episcopate, too brief to effect anything worth naming, and yet not wholly insignificant. Certainly when I came here I thought that I was entering on the final phase of my career, for, though there were many persons in Durham who spoke of my returning thither as Bishop, I did not myself think that there was the smallest likelihood of their expectation being fulfilled. It seemed quite incredible that I should be regarded as safe or suitable for translation in view of the outcry raised against me at my consecration. I acted on the supposition that I should live out my life in Hereford. With that view I spent money in stocking the garden with fruit trees, &amp; in making the Palace habitable by putting the drains to rights, &amp; installing the electric light (i.e. in extending the installation). Had I known that my stay here would have been so brief, I might have saved my money. As it is, my successor<persName xml:id="4851"></persName> will reap the benefit.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, &amp; to Symonds of Montreal. After lunch I walked my guests to the top of Dynedor Hill, a hot but pleasant expedition. The view was obscured by the mist, but even so was worth going to see. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dillon came to tea. I wrote to the Hotel Rydberg to secure rooms from Sept. 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> to 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>: and to the Chaplain at Stockholm suggesting that I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">ld</hi> confirm certain young women on the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>We all attended Evensong in the Cathedral, when Streeter<persName xml:id="3230"></persName> preached the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> of his lectures on the Creed. His subject was the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> article: ‒ "I believe in His only Son our Lord". He quoted the Christian <hi rend="underline">Sadhu</hi> who has made so great an impression in England recently, &amp; mentioned that he was engaged on a small book about the <hi rend="underline">Sadhu's</hi> work. <hi rend="bold underline">Like all Streeter's sermons it was too sketchy, suggesting haste and carelessness; but he said some striking things, &amp; held the attention of his congregation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dillon came to supper. She was at Newnham, &amp; had common ground with Elizabeth<persName xml:id="3077" display="no"></persName>.<hi rend="bold">] </hi>Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> brought the synopsis which he had prepared of the Swedish Lectures, &amp; stayed to supper. </p>
         <p>So ends my last Sunday in Hereford, a brilliant day, but with sad suggestions. When shall we have again a settled home? The problem of Auckland Castle doesn't grow easier of solution as time passes. It seems evident that one <hi rend="underline">must</hi> go into the great house, and highly probable that one will not be able to stay there! The immediate question is how and when we can get into the place.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>