<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received a second type&#8211;written communication from the Prime Minister's Secretary, informing me that the P.M.<persName xml:id="234"></persName> "would like to announce the 3 appointments (Carlisle, Ripon, &amp; Durham) simultaneously". This assurance that my acceptance had been duly received led me to venture writing to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; telling her <hi rend="underline">sub sigillo</hi> [under seal] what had happened. In the course of the day I informed the Dean<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> &amp; Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> under pledge of secrecy. It seemed difficult to go along without letting them into the secret. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Later I wrote to the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, enclosing a copy of my letter to the Prime Minister</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi>After lunch we motored to Morton Court, where M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hill gave a drawing&#8211;room meeting in the interest of the Church Army. I presided, &amp; made a short speech. Then I went back to the Palace, &amp; wrote the letters with Wynne&#8211;Willson. For the rest, I worked at a sermon for Cambridge on Sunday. It is woeful work when one's mind is pre&#8211;occupied with quite other matters.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Lord Halifax's<persName xml:id="5132"></persName> answer to the eminent persons who claimed important appointments from William III's Government on the ground that they had been prominent supporters of the Revolution is worth remembering:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I remember to have read in history that Rome was saved by geese: but I do not remember that the geese were made consuls</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It may well be the case that I shall have occasion to make use of that caustic and searching aphorism when, as Bishop of Durham, I administer my patronage.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>