<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I left Hereford at 9.55 a.m., &amp; arrived in Cambridge at 6 p.m.</hi> travelling from Liverpool Street very stupidly by a slow train, &amp; so missing Burkitt<persName xml:id="574"></persName> &amp; the car, who were naturally meeting the fast train which arrived at 6.8 p.m. There was a pleasant dinner&#8211;party, &amp; a very good dinner. I was particularly glad to meet Professors Sorley<persName xml:id="4852"></persName> &amp; Bethune&#8211;Baker<persName xml:id="4131"></persName>. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sorley is a sister of George Adam Smith<persName xml:id="244"></persName>.</p>
         <p>The idea occurred to me that I might seize the opportunity of being in Cambridge to lay the foundation of a connection with the University in the matter of getting suitable Ordination candidates. <hi rend="bold underline">So I privately told Burkitt<persName xml:id="574"></persName> &amp; Bethune&#8211;Baker that I had accepted Durham, &amp; that I wanted their help in recruiting</hi>.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sorley told me that W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> had sent her the following couplet:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>The Mitre lights after <hi rend="underline">suspension</hi></p>
         <p>Upon the head of Herbert Henson.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The facts are inaccurately stated for "inhibition" is not so severe a punishment as "suspension", &amp; I was only "inhibited"! <hi rend="italic">It is difficult to imagine a more complete indication of Anglican confusion than the fact that a clergyman "inhibited" in 1909, and disregarding the sentence, is himself raised to the Episcopate in 1918, and in spite of a mighty clamour of protest is preferred to one of the greatest positions on the Hierarchy in 1920! There is no doubt that the C. of E. is so incoherent &amp; divided, as really neither to think nor to act as one body.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>