<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>We arrived at Gothenburg in good time, &amp; were met on the steamer by the British Consul, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Brown, and by the British chaplain who is also Vice&#8211;consul, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">Finding it quite impossible to obtain rooms in any hotel, we decided to go on to Stockholm by</hi> the night train. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin constituted himself our guide, &amp;, having borrowed a car from a friend, drove us to see the magnificent park. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>I noticed a great green wood&#8211;pecker as we ascended the hill to the view&#8211;point. Then we went to the sea&#8211;side, &amp; gained a fine view of the Gotha river. After coffee<hi rend="bold">]</hi> we returned to the city &amp; called on M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Liethandler</hi>, the owner of the car which had been placed at our disposal. He forthwith asked us to dinner. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>After lunch in the hotel, we vainly essayed to see the local museum, which closed at 3 p.m. just too late for us.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> At 6 p.m. we dined with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> L. very pleasantly. His wife &amp; her sister were English, he himself a Swede. He is a merchant and a member of Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>. I had much conversation with him on political matters. <hi rend="bold underline">He thought that there was no real danger of Bolshevism taking root in Sweden, &amp; that the Socialist government was perforce returning from its more extravagant positions</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Branting,</hi> the Prime Minister, was personally very hostile to Bolshevism. He held that the Church was not really unpopular, though disestablishment &amp; disendowment were included in the Socialist programme. <hi rend="bold underline">Baldwin gives an ill&#8211;account of the bigotry of the Swedish clergy, who belong mainly to the Schartau<persName xml:id="5227"></persName> faction, which appears to be a variety of Evangelical</hi>. We went to the station in good time, and were accompanied by our two friends, whose assiduous attentions had not failed throughout a long day.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>