<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>This was the day of the experts. In succession there came before the Reunion Committee, Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName>, Armitage Robinson<persName xml:id="44"></persName>, &amp; Cuthbert Turner<persName xml:id="2950"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">Ryle alone was in any sense friendly to going forward in the attempt to unite with the Presbyterians</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The others were extremely uncompromising in their hostility. Robinson excelled himself in bigotry, delivered with an assumption of omniscience which was almost ludicrous. There was some questioning of these pundits during the afternoon, but nothing close or severe enough to match their performance. Several bishops commented on the contrast between the sermon which Robinson preached in the Abbey on 'Unity' before the Lambeth Conference<orgName xml:id="114"></orgName> of 1908, &amp; the evidence he gave today. I observed that it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have been but decent if he had donned a white sheet for the occasion. Individuals are beginning to disclose their quality. <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Armagh<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> is the most effective person on my side. The Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, the least</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Consistent &amp; rather bitter opposition comes from the Scottish bishops. The Americans are mainly hostile. Rheinlander<persName xml:id="3067"></persName> (Pennsylvania), Brent<persName xml:id="2253"></persName> (Western New York), Gailor<persName xml:id="5216"></persName> (Tennessee), &amp; the Bishop of Southern Ohio<persName xml:id="5219"></persName> are the leaders. The Bishops have not yet emerged from their mutual courtesies, but the tension is plainly increasing. The Bishops of Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName>, Chichester<persName xml:id="301"></persName>, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's<persName xml:id="1602"></persName>, &amp; Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> are very restive: &amp; the Talbots, p&#x00E8;re<persName xml:id="105"></persName> et fils<persName xml:id="2023"></persName>, play up to their more plain&#8211;spoken brethren!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p>There seems some likelihood that the "Catholick" bishops will insist on raising Confirmation to the rank of an essential condition of Reunion. Our experts (except Ryle) were very insistent on it, &amp; as they base it on scripture our Evangelicals are reduced to silence! <hi rend="italic">I had a long talk with Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> after dinner. He expresses himself very liberally, &amp;, though he declares his strong affection for Gore, he does not scruple to acknowledge that he dissents from his views.</hi> <hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">I was pleased to learn that he disapproved of the proposal to transfer to the new parochial councils the rights of the vestry.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>