<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dolphin</hi><persName xml:id="2798"></persName> enclosing a cheque for &#x00A3;25. Then I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; there spent the morning. <hi rend="bold underline">Watkins<persName xml:id="590"></persName> again made his appearance and again was alarmingly affectionate</hi>! I turned up the account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Morton</hi><persName xml:id="4636"></persName> in the Dictionary of National Biography with a view to considering how far I could choose him for my model. He too lived in a revolutionary age: he was an earnest advocate of Protestant reunion, and an opponent of Laudian extravagances. He was an excellent administrator &amp; had a certain taste for magnificence. 'He is described as small of stature, upright in person &amp; sprightly in motion, preserving the vigour of youth in extreme old age'. His position as a churchman was that of Usher<persName xml:id="2752"></persName> &amp; Bedell<persName xml:id="5187"></persName>. Among his friends was numbered Richard Hooker<persName xml:id="969"></persName>. His long life (1564 to 1659) covered a critical epoque of English History. Elizabeth had reigned for 6 years when he was born, and he died in the year before the Restoration.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I left Victoria at 2.35 p.m., and arrived at Birchington</hi> at 5.24 p.m., <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName> was on the platform to meet me. I found <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName></hi> cheerful and well, though frail and visibly aging. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi>. </p>
         <p>It is reported in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> that "the only preserved original of the Bull of 1520 against Luther has been discovered in the Wurtenbury State Archives". This is an interesting discovery, &amp; must provoke much thought in German minds. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>