<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The sermon for the University of Glasgow is even more baffling. To choose a subject is difficult enough: to compose a sermon is almost impracticable. The sinister turn taken by the Labour dispute adds to my difficulties: for everybody's mind will be filled with the Strike. Several letters have reached me from Scotland and America enquiring whether I can indeed be the author of the opinions on Prohibition which the Brewers have published far &amp; wide. So far as I can see the Brewers have done no violence to the letters of mine which they quote. No doubt <hi rend="underline">their</hi> emphasis is not the same as mine; and their <hi rend="underline">motive</hi> must needs be very different: but I am agreed with them as to the intrinsic unsoundness of the principle &amp; policy of Prohibition. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Serres</hi><persName xml:id="4066"></persName> called to take me for a walk. Before starting I made use of his services as a witness to my signature on a number of documents sent on to me by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Our walk was curtailed by the rain which began to fall steadily as the afternoon drew towards evening.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" reports that my successor<persName xml:id="4851"></persName> was enthroned yesterday as Bishop of Hereford. I begin to feel impatient at the long delay in my own enthronement. We are drifting into the Castle, and so to speak, putting our necks into the noose. But &#x3B1;) the great House is in our hands: &#x3B2;) our furniture must go somewhere &#x3B3;) we have nowhere else to live &#x3B4;) the abandonment of the old historic home ought not to be decided upon except on plain grounds of necessity.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>