<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The distractions of the hour take my mind off the subject which ought now to be thrusting out every other &#8211; this great task in Durham to which I must put my hand. What shall be the pronouncement which I must make at the Enthronement on the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> October? The coincidence of that function &amp; an acute phase of industrial unrest will recall to everybody's mind the coal&#8211;strike of the early nineties, &amp; Bishop Westcott's<persName xml:id="1047"></persName> memorable action. But the mere reference might be interpreted as a suggestion that I might myself play a similar r&#x00F4;le in another &amp; more formidable strike, &amp; that could not fail to provoke a kind of resentment. Yet it will hardly be possible for me to avoid referring to the economic situation, &amp; to my attitude as bishop towards it. But what can I say that is honest, judicious and worth saying? I certainly cannot usefully or sincerely echo the plattitudes, half&#8211;truths, &amp; sentimental fallacies of "Christian Socialism": yet to speak with simple directness what I actually think might well give a measure of offence which is not wise to give at the start of my episcopate. Then there is the subject of Reunion, which can hardly be avoided since the Lamberth Conference has given it such prominence, and I shall have delayed my enthronement in order to visit Sweden in its interest. I fear that the only conception of Reunion which the Durham clergy have is just the washy mutual embracement which I hold in contempt. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>The type of sectary in my diocese is not the best: it would be wholly impossible to accept most of the ministers as candidates for Ordination even if they were willing to present themselves.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> We cannot talk beyond the limit of our willingness to act.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi></p>
         <p>Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName> at his enthronement spoke mainly of Butler<persName xml:id="1856"></persName>. This was perhaps inevitable as both were celibates &amp; both bore the same Christian name. Which of my predecessors could I most fitly select for special mention? There is the princely Tunstall, who linked the old order with the new at the Reformation: Morton<persName xml:id="4636"></persName>, on whom fell the stroke of the Great Rebellion: Cosin<persName xml:id="2820"></persName>, the restorer of Zion: Van Mildert<persName xml:id="4869"></persName>, the founder of the University: Lightfoot, the scholar: Westcott<persName xml:id="1047"></persName>, the prophet. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Something must be said about Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>, the "Saint", though I cannot pretend to number myself among his disciples or his admirers.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>We went to the English church at 11 a.m. The service consisted of Litany &amp; Holy Communion. I was the celebrant. Afterwards we motored to the Hotel Adlon, &amp; were there entertained at lunch by General Bingham<persName xml:id="5230"></persName>. Lord Kilmarnock<persName xml:id="717"></persName> was also of the party. We talked much but I recall but little of the conversation, save that our host described the scene, when the German troops had to salute the French flag at the Embassy in atonement for the removal of the flag by some unknown patriot. The salute was witnessed by a great crowd which looked heartily all the while; &amp; the saluting troops, as soon as their unpalatable task was ended, broke into "<hi rend="underline">Deutschland &#x00FC;ber alles</hi>". General B. commented on the folly of the French in heaping humiliations on their fallen enemy, thereby not so much cowing the said enemy as earning his deeper &amp; more enduring hatred. Our hosts motored us to Sans Souci and Potsdam. We were interested to see the rooms in which two of the archest villains of history &#8211; Frederick the Great &amp; Voltaire &#8211; once plotted and played the fool.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Thelwall</hi><persName xml:id="4861"></persName> before going to bed. He says that the accusations against the German troops were, so far as his knowledge went, baseless. In particular, the two allegations which were so confidently made in England, viz: that the Germans used the corpses of the soldiers to make glycerine, &amp; that they organized a system of increasing the population by using soldiers, were quite false. The first (as he vainly pointed out to the authorities at the the time) was the result of a (possibly honest) misunderstanding of the German language; the last was probably invented as a jest. Both were shamelessly used for 'propagandist' purposes. <hi rend="underline">He was convinced that the German army was in point of humanity &amp;c fully equal to every other, except possibly the English, who were a more kindly people</hi>. If any difference seemed evident, it arose from the circumstance that during the war, the Germans were generally in the position of victoriously advancing troops, &amp; that in that position all troops were in a state of excitement which made extravagances of every kind possible. The worst damage to French towns &amp; villages was inflicted, not by the Germans or by English, <hi rend="underline">but by French troops</hi>. Nothing could exceed the filthiness of the French. I inquired about the behaviour of our troops in Cologne, &amp; was told that it had been bad for a brief period after demobilisation began, &amp; that <hi rend="underline">the root of the mischief was the worthlessness of the 'improvised' officers.</hi> As these had been removed, &amp; replaced by regulars, order had been reestablished. Intermarriages between our soldiers, and our officers &amp; German women were not as infrequent as might be supposed. <hi rend="underline">There are not many marriages between French &amp; English, but a good deal of illicit intercourse</hi>.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi></p>
         <p>The illustrated Sunday paper contains a photograph of the football teams, English &amp; German, who played against one another a few days ago. This was the first occasion on which the two nations had played a football match, &amp; the Germans had won. This is a salutory fact, and gives cause for hoping that a kinder feeling is beginning to grow up.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">[</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Warburton</hi> sent me a cutting from a recent issue of the "Sunday Times" headed "The truth about Poland". It gave the blackest account of the Poles. Their cowardice, ingratitude, incompetence, and insane vanity are described as almost passing belief. Only the amazing badness of the Bolshevist troops, &amp; the direction of the French officers, can explain their recent successes. It is obvious, however, &#8211; if there be any substantial truth in the writer's statements &#8211; that Poland is utterly useless. The French policy of depending on the Poles for the holding down of the Germans, &amp; the holding back of the Bolshevists must end in failure.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p>The German President <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ebert</hi> is said to be under the control of his wife, who is physically far more imposing than he. But the stories that are current about this lady indicate that she is a woman of considerable intelligence. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ebert</hi> himself is described as "a good party man" with a capacity for reconciling differences among his colleagues.</p>
         <p>The old guide at Sans Souci, who had the aspect of Col. Newcombe, expressed his belief that the Monarchy woud have to be restored as the Germans were quite unfit for a Republic, &amp; needed a man to rule over them with a big stick. This, however, is hardly the formula of a constitutional monarchy.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>