<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName> accompanied me to the station, when I left Birchington by the 8.15 a.m. train. There is always now the sombre reflection that I shall probably not see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName></hi> again in the flesh. I travelled comfortably to Cannon Street. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; deposited my bags. I walked to Westminster &amp; called on the Dean<persName xml:id="325"></persName>. He told me in the course of conversation that the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> receives &#x00A3;1500 yearly from the diocese in order to make it possible for him to go on living at Farnham. There are clearly advantages in being a recognised "Catholick" leader! I went to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Rees</hi>, and bought a novel of Wells to beguile my journey. It just lasted me from Euston to Carlisle. I found a room reserved for me in the Station Hotel.</p>
         <p>The procession of unemployed men which marched yesterday to Downing Street included an element of revolutionaries, or at least of rowdies. There was something which nearly amounted to rioting<hi rend="bold underline">. I noticed broken windows in Whitehall as I passed by this morning</hi>. The papers still speak of mediation as possible, and an early ending of the Strike: but the miners themselves are in a truculent mood, and it is quite impossible to believe in the good faith of any of the Labour leaders. The next move will be made by Parliament which happily has resumed sitting. Probably a Committee will be appointed. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>