<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Today I must set myself to composing the address which I must deliver at my enthronement. The situation is extremely difficult &amp; complicated. That the proposed arrangement with the miners has been rejected by overwhelming majorities is now certain, and the prospect of peace recedes farther than ever. I can hardly avoid some reference to this matter. The tradition of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="1047"></persName> is more embarrassing than serviceable. I suppose some reason must be offered for my long delay in entering on my duties, and this will necessitate mention of the Lamberth Conference, and of the visit to Sweden. This mention will in turn suggest some pronouncement of my own wishes and intentions as to the resolutions of the Conference. Then I cannot avoid saying something about the School, and the University: and there must be proper reference to my predecessor. The problem of Auckland Castle must be glanced at, and it will raise the whole hateful subject of clerical poverty, which does not lose its urgency by acquiring offensiveness! Or, would it be better to follow <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lightfoot's</hi><persName xml:id="1817"></persName> example, and to preach a sermon of the ordinary type, save of course for its obvious reference? <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lightfoot </hi>made great use of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler</hi><persName xml:id="1856"></persName>, his namesake, who like him was an unmarried man, and, perhaps was felt to be similar in type &amp; character: but there is hardly any of my predecessors who can quite so obviously serve my turn. I might might save my references to the threatened Strike for the speech at luncheon, or at Darlington.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>