<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I noticed in the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi>" that the amazing situation in Ireland has moved the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> to issue yet another appeal for prayer; and this has been immediately followed by a similar appeal from a number of "religious leaders" including of course all the habitual signatories of such documents. I find it very difficult to believe that any good purpose is served by such appeals. To begin with, they are almost certainly ineffective so far as their professed object is concerned, for nobody can pray to order, &amp; everybody must pray when they can since, as the hymn says,</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Prayer is the heart's sincere desire</p>
         <p>Uttered or unexpressed.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Then, this Irish problem is unsolved, not from any lack of goodwill in Great Britain, but because it is properly insoluble on any lines yet perceived. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Morley</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Asquith</hi><persName xml:id="215"></persName> have not really contributed any new or hopeful suggestion by their recent letters to the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi>"; and only the virulent hatred of the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="234"></persName> which now determines the policy of that journal can explain its respectful allusions to them. If the Archbishop or any of the others who bid us pray, have any practical proposals to offer, in God's Name let them make no delay in offering them: but to talk of prayers when the one thing needful is a workable plan is to move men to anything rather than devotion. There is a time to pray, and a time to rise from one's knees, &amp; take up the more religious tasks of thinking &amp; working.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[166]</hi></p>
         <p>After packing our bags, we changed the check for &#x00A3;10. partly into Belgian partly into German. The exchange for the first was 48 francs to the &#x00A3;, for the last 222 marks to the &#x00A3;. My bill for the 2 nights was 233.50 so that for our very luxurious lodgement we paid little more than &#x00A3;1. Then we walked to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Gereon's, a most interesting church. The 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century crypt with its quaint mosaic pavement is hard to beat. We visited a museum, mostly filled with furniture &amp;c, old &amp; new, which bored me; &amp; we looked into S. Ursula. Then we returned to the Hotel, paid our reckoning, &amp; went to the railway station. The kindness of the military reserved a carriage for us, so we travelled to Li&#x00E8;ge very comfortably. The customs were passed at Herbesthal, &amp; we showed our passports several times. At Li&#x00E8;ge <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dolphin</hi><persName xml:id="2798"></persName> met us at the station.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dolphins</hi> might seem rather specially qualified to bear trustworthy testimony as to the behaviour of the German troops in Li&#x00E8;ge during the occupation, for they had been resident there before the war, had fled before the invaders leaving the house to their handling &amp; have returned to occupy it again after their departure. So far from any brutal damage having been done by the German officers who lived in the house, the rooms were so uninjured that nothing had to be done to them before the Dolphins re&#8211;occupied them. A few pictures &amp;c have disappeared, &amp; many things were packed up for removal, but left in the hurry of departure. This extent of looting can be alleged against them, but nothing more.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
         <p>The Liegiois did not dislike the Germans. On the contrary, they desired to have German soldiers quartered on them, both because their presence ensured protection, &amp; because it brought more food into the house. <hi rend="bold underline">The worst fault alleged against the Germans was drunkenness, &amp; this led occasionally to violences against the citizens</hi>. But the latter do not appear to have been quite so innocent as we have been assured was the case, for Mrs Dolphin tell us that she knows Belgians who boast of having poured boiling water on the German troops as they marched in, &amp; of other similar performances which must needs have exasperated the invaders, &amp; provided excuses for severity. <hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Everything points to our having been greatly deceived in England</hi>. The Canadians are said to have left a very evil memory in Belgium, but<hi rend="bold">]</hi> the British made themselves well&#8211;liked. Dolphin tells me that he has frequently met British soldiers who have come to visit Belgians, with whom they have formed friendships during the War. He says that many ex&#8211;service men come to Belgium in order to visit the graves of fellow&#8211;soldiers, not always their own former comrades, but often the sons or husbands of neighbours. </p>
         <p>There is, thank God, a treasury of loving&#8211;kindness in men's hearts which not even their own brutal passions can altogether destroy. The Belgians are rapidly regaining their prosperity. There is an air of alertness in the country, &amp; a mighty bustle of activity which contrast with the despondency &amp; stagnation of Germany.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>