<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The miners appear resolutely determined to strike: the only doubtful question now left open is whether the Railwaymen and Transport workers will strike also. It is difficult to believe that they would be so obstinate, if they were not assured of the support of the other Unions. The first consequence of the Strike will be a considerable curtailment of railway traffic, and probably the restriction, or even prohibition of private consumption of petrol. I wish I were established in the diocese, and not doomed to a fortnight's moving about between Scotland and London.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a sermon for delivery in the parish church here tomorrow. The Epistle for the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sunday after Trinity supplied me with the Text: "<hi rend="underline">Look carefully therefore how ye walk, not as unwise, but as wise: redeeming the time because the days are evil. Wherefore be ye not foolish but understand what the will of the Lord is</hi>". Would it be possible to develop what I have written into a sermon suitable for the University of Glasgow? Might not some references to the economic crisis be fitly grafted on to an application of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's admonition to the case of modern believers? As Bishop of Durham I shall be expected to speak about the Strike, and yet it were better to hold my peace than to say anything which could embarrass me just at the moment when I am making my entrance into my Bishoprick.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>