<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to the hair&#8211;dresser &amp; had my Samsonic locks shorn and cleansed. Then I walked to Westminster and saw <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lee</hi> about the homage. He suggested that I should write to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, and I did so later in the day. Then I walked round the Abbey, &amp; joined the crowd which had gathered to welcome the Prince of Wales<persName xml:id="5186"></persName>. H.R.H. looked pleased and healthy as a young man should. Then I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> in little cloisters, and had much pleasant talk with him. He says that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bethune&#8211;Baker</hi><persName xml:id="4131"></persName> is far the ablest of the Cambridge professors of divinity: that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stanton</hi><persName xml:id="5234"></persName> is thought to be growing more liberal as he grows older: that the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" wave in the college chapels expresses the desire of the college&#8211;authorities to attract what religion yet lingers among the undergraduates: that the <hi rend="underline">Christian Students' Union</hi> moves towards a synthesis of religious belief, and that, if it could succeed in including Anglicans, would probably draw into its membership most of the serious religion in the University. He said that his Sermon to the British Ass<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> brought him more than 400 letters, of which many were simply abusive, many were sorrowfully distressed, and some were eagerly appreciative. Some came from opponents of Christianity who claimed him as one of themselves. I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; wrote a few letters. Then I walked back to the Deanery. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watkins</hi><persName xml:id="590"></persName> was in the Club, &amp; told me that the Provost (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard</hi><persName xml:id="225"></persName>) was to officiate at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Maureen's</hi> wedding on November 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> next.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>