<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Still the fortunes of the great effort to arrange a settlement of the miners' strike hang in the balance, but the tone of the morning papers is hopeful. The general feeling here seems to hesitate between a desire for peace, &amp; a conviction that lasting peace can only follow a fight to a finish. It is evident enough that the railwaymen will not back the miners, whom they envy as men better paid than themselves, and whom they look down upon as their social and intellectual inferiors. There is, however, a considerable section of railway men, who w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be prepared to go all lengths with the miners: and they are mainly the younger men, whose is the future. The fate of the country turns on the point, whether or not they are powerful enough to "call the tune".</p>
         <p>I lunched with The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mrs Watkins</hi><persName xml:id="2762"></persName> to meet the Crewe Trustees &#8211; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Armstrong</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Priestman</hi><persName xml:id="1237"></persName>, the Archdeacon of Northumberland<persName xml:id="5240"></persName>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi> of S. Margaret's, Durham, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bayley</hi><persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, the Archdeacon of Sedgefield &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rowlandson</hi><persName xml:id="2808"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName> had tea with me. I showed him what I propose to say in the Cathedral on Saturday &amp; he took away the MS. as he has undertaken to write something for the Y.P.</p>
         <p>That most kindly &amp; generous of men, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to bring an engraving of Auckland Castle framed for <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. He undertook to make some enquiries about a suitable ex&#8211;service man for the Lodge &amp; gardens. He suggested that he and I might combine in a Secretary.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>