<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[160]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Packing is the continuing shadow of the traveller's life: and the war has darkened it by adding the new anxiety as to the fate of one's registered luggage, which the War has created. For a wave of dishonesty is passing over Europe. The disbanded troops retain the habits of "military licence", when they lay aside their weapons: and the poverty in which they find themselves immersed as civilians adds a fresh incentive to dishonesty. Here in Germany the worst accounts are given as to the stealing practised on the railways. One parts with a suit&#8211;case in the temper of that pathetic sentiment which invests a farewell which is believed to be final!</p>
         <p>We were unfortunate in finding the museums 'geschlossen', and we failed in an attempt to see the cathedral. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Then Angel<persName xml:id="1812"></persName> and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> dragged me, a reluctant victim, to some beastly vanity&#8211;show, (I think it was Wertheimers) where I spent a miserable hour in seeing silly things set out to tempt silly women. After this we picked up Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName> at his office, and lunched at Hotel Adlon, where we found <hi rend="doubleunderline">General Bingham</hi><persName xml:id="5230"></persName>, who most kindly offered us Saturday's London papers in his room.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the Zological Gardens &amp; Aquarium, both of which were excellent. We regretted that we had not time sufficient for seeing them properly. Then we went to the Opera, &amp; witnessed the 'Tales of Hoffman". The music and staging were both very good: but I was most interested in the enormous tragedy implied in the great imperial stall, now bereft of its crown &amp; filled with the general public,where once the Kaiser sate in majesty with his courtiers about him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>