<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>If, as seems dreadfully probable, the revolutionaries in the Labour party are now calling the tune, what will be the probable course of events? A strike of the "Triple Alliance" would create an appalling situation, which might pass into the tragedies of violent Revolution at very short notice. To guarantee food supplies and maintain order would tax to the uttermost the normal resources of the State, and unhappily the State's resources at present are far less than normal. The Labour Leaders who are now in the ascendant do not appear to be men of extraordinary ability, and the academics, who stand in the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> line, do not seem less windy &amp; futile than their fellows in Russia and Germany. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tawney</hi><persName xml:id="5035"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cole</hi><persName xml:id="4741"></persName> are representative of a section of University&#8211;bred men, who are theorists and writers rather than men of action. If personal ability could determine the course of politics, there would be small reason for fearing the victory of Revolution in Great Britain: but authority goes in these times, not to men of character, nor to men of ability, but to the monomaniacs of the moment, who express the dominant idea, and shout the cant phrase most effectively. And certainly such monomaniacs are not far to seek. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lansbury</hi><persName xml:id="4984"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Williams</hi> are precisely men of this kind, and along with them is a whole multitude of crazy zealots &#8211; clergymen, dissenting ministers, schoolmasters, and women &#8211; who could inspire the mass of hungry and demented artisans to all extremes of violence and folly.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[191]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi> went back to Auckland Castle, judging it prudent to abandon her projected visit to Helensburgh, rather than imperil her chance of getting a train. I went on to Glasgow in order to carry out my engagement to preach to the University, but I decided to give up the Bishop's Meeting next week, and to go to my rooms in Durham Castle as expeditiously as possible on Monday.</p>
         <p>The Principal (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Donald Macalister</hi><persName xml:id="5235"></persName>) being absent in London, &amp; not due to return home before 11 p.m., Lady M. took me to dine at Professor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Milligan's</hi><persName xml:id="5236"></persName> House, which is not far from the University. After dinner D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Macaulay<persName xml:id="3541"></persName> and Prof. Rait<persName xml:id="3475"></persName> came in, &amp; had some talk with me. I inquired of the former how far <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maclean</hi><persName xml:id="3547"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fleming</hi><persName xml:id="566"></persName> represented Presbyterian opinion in their rather acrid attacks on the Lambeth Appeal. I was assured that lay opinion disapproved the tone of these attacks, &amp; that there was a general belief that a real step towards a better relation between the churches had been taken by the Bishops. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M. particularly expressed his disagreement with Maclean in his attempt to show that presbyterian orders were as sound as episcopal in the point of succession. It is evident that there are very many presbyterian ministers who would be glad to receive ordination from the bishops, if the process could be guarded against any suggestion of re&#8211;ordination. But this condition seems almost unattainable in view of the actual state of opinion within the Churches. The invalidity of presbyterian orders &amp; sacraments is an article of faith with all Anglo&#8211;Catholics.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>