<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[170]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The end of our 'tramp abroad' is at last in sight. Exactly four weeks have passed since we left Newcastle on board the 'Patricia', and now, like an Indian brave returning from a foray, we may count our scalps i.e. review our experiences. Gothenburg, Stockholm, Upsala, Lund, Berlin, Cologne, Li&#x00E8;ge &#8211; all now are memories to be stored in our heterogeneous collection which fills the museum of my mind. Do they enrich, or discredit, it? I have been brought into momentary contact with a number of persons. Am I permanently the better, or the worse, for having joined hands with them? Have they received from me ideas or impressions which will help or hinder them? My character as a Christian Minister has not been wholly concealed, for I have exercised all the principal functions of my ministry. At Stockholm I confirmed and preached at Upsala. I helped to consecrate. At Berlin I celebrated: At Li&#x00E8;ge I baptized. During these weeks I have written a number of letters. What effect will they have on their readers? Very beautiful scenes of Nature have passed before my eyes, have I taken anything of lasting value into my character? Am I strenghtened in any good purpose, released from any delusion or ill habit, by being set&#8211;free from the normal routine for these four weeks? It would be the answering of those questions as these which would really disclose the value of this holiday: &amp; it is precisely the answering of these questions which is beyond my powers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi></p>
         <p>We left Li&#x00E8;ge by the 9.27 a.m. express to Ostend, being very comfortably despatched by Dolphin<persName xml:id="2798"></persName> and his clerk, who registered the luggage &amp;c, most obligingly. We arrived at Ostend at 1.45 p.m, and went on board the steamer, but instead of starting at 2.30 p.m. as announced we were delayed until 4.30 p.m., in order to accommodate some Balkan dignitary whose train was very late. <hi rend="bold underline">We crossed the Channel without discomfort, and were not excessively bothered by the customs, whether Belgian or British. We arrived at the Deanery St Paul's about 11.30 p.m., and after some clamour, gained admission, and were welcomed very warmly by the admirable </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, who for the present is staying here.</hi></p>
         <p>Thus ends an experience which has been interesting, and may have been important. It has also been expensive in spite of the fact that we have been very generoulsy entertained most of the time. We have been favoured with fine weather throughout so that, not only have we been able to see the country to advantage but also (no inconsiderable matter for such bad sailors as we are) our marine passages &#8211; the North Sea, the Baltic, &amp; the English Channel &#8211; have been comparatively comfortable. We have had no difficulty with revenue officials, and our passports were everywhere respected. Our health throughout has been excellent, and our packing marked by fewer <hi rend="underline">oblivions</hi> than usual. So far as we know at present, no letters have gone astray for us of from us.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>