<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I left Glasgow after breakfast, and travelled to Durham by way of Newcastle, and Carlisle, arriving about 5.30 pm. The first person to greet me was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Low</hi>, with whom I walked up to the Castle, where I found myself expected. It was with a new appropriating interest that I viewed that mighty pile, and entered into its possession. For nothing short of possession was the quality of my residence. As I sate in the tapestried room, very dark and immemorial, a great wave of historical memories passed over me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler</hi><persName xml:id="1856"></persName> occupied his room, and tried to formulate a tolerable version of his duty in front of these tapestries! I dined in Hall, and had some pleasant talk with The Master<persName xml:id="3459"></persName>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pestle</hi><persName xml:id="5238"></persName> in the Common Room, before settling down to my letters. There are 62 undergraduates here this term, almost an unprecedented number. It is the same with all the Universities. The War has greatly augmented their numbers. After dinner I wrote many letters, and tore up as much of my papers as I could safely dispose of.</p>
         <p>The amount of speech&#8211;making, which I am committed to in connexion with my entrance on the See of Durham is certainly rather alarming. 1. Darlington. 2. Durham &#x3B1;) Cathedral &#x3B2;) Luncheon in Castle Hall 3) Bishop Auckland. 4. Sunderland. In ordinary times this must needs be a difficult performance: but these times are not ordinary. In the midst of a grave economic crisis every word must be weighed. I don't want to get across the miners at first start, but I don't want to speak falsely for the sake of peace.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>