<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather was fine for the time of year, and might have been called "a grey day". There was no wind, and there was a pleasant temperature. The little church had been prettily decorated for the wedding, and was quite full when the service began. I was not greatly impressed by the bridegroom, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain James Galbraith</hi>, but impressions are not always as trustworthy as they are vivid. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Buff</hi><persName xml:id="836" display="no"></persName> looked very beautiful &amp; happy. The service was simple, hearty, and (so far as could be seen and felt) sincere. I took the first part of the marriage service and gave the address. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Knowles</hi>, the parish minister, read the second part of the service. My address from the words, "<hi rend="underline">Those whom God hath joined together let no man put asunder</hi>", lasted about 10 minutes, &amp; seemed to give much satisfaction to the company! Afterwards, I signed the register in the house, and proposed the health of the bride &amp; bridegroom. Then I escaped from the company, and took refuge in my bedroom! The newly&#8211;wedded pair went off in the bridegroom's car to spend their honey&#8211;moon in the moors. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray</hi><persName xml:id="227"></persName> and I went off for a walk along the banks of the Annan. He encouraged me to hope that we might come upon a heron fishing, but I had no such luck. Returning to the house I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> accepting the invitation which he and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ellershaw</hi><persName xml:id="3459"></persName> sent me a week ago, viz. to dine in the Castle on the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, after the Enthronement: I took occasion to indicate that I should use the Bishop's Rooms until my study at Auckland were ready for use.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>