<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Our guests departed after an early breakfast, &amp; after they had gone, Lionel and I went through the letters.  The post brought me some satirical verses signed <hi rend="bold underline">''A.M. Oxon''</hi> and headed <hi rend="bold underline">'The Primate's Testimonial'</hi>:</p>
         <p>Pity the present plight of Primate old. </p>
         <p>Whose resignation brings him to your door.</p>
         <p>Now join the tribute to him manifold.</p>
         <p>And give your offering, be it less or more.</p>
         <p>He has, throughout a century's quarter here –</p>
         <p>The period which constitutes an age –</p>
         <p>Received just &#x00A3;15,000 a year,</p>
         <p>And that we own is quite a living wage.</p>
         <p>But now this living wage is gone for aye.</p>
         <p>Save what is left a decimated sum –</p>
         <p>A paltry pension of &#x00A3;4 a day</p>
         <p>To make provision for the time to come.</p>
         <p>There are other verses, but these suffice to indicate its character. A note is appended:</p>
         <p>'Your satire is quite just'</p>
         <p>A member of the House of Commons.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I prepared notes for a speech on Education, and then being distressed by a violent headache, I did nothing until 3p.m. when accompanied by Lionel and Kenneth, I was carried to Newcastle in Lionel's car. There I attended a meeting of the Durham Castle Preservation C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi>. Where Blackitt made himself a great nuisance. Pears attended, &amp; was useful, but little progress was made, &amp; I came away leaving the Committee still in session. ''Now you can understand the existence of men'' like Cook'', observed Lidderdale to me, as he saw me out. ''What reasonable man could put up with a manager like Blackitt?''</p>
         <p>I went to the Rectory at Gateshead, &amp; had tea. Then I went to the parish church &amp; confirmed 4 young men. After this I went to the Town Hall and delivered my address on 'Education' to a numerous assembly of ''educationists'', mostly school teachers. I spoke for 40 minutes, and when I sat down I was much applauded. Then came the giving of thanks, a nauseous exhibition! After the meeting had ended, we returned to Auckland Castle, arriving about 10.15 p.m</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
