<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Much to my astonishment, I received from Father<persName xml:id="11">Puller</persName> the following letter:–</p>
         <p>September 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1928.</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Bishop,</p>
         <p>I have just now finished reading your admirable paper entitled Reflections on the Crisis, with every word of which I find myself in complete agreement; and I cannot refrain from writing these few lines to express my heartfelt thanks to you for your courageous setting forth of the truth.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely &amp; very respectfully,</p>
         <p>F. W. Puller S.S.J.E. </p>
         <p>Father Puller was born as long ago as 1843. He is now an old man of 85. It is many years since I met him. He was a friend of Sir William Anson. But I know that he and his friend, the present head of the Pusey House, were violently opposed to my consecration to the Bishoprick of Hereford.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I replied as follows:–</p>
         <p>September 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1928</p>
         <p>My dear Father Puller,</p>
         <p>It was very kind of you to write. I appreciate very deeply your approval of what I have written: and I take leave to ask for the further charity of your prayers in this difficult time, when the way of duty is not always clear, and never easy to tread.</p>
         <p>With great regard,</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Most sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         <p>I begin to feel uncomfortable about the approval which I am receiving from High Church Leaders. I notice, indeed, that they are old men whose High Churchmanship has little in common with the Romanising Anglo–Catholicism, which has been mainly responsible for wrecking the Revision. But I am discovering more plainly every day that I am thoroughly obsolete in thought &amp; feeling!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Congress Sermon. In the afternoon I talked with the folk who came to play tennis and have tea. Among them was Gerald Rainbow and his mother. I gave the boy a £ as he had a good report last term, and returns to school next week.</p>
         <p>The 'Church Times' calls attention to an interview with the bishop of Birmingham which Iremonger published in a book noticed in the papers this week.  There is nothing particularly new in the opinions expressed, but they have an offensive aspect, &amp; will no doubt excite alarm.  There is an indefinable air of amateurish impudence about them which is certainly provocative.  The concluding comment is the following:– 'These are the considered statements of a prelate whom Catholic priests are asked to obey'.</p>
         <p>I suspect that the Modernist issue is to be raised by the Anglo–Catholicks. It will divert attention from themselves, divide their opponents, and open the door to new developments of many kinds. The Prayer Book revision will fall out of mind in the resultant confusion.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
