<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Love of freedom has not always been, nor will it always remain, the predominant note in the English mind. At times the English people have pursued it through battle &amp; murder with grim determination, but other times have seen other ideals. On occasion the demand has been for strong government irrespective of its methods, and good government has been preferred to self&#8211;government. Wars of expansion &amp; wars of defence have often cooled the love of liberty &amp; impaired the faith in parliaments: and generally English ideals have been strictly subordinated to a passion for material prosperity.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pollard</hi>. '<hi rend="underline">Henry viii'</hi>. P. 34.</p>
         <p>This passage excepting only the last sentence is repeated in the author's "Factors in Modern History", p.73. The fortunes of Magna Carta illustrate the changes in English sentiment. Ignored or forgotten by the Tudors, it was under the Stuarts idealized as the very palladium of English liberty. Modern estimates are more moderate &amp; discriminating. 'In reality magna Carta made few lasting innovations, &amp; asserted no new liberties'. (Davis).</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>And here I am at a loss what to say, upon the frequent custom of preaching against Atheism, Deism, Free&#8211;thinking, &amp; the like: as young Divines are particularly fond of doing, especially when they exercise their talent in churches frequented by people of quality; which, as it is but an ill compliment to the audience, so I am under some doubt whether it answers the end. Because persons under such imputations are generally no great frequenters of churches, &amp; so the congregation is but little edified for the sake of three or four Fools, who are past grace.</p>
         <p>Swift.  'A Letter to a Young Gentleman lately entered into Holy Orders.' </p>
         <p>I read 'large' about the Magna Carta with a view to my sermon at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Edmundsbury on October 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. The good Burghers have decided to celebrate the fact that the Barons met in their borough in 1214, &amp; thus to link themselves on to the Langton Commemoration – the 700<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> anniversary of his death.  It is the most circuitous method of justifying a municipal 'flare&#8211;up' that I can recall.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
