<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Marshall</hi> writes to me from Fulham Vicarage:</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"I do not think there is the remotest chance of our Bishop resigning. He is full of health and vitality, still plays an excellent game of tennis, &amp; gets through an amazing number of engagements. He is still very popular, &amp; he loves crowds"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Barry</hi>, formerly of Knutsford, now Vicar of S. Mary's and Fellow of Balliol, writes to me with respect to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Daly</hi>, now an assistant curate at S. Mary's, Tyne Dock, whom he wishes to draw away to be his curate in Oxford.  He is good enough to say that he will not approach <hi rend="doubleunderline">Daly</hi> without my full approval.  I wrote at once to say that such full approval he could not possibly have.  But it startles me that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barry</hi>, who may be presumed to know something of the desperate straits to which the industrial districts generally &amp; Durham in particular, have been reduced for lack of clergy, should even think of withdrawing a young clergyman for the carpet&#8211;cleric "work" of an Oxford curacy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes expressing dissent from my attitude on Disestablishment, &amp; professing himself "an Erastian unashamed", and Ella is in raptures at finding so thorough&#8211;going an ally!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We motored to Cornhill, and had tea with Canon &amp; Mrs Holland, a vigorous old couple, though both octogenarians, remarkably alert and interested in the course of the world.  Their sons are amongst the best known of the younger clergy, William the missionary and his brother, the sub&#8211;dean of Coventry.  The old man has been Vicar of Cornhill for 47 years, &amp; is now 82.  But he has no mind to contemplate resignation until he has kept the Jubilee of his ministry in the parish.  He told me that of his 800 parishioners, about four fifths were Scottish Presbyterians, &amp; that there was really no need for the parish church, since the Scottish Episcopalians had built a church in Coldstream, some devout ''Anglo&#8211;Catholick'' lady having taken offence at the Protestant simplicity of Cornhill, &amp; built a church to satisfy herself!  Sir Francis Blake &amp; his sister, Mr Butler &amp; his daughter, &amp; Mr De la Heye, the vicar of Berwick &amp; his wife were also present.  I had some interesting conversation with Sir F. Blake, about the present state &amp; future prospect of the coal industry in Northumberland &amp; Durham.  He was as little able to discuss any justification for optimism as 1 am. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
