<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Macaulay</hi>, a Fellow of King's College, Cambridge, who has already subscribed largely to the Fund for restoring Durham Castle, wrote to me promising to subscribe yet another &#x00A3;500, so soon as the work has actually begun.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in reading a very stimulating and masterly work by <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> R. H. Murray</hi>; '<hi rend="underline">The Political Consequences of the Reformation</hi>'. It abounds in luminous obiter dicta.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> and I motored to Sunderland, stopping on the way to see the Bishop of Jarrow.  I instituted, or rather collated the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. W. R. Dawson</hi> to the Rectory of Sunderland, in succession to the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Septimus Pates</hi>.  The church, which is a large one, was crowded, and there was a fair muster of the local clergy.  I was impressed by the squalid appearance of the considerable crowd which had gathered in the street to watch my departure.  The population consists largely of Popish Irish, who are always the most squalid and criminous [sic] element of the population. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Edgar Jackson</hi> acted as Rural Dean, &amp; inducted the Rector after he had been collated.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
