<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Rolt who was living in Cape Town with her husband the Dean of the Cathedral there when Hickson came thither on his faith&#8211;healing mission, told me much about the man and his methods.  About 2000 persons passed under the Healer's hands, but when subsequently the results had to be appraised &amp; registered with a view to public thanksgiving, <hi rend="underline">no more than 3 cases could be certified as "super&#8211;natural"</hi>. I inquired particularly about the man himself, &amp; I was told that he left an unpleasing impression of avarice and self&#8211;indulgence, not clearly of dishonesty and excess, but quite clearly of mundane &amp; self&#8211;indulgent temperament &amp; habit. "<hi rend="underline">We have the treasure in earthen vessels</hi>", and it would ill become us to quarrel with the Instruments which the Almighty wills to use in working His "magnalia". Nevertheless, we are so built that we inevitably demand a measure of congruity between the man and his message. '<hi rend="underline">By their fruits ye shall know them</hi>' tends to justify this demand, &amp; it seems plainly taught in the New Testament that there is a definite connexion between moral quality and insight into the things of the spirits. "<hi rend="underline">The pure in heart shall see God</hi>" said our Saviour, &amp; He seems to disclose a principle of the Divine Economy, supremely illustrated in Himself.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There were 10 communicants including all our guests except John Rolt, who came to chapel but retired feeling faint.</p>
         <p>I wrote to William at Bulawayo: and to the Bishop of Guildford.</p>
         <p>Then for an hour I walked in the Park with Cock and the two boys.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cock</hi> accompanied me in the motor to <hi rend="underline">Winlaton</hi>, where the centenary of the parish church was being celebrated.  The church, (which, however, is of no great size) was crowded, &amp; the congregation listened to my sermon very attentively.  After the service I had some talk with old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Jones</hi> who has held the Rectory for 44 years, since 1884.  He was ordained as long ago as 1876.  <hi rend="underline">Winlaton</hi> contains 16,500 parishioners, is stated to have an endowment of &#x00A3;500: &amp; is in the patronage of the Bishop of Chester.  There are two mission churches, but the combined accommodation of all the three buildings is only 770: and – this is the sinister fact – is abundantly sufficient for the huge population.  I had a good deal of conversation with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cock</hi> on the way, &amp; was pleased with him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
