<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Philip and I walked to the Church, &amp; received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. Later we attended Mattins, and listened to an address from a Cambridge under&#8211;graduate named Dart, on the subject of the "World Call". He is here with another young man on one of these 'undergraduate missions', which have become so numerous in recent years. After service I walked for an hour with a Balliol man, named Smith, who is staying here.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon we all went for a short walk, &amp; then returned to tea, when some neighbours came in. One of these, Major Royds, said that he had met me some 30 years ago, &amp; entertained me when I came to address a meeting of the Bible Society in Wolverhampton: but I had to confess that I had no recollection whatever of having seen him before!!</p>
         <p>There was a large and very attentive congregation at Evensong in the parish church, when I preached from the words, "<hi rend="underline">Desire earnestly the greater gifts, and yet declare I unto you a more excellent way.</hi>"</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Marcus Montague, the Liberal candidate, went off by the night train to Scotland, hoping to recover his lost luggage at Crewe.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
