<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning and part of the afternoon at Lambeth in the Bishops' Meeting. There was a curious 'throw&#8211;back' to abandoned positions by some of the Bishops, which caused much waste of time: but in the end not much harm was done. I came away at 3.30 p.m. and walked to the Athenaeum, where I had tea, &amp; talked with the late President of Magdalen, who tells me that he is going to live in Oxford. I travelled to Darlington by the 5.30 p.m. express, &amp; was met there by Lionel and the car.</p>
         <p>The Dean of Westminster &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Norris had arrived at the Castle during my absence for a brief visit.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Oman</hi> has a very interesting article in the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi> on the subject of finds of Roman coins in this island.  He says that these are mostly of copper coins which are almost worthless.  He himself found a hoard of 37,000 coper coins.  "Treasure trove" is limited to gold and silver coins.  Most commonly the discoverer keeps the matter secret, &amp; disposes of the treasurer [sic] quietly: but local vanity often makes the fact public, &amp; then the find is confiscated.  Coins of the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> century appear to be very rarely found. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>The attitude of the bishops was not very dignified nor yet very intelligible.  Their minds were plainly dominated by the dread of dis&#8211;establishment, though they still used the language of independence.  Both the Archbishops&#8211;designate were ambiguous and temporising, reflecting very obviously the sentiments of the politicians to whom they owed their preferment.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> incidentally disclosed the fact that he had been recently talking over the situation with various leading men, &amp; that they had all urged the need of a quiet interval during which opinion might settle on some revision of the existing Establishment.  I asked whether any sane man supposed that there was even the slightest probability that Parliament would agree to any revision which would guarantee the Church against a repetition of our recent experience, &amp; there was none to answer.  And if we knew that no satisfactory revision of the Establishment was really possible, were we acting self&#8211;respectingly in pretending the contrary?  But, as in the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, so in the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, it is the case that '<hi rend="underline">Clerici Anglicani semper pavidi</hi>' [Anglican clergy always fearful].</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
