<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I sent copies of the letters exchanged between Lord Joicey and myself to the following <hi rend="strikethrough">5</hi>6 newspapers viz: 1. The Times. 2. The Yorkshire Post. 3. The Manchester Guardian. 4. The Morning Post. 5. The Newcastle ^Daily^ Journal. 6. The Newcastle Daily Chronicle &amp; North Mail.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi> seems to be 'tuning up' for some dramatic action at the Church Congress.  The Church Union is to protest against <hi rend="doubleunderline">Major</hi>'s admission as one of the readers of papers.  Certainly it cannot be denied that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Major</hi> has been extraordinarily provocative, and even those who, like myself, are prepared to do much in order to keep the Church of England a widely tolerant Church are wondering whether his teaching can be fitted into any coherent version of Christianity.  His arrogance is as exorbitant as his "liberalism".  I notice in the 'Modern Churchman' an evident desire to quote passages from works of mine which may give the impression that I am either as much a heretick as Major, or an egregious 'turn&#8211;coat'.  So far as I know myself the first is untrue, and the last is libellous: but angry men do not measure their words, and I suspect that Major &amp; his Protestant allies are both embittered and perplexed by the ^situation created by the ^ ejection of the Revised Prayer Book.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
