<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Christianity was proscribed, not as a religion, but as interfering with that organization of      society which the Empire inculcated and protected…… The proscription exercised a strong influence on the Church, causing it to unite still more closely through mutual sympathy &amp; the tendency among the persecuted to help one another: but it was unable to diminish seriously the number of the Christians.  It merely made the Church stronger, more self&#8211;reliant, &amp; more spirited.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Ramsay, "The Church in the Roman Empire" p. 372, 374 </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cock</hi> went off after breakfast: &amp; was soon followed by Mrs. Rolt &amp; her two boys. </p>
         <p>I worked at the Congress Paper, but I cannot get on. I don't really know what I want to say!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lacey</hi> writes to me: &#8211;&#8211;</p>
         <p>I am not happy about Cosmo going to Canterbury.  My feelings about him have always been queerly mixed,—agreement without confidence.  There are others who suggest much less agreement &amp; very great confidence.  Some years ago I would not have liked to see you in <hi rend="bold">[60]</hi> that throne: all this year I have been desiring you."</p>
         <p>This is equally surprising and disconcerting, for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lacey</hi> is certainly a very rigid "Anglo&#8211;Catholick", and that he should profess confidence in me suggests that I must have given a very false impression of myself to him.  </p>
         <p>The Secretary of the <hi rend="underline">'Church Reform League</hi>' sends me a very civilly expressed invitation to join that body, but I dictated a polite but decisive refusal.  What have I to do with those bustling agitators to whom we owe The Enabling Act? </p>
         <p>The situation is extraordinarily perplexing. On the one hand, the tests of Church membership which alone can be observed – Communicants, parish electors &amp;c – are fearfully untrustworthy. On the other hand the very notion of the spiritual society, such as, on any showing, a Christian Church must be, is contradicted by the action of the House of Commons. If I believed in the possibility of maintaining the Establishment self&#8211;respectingly in the future, I would bring myself to acquiescence in the situation which has been disclosed, but I cannot bring myself to believe this.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
