<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Christians were on the earth ere Christ was born; </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">His laws, not yet a code, were follow'd still</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">By sightless Pagans in the dark forlorn,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Groping toward the light, as blind men will:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Thousands of years ago men dared to die</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Loving their enemies &#8211; &amp; wonder'd why!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Robert Barnabas Brough. 1823&#8211;1860</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">'And other sheep I have which are not of this field. Them also I must bring: and they shall hear my voice, and they shall become one flock, one shepherd.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The claim of Christianity to be the religion of mankind is grounded on this fact, that the moral victories of men of every description and in every age are recognizably accordant with the Christian version of morality.  Christ does apparently embody a moral ideal which is endorsed by the human conscience everywhere, &amp; which in the best individuals of the race has been wonderfully approached.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"I, if I be lifted up, will draw all men unto Myself</hi><hi rend="italic">" is an utterance, which might serve as the summary of the effect of Christianity in the world's life.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[14]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My reverend Brother,</p>
         <p>I have thought it necessary to direct the inquiries of my second Quadrennial Visitation to the actual methods by which the 'Cure of Souls' is being effected in the parishes of my Diocese.  You will observe that I have omitted many of the formal obligations which the Law imposes on every parish clergyman, and also those intimate personal ministries which, though of the highest spiritual importance, must needs lie outside the Bishop's direct concern.  I have limited myself to the pastor's accustomed and normally indispensable activities.  It is in the conscientious fulfilment of his normal functions in dependence always on the help of God, that the Christian Minister's efficiency must be demonstrated.  The circumstances in which the work of the Ministry must be carried out in modern England have become extremely difficult.  There seems reason for thinking that the most approved pastoral methods are failing to match the new social conditions.  By answering frankly and carefully the Visitation questions you will certainly assist me to form a just estimate of the situation <hi rend="bold">[15] </hi>in our Diocese, and I think you will yourself be helped to a deeper realization of the magnitude and dignity of our sacred work.</p>
         <p>I am, Your faithful friend &amp; bishop</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         <p>I drafted the above as an introduction to the Visitation inquiries, which are of an unusual character &amp; may be thought to need some explanation.</p>
         <p>[symbol] Parker Smith sent me a long cutting from the Sunday Times of August 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, containing a sensationally&#8211;worded report on the Malines Conversations, of which the exact account (so it was asserted, but I think, untruly) is immediately to appear. This effusion is startlingly headed:</p>
         <p>Church of England &amp; Rome</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Minutes of the Malines Conversations to be published.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Surprising Disclosures.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">"Special Precedence" for Archbishop of Canterbury</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I suspect that this is a journalistic stunt inspired by our Papist friends with the object of fomenting the disputes within the Church of England occasioned by the Revision Controversy, &amp; of damaging the reputation of the outgoing Archbishop. It will not however have much effect. Malines is a spent bullet.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">'De mortuis nil siri bonum'</hi>. This maxim has been given full weight in the obituary of Mr. Hervey, the late Ambassador from the U.S.A. to Great Britain, whose death is announced this morning. I never heard anybody say a good word for him when he was here, and among those who said worst of him his own fellow&#8211;countrymen were the loudest. Now we are assured that no man was more highly regarded, or with such good reason! Who could be so foolish as to attach importance to the good opinion of contemporaries, when he considers the objects of their eulogy, &amp; the capriciousness of their favour?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Nicholas Murray Butler</hi> has again 'let himself go' on the subjects of naval defence and prohibition as presented in the Republican candidate's address.  He plays the rôle of an American Cato, &amp; plays it with courage, perseverance, &amp; ability.</p>
         <p>The weather was again detestable.  We motored to a house not far from Kelso, &amp; had tea with Mrs. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Taylor</hi>, whom I met years ago at Broad Meadows as Joe Lang. Se has a fine young family of 4 boys and a girl. Her husband is the son of Mr. Taylor of Chipchase.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
