<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]The action of the clergy in the great struggles of the period has been already noted, in its proper proportion to the general detail. They by their vindication of their own liberties showed the nation that other liberties might be vindicated as well, &amp; that there are bounds to the power &amp; violence of princes. They had fought the battle of the people in fighting their own. From them too, as subjects and not merely as churchmen, the first movements towards national action had come.["]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Stubbs</hi>. '<hi rend="underline">Constitutional History</hi>. i. 632</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gadd</hi><hi rend="italic"> sends me the following: The great Irish historian, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lecky</hi><hi rend="italic">, once found himself at a dinner where the guests were mostly celebrities in one field or an other, beside a young charmingly dressed American who begged him to identify the principal persons for her delectation.  Finally, she asked, 'And what do you do, Sir?  'I am a writer: I suppose I may say I am by way of being an historian.  Are you by any chance interested in history, Madam?'  'Oh no, not a bit,' she answered blithely.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'I always say, Let bygones be bygones'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hopkinson</hi> telegraphed that her husband had died, and was to be buried at Whitburn on Friday.  This releases an honorary canonry.</p>
         <p>The Rector of Burnmoor wrote to ask me to preach Funeral Sermons for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi> next Sunday, but I declined.  There can be no denying that, however much the circumstances of his marriage may dispose one to a sympathetic judgment, the late Lord lived immorally, and had no connexion with the Church in the diocese save to exercize his right as a patron, &amp; to contribute to parochial objects.  His career, in which the outstanding feature was his devotion to horse–racing, could not possibly be commended, &amp; I think it would be properly scandalous for a Bishop to pronounce eulogies on him in the parish Church.  This is not the less evident because my personal liking for Lord D. would dispose me to speak flatteringly of him.  Moreover, I have a dislike of "funeral sermons", which almost amounts to loathing.  Their popularity emphasizes their inherent impropriety.  In the case of apparent Saints (if there be such) and known benefactors, it may be proper to hail their departure with tributes of praise, but for the rest of us, who are neither Saints nor benefactors, No.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel </hi>and I motored to Boldon, where I addressed a gathering of subscribers to the Waifs &amp; Strays Society's Home. The boys – 20 in number – sate in front of me. After the meeting I had tea, and inspected the Home. Then we went to the parish for a service in the course of which I dedicated a tablet containing the names of the Rectors of Boldon since A.D. 1220. Then I went to the Rectory, and had an interview with Chapman, the Vicar of S. Peter's, Jarrow, at his own request. After this, we returned to Auckland Castle, arriving in good time for dinner.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">[symbol]</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Derek Elliott</hi><hi rend="italic">, the red–headed boy, whose fees I am paying at Durham School, writes to me a cheerful letter , in which he expresses himself enthusiastically about the School, and winds up "Yours affectionately". The heart of a boy is wonderful in its simplicity. Budworth tells me that Derek has good wits, and is working well.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John McKitterick</hi> is nearing the end of his time at Leatherhead, &amp; hopes to get to Oxford with the help of a 'sponsor'.  He writes to me with obvious propriety, but at 19 one does not retain the simplicity of 14.  He hopes to be ordained, but I am not very confident that his health would justify Ordination.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
