<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A telegram from <hi rend="doubleunderline">D'Arcy Lambton</hi> was brought to me: "<hi rend="underline">Our brother passed quietly away this morning</hi>".</p>
         <p>So vanishes from the scene <hi rend="doubleunderline">John George Lambton</hi>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Earl of Durham.  He was born in 1855, so that he was 73 years 3 months of age when he died.  Forty six years ago he married <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Ethel Milner</hi>, who almost immediately lost her reason, &amp; still survives in a private asylum. I made his acquaintance when I came to Durham in January 1913 as Dean, saw a good deal of him during the War, and resumed touch with him when, after 2½ years at Hereford, I returned to Durham as bishop.  I had a genuine regard for him, and formed a high estimate of his abilities.  His calamitous marriage wrecked his life.  By nature affectionate &amp; impulsive, he needed the steadying grace of family life.  Had he been granted a suitable wife, he might have made a great name for himself in public life: for he was handsome, attractive, and eloquent.  The people in Durham pitied his misfortune, &amp; liked his person.  The general impression made on me by his life is one of profound sadness.  So much that was good and potentially great leading to no achievement for the public good.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[78]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for S. Edmundsbury. After lunch I went into the Park, &amp;, falling into discussion with four unemployed lads, and having nothing better to do, I took them round the garden, &amp; then round the Castle. Then I gave the tractate on Durham Castle, &amp; wrote their names severally thereon. Tea being out&#8211;spread in the library, I gave them each a piece of gingerbread, &amp; so sent them away. Well&#8211;spoken decent lads enough, but woefully cast&#8211;down over their failure to get work.</p>
         <p>Then Jack Boden and his wife arrived in their car. She is not an impressive looking lady, but may for all that possess powers adequate for the very difficult rôle of the parson's wife in an artisan parish.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Penelope Webbe</hi> arrived on a visit.</p>
         <p>An old lady, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss F. Geldard,</hi> sent me a cheque for &#x00A3;21 for the assistance of the miners in this district.  I suppose it will get to them most usefully if I send it to the Vicars of Witton Park, Evenwood, Eldon, &amp; West Auckland, where the mines are not working.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
