<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Funeral of the Earl of Durham </hi>
         </p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McCullagh and Lionel accompanied me to Burnmoor in order to attend Lord Durham's funeral.  There was a great concourse of people in and out of the parish church. I read the lesson, and took the prayers at the graveside.  Before leaving the grave I shook hands with the new Earl &amp; his brothers.  I noticed Lord Lascelles, Earl Grey, &amp; many county notables in the congregation.  At the end of the service a military salute was fired, &amp; the reveillé was blown on the cornet.  Coincidentally with the burial a service was held in Durham Cathedral, to which Ella went with our guests.  It appears to have been numerously attended.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Durham</hi> once said to me that he feared that he would be last <hi rend="underline">'Lambton of Lambton</hi>', since his nephew (the new Earl's son) would not consent to live there. He expressed sorrow at the prospect, &amp; no doubt sincerely, for he had a keen consciousness of his ancestral greatness in the County. If Lambton Castle is to be added to the long list of deserted mansions (which already includes Brancepeth &amp; Ravensworth) another blow will have been given to this woeful county, &amp; another aid to Communism will have been given.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Kenneth came to lunch, and afterwards walked with me in the Park for an hour. We discussed the possibility of his taking Holy Orders. He is, I think, inclined to do so, but shrinks from committing himself. I am reluctant to bring even an indirect pressure to bear on him, &amp; yet I cannot exempt myself from the duty of making him consider that career. He is, of course, very young, &amp; he knows little of the world, &amp; less of himself, but he is candid &amp; modest. He seems also religious. I did not conceal from the doubtful prospects (from a worldly point of view) which now belong to Ordination.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">(</hi>On the tall spire of N___h a sparrow was sitting.</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">Alack, I am lonely</hi>", the poor bird cried:</p>
         <p>But a hen–bird had heard him and swiftly [a friendly hen near his perch] came flitting</p>
         <p>He sighed, &amp; he fluttered, &amp; was not denied.<hi rend="bold">)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Dean of Hereford &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mrs. Waterfield</hi> arrived to spend the week–end with us.  I wrote to William.  Our dinner party numbered 12, including Lady Eden, &amp; an agreeable barrister friend of hers named Berry.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
