<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I motored to Cuddesdon, &amp; lunched with the Bishop.  We were alone, &amp; had some intimate talk, that is, as intimate as </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Strong</hi><hi rend="italic">'s evasive &amp; enigmatic temperament permits.  Attractive in many respects as he is, and friendly in manner &amp; speech, I have never yet succeeded in getting through his protective crust of foolery.  He resembles </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Alington </hi><hi rend="italic">in this respect, but whereas in </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Alington</hi><hi rend="italic">'s case, I suspect an essential frivolity, in </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Strong</hi><hi rend="italic">'s I incline to believe that there is a fundamental gravity.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Strong</hi><hi rend="italic"> affects to think that when all these precious Synods have declared themselves, the Bishops will have sufficient assurance of clerical support to justify their procedure.  I reminded him that London, Liverpool, Manchester &amp; Blackburn were considerable exceptions, &amp; that his own Synod had shown a disconcertingly large dissentient minority, &amp; that at least 6 dioceses had no Synods at all.  He admitted the seriousness of these facts, but hardly seemed to appreciate their force.  After lunch I picked up </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mrs. Pember</hi><hi rend="italic"> in an adjacent house, and returned to Oxford, where I wrote letters, and then dined in a pleasant party with mine hostess.</hi>
         </p>
         
         </body></text></TEI>
