<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928, Manchester.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burgess told me the following story:–</p>
         <p>During the General Strike, his son, an undergraduate volunteered for work, &amp; was allotted a position as a stoker on an express.  He was much surprized to receive in due course a cheque for his wages amounting to £4:9:6.  The 9/6 he sent to his little sister at school.  Of the rest, he sent £1 to his father saying that, as his father had expended much on his education, he thought it only fair that he should have a share of his <hi rend="strikethrough">first</hi> own ^first^ earnings.  D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burgess, naturally touched by this proof of filial piety, placed the pound note in an envelope, sealed it up, &amp; deposited it in his safe endorsed – '<hi rend="underline">Part of his first earnings sent to me by my son Robert John Burgess</hi>".  Shortly after, the burglars broke in to his house, opened the safe, took his wife's jewels &amp;, about £200 in cash, threw about his documents, and opened the envelope but replaced the note, &amp; left it behind them.  May we not interpret this as an indication of the same kind of chivalrous sentiment in crime which adorned <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin Hood</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick Turpin</hi>?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Burgess</hi> obligingly lent his car to take us to the Cathedral for the morning service which consisted of Mattins up to the Benedictus, &amp; then the Holy Communion.  The sermon followed the Nicene Creed.  There was a considerable congregation, largely composed of men.  I preached from I. Cor. xv. Ii. "<hi rend="underline">Whether it be I or they, so we preach, &amp; so ye believed</hi>."  The sermon took exactly 22 minutes to deliver, which was not excessive.  After lunch I rested for an hour in order to save my voice, which cannot stand the strain of continual talking.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Burgess</hi>'s car carried us to the cathedral for the special service at 3.30 p.m. There was a large gathering of doctors, medical students, &amp; nurses, but the place was not crowded. I preached from Acts xx.35. "<hi rend="underline">In all things I gave you an example, how that so labouring, ye ought to help the weak, &amp; to remember the words of the Lord Jesus, how he Himself said. It is more blessed to give than to receive</hi>." I preached for exactly 30 minutes by the pulpit clock. Rather to my surprize the verger handed me a cheque for three guineas.</p>
         <p>After tea I wrote to William, sending him good wishes for his birthday on November 26<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. He is as old as the century – 28 – surely the very prime of life.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Armstrong College branch of the Student Christian Movement takes itself very seriously. With reprehensible rashness, I promised some weeks ago to address it next Tuesday. My directions are thus given:–</p>
         <p>"My committee has been discussing this meeting during the last few days, &amp; we are agreed that it should attempt 1) to show the importance of religion &amp; its relevance to life; and 2) indicate how trifling are our own intellectual difficulties compared with the moral &amp; spiritual challenges that Christianity presents. As some of us pointed out, it may pass the wit of man to treat these themes adequately in one address: nevertheless we should be glad if your lordship could keep these two ideas in mind."</p>
         <p>Here is indeed a generous programme: but it lacks in precision what it gains in generosity.</p>
         <p>Religion has its roots in certain facts which confront men, &amp; which, as men advance in civilization, require explanation. These facts suggest 3 questions, the answering of which is the purpose &amp; the test of religion.</p>
       
            <p>1. What is the source &amp; the significance of life?<br />
           2. What is the explanation of moral conflict?<br />
            3. What is the meaning &amp; importance of Death?</p>
       
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>[symbol] <hi rend="italic">Divers people came to supper, &amp; among them the well–known editor of the Manchester Guardian, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">C. P. Scott</hi><hi rend="italic">.  He sate by me, and we conversed freely.  He said that there was no reasonable prospect of the Labour Party coming into power for at least 20 years: that the Liberal party would act as a determining factor, &amp; would be strong enough to restrain Labour from its worst blunders.  He himself desired a Labour Government maintained by the Liberals on terms.  He was very positive that none of the parties would touch </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Disestablishment</hi><hi rend="italic">.  We spoke of the condition of America, &amp; I was rather surprised to find him heartily endorsing my unfavourable opinion.  He had read </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Judge Lindsay</hi><hi rend="italic">'s books, &amp; was properly horrified by their disclosure of American morals.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Bishop of Middleton, <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Parsons</hi>, is a heavy man with a self–consequential manner &amp; an abhorrent reek of stale tobacco.  His wife is a doctor, but not in any settled employment.  They are said to keep no servant, &amp; she acts as her husband's chauffeur.  Archdeacon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Aspinall</hi>, a hideous little man with an amiable expression, was also present, but I got no speech with him.  </p>
         <p>The weather all day has been pleasant, though with an autumnal touch in sight &amp; feeling.</p>
         
        </body></text></TEI>
