<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]                                                        </hi>
            
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left 21 Park Lane after breakfast, &amp; after leaving my bags at the Athenaeum went onto the Church House, &amp; spent the morning in attending the Assembly. The Cathedrals measure was the subject of debate. Cuthbert Turner made a characteristic speech against the measure &amp; was applauded. The quaintness of his appearance &amp; his well&#8211;established reputation for learning added zest to his speech. I lunched at the Westminster Deanery, &amp; then returned to the Assembly. Then I went to the Club &amp; had tea. After which I drove to King's Cross, and took train for Darlington, where Lionel met me with the car, &amp; drove me to the Castle through heavy rain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Among my letters awaiting my return was one from Kenneth written in a careless contented tone, which indicates but too clearly that he has little understanding of his position. He has a rude awakening for, if (as seems probable) he has to leave Oxford, &amp; return to the old familiar places in which for the last 18 months he has strutted with the pride &amp; consequence of academic character, he will experience the mortal chill of a humiliation hard to bear.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
