<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[139]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"This wonderful book is one of the few books which may be read over repeatedly at different time, &amp; each time with a new &amp; different pleasure. I read it once as a theologian &#8211; &amp; let me assure you, that there is great theological acumen in the work – once with devotional feelings &#8211; &amp; once as a poet. I could not have believed beforehand that Calvinism could be painted in such exquisitely delightful colours."</p>
         <p>v. S. T.Coleridge 'Table Talk'. P.89</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"I know of no book, the Bible excepted as above all comparison, which I, according to <hi rend="underline">my</hi> judgment &amp; enforcing the whole saving truth according to the mind that was in Christ Jesus, as the 'Pilgrim's Progress'.  It is, in my conviction, incomparably the best <hi rend="underline">summa theologice evangelicos</hi> ever produced by a writer not miraculously inspired."</p>
         <p>v. Note by Coleridge in his copy of the P.P.</p>
         <p>Yet M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Noyes</hi> writes of the Pilgrim's Progress:&#8211; "It displays not a single gleam of original thought or insight into the spiritual world"  It is said that this critic has recently joined the Roman Church.</p>
         
          <p>
	 	<hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
	 	         </p>
	 	         <p>
	 	<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
	 	         </p>
	 	         <p>Lionel and I motored to Stanley, by Crook, where I instituted the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Robert Tindal</hi>, lately assistant curate of Monkwearmouth, to the vicarage of that parish (Stanley). There was a very large congregation which included a considerable number of young miners. There is no doubt about the response which the people would make to the appeal of Religion if only we had competent clergy in adequate numbers. The shadow of unemployment lies heavily on Stanley, as on so many other pit parishes.</p>
	 	         <p>[symbol]</p>
	 	         <p>
	 	<hi rend="italic">The papers report the voting at the "Synods" of London &amp; Liverpool.  Both voted </hi><hi rend="italic underline">against</hi><hi rend="italic"> the episcopal proposals with decision!  In both the bishops were themselves largely responsible for the decision.  None the less, the action of the clergy is an untoward event, which cannot but have unfortunate consequences.  It may not improbably affect the voting in the other "synods", &amp; it has gone far to make the Bishops look ridiculous.  For the Bishop of London, in view of his speech, the decisive vote contrary to his wishes must needs be an extreme humiliation.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
