<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The morning post brought the ill news that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fuller</hi>, Vicar of Norton was gravely ill with double pneumonia, and this was followed in the evening by a telegram saying that he had died.  This removes yet another of the abler incumbents.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Morris</hi>, the vicar of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Oswald's Durham, informs that he has accepted a transfer to the South &amp; will be leaving the diocese immediately.  Then I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hunter</hi>, the Rector of Ryton, telling him frankly that the state of his health made it his duty to resign the benefice.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Countess of Carlisle</hi><hi rend="italic"> and M</hi><hi rend="i superscript">r</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Duff Cooper</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to lunch.  Also Sybil, Lady Eden &amp; Latimer.  Whilst the ladies were at the sale in the Town Hall, I walked round the Park with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Duff Cooper</hi><hi rend="italic"> whom I found both interesting &amp; intelligent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Nicholson</hi>, the assistant curate of Ryton, came to see me. I gave him permission to continue officiating in that parish until the end of the year.</p>
         <p>The weather today has been tempestuous &amp; raining, altogether as comfortless as possible. I started after dinner to read 'Pilgrim's Progress' again, in order that I might be the better qualified for appraising the denunciatory abuse of Mr. Alfred Noyes in 'The Bookman'.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
