<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[154]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Sunday was filled with various experiences.  First, I attended the University Service in S. Mary's, and heard a sermon from a youngish&#8211;looking parson.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Brooke</hi><hi rend="italic">, Chaplain of Lincoln. He preached a fair but nowise remarkable discourse from the Words of Christ. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Except ye be converted, &amp; become as little children, ye cannon enter into the Kingdom of Heaven</hi><hi rend="italic">". After emphasizing our Lord's "break&#8211;away" from the current religious system, &amp; His insistence on religious simplicity, he affirmed that in these respects He was the norm of religious reformers, instancing S. Francis &amp; Luther. Then he made the inevitable reference to the alienation of modern youth from Religion, &amp; the controversy over the Revision of P.B, connecting them as effect ad cause. This I thought was rather "cheap", for if the P.B. needed revision, it had to be revised; and the controversy was as unavoidable as it is regrettable. Modern alienation from religion has deeper roots.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi rend="italic"> pursued me into the Coffee Room in order to give me his County Council Cheque, &amp; we walked for half an hour.  Then </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mary Radford</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; my god&#8211;son fetched me in their car, &amp; carried me to 4 Marston Ferry Road, stopping on the way to show me the Dragon (Lynam's) School </hi><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi><hi> [symbol] </hi><hi rend="italic">where John is now 'Head of School'. I lunched with the Radford Family, who accompanied me as far as New College, where I called at the Warden's House to see Lady Lawrence who is staying there. I find Fisher entertaining a crowd of undergraduates. On our way through the Parks I stopped to inquire after Fletcher, who had been knocked down by a motor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">At 6.30 p.m. I preached in Quinn's College to about 90 undergraduates.  The sermon on 'Friendship' was substantially that which I preached to Winchester School a few months ago.  I dined in Queen's, sate between old Sayce and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Walker</hi><hi rend="italic">, the Vice&#8211;Provost.  Magrath, the Provost, still flourishes at the age of 90, &amp; declines all thought of resignation.  I had some interesting conversation with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Walker</hi><hi rend="italic">. Hunt, the papyrus&#8211;man, was there.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After dinner Berrisford, the Chaplain of Queen's College, took me round to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Wadham</hi><hi rend="italic">, where I addressed a considerable meeting of undergraduates in the interest of the Oxford House.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi><hi rend="italic"> presided, &amp; a rather lugubrious looking fellow named </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Wyndham Deedes</hi><hi rend="italic">,the Vice&#8211;President of the Oxford House followed me.  I did not speak well, but the men seemed to be interested.  Kenneth walked back with me to the College. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
