<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[116]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> came to see me, &amp; to say Goodbye before going to Oxford tomorrow.  We discussed his choice of subjects in the History School and this led on to the question of his future career.  He told me that he had been thinking over the matter, &amp; had reached the definite decision to be ordained, if that were possible.  I gave him the Loeb edition of '<hi rend="underline">S. Augustine's Confessions</hi>', and then we went into the chapel &amp; said prayers together. The hearts of young men are generous, but their purposes are unstable &amp; their wills infirm. May God accept and strengthen him!</p>
         <p>The rain which fell with relentless persistence, hindered the walk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> which I had intended, but, after his departure, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> &amp; I walked for more than an hour.  Then I wrote letters.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charnwoods</hi> arrived before dinner, having motored from Edinburgh.  They 'filled the horizon' to the exclusion of everything.  There can be no doubt that visitors are a woeful interruption to work, and so much for the actual time that has to be devoted to them as for the atmosphere of fidgety unrest which they create.  One's mind to work is dissipated.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
