<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]                                                        </hi>
           
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The ethics of breaking engagements is a subject of some difficulty into the discussion of which many considerations of varying importance enter.  One's own preference is, perhaps, both the strongest and the least respectable of these.  The quantity and quality of the inconvenience, or annoyance or genuine disappointment inflicted on others are certainly considerable.  Nor may one omit altogether the impression creditable or the reverse which may be conveyed, for one's own character &amp; reputation are not negligible.  Tonight I promised to dine with 'The VII' in the Liverpool Street Hotel — a dull company &amp; an odious dinner in a remote &amp; unattractive place.  Lady S. tells me that she has a pleasant party (including </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi><hi> whom I much want to see) originally convened on the supposition that I was 'dining in'.  My own blunder in dates is the sole reason why this programme may not be carried out.  Is there not here sufficient reason for my sending a telegram to cancel my promise, which was not </hi><hi rend="underline">wholly</hi><hi> unconditional, to dine with 'the VII'?  The casuistry which leads to the conclusion that one may do what one wants to do is always suspicious, but generally convincing!  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[172]</hi>
           
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a very disconcerting letter from the Warden of Wadham.  It appears evident that Kenneth's career in Oxford is destined to end ignobly in complete failure.  Through failure to get through his examinations he is likely to forfeit his County Council Scholarship, and even to be 'sent down' for good.  Then comes this decisive verdict: &#8211; </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"He is not, I think, devoid of brain, but is weak in character, and a foolish person…… I am afraid also that we must face the possibility of his failing to get through Pass Mods this Xmas, with the result that he will have to go altogether."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This is a sharp disappointment: and creates a situation of considerable perplexity.  Of course Kenneth was very young, and, I suppose, his head was turned by the life of Oxford.  He has a certain facility in writing, &amp; his scholarship seemed to authorize expectations.  But evidently it is 'cruel kindness' to encourage him to seek a degree in Oxford.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[173]                                                       </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I decided to 'throw over' the dinner with 'The VII', and to "dine in" with mine hostess.  The most part of the day was spent in the Assembly, where I made a short and fatuous speech about the resignation of ancient incumbents.  I lunched with Vincent Baddely in the Travellers' Club, and then walked to Westminster with the Marquees of Bath.  In the afternoon I interviewed an Ordination Candidate named William Ward, the son of a Salvation Army Officer.  I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow in the Athenaeum, and then talked with Justice Sankey &amp; Sir L. Dibdin.  There was another interesting dinner&#8211;party viz: &#8211; </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>General &amp; Lady Braithwaite, Sir Henry Hadow, Lady Gainford, Lady Gerald Wellesley, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> ______ (he is on the staff of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>, and she is a daughter of Buckle).  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Lady Gainford &amp; her husband were at S. Mary's, Oxford, on Sunday morning, &amp; of course, raved about the sermon to my extreme humiliation. I do think that these ardent women, who pay you gross compliments in the presence of other people, are really detestable!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The heat today has been great.  I nearly fainted on reaching my room this afternoon. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
