<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A chilly and shadowed morning, with intermittent gleams of sunshine. The change of clocks was made last night, and we all had an extra hour in bed. This carries the melancholy assurance that summer has gone, and that the gloom of winter is near at hand. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We were only 6 communicants including John.</p>
         <p>When, accompanied by Kenneth, I motored to Gateshead in order to preached [sic] in S. Chad's on the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> anniversary of the church's consecration, the weather had becomes wet and blustering.  The "high Mass' was less lawless than I had feared, for the entire service as appointed in the Prayer book was used, &amp; the 'extras' did not include incense.  But there were no communicants, a circumstance to which I called attention afterwards.  There was a considerable congregation which listened to my sermon very attentively.  After the service we returned to Auckland for lunch.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Headlam, Archdeacon Cornwall, Leshè[?], Olaf, and William. Also, I sent to Olaf a copy of "The book and the Vote", &amp; my 'Reflections on the Crisis'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then I went through the miserable collection of documents, which constitutes the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">dossier</hi><hi rend="italic"> of N.H. whose clerical career would appear to have now been finally arrested.  It was as I feared.  He was carrying on his abominable activities in Brandon with, as his lay assistant, that wretched theological student, S.A., whom I had to refuse for Ordination.  Both these men were prominent in work with Boy Scouts, work which provided them with a sphere in which to pursue their filthy aims.  It is easy now to explain the uncomfortable impression which I always received when I went to that parish for Confirmation.   The numerous choir boys were so ill–ordered, impudent and familiar that it was plain enough that they held the clergy in no respect.  It is heart–breaking to reflect on what must be gossiped about in that parish.  The truth is that we are so pressed to find voluntary workers with Scouts &amp; C.L.B. that we take anybody who offers, without any adequate securities for good character.  The fact that men volunteer for work with boys </hi><hi rend="italic underline">may</hi><hi rend="italic"> be evidence of an unwholesome tendency, if not even of an unclean habit!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
