<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the sermon for S. Mary's, Oxford. It was mainly a re&#8211;hash of old material!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the afternoon we (i.e. Ella, Fearne, &amp; I) motored to Durham, &amp; attended a meeting at the Deanery, gathered to hear </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Meston</hi><hi rend="italic"> discourse on India.  It was an interesting &amp; most informing speech.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I asked him afterwards whether he did himself think that there was much chance of our experiment in India ultimately proving successful. He replied in the negative</hi><hi>. After having tea in the Deanery, I called on Dawson Walked, &amp; suggested that he should exchange his Professor&#8211;canonry for the canonry &amp; Archdeaconry which Derry's death vacated. He asked for time to consider. Then I went to Knight, &amp; talked with him for an hour. At 6.15 p.m. I joined Lionel, &amp; we motored to Esh, picking up Cecil Ferens on the way. There I instituted the new Vicar, Newport, a youngish man. The little church was crowded, &amp; I think the people were impressed. After service, I was introduced to the Vicar's wife, a pretty young woman with 2 small children. We returned to Auckland, were Caröe had arrived in order to make a survey of the Castle with a view to Dilapidation.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
