<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A very unpleasant day, and very wet.  </p>
         <p>I wrote a number of letters, paid many bills, and then prepared notes for the Bristol speech. After lunch I walked in the Park with Lionel, and got wet enough, in spite of a mackintosh, to have to change when I got back to the Castle.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Fuller</hi> wrote to say that his mother was ill with pneumonia, &amp; likely to follow her husband to the grave.  This is a tragic happening.</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>' has a brief report of my short speech to the Diocesan Conference, noting that I "avoided reference to the Prayer Book controversy". The '<hi rend="italic">Yorkshire Post</hi>' gives rather more of what I said, including the lines by which I rendered the grotesque Latin proverb about the relations of clergy and laity.  There was a leading article on <hi rend="underline">Synods</hi> in the same paper, which perhaps indicates an intention in some quarters to start an agitation for the "restoration" of these doubtful and little&#8211;known assemblies.  The silly project of a '<hi rend="underline">constitutional episcopate</hi>' robs Presbyterianism of its independence, &amp; episcopacy of its authority, making the worst of both systems.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
