<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
             
         </p>
         <p>The notion that I would adopt as the title of my 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Charge, the motto of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, '<hi rend="underline">Nec tamen consumebatur</hi>" [nothing however will be achieved].    </p>
         <p>We left Carlton&#8211;on&#8211;Trent at 11 a.m., &amp; motored to Auckland Castle by way of Doncaster, Boroughbridge (where we lunched at 'The Three Arrows'), Catterick &amp; Piercebridge arriving at 3.30 p.m. Then I fell to work on the letters, which contained little of interest &amp; nothing of importance.</p>
         <p>That queer crank, the "<hi rend="underline">Communist Catholick</hi>", whom I first learned of from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rashdall</hi>, writes to me in terms of warm approval of my Congress sermon. He claims me as an ally, though unconfessed, of "Copec".</p>
         <p>"While regretting that you adhere to a somewhat critical attitude towards COPEC, I cannot but feel that you are contributing powerfully, along independent lines, towards the creation of such a spirit and outlook as COPEC (at any rate , as I understand its principles and objects) is concerned to strive for.  I think, therefore, that the adherents of that movement &amp; of such bodies as The League of the Kingdom of God, may well recognise in your Lordship – at least as regards the main fundamentals – a <hi rend="underline">de facto</hi>, if unacknowledged, ally."</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
