<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Today Davidson leaves Lambeth in order that Lang may enter. The tradition of Scottish canniness and servility is to continue. No principle is to be too boldly asserted: &amp; no interest too rashly challenged. The "opportunism" that postpones issues, &amp; clutches at chances has to handle the gravest situation that has faced the Church of England since the Restoration.</hi>
            
<hi rend="doubleunderline">R.J Campbell</hi><hi> writes about the new Primate in the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi><hi>', crediting him with high courage, &amp; a large wisdom.  But the evidences of both lie in the future.  The policy of seeking genuine autonomy within the Establishment – which I suppose to be </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi>'s – will serve well enough to dispense with any immediate steps to "</hi><hi rend="underline">vindicate the inherent spiritual authority</hi><hi>" of the Church, but cannot possibly be regarded as a practicable policy. Autonomy could not consist with the Crown nomination of Bishops, nor with the final appellant jurisdiction, nor with the supremacy of Parliament. It could only mean Disestablishment without Disendowment: and that is a policy which commands acceptance in no quarter of the political world. I cannot regard it as sincerely contemplated by so intelligent a Primate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Oxford at 10.8 a.m., and travelled to Paddington in company with the Bishop of Oxford.  I drove to the Athenaeum, and then went to the hairdresser.  After lunching at the Club, I proceeded to Westminster for the meeting of the Assembly.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi> presided in the capacity (as he was careful to explain) of Vice–Chairman, and moved a resolution of gratitude and affection to to his predecessor, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi>.  This was seconded by the Chairmen of the Houses of Clergy and Laity, the Dean of Westminster and the Earl of Selborne, &amp;, of course, carried unanimously.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Selborne</hi><hi> has grown a beard, &amp; is scarcely recognizable.  Then we fell to a boring discussion of a Measure for improving the method by which parsonage houses may be sold.  I came away while the House was still sitting, and then I walked to the Athenaeum, where I had tea &amp; talked to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry Newbolt</hi><hi>.  After this I went to Park Lane, &amp; found Ella with Lady S.  She was presumably embarked on the desperate venture of persuading that rather elusive lady to undertake something for the Durham Castle Fund. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[symbol] </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Scarbrough</hi><hi> expressed great disgust at Inge's treatment of his Bishop: and, indeed, I think it is really indefensible.  After all, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> owes to his Bishop whatever deference is implied in 'canonical obedience'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined in Park Lane. It was a very interesting party viz: M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Baldwin, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Neville Chamberlain,<persName xml:id="4164"></persName> Lady Nunbarnholme, Lord Hardinge, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Rochfort Maguire, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi>Tanner.  Conversation was animated, discursive, and well–sustained.  Lady N. repeated to me the statement about the ill state of Oxford morals, which, on the authority of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi><hi>, I had contradicted to the Bishop of Blomfontein.  She was very positive about it in spite of my protest.  I wonder what the source of this rumour really is.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rochfort Maguire</hi><hi> was very insistent on the scandal of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi>'s money–making.  </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead</hi><hi> had assured her that he (the Dean) was making £</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">8000</hi><hi> a year: but how his Lordship should know this is not easy to understand.  I was surprised to hear how general was the disapprobation of the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Tribute</hi><hi>" collected for the outgoing Archbishop.  How hollow is Society!  Under the masque of superlative eulogy, tongues wag freely enough in depreciation, and calumny follows hot–foot on adulation!  </hi> 
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
