<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Their Majesties' Visit&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella, Lionel, and I left the Castle at 9.15 a.m., and motored to Benwell Tower, where I robed, &amp; then proceeded in the Bishop's car to the new bridge.  Ella and Lionel came also: he attended me as my chaplain.  Immense multitudes crowded all the approaches to the bridge, &amp; we could only proceed at a snail's pace.  The weather, which had been very unpropitious, cleared in good time, &amp; the royal Carriage drove up in brilliant sunshine.  There was a great gathering of notables, &amp; many were presented to their Majesties.  <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Then the Bishop of Newcastle read a prayer, &amp; I pronounced the Benediction.</hi>  The Lord Mayor then requested the king to declare the bridge open.  His Majesty read his reply with emphasis, &amp; in a loud voice.  Then he inspected the guard of honour.  The Queen talked to me about the Castle.  After this their Majesties resumed their carriage, &amp; went on to Gateshead.  We (i.e. the Bishop of Newcastle, Ella, Lionel &amp; I) returned to Benwell Tower.  Their [sic] we separated, the Bishop &amp; I going to the Assembly Hall for the luncheon, Ella &amp; Lionel going to the <hi rend="bold">[115] </hi>Station Hotel. The Luncheon was o formidable business. Some 300 guests were entertained by the Lord Mayor of Newcastle, and the Mayor of Gateshead. We began at 1.45 p.m. and ended at 4.45 p.m. The speeches were many &amp; (some of them) lengthy. I proposed 'The two Counties', and coupled with it the names of the two Lords Lieutenant, the Duke of Northumberland and the marquis of Londonderry, both of whom replied very felicitously. Then 'the bridge' was proposed by Sir George Lunn in a speech of 'cataractic eloquence'. He is a prominent local preacher, &amp; a born orator. The lunch ended, I rejoined Ella &amp; Lionel. We motored back to Auckland Castle, stopping at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Edmund's Vicarage for tea on the way.</p>
         <p>The attitude of the crowd at Newcastle interested me. It indicated rather friendly interest than fervid loyalty. A handfull [sic] of Communists is said to have attempted to make a disturbance, but I saw nothing of them: &amp; the general spectacle was magnificent and harmonious. There is, perhaps, a belief that the visit of the sovereign will assist a return of prosperity to the district, &amp; this belief, equally baseless &amp; strongly rooted in the popular mind, does unquestionably enter into such a demonstration of 'loyalty'.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
