<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]                                                        </hi>
            
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A letter of considerable interest appears in the Times under the heading 'Church and State' over the signature of Adolf Keller, 19 Rue de Candolle, Geneva. Of the author I know nothing but, as the letter is printed in large type, I assume that he is a person of some authority: He writes:–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>'The Prayer–book situation is developing into a general European discussion of the relationship between Church and State, as is shown in a series of articles in Sir Henry Lunn's Review of the Churches and in the Continental Press.  Not only is a great medieval problem like a ghost coming thus back again, but the whole continent of Europe is taking a keen interest in the situation.  The problem of Church and State is of a paramount importance in every continental country to–day, even where disestablishment is accepted, as in Germany or in France, where the Government feels just now compelled to seek a 'readjustment' of the former solution reached in 1905.  In other Continental countries this question has become acute with the conclusion of many concordats between the State of the Roman </hi><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi><hi> Church.  It is, therefore, really one of the great issues of the Church in Europe in her effort to adjust herself to modern life.'</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the Bunyan sermon, &amp; wrote to the Dean of Westminster in answer to an inquiry from him, suggesting that a congruous hymn to follow it would be "When I survey the wondrous cross".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lionel &amp; I walked round the Park together, &amp; then wrote letters until it was time for me to dress for dinner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ella &amp; I motored to Durham, &amp; dined in the Castle with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice &amp; Lady Roche</hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="5462"></persName>.  The High Sheriff &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi>Forster, Bayley &amp; his wife, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi>Cowan, Miss Roche &amp; Richardson the Marshall made up the party.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The evening paper announces the sudden death of Lady Grey of Falloden</hi><hi>. This is truly a tragic happening. Grey's blindness was a heavy blow, this bereavement will be overwhelming. There is no public man for whose personal sorrows more people will feel a genuine concern.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gwilliam</hi><hi> the Vicar of Heworth died yesterday.  He was not a wise man, but, in his own fussy and tactless fashion, he laboured at his vocation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Loney</hi><hi>, of St. James's, Stockton, writes to offer his resignation.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
