<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the day in Cheltenham attending the Congress. There was some apprehension about the evening session, as it was thought not improbable that the Anglo–Catholicks might make some kind of a protest against Major: but everything passed off quite harmoniously.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Streeter</hi> spoke very persuasively on 'Modernism', and was deservedly much applauded.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Selwyn</hi>, speaking for the Anglo–Catholicks, definitely "threw over" <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halifax</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chavasse</hi>, the exponent of 'the Evangelical Movement', was aggressive in manner, truculent in tone, and badly controversial in substance. Indeed, the Bishop felt it necessary to interpose the singing of the '<hi rend="underline">Veni Creator</hi>' between his speech and the next.  Yet this utterance was loudly applauded by the audience.  </p>
         <p>Of the evening speakers on 'The Anglican Interpretation of the Christian Faith' <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Quick</hi> was the best, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Goudge</hi> the worst: <hi rend="doubleunderline">Major</hi> was meek as Moses and mild as milk rather to the disappointment of a Congress which had come to the Hall with hope of a fray.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nairne</hi> was saintly &amp; irrelevant.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
