<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]                                                                                                            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I believe the superstition of our Bishops (if they have any) is more towards </hi><hi rend="italic underline">New Moons</hi><hi rend="italic"> than </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Sabbaths</hi><hi rend="italic">. By new moons, I mean new Ministers of State, who, like those, receive their borrowed lustre, from our civil suns; and, like these, have of late been as changeable. I think they deserve a stroke of your animadversion.̶</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A Presbyterian is only the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">caput mortuum</hi><hi rend="italic"> of an old Puritan Methodist, which is not less rancorous for being less fiery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">As to the Alliance you speak of between the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Cloak</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Rocket</hi><hi rend="italic">, it is not like mine, between </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">State</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">which is an alliance of Truth and Utility, this is of utility alone, and which is likely to outwit the other, I cannot tell</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop Warburton to D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Stukeley.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Aug. 13. 1763 (v. Nichols Literary Anecdote. Xi. 58.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He would be a very bold man who ventured to defend the present Establishment of the Church of England as "an alliance of Truth and Humility [sic]".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Durham, and licensed two clergy in the Castle, as well as instituted Thompson to the vicarage of Heatherycleugh, and P.Y. Knight to an honorary Canonry. Then I lunched with Wilson in the County Club, and afterwards had an interview with that grotesque blend of imbecility and conceit, Glynne, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Cuthbert's Durham.  He complains bitterly of his treatment at the hands of certain members of his Parochial Church Council.  They seem to have criticized somewhat sharply his finances.  I told him that he ought to have nothing to do with parochial finance.  When he had gone, I had interviews with two youths, now students at S</hi><hi rend="superscript">t. </hi><hi>John's College, &amp; approved them for grants from the Clergy Training Board.    Then I discussed matters with my suffragan.  At 4.30 p.m. I received in my rooms at the Castle a deputation from Holy Trinity, Stockton, which desired to inform me as to the needs of that parish, to which I must send a new Vicar.  I gave them tea, &amp; then discussed the matter with them.  We motored to Firtree (Howden&#8211;le&#8211;Wear), where I instituted the Rev. E.E. Pearson to the incumbency.  There was a crowded, &amp; very attentive congregation. </hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
