<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A woeful day, wet &amp; comfortless. Lionel and I motored to Edmundbyers, a little parish far up on the moors with less than 300 inhabitants, where Dolphin has reigned for the last 14 years. There, in pitiless rain, I consecrated an addition to the churchyard, improvising the service, as through some blunder, no printed forms had been provided. In spite of the rain a considerable body of the parishioners had collected, &amp; the service in the Church, when I delivered an address from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's words "<hi rend="underline">Glorify God, therefore in your body</hi>", was not unimpressive. We had tea in the adapted Barn which, having let his rectory house, Dolphin inhabits, &amp; then returned through the rain to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Arthur H Godfree &amp; Co. Ltd. 3 Adelphi Terrace, Strand, ordering a supply of port wine.  The last supply appears to have been paid for on Jan. 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1928.</p>
         <p>Earl &amp; Countess Grey arrived in their motor about 6 p.m. and were soon followed by Canon Partridge. Sybil, Lady Eden, joined us at dinner.</p>
         <p>Before going to bed Grey &amp; D. Partridge talked with me at length on ecclesiastical matters. It appears that the number of men ordained last year was 8 fewer than the year before.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
