<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928, Manchester.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore</hi><hi rend="italic"> sent me his congress sermon, now published under the title '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Danger and Duties</hi><hi rend="italic">'. It is a characteristic composition, with which I found myself in so much agreement that I wrote a civil acknowledgement. It is the compromising associations of his "Catholick" past that make Gore's most liberal–sounding declarations so unsatisfactory. He and I have some obvious points of resemblance. The Anglo–Catholicks regard him much as the modernists regard me. To the one &amp; to the other we are 'lost leaders'! Both of us are handicapped by our previous history: neither of us wholly merited the confidence which our former supporters placed in us, for we were both too large for any party connexion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This is the 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> anniversary of my marriage.  The psalm which we read in chapel was very appropriate – the 103<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, and as we left the chapel the landscape was spanned by a glorious rainbow.</p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, &amp; took train for Manchester. I left at 1.7 p.m., changed at York, and arrived at the Victoria Station in Manchester at 4.40 p.m. Canon Scott was on the platform to receive me.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Scott</hi> and his wife are growing to be very old.  Their contributions to conversation are explained &amp; excused by the fact.  <hi rend="bold underline">They both express an extreme fear of Disestablishment, &amp; evidently regard me with </hi><hi rend="b strikethrough underline">extreme</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> ^deep^ suspicion</hi>! I suppose that for the majority of church people the cause of the Church and the maintenance of the Establishment mean precisely the same thing. To require them to draw a distinction between them, &amp; even to contemplate them as conceivably opposed, is to make a greater demand than they can satisfy. Ella is quite representative in this respect.</p>
         <p>There was a pleasant dinner–party of doctors &amp; academicks. As usual I could not remember who was who: but I did distinguish the Vice–Chancellor of the University, Moberly [Moberley],<persName xml:id="5456"></persName> and a notable surgeon named Burgess. With both of these I had some agreeable conversation. Burgess had been travelling in Germany recently with Grey Turner, who operated on me in Newcastle. We talked about the problem of education, and I was gratified at finding myself in agreement with Moberly on the point of getting rid of the 'Dual System' as soon as possible. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Moberly also was a pleasant person, but we were nearing conflict on the matter ^of^ co–education when we parted!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
