<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant day after yesterday's rain.  I spent the morning in a vain attempt to write a sermon for the college service on All Souls Day.  In the afternoon I went to <hi rend="underline">Haughton–le–Skerne</hi>, &amp; there consecrated an addition to the churchyard.  After the service, I looked at the parish church, which, though "restored" out of all recognition, contains some interesting featurs [sic] e.g. two Jocobean pulpits (of which one serves as a lectern) some Anglo–Saxon stones built into the porch &amp; wall +c.  Then I had tea in the Rectory, a large rambling house, of which the larger part was built by Joseph Butler, when he was Rector for 4 years.  There is a large garden, &amp; some glebe.  We returned to Auckland Castle, but only to leave it again at 5.45 p.m. in order to go to <hi rend="underline">Herrington</hi>, picking up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi> in Durham on the way.  There I instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">P. D. Bailey</hi><persName xml:id="5587"></persName> to the perpetual curacy.  He appears to be pleased with his new parish, &amp; evidently very glad to have got away from Heatherycleugh.  After service we returned to Auckland Castle, dropping the Rural Dean at Houghton–le–Spring, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi> at Durham.  On arriving we learned that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi> &amp; his wife had arrived.  The prospect of quiet &amp; work grows fainter every day!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
