<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Diocesan Conference</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most dismal, damp, depressing day.  I spent the morning in preparing a brief Presidential Address for the Conference, which met in the Chapter House of Durham Cathedral at 2.15 p.m.  There was a large attendance.   <hi rend="doubleunderline">Earl Grey</hi> spoke on the financial needs of the church, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Partridge</hi> on the Education of the Electorate.  The first was mortally dull: the last voluble but rather absurd.  Both, however, were listened to with exemplary patience, &amp; decorously applauded when they sate down  Nobody either made speeches or asked questions, &amp; the proceedings were over before 4 p.m.  <hi rend="italic">Some slight commotion was occasioned as the members were dispersing, by the fainting of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><hi rend="italic">, a large man invested in a Jesuitical cloak, who had been sitting by a radiator! He was not seriously ill, &amp; himself came to the car when I stopped on my way home to inquire of his condition.</hi>  Then we (i.e. the Greys, Partridge, Pemberton, Lionel, Ella and I) went to the Castle &amp; had tea in my room.  Then we returned to Auckland &amp; the Greys to Howick.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
