<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Beyond walking in the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi>, writing letters, and bestowing some final touches on the Address to the P.C.C.s, I have done nothing today.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Braley</hi> and his wife came to lunch.  That garrulous creature, Knight of Ryhope came to tea, &amp; to see the portrait.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">R. Graves</hi>'s Autobiography has already been sold to the extent of 40,000 copies.  It is not a good book, either from the point of literature or from that of morality.  It may represent the mind of the post&#8211;war generation.  The author was a born Bohemian, and could not have been normal in any age, but in such an age as this he was bound to "out&#8211;Herod Herod" in his revolt against convention.  Probably, he is regarded with envy &amp; admiration by the youth just in their twenties.  I infer from the fact that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> sent it to me for a Birthday present that <hi rend="underline">he</hi> thinks it magnificent.  It strengthens the ill disposition bred in the foolish youngling's mind by "Simon called Peter" which he said expressed his feelings completely.  It is an ill look&#8211;out for him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
