<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It has suddenly dawned on me that I am pledged to address the <hi rend="underline">Rotarians</hi> at South Shields tomorrow.  The choice of a subject is not easy, for it must be both <hi rend="underline">interesting</hi> and <hi rend="underline">non&#8211;controversial</hi>, and these are hardly compatible qualities. Most interesting subjects are also controversial, indeed the keenest of the controversy is a measure of the intensity of the interest. To be '<hi rend="underline">safe</hi>' is surely also to be '<hi rend="underline">dull</hi>', and all our wisest advisers bid us '<hi rend="underline">live dangerously'</hi>. To do that can hardly mean anything else than to live in the thick of controversy. Recently the '<hi rend="underline">Times'</hi> has had a correspondence on "<hi rend="underline">sneak&#8211;guests</hi>", &amp; I might, perhaps, take that as my text.  It would naturally enough lead on to a discussion of the legitimacy of privately recording the <hi rend="underline">obiter dicta</hi> of great men, which one hears in private company.  The whole question of keeping a private journal would be raised, and the further question, which has become acute since the war, of the rightness of <hi rend="underline">publishing</hi> conversations which have never been checked by one of the parties concerned in them.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> went with me to Durham, where she took train for Sunderland, and I betook myself to the Castle.  There I collated to their honorary canonries both <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi>, admitted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brain</hi> to the chapelry in his parish, &amp; gave <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ainsworth </hi>of S. John's College a general licence.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> &amp; I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed more than 100 persons in S. Luke's Church.  The sexes were about equally represented.  I had no reason to complain of the inattention of the candidates, but it is not a pleasing church, &amp; the parson is a dull, listless fellow, whose natural defects are emphasized by his domestic troubles.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> includes in its page of photographs one of my portrait.  It is not large enough or distinct enough to be impressive.  I shall be much interested by the comments and criticisms which it will evoke, if it should appear in the Academy's Exhibition next year.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
