<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A tremendous tempest of wind and rain was raging when morning broke, and continued with varying measures of violence throughout the day rising into its original virulence at nightfall.</p>
         <p>I prepared notes for a speech on '<hi rend="underline">The Sneak&#8211;guest</hi>' and then motored to South Shields, and I fired it off in the Royal Hotel to a company of about 90 Rotarians.  They received it with enthusiasm, &amp; were, I trust, as much edified as I was bored! Then I went on to Newcastle, and was dealt with by the hair dresser.  After having tea in the Railway Hotel, I proceeded to the Rectory at Gateshead, where I had interviews with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ross </hi>and the young layman who aspires to be ordained next year. Then we had an early dinner, from which we rose in order to attend the Collation of the new Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert's, Bensham (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sharpe</hi>). This was a disappointing, even a depressing service. The congregation was meagre, &amp; consisted largely of 'Boys' Scouts'! There was an air of lifelessness and listlessness over everything, which suggested that the outgoing Vicar had been anything but energetic. After the service, we motored back to Auckland Castle in a tempest.</p>
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
