<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[15]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Southwark</hi> writes to me:&#8211; </p>
         <p>"I am very interested in what you say about your visits to your Parochial Church Councillors.  Your impressions of the councillors would be true of the poorer parishes in this diocese, though there are much stronger members on the Councils in the suburbs and in the few country parishes we have.  As far as Anglo&#8211;Catholicism is concerned, as a rule they reflect the opinions of the Incumbent, <hi rend="underline">who succeeds after a time in inducing his critics to resign</hi>."</p>
         <p>I received a letter from the Editorial Secretary of S.P.C.K. saying that the Committee "hope they may have the pleasure of publishing your lordship's address on Church and State," and adding that 'naturally they wish to see the MS. before making a final offer.'</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson </hi>and I motored to Darlington, where I addressed the P.C.C.'s of that Rural Deanery. The Rural Dean (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Cosgrove</hi>) presided.  There were about 90 present, which he thought satisfactory, &amp; I thought poor.  They listened closely, but without enthusiasm, and, as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> conjectured, without agreement.  The questions were nowise important or illuminating.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
