<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright, mild morning, cheating the birds into the belief that spring, not winter, is at hand! When I went over to S. Anne's at 8 a.m., they were singing hilariously, &amp; some hallucinated rooks were starting a nest! I celebrated the Holy Communion. The communicants included Ella, Alexander, and John.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, sending him (£10) for the purchase of a wedding present.  Also, to Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi>, sending him the extract from the Act of 1836 which constitutes the King 'Count Palatine of Durham', &amp; leaves the Bishop of Durham nakedly &amp; conventionally episcopal!</p>
         <p>Having finished Milman's account of the destruction of the Order of the Temple, I proceeded to read through the very careful and critical version of the facts given by <hi rend="doubleunderline">H. C. Lea</hi> in his History of the Inquisition.  Both agree that the proceedings were an abominable travesty of justice, &amp; that, on the evidence, the Templars must be acquitted.  I remember hearing Bishop Stubbs express the opinion that the Suppression of the Templars was "<hi rend="underline">the blackest crime of the Middle Ages</hi>".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[19]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Macdonell</hi> includes the trials of the Templars in his "<hi rend="underline">Historic Trials</hi>", and decides emphatically for their innocence.  His is a particularly weighty judgment.  "I have examined the original documents: I have come to their perusal with no preconceived opinion: and I have tried to look at the long–standing controversy chiefly from the point of view of a lawyer, applying the ordinary canons of evidence".  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Döllinger </hi>appears to have taken the same view as Milman, Lea, Stubbs, &amp; Macdonell. "<hi rend="underline">If</hi>", he wrote, "<hi rend="underline">I were to name one day in the whole extent of world–history which appears to me to be in very truth dies nefasto, I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d.</hi><hi rend="underline"> name no other than the 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> October 1307</hi>".  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonell</hi> comments: "A strong statement, but one for the truth of which much may be urged".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> motored with me to Felling, where I dedicated a vestry–door, and confirmed 98 persons in the parish Church.  There was a large congregation, &amp; a service which was both "hearty" and sincere.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Belts</hi>, the present Vicar has only held office for 9 months, and the church has been transformed. He is young, capable, determined, and ambitious. I think he is also sincerely religious. If the newspapers will leave him alone, he may do some really good work in that squalid parish.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
