<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Eve, Tuesday December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The last day of the year begins in the calm brightness of a perfect winter's morning.  My morning was occupied in writing letters, official and personal.  After lunch I walked round the Park with the doctor: and then I dressed, and went with Ella to Wynyard to spend the last hours of this bad 'Old Year' <hi rend="sub">̭</hi>in<hi rend="sub">̭</hi> that gay &amp; hospitable society.</p>
         <p>We picked up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sibyl, Lady Eden</hi>, at Windlestone, and so made our way to Wynyard.  The party was smaller and less important than in former years, but it was none the less very pleasant.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Zetland</hi> with her children was there, and, of course, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Hedworth Williamson</hi>.  I had much and interesting talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Neal Chaplin</hi>, mine host's nephew and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Maureen</hi>, who is prettier and more charming than ever.  Chaplin has just returned from New York after more than two years stay in America.  He is a stock–broker, and traversed the crisis of the recent collapse.  He gave me a striking description of the confusion and misery.  There were 11 suicides in two days.  He said that <hi rend="underline">some well–known clergyman were conspicuous among the gambling speculators</hi>! He had been in Paris, and heard the shopkeepers there lament the cancelling of orders from their American customers ruined by the crisis.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Maureen</hi> was in a "good" phase, &amp; talked demurely of religion and morals in the character of the distracted xx<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century <hi rend="underline">illuminé</hi> who has out–passed the 'stuffy' rigidities of the pre–war epoch, &amp; now faces a world of chaos with nothing in heaven to direct, nor on earth to trust.  I promised to stay with her &amp; Oliver, &amp; 'talk it out'.  One of the difficulties in discussing ultimate things with people like <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maureen</hi> is that they have no knowledge of elementary Christian beliefs.  A peasant's child from an elementary (church) school would be better equipped for facing the world.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi> is a curious blend of piety and worldliness, &amp; I sometimes wonder which is the category in which she must finally be placed.  The little play, in the afternoon was a rather squalid production, picturing a night–club, not at all worthy of such a house.  Later, she talked with me in quite an edifying way of the necessity, now becoming apparent in English Society, for Christians definitely asserting their principles against the oppugnant [sic] fashion of current life.  She illustrates a phase of English life which is extraordinarily &amp; pathetically interesting.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1929</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The year marked the passing away of several persons who have entered with varying degrees of intimacy into my life.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Marshall</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">James Parker Smith</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir George Craik</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowlden</hi> – all have gone, and left voids in my familiar <hi rend="underline">entourage</hi>, which cannot be filled.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Begbie</hi>'s death removed a man who did some injury to my reputation, &amp; did so in circumstances which were uncommonly discreditable to him. In appointing <hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip Baker–Wilbraham</hi> to be my Chancellor in succession to <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Vernon Smith</hi> I indulged a personal friendship as well as gained a valuable colleague.  Another, &amp; not less important appointment is, perhaps, more open to hostile criticism.  In choosing <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> to succeed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derry</hi>, as Canon of Durham &amp; Archdeacon of Auckland, I brought a pronounced Anglo–Catholick of the '<hi rend="underline">modernist</hi>' type into the diocese, &amp; into a position of great influence therein. By this appointment I did certainly open the door to some formidable possibilities. Would the new Archdeacon 'hit it off' with his colleague, the Bishop of Jarrow? Would he be loyal to the Diocesan? Would he make himself the centre of an Anglo–Catholick propaganda?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is certainly too soon to answer these questions confidently, but the year's experience justifies the hope that the total influence of Archdeacon<hi rend="doubleunderline"> Rawlinson</hi> will be favourable to the moral and mental life of the Diocese.  He has certainly disclosed a great desire to make himself serviceable: he has great gifts: and is gaining much influence.  The least satisfactory element in the situation is the evident lack of mutual understanding between the two Archdeacons.  This may lead to considerable mischief: but we will hope for the best.</p>
         <p>The carrying out of the very extensive "<hi rend="underline">dilapidations</hi>" has caused considerable unrest in our domestic arrangements.  We went abroad for the greater part of April in order to leave the workmen free to carry out their work inside the Castle, but they were still working in the Chapel when the year closed.  The <hi rend="underline">Ecclesiastical Commissioners</hi> consented to accept responsibility for the Chapel and Boundary Wall of the Bowling Green, a circumstance of no small importance in view of the expenditure, which exceeded £<hi rend="doubleunderline">3000</hi> on these two items alone, apart from my own dilapidations on the Castle itself.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The sermons preached in Liverpool Cathedral (July 21) S. Mary's Cathedral, Edinburgh, (October 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) and in Magdalen College Chapel, Cambridge (November 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) had rather a special interest.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> my 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Quadrennial Charge was published under the title</hi> '<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>'. In a lengthy Introduction I offered some kind of Apology for my change of view on the question of Establishment. The book was sent to all the clergy of the diocese, &amp; to the diocesan bishops. It was reviewed extensively, &amp; for the most part, sympathetically: but its sale was meagre, &amp; its apparent effect insignificant. An address which I gave to a church Institute at Nottingham on October 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> was rather conspicuously reported in the '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>': <hi rend="bold underline">and later I made a tour of the Rural Deaneries in my diocese addressing the parochial church councillors on the Relations of Church &amp; State</hi>. In the September issue of "<hi rend="underline">The Nineteenth Century – &amp; After</hi>' I had an article written in answer to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Boys– Smith</hi>, &amp; entitled '<hi rend="underline">The Value of Church Establishment for Religion – a Rejoinder'</hi>.  Thus my association with the abhorred policy of 'Disestablishment' was rendered closer &amp; more apparent with the result that I grew ever more <hi rend="bold">[52]</hi> odious to the general body of church–people.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The General Election had the result of placing a Labour Government in office</hi>. It is already apparent that their extravagant expenditure will necessitate large additions to already excessive taxation. This is a circumstance of ominous import for the Church of England for the pressure of financial need is already the most degrading factor in ecclesiastical life, &amp; increased taxation will make that pressure still more severe.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The death and resignation of the older incumbents and the preferment of the abler assistant–curates to benefices in other dioceses are telling disastrously on the efficiency of Durham diocese.  There is no improvement yet apparent in the matter of candidates for Ordination.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The painting of my portrait by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Speed </hi><hi rend="italic">gave a touch of finality to my episcopate. There remains nothing now but for me to recede into history like my predecessors, &amp; leave the stage clear for another Bishop. I never was so conscious before of having reached the end of my possibilities, and being classed &amp; done with!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
