<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I revised yet again my address to the P.C.C.s, which I shall ultimately print as a pamphlet. It will at least answer sufficiently the tract "<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>" which the Bishop of Norwich has issued, and in which (no doubt deliberately) he avoids all reference to me.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I walked round the Park, and, later, motored to Newcastle, where I addressed the P.C.C.'s from the Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street Deanery.  The heavy rain must have kept many from coming, but there were more present than I expected.  They listened attentively, but the questions were not very relevant or intelligent.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella </hi>had requisitioned the car to take her party to the Ball at Witton Castle.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson </hi>of Burnopfield motored us to Durham station where we had appointed a taxi to meet us. We were back at Auckland about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hon. Mrs. Ruthven</hi>, whom I prepared for Confirmation as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Angela Manners</hi>, together with her twin sister came to tea.  Her husband has succeeded <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stobart </hi>in command of the D.L.I.  They have rented Whorlton Hall from <hi rend="underline">Headlam.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
