<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><!101229>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Baker&#8211;Wilbraham</hi> went away after breakfast.  I wrote a number of letters, &amp; then did some more work on the Address to the P.C.C.s.  After lunch I walked round the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and the dogs.</p>
         <p>We motored to Consett, where I addressed the P.C.C.s of that Deanery.  There was a good attendance, and the uRral Dean, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Myers</hi>, presided.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Priestman</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parr</hi> of Medomsley, respectively moved and seconded a vote of thanks.  There was only one, and that a fatuous question, but the attendance was close and sustained.  I was assured that everybody was interested.</p>
         <p>Three impressions are made on me by these gatherings<hi rend="italic">:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>1.  <hi rend="italic underline">The poor social quality of the P.C.C.s in the diocese</hi><hi rend="italic">. "Not many mighty, not many noble" are called to office in this diocese, &amp; I suspect the same holds for the whole country.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>2<hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Their total ignorance of all that Establishment has meant and does mean</hi><hi rend="italic">. The whole subject is unfamiliar and bewildering to them.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>3. <hi rend="italic underline">Their dread and dislike of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism</hi><hi rend="italic">". They have not been reconciled to it by all the missioning of recent years. No doubt the agitation against the Revised Prayer Book has not been without effect, but this hatred of 'Anglo&#8211;Catholicism' is an older sentiment.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
