<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Witton Castle Ball</hi> party returned about 4 a.m., and (with one exception) were all down to breakfast!  I spent the morning in revising the address, which I design to have published.  After lunch <hi rend="underline">Pattinson </hi>and I motored to Eastgate where (in spite of the weather) about 120 parochial C. Councillors from the Stanhope Rural Deanery had assembled in the little parish church.  Old Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Croudace</hi>, the Rural Dean, appeared.  I donned my robes, &amp; used the desk set out for me at the Chancel step.  My address occupied about an hour in delivery, &amp; was listened to with close attention.  As we were in Church, I did not invite questions, but said a prayer, &amp; pronounced the Benediction.  We went back to Auckland immediately, declining an invitation to tea in the schoolroom.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shebbeare</hi> was there, feeling no doubt profoundly dissentient, and with him was his curate, the amiable but feeble Collier.</p>
         <p>The Editorial Secretary of the S.P.C.K. writes to say that he has no doubt that the Literature Committee will agree with himself in welcoming the idea of S.P.C.K.'s publishing such a pamphlet as my address will constitute, and promising to write again when the Committee has held its meeting next week. I should be glad if they published the poor thing.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
