<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[34]</hi> [sic]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The post brings shoals of Christmas cards, but, happily, not much else.  I spent the morning in writing letters, &amp; sending out copies of the little futile book of mutilated sermons, published by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Stockwell</hi>.  It is at least sufficient for Festival purposes!  In the afternoon I visited 2 sick parsons – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harlow</hi>, the Vicar of S. Paul's, Stockton, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">West</hi>, the Rector of Easington.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Vincent Harlow</hi><hi rend="italic"> was at home.  He gave me a very unfavourable report of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi rend="italic">, which agrees with ominous closeness with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Mary's</hi><hi rend="italic"> ill account.  It is evident enough that he is idling his time, and that the prospect of his taking a degree is very small.  Nor is it easy to resist the impression that he talks falsely &amp; absurdly.  Thus he had told </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Harlow</hi><hi rend="italic"> that he proposed to spend his vacation in Paris, which would seem unlikely enough.  I suspect that he has a habit of 'gasconading'.  After hearing Harlow's account, I ceased to regret the severity of my language about him, when talking to his mother last night.  The only chance of bringing him to common sense is to make him see that we will not endure is folly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
