<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went across to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion.  There were about 50 communicants, among whom were <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Elland</hi>, and John. The morning was mild and windless, but the sky was heavily clouded.</p>
         <p>I wrote to George Nimmins, and then read in Lippmann's "A Preface to Morals" – a book which I find to be in no common measure suggestive and interesting. Ella and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Speed having returned from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's, they with speed &amp; myself walked in the Park for an hour before lunch.  They day had developed well, &amp; nothing could have been more agreeable.  The Park looked at it's winter's best, leafless but with the bright colouring of fallen leaves, and the sun shining fitfully through naked branches.</p>
         <p>We all motored to Seaham Harbour, and had tea with the Dillons. The subscribers to the cost of the bells which were to be dedicated were there, including Lord &amp; Lady Londonderry, &amp; the room was uncomfortably full. We went on to the parish church, where I dedicated the bells, &amp; preached the sermon. Lord Londonderry read the lessons. The church was filled to overflowing. Many could not gain admission. After the service we all returned to Auckland Castle.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
