<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Thomas's Day, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>
                  <p rend="Normal" style="text–align: left; text–align: left;">
<hi rend="bold">Candidates for Deacon's Orders</hi>
                  </p>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>1.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>Reginald Dru Drury, St. Chad's. L.Th. Age 29.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>2.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>William James. Literate, age 33</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>3.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>Joseph McManners. Literate, age 37</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>4.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>Cyprian Marr. B.A. (Camb.) Westcott House. Age 23</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>5.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>Percy William Slater. B.A. (Dur.) S. John's. Age 23</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>6.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>John Frederick Shreeve. B.A. (Dur.) S. Chad's. Age 33</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>
                  <p rend="Normal" style="text–align: left; text–align: left;">
<hi rend="bold">Candidates for Priest's Orders</hi>
                  </p>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>7.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>Herbert Frank Bishop, Oxford &amp; Cuddesdon</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>8.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>James William Samuel Capron. Oxford &amp; Cuddesdon</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>9.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi rend="bold underline">John Mabey Carr</hi><hi>. Durham Westcott House</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>10.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi>George Lamb. Durham &amp; S. Chad's</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>11.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi rend="bold underline">William Aubrey Monsell Pike</hi><hi>. Cambridge &amp; Cuddesdon</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>
<hi>12.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi rend="bold underline">Allan Marat Ross</hi><hi>. London B.A.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>The deacons were inferior – socially, academically, and personally – to the priests. My hope of a succession of Cuddesdon men through the goodwill of the Principal has been dashed by the Principal's preferment to the Bishoprick of Wakefield. That diocese now receives the candidates who would otherwise have come to Durham. The outlook cannot yet be said to be brightening.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was more snow during the night.  I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m.  All the candidates communicated.  <hi rend="underline">By the chaplain's error, the candles were not lighted, a circumstance which distressed me because I know the extreme sensitiveness of our pious youth on these matters</hi>, &amp; was sorry that they should be, even in a small thing, "offended". The gravity of the pettiest incidents at times of tense emotion cannot wisely be ignored by the man who has to deal with this irrational and irresponsible amalgam of instincts &amp; tendencies which we call 'human nature' Nor do we commonly appreciate the hold over us which little things acquire by virtue of their associations. The lighted candles on the Altar of the Eucharist have a mysterious significance for the devout "Anglo–Catholick", which the pachydermatous Protestant can neither understand nor appreciate. He cannot imagine why candles should be lighted save as an aid to his eyes; the other wants them for the comfort of his spirit. Explanation is altogether impracticable, for the two men are moving, thinking, feeling on different planes. "<hi rend="underline">The natural man understandeth not the things of the spirit; they are foolishness unto him</hi>".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Gordon's two addresses to the candidates were excellent, alike in what they said and in what they suggested. I watched the men, and could see they were deeply impressed.</p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and afterwards presided over the legal business in the Chapter House. After this we all had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight: &amp; then attended meetings of the Barrington and Lightfoot Funds</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson Walker</hi> came to dinner, &amp; helped in the reading.  Bigg's Lectures on the English Reformation were sufficiently luminous to provoke audible guffaws from the candidates! </p>
         <p>I noticed that all the candidates for Priesthood abstain from meat, except <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carr</hi> who is not an Anglo–Catholick: and some of the others are doing the same.  I confess to surprise at seeing Ross among the rigorists.  He is certainly in a state of spiritually, unstable equilibrium, &amp; I doubt whether the Church of England will be his final home.  He has been bred a Nonconformist : he became a Unitarian: he is now a restless Anglican: there remains yet one more stage!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I delivered my "Charge" at [Compline].  It was, I fear, as unhelpful as it certainly was 'unspiritual', and yet, I think it may be serviceable in retrospect, for I had taken pains to make my points clearly, and they were points that ought to be remembered.  After the service I heard C's confession, and afterwards had some talk with him about his plans.  His mind seems quite definitely set on going abroad as a C. M. S. missionary.  He had been in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lasbrey's</hi> parish, and is eager to go out to Africa &amp; work under him in his Nigerian diocese.  I cannot condemn what is plainly a disinterested spiritual ambition, but I cannot but lament the drift away from this distressed diocese.  There is something very disheartening about the knowledge that the men, whom one ordains, are already meditating departure.  The link between Bishop and Clergy grows thinner.  Nine tenths of what has been said to them at Ordination has been irrelevant, for we assume that the men, whom we ordain, will find their career in England &amp; probably in the diocese: and we speak to them on that assumption: meanwhile, their thoughts and purposes are pointing altogether in another direction.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
