<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">THE ORDINATION.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Most Merciful Saviour.  Who art the Good Shepherd and, of Thy boundless compassion, hast willed to call us to feed Thy sheep, look with mercy upon us at this time, and pardon all our transgressions.  Apart from Thee we can do nothing.  Be with us as we receive the yoke of Thy Service: sustain us under its weight, &amp; strengthen us for its burden.  Thou knowest all the past with its sins &amp; failures: all the present with its hopes &amp; fears: all the future with its risks and chances.  Lord, Thou knowest all things, Thou knowest that we love Thee.  Make Thyself known to us this day as we give, and receive the Commission to be Thy Servants.  Give us the comfort of Thy presence, and nevermore forsake us.  <hi rend="underline">Show Thou us the way that we should walk in for we lift up our hearts unto Thee. Lord, we believe, help Thou our unbelief.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[33]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Only 4 of the 12 candidates came to breakfast, and they ate the slenderest of meals. It is the energetic propaganda of these Cuddesdon men which is creating a conscience in these matters. "<hi rend="underline">Touch not, taste not, handle not, which all are to perish with the using</hi>". If only there were a conscience with respect to "<hi rend="underline">the greater matters of the law</hi>"! It is a sense of proportion which is lacking in the English clergy.</p>
         <p>The Ordination was carried through without any unfortunate incident.  There was a considerable congregation, which, in view of snow and slush, was noteworthy.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gordon</hi> preached a remarkably good sermon, which was listened to very closely.  Save for the ill reckoning of the number of communicants, which caused [me] to consecrate much more Bread and Wine than was necessary, the service seemed to me edifying and impressive.  I entertained candidates &amp; their friends to lunch in the Castle and then we (i.e. Ella, Fearne, Canon &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gordon and I) returned to the Castle at Auckland.  I rested myself until tea&#8211;time, and, after tea, took <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gordon</hi> to my study, and had much talk with him.  He is a good fellow, and intelligent.  Certainly his addresses and sermon were much above the average.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
