<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and I motored to Durham, &amp; attended the convocation of the University.   The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duke of Northumberland </hi>presided as Chancellor.   Hon. doctorates were bestowed on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Trevelyan</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir W. Marris</hi>, the new principal of Armstrong College.  After the function I showed the library to the Duke &amp; Duchess of N.  Then his Grace entertained a company in the Common Room of the Castle.  I sate beside the Duchess, &amp; had much talk with her, &amp; also with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir W. Marris</hi>, who sate on my other side. I had to come away early in order to motor to Barnard Castle where the P.P.C.'s of that Rural Deanery had been convened. This was, in number present, the smallest gathering I have yet addressed. It was also the least sympathetic, a fact attributable to the exertions of the Vicar of Barnard Castle (Bircham), who made himself very offensive, &amp; actually distributed copies of a letter which appeared in the local press, a fortnight ago, entitled "<hi rend="underline">The Bishop of Durham &amp; Church &amp; State</hi>".  After the meeting, one of my hearers expressed to me disgust &amp; regret at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bircham</hi>'s rudeness. I think it is probably true that I am more definitely disliked in that part of the diocese than elsewhere.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
