<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Is there going to be a "crisis" over 'modernism' in the Church of England?  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> has exasperated his 'Anglo&#8211;Catholicks' so deeply that they are in the mood for 'reprisals', i.e. they incline to raise the cry of 'the Faith in danger'.  The Papists, vigilant to 'buy up the opportunity' are doing what they can to fan the flame of Anglican dissensions. Besides these sectarianly interested minorities there is the "religious world", which is showing evidences of real spiritual distress.  The '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Modern Churchmen</hi><hi rend="italic">' are so persistent in their attacks on the orthodox tradition, so scornful and aggressive that a considerable resentment is growing in the public mind. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Fundamentalism</hi><hi rend="italic">" and "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">No Popery</hi><hi rend="italic">" are frenzies latent in Protestant English folk which, once quickened into activity, may be both violent and intractable.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> has hitherto averted Fundamentalist opposition by making himself the darling of the "No Popery" fanaticks: but when his 'Anglo&#8211;Catholick' victims turn on him with an open denunciation of his religious opinions, even his Protestant following begins to fall away.  The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" publishes an effective letter </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">by the Papist litterateur, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Alfred Noyes</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic"> headed '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Christian Tenets. Belief with Mental Reservations</hi><hi rend="italic">' in which he attacks </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> very fiercely.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Noyes</hi> is the man who wrote an atrocious attack on <hi rend="underline">Bunyan</hi> in the Bookman: &amp;, therefore, he carries little weight: but he has a 'pretty pen', and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi> provides a tempting morsel to a competent controversialist.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi> sent me her photograph, and a clever satire: "<hi rend="underline">The Young Person's Complete Guide to Crime</hi>" by <hi rend="doubleunderline">C. G. L. Du Cann</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&amp;#x00F6;e</hi> and his son <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alban</hi> arrived about lunch time, &amp; made a hurried inspection of the Chapel.  After lunch Leng drove them both to Darlington.  I gave him a photograph of the portrait.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park in spite of the weather which was wretched, deluges of rain &amp; driving gusts.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Sands</hi> thanking him for his book on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Scott</hi>'s mysterious love affair. He has bestowed an infinity of labour on a matter of trivial importance, which he leaves as obscure as he found it. But such literary trifling is a respectable and comparatively harmless mode of "killing" time after retirement from the active work of life: &amp; he is really to be congratulated on having mind &amp; will to fill his leisure thus.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
