<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The mild spring weather continues.</p>
         <p>Sir Frank Brown sent me &#x00A3;100 for the Ordination candidates' fund to be expended at my "sole discretion". Mrs. Sykes wrote to me gratefully about her husband, but I remain sceptical!</p>
         <p>I expended the morning very uselessly in trying to write an article for the XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century.</p>
         <p>Pattinson and I motored to South Moor, where I confirmed 69 candidates from the parishes of South Moor, Cragside, and Holmside. The church was filled with a congregation almost entirely composed of women. These parishes are almost entirely inhabited by miners, on whom the Church has little hold.</p>
         <p>I paid my Income Tax and Sur&#8211;Tax, <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;918:9:0</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Such notices as appear in the newspapers indicate that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Papists and Sectaries are perturbed by the prohibition of prayers for the Russian Church in the Army services</hi><hi rend="italic">, but they are reluctant to make a demonstration, partly, perhaps, because so many of both, especially of the Sectaries, are far more concerned with toadying "Labour" than with the distresses of the Russian Church, which the one hold to be schismatical [sic] and the other grossly superstitious.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
