<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. There were 8 communicants, including John.</p>
         <p>The weather continues to be wonderfully mild.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Ernest who, with characteristic lack of restraint, has thrown himself into the agitation on behalf of the persecuted Russian Christians, and to Brooke, on the ecclesiastical situation.  Also, I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Di Darling</hi>, &amp; sent her the pamphlet.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I walked round the Park. Lambs were disporting themselves there, &amp; birds singing. If one could exorcize the fear of winter's return, one could rejoice in the first fruits of spring.</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>' gives prominence to the fact that <hi rend="doubleunderline">President Masaryk</hi> has reached his 80<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year.  It publishes an excellent photograph, &amp; an extremely interesting biography.</p>
         <p>I read much of a very interesting book by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Louis Madelin</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">The Revolutionaries 1789[?]&#8211;1799</hi>".  It is full of acute and suggestive <hi rend="underline">obiter dicta</hi>, as well as of brilliant sketches of some leading figures of the Revolution. The tragical[sic] developments in Russia have send me back to that earlier tragedy in France, which has provided so many terrible precedents for the direction of the Russian criminals. The pupils have outpassed their masters!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
