<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very wet, unpleasant day.  I spent it mostly in writing a fatuous article for the <hi rend="underline">Church of England Newspaper</hi> on Church &amp; State, and in having interviews (i) with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bott</hi>, the Vicar of S. John's, Stockton, who wanted my approval of his plans for a new mission&#8211;room:  (ii) with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi>, who reported his interview with D. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi> respecting the vacant curacy in Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street  (iii) with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Battensby</hi>, a sturdy&#8211;looking young man, who desires to be ordained, &amp; hasn't got a penny for his training!</p>
         <p>Sargent, the chaplain of Barnard Castle School, whom I cannot even "put a face on", &amp; who has but recently been ordained, sends me a letter of good wishes on the anniversary of my consecration, 12 years ago. Now what could have led him to do this?</p>
         <p>The first number of "The York Quarterly" arrived. It is admirably printed, &amp; on good paper. The price – one shilling annually – appears preposterously little, especially as there are no advertisements. It contains 28 pages, &amp; provides much 'mixed feeding'. Nevertheless, I doubt if it is 'long for this world'. It hardly meets any apparent &amp; continuing need.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
