<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright, beautiful day, more May than March.</p>
         <p>There came to lunch M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi>, &amp; Miss Loxley from Coniscliffe, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dick from Annfield Plain, &amp; with them M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. Rumney, a non&#8211;Anglican minister who aspires to be ordained.   On the whole he impressed me well: but he has evidently but little knowledge of the doctrine &amp; discipline of the Church of England: he is 41: &amp; knows no Latin and Greek.  He served during the War as a stretcher&#8211;bearer: &amp; afterwards was trained at the Bible&#8211;Training Institute in Glasgow.  Then he served for 5 years in Nyasaland, in an undenominational Mission.</p>
         <p>Pattinson &amp; I motored to South Shields where I confirmed nearly 200 persons in S. Hilda's. The service went well enough, save for the coughing of the congregation which was insistent and incessant.</p>
         <p>Geoffrey Sykes wrote to tell me that his Father was worse, &amp; that, after consultation with the Doctor, he had come to the conclusion that he must resign his benefice. I am relieved that he has decided thus without my having to insist on resignation. But it is a melancholy &amp; unexpected ending of his ministry at Sedgefield.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
