<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[181]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet and thunderous day. The rain stopped for a few hours, &amp; then came on just in time to spoil the Football match between Durham and East Yorkshire. Superintendent Headon had asked me to attend, so I was in the Pavilion with the Chiefs of the County Police. Xan Wynne&#8211;Willson, who had come to lunch, was with me.</p>
         <p>I received letters from John &amp; his employer, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">le Fleming</hi> informing me that he had been allowed to withdraw his notice, &amp; was continuing his place.  I hope he will now settle down happily.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Xan</hi> accompanied <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and me when we motored to Cleadon for the Confirmation there at 7.30 p.m.   We dropped him at Bishop's wearmouth Rectory.  I confirmed 70 persons. The little church was densely crowded, many having to stand throughout the service.  Everything was pleasing to me, and, if I could trust my impression (which I certainly cannot) it was an impressive and edifying function.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Xan</hi>'s latest plan is to go at once to Lincoln Theological College. He will be 22 in June, so that he has rather more than a year before he could be ordained. Westcott House is too full to take him in.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
