<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very cold &amp; blustering day with snow on the hills.  I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Vaisey</hi>, dissenting from his opinion that that Disestablishment would <hi rend="underline">not</hi> bring to the Church any greater measure of liberty than it has now &amp; sending him my pamphlet on 'Church &amp; State'.</p>
         <p>I received an angry letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Priestman</hi>, and sent him a mild one in return.</p>
         <p>I finished reading Fisher's attack on Christian Science – "<hi rend="underline">Our new Religion</hi>" – and conceived the idea of taking as my subject for the Address to the Medical Students something suggested by Psycho&#8211;therapy viz. the irrationality of taking sharply specialized views of that human nature which is the subject&#8211;matter of the medical art. Something might, perhaps, be made out of this. Ignorance compels me to steer clear of anything specific; but this subject approaches near enough to my own "line of country" to justify my talking about it.</p>
         <p>Pattinson and I motored to Sunderland, and there I confirmed 90 persons in S. Barnabas Church. The new Vicar, Rhodes, an ex&#8211;curate of Hull, told me that he was shortly to be married! We got back to the Castle about 10 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
