<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Chichester (Bell)</hi> writes to me:–</p>
         <p>"I am deeply interested to hear of your promise to address the E.C.U. on July 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, &amp; I like your mode of preparation. I do indeed hope that the Archbishop is addressing himself to the formation of the Church and State Commission. But I see no signs of haste anywhere on this matter, &amp; I deeply regret the delay. I am entirely with you in wishing that the urgency of the matter were realized, &amp; that action were being taken swiftly."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi>, and I motored to Stockton where I officiated at the funeral of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simpson</hi>, the Vicar of Evenwood. He belonged to the district, &amp; had for some years been assistant curate of Holy Trinity. There was a large congregation in the church.</p>
         <p>We drove to Whitburn, where I baptized <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anne Rosemary Linnell</hi> in the little mission church, where her father ministers.  We had tea with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Linnells</hi>,<persName xml:id="5468"></persName> &amp; then went on to the Rectory, where, after an early dinner, we went to the church.  There I dedicated divers gifts presented by the family of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hopkinsons</hi> in memory of their father &amp; by the Rector &amp; his wife as a thank–offering.  After the service we returned to Auckland. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
