<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Gateshead, where I presided over a meeting of the <hi rend="underline">Preventive &amp; Rescue Association</hi> in the Town Hall.  There was a large attendance.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi> was the principal speaker, and acquitted herself very well.  She has a pleasant voice, a frank winning manner, &amp; a good presence.  The Mayor, a scrubby–looking Wesleyan, moved a vote of thanks to her: &amp; the deputy Mayor, did as much for me.  When the meeting was over, we all had tea with the Mayor in his official parlour.  Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> went to pay calls, &amp; I walked to the Rectory, and remained there until it was time for me to go to <hi rend="underline">S. Cuthbert's, Hebburn</hi>, for the Confirmation.  <hi rend="italic">I confirmed nearly 100 persons from the three parishes into which Hebburn is divided.  There was a crowded congregation.  I always feel that there is a genuinely religious spirit in this Church.  The Vicar, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Marr</hi><hi rend="italic">, is an Anglo–Catholick of a genuine spiritual type.  </hi>[inserted in margin: <hi rend="italic">Marr died in Aug: 1930, to my great regret.</hi>]  <hi rend="italic">We returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Simpson</hi> came to say, Goodbye.  He goes to his new employment tomorrow.  We said prayers, &amp; parted Christianly.  I think he is really sorry to go, but – and this is the abiding shadow on all relations with young persons – the relentless movement of the years makes a "move on" indispensable.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
