<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
            <seg>                   </seg> 
            <seg>   </seg>
            <seg>   </seg>  
            <seg>  </seg>
            <seg>  </seg>  
         </p>
         <p>Snow covers the country. A wintry scene.</p>
         <p>I worked all the morning at the Russian sermon.  It is not very easy to make these savages attractive, but it <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> hard on them that their inevitable medievalism should be inevitably judged by modern standards!</p>
         <p>I called on old <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullogh</hi>, and lent him <hi rend="doubleunderline">Maurois</hi>' '<hi rend="underline">Byron</hi>'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Jarrow Grange, where I confirmed 73 persons from two parishes viz.  Christ Church &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mark's.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wallace</hi>, the Rector of S. Mark's, observed <hi rend="bold underline">that there seemed to him more sickness among his parishioners than in former years, &amp; this he attributed to the depression caused by continuous unemployment.</hi>  Many men in his parish have been unemployed for 5 or 6 years.  There is no improbability in this view.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dobson</hi>, explaining the fewness of his male candidates, says that he found no organizations whatever for men &amp; boys in the parish, but very good ones for women &amp; girls. This throws an unpleasing light on his predecessor's performance of duty. I suspect that the females are much easier to "organize".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
