<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>March goes out like a lamb with a mild day.  Ella and I motored to Newcastle, where she visited the dentist, &amp; I had my hair cut.  We returned to the Castle for lunch, whereto came <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Porteus</hi>, who is an aspirant for the Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street assistant curacy.  He is a bland Anglo&#8211;Catholick, who hails from Mirfield, but was originally one of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Easby</hi>'s flock.  Also, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Watts</hi> lunched here, and afterwards walked round the Park with me.  He is an excellent &amp; loveable youth, who is full of a generous purpose to be medical missionary in Africa.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Gateshead, where I confirmed 130 persons in S. George's Church.  They came from the parishes of Lamesley, S Helen's, S Edmund's, &amp; S George's, and more than half of them were males.  I was pleased with their attention, &amp; reverent demeanours.</p>
         <p>I revised &amp; sent to Carter the material for the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> viz. an article headed '<hi rend="underline">Reflections</hi>', and the sermon on the Russian Persecution which was read for me in Newcastle Cathedral on 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March.</p>
         <p>I was chagrined by receiving letters from <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Simpson</hi> and his employer informing me that he had given notice to leave his situation, I wrote to both of them urging the one to make &amp; the other to accept a withdrawal of the notice.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
