<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi>, &amp; showed him some of my books. He strikes me as a lad of good ability, and, if he is also industrious and reasonably ambitious, he might go far. He went back to school in the afternoon, leaving a pleasant impression behind him.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, where I presided over the Religious Education Committee, where everything was very harmonious and very hollow.  Then I walked in the Banks with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi>. After having tea with the Bishop of Jarrow, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>[symbol]  <hi rend="italic bold underline">Lord Hugh Cecil has declared himself a thorough&#8211;going opponent of the South Indian Scheme of Reunion</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> This might have been expected, but, none the less, it arouses vehement resentment as if it were a strange discovery.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">That precious hybrid is likely to break up the Anglican Communion unless it can be hustled out of the way</hi><hi rend="italic">. The truth is that there are two churches gathered under the description 'the Church of England', and these are contrary the one to the other, so that neither can insist on its own principles without bringing the precarious combination to disaster!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
