<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A glorious day, mild &amp; brilliant with the sunshine. The birds deliriously domestical, &amp; singing exstatically.</p>
         <p>I received <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Watson</hi> at 10 a.m.: he told me that his grandfather was D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McCullagh's partner: that the father of the McCullagh's was the Wesleyan minister in Bishop Auckland: &amp; that he approved of his sons being confirmed &amp; becoming Anglicans. He (Colonel W.) thinks that Bircham will shortly resign the benefice of Barnard Castle. I wish I could believe it. I worked at the Edinburgh Sermon.</p>
         <p>There came to lunch the Rector of Penshaw, and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Battersby</hi>.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park, &amp; there fell in with a young man, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joseph William Alderson</hi> (3 Silver Street, B.A.) aged 20, who has just left the R.H.A.  He intends to join the Police Force.  I took him round the garden, and into the Chapel.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> John Anthony Hutton</hi>, the son of the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's, Gateshead, came to be inspected as an applicant for a diocesan grant for training.  He is now at Leatherhead, &amp; seems an ingenuous youth.  He aspires to go to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's College, Oxford.  I approved him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to S. Mary's, Tynedock, dropping young <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton</hi> at his father's vicarage on the way.  I had an interview first with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Garland</hi>, and then with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simmonds</hi>, shewing both of them the Bishop of Birmingham's letter to me, &amp; its enclosure.  Their explanations appeared to me quite satisfactory, and I promised to write to the Bishop &amp; suggest that he should address himself to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Garland</hi>. Then we motored to the Church of the Venerable Bede, where I confirmed 49 persons viz. 10 males &amp; 39 females. These came from the Parishes of the Ven: Bede (3 males 17 females), Monkwearmouth (4 males 10 females), S. Cuthbert's (3 males 2 females), and S. Columba's (6 females). The congregation brought my address to an abrupt conclusion by coughing: and after the service I called attention to the fewness of male candidates, and asked for some explanation. Of course none was forthcoming, &amp; there was some disposition to resent the suggestion that the real cause of the failure to secure male candidates lay in the idleness of the incumbents. So I went home in a rage.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
