<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[63]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I celebrate Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.   We motored into Durham for the morning service in the Cathedral, when I preached my "New Year" Sermon, reviewing the situation in Church and State.   There was but a meagre congregation.  The University is not in residence, and many of the regular congregation are absent on holiday.  Still it ought to have been larger.  As we passed the new golf links just outside the city, I noticed that there were many golfers at their sport.  After the service, I took a short walk in the Banks with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Eric Dawson–Walker</hi><hi rend="italic">, who is employed in teaching the students at the new Evangelical Seminary in the North of London.  We lunched with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dawson–Walkers</hi><hi rend="italic">, the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pembertons</hi><hi rend="italic"> who were also there, &amp; (staying in the house) the Vice–Principal of the said Seminary.  He told me that it was founded by one of the Baring clan as a thank–offering for the defeat of the Revised Prayer Book: that it was conducted on rigidly Fundamentalist lines: that there were 19 students ranging in age from 18 to 32; that these were mostly of a humble social type, but included </hi><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">two public school boys; that the effect of the Fundamentalist fanaticism of the Principal was so far wholesome that it provoked a vehement antagonism in the minds of the students; and generally that the future was not secure.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I inquired what books were used in this precious establishment, and was informed that recently £100 had been expended in the purchase of books.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Spurgeon</hi><hi rend="italic">'s sermons, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Walsh</hi><hi rend="italic">'s secret history of the Oxford Movement, &amp; "books" of that kind were being provided. This "college" would appear to be a citadel of the Protestant underworld; yet it is not without significance that its Vice–Principal &amp; one of its teaching staff should so frankly express their disgust of its distinctive principles. Obsolete fanaticism insincerely expounded has not an attractive appearance. After lunch we returned to Auckland. The weather which had been moderately fair had now definitely deteriorated. We motored homewards though wind and rain. Happily I had made no preaching engagement for the evening and remained in my study.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">Pray does Luther dream </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">His arguments convince by their own force.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">The crowds that own his doctrine?  No, indeed! </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">His plain denial of established points </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Ages had sanctioned and men approved.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Could never be oppugned while earth was under</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">And heaven above them – points which chance on time</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Affected not – did more than the array</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Of argument which followed.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Boldly deny</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There is much breath–stopping, hair–stiffening</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Awhile: then, amazed glances, mute awaiting</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The thunderbolt which does not come; and next,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Reproachful wonder and inquiry; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">those</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">Who else had never stirred, are able now </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">To find the rest out for themselves, perhaps</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">To outstrip him who set the whole at work,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">– As never will my wise class its Instructor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Browning</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Paracelsus</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i bold underline">This is what the Modernists are illustrating now. Their precious critical theories interest nobody, but their insolent challenge to established beliefs, and their open scorn of all sacred things are multiplying sceptics, &amp; overturning everything.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
