<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[233]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">April 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">The Spital Sermon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I had a bad night and got up feeling woefully inadequate to the burdens of the day. The spiritual distress caused by the West Hartlepool business following on a strenuous Sunday, formed an ill preparation for the physical exertion of an expedition to York yesterday. So I am quite at my weakest and worst!</p>
         <p>Pattinson and Derek accompanied me to Darlington where I caught the early train to London.  Happily I had a compartment to myself.  Arrived in London, I went to the Athenaeum &amp; there deposited my bags.  Then I went to the hairdresser, &amp; was made ready for my public functions.  The Spital Service in Christ Church, Newgate Street, was attended by a congregation which fairly filled the floor, leaving the vast galleries unoccupied.  The sermon was attended by the Lord Mayor &amp; the Corporation together with the Governors of the School.  An interesting visitor was the Burgomaster of Amsterdam, who had just flown over to London on a private visit to the Lord Mayor.  He sate under the pulpit.  I think my discourse was listened <hi rend="bold">[234] </hi>to with interest. Several persons thanked me for it afterwards. Ernest Pearce, who was in the Church, thought it was "over the heads" of the audience. Mr. Ryecroft, an Ordination candidate, came to see me in the Vestry of the Church. I said that, if he passed the G.O.S. and his character was sufficient, I would ordain him. Then after tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hine. Haycock, I went to Lambeth, which I found full of colonial Bishops.  I attended the Easter Banquet in the Mansion House, &amp; proposed the toast of the Royal Hospitals of London.</p>
         <p>My speech was dull, ill–delivered, &amp; not particularly well–received. But I am no good at that Kind of oratory. The Corps diplomatique was present, including the dubious knave from Russia! Dancing followed the Banquet, but I came away after writing my name in the Lord Mayor's book. I got back to Lambeth shortly after 10 p.m. and had a long talk with the Archbishop about the situation in Birmingham, the Church &amp; State Commission, the Lambeth Conference and this lamentable business in West Hartlepool.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>
