<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
            <seg>    </seg>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">an invitation to preach to the King at Windsor on the 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of April, and to the [sic] stay the weekend at the Castle</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  Is this an 'olive&#8211;branch' from a placable Sovereign? or, rather (and this <hi rend="underline">is</hi> more probable) just a friendly action of Lord Stamfordham?  </p>
         <p>Anyway, it dislocates my arrangement for the Confirmations, and involves a journey to London.  I <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to get a new suit of clothes, for I am fearfully shabby, but I shan't!</p>
         <p>I finished the Russian sermon, which is too long, too dull, too discursive, and too honest!!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to <hi rend="underline">Beamish</hi>, where I confirmed about 100 persons from the three parishes – Beamish, Tanfield, &amp; Burnopfield. The discrepancy of numbers between the sexes was painfully obvious, for there <hi rend="strikethrough">were</hi> 
<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>was<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> about one male to five females.  I called attention to this fact when, after the service, I talked with the clergy.  There really is no explanation that omits the failure of duty on their part.  As the women monopolize the church, the men cease to appear, &amp; the notion that religion is an affair of women and children roots itself in the general mind.  We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
