<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">The original drawing of Durham Castle, which was published in the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Times</hi><hi rend="bold">, &amp; which I had desired to purchase, has most courteously been presented to me by the authorities of the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Times.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Secretary of S P C K. </hi>writes on the obvious assumption that they are proceeding with the publication of my lecture on "<hi rend="underline">Church &amp; State in England.</hi>" He says it will make 48 pages of a 6<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> pamphlet.</p>
         <p>I decided to publish in the '<hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>' the lecture on the Palatinate which I delivered at Harrogate in the interest of the Preservation Fund. I prefaced it by a short article headed "<hi rend="underline">The Bishop's Portrait</hi>' in which I made some general observations on the 28 Bishops who have reigned since the Reformation. After lunch I motored into Durham, &amp; left the MS. at Carter's office together with a photograph of my portrait.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi> sends me a new Office Book sumptuously bound.  The affection of one's officials is an asset of real value in such a world as this.  It oils the wheels of the rather dilapidated machinery of administration.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I have received an invitation to preach &amp; speak in Edinburgh on the 42<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> anniversary of the <hi rend="underline">Wesleyan Methodist Mission</hi> in that city.  I have preached to Presbyterians and to Episcopalians in Edinburgh.  Is there any valid reason why I should refuse to preach to Wesleyan Methodists?  Is it, if not wrong in itself, expedient to do so?  The newspapers announce that the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Winchester</hi> has refused his sanction for a 'common communion' in his diocese; and the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Carlisle</hi> has withdrawn the provision for a Nonconformist to preach in a parish church.  Have these Bishops acted rightly, or expediently?  Ought the probable exasperation of the Anglo–Catholics with some denunciatory paragraphs in the <hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi> to operate as a permanent veto on all friendly dealings with Nonconformists?  Are the practical embarrassments which may grow from public association with Sectaries so formidable as to make it prudent to abstain therefrom?  Personally I find these Sectaries immensely trying, &amp; intercourse with them has no kind of attraction for me.  But there is a great principle at stake – <hi rend="underline">the essential solidarity of Christian Folk as against non–Christian Society</hi> – &amp; I hold myself bound to maintain it.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
