<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Bishoprick Article.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dalton</hi> our "Labour" member, came to lunch.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Eustace Hill</hi> and his wife with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Christopher</hi> and ourselves made up the party.  He was very agreeable, and talked on non&#8211;committal subjects very reasonably.  He assured me that the Labour party was nowise hostile to the Establishment, and contained many ardent churchmen.  I gave him my pamphlet on Church and State, and, said that I thought Disestablishment ought to be amicably arranged.</p>
         <p>Ella and I walked for an hour in the Park. The wind was surprisingly cold.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">The 'Nineteenth Century and After' arrived.  </hi>Harris has drawn on the College for no less than 3 articles: &#8211; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Amery</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prothero</hi>, and myself.</p>
         <p>My article '<hi rend="underline">Crossing the Rubicon</hi>?' follows <hi rend="doubleunderline">Amery</hi>'s '<hi rend="underline">The Crisis in the Unionist Party</hi>'.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prothero</hi> writes on '<hi rend="underline">Seventy years of English Corn&#8211;Growing</hi>'. So we are all true to type, &amp; none of us quite as demurely orthodox as would be desired! My article fills 9 pages, Amery's 13, and Prothero's 11. On the whole I incline to think that my article will be useful as reminding their Graces that they must really appoint their precious Commission!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
