<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"More than fifty years ago a Berwickshire minister preaching on Acts XVIII. 17. is reported to have said: " <hi rend="underline">And why did Gallio care for none of these things? Because he was so much taken up with his telescope that he had no interest left for anything else</hi>".</p>
         <p>[from a letter in the Observer. April 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1930)</p>
         <p>A very troubled and sleepless night. This miserable 'discipline' case haunts me. On the whole my mind inclines to my standing aside, &amp; letting the aggrieved parent prosecute. Then, on the basis of the verdict in the civil court, I could act as Bishop. If I myself prosecute in the Consistory Court, I should presumably save the guilty parson from imprisonment, but so far as the public scandal goes, nothing would have been lost for the public might fairly ask why there should be any distinction in such a case between a clergyman and a layman. After breakfast I motored to West Hartlepool and saw both Poole and Lilburn. Then the latter took me to see M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Young, the father of the lad concerned.  He is a feeble–looking man with <hi rend="bold">[230]</hi> a weak heart, and perforce workless.  Both he and his wife appeared to be simple &amp; religious folk, who were desperately distressed about their son, &amp; the possible consequences of the episode on his morals &amp; reputation.  I was at great pains to make clear to them that they were not to suppose that I desired to protect G. from the legal punishment due to his offence: but they finally resolved to 'leave the matter in my hands'.  My fear is that there may be other boys affected, and that much harm to the Church's influence will result.</p>
         <p>I returned to Auckland for lunch, and then went to Hamsterley, &amp; officiated at the funeral of the late Vicar, McGowan. There was a considerable gathering of clergy &amp; parishioners.</p>
         <p>G. came to see me, and we had a painful and perplexing interview. The case is enormously puzzling. Finally, I said that I would think over the whole matter in the light of all he had said, and would send him my final verdict in a fortnight. I shall try to get an opportunity of consulting the Archbishop.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek Elliott</hi> arrived about 6 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
