<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">WINDSOR CASTLE</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I noticed that the King sate down in the smoking room after dinner.  On my previous visits he always stood.  He spoke with great admiration of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smuts</hi>, whom he regards as the ablest ('the biggest brain') of living politicians.  Of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Amery</hi>, rather to my surprise, he spoke with something like dislike ("<hi rend="underline">as for little Amery, I've no use for him</hi>"). He allowed that he was zealous for the Empire, but he had no wisdom. His references to the present Government were interesting. He evidently dislikes "<hi rend="underline">Labour</hi>" but he spoke favourably of <hi rend="doubleunderline">MacDonald</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Snowden</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas</hi>. '("<hi rend="underline">They haven't shaken hands with that Russian fellow. I have to: but I didn't talk with him, beyond asking whether this was his first visit to England</hi>.")  His references to that "poor little man <hi rend="doubleunderline">Passfield"</hi>, amused me. He evidently thinks him a senile but amiable fumbler. ("<hi rend="underline">He told me that he was too old for his work, &amp; ought to be two men. I couldn't contradict him</hi>".) </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>He quoted the <hi rend="underline">mot</hi> of a French Wit, which is not new, that "After <hi rend="underline">the War there would be only five King's left in the World – the King of Clubs, the King of Hearts, the King of Spades, the King of Knaves, and the King of England</hi>".  I expressed the hope that he would not overtax his strength &amp; command on the formidable programme of work that lay in front of him this year.  This started him on the Imperial Conference, and generally on the shaping of the Empire which its resolutions were attempting.  He was wholly sceptical of its practical value, and emphasized the vital need of keeping our constitution in the future what it had been in the past – <hi rend="doubleunderline">unwritten</hi>. He said that he was going to tell the Conference as much. ("<hi rend="underline">I've been at this business longer than any of them. It will be 20 years since I became King: &amp; I know more than they do</hi>.")  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smuts</hi> had counselled him to talk separately with the Colonial representatives, but he himself doubted the wisdom of this course.  Of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Herzog</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cosgrave</hi> he spoke with something like aversion.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I was called at 7 a.m., and had comfortably ample time to dress, and get out to St. George's Windsor for Holy Communion at 8.30 a.m. The whole collegiate body – Dean &amp; 3 canons, for one canonry has been suppressed for the benefit of the fabric – were present, but two of the canons came in after the service had started. The Dean celebrated. There were 11 women and 4 laymen in the congregation. Including myself the clergy numbered 7. Is this representative of Anglican services?</p>
         <p>I breakfasted pleasantly with the household and had much talk with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> T.S. Dawkins and the rest.</p>
         <p>Both <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> &amp; the Dean had exhorted me to speak up, as the King is beginning to grow deaf: &amp; I followed their counsel.   I got the impression that everybody was interested and attentive, but, of course, such impressions are more often than not, misleading.  My text was Psalm 119.96.  "<hi rend="underline">I see that all things came to an end; but Thy Commandment is exceeding broad</hi>". We were out of the Chapel by 5 minutes after noon.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went for a short stroll with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> before lunch.  He asked me to recommend to him some clergy who could fitly be asked to preach to the King at Sandringham.  I promised to think it over, and send him some names.</p>
         <p>I lunched with the household at 1.15 p.m. We had much pleasant and vivacious conversation.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Deane</hi>, with whom I had some conversation. He is evidently a man of ability and ambition, whose foot is on the ladder of preferment, and who may go far.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[</hi>When the report that <hi rend="doubleunderline">M. Waddington</hi>, the French Ambassador had been assassinated was circulated, &amp; obtained some credence, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Beaconsfield</hi> was informed that there was no foundation for it.  "<hi rend="underline">I am very glad to hear it</hi>", was his reply, "<hi rend="underline">It would make assassination ridiculous</hi>"!</p>
         <p>When Lord B. lay a&#8211;dying, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Queen Victoria</hi> visited him.  A message was sent to inquire whether he could see her Majesty.  The Earl, in spite of his extreme weakness, ejaculated, "<hi rend="underline">Ah! A last message to Albert</hi>!" Who could but love the incorrigible old satirist? In fact he was greatly loved.<hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I called on old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Dalton</hi>. At 91 he is still mentally alert and physically active. But I gathered from his capitular colleagues that his faults &amp; foibles gather strength as he approaches his Century, and that he is very trying indeed!</p>
         <p>A small girl taken to see the Exhibition of Italian Masters, &amp; much bored by many Madonnas, at length broke out imprefsibly – "<hi rend="bold underline">O Mammy, when I grow up I won't be a Virgin!"</hi>  This was told to me by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Bertha Dawkins</hi>! </p>
         <p>I had tea with the Dean, who is a hearty pleasant fellow, but not conspicuously intelligent.  Then I attended Evensong in St. George's &amp; heard Dvorak's <hi rend="underline">" Blessed Jesu! Fount of Mercy</hi>", sung exquisitely by the choir. After the service I returned to my room, 335 York Tower.</p>
         <p>Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> came in, and talked for nearly an hour.  He strikes me as rather sad &amp; lonely.  He is past 80, and really very wonderful for so great an age.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I sate beside the Queen at dinner</hi>.  She was very friendly, &amp; expressed high approval for my sermon: which, however, the King could not easily hear.  I asked her whether she kept a Diary, &amp; she replied that she had done since 1890.  In the smoking room the King made me sit down again, &amp; I talked until bed&#8211;time.  My contribution to the conversation was very slight.  <hi rend="bold underline">He spoke of the Duke of Westminster's marriage with Miss Ponsonby</hi>: &amp; said that she w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be received at Court but not his Grace her husband.  His Majesty delivered his opinions on 'birth&#8211;control', and <hi rend="bold underline">professed a thorough&#8211;going advocacy of the method of sterilizing the unfit</hi>. He again spoke of his repugnance to receiving the Russian Ambassador, whose "wife", he understood, was a spy of the Cheka sent to keep her husband up to the mark. In saying, goodnight, the King thanked me for my "excellent sermon": and the Queen was very gracious. Their Majesties are certainly capital hosts. After they had departed, I came away to my room on the whole well&#8211;content that the day was over, &amp; so far as I know, without any "disaster"!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
