<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Lady <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wrightson </hi>with her son <hi rend="doubleunderline">John</hi>, and two friends came to lunch: and, after their departure, Ella and I motored into Durham, where we parted, I going to the Castle for business, &amp; she going to pay calls. The Archdeacons joined me in my room in the Castle, and we discharged divers matters of diocesan business. Then the deputation from Roker, Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Logan</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hope</hi>, arrived, and, after tea, we discussed the situation inthat parish. Then I rejoined the car, &amp; returned home with Ella, who had picked up Fearne &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Thorpe.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I finished reading Archbishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">D'Arcy's</hi> little book "<hi rend="underline">The Christian Outlook in the Modern World</hi>".  It is amazingly suggestive and informing.  How true it is that only a great man can write a small book!  I am more than ever surprized and regretful that the Author should be unable to rise above the fierce and narrow Protestantism of Northern Ireland, when he speaks &amp; writes about the Revised Prayer Book.  He wrote privately to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi> counselling him to vote for the Prayer Book Measure in the House of Lords, yet, when the <hi rend="strikethrough">B</hi> Measure had been rejected in the House of Commons by the aid of Irish votes, he did not scruple to justify the action of the Irish members!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
