<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi>, thanking him for his very interesting address on "<hi rend="underline">The Mechanized Age of Today and its effect upon the human race</hi>", of which he had sent me a copy. Incidentally he says that '<hi rend="underline">a large majority of riveters in ship&#8211;yards, at a comparatively early date, lose their hearing owing to the loud noise injuring the delicate mechanisms of the ears</hi>': and he gives reasons for thinking 'the burden of industrial activity seems to weigh more heavily' on women than on men.</p>
         <p>[symbol]  <hi rend="italic bold underline">Derek Elliott arrived about 6 p.m. He is growing tall, &amp; has a pleasant intellectual face. He is just 17 years old, so that his time at school is drawing to a close</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  Living in Glasgow, he has the University easily &amp; cheaply accessible: so that he may hope to take a degree, &amp; thus open the door to one of the 'learned professions'.  I asked him whether he had made choice of a career, &amp; he said that he thought he would like to teach.  It needs no saying that I coveted him for Holy Orders, but, if he moves in that direction, it must be by the suggestion of his own mind.  The outlook for the Christian ministry is so unpromising that it hardly seems right to urge any youngster to embrace that career.  God will find and claim His own.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
