<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A local Doctor, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Weekes</hi>, came, &amp; prescribed: and, of course, I had to stay in bed. The Bishop undertook to read my sermon for me. I was sufficiently recovered to beguile the tiresome day by reading the remarkable book "<hi rend="underline">England</hi>" by a German scholar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilhelm Dibelius</hi>,<persName xml:id="5503"></persName> which is warmly recommended in a Preface by the Master of Balliol.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Mine host visited me from time to time, and we talked much. His conversation deals much with football, in which he was himself formerly eminent, &amp; on which he depends much (i.e. on his athletic reputation) as a means for attracting Ordination candidates to his diocese. Here, indeed, I could but listen, and marvel. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">God fulfils Himself in many ways</hi><hi rend="italic">": although the Psalmist held that "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Lord regarded no man's legs</hi><hi rend="italic">", it may be the case that He makes an exception to His general rule in the case of a population, so absorbed in Football, as the Northumbrian. The Bishop grows, perhaps, rather tiresome in his incessant stories of the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">magnalia Dei</hi><hi rend="italic">' which he witnessed in Durham under Bishops </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lightfoot</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Westcott</hi><hi rend="italic">: of these stories the incandescent memory of a cheerful soul rather than the facts is probably the main foundation.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
