<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The plan of the '<hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>' article begins to shape itself in my mind. "<hi rend="underline">Westminster and (or) Lambeth</hi>' would, perhaps, serve for a title. The recent rejection of the Revised Prayer Book in Westminster, the seat of government, in the Established Church, and the supreme direction of the Anglican Communion in Lambeth, the centre of widely dispersed fellowship represented in the Conference, provide a contrast which carries its own moral. The suggestion of a new policy for the Church of England w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> follow as an inevitable epilogue.  A choice must be made between the secular chains of Westminster and the spiritual liberty of Lambeth.  I think there are the materials for what the Sectaries call a 'message' in this.  And by bringing in Lambeth I shall not only provide myself with an obviously suitable "peg" on which to hang the said 'message' but I shall avoid the suggestion of an unrelieved pessimism which a concentration on the Church of England might to easily make.  I wish, however, that I felt more confident in this Anglican Communion.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  There were 11 communicants including the 4 <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brydens</hi> &amp; the new <hi rend="doubleunderline">John</hi>.</p>
         <p>After breakfast I motored to <hi rend="underline">Stranton</hi>, &amp; preached at Mattins in the Parish Church. There was but a moderate congregation, which, however, contained an unusual proportion of men. The attention was close &amp; sustained. I lunched with the Vicar (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kirner</hi>) and his wife, &amp; rested for an hour.  Then I motored to <hi rend="underline">Stockton</hi>, &amp; preached to a large congregation of Freemasons in Holy Trinity Church, at 3.15 p.m. They were evidently interested in my discussion of Bolshevist persecution, &amp; listened with admirable closeness of attention to a rather long discourse. Then I had tea with the Vicar (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Petrie</hi>) and his wife.  The Mayor &amp; Mayoress, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leonard Ropner</hi>, &amp; several others were present, and I "made myself agreeable". Then I returned to Auckland Castle, &amp; read the '<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>' which is full of <hi rend="underline">Balfouriana</hi>.</p>
         <p>The long account of his relations with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Drew and the Gladstone&#8211;Lyttelton families is extremely interesting.  His passion for music in early manhood persisted through life, and his personal charm never seems to have altered with time &amp; circumstance.
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
