<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Mr. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arnold Pinchard</hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="5422"></persName> accepting the invitation to address the members of the E.C.U. in the Albert Hall on July 3</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rd</hi><hi rend="italic"> on the subject of Disestablishment.  It is difficult to imagine a stranger revolution of attitudes on both sides, but mostly on that of the E.C.U.  Twelve years ago they mobilized their ample resources of conspiracy and calumny in order to keep me out of a bishoprick: now they will insist on my addressing their annual meeting!!  Then I wrote the Article on 'Disestablishment' which I had promised to the Editor of the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Daily Herald</hi><hi rend="italic">' reminding him at the same time of his promise to send a contribution of ten guineas to the Durham Castle Fund.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I left the Castle at 1.50 p.m. and motored to Durham, where we left Ella, &amp; then continued to Harton, where I consecrated an addition to the Burial Ground.  The Mayor &amp; Corporation of South Shields were present, &amp; walked round the ground with us.  There was the choir of St. Michael's &amp; a good muster of the clergy.  After this function we went to the Town Hall in South Shields, &amp; were entertained at tea.  There were speeches of flatterous &amp; fatuous as the occasion required: and then we motored back to Auckland Castle.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
