<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent the day in dictating and writing letters, in walking round the Park, reading through my private Journal for 1917 – 1918 in order <hi rend="italic">to make selection for Archbishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi rend="italic">, and in finishing </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'Babbitt</hi><hi rend="italic">'. Voila tout!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I caused the copies of the Bishoprick to be sent to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Budworth</hi> for presentation to the Sixth.  It seemed to me that as Dunelmians they ought to know something about the Palatine Bishoprick.</p>
         <p>I declined the invitation of the Committee of <hi rend="underline">the Society of Jesus and Christians</hi> to become one of their number.  The objects are, of course, unexceptionable, but the inevitable suggestions of the combination of Jews &amp; Christians in pursuit of them is that there is a fundamental agreement between the Allies which can justify an ignoring of their differences.  If only "Modernist" or 'Liberal' Christians were in question, I think it would be fair enough to assume such a fundamental agreement; but I must needs think that such Christians are neither representative nor satisfactory examples of the Religion of Christ.  My membership of such a Committee could not but be misinterpreted.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
