<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The proof of my little article in the "<hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century and After</hi>" arrived. It is headed "<hi rend="underline">Crossing the Rubicon</hi>?" and only fills 9 pages. I corrected &amp; returned it. Then I began some notes for the<hi rend="underline"> Spital Sermon</hi> on April 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>There came to lunch the new Vicar of Usworth, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi>, who for 16 years was a missionary in Corea [sic]. He says that the Coreans have a keen sense of humour, a quality of which their masters, the Japanese, are wholly destitute. I hope rather than expect that he will be equal to the charge of that large parish. He succeeds an indifferent pastor, Begg, who gave much of his time to lecturing, &amp; neglected the parish.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> &amp; I walked round the Park in a hailstorm.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Penelope Webb</hi> writes to tell us that she is engaged to be married.  Of course she will have me "tie the knot", and since the bridegroom was a boy at Westminster School, of course the ceremony must be in Westminster Abbey!  They are ever the same, these daughters of Eve.  "<hi rend="underline">Sic volo: sic jubeo</hi>".  But, unless the theory on the subject has greatly changed since I was a Canon of Westminster, the sweet child has as much chance of being married in the Abbey as of being married in the moon.  Indeed the last is not the most lunatick of the alternatives! </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
