<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[231]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent most of the morning to prepare notes for my speech tomorrow when I am to propose the toast of the Royal Hospitals of London.  This kind of public speaking shows me at my worst.  The pulpit is no good preparation for post&#8211;prandial oratory.  Yet some eminent preachers have excelled in it.  Of my own contemporaries <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> are certainly far above the average, though the last always errs by undue length.</p>
         <p>Mr. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward James</hi>, and Ordination Candidate from Goole, Yorks, came to be inspected. A solid youth of 30 with an emphasized lower waist which suggests lack of exercise or unwisdom of feeding. But he did not impress me ill, and' if he can pass the G.O.E. and commits no disqualifying iniquity in the interval, I shall ordain him. But we have travelled far from "<hi rend="doubleunderline">A Gentleman &amp; a scholar in every parish</hi>", the formula of Church defenders when I was ordained, and a long way from the truth even then. This man's education is limited to that provided by the Goole Elementary School, but he was four years in the Army, and can claim for that reason something like 'most favoured candidate' treatment.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[232]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Speed</hi> informing me that my portrait is in the academy Exhibition.</p>
         <p>"The portrait is in Room N<hi rend="superscript underline">o </hi>8. Where the rooms turn, and it is hung so that it can be seen from the room opposite through the door, so that it has a good show. But picture exhibitions always remind me of concerts when all the performances take place at once round the room. But there is not much on either side of it to distract."</p>
         <p>From which I gather that the artist's exorbitant vanity's not wounded!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi> and I motored to York, and went over the Minster.  The nave was full of chairs in preparation for the Military service next Sunday.  The verger recognized me, &amp; insisted on showing me the Chapter House.  Then the Dean showed me the pulpit, &amp; explained the working of the "loud speaker".  Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Talbot</hi>, on crutches, insisted on seeing me, &amp; was most affectionate.  I introduced <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi> to him: &amp; then the senior verger showed us the marvellous crypt &amp; the vast Eastern window.  We had tea at the Hotel, &amp; were back in Auckland by 7.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
