<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I made notes for the Spital Sermon.  It occurred to me that something might be made of the parallel and the difference between pre&#8211;Christian &amp; Christian civilization as illustrated by the Royal Hospitals of London.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rostovzeff</hi>'s "Social &amp; Economic History of the Roman Empire" is rather suggestive.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to South Shields, where I confirmed about 65 persons in S. Stephen's Church.  The sexes were about equally represented, a welcome spectacle after the gross disparity at Beamish.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anderson</hi>, the Vicar of S. Aidan's, told me that he had been making a special visitation of his parish in order to discover what children it contained, &amp; that he had found a disconcertingly large number of houses without any children at all.  They are occupied by elderly couples, either childless or with grown&#8211;up families.  The younger married people had generally moved to the new houses builded [sic] by the municipality in the suburbs.  <hi rend="bold underline">The absence of children is an untoward condition of parochial life.  It takes half the interest out of pastorate and all the joy.  We returned to Auckland after the </hi>service in a heavy snow&#8211;fall, but the temperature is too high to admit of anything but slush.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
