<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Is it, or is it not, a defensible expenditure of a bishop's time to address '<hi rend="underline">Rotarians</hi>'? The gatherings at '<hi rend="underline">Rotarian</hi>' lunches are not, save in the view of the Rotarians themselves, important, but the reporters are sure to attend, &amp; their presence constitutes a danger, and provides an opportunity.  A bishop cannot wisely 'play the fool', nor can he, if he have any credit with the public wisely speak without thought &amp; knowledge.  This means that he must needs take pains to prepare his speech, and such preparation, (since the subject must not be either religious or political, and cannot, in the circumstances, be literary or scientific,) must be something that lies outside the normal limits of his reading.  And this takes time and diverts energy.  And, beyond a fallacious good fellowship which leads to nothing, what has been gained?  <hi rend="underline">But something may have been avoided</hi>, viz. the resentment which is caused by the rejection of a courtesy, and, perhaps, a confirmation of their mean opinion of the clergy, which in any circumstances the laity are apt to form. On the balance, therefore, one groans, &amp; accepts the invitation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, and lunched with the <hi rend="underline">Rotarians</hi> in the Havelock Restaurant.  The Rector was in the Chair, I sate beside him, having the Mayor on my other side.  There was a numerous company.  I spoke for about half an hour on '<hi rend="underline">Advertisement</hi>' and they seemed to be entertained.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Fuller</hi> saw me for a few minutes, and told me that he had been asked to return to his old curacy in Liverpool, and that he was disposed to go.  I did not attempt to dissuade him, for I think he is better fitted to work as a subordinate than on his own.  But it means the loss to the diocese of a comparatively young man.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dr. Cooper</hi> came to see me with reference to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Sykes</hi>, and stayed to tea.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Chilton Moor, where I admitted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shore</hi> to the perpetual curacy, in succession to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Keith Frazer</hi>, under whom religion had well&#8211;nigh perished. The dismal little church, which was horribly damp and cold, was fairly filled with a congregation almost altogether composed of women. The Rural Dean (Watson) and several of the adjacent incumbents, but it was a cheerless service enough notwithstanding.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
