<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><!201030>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I reflected on the Sermon which I must preach in Westminster Abbey on February 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and I decided that I would take as my subject <hi rend="underline">the severity of Christ's demand on his disciples</hi>. It will connect itself in my mind, and perhaps in my discourse, with the "Church and State" discussion in The Assembly.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Sons of the Clergy and Pensions Board.  We appointed </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Carter</hi><hi rend="italic"> to be hon: secretary on the place of Burrell, who retired on the ground of health.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Derek Elliott</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> sends me a pleasant "Collins".  He is evidently Thinking over my suggestion that he should, in due course, become a clergyman.</hi><hi rend="italic">It is, perhaps, questionable whether one ought to suggest Ordination to a boy of 17, but it seemed to me not unfair to ask him to consider this career as one of the possibilities which lay before him. It is difficult to suppose that, apart from such suggestion, the matter would ever come within his view. He is, if one can reasonably form a judgement so soon, temperamentally well&#8211;fitted for the clergyman's life.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
