<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[223]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Rain fell heavily during the night, and the day was damp &amp; clouded. I left Dargavel at 10.30 a.m. and motored to Auckland Castle, where I arrived at 5.25 p.m. The weather improved as I went south. At Appleby I had teas, &amp; visited the parish church. I learned without surprize that the motor racing which had been arranged for Easter Monday had been postponed on account of the sodden stated of the ground. The Vicar had left a message for me conveying the information that M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Gowan, the Vicar of Hamsterley, had died. He was instituted as recently as 1927. I have now 3 livings in my gift vacant viz: Sedgefield, Evenwood, and Hamsterley. Per contra, I found a letter from the Rev Robert Wilson accepting the appointment to All Saints, Monkwearmouth.</p>
         <p>The papers inform us Dean Welldon reaches the age of 76 today. He is rather older than I thought. He adds the garrulity of old age to the tactlessness, proper to his temperament: and charity suggests that we should be magnanimously indulgent to the exasperating outcome! His Easter Day sermon on the absenteeism &amp; unspirituality of Bishops as the fontes malorum in the Church was_______ [sic]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[224]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>April 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1930</p>
         <p>My dear K.</p>
         <p>I returned from Scotland this afternoon. Your letter came into my hands at 8.15 p.m. However, I hope the enclosed will reach you in good time.</p>
         <p>This is your last term at Oxford, and I shall not continue my assistance further. You have yourself limited our intercourse in the matter of 'giving &amp; receiving', and therein, no doubt, disappointed me, the more since it destroys my power to befriend you further. I earnestly hope that you will get your degree, &amp; get to work without delay. If you could overcome a morbid self&#8211;consciousness which makes friendship impossible, &amp; w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> address yourself to your duty in a manly spirit, you might yet play a man's part in the world.  Anyway I wish you well.</p>
         <p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
