<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">An affectionate letter from Derek telling me that he wants to be ordained. He has not yet spoken to his mother, but will do so. A lecture in the school on Missions, &amp; a sermon in Chapel seem to have impressed him much. The purposes of the young are as words written on water: nevertheless they are sometimes the spring of very noble things</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked at the Spital sermon most of the morning, still very helplessly.</p>
         <p>There came to lunch a queer&#8211;looking person named Wintle, who desires to be appointed Assistant&#8211;curate of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street. He is colonially ordained, &amp; has rather an odd record: but, in these ill times, we may not refuse anybody who is not actually scandalous!</p>
         <p>Then I called on old D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McCullagh, and had tea with him &amp; his wife, returning to the Castle in time to see Ella's party – General &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Surtees, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sam Story, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Farquharson.   </p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow came to see me. He is evidently getting into rather strained relations with the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, who find a champion in his brother Archdeacon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
