<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[227]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Low Sunday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Scouts in the Cathedral</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A thick mist covered the country when day broke, and evidently the night had been rainy. There was no wind, and the air was warm &amp; even languorous. I celebrated the holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but 5 communicants.</p>
         <p>I wrote at length to Brook Westcott in answer to a letter from him asking my advice on a rather petty matter viz: should he approve a British Legion Service which has been hitherto held in the church, being held this year in the open air, &amp; made what it is the fashion to call rather oddly, an 'united' service? I told him to show himself accommodating and magnanimous. I am afraid he has 'got across' his parishioners, &amp; that, together with much that is sincere &amp; attractive, his character includes a strain of hair–splitting quarrelsomeness in which an aspect of his illustrious grandfather's personality may be discerned! His father, who is a neighbouring incumbent, is said to be rather cantankerous. He is too young to be well placed in a 'fat' living. The situation provokes jealousy in his neighbours.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The cathedral was thronged by boy–scouts.  Lord Barnard estimated that nearly 4,000 were present; and in addition there was a considerable gathering of adults.  The service was Evensong with special lessons, and some shortening of the prayers.  This was ill suited to such a congregation, and there was much restlessness.  My sermon was ill attended to, and lord Londonderry, who spoke from the chancel steps after presenting a medal to one of the scouts, could not be heard beyond his immediate neighbourhood.  The spectacle of the great church crowded with boys to its utmost capacity was very impressive: but I cannot say that the service was successful.  After tea at the deanery, I went to Rawlinson's house at his request, &amp; received from him a horrifying story of clerical misconduct, which may well mature in an immense scandal.  <hi rend="underline">Quis custodiet</hi>? I went to S. Oswald's, and preached at Evensong. Before the service I called at the Vicarage, and was shown the arrangement by which the house has been bisected, and one part let to a tenant.</p>
         <p>I returned to Auckland when evensong had ended.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
