<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A white frost. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 9 communicants including three Brydens.</p>
         <p>I prepared notes for an "extemporaneous" sermon at Witton Park, and then wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Boden</hi>. His "Modern Churchmen's Union Pamphlets', of which he had sent me the first two' advance specimens' are poisonous productions. I expressed myself with frankness.</p>
         <p>A Canadian Archdeacon (retired) named Hayes, who had preached in S. Anne's as a deputation for S.P.G. came to tea.  I inquired about the Union of Churches in Canada, &amp; he said that it but added one more Church!  The Presbyterian minorities did sometimes represent the wealth of the Church.  In some cases they were joining the Anglicans, &amp; raising the usual difficulty about Confirmation.  His account of Prohibition in U.S.A. was amusing.  At Chicago he had asked for a magazine, &amp; was brought a bottle of whisky!  Inadvertently he had used the current bootlegging term.  He said that the Archbishop of New Westminster, having to attend a meeting on the American side of the Niagara river, had accepted the courteous proposal of some motorists to carry him over <hi rend="bold">[92]</hi> [symbol] the bridge.  When he thanked the motorist, he was somewhat disconcerted to learn that he had been sitting on a large consignment of whisky!  In spite of himself, he had played the bootlegger!  He described the system now established in Canada as "ideal".</p>
         <p>I went to Witton Park, &amp; preached at Evensong. This is a derelict parish with a very bad name: most of the people are unemployed. There was a good congregation. The choir consisted of 15 boys, 10 young women, 10 young men, and 14 members of the Mothers' Union. The behaviour was exemplary, &amp; the singing of the anthem quite creditable. After the service I was introduced to a number of women who voluntarily wash &amp; clean the church. Evidently the Vicar has got hold of the people. Birney was one of Lomax's young men. He has had no academic training. I myself ordained him to the diaconate in 1919, &amp; to the priesthood on 1921. I appointed him to Witton Park in 1924. He is an example of a clerical type as rare as it is valuable.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
