<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[184]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"So, one of these days, I expect that we shall find ourselves put into the position of having to choose between making the church co–extensive with what can be called the religion of the whole nation <hi rend="underline">or giving up our present position</hi>.  I think it will be an evil thing for the present generation at least when that time comes; for certainly no machinery, that I can see, could take the place of the Church in the country districts; and with all their innumerable shortcomings, the English clergy, as a whole, have worked well &amp; hard for the poor &amp; helpless, who would be badly off without them.  <hi rend="underline">But no doubt the times must come</hi>."</p>
         <p>Dean Church 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Feb. 1870</p>
         <p>(v. 'Life &amp; Letters p. 187.)</p>
         <p>Sixty years have passed since the great Dean wrote thus: and every circumstance which then led him to despair of the Establishment has gathered emphasis. Can it be doubted that, if he were now living, he would insist that we must make no terms with the present tyranny?</p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Pattison accompanied me to the station where I caught the early train.  On arriving at King's Cross, I drove to the Athenaeum.  There I found Sir <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lewis Dibdin</hi>, and had some speech with him.  He spoke <hi rend="doubleunderline">of Abp. Davidson's</hi> condition, which he thought serious.  As he had seen him as recently as yesterday, this is grave tidings.  <hi rend="bold underline">We spoke of the Birmingham episode. He said that the Judge was in much perplexity: that he himself had been consulted: and that in his judgment a wrong procedure had been adapted. His legal jargon was puzzling, but I gathered that, not a quare impedit but a 'duplex querela' would have been the better course. For there the Abp of Canterbury could have been required to institute over the head of the Bishop of Birmingham.</hi>  Then I went to Paddington, &amp; took train for Winsor.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Deane</hi> introduced himself to me, and shared my carriage.  He told me that he wrote all the ecclesiastical articles for the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>.  He also spoke of the trouble at Birmingham, and blamed the Bishop for his tactless &amp; crude methods of language.   </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A carriage drawn by two white horses, and a tall footman in red met me to the station, and carried me to the Castle, where I was received by the Master of the Household.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><hi rend="italic"> came in, and talked pleasantly for half an hour.  He said this room was that which was always used by Dizzy.  We spoke of the persons he had met, and the crises which he had traversed during the 50 years of service.  I asked him if he had kept any record: &amp; he said no.  But he had many papers, and had been much consulted.  The worse job he had ever been required to do was telling </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Curzon</hi><hi rend="italic"> that he was not to be Prime Minister. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Curzon</hi><hi rend="italic"> had plainly counted on appointment, and came into the room with his countenance wreathed with smiles.  When he received the fatal news, he collapsed, declared that he would retire from public life &amp;c. But when he got home, probably by his wife advice, he decided to serve under</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Baldwin</hi><hi rend="italic">, and carried himself with loyalty &amp; dignity. Lord S. spoke freely about the crisis which preceded the Parl</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Act.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was guided to the drawing room, where we awaited their Majesties.  I sate beside the Queen at dinner, and had much talk with her.  On my other side was </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Desborough</hi><hi rend="italic">.  The King motioned to me to say Grace, though Canon Deane was present, &amp; I should have imagined could have naturally acted as chaplain.  After dinner, the King smoked, and talked to me all the time.  He speaks with strange freedom, and does not hesitate to express his opinion of individuals.  He spoke with loathing of the Russian ambassador, with whom he had had to shake hands.  I asked him what he thought of the situation in Spain.  He said that the outlook was not good; that the Republican party was very strong: &amp; that the King had mainly to depend on himself.  It was odd to hear him talking so plainly of the probability of the downfall of Monarchy.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">He expressed strong disapproval of the agitation against the Russian Persecution of Religion, though he regretted our getting into diplomatic relations with the Soviet Government.</hi><hi rend="italic">  Earl de la Warre is here.  I had a strong talk with him before going to bed.  </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
