<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote a letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Simpson</hi> condoling with her on her husband's death.   It was recently as last year that I instituted him to Evenwood, where he was doing good work.  The post brought me a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Llewelyn</hi>, the assistant curate of New Shildon, telling me that he has accepted a living in the Leicester diocese. Thus my dwindling force of working clergy is reduced by two of the younger men.</p>
         <p>Wilson, the Vicar of Allendale, lunched here. He has been recommended for appointment to All Saints, Monkwearmouth, &amp;, if he can stand the noise &amp; dust, he might serve well enough.</p>
         <p>Pattinson and I motored to Blackhill, where I confirmed about 60 persons. There was but a sparse congregation, but the candidates were attentive &amp; devout, so that I came away not wholly displeased. Jenkin Jones, the Vicar, told me that his parish was largely peopled by Roman Catholicks. The Sunday Mass was said to be attended by as many as 2000 persons. The Papists were not polemical, being mostly Irish; &amp; not particularly interested in the standing conflict with the English church. He had nearly 1200 persons on his parochial roll.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
