<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote at length to the Wesleyan Methodist minister, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Holtby</hi>, who desires to be Ordained in the Church of England, indicating the difficulties which I felt, and suggesting that he should address himself to the Bishop of Chelmsford.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><hi rend="italic"> wrote to me at some length thanking me for the photograph of my portrait, which I had sent him at Christmas: He was evidently pleased with the attention.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hawkins</hi>, the new assistant&#8211;curate of Brandon came to lunch, and to discuss his arrangements.  He has reached a <hi rend="underline">modus vivendi</hi> with his Vicar, according to which he will do brless work and accept a reduced stipend.  </p>
         <p>When he had gone, I walked round the Park by myself in a vehement gale.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fosca</hi> arrived on a visit.  Unfortunately, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> has gone off to London on some G.F.S. business.  How I wish that I could persuade myself that all these organisations and meetings were really worth while!   Of course, if one followed one's inclination &amp; had nothing to do with any of them, we might as well go out of the world.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
