<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[225]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A warm dull day, rather enervatingly depressing. I worked on the sermon for the troops in York Minster, but I did not produce anything at all adequate to my intentions. These great parades are from the preacher's point of view quite hateful.</p>
         <p>A tract on "<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>" by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Partridge</hi> arrived, and I read it through.  The style is cumbrous and stilted: the thought confused: &amp; the argument unconvincing.  There is plainly no background of adequate legal knowledge, &amp;, perhaps, no sufficient general culture.  I wrote to him correcting one error, &amp; sent him a copy of my pamphlet, which is at least readable and connected!!</p>
         <p>The cheque (&#x00A3;9) from the <hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century &amp; After</hi> arrived.  It represents the nine pages of my Article.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Abp of Canterbury</hi> has asked me to stay at Lambeth next Wednesday, when I go up to London for the Spital Sermon.  I have accepted his invitation in the hope of being able to have some speech with him about the Commission on Church and State.  No announcement as to its composition has yet been made, and I do grievously suspect that his Grace would like to let the whole matter 'fizzle out'.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[226]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"The art of mummification, in fact, is the nucleus around which the fabric of civilization, its architecture, its stone&#8211;working, carpentry, and portrait statuary was crystallized. But it represents the essential inspiration of the assurance of resurrection and immortality."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">G. Elliot Smith</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Human History</hi>" p. 373.</p>
         <p>"How our Lord's Resurrection was the instrument by which a new life of hope was brought into mankind may be read in many places of the Acts and the Epistles. It reversed every doom of every kind of death, and thus annulled the hopelessness which must settle down on every one who thinks out seriously what is involved in the universal Empire of death. It was by the faith in the Resurrection that mankind was enabled to renew its youth."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hort. </hi><hi rend="underline">First Epistle of S. Peter</hi>. p. 34.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
