<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[109]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There was a full house &amp; a crowded gallery for the debate on Temple's motion for a Commission on the relations of Church &amp; State.  Temple's speech, which occupied 80 minutes in delivery, was admirable in form &amp; substance, &amp; it was admirably delivered.  He was loudly applauded when he sate down.  The Bishop of Winchester seconded, but he was at some disadvantage in having to follow Temple, &amp; his speech was not very effective.  Then came three laymen, more or less in opposition, &amp; all bad speakers.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I followed, &amp; spoke for half an hour. I produced much amusement by describing episcopal essays in extra–legal procedure: &amp;, when I sate down, was loudly applauded. Many persons congratulated me on the speech, &amp; so I must conclude that it was successful, but it did not satisfy me</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  I was followed by Sir Thomas Inskip, who was less </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough">successful</hi> 
<hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">effective</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">than I had expected.  I lunched at the Deanery.  After lunch the debate was resumed, &amp; continued in deepening dullness </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough">much</hi><hi rend="italic"> all the afternoon.  Then the Archbishop wound up with an astute but over–lengthy speech.  The voting was decisive:– Bishops 33 to 1: Clergy 198 to 38: Laity 151 to 66 in favour of the motion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I dined at Grillions, &amp; was placed in the chair. We only numbered seven, viz:</p>
         <p>1. Lord FitzAlan<lb/>2. Owen Seaman<lb/>3. Sir John Simon<lb/>4. The Master of the Rolls<lb/>5. Lord Desart<lb/>6. Lord Donoughmore<lb/>7. The Bishop of Durham.</p>
         <p>Simon said that he had read through all the depositions in the famous anarchist case in America described in the novel 'Boston', and that <hi rend="bold underline">the two men were in his view certainly innocent</hi>.</p>
         <p>Lord Desart told me that he was over 81: and that the Benchers had made up the income of the Master of the Temple to £1000 per ann.</p>
         <p>I received a letter from Froggatt, telling me that <hi rend="bold underline">poor Harlow had died</hi>. It is, perhaps, a merciful release, for he could never have recovered his health. This living also is in the gift of the Crown. Two Crown livings are now vacant in the diocese.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
