<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I corrected the proofs of the 'Bishoprick' article: wrote to the Master of the Household some sort of an indirect "Collins", sent Lord Stamfordham a list of suitable Sandringham preachers &amp; prepared some noted for the N.S.P.C.C. meeting.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sybil, Lady Eden</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Clarke</hi> as a representative of the S.P.C.C. Society lunched here before the meeting in the State Room.  There was a very large company, &amp; the collection exceeded &#x00A3;16.  Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Morris Young</hi>, the Vicar of New Shildon, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Llewelyn</hi>, his assistant curate came to tell me that the latter had been offered a living in the Leicester diocese. I advised him not to accept the offer until he has ascertained all the relevant circumstances and could have reasonable security that he could afford to hold the living. He was ordained to the diaconate by me in 1926.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Murton where I confirmed 131 persons in the parish church.  Doncaster the Vicar is without a colleague in a parish of nearly 13,000 people, all miners.  I was pleased with the appearance of the candidates, and with their reverent demeanour.  The church was crowded, many standing.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
