<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My whole morning was wasted in writing letters, none of which was of any real importance. Pattinson and I motored to Ryhope after lunch, and there I confirmed 114 persons. This was a pleasing service. After tea with the Vicar, we went on to Bishopwearmouth, where, after an early dinner at the Rectory I confirmed 85 persons in the parish church. Among the female candidates was Nancy, the Rector's daughter. I gave her a copy of Thomas à Kempis. In spite of the wetness of the night, there was a large congregation.</p>
         <p>I received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">G. M. Trevelyan</hi><persName xml:id="3598"></persName> a most interesting reply to my inquiry about Wingfield Stratford,<persName xml:id="5482"></persName> whose history of British Civilization had interested me so much.</p>
         <p>"He has reading of an extensive &amp; discursive kind: whether he has learning depends on one's definition of the word, for his mind is a curious one.  He always walks by himself alone up any alley that offers.  Consequently he is often illuminating &amp; suggestive, often unnecessarily and paradoxically wrong. <hi rend="bold">[197] </hi><hi rend="underline">His mind remains as it was twenty years ago, that of a clever undergraduate</hi>.  He is a strange mixture of old Tory and rash Radical in his opinions.  If he is prejudiced, they are his own prejudices – &amp; that is something.  <hi rend="underline">The good and bad of him is that his mind is always on fire</hi>.  It is long since he has been at Cambridge, but his old friends there – historians &amp; others – regard him with affection tempered by a fear of being bored, for <hi rend="underline">he is one of those endless talkers, good for the first hour &amp; then superfluous</hi>. I don't think he has balance of judgement, but he has intellectual zeal, wide reading, and passion".</p>
         <p>This is an acute and discriminating description.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Trevelyan</hi> proceeds to discuss the attitude of Cambridge towards Christianity in a very interesting way.  He thinks that there is less hostility than heretofore: partly, because the anti–Christians are largely disillusioned with their own substitutes for the Gospel: &amp; partly because the cause of Christianity is now represented by a far more attractive &amp; reasonable type of advocate.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
