<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have suddenly realized that I am pledged to preach at Westminster Abbey on Sunday, February 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.  The first &amp; not the least difficult question which must be answered is that which concerns the choice of a subject.  What shall I preach about?  <hi rend="bold underline">My mind for some while past has been turning in the direction of a plain sermon on the old issue which our Modernists have clothed with new urgency</hi>.  <hi rend="underline">What think ye of Christ? Whose son is He</hi>? But the difficulty of indicating the answer in a discourse which may by no means exceed half&#8211;an&#8211;hour in length is as considerable as it is apparent.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi> and I motored to Newcastle, &amp; had the coal&#8211;dust washed from our heads by the hair&#8211;dresser.</p>
         <p>The Officers of the D.L.I. territorials gave their annual ball in the Drill Hall.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> took a party of young men &amp; women who dined here beforehand.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi> and I had a great talk on all sorts of '<hi rend="underline">problems</hi>'. Perhaps because he is so much younger than I, he is far less "pessimistic", but, indeed, I am not cheerful company at present.</p>
         <p>The weather, which was fine in the morning, grew to be wet and stormy at nightfall.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
