<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[173]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished the Spital Sermon, a long, dull, and not very suitable composition.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Champion</hi>, the new Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>  Paul's, Stockton, came to lunch and to discuss matters.  A little, sleek mild man, with a pleasant voice &amp; manner, describes himself as a 'Liberal Evangelical', who is interested in <hi rend="underline">von Hügel</hi>, and that kind of reading. He says that he and his wife are musical. Mainly, l liked him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Gateshead, where I confirmed 220 persons in the parish church.  Before beginning my address, I said a few words about the episcopal chair, presented by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Reid</hi>, which was then used for the first time. I had refused to dedicate it. The candidates were mostly of the poorest type. Many of the boys were genuine 'slummites'. After the service we returned to Auckland, &amp;, though there were so many confirmees, and the service did not begin until 7.30 p.m., we were home by 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Mangin</hi> were here for the night.  He has been preaching in South Church to the members of the Mothers' Union.  He is an elephant of a man in body, and in mind?  Well, hardly elephantine.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
