<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>An unpleasant blustering day for All Souls. I copied out an abbreviated version of my sermon on Psalm 119–96, for use at Windsor next Sunday. It will have to serve.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hitchcock</hi>, the assistant curate of Willingdon, came to see about the proposal that he should succeed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fuller</hi> at South Hylton.  There is a pension on the living, so that the entire income is no more that &#x00A3;300, and the rates amount to &#x00A3;50.  Of course he has no private means whatever.  It hardly seems safe for him to take on.</p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, &amp; confirmed 55 persons in S. Thomas's Church. It was rather a depressing service, and the number of candidates hardly justified a separate confirmation.</p>
         <p>After a prodigious search I found in my journal for July 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1927, the extract from Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Boutflower</hi>'s article in the <hi rend="underline">Contemporary Review</hi>, Dec. 1903 on '<hi rend="underline">Some Sayings of Bishop Westcott</hi>.</p>
         <p>"I should like to know whether my idea is true that the great epochs of church building have always been the times of greatest spiritual depression".</p>
         <p>There is a spate if Cathedral building in U.S.A. now!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
