<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>[^written in Greek^]</p>
         <p>How long is obedience possible on these terms? When once it is clearly seen that the teacher's theory and practice cannot be harmonized, how long will the theory be able to command acceptance? Is not the weightiest evidence of the soundness of the theory the fact that its expression in practice is so plainly excellent? Take that fact away, &amp; compel the theory to stand alone, nay worse than that, shown to be practically powerless, and what effective appeal to the conscience &amp; the intellect any more remains to it? The discord between a moral teacher's precept and his personal behaviour stamps him with the evil mark of hypocrisy, as well as displays the ineffectiveness of his teaching. Who can surmount the disgust which hypocrisy must needs provoke? "<hi rend="underline">Woe unto the world because of causes of stumbling</hi>", said Christ, &amp; added that "<hi rend="underline">it must needs be that causes of stumbling should come</hi>". He did not ignore the immense difficulty of yielding obedience to the official hierarchy, when that hierarchy has become scandalous through its personal unworthiness. Indeed He followed up His admonition to obedience by a tremendous denunciation of the "<hi rend="underline">scribes &amp; Pharisees, hypocrites</hi>," for whose official authority He had just made Himself the apologist.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p>After lunch William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored us (viz. mine host &amp; hostess, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Nightingale, and ourselves) to see some Highland sports at Craigievar Castle. We were received very courteously by Lady Sempill, who showed us the Castle, which is an extremely good specimen of Scottish baronial architecture. It was begun in 1610 and completed in 1626. The inconvenience can hardly be less than the architectural interest. The winding narrow stair&#8211;ways of stone would hardly permit the carriage of luggage. We had tea in the Hall, a fine room with an elaborate plaister ceiling, and many points of antiquarian interest. Among the spectator of the games was the Bishop of Lincoln, disguised in lay garments. The weather, which in the morning had been brilliant, deteriorated as the day advanced, and we returned to Bealack with the car closed.</p>
         <p>Mine host is decided as to the mischievousness of <hi rend="underline">sparrows</hi>, whom he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi>massacre without mercy. <hi rend="underline">Rooks</hi> he holds to be mainly serviceable, but thinks they do so much damage to the crops in seeking for the grubs which they destroy, that they might almost as well attack the crops directly. <hi rend="underline">Herons</hi> are in his opinion too numerous, &amp; ought to be "kept down". Against <hi rend="underline">squirrels</hi> he wages a truceless war, affirming that they do much damage to the young trees, gnawing the bark &amp; devouring the shoots. Patches of snow are visible on the higher hills. These are the relics of last winter. It would seem probable that there will be an unbroken continuity of snow from winter to winter.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>