<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, whose never&#8211;failing providence ordereth all things both in heaven and earth; We humbly beseech thee to put away from us all hurtful things, and to give us those things which be profitable for us; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This direct, undoubting movement from the fact that the Divine Will sustains the illimitable Universe to the Divine concern for the petty requirements of individual life is eminently characteristic of Christianity. None can dispute that its justification lies in the clear teaching of Christ Himself. "<hi rend="underline">Fear not, little flock, it is your Father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom</hi>." The Epistle for the day suggests that its proof lies in the believer's heart. "<hi rend="underline">The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are the children of God</hi>." The Revelation of God's Fatherhood by the Incarnate Son answered to, welcomed, &amp; appropriated by the Spirit of Sonship in the disciple – there is the secret of the Gospel. "<hi rend="underline">The Spirit of Man is the candle of the Lord</hi>", says the Old Testament. "<hi rend="underline">If any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of His</hi>", adds the New. But before "<hi rend="underline">the spirit of Man</hi>" knows itself as the "<hi rend="underline">spirit of Christ</hi>" there must be an enfranchising, and cleansing process, which is called "<hi rend="underline">Redemption</hi>". Christianity is essentially a Redemptive Religion. "<hi rend="underline">He shall save his His People from their sins</hi>." And this Redemption is the recovery &amp; vindication of a natural franchise, the realizing of an inborn potency.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p>We walked a mile and a quarter to the parish church of Dalton, a modern building without aisles embellished with stained glass windows at the eastern end, &amp; presenting a more churchly appearance than is common in Scottish churches. The minister conducted the service, and preached the sermon. Perhaps in deference to me – for he knew I meant to be there – we had the collect for the day as the prayer before the sermon, &amp;, as the lesson from the New Testament, the narrative of the Transfiguration. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowles has the rather artificial melancholy which most Scottish ministers appear to think becoming in Christian preachers: and his delivery is unimpressive. The discourse was unpretentious, but well&#8211;expressed. He gives the impression of a good man who takes himself seriously. I do not think the Scottish clergy work as strenuously as the English. The entire service for this Sunday was a short service with sermon in the parish church at noon, and an address in the Mission chapel at 7 p.m. There may have been attendance at the Sunday School in the interval. The population of the parish numbers about 450, and there is a U.F. Church as well as the parish church.</p>
         <p>I slept in the garden during the afternoon. At tea there were guests – M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Reid, Miss Campbell, &amp; another lady – all pleasant folks. Afterwards mine host and I walked for an hour before dinner. After dinner I read aloud "M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sludge, the Medium". It was suggested by our conversation at table, when we discussed ghosts etc etc. respecting which I am wholly unsympathetic.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>