<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Deplorable weather: rain all night &amp; continuing. I went thro' the letters with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> before breakfast, and afterwards settled down to a sermon for the Ripon Cathedral Sermon. My guests were motored into Durham, in spite of heavy rain. At 6.30 p.m. I dedicated the War memorial. There was a large concourse of people. But the delay spoiled everything. I omitted my speech altogether, &amp; reduced the prayers to the smallest amount possible. <hi rend="doubleunderline">General Sir Ivor Maxse</hi> &amp; his A.D.C. Captain Howie came to the Castle for the night. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi><persName xml:id="344"></persName> arrived during the afternoon, so there was a party of 14 at dinner. After the ladies had retired to bed, Maxse, Craik, Richmond<persName xml:id="3112"></persName> &amp; I had a great discussion over the <hi rend="bold underline">League of Nations, which I alone endeavoured to depend against the other three. I was rather startled at the opinions they expressed, &amp; realized more than before how very far we have to travel before we reach the Millennium! One thing which the General told me of his own knowledge is worth recording. He said that President Wilson's<persName xml:id="2814"></persName> energy in hurrying the American troops, though unarmed &amp; untrained, to France enabled Foch to launch his decisive offensive. Foch himself told him this, alleging that he could not have ventured his mighty attack if he had not known that he had a great reserve of men in the country. The General spoke with utmost contempt of the Irish regiments. They had neither courage nor discipline</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>