<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[^written in Greek, Matthew 26^]</p>
         <p>To make a kiss the token by which to point out his Victim to the soldiers was truly a chef d'oevre of treason. For of all human actions the kiss is the most impulsive, the most significant, the most unforgettable. Between adults, if they be considering , cultivated, self&#8211;respecting persons, the kiss is a decisive episode, the symbol of a covenant betwixt them, which cannot lightly be broken, and can never be altogether forgotten. If it be less than this, it must needs be an indefensible indulgence drawing with it a certain cheapening of the highest sentiment, &amp;, in fact, a measure of self&#8211;degradation. Here in the narrative of the Passion it is precisely the pledge &amp; symbol of the best relation between men which is shown to be deliberately ordained to be the pledge &amp; symbol of the Worst. Judas betrayed a consciousness of his monstrous fault by overdoing the miserable part which he had chosen for himself [^written in Greek, Matthew 26:49^], he kissed him with effusive affectionateness, as if designing to apprize the onlookers of the extraordinary ardour of his friendship. Is not this the key to the success of hypocrisy? Protesting conscience has to be bludgeoned into acquiescence before it can endure the worst insults.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p>The "Scotsman" reports that "the Conference of German Bishops has, according to the "<hi rend="underline">Germania",</hi> passed a resolution to send a solemn protest to the Holy See against the repeated unjust assertion that Germany is responsible for the War. "The Conference", adds the journal, "herewith reiterates the contention of the joint pastoral letter of 1914, in which it was declared that the German people are not responsible for the outbreak of the war, which has been forced upon us, as we can declare before God and the World".</p>
         <p>The Roman Catholic Church, long before the War, had shown itself strangely complaisant towards the Imperial Government of Germany. It hardly came to the crisis with an unbiased mind. The political interest of the Papacy was too closely bound up with German Victory to make its approval of German Action morally impressive. If there be such a thing as the "public opinion" of the world, it would seem that the opinion of neutrals would be the most natural instrument of expression: &amp; <hi rend="underline">that</hi> opinion was adverse to Germany. Some neutrals, e.g. Italy, Romania, America, came into the struggle against Germany: others e.g. Holland, Denmark, Norway , Sweden, declared themselves, so far as they dared, favourable to the Allies. Spain alone, more completely subject to Vaticanist influences than any other state, was consistently hostile to the Allies. In every case, of course, there was a marvellous blending of tendencies, but broadly the verdict for or against Germany was sufficiently plain. Certainly, so far as we can discover the facts from the records of diplomacy, Germany was directly &amp; immediately responsible for the War.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[80] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>For the whole month I have been staying in Scottish country houses, received with considerate kindness, and terribly bored with conversation that rarely moves outside family pedigrees, the fortunes of properties, and the records of sport! The narrowness of the range of conversation reflects the self&#8211;centeredness of a small class, &amp; its enormous pride. Perhaps the practical effectiveness of the Scot is not unconnected with his complete indifference to everything that does not bear upon himself. He moves through the world with the single&#8211;mindedness of a cattle&#8211;stealing Borderer, and a no less strong resourcefulness. Scott knew his countrymen through &amp; through – Dugald Dalgetty, Andrew Fairservice, Baillie Nicol Jarvie, Cuddie Headrigg – they are the very types of the Scots who are today "running" the British Empire. Does the modern world know also the types of Rob Roy, Caleb Balderstone, the Antiquary, Jeanie Deans, and the Baron of Bretwardine? No one who has known intimately Thomas Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName> and W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> can doubt the existence of Scotsmen who are high&#8211;minded, generous, &amp; romantic: but none who has known <hi rend="underline">them</hi> will regard them as representative of their nation. I must needs incline to think that they are survivals from a generation which is nearly extinct. During recent years the policy of Great Britain has been largely determined by Scots: and Scots have played a decisive part in the government of the Church of England. Will any considering &amp; well&#8211;informed person say that British Policy has been superior in point of morality, &amp; wisdom? <hi rend="italic">Has the Church of England been really well&#8211;governed by its Scottish primates?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote letters to Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName>, Willie Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName>, and Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>: took a walk in the grounds before lunch: &amp; was taken a motor drive afterwards. As the rain fell steadily, the drive was not successful. I read the "<hi rend="underline">Scotsman</hi>", and wrote in my Journal. There came together a considerable party, mostly of very aged persons, to tea. Among them were two Scottish ministers, the one belonging to the Established Church &amp; the other to the United Free Church. I catechized them as to the position of the Reunion Movement, &amp; they both protested that the matter was moving forward with all reasonable expedition. Then they turned the tables, &amp; catechized me about what they called "the Modernist Party in the Church of England". I told them to distinguish between the new Modernists who were a section of the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick party", and represented in the English Church the followers of Abb&#x00E9; Loisy in the Roman: and the Liberals who were the lineal descendants of the Latitudinarians of the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. The former had their origin in Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName> Essay in "Lux Mundi": the latter had received a new character from the development of Biblical Criticism.</p>
         <p>Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Fergusson</hi> talked much with me. He recalled the circumstance that we met at Sauchieburn some years ago. He is now 88, &amp; still vigorous. His sister, who enjoyed a reputation as a singer, obliged the company with a series of superannuated songs, for which she was lavishly complemented, her courage meriting the applause which her musical exertions could hardly evoke. The younger members of the party appeared to be deaf.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>