<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>The rain has ceased, and the sun shone intermittently from a clouded sky. The Richmonds<persName xml:id="3112"></persName> left after breakfast, &amp; were quickly followed by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Belloc Lowndes &amp; her daughter. I finished the sermon for Ripon Cathedral. After an early lunch I accompanied Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> to Darlington in the motor. He took the train to London, and I returned to the Castle.</p>
         <p>James, who had been visiting his coal–mine, brought the mine–manager M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hare to tea. He looked at the bowling green, &amp; seemed to think that the fears as to subsidence were not chimerical. He assured me, with perhaps suspicious insistence, that the responsibilities of <hi rend="underline">his</hi> company ceased at the Gaunless, <hi rend="bold underline">and added that it was generally believed that most part of Bishop Auckland is built over ancient workings, the precise direction of which was unknown. This is more interesting to hear than pleasant to reflect upon!</hi> He said that he was having considerable difficulty in getting the men to resume work in the mine in spite of the wide–spread unemployment. The dole supplemented from the rates by the foolish lavishness of the Guardians really made it worth the while of the lower ratings of miner to continue in idleness. Is it possible to imagine a more fatuous system, or one better adapted to transform English labourers into the similitude of Neapolitan lazzaroni? In order to avoid "Revolution" we had recourse to doles: now the doles have 'come to stay', and their pressure on our shoulders is likely to exhaust us altogether!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>