<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>A stormy day with rain at intervals. I finished the sermon for the Freemasons. After lunch I motored to Windlestone, where a C.J.B. Fete had been organized by Sir Tomothy Eden &amp; his mother. The threatening weather had its effect in reducing the attendance, and I formally opened the Fete in the presence of a disconcertingly small company. After squandering about 45/_ I returned to the Castle.</p>
         <p>At 6p.m. there was a gathering of Foreign Mission Workers in the Chapel. I preached to them on a subject of which my knowledge is insufficient, &amp; my interest is distressingly tepid. However they seemed to be very attentive.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After the service Ragg, the Vicar of Evenwood, came to see me. He goes to Harrogate for the rheumatism on Monday, &amp; wanted to explain the arrangements he had made for his parish during his absence. He told me that there are no fewer than 6 sects established in his parish of 4000 people besides the Church. His communicants last Easter were but 97 in number.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">He says that "Missions" are so frequent that they have become contemptible among the people</hi><hi rend="italic">. They are furious &amp; meticulous fanaticks on the subject of total abstinence, but do not always observe the rigorous rules on which they insist. The Dissenters have been longer established in the place that the Church, and are better equipped with buildings. Altogether his account of Evenwood was depressing. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>