<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>[^written in Greek^]</p>
         <p>Surprise, mortification and fear blend in the question. The disciples had just realised that He was the Christ, and their confidence in His power was at its height. Yet here, on the first trial of it, they are defeated. And Christ tells them that their failure was [^written in Greek^]. They had been more filled with their own importance than with the Mission. Perhaps the afflicted father made his appeal to them because some claim, implicit or explicit, was made on their behalf. <hi rend="underline">They</hi> were the official representatives of the Christ. Men must seek His gifts at <hi rend="underline">their</hi> hands. So they stand in the sacred narrative as symbols of the continuing Error and Failure of official Christianity. Our woeful little sermonettes are solemnly presented "in the Name of the Father &amp; the Son &amp; the Holy Ghost". No Sacraments are valid if they be not ministered by us. None but ourselves can pronounce the Sinner's absolution. Yet, as we honestly review our ministry, and take account of its strange ineffectiveness, we find ourselves asking with the humiliated Apostles, Why could not we cast it out? Why is there so disconcerting a discrepancy between our theory and our achievements? Why are our sermons so powerless? Why do no evident moral consequences follow from the Sacraments which we administer with such an impressive parade of Divinely constituted authority?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi></p>
         <p>I had a heavy cold which gave me much discomfort. Nevertheless, I went into Glasgow, though the weather continued abominable, and got my hair cut. I lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Maxwell in a Ladies Club (The Kelvin Club) in Buchanan Street. We returned together to Dargavel, and then called on Lady Renshaw. She complains of the impossibility of keeping up Barochan, now that the carpet factory pays no dividend, and the income tax remains so high. Griffith Jones and his family were there. I don't like the man, who is a quite shameless beggar for preferment, but he is adhesive and irresponsible, &amp; one tolerates much for the sake of the old people. I bought Samuel Butler's "Erewhon", and read it. There are many curious errors in the book, e.g. <hi rend="underline">Christening</hi> is distinguished from <hi rend="underline">baptism</hi>, Paley is an Archbishop, Moses beholds Palestine from <hi rend="underline">Sinai</hi> instead of Pisgah.</p>
         <p>The "Glasgow Herald" has an account of a conflict between a thrush ad a hawk, which was carrying off one of her young birds. The hawk was so vigorously attacked that it had to release its victim.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">An owl attached a cat in the garden here, &amp; ronted it utterly</hi>. It is amazing to note the courage which maternal instinct infuses into the weakest creatures.</p>
         <p>Just 100 years ago George IV visited Edinburgh, and was received with immense enthusiasm. Sir Walter Scott was at the height of his influence, and threw himself into the congenial task of organising &amp; expressing the feelings of the people.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>