<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[^written in Greek, Matthew 25:29^]</p>
         <p> A dark saying very sad to reflect upon when one is nearing sixty, &amp; cannot but know that one has disclosed all the potencies of one's life, &amp; can henceforth only discover its failures. </p>
         <p>We left Blelack a few minutes before 11 a.m., and motored to Balhary, near Meigle in Perthshire, a distance of more than 100 miles. The weather was brilliant: our road lay over the Spital of Glenshire through the finest scenery in Scotland. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> negotiated the Devil's Elbow without difficulty: it is an ill&#8211;looking piece of road. We lunched at White House, Doumore [sic] with Susan &amp; Gertrude Ramsay: and had tea at Pitlochrie. We arrived at Balhary about 7 p.m. having had a thoroughly successful day. </p>
         <p>Here we found old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Thomas Dunroch with his wife and family – the widowed daughter, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Higgon, a younger daughter, &amp; his son Lewis. There was staying in the house a young lady, Miss Hill Witston, who sang very charmingly after dinner. Mine host affirmed that when he was an undergraduate at Merton College, he cannot remember ever to have seen a man drunken. Lewis, who was in Oxford after the War, testified that there was very little drunkenness. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>