<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>We left Riccall about 10.40 a.m., and motored home, arriving at the Castle at1.25 p.m. As the distance cannot be less than 70 miles, this is very good travelling. I paid for my new bookcase &#8211; &#x00A3;42., a sum which seems to be rather large. The bookcases in my study have now cost me at least&#x00A3;80. Then I went round the garden with Laws, &amp; listened to his account of the depredations of earwigs. It appears that there is something like a plague of these repulsive insects this year. In some districts the peasantry are almost panic&#8211;stricken by them, for their horrible reputation as creatures that penetrate the brain through the ear is still generally credited. Laws himself was fully convinced of the fact! <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked in the Park, and noted that the repair of the bridge had been completed. I talked with two well&#8211;looking lads; one of them had been without work for no less than 2 years. I inquired how he spent this vast leisure, and whether he did any reading. He seemed to have no conception of any other method of passing the time, than sitting or walking about. I sent copies of 'Anglicanism' to Sir John Butcher and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> William Coltman.</p>
         <p>Thus my holiday ends. <hi rend="bold underline">After 5 weeks absence</hi> from duty, I return to my <hi rend="bold underline">work. Am I anywise better</hi> fitted for its performance? <hi rend="bold underline">Is a single known defect remedied?</hi> Do I see the solution of a single problem? </p>
         </body></text></TEI>