<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. My guests communicated, &amp; both William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and Frank Berry. The last&#8211;named joins his ship tomorrow. After breakfast a hired motor arrived, &amp; carried me to Winston, where I preached in the parish church. This is a fine building of the early Gothic period. The parish is in my gift, &amp; is most attractive. The view from the Rectory, which is perched on the bank of the Tees &amp; has its gardens running down to the river, is entrancing. Add that the endowment is above the average, &amp; the attractiveness of Winston is sufficiently demonstrated. I lunched and spent the afternoon with the Headlams<persName xml:id="552"><persName xml:id="553"></persName></persName> at Whorlton Hall. He and I walked to Wycliffe Church, &amp; beside the Tees. After tea I motored to Egglestone, and there I preached in the parish church. This is a modern building, beautifully placed on the hill&#8211;side, commanding the loveliest prospects. The parish, 850 feet above sea level, is inhabited by small holders, who unite tenancy or ownership of a few acres, with labour in the mines. The endowment is not much more than &#x00A3;200 per annum: &amp; the patronage is in the Crown. The parson, Butler, is married, &amp; has two children. They all look half&#8211;starved, &amp; the vicarage has a poverty&#8211;stricken appearance. I returned to the Caste after service arriving about 9.15 p.m. The drive over the moors in the declining sunlight of a brilliant day was relieved by the views of a romantic &amp; varied country.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>