<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S. Matthew's Day, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A dull wet morning enormously depressing. Is it merely an irresistible physical condition that is expressed in the mental distraction &amp; discouragement which such an atmosphere creates? or, has one's state a deeper &amp; less respectable origin? Anyway, I feel as grim and grey as a broken soldier crawling out of a fight in which he has lost his limb and his credit!</p>
         <p>Today I exercise the highest, most responsible, &amp; intrinsically the most important function of the episcopate – Ordination. Only two young men are to be ordained, and the needs of the diocese require twenty at the least. The service in the chapel was very solemn. Moulsdale<persName xml:id="3159"></persName> sung the Litany. A number of the clergy formed a choir, and sang Marbecke's setting. Kennett's<persName xml:id="572"></persName> sermon was highly suggestive, &amp;, perhaps, too provocative for the occasion. The communicants numbered more than 50. Afterwards there was a numerous company at lunch.</p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, &amp; Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> returned to Durham in the motor. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I continued the journey to Silksworth, where I consecrated an extension of the churchyard 'with maimed rites' on account of the heavy rain. Later I preached to a crowded church. It was not a little encouraging to see the eagerness of the people undaunted even by the rain. We returned to Auckland as soon as the service was over, arriving about 10 p.m. The rain had fallen continuously all day.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>