<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>The more I think over Kennett's<persName xml:id="572"></persName> sweeping statement that the Old Testament contains no confessions of <hi rend="underline">individual</hi> sinfulness, the more incredible it appears. Indeed, I doubt whether the habit of personifying the nation so completely as to confess national transgressions in terms of personal repentance does not itself indicate a deep sense of individual sinfulness. In any case, I can see no greater reason for denying the individualness of the <hi rend="underline">penitence</hi> than for denying individualness of the faith <hi rend="underline">"Into Thy Hand I commend my spirit"</hi> (Ps. 31.5) – can this be the expression of the personified Nation's faith?</p>
         <p>The weather improved as the day advanced, and the afternoon was brilliant. Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName>, Kennett, and I walked for 1 1/2 hours in the Park. I received an affectionate letter from George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> by the afternoon post, which pleased me much. The announcement of the capitular appointments appeared on the front page of the "Times", a position of rather unusual prominence.</p>
         <p>The Fieldens arrived in their car about 6.30 p.m. They are rather a different type from that of most visitors to an episcopal house. They belong to the upper range of commercial life, where it finds glad but slightly embarrassed entrance to the nobility. They are rich, educated, public&#8211;spirited, pleased with the world, not deliberately ostentatious, but glad that men should know of their achievements.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Morris,</p>
         <p>I enclose for your guidance a copy of the Resolution adopted by the Lambeth Conference of 1908. You have my permission to use the form in the Prayer Book of 1549. If you think it necessary that the oil which you propose using should first be consecrated, then you must consecrate it yourself. It is not my intention or desire to encourage or facilitate in the diocese a practice which has no authorisation in the Prayer Book, which was deliberately laid aside by the Church of England in the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, and which lends itself but too easily to much misconception and superstitious materialism.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Theodore H. A. Morris</p>
         <p>S. Oswald's Vicarage, Durham</p>
         </div>
         <p>Two days later I received a note from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Morris informing me that my permission had arrived too late. He was unconscious and had died before the Unction could be administered. I am on the whole pleased that the precedent has not been created, for in these strange days one never knows what superstructures of imprudent lawlessness may not be builded on the foundation of it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Sir</p>
         <p>It would be unserviceable to you, and unreasonable in me to embark on a discussion through the post of the question proposed in your letter. The immortality of the soul or Self of man is the assumption of Christianity, &amp; underlies the Apostolic writings at every point. It has been justified by many great arguments of divines, philosophers &amp; moralists, and cannot reasonably be called in question on no better grounds than a sentence from the Book of Genesis. It is certainly the case that the Immortality of the Self or Soul of man was a truth gradually gained, &amp; but obscurely disclosed, if disclosed at all, in the Old Testament. In the words of S. Paul, it was Christ Jesus who <hi rend="underline">"brought life and immortality to light through the Gospel"</hi> (2.Tim.I.10) He himself said <hi rend="underline">"I came that they may have life, &amp; have it abundantly"</hi> (S.John.X.10). Throughout Christian History there has been much speculation as to the fortunes of the Self in the world beyond the grave: but in as much as this speculation has been mostly without any secure basis of knowledge, it has been rather serviceable to superstition than to truth or morals. I cannot embark on any such futile course.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>