<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[^written in Greek^]</p>
         <p>"The signs of the times" (i.e. those occurrences which are truly illustrative of the specific &amp; distinguishing quality of the age and which for that reason merit the particular attention of observant &amp; considering men) are not always or often easily perceived. The stream of life runs on, and its mingled waters are always taking in fresh elements which blend &amp; are lost in its hasting mass. Who shall recognize, and by what tokens, those elements which really affect its fortunes or its quality? In the long retrospect of history it is possible to discern between events, and to appraise them justly, but in the actual course of life the task of discernment is enormously difficult, perhaps wholly impracticable. I am disposed to regard the recent divorce case, Russell v. Russell as properly entitled to be regards as a "sign of the times" for it lifted the veil, and showed the mental &amp; moral points of view characteristic of the fashionable world which is under twenty&#8211;five. The incredible coarseness with which the mysteries of sex &amp; child birth are therein regarded, the shameless effrontery with which the immemorial restraints &amp; reticence of social intercourse are repudiated, the perilous courage with which young men &amp; women "play with fire", the total absence of any respect for Religion or Morality, the brazen indifference to public opinion – these surely are new phenomena, and infinitely suggestive.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The Bishop of Durham has no nephew of the name of Henry Henson, nor, so far as he knows, any relation of that name. His Lordship, of course, does not undertake to carry a complete family tree in his head".</p>
         </div>
         <p>The above was my response to an inquiry from South Shields. The writer is not apparently an educated person, &amp; presumably a Dissenter of some sort. The letter runs thus:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My Lord,</p>
         <p>I hope your Lordship will pardon me for writing &amp; asking if you have a nephew in South Shields known by the name of Henry Henson residing at 114 Lytton Street. This man has recently joined the church to which I belong and is passing himself off as such. If this is not the case it ought to be stopped &amp; we cant do it unless we write &amp; ask you. So again I ask your Lordships pardon for troubling you.</p>
         <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> M. E. Scoller</p>
         </div>
         <p>This letter is addressed from 31 Shrewsbury Terrace, South Shields. I can, of course say what nephews &amp; nieces I have, for there are but four all told – Harold<persName xml:id="1097"></persName>, Edith, Albert, &amp; Sissie; but when one moves out into the <hi rend="underline">terra incognita</hi> of cousin&#8211;hoods, I find myself considerably perplexed, for though I know few cousins, I suspect the existence of more, of whom I know nothing.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>August 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I learn with great satisfaction that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dowson's debts have been paid &amp; that the grave scandal which they have caused has been mitigated, if not even removed.</p>
         <p>You probably know that M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dowson was admitted to the diaconate by my predecessor Bishop Moule, on what I must needs think very inadequate assurance as to his character &amp; ability. He has twice failed to satisfy my examining chaplains, &amp; his general behaviour has not disposed me to make any exception in his favour.</p>
         <p>I shall, of course, be very willing to see you on my return to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, but I cannot hold out the smallest hope that I should permit M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dowson to receive Ordination to the Priesthood in my diocese. He does not appear to me really qualified for the Christian Ministry.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm</p>
         <p>J. Dixon Johnson Esq.</p>
         <p>24 Foyle Street</p>
         <p>Sunderland</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi></p>
         <p>After lunch we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Miss Roberson, and I) motored to Row, and had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Smith, with whom were divers others of Ella's relations. Among these was Olive<persName xml:id="1696"></persName> whom I have not seen since her marriage in 1920. She is now the mother of two girls. She looks much thinner, but still remains a sweet &amp; attractive woman. Her brother Walter is home from Nigeria. He says that the colony is still very depressed, and, though the natives admit that they are more mildly &amp; justly governed that they were by the Germans, they yet refer to the German regime as the time when they were prosperous. <hi rend="bold underline">The French are secretly hostiie, and corrupt the natives by importing gin contrary to their treaty obligations. The officials exhibit much fear of the natives, a sure sign that they are treating them badly</hi>.</p>
         <p>The "Times" contains an account of the pitiable destruction of sea birds on Ailsa Crag through the oil from the steamers. The wretched fowl get their wings clogged hopelessly; they flutter &amp; crawl to the shore, &amp; there they perish miserably from starvation. The same report comes every part of the coast. We shall soon lose irrecoverably all these beautiful &amp; interesting creatures, which give variety and distinction to our shores. How hateful a thing is civilization!</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After dinner we had some talk about Burmah, with which mine hosts appear to be personally acquainted. The Burmese are more like the Chinese than like the Hindoos; but the leaven of "democracy" is already working even among them.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>