<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[104]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>September 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922. </p>
         <p>My dear Madam,</p>
         <p>I have made inquiry in Gateshead where Sister Miriam was employed, and am informed that she failed so completely that her dismissal was necessary in order to save the work from total collapse. </p>
         <p>The Rector, Canon Stephenson, tells me that he has paid for storing her furniture, &amp; will continue to do so for the present, if necessary. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Haslewood can hardly be entitled to offer an opinion on Sister Miriam's position on ability or she never attended any of the meetings which considered her case: &amp; was not able to judge of the condition of the House. </p>
         <p>In these circumstances, I cannot think that any responsibility for Sister Miriam's situation can fairly be fastened upon the Committee in Gateshead by whom she appears to have been treated with much patience and consideration. </p>
         <p>Believe me, </p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Angela R. Kempson</p>
         <p>at Ar(e)ley House,</p>
         <p>Stourport</p>
         <p>Worcestershire </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to D.W.<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> suggesting the he should move from the academic to the ecclesiastical sphere: and I reported my action to the Bp. of J.<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> asking his counsel about the parochial appointments.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham and lunched <hi rend="bold underline">with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in order to meet his relative Aylmer, the owner of Walworth Castle.</hi> He has just come away from his house in Ireland, finding as most loyalists are now finding, that life is impossible under existing conditions. He gave a very black account of the situation, and was very sure that after a few years we should have to re&#8211;occupy the country. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burgess, the American Lady whose acquaintance we made in America, &amp; who is an attached friend &amp; admirer of Bishop Brent, proposed herself for a visit. She arrived today. <hi rend="bold underline">The poor woman is so deaf that conversation with her is 'labour &amp; sorrow'. She told me that Bishop Brent had been sent for the "White House", and asked to undertake a mission of inquiry in Russia: that he had formulated certain conditions to which the Soviet Government must consent before he would adventure on the business: &amp; that Lenin had refused to accept these conditions.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>The sunset tonight was brilliant, the whole western sky was flaming with colour. This might, perhaps, prognosticate fine weather: but the reports are doubtful: &amp; the account of the harvest distinctly melancholy. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>