<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather was propitious. Though there was little sun, there was no wind. We completed our preparations, and set out in a well&#8211;laden car shortly after 11 a.m. We motored by way of Tow Law &amp; Riding Mill to the Wall, and had luncheon comfortably by the road&#8211;side. Then we continued our journey to <hi rend="bold underline">Murraythwaite</hi>, where we arrived about 4.30 p.m., and were warmly welcomed. After tea Willie Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName> walked with me for nearly 2 hours. The evening was brilliant, and the country with its wealth of crops and cattle had an alluring aspect. Mine host has decided to abandon politics, and to live at home on his ancestral property. I think he is acting very wisely: for not only is attendance in the House of Commons incompatible with his health, (a matter on which his medical advisers are decisive,) but also the life of a country gentleman may well be more truly serviceable than that of a politician. And this estate is itself very attractive, neither too large for residence, no too small for dignity. Parliament has so fallen in the regard of the people that a seat therein confers no consequence and opens small opportunity. The demands of constituencies grow ever more exacting, but the attractions of political life grow ever smaller. No man who values either his health or his independence would readily consent in present circumstances to stand for Parliament.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>