<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I was rather surprized to hear Canon Cosgrave, a man of judgement, as I esteem him to be, and with a large knowledge of India from the point of view of a missionary, speak strongly about the unwisdom of the Government's declaration of policy. He thought there was no case for fighting the Turks. But he did not appear to realize the risks of allowing them to put the Balkans in a flame.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> offering him the living of Sedgefield which Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> will vacate on becoming Canon of Durham.</hi> I think its net value can hardly be less than &#x00A3;1400 per annum: but the Rectory is almost palatial.</p>
         <p>After lunch I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> until tea&#8211;time. Then I had 'interviews' with the two deacons. Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName> &amp; Kennett arrived at 6 p.m. I walked with Kennett<persName xml:id="572"></persName> in the Park for an hour. After the ladies had retired for the night Kennett, Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> came into my study, and we had a considerable discussion. Kennett is certainly a very "advanced" critick, and, like many academic theologians, he greatly overrates the popular concern with the questions which interest himself. He goes farther than I approve in belittling the spiritual value of the Old Testament, and his presentment of the Christian message seems to have little in common with that of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul. But we live in strange times.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi> 
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Sept. 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922. </p>
         <p>My dear Duncan,</p>
         <p>I do not gather from your letter whether you have already volunteered for service as Chaplain if required, or whether you are seeking permission to do so.</p>
         <p>If the latter, then I can have no hesitation in saying that I think you could not rightly leave your parish for service in the Army in the circumstances which now exist. You cannot ignore the actual obligations under which you stand, and these are such that you are not morally free to offer yourself for Chaplain's duty until there be so clear a case of necessity that everything ought to give way.</p>
         <p>It is surely both premature &amp; improper to be making arrangements for your own succession. In my judgement it is rarely, if ever, advisable for an assistant curate to succeed his Vicar. I hope very much that you have taken no decisive step, and that you will not do so without very anxious &amp; religious thought.</p>
         <p>You have been doing well in your parish. I have noted with much satisfaction your zeal &amp; effort. I cannot approve your departure.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>