<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> assisted, and, apart from the clergy, there were 11 communicants. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated, &amp; 4 of the household. After breakfast Boden brought me the MS of his sermon preached in the Abbey on August 20h. I read it through and was favourably impressed alike with its form and its matter. I wrote letters to Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, Briliorth, Sir Robert Lighton, and George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. We all, save <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Campbell Dodgson, motored to Durham and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. Jack Boden acted as my Chaplain, and carried the staff. Afterwards we had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>. Miss Christopher<persName xml:id="3679"></persName> was there &amp; Turner from Oxford.</p>
         <p>I reflected much on the appointment of a new Archdeacon, and I reached the decision to try to create a vacancy in the Divinity Professorship. This idea originated in my own mind, but it was suggested also by Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> to whom I had written an inquiry about Matthews of King's College. His verdict was highly favourable, but he said that he would make a much better Divinity Professor than Archdeacon. Of course the sitting tenant may refuse to leave the Chair. In that case I shall be but where I was before. Certainly the clergy would be less likely to resent the appointment from outside the diocese of a Divinity Professor than of an Archdeacon. And we <hi rend="underline">must</hi> get "new blood" into the diocese.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>