<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold"> Wednesday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The non&#8211;appearance of Ordination Candidates is now threatening the whole work of this diocese, for the "natural wastage" far exceeds the recruitment. The quality, social &amp; intellectual, of most of the clergy ordained since 1901, when Bishop Moule entered on his episcopate, is woeful. Such good men as he ordained have mostly gone into the Mission Field. There is no sign anywhere of improvement. I am now really embarrassed in administering my patronage. Curates cannot be obtained. No titles are sought for. The best incumbents are beginning to break down. Yet, though Durham is not specially injured by the general calamity save that the relatively large number of unbeneficed clergy exposed in [sic] beyond most other dioceses to the depredations of alien patrons, there seems to be little evidence that the Church is aware of the extent and urgency of the evil. Fatuous projects for multiplying bishopricks still command the ardent support of the zealots, and schemes for "reforming" patronage &amp; indeed everything else engage the labours of more serious Churchmen. Yet all these things presuppose the existence of a working clergy, holding all the parishes: and that indispensable presupposition is now plainly becoming insecure. Shall we adopt Jeroboam's policy without his schismatical motive, and ordain priests of the lowest of the people?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington, where I arrived soon enough to catch an earlier train than I had intended to travel by. It was well that I did so, for the meeting of the Committee began at 10 a.m., not at 10.30 a.m. as originally determined.</p>
         <p>The Patronage Committee sate from 10.30 a.m. to 1.30 p.m., &amp; again from 2.30 p.m.to 4.30 p.m., and we discussed the <hi rend="italic">Report about Sale of livings, and the Parson's Freehold. It is plain enough that these "Reformers" are bent on transforming the independent clergy of the Church of England into such poor, dependent sycophants as the Dissenting Ministers are seen to be. They cannot understand, still less sympathize with, the feelings of an honourable &amp; self&#8211;respecting clergyman, who writhes with indignant shame at being discussed &amp; handled as if he were a pauper or a clerk.</hi></p>
         <p>I got my hair cut, &amp; had tea with the Deanery ladies, while my colleagues went out to Bishopthorpe to take tea with the Archbishop. We were entertained at dinner in the Treasurer's House, a most interesting building partly medieval, partly Elizabethan. The house has been excellently restored by the present owner, a wealthy ironmaster named Green. He has collected a remarkable amount of old furniture, which is displayed with great effect and in excellent taste.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>