<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>July 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Gentlemen,</p>
         <p>I hear from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName> that you are prepared to undertake the dilapidations of <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, &amp; that your estimate for doing the work amounts to £1302. I shall be ready to accept that estimate, and desire that you may be able to begin the work with as little delay as possible. I am leaving for Scotland on the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> of August, &amp; shall be away until the first week in September. If the work is indoors &amp; the painting could be finished before my return, I should be glad.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm: </p>
         <p>Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cornish &amp; Gaymer</p>
         <p>North Walsham, Norfolk.</p>
         </div>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">The 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="underline"> year of our Translation</hi>" begins with the important decision expressed in the above letter. "Dilapidations" is one of those which grows in terror the longer it is fled from. Once faced &amp; conquered it can be domesticated with comparative ease.</p>
         <p>I walked with Brilioth<persName xml:id="5198"></persName> to Encombe, &amp; showed him the "Saxon" church. The inevitable vicar showed us round, &amp; accompanied us far on our homeward journey! Does he ever visit anybody in his parish? He seems always at home, and always unemployed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Brilioth is engaged in a study of the Oxford Movement, and he has exhibited a praiseworthy conscientiousness in reading the literature of the Tractarians. He thinks he can distinguish between a politico–ecclesiastical and a genuinely religious movement; he is evidently fascinated by Kearman and Froude; and not a little disconnected by the rigorous anti–Protestant is not likely to hear only the conventional eulogies of Tractarianism, but the Oxford "Anglo–Catholics "have had their eye on him, and have spared no pains to make him "see light in their light." He is plainly attracted by the notion of "liberal Catholicism", but was impressed when I pointed out that the phrase itself enshrines a paradox. "Catholicism" cannot be "liberal". Many people assume that because they approve "Catholic" beliefs &amp; practices, they are themselves "Catholic", whereas all turns on the grounds of their acceptance. "Private judgement" is not altered by the method of its exercise. I drew his attention to the frame "Inhibition" which Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> launched at me on 1909, when I preached for Joarett in Birmingham, and which now holds a prominent place on my study–wall. It is a curious comment on the spirit of "liberal Catholicism", and an impressive disproof of its claim.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
