<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A fine September day – heavy mist to begin with developing into sunshine and warmth. After breakfast we talked in the smoking room, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">mine host laid bare his difficulties with his parson</hi>. They were of the usual kind – "Catholic" innovations on "Protestant" tradition. He had ceased attendance at the services in consequence. I told him that therein he acted unadvisedly as, apart from higher considerations, an absentee "put himself out of court". But he was not even on the Electoral Roll, &amp; knew nothing about the Parochial Church Council! <hi rend="bold underline">Yet he had voted for the Enabling Act!</hi> We walked out, &amp; looked at the parish church, a fine commodious building, which has been restored. The Norman door is very splendid: it has the bird's beaks which make so conspicuous a feature of Iffley Church.</p>
         <p>After lunch we motored to Cawood, where we saw the remains of Archbishop Wolsey's palace, &amp; picked up a half&#8211;drunken man, who begged for a 'lift' to Selby, &amp; joined a pot&#8211;house as soon as he left our car! We continued to Sherborne, where we visited the parish church, a fine building finely placed on a rising ground. The most curious feature in this church was a pair of medieval stone crucifixes, which have been unearthed in recent years. We went on to Selby, where we were shown over the noble church by the Vicar, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sollerway, who evidently is proud of his charge, &amp; well&#8211;informed about it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Sir John Butcher was chairman of the Commission which investigated the treatment of British prisoners in Germany, and he expresses himself with the fierce horror of all things German which marked the War. He and the General are vehemently pro&#8211;French, and their opinion of the Prime Minister is that of Leo Maxse<persName xml:id="5367"></persName> in the "National Review". I was very much interested to hear the General speak scornfully of the fighting quality of Irish troops. He said that the non&#8211;commissioned officers were mostly Protestants, as Papists were generally useless. While generally allowing the excellent quality of the R.I.C., he said that they could not be trusted to act against priests, and illustrated his statement by some remarkable experiences of his own. Of Michael Collins he spoke with much bitterness, but how far he had independent knowledge I cannot decide. I was surprised to learn from mine host that Austen Chamberlain<persName xml:id="343"></persName> claimed to be the author of the political <hi rend="underline">volte&#8211;face</hi> which secured the "Treaty" with the Sinn Feiners. He suggested the idea to the Prime Minister, who, with characteristic contempt for his own consistency, adopted it. Both Butcher and the General were confident that the "Treaty" could not succeed; and, indeed, it is difficult to imagine a stable political system being built on such foundations as are now being laid. The material resources of the country are being wantonly &amp; rapidly destroyed. It is hard to see how the unavoidable expenditures of government can be met. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>