<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>We left Sunderland Hall at 10.30 a.m., and motored to Bishop Auckland, arriving at the Castle about 5.15 p.m. We stopped to see Jedburgh Abbey, a magnificent ruin, probably the finest in Scotland. The weather, which was dull when we started, improved steadily as we drew near to the English border, and we lunched on the moor under bright sunshine. The prospects on every hand were truly glorious, and, though we had seen the Highlands, we could not feel any sense of disappointment. We called at the Deanery, &amp; found the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> at home. We had tea, &amp; then continued our journey to Auckland. The front of the Castle had been painted: some workmen were still busy: but mainly I was rather disappointed at the amount of work which had been accomplished in our absence.</p>
         <p>I learned that another incumbent had died, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mark's, Millfield, Sunderland. This living is in my gift, and is said to be worth &#x00A3;430 net. There is a population of 10,000 souls. There are now, or will be immediately, 3 livings at my disposal, viz:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">New Shildon.</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;350 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">net. 7500 people.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">South Hylton.</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;250 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">" 5000 "</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">S. Mark's Millfield</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;430 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">" 10,000 "</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>The Rev: Thomas Romans, ordained 1902, Curate of Staindrop. 1909.</p>
         <p>The Rev. H.G.H. Shaddick, ordained 1910 . . Stanhope. 1910. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>September 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I have read D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett's Article with much interest &amp; sympathy, and if I am unable to approve the practical proposals which it includes, I none the less applaud the spirit in which he writes, and the ardour of his desire to advance peace on earth. But I cannot bring myself to believe that any considerable or lasting result would follow from such meetings &amp; Conferences as he proposes: nor do I think that, in the present state of the world, much advantage arises from large &amp; eloquent statements of political ideals while the "details of problems" are ignored. It is precisely in their details that the problems of politics disclose their real difficulty. Before "letting one's self go" in the large freedom of the pulpit or the platform, the Christian Minister ought to picture himself in the Cabinet actually confronted with the necessity of taking the decisions upon which the safety &amp; prosperity of his own nation primarily, and finally of mankind must turn. Moreover, Christian experience does seem to me quite decisively hostile to these prompt heroick procedures which D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett seems to recommend. His language is, indeed, not free from ambiguity, but I think Savonarola's purpose &amp; method would be fairly enough described by it.</p>
         <p>At the present juncture, I can think of no better advice to give Christian citizens in every nation than that should support with all their power the League of Nations, and should seek to cleanse the public witness of the Churches from whatever <hi rend="bold">[95]</hi> [symbol] (and there is confessedly very much) tends to make their witness to "the things of the Spirit" practically unimpressive.</p>
         <p>I have so high a regard for D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett that it distresses me to find myself unable to endorse his practical suggestions, but it seemed to me uncandid not to say that that is the case. The world's escape from the supreme folly &amp; malediction of War must be gained by the slow and difficult process of bringing home to the reason &amp; conscience of civilized men the conviction that the objects for which War is alleged to be properly required can be secured by other methods, more reasonable &amp; more humane. In facilitating this process by creating that temper of Justice &amp; Fraternity which is properly Christian because genuinely human, the Church of Christ may confer great benefit on the world.</p>
         <p>Believe me, my dear Sir,</p>
         <p>Yours most faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>Sir Ernest Hodder Williams C.V.O.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The above was my reply to a letter asking me to comment on "an article of great importance, What has the Church of Christ to say? By D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> J. H. Jowett" which was to appear in the forthcoming issue of the 'British Weekly'. In this Article he suggested that on an appointed Sunday, the congregations sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> make a solemn declaration of their desire &amp; purpose for peace, &amp; their belief in the common brotherhood of mankind. He also suggested a great Christian Conference in London.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>We motored to Durham, and lunched with the Dean. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> was there. <hi rend="bold underline">It was oddly suggestive to observe that no one of us, Bishop, Dean, Canon, could conceal the sense of relief which was bred in our minds by the Archdeacon's<persName xml:id="590"></persName> death. Yet we were not ungenerous men, nor were we forgetful of the charitable rule, </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">De mortuis</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, but we all in our repective capacities had suffered so much, &amp; been brought to so great perplexity, by the behaviour of our deceased colleague, that we met with the irrepressible sentiment of satisfaction that now at least we were freed from our necessity of self&#8211;suppression and caution</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>There was a great assemblage of the clergy in the Cathedral, &amp; the general public nearly filled the nave. Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> read the lesson, May intoned the versicles etc., I read the Committal prayer, etc. &amp; gave the Benediction, the Choir did the rest. The urn containing the ashes was carried in the procession by Hughes, &amp; lowered into the vault in the Nine Altars by Jobling. The singing of the Choir – which has now reached a high level of efficiency – was exquisite, for the "Nine Altars" has admirable acoustic qualities. Immediately after the service, we returned to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>, picked up our bags, and motored by way of Darlington, Northallerton, Thirsk, &amp; York to Riccall, where we were the guests of Sir John and Lady Butcher. Lady Prothero<persName xml:id="664"></persName>, Sir John's sister, the widow of Sir George Prothero<persName xml:id="319"></persName>, the historian, was staying in the house, and also General Manning who said he had met me before.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>