<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A heavy sultry day, enervating to body and mind. Carȏe<persName xml:id="648"></persName> called to see the progress of the dilapidations He urged me to consent to the stripping of the ivy from the house, for, he said, it actually grew inside the rain&#8211;water pipes and burst them. I yielded reluctantly for I love the mischievous parasite better than the naked walls. After lunch I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, but soon abandoned the game as there was a threatening of rain. There was a concourse of bodies at tea. Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> and Elizabeth Smith<persName xml:id="3077"></persName> arrived during the afternoon, &amp; Ernest &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Campbell Dodson just before dinner. <hi rend="bold underline">These gatherings of guests play havoc with my work.</hi> I walked in the Park with Boden. He told me that his vicar, Manning, who was esteemed a liberal churchman, &amp; had long been Secretary of Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName>, is now turning to orthodoxy, is high in favour with the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's, &amp; has been made an hon. canon of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's. He said that Foakes&#8211;Jackson is reported to have broken with Kirsopp Lane. This would not be surprising for neither of them is easily capable of working with anybody else. I learned with some concern that the silly report, as baseless as It is absurd, that J.G. meant to send me to Canterbury, was being freely discussed in certain quarters. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Nothing could be more injurious to my public credit, or more likely to stain relations between the Archbishop and myself. It is difficult to see how I can take any step to restrain his idle and hurtful gossip without seeming to confirm it! </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>