<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A thoroughly wet day. There was nothing for it but to spend the time indoors. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dicey</hi> thanking her for the photograph of the old Professor<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, which arrived at the Castle on the very day of our departure. Also I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carissima</hi><persName xml:id="76"></persName>. The newspapers &amp; talk with mine host filled "the impracticable hours" until lunch time: and afterwards we donned mackintoshes, and walked out in the rain as far as the Manse, where we called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Knowles</hi>.</p>
         <p>The control of a Scottish churchyard is vested in the heritors of the parish, who alone have power to determine what monuments and inscriptions may be allowed. As the heritors may be numerous, &amp; scattered, they commonly delegate their authority to one or more of their number, who often associate the minister with them. This system is said to work well enough, but it has an uninviting aspect: &amp; certainly Scottish churchyards <hi rend="underline">look</hi> detestable. The income of the minister of Dalton is &#x00A3;300 per annum with a manse, and two or three fields. This is regarded as a fair endowment.</p>
         <p>We dined with Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Critchley, with whom the Bishop of Cork was staying. This prelate had until recently been favourable to the policy of the Treaty in Ireland, but now he has changed his opinion, and now sees nothing but disaster before the Irish Protestants. Many of these have deserted the country.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>