<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>I went to the cathedral and received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. A minor canon celebrated, waving his arms rather disconcertingly and gabbling so that I could not keep pace with him. The "Evangelical summary" was substituted for the Decalogue, illegally, but (as the Dean assured me) with the express permission of the Archbishop. The regime of lawlessness which is bringing the Establishment to an ignoble conclusion has its advocates in the Heads of the Hierarchy! The vastness of the Cathedral impressed me more than ever. My own Durham is almost small beside it, small but more sombrely magnificent.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The morning paper reports the confirmation of G. K. Chesterton by the Papist Bishop of Northampton.</hi></p>
         <p>The Patronage Committee sate for 3 hours before lunch, and for 2 hours afterwards. In the luncheon interval the Dean of York took us into the Cathedral<hi rend="bold">,</hi> and explained what was being done to the windows. Their brilliance after repairing is astonishing. The Lord Mayor of York invited us to tea in order to exhibit the municipal plate, which is ancient, beautiful, &amp; interesting. One piece, a tankard, was said (but I cannot believe it) to date from the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. The most sumptuous pieces were Caroline. I caught the 6.25 p.m. train to Darlington, and was there met by my dear William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; motored to the Castle. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>