<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Some while since I send a copy of "Anglicanism" to the Bishop of Zanzibar. Two days ago the book was acknowledged in the following letter which merits insertions:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Bishop</p>
         <p>Into the wilds of Africa, to a weary missionary bishop on his walks, came your book on Anglicanism, which you were so kind as to send me. I have waited to acknowledge it till my thousand mile tramp is well over, &amp; I'm a bit rested. I was really grateful for the book: &amp; for your kindness in sending it.</p>
         <p>You will not expect me to agree with you in your estimate of the English Church: I think we see things from two exactly opposite points: &amp; sometimes I doubt if we are looking at the same object! The doubt is heightened by your admirably lucid description of what you believe you see. This, however, makes life all the more interesting: &amp; some day we shall know what it is we were trying to describe.</p>
         <p>On one point I agree with you to the death: &amp; that is in mistrust of the National Assembly. For it is </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi> arguable whether you, or I, are right about <hi rend="underline">Ecclesia Anglicana</hi>: it is surely beyond dispute that the National Assembly is a freak, accepted by men in an hypnotic trance.</p>
         <p>With all best wishes,	</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely</p>
         <p>Frank Zanzibar </p>
         </div>
         <p>A damp dull day, infinitely depressing. After finishing the correspondence, I settled down to a sermon for Liverpool, &amp; wrote most part of it. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gaymer, the dilapidating contractor, came to see me. I sent him a first instalment, on Car&#x00F6;e's<persName xml:id="648"></persName> certificate, last night for &#x00A3;250.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A letter from Rait informs me that he has undertaken a memorial volume of Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>. Remembering the time and pains I wasted on the little Anson book, I compassionate him sincerely. He asks me to "write an appreciation of his personality". It is hardly possible for me to refuse such a request, but almost certainly impossible for me to satisfy it. For my knowledge of Dicey was late, intermittent, &amp; for the most part superficial. I never met him before I was elected to a fellowship at All Souls, when he was nearing fifty, and I was twenty one.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Ripon, where we arrived about 4.45 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; I went into the cathedral, &amp; saw Wilfrid's crypt &amp; the miserere stalls before the service at which I preached. The new reredos is a fine piece of work, &amp; makes an effective War Memorial. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>