<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>In spite of the gorgeous sunset, the day was wet and stormy. I wrote a sermon for use next Sunday at West Hartlepool. In the afternoon I walked in the Park with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. More guests arrived at the Castle viz. <hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Belloc Lowndes &amp; her daughter, President Richmond<persName xml:id="3112"></persName> with his wife and daughter.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> returned from his holiday, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> fetched "<hi rend="underline">Beck</hi>" from the station. The poor little beast was delighted to get into friendly hands after the novel experience of a railway journey<hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Cutty disgraced herself by biting M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Burgess's nose. The poor lady displayed much good temper, and appeared at dinner with a plastered nose, suggestive of a Monday metropolitan court</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">President Richmond told me that the Jews were becoming a menace to America.</hi> May had ousted the Irish from control of "Tammany", and were pushing themselves into the Universities. He spoke much, and severely, of President Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName>, who, he thinks, was solely responsible for the fact that the War became an affair of a party &amp; not of the nation as a whole. I asked him about Prohibition, which, he frankly admitted, was in principle unsound. Nevertheless, he was confident that the American people would not go back on the policy, which, in spite of many scandals, was justifying itself in practice. <hi rend="bold underline">I observed that the President himself drank wine at Dinner.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>