<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The rain continues still. After breakfast I had more talk with the General. He is plainly a man of considerable intelligence, of strong prejudices, and of a certain self&#8211;assertiveness. He complains that the local secretaries of the League of Nations Union are in many cases pacifists and even conscientious objectors: that <hi rend="underline">their</hi> advocacy of the League has little in common with the caution &amp; loyalty which, he says, marks mine: that they gain influence under colour of the approval of the League which I &amp; other bishops expressed; and that they are really "deceiving the people". In all this there is of course a measure of truth, but there is also a hopeless misreading of the situation. Richmond<persName xml:id="3112"></persName>, Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>, Ernest, and I walked for an hour in the Park, while <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> motored M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Belloc Lowndes &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burgess into Durham.</p>
         <p>D.W.<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> having definitely declined my offer of the Archdeaconry, I offered it to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Also I offered S. Mark's, Millfield to the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. Romans, Curate of Staindrop.</p>
         <p>James Parker&#8211;Smith<persName xml:id="412"></persName>, Maimie<persName xml:id="275"></persName> &amp; Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName> came for a visit. The party at dinner numbered no less than sixteen.</p>
         <p>I gave Ella the Italian translation of Richard de Bury's 'Philobiblon', a rather sumptuous volume with many curious &amp; interesting illustrations.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>