<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[147]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I did not sleep, partly because of the shunting and whistling of the trains which proceeded in the immediate neighbourhood of the house, partly because (with unpardonable folly) I had drunken coffee after dinner. So I reflected on the diocesan situation. Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName>, rather to my astonishment, condemned the Durham syllabus for Ordination candidates as too high. This must certainly be considered. Perhaps a conference of examining chaplains might be advisable. After all, if one insists on the degree and age limit, the examination is not of such great importance. <hi rend="bold underline">Most of Moule's candidates would have been rejected as without degrees, and above the age</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi> But any lowering of the published requirement would have the aspect of pulling down one's flag. "Needs must when the devil drives". Ordination candidates cannot be dispensed with.</p>
         <p>I left the Deanery at Carlisle, and travelled by way of Newcastle to Durham. At Hexham a lady got into the carriage, &amp; introduced herself as the person who told me how to hold the Baby at a Baptism in Ainderly Steeple, when I held a locum tenancy more than 30 years ago. She told me that her husband was the grandson of Archdeacon [Thorp], the first warden of Durham University, &amp; that he was the owner of the Farne Islands which he desired to sell.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[148]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName>,</p>
         <p>If the Boys have been baptized by the Congregationalist minister, and give you evidence of the fact, you must in no case re&#8211;baptize them. If however, evidence of their baptism be lacking or insufficient, you should baptize them conditionally. You will find the form for conditional baptism at the end of the office in the P.B. for the private baptism of infants.</p>
         <p>I think you should refuse to present the lad who "does not want to leave the congregationalists" if you are on other grounds satisfied that he is sincerely purposed to profess himself a Christian by being confirmed. It may well be the case that his feeling springs from a scrupulous sincerity, which is a temper in the things of the Spirit which we must seek to encourage.</p>
         <p>Very precious in the Sight of God is the candour of the young. I wish we could carry more of it into our adult life.</p>
         <p>Yours affectionately</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>