<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Keble's lines for this Sunday exalt the spiritual value of solitude in mountains.</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>No sounds of worldly toil ascending there,</p>
         <p>mar the full burst of prayer;</p>
         <p>Lone Nature feels that she may freely breathe,</p>
         <p>And round us and beneath</p>
         <p>Are heard her sacred tones: the fitful sweep</p>
         <p>Of winds across the steep,</p>
         <p>Through wither'd beats – romantic note &amp; clear,</p>
         <p>Meet for a hermit's ear, &#8211; </p>
         </div>
         <p>My edition of the "Christian Year" bears date 1844. Some one has written in pencil above this poem: 'The popish tendency scarcely contradicted by the last verse'.</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>'Raise thy repining eyes, and take true measure</p>
         <p>Of thine eternal treasure;</p>
         <p>The Father of thy Lord can grudge thee nought, </p>
         <p>The world for thee was bought,</p>
         <p>And as this landscape broad – earth, sea, and sky &#8211;</p>
         <p>All centers in thine eye,</p>
         <p>So all God does, if rightly understood,</p>
         <p>Shall work thy final good."</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is the Pauline claim: "<hi rend="underline">All things work together for good to them that love God</hi>".</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. All my guests communicated. I remained in my study until lunch time preparing my sermons for Sunderland.</p>
         <p>At 1.30 p.m. I left the Castle, and motored to Sunderland, where I preached to a congregation of members of Friendly Societies in the Parish Church. There were fewer than was expected, &amp; an air of listlessness &amp; unreality hung over pew &amp; pulpit. Perhaps the political crisis has killed interest in every other subject. I went to the Rectory and had tea. Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> was there. He talked to me gravely about overworking myself, and seemed really concerned, but what cure is there for the worry of such a time as this?</p>
         <p>I went to S Aidan's, a little church in the parish of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's Roker, which the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's finds rather embarrassing. It seems originally to have been an Adullam cave for discontented Protestants, who found the services of the parish church distasteful. That aspect has vanished, but a congregation deeply attached to the little Church exists, &amp; the problem is how to transfer it to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's. This is an instance of the folly of solving one problem by creating another. I dedicated two small windows to the memory of five old choristers who had fallen in the war, and repeated substantially the sermon which I preached in Ripon Cathedral. There was a crowded church. After service I motored back to Auckland, &amp; arrived at 9.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>