<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[224]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I walked into the City, and found that the Church Printing Society had moved from Burleigh Street to 3 Plough Court, Fetter Lane. I bought also some note&#8211;books and a device for "organizing" my literary work. This was with a view to Rede Lecture. I went into the National Gallery, and spent an hour looking at some of my favourites. Then I lunched in the Club.</p>
         <p>During the afternoon I wrote letters, talked to divers friends, &amp; read a detective story right through!</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" contained the short letter which I wrote as a rejoinder to Lacey<persName xml:id="1936"></persName>. From what the Bishop of Bangor said to</hi><hi rend="italic"> me on Monday, and from Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> observations last night, I gather that an effort will be made to induce the Bishop of Monmouth to give an undertaking not to repeat his "Use". In that event, the issue will be rather shelved than settled. It is sufficiently evident that the Welsh Bishops are much perturbed and perplexed. They were assuming that all things were going so harmoniously &amp; with such success, &amp; they are naturally chagrined at being established to the public as no more divided and orderly than the Church of England. I doubt not that they are more angry with me than with the Bishop of Monmouth.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>