<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[194]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I breakfasted with L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Scarbrough, who is very pleased with the political development. Then I walked to the Athenoeum. On the way I fell in with L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, &amp; walked with him as far as the Palace. He also professes to be pleased at having got rid of L.G. <hi rend="bold underline">In the club the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t </hi><hi rend="bold underline">David's had some talk with me about 'the Monmouth Use'. He agrees with me that the Bp. of M.'s letter in the 'Times' was quite irrelevant.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>I walked with Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName> to Lambeth, and spent the afternoon at the Bishops' meeting. The Archbishop made a woeful report of the situation of the eastern churches, and read out a letter which he proposed send to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bonar Law, </hi>and which he wanted to support. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName> and I raised the question of episcopal patronage. He says that L.G.'s speech at Leeds was not heard by nearly two&#8211;thirds of the audience owing to the bad acoustics of the Hall in which the meeting was held. He thinks that the Coalition was mainly wrecked by the unpopularity of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Birkenhead</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winston Churchill<persName xml:id="2441"></persName>. Athelstan Riley</hi><persName xml:id="213"></persName> caught hold of me as I was leaving the club, and talked about the ecclesiastical situation. He said that both he and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> thought that disruption could not be much longer averted.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>