<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Clifford Allbolt</hi>, Regius Professor of Physic at Cambridge in his opening address of the winter session at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's Hospital Medical School on October 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, spoke plainly and severely about "psycho&#8211;analysis".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"This 'psycho&#8211;analysis' was no new thing. For many a century it had been known by the churches, both in theory and practice, as confession and casuistry. The one implied the other, and broadly speaking, beneficient as might have been &amp; still might be its value in particular cases, yet, <hi rend="underline">on the whole, it had been condemned by the honour , good feeling, purity, and common sense of the majority of mankind</hi>. Yet after all this experience, it was now proposed to turn any teacher or incidental doctor who had a fancy for analysis to probe into the minds of adolescents and even children, &amp; this too often with dirty tools".</p>
         </div>
         <p>This represents the traditional view of English laymen, and it would seem that it also expresses the verdict of scientific men, whose special studies have compelled them to come to a conclusion on the matter in question. Yet "psycho&#8211;analysis" is urged on the credit of confession, and confession is pressed as the true religious analogue of psycho&#8211;analysis; and the amalgam of bad science &amp; worse morals is consecrated as an essential part of the Christian Ministry's task!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Reasons why there are few Ordination Candidates in Durham:</p>
         <p>1. The raising of the standard of the Bishop's Examination.</p>
         <p>2. The poor quality, social &amp; intellectual, of many of the Incumbents</p>
         <p>3. The unpopularity of the diocese, where there are far few amenities and an obsolete type of churchmanship.</p>
         <p>4. The "boycott" of the Diocese by the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" colleges.</p>
         <p>5. <hi rend="bold underline">The dislike of the reigning Bishop</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The last may be more widely operative than I know, for it is the case that I am openly opposed to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">all</hi><hi rend="italic"> the prevailing movements of my time – Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, Christian Socialism, Prohibition, Feminism, Spiritualism, Psych&#8211;therapy, psycho&#8211;analysis. I abhor them all, &amp;, of course they have their revenge.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I left the Castle at 1.30 p.m., and motored by an infamous road to Jarrow, where I preached at the Centenary Celebration of the Primitive Methodist Church. There was a crowded congregation, and a hearty &amp; reverent service. I was particularly pleased to see the Rector of Jarrow, and some of the other clergy present. I returned to Auckland through Gateshead, dropping Clayton at Heworth, where he was pledged to preach at the Harvest Thanksgiving.</p>
         <p>Edmund Parkes arrived in his car. After dinner we walked out to look at the Castle under moonlight.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bowman</p>
         <p>I saw M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Beaglehole on Sunday, and, subject to the necessary provisos, accepted him as a candidate for Ordination. He cannot, in any case, be ordained before Trinity: and I think it is rather premature for him to decide about his title.</p>
         <p>My only feeling (which I find to be widely shared by experienced parish clergymen) is that whenever possible a deacon should receive his title from a parish where there are other curates. Probably the best part of a young man's training comes from his fellow curates. This consideration makes me hesitate about definitely accepting the title you offer him: but if you repeat the offer in six months time, and there is no more suitable sphere for him, I shall not refuse to accept your nomination.</p>
         <p>Believe me.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         <p>The Rev. F. E. Bowman</p>
         <p>Vicarage. Wingate R.S.O</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>