<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and there presided over a meeting of the Archdeacons, Rural Deans, &amp; representatives in the National Assembly, convened to consider the proposed Dilapidations Measure. We agreed to support it. Then the Representatives took their departure, and the Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans proceeded to consider the date &amp; procedure of my projected visits to the Rural Deaneries. Also they re&#8211;elected Moscroft to be the Diocesan Surveyor.</p>
         <p>I licensed a number of curates, &amp; instituted Bishop Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> to the Archdeaconry of Durham. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter on "The Use of Monmouth" appears in the "Times", set out prominently on the front page with a heading "Bishop of Durham's protest". It must, I think, bring some kind of a rejoinder from Wales</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>I bought a copy of Scott's Poems, &amp; read through the admirable 'Biographical &amp; Critical Memoir' by F. T. Palgrave, which is certainly the best account of Scott that I have seen. This mighty genius, whose range &amp; insight 'place second in our creative of imaginative literature to Shakespeare' had yet some limitations. He was unable "to master even the elements of landscape drawing", and (like Dean Stanley) he had an 'almost total want of ear for music'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Grey towers of Durham! there was once a time</p>
         <p>I view'd your battlements with such vague hope,</p>
         <p>As brightens life in its first dawning prime;</p>
         <p>Not that e'en then came within fancy's scope</p>
         <p>A vision vain of mitre, throne, or cope:</p>
         <p>Yet, gazing on the venerable hall,</p>
         <p>Her flattering dreams would in perspective ope</p>
         <p>Some reverend room, some prebendary's stall,</p>
         <p>And thus Hope me deceived as she deceiveth all.</p>
         <p>Well yet I love thy mix'd and massive piles,</p>
         <p>Half church of God, half castle 'gainst the Scot,</p>
         <p>And long to roam these venerable aisles,</p>
         <p>With records stored of deeds long since forgot;</p>
         <p>There might I share my Surtees' happier lot,</p>
         <p>Who leaves at will his patrimonial field</p>
         <p>To ransack every crypt and hallow'd spot,</p>
         <p>And from oblivion rend the spoils they yield,</p>
         <p>Restoring priestly chant and clang of knightly shield.</p>
         <p>'Harold the Dauntless' Canto III</p>
         </div>
         <p>Did Scott ever really covet a canonry of Durham? If so, and his desire had been granted, would his sermons have made up for the loss of the Waverly novels?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>