<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[195]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the day at Lambeth from 10a.m. to 5.30p.m. – a dull &amp; wearisome experience. Taro discussions were illuminating – the one on <hi rend="bold underline">reservation </hi>raised by the Bishop of Norwich, the other on the training colleges (theological) raised by the Bishop of Chichester. The first disclosed the helpless state into which the Bishops have drifted: the last proved the incorrigible bigotry of the "Catholic" faction. The Bishop of Newcastle proposed, and I seconded a proposal to delete from the Report on the training of Ordination candidates a clause which excluded Ripon Hall on account of Major's opinions. This was shelved by a motion "that the Report to be received", a motion which the Archbishop assured me implied no approval.</p>
         <p>The discussion was illuminating. The seven bishops supported Major viz. Newcastle, Durham, Manchester, Worcester, Southwark, Oxford, &amp; Carlisle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of Oxford made a statement about his action towards the Duke of Marlborough.</hi> It appears that some members of the Oxford Diocesan Conference had intended to raise the question of the Duke's fitness to be a member of that assembly, &amp; that the Bishop had informed the Duke of the fact, &amp; told him that he was lacking in the necessary qualifications viz. possession of the status of a communicant.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury gives the impression of being very pleased at the Fall of Lloyd George.</hi> He will be able to carry more weight in Downing Street under the new Government. The Cabinet includes a strong element of "Anglo&#8211;Catholics" – L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Salisbury, Bridgman, and Edward Wood. Bonar Law, being himself a Scottish Presbyterian, will probably defer to the Anglicans in his Ministry when ecclesiastical affairs are in question. <hi rend="italic">The poor Church of England will be under the control of 3 Scots – the Prime Minister &amp; the 2 Primates!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> was in the Club. He says that he is being pushed for the bishoprick of Gloucester. That would be an excellent appointment, but there is a rumour that a Mirfield Father is not unlikely to be appointed.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Monmouth had a subject down to his name – 'Welsh Ecclesiastical Courts' – but asked leave to withdraw it as the hour was late. I noticed that all the five Welsh Bishops were in attendance. They are evidently disconcerted by the Monmouth Use, but rather puzzled what to do.</p>
         <p>I looked up in the Cambridge Historical Register the subjects of the Rede Lecture. They are apparently more commonly scientific than literary or historical, though there are sufficient instances of the last to justify my selecting a theme of that kind. But what can I do that w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be adequate in the time?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>