<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I am pledged to preach next Friday in the great Abbey Church of Selby. It is the anniversary of the Fire which broke out in 1906. The re&#8211;opening of the Nave took place in 1907, and that of the Choir in 1909. What shall I preach about? The church has rather an unusual dedication – The B. V. M. and S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Germanus. Germanus was born about 378 and died 448. I might, perhaps, dwell on the value of great historic buildings as embodying national memories, and symbolizing eternal verities. They antedate all our sectarian conflicts, they claim us by a title which provokes no resentment. Hence they have a real value in mitigating differences &amp; unifying sentiment. Then there is the value they possess as sustaining a standard of aesthetic taste in the community.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Haig, one of the tutors of the Knutsford Test School, came to lunch. I gather that "Father" Frere is interesting himself closely in the continuation of the school for civil candidates. This hardly has a reassuring aspect for those who suspect that the Test School will be an instrument worked in the interest of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism".</hi></p>
         <p>I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; was badly beaten. I read through L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Halifax's pamphlet, and Ralph's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> striking Essay, "Confessio Fidei".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>