<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[155]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I "fooled away" the morning in putting together some notes for the Scott Lecture. After lunch, I played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and was badly beaten!</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" joins in the cry against the Prime Minister, &amp;, of course, the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" "rubs it in". I suspect that a good deal of the rather base jealousy of <hi rend="underline">novas homo </hi>is being released, now the tide is plainly turning against him. There is, however, a widely extended, and, I fear, well&#8211;grounded feeling that our affairs have been badly mismanaged, &amp; that one element in the mismanagement has been the impulsive, versatile, and heedless temperament of the Prime Minister. I hate joining in a cry against a hardly pressed man, but I must needs think that if the English genius could replace the Welsh in the conduct of British affairs, all the world would gain.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Gateshead and I interviewed M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wilson at the Rectory before he left England for 2 or 3 years work in Persia. He hopes ultimately to be ordained, &amp; to settle in the diocese. I attended the Convention for the Gateshead Deanery, which will proceed in Christ Church, this week. </p>
         <p>I had some conversation with Canon Cunningham, who is conducting the Convention, with respect to Ordination candidates from Cambridge.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Bishop</p>
         <p>My whole attitude towards Revision is, as I said to the N.A., determined by the <hi rend="underline">arriere pensee </hi>of enforcing the revised book i.e. of restoring the regime of Law.</p>
         <p>I do not see how this objective could be reasonably proposed except on the basis of conceding all that can rightly be conceded i.e. all that really is consistent with our principles as a Reformed Church.</p>
         <p>Inasmuch as the proposed changes in the Communion Service have long been part of the Liturgy in Scotland and America, they can hardly be described as inconsistent with Anglican principles.</p>
         <p>Inasmuch as all the proposed changes are optional, so that the Churchmen who dislike them need not use them, I apprehend that there will be no grievance in practice.</p>
         <p>Therefore, I am ready to accept the proposals of the Committee, which, however, will not meet the demands of those for whose sake they are made. These latter – the Anglo&#8211;Catholics – will, I expect, wreck the whole scheme of Revision in order to perpetuate the present anarchy, which has served them so well.</p>
         <p>I think we shall probably be playing into their <hi rend="bold">[157]</hi> hands if we assist in wrecking Revision: &amp; that would be unfortunate. Whereas they will prejudice themselves in the general mind if they are seen to be factious folk whom no reasonable concessions can satisfy.</p>
         <p>In the interest of the fight <hi rend="underline">a outrance </hi>with the Romanizing clique, which is now carrying all before it, we should join frankly in Revision.</p>
         <p>I was watching the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> with the intention of cutting in on your side if there had been need: but it is clear that the bishoprick&#8211;makers are for the nonce "taking a back seat" in the Anglican Coach.</p>
         <p>My brother of Newcastle has just started to wear Cope &amp; Mitre, &amp; has printed the Anglo&#8211;Catholic programme in his diocesan Gazette. <hi rend="underline">Quis custodiet?</hi></p>
         <p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi></p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Norwich</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Walter Smith<persName xml:id="2803"></persName> told me that when, in the course of the East African campaign, he followed where the South African troops had passed, he noticed that the deer were generally limping: it being the Dutch notion of sport to fire broadsides into the herds! This has a repugnant sound</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>