<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[191]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">O God, forasmuch as without thee we are not able to please thee, mercifully grant, that thy Holy Spirit may in all things direct and rule our hearts, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Amen.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>The doctrine of grace, and the Trinitarian theology lie behind this brief and beautiful collect. The problem is exactly that which our blindness and instability suggest. Direction and Government are the havens for which we cry out. "<hi rend="underline">Show thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift my soul unto thee.</hi>"</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m<hi rend="italic">. How far ought an English Bishop to be troubled by the fact that he is generally disapproved, disliked, and denounced ? It must needs be a grave matter to dissent from the judgment and policy of the majority of one's episcopal colleagues. Of course one need not be greatly troubled by finding one's self condemned by those whose avowed principles require such condemnation, but when the men with whom one normally agrees, take a course opposed to one's own, what can one do but anxiously &amp; with scrupulous care go over the whole subject, &amp; re&#8211;consider one's own course?</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Wolsingham where I preached at Mattins. I lunched with the Vicar, called on Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> at Stanhope, &amp; Canon Crondace at Eastgate, &amp; preached a S. John's Chapel at Evensong.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[192]</hi></p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. W. Pattison, Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's Chapel&#8211;in&#8211;Weardale, was ordained as long ago as 1882. He was "educated" at Lichfield College, and has no degree. He started in the diocese of Ripon, but soon moved into Durham, where he has served since 1885. He has held his present position for 16 years. He is married, &amp; has several daughters. The Rural Dean describes him as a good man of a melancholy temperament. The circumstances that his parishioners are mostly dissenters does not perhaps tend to make him cheerful! I inquired about the owls which had built in the churchyard, &amp; was assured that they had brought up their brood successfully. One of the daughters, an amateur photographer, exhibited two very successful photographs of the birds sitting in their tree. Finding that I was interested in birds the Vicar launched out on the subject. His predecessor had been wonderfully successful in winning the confidence of birds &amp; beasts, being an eccentrick saint like S. Francis. The starlings came together in such a multitude that "you need an umbrella" when they fly above you!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Dissenters closed their chapels in order that they might come to church &amp; "hear the Bishop. I was impressed with the congregation which thronged the little church It was mainly composed of men, and its attentiveness was beyond praise.</hi> I preached on the Bible, taking occasion from S. Luke's Festival. The 109<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> psalm, which was sung during the service, gave me opportunity for saying some necessary things.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>