<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[219]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended service in the college&#8211;chapel and indulged in a general resurrection of dead hopes and plans! I went to the University Sermon and heard Armitage Robinson preach an excellent sermon of the spiritually edifying type from the best of texts – "<hi rend="underline">Come unto me, all ye who labour &amp; are heavy&#8211;laden, and I will give you rest</hi>". He took much the same line of interpretation as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> took at the Ordination in my chapel but with the difference between the men expressed in their sermons. I called on the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spooners</hi><persName xml:id="383"><persName xml:id="2162"></persName></persName>, and on old <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dicey</hi>. With the latter I had a brief and embarrassed conversation. After lunch, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank</hi> motored me and Hester Pinsent, a niece of the late law Lord Parker, to Cornbury House, a wonderful old mansion dating from the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century but mainly built by the great Clarendon in the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and now owned by a wealthy brewer named Watney. The owner most courteously showed us over the house, &amp; told us the history. It is full of priceless pictures and fine old furniture. I was particularly interested in a full&#8211;length portrait of Edward VI, which gave him a far more attractive and boy&#8211;like aspect than the more familiar portraits. We returned to All Souls in time for me to get to Balliol, and preach in the Chapel there. After service I dined in Hall with the master, and drank wine in the Common room – a very dull business.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>