<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote a sermon for the Sectaries, and played bowls with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Also, having heard from the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> David's that the Bishop of Monmouth was contravening the Constitution of the Church in Wales by his fantastick ceremonial at the Ordination on S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Matthew's Day, I addressed a letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> on the subject under the heading, "The Use of Monmouth".</p>
         <p>The author sends me a substantial volume. "<hi rend="underline">Shaken Creeds: the Virgin Birth Doctrine, a Study of the Origin by Jocelyn Rhys</hi>" (Watts &amp; C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi>). I should hardly have ^<hi rend="bold">thought</hi>^ that, at this time of day, that particular form of attack was worth making.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"> A certain Canon Bell is reported to have said at the church Congress that "a frank, unrestrained, and unashamed sacramentalism was the only medium through which religion ever had made or ever could make a general and catholic appeal to human nature". Bishop Chandler followed with the statement that "the church's system was summed up in the sacraments, or sacramental rites, of Confession, Unction or Laying on of hands, and Communion". If this be indeed the case, the Prayer Book must be a curiously unsatisfactory manual for Anglican guidance, for save in the case of the sick man, no provision is made for Confession, Unction is conspicuous by its absence, &amp; the Communion is normally to be received three times in the year!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>