<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A most beautiful autumnal day. I left Glasgow after breakfast, and travelled to Carlisle, where I was courteously received at the Deanery. I found Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> much stronger than I had been led to expect. After lunch we walked together for more than an hour, &amp; then attended Evensong at the Cathedral. A telegram from Evelyn Parker informed me that "owing to an outbreak of scarlet fever all arrangements for anniversary service at Seaman's Orphanage on Sunday have had to be cancelled". I decided in these circumstances to return to Auckland tomorrow, and sent a telegram to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to that effect.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic underline">Chesterton has been explaining why he has become a Papist. He says that he was led to his decision mainly by the Dean of St Paul's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and Bishop Hensley Henson. Apparently, a church which could tolerate two such men among its clergy could not be genuinely Catholick</hi><hi rend="italic">!!</hi></p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Stones the wife of the neighbouring Vicar of St Cuthbert's came to dinner. She said that one of her sons had just made his start at Durham School.</p>
         <p>Rashdall and I talked much on ecclesiastical affairs, but we neither of us said anything that we had not said a thousand times before; so that our conversation left nothing worth recording!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>