<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>My work was much hampered by the smoking of my study fire. This was at last remedied by a new sweep who brought down an immense quantity of soot. It appeared that the chimney had been practically blocked by an accumulation of soot at a bend which the sweep's brushes had not extended. The new man was acquainted with the geography.</p>
         <p>After tea Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Darlington, where I was taken to the Bank, and shown the falchion which ought to have been presented to me on my entrance into the bishoprick. It is more like a butcher's chopper than a sword, and suggested an Eastern origin.</p>
         <p>I gave an address on the Social Influence of Christianity in the new Church Institute, which has been created out of the disused parish church. Originally the building was a Baptist chapel: then, when the congregation was reduced to nothing, it was sold to Bishop Lightfoot, who made it the parish church of a new parish. Having become unsuitable for this purpose also, and a new parish church having been erected, it lay derelict save for occasional use until, on Warth's arrival in the parish, a faculty was obtained authorising its transformation into a parochial institute. There was a gathering of about 150 people of the artisan class, who listened to me with decorous but non&#8211;committal attitude of Northerners.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>