<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>October 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>,</p>
         <p>It is, of course, very futile to discuss personal futures, one's own or another's: but we are old friends, &amp; neither of us is, in any unworthy sense, an ambitious man: therefore I shall allow myself to say this.</p>
         <p>If you are offered the Bishoprick of Gloucester, <hi rend="underline">take it</hi>. Your doing so will not prejudice, and probably would facilitate, your going to London, or to one of the Primacies. It is to be remembered that these greater sees are generally filled by translation, and that there is a strong tradition to follow that policy in Downing Street. Indeed, if translation be allowed at all, it could hardly be otherwise.</p>
         <p>Moreover, you are now 60 years old, and, as men think now, that is a relatively advanced age for appointment to a bishoprick.</p>
         <p>Great as is the importance of your present position, and wide as is your influence, I have come to the conclusion that <hi rend="underline">you could do the best work now as Bishop</hi>. The Church of England needs a strong man with knowledge &amp; a considerable backing of public confidence <hi rend="underline">on the Bench</hi>. In some ways a comparatively light see like Gloucester would be better than an absorbingly heavy see like London.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p>No one who has not an inside knowledge of episcopal counsels can realize how greatly the Church needs strength and independence <hi rend="underline">there</hi>. Therefore, I do beg of you, if the offer is made, to regard it as the Call, and to obey.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Always your friend,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a long letter to Canon Guy Rogers on the subject of his proposed preaching in the <placeName xml:id="106">Westminster Chapel</placeName>. Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Rokeby, and lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Morritt, the wife of the owner who is great nephew of "the old squire", Scott's friend. The originals of Minna and Brenda in the Pirate were daughters of the house. <hi rend="bold underline">The late proprietor owned the great Velasquez 'Venus' which was purchased a few years ago for &#x00A3;45,000 by public subscription for the National Gallery.</hi> The owner offered it to the Gallery for &#x00A3;20,000. The offer was declined. Then Agnew bought it privately for &#x00A3;30,500: and sold it for &#x00A3;45,000! After lunch we walked by the banks of the Greta as far as the "Meeting of the Waters", and visited the little cave with the table on which Sir Walter is said to have written 'Rokeby'. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>