<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">O God give me a deeper sense of duty, a perception of the awfulness of spiritual ministry, a more complete devotion to the truth, a more vigilant and faithful life. I am Thy servant, O grant me understanding. Keep Thy servant also from presumptuous sins lest they get the dominion over me, so shall I be undefiled, and innocent from the Great offence. O Lord, my strength &amp; my Redeemer. Amen</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>A most beautiful morning after the rain. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. At 9.25a.m. I left the Castle, &amp; motored to Gateshead, where I was pledged to a series of engagements. At 10.45 a.m. I instituted Blackwall to the Vicarage of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Cuthbert. The congregation was smaller than I had expected, but, as most of the (205) stayed to the Communion, I conjectured that an effort had been made to confine the attendance to communicants and Stephenson confirmed this conjecture. Of all conceivable services, that for the institution of an incumbent might seem the most genuinely parochial in the full sense of the word, but the sectarian spirit which carried the Enabling Act, is prevailing everywhere, and, so far as they can, the Parochial Church Councils are "warning off" the parishioners <hi rend="underline">eo nomine</hi> from all concern with the "National" Church! Blackwall took his vows &amp; made his declarations in a clear voice which sounded sincere.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p>At 3 p.m. I gave an address in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's Church on "Religious Education". There was large assembly and it included a considerable number of the male teachers from the Council Schools of Gateshead. It is significant of much that no Christian can reflect upon without humiliation that <hi rend="bold underline">the Gateshead Corporation refuses to allow any minister of religion to be a member of its Education Committee.</hi> Stephenson assured me that the Committee treated the Church very fairly &amp; considerately, and said that for himself he did not regret the exclusion of ministers; but the rule is too humbling in its suggestions. At 5.30 p.m. a gentleman, named Beaglehole, came to see me. He is an aspirant for Ordination, &amp;, as he has taken, or is about to take his degree, and is of competent age, I accepted him, though he halts like the Patriarch on his thigh, &amp; has a mutilated right hand! I apprehend that by the canon law he wd. be disqualified, but we have to ignore much in these evil days.</p>
         <p>At 6.30 p.m. I dedicated an altar and panelling in S. James's Church, and preached to a very large congregation. I noticed with surprise that the altar was equipped with a locked receptacle for the Reserved Sacrament. This parish contains about 14000 people, almost all rather squalidly poor. The parish church is said (but I cannot believe it) to hold 600 people. This, with a small mission hall, provides all the accommodation there is for that great population, &amp; it is ample! We arrived back in the Castle at 9.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>