<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[227]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>November 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lee,</p>
         <p>The answers to your questions are as follows:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. There are no literary profits in 1921.</p>
         <p>2. I have no untaxed income from War Load.</p>
         <p>3. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Henson's<persName xml:id="112"></persName> Income from Taxed Investments for 1921 appears to have been no more than &#x00A3;158:14:0. My own private income is nil – save for &#x00A3;30 the interest of &#x00A3;600 War Loan.</p>
         <p>So far as I know, no part of my official income is derived from Tithes or payments in lieu.</p>
         <p>I return the enclosed papers, signed and directed.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>T. Hugh Lee Esq.</p>
         <p>P.S. The income from War Loan Section A &#x00A3;116:18:8 includes Wife's Income &#x00A3;86:18:8 my own &#x00A3;30.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[228]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in clearing off the correspondence which had accumulated. After an early lunch, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Barnard Castle, where I distributed prizes at the North&#8211;Eastern Counties School, and made a speech. The room was horribly over&#8211;crowded &amp; the atmosphere asphyxiating. We motored to Durham &amp; had tea with J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, after which I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; talked over some matters of business with him. Then we got back to the Castle in time for dinner.</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> bought me, as a birthday present, an admirable photograph of himself duly signed.</p>
         <p>After dinner I wrote many letters, answering those which my Birthday had brought me. Really the task of keeping fairly abreast of one's correspondence is a waxing burden: and leaves very little margin of leisure or energy for other things. The Rede Lecture hangs heavily on my mind. If theological and ecclesiastical subjects must be ruled out, as appears to be the case, my choice is disastrously limited. Even the age – the XVII<hi rend="superscript underline">th </hi>century – where I am most at home is so deeply tinged with Religion that it is almost excluded. Yet, a choice must be made, and quickly.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>