<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> &amp; I motored to Hartlepool, where I celebrated the Holy Communion at 11 a.m. in S. Hilda's and addressed the clergy of the Rural Deanery. There were about 25 of them present. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bainbridge</hi>, the bank manager, brought me some yellow forms to sign, and I wrote a cheque for &#x00A3; 400 for ‘<hi rend="underline">National Savings Certificate'</hi>.  In six years time, this will bring me &#x00A3; 500.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I had a brief and painful interview with a bibulously minded curate.  </hi><hi rend="italic">"Do you think I look </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough">that</hi><hi rend="italic"> like drinking?" he asked indignantly: to which I replied, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"Well, since you ask me: I cannot honestly say that your countenance provides a final disproof of the suggestion.</hi><hi rend="italic">" He was a heavy, fat fellow, with a rather bloated face, decorated with pimples!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then I shifted books to fill the bookcase which Ella gave me "as my birthday present", sending me the bill from the shop!  Also, I wrote letters, &amp; had an interview with the doctor.  Thus was another day frittered away, mostly in futilities, &amp; my mass of work is still unattempted!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
