<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[19]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent most of the morning in the company of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anthony Eden</hi>, who showed me the exterior of the Castle, which is most imposing.  Also I saw the great Graeco&#8211;Roman Vase presented by Sir <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Hamilton</hi> to Lord Warwick.  He found it in Hadrian's Villa, &amp; had it transported to England.  One head which had been broken off had been replaced by a representation of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Hamilton</hi>, on whom, however, the Hostile sculptor had inflicted a fawn's ear!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The quaint, little, truncated marriage service in S. Mary's Church went off without untoward incident.</hi>  Among the congregation were <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank </hi>&amp; his wife.  They had motored from Oxford.  The bride looked a mere child, although she was an "<hi rend="doubleunderline">innocent divorc&amp;#x00E9;e</hi>".</p>
         <p>I was immensely impressed by the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Beauchamp</hi> Chapel. The tombs, undamaged &amp; elaborate, must be unequalled.  The stained glass is of the best medieval work, &amp; there is an elaborate frescoe [sic] of the Last Judgement on the Wall.  A wooden piscina in the exquisite little oratory annexed to the Chapel is curious, and, as far as I know, unique.  The incumbent most civilly showed me the Chapter House, <hi rend="bold">[20]</hi> (for this was a collegiate church), which is now almost filled by the tomb of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fulke Greville</hi>, the poet, who was a friend of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Philip Sydney</hi>, &amp; state the fact on his monument.  There are many memorials of Sir P. Sydney in the castle.  Perhaps the most interesting is a <hi rend="underline">verse paraphrase of the entire Psalter, copied out in the poet's exquisite writing.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">After the wedding I was shown the dungeons</hi>, which are rather terrible, and pathetically adorned with the graffiti of the prisoners.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Warwick</hi> sent me in the car to Leamington, where I took train for Liverpool, where I arrived about 7.30 p.m., &amp; was met by the Bishop's car. There came to dinner Evelyn Parker, who is some kind of a connexion of Ella's. The Bishop's family were at home, the school vacation being still in process. The eldest, a lad of 18, stutters fearfully. He is beginning his course as a medical student at the university. The next, a bright looking boy is at Rugby. He has had some frightful internal operation, which <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to have killed him.  Then there are two younger children, a boy &amp; a girl, of whom the former is deaf.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
