<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We were but 5 – three maids, William, &amp; myself. The wonderful Hymn on Charity strikes a note, which it is good to hear, and hard to hold, in such a world as this.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I made an observation to William in the Vestry on the beauty of the Epistle, and added, "S. Paul was indeed great". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His answer amused and interested me. "Yes, my Lord, but I prefer S. Peter myself. He was so patriotic</hi><hi rend="i bold">." </hi><hi rend="italic">Am I mistaken in connecting his opinion with some observations of the Adjutant in whose service he was before he entered mine? The futile but valourous episode in Gethsemane, when S. Peter drew his sword on the high priest's servant, would commend itself to the worthy soldiers as "patriotic", &amp; would probably appear in his eyes the most attractive &amp; significant part of the Record of the Passion! I believe we go widely astray when we credit the ordinary layman, whose interest in religion is mainly conventional, with any very deep, coherent, or spiritual understanding of what he reads in the Bible, or hears in the Church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Charles and I motored to Westgate, where I dedicated some gifts to the Church, and preached to a congregation largely composed (as the Vicar assured me) of Methodists.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
