<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most unpleasant day, wet and stormy. I went in to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Board of Finance. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carlis</hi> presented the Balance Sheet for the year, which did actually show a small balance. But this happy fact must be discounted by the receipt of two "extraordinary" donations viz. &#x00A3;250 from the Lightfoot Trust; and &#x00A3;100 from myself.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> and I motored to Darlington, where I admitted the Rev</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> L.A. Hoare to the perpetual curacy of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Hilda's</hi>. There was a good congregation, but a very sparse attendance of the clergy. In my address, I emphasized the value &amp; obligation of house&#8211;to&#8211;house visitation, and made some severe observations on parsons' motors. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hoare</hi> is a good&#8211;looking parson, &amp; seems to promise well. If he avoids "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" extravagances, he will do well enough. </p>
         <p>I finished reading a rather gross &amp; very absurd <hi rend="italic">book, written in the interest of feminism – "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Salome, the Wandering Jewess by George Sylvester Viereck, and Paul Eldridge</hi><hi rend="italic">". It is soaked, saturated, &amp; sodden with Sex, and leads up to a conclusion of sheer Fiasco. It gives one furiously to think that such mad dreamers should have prevailed, &amp; it promises grave </hi>calamities as the effects of their victory are disclosed.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
