<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[11]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The frost shows signs of weakening.  I motored into Durham, &amp; attended the funeral of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Samuel Rowlandson</hi>, the Receiver of the Dean &amp; chapter. The cathedral was nearly filled with a congregation mainly of men. He was an enormously fat man, &amp; the wonder is that he lived to be 54 before having a stroke which was so swiftly fatal. He was an efficient man of business, &amp; well&#8211;liked. His death makes an end of a connexion between his family &amp; Durham Cathedral which has continued for 100 years. He had a remarkable power of drawing caricatures. The County Club is adorned with many of them. After I had read the Prayer of Committal, &amp; pronounced the Benediction, a salute was fired by a detachment of the D.L.I.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> came to lunch with an Ordination Candidate named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Athol Dalston Davis</hi>. He is 40 years old, and has had a rather unusual career. He seemed sincere. After they had departed I finished a sermon for Stockton.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Robinson was engaged in measuring the out&#8211;buildings, having therein William's assistance as tape&#8211;holder.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="bold underline">Pope's Encyclical on Marriage</hi> is well&#8211;received by Mussolini's press.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
