<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">,</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather was horrible, gloomy, stuffy, and wet throughout the day.  We traversed the distance (123 miles) between Auckland Castle &amp; Carlton Hall in the most depressing conditions imaginable.  We had tea in a roadside inn a few miles before reaching Doncaster, &amp; this was well enough, save that the room smelled villainously of fresh paint.  Our journey was saddened by the almost continuous spectacle of destruction which encountered us.  The roadside trees and hedge&#8211;rows, beloved of singing birds, which have been the glory of rural England are everywhere disappearing in order that wide straight roads, suitable for the frenzied motoring, which now is the habit of Englishfolk, may be constructed. It is to a lover of the country heart&#8211;breaking. There was extremely little traffic on the road, which surprised me, for I had supposed that the heavy goods traffic would have been unaffected by the weather. The slump in trade might account for much, and probably the holiday season has the effect of arresting commercial activity.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]    </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>Before leaving the Castle I wrote to Sir Thomas Oliver suggesting that he and Sir Robert Bolam should have a 'private and unofficial' interview with me to discuss the situation in Newcastle.  I expressed myself cautiously about my right as Visitor to intervene officially, not feeling very sure of my ground, &amp; being really anxious not to have that issue debated : but I assumed that there could be no reasonable objection to my being greatly concerned about proceedings which could not but affect the credit of the University.  If they accept my suggestion, &amp; we have a talk together, it is just possible that some middle way of conciliation may be discovered.  Even, if that be not the case, I shall be strengthened, first, by being better informed as to the facts, and, next, by having shown myself anxious to heal the feud.  The more I reflect on the matter, the more difficult and potentially mischievous does it appear.  I wonder whether the other new universities have' Visitors'; and, if so, whether the functions of those officials are anywhere laid down authoritatively.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
