<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[84]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">h</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A mild day, mostly bright but windy. I have <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">Lightfoot's Philippians</hi> for a Birthday present, as he attains the age of 27 today.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Conference Address. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Darlington, where I confirmed 99 persons in S. Cuthbert's Church. They came from four parishes – S. Cuthbert's, S. Paul's, Hurworth, &amp;, Ingleton. The four Incumbents – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jardine</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Faber</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Suthrien</hi> – came with their candidates. The males numbered hardly more than one fourth of the whole. There were no men in the choir. Generally I was not well&#8211;pleased. After service we went to the Vicarage, &amp; dined. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Esmond Drury</hi>, a fine upstanding young man, was there. He has just returned from Kenya, where, like so many others, he has tried &amp; failed to earn his living. His parents think that he is well&#8211;suited to become a clergyman, &amp; they are evidently indicating as much to the youth himself. But I am not very favourably disposed towards the now&#8211;common practice of turning to the career of the Christian minister after having failed to "make good" in some secular career. In any case, the young fellow must offer himself of his own unforced will, not to please even his parents.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
