<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Record</hi><hi rend="italic"> is unusually informing in its Church Assembly Notes e.g. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Durham's diatribe was generally condemned in the lobbies</hi><hi rend="italic">. One bishop characterised it as vulgar; another used a more startling adjective. To me it seemed like the swan&#8211;song of a broken &amp; self&#8211;ruined man. I thought he looked very ill &amp; unhappy." !!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">However the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic">" considers that the only advantage of the discussion was that "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">it gave the Bishop of Durham an opportunity to make one of his most brilliant speeches</hi><hi rend="italic">", and the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" quotes my speech with approval. The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Family Newspaper</hi><hi rend="italic">" accuses the said Bishop of "a lamentable exhibition of party spirit." – "Some of the phrases he used, and the bitter tone in which they were uttered, stirred the forces of partisanship in a most regrettable way." !!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yet few speeches were more loudly applauded, or more extensively reported: &amp; I have rarely received so many compliments. I suppose the lapse of a week has allowed the Protestant resentments, which were cowed for the moment, to recover their normal vigour. And, of course, these Trusts </hi><hi rend="italic underline">are</hi><hi rend="italic"> the back&#8211;bone of "Protestantism".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Richardson</hi>, the Vicar&#8211;designate of Pelton, came to lunch. I arranged to institute him Wednesday, May 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. He was evidently pleased at the prospect of independent work. The state of the Church in Pelton would appear to be deplorable, for no more than 10 children attended the children's service. The population is about 10,000.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Short</hi>, the Vicar of Kelloe, came to ask me to dedicate a memorial window in his parish church. It has been erected by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wood</hi> to the memory of his sister. I promised to do so on Palm Sunday evening.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfre Toomey</hi> came to tea, &amp; to tell me that the doctor advised him to go to a specialist in Newcastle, &amp; be examined. I fear that his health is going to become a grievous handicap on his clerical career. It is a great pity, for he seems to have the makings of an excellent clergyman.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi><hi rend="italic"> wrote to me from Keble College. He has been attending the Mission to undergraduates, which Archbishop Temple is conducting, &amp; seems to have been greatly impressed. The Warden of Keble has allotted to him a small prize for his English work, &amp; he is much exalted. He sends me his photograph. He is certainly one of the most promising of the Ordination candidates. He will not be ready for Ordination before 1932.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
