<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to Robertson asking him whether Birmingham had a visitor, and, if so, what were his functions, and how they were exercised.</p>
         <p>Then we strolled about the garden where the daffodils are in full glory, &amp; the apple blossom is breaking. We walked down to the riverbank and observed with surprize the new works for dredging up gravel from the river bed. The gravel appears to be of most excellent quality, and of unlimited quantity. A brisk trade is quickly developing. We called on the Vicar, a genial middle&#8211;aged bachelor with a wooden leg.</p>
         <p>There came to tea a party of the neighbours including M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin &amp; Gilbert, M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Hole and John (who is gigantic), a parson named, I think, Mitchell, &amp; others.  When these had departed, I strolled alone in the garden, which was vocal with birds singing their vespers.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin "gushed" about Lord Irwin: but I suspect that the cause of her enthusiasm is rather that excellent man's "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism", than his policy or achievements.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                                                                  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">And I must needs observe the unequal treatment which men receive in this world</hi>.  Had <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Irwin</hi> not been the son of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Halifax</hi>, and himself an ardent Anglo&#8211;Catholic, would his action in India have been so favourably regarded by all that important section of English Society which, so far as it is religious at all, is "Anglo&#8211;Catholick"?  Had he not been, as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi> himself told me that he was, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin's</hi> "dearest friend", would the Conservative leader have backed him so steadily?  Had he not been a Fellow of All Souls, &amp; in that capacity <hi rend="strikethrough">become</hi> the friend of the Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Simon</hi>, &amp; others, would his Indian policy have been so gently handled?  Finally, if he had not been the heir&#8211;apparent of <hi rend="strikethrough">a</hi> one great Yorkshire family, &amp; connected by marriage with another, would discontent with his public conduct have been so inaudible?  <hi rend="underline">He owes his exemption from the normal severities of public life far more to these irrelevant circumstances than to his own merits: The unconfessed, and largely unknown factors play a vastly greater part in fashioning personal reputations than is commonly realised.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
