<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930</hi> [sic] <hi rend="bold">[1931]</hi>.</p>
         <p>I made a few final alterations in my letter for the '<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishoprick</hi>', left the MS. with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carter</hi> as I passed through Durham on my way to Newcastle.  After lunching with the Bishop, who is more provokingly contented and optimistic than ever, I accompanied him to the Victoria Infirmary where the new wing for the accommodation of the Nurses was to be formally opened by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Runciman</hi>, the donor of &#x00A3; 50,000 towards the expense.  The room was densely crowded, and, the atmosphere really asphyxiating.  I made a short speech in moving a vote of thanks to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Runciman</hi>. After the meeting I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I motored to Eldon, and there instituted the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> William Brown</hi> to the perpetual curacy, to which he had been nominated by 'the Crown', i.e. "Labour".  There was a fair attendance, and a good service, but all the while there was a consciousness that everybody resented the appointment, &amp; looked forward to the new Ministry with apprehension.  I felt quite woefully unreal, a '<hi rend="underline">particeps criminis</hi>': but what can one do?</p>
        
            </body></text></TEI>
