<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I walked to Westminster, and attended the funeral of Archdeacon Charles</hi>, sitting in the stall which I occupied as Canon.  The ceremonial was simple but stately: but the array of copes &amp; candles, not to mention the prayers for himself would have startled, perhaps angered, his Protestant spirit.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> was a genuine, though, perhaps, an erratic scholar.  His enthusiasm for learning, his tireless industry in its pursuit, and his eager desire to communicate it were admirable.  I shall ever count it to myself for righteousness, that I urged on the Prime Minister his appointment to the canonry, saying that it was really scandalous that so distinguished a scholar should have received no Crown preferment.</p>
         <p>I attended the Assembly where an energetic debate on the Staffing of the parishes had been introduced by the Bishop of Southwark.  It had been my intention to make a speech, but, when I observed how many members were eager to hold forth, I changed my mind, &amp; said nothing.  Most of the speaking was very poor stuff indeed, especially the orations of "Jix", Mitchell, and Canon Hinde.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>As I was leaving Dean's yard, I fell in with Sir Charles Trevelyan, who pressed on me the importance of getting the H. of L. to pass his precious Education Bill.  I said that, if it were thrown out, it would be on the general ground that we must ^not^ place fresh financial burdens on the country at the present time.  I fell in also with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kate Pearce</hi>, the sister of the late Bishop of Worcester.</p>
         <p>I wrote letters of condolence to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Charles and to Colonel Greenwell.   <hi rend="bold underline">The death from pneumonia on the same day of both Sir Francis &amp; Lady Greenwell is really very tragic</hi>.  I sate beside the old lady at lunch in the deanery, Durham, on January 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> when we gathered to the cathedral for the Commemoration of founders &amp; Benefactors.</p>
         <p>I dined very pleasantly at Grillions.  There were eleven members present viz:–</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>1.</cell>
               <cell>Lord Fitzalan</cell>
               <cell>7.</cell>
               <cell>Owen Seaman</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>2.</cell>
               <cell>"   <hi rend="strikethrough">Lock</hi> Lloyd</cell>
               <cell>8.</cell>
               <cell>Lord <hi rend="strikethrough">Edward</hi> Eustace Percy</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>3.</cell>
               <cell>"   Darling</cell>
               <cell>9.</cell>
               <cell>Lord Bridgman</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>4.</cell>
               <cell>"   Londonderry</cell>
               <cell>10.</cell>
               <cell>Sir Richard Cavendish</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>5.</cell>
               <cell>"  Hugh Cecil</cell>
               <cell>11.</cell>
               <cell>The Bishop of Durham</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>6.</cell>
               <cell>Sir Austen Chamberlain</cell>
               <cell"/>
               <cell"/>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Darling told me that the Scotch verdict "non proven" set the prisoner ^free^, but that he could be re–arrested and tried again in certain circumstances.  L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Bridgman agreed with me that, had he been on the jury in the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rouse</hi> case, he could not have agreed to bring the wretch in "Guilty", and, I think, that was the general opinion, but all agreed that his aspect &amp; conduct in the witness box might have been decisive against him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Austin Chamberlain</hi> raised the question whether we ought to maintain the traditional non–party character of Grillions by electing the present Prime Minister, but there seemed a doubt whether he would accept election.  Should he "sound" him on the point before formally proposing him?  Several members urged objections to this course; &amp; it was finally decided that he should be nominated in the usual way without his knowledge.  I wonder whether there is any other country in which such a Club as Grillions exists, wherein no divergences of Church or Party are allowed to affect the frankness of social fellowship, &amp; where even the deeper cleavages of birth, wealth, &amp; professional habit are not given any recognition.  A single "black ball" excludes from election.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
