<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored into Durham with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>. She attended a County Nursing Committee in the Shire Hall, and then joined me in the Cosin Library, where I was presiding over the annual meeting of the Preventive Rescue Association. When this was over, I went to the Castle, and instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bell</hi> to the united parishes of Dinsdale with Sockburn, licensed 2 assistant curates, and gave a preachers's licence to a dingy looking parson from Canada. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles </hi>and I lunched together in my room. At 2 p.m. the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lewis Henry Webster</hi>, also a colonially ordained clergyman, came to complain that he was wickedly depreived of &#x00A3;2:13:0, due to him from the Vicar of Brandon. I noted the particulars of his plea, said that I must hear the said Vicar's defence before I could determine its justice, &amp; promised to send him my decision.</p>
         <p>At 2.30 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi> came to discuss the hateful business in Newcastle, but, though we talked much, I received little light, &amp; came away more perplexed than ever. At 4.15 p.m. the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Jarow</hi> came to tea, &amp; talked about diocesan business. Then Charles drove me back to Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
