<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I met an anaemic youth as I entered the Park this afternoon and supposing him to be <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ronnie</hi> Roddam who has recently been ill, I addressed him in friendly familiarity: after a&#8211;while, however, he asked me whether I was not mistaking him for somebody else!  He turned out to be <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alan Messenger</hi>, an assistant or apprentice in Boot's chemical store, who will be 21 on April 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, and has been ill for some weeks.  The poor lad looked terribly ill.  We walked together, &amp; I learned that I had myself confirmed him, &amp; that he attended South Church.  So I showed him the Chapel, &amp; we parted the best of friends.  As we approached the Castle, we encountered <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> accompanied by a young girl.  He is a very cool, not to say also brazen, young man.</p>
         <p>Then, I had an interview with Ronald Charleton Thornton, of Keble College and Wycliffe Hall, who aspires to be ordained in this diocese &#8211; a heavy shy youth, but probably genuine enough.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Simpson</hi> at Broad Leys Windermere reminding him of the duty of Easter Communion.  Domestic service, especially at holiday times, is not favourable to the fulfilment of spiritual obligations.  The way of religion in a secularised society is difficult.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]   </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>That excellent good fellow, Philip, came from London to consult with me about this tiresome &amp; complicated "Appeal to the Visitor". Ella met him with the car at Darlington, and brought him to the Castle. We went through the papers before dinner. The case certainly does not become less difficult the more it is examined. Both of us agreed that on the face of it the Professor has a case: and, therefore, that I cannot refuse to go into it. There are ambiguities which need explanation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic underline">The evening papers announced the death of Lord Stamfordham.</hi><hi rend="italic">  I first made his acquaintance in 1913, when, as Dean of Durham, I preached at Windsor, and stayed at the Castle.  Immediately I formed an attachment to him, which has grown steadily, &amp; was far stronger than the actual slightness of our personal intercourse might seem to justify.  I liked his simplicity, candour, &amp; frankness of demeanour, &amp; I think that he liked me.  We talked together with much freedom, &amp; I retain nothing but pleasant recollections of my dealings with him.  My last visit to Windsor was in May, 1930, and there I had much talk with him.  We corresponded since about </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Spencer Wade,</hi><hi rend="italic"> to whom he was extremely kind, and the appointment to Stamfordham</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
