<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went across to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi>'s house, and saw him before he left in the car for the Hospital in Harrogate. He looked better than I expected, but complained of much pain in his sciatica leg.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I walked in the Park during the afternoon. The wind was extremely cold.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Welch</hi>'s last letter from Nigeria is almost a treatise, for it fills no fewer than 38 fairly large sheets. With it he sent a copy of his report to the C.M.S., and a paper on "<hi rend="underline">Female Circumcision</hi>" which he has drawn up. He is evidently something of "a bull in a China Shop" among the C.M.S. Missionaries, and it is easy to see that he is by no means contented with his position. His observations on the religious policy of the British Government which protects Mohammedanism in Northern Nigeria and prohibits Christian Missions are rather disconcerting. We seem to be repeating in Africa the doubtful "neutrality" which we have maintained in India. I suspect that in the long run we should better serve the interest of the Africans if we adopted the policy of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlemagne</hi>, suppressing paganism with a firm hand, and imposing Christianity as a Government Religion.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
