<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[137]                                                               </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Ella went with me to Sunderland, in the afternoon<hi rend="bold underline">, where I officiated in the parish church of Bishopwearmouth, at the marriage of James Edgar Dobbie and Joyce Isobell Jopling</hi>. The Church appeared to be full, and everything passed successfully. A curious accident happened to me. I dropped my notes for the address unwittingly, &amp; had to do without them! They were found after the service on the flowers beside the Chancel Step. We attended the reception, and I proposed the Bride's health. Jimmie and his wife went to Norway for their honeymoon.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson–Walker</hi>, who, being himself a doctor working in Newcastle has personal knowledge of the academic situation in that city, came to dinner, and afterwards had much talk with me in my study.  He did not add anything material to the information which I already possess.  The precise position which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchens</hi> held in the College remains unexplained.  He held <hi rend="underline">some</hi> position there for two years before he was appointed Health Professor.  It seems difficult to suppose that that position was absorbed into the Professorship, and did not survive as an independent Collegiate position.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
