<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> January, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Claxton Turner</hi> went off after breakfast, and after finishing the letters with Charles, I essayed to do some work, but I had so heavy a chill that I could do nothing, being both voiceless &amp; "all&#8211;overish". I sent Charles into Durham, to do what was possible in transforming my engagements for the afternoon &amp; evening. He was successful, &amp; I had so much relief.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I promised </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi><hi rend="italic"> that I would send him a letter on the whole project of the Book on Bishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lightfoot</hi><hi rend="italic">.  He reigned at Auckland when rates were low, when income tax was stated in pence, when neither surtax nor death duties had been invented.  On the lowest estimate I have had to pay every year in rates &amp; taxes &#x00A3; 1500 more than he paid: &amp; if he maintained a larger household, wages were so low, &amp; the price of important commodities like coal </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">were</hi><hi rend="italic"> so small, that the gross expenditure in the establishment was probably not much greater than now.  No "Labour Party" existed: the last three Franchise Bills had not been passed: and the great local industries, mining &amp; shipbuilding were extremely prosperous.  There was no difficulty about raising money, &amp; there was no shortage of excellent Ordination candidates.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[36]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" was not as yet an organised force, coming between the Bishop and the young men, whom he ordained: nor was there that ravenous pursuit of young men by the Missionary Societies which has now added a considerable perplexity to diocesan life.  Social life was stable, &amp; regular.  There were no motors, cinemas, or wireless to distract &amp; divert the attention of the people.  Lightfoot was one of a small set of very able Cambridge men – Benson, Westcott, Hort, Farrar – who "boosted" one another with extraordinary pertinacity: and his policy of surrounding himself with young men, who 'saw light in his light' ensured in every part of the kingdom an ardent &amp; unfailing advertisement.  His merits &amp; his achievements were very great, &amp;, on any showing, he must take rank <hi rend="strikethrough">of </hi> as one of the most eminent of Anglican Scholars &amp; Ecclesiastics, but I do not <hi rend="strikethrough">think</hi> believe that he was quite so amazing a phenomenon as is generally affirmed, nor do I think that his administrative policy was  o sound or so successful as is commonly assumed.  In all the circumstances, he had a comparatively easy course, &amp; a posthumous reputation which was artificial.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[37]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I had so heavy a cold, and felt so infirm, that I decided to "cry off" my engagements, to the injury of my reputation, but in the circumstances unavoidable.  So I betook myself to bed soon after dinner, &amp; composed myself for the comfortless experience of a restless night.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">My mind returned continually to the subject of Bishop Lightfoot. How far am I swayed by a certain prejudice against a great predecessor, who is continually being paraded as the model Bishop of Durham, and placed in contrast, suggested rather than stated, with his degenerate successor</hi>?  How far am I applying to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lightfoot</hi>'s episcopal administration, a standard which it is impossible that he could have accepted then? He came to Durham in total ignorance of the working system of the Church: &amp; very naturally, he accepted &amp; urged forward with characteristic single&#8211;mindedness, the policies which were <hi rend="strikethrough">urged</hi> pressed on him.  He did not originate the disastrous project for dividing the historic see: but surrendered himself to what was then the fashion in clerical circles.  I find it difficult to acquit him of all responsibility for the "cheap &amp; nasty" parish churches, which were built during his episcopate.  He seems to me to have had little imagination, and less originality: but he inspired affection &amp; admiration in all with whom he personally associated.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
