<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[134]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant morning. We rejoice in it "with fear and trembling" having in mind the evil forecasts of the weather prophets, and the heavy commitments of tomorrow. But 'carpe diem' is a word of wisdom in April, and we seek no profounder philosophy.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8:00 a.m.  We numbered more than 20 communicants.  The males were the following: <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ashton</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leng</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Elland</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Bryden</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Bryden</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Paine</hi> &amp; his son.  My voice was husky and uncertain, &amp; I felt woefully feeble.  Nevertheless, I am glad that I was able to celebrate.</p>
         <p>I went to South Church for Mattins, &amp; preached.  My text was <hi rend="underline">1. Corinthians xv. 3&#8211;5 </hi>and my sermon a truncated version of that which I wrote in 1928 for use in S. Nicholas Durham.  There was a better congregation than I had expected, and it was largely composed of men &amp; lads.  A good contingent of C.L.B. sate under the pulpit, &amp;, though the sermon was quite beyond them, listened with exemplary attention.  They are looking forward to their visit to the Park tomorrow, but the weather!  All the omens are unfavourable, but the belief in miracles is ineradicable!  I celebrated the Holy Communion after the service; there were about 80 communicants, <hi rend="bold">[135] </hi>and again I was struck by the unusual proportion of males.  I took occasion to speak to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Toomey</hi>, urging him to see the family doctor when he was at home &#8211; he goes home by the midnight train &#8211; &amp; to get some advice for himself. I told him also that he might not be overmuch discouraged, that I was much pleased with his reading of the prayers &amp; lessons (lefsons). He is certainly a very loveable youth, but his future is darkly shadowed, &amp; I am not easy about him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> went with me to Durham, where we attended Evensong in the Cathedral.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi>, who had been taking the Easter duty at Pallion, joined me, &amp; carried the staff. I occupied the Throne, &amp; pronounced the Benediction.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I motored to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Tudhoe Grange</hi><hi rend="italic">, and preached at Evensong in the Church of St. Andrew.  Also I read the lessons in response to a special request sent to me beforehand.  There was a large congregation in which the sexes were fairly divided.  I was particularly pleased with the hearty yet reverent singing of the people.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Moore</hi><hi rend="italic"> has clearly made a good start, and the people like him.  He is young and unmarried, &amp; on both counts welcome to the young.  He read the prayers well and audibly</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
