<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Installation of the chancellor</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi> went off before breakfast bent on another whirlwind rush of official engagements.</p>
         <p>We all went into Durham for the function, which was admirably arranged, &amp; most successfully carried out.  The weather, which had been threatening, turned out well.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi> performed his part to perfection.  When he was brought in for installation, he was preceded by two pipers in the Stewart plaid.  The scene was really very impressive in the Castle courtyard, which was crowded by the dons &amp; undergraduates.  The service in the cathedral was <hi rend="strikethrough">very</hi> apparently successful.  It was well attended, not too long, &amp; well arranged.  <hi rend="bold underline">My sermon gave satisfaction to some, &amp; was closely listened to by all.  </hi>Among the recipients of hon. Doctorates were <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Dawson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Eddington</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Livingstone</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gwynne</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Heawood</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Londonderry</hi>'s speech was dignified &amp; excellently spoken. Then followed the lunch in Hatfield, and the Garden Party at the Castle, which were not more boring than such affairs commonly are.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
