<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from Newcastle an appeal to me as Visitor of Durham University signed by a number of professors &amp; others, asking me to intervene in the matter of the dismissal of a professor without reason assigned</hi>. I sent an acknowledgement, promising a reply in a few days time. Meanwhile I must ascertain what are the limits of my visitatorial authority, and discover something about the real causes of the appeal.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Robinson reports that he has succeeded in patching <hi rend="italic">up the quarrel between the Rector of Winlaton and his curate. I thanked him, &amp; wrote to the two peccant parsons.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We all motored in to Durham to listen to the music in the Cathedral. I had tea in the Castle with Ellershaw, who undertook to procure for me some necessary information about the Appeal. Then I went to S. Nicholas' Church, and confirmed 116 persons. The service was satisfactory save for the circumstance that a stout woman, whom I had just confirmed fell into an epileptic fit, &amp; had to be carried struggling from the Church. Pickering, the Vicar of S. Nicholas, and Thurlow, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's, are clearly good working parsons, and are making way with their parishioners.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
