<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Diocesan Conference</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored into Durham, where I presided over the "business" meeting of the Diocesan Conference. There was a fair attendance. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax</hi> excelled himself in perverseness and pertinacity. Indeed, I was forced to be almost brutal to him, which annoyed me though in the circumstances, I cannot blame myself. There really was not time enough for condoning his time&#8211;devouring irrelevancies. <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Mess</hi> introduced the subject of <hi rend="underline">Vagrancy</hi> after we had disposed of the Budget.</p>
         <p>I gave lunch to <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Mess</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephenson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spurrier</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carter</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi>.</p>
         <p>After the Conference had ended, the Bishop of Jarrow came to my room for tea, &amp; we discussed this puzzling business in Newcastle. He thought that I could not decently refuse to receive the deputation of Professors, since they ask to be received; but I don't see how I can fitly as Visitor interfere with the action of the authorities of the College of Medicine so long as their action is legal. Yet the Visitor's jurisdiction is rather concerned with equity than with law.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
