<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A woeful dull wet day. After breakfast I left Park Lane, and went to the Athenæum, where I employed myself in writing letters, including one to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> protesting against the inclusion in the Persian Art Exhibition of Item. 123. which in the Catalogue is thus described:&#8211;</p>
         <p>["]123. Cope, brocaded with silk tissue, polychrome figures on silver ground. Early xviii cent. <hi rend="bold underline">Lent by Soviet Union Government</hi>.["]</p>
         <p>I ended my letter with the question. Is Art as morally callous as Commerce? Probably I have made an ass of myself, but possibly not.</p>
         <p>As I was leaving the club, I was hailed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Clayton</hi>, who had come up to London in obedience to a telegram summoning him to attend at the Temple, and have his voice tried. He is one of the four "selected" candidates for the vacant Readership. He seemed to be much pleased with the courtesy of the Benchers, &amp; to be in some hope of the appointment. May he not be disappointed! We walked together to Westminster Abbey, where we attended Evensong. Afterwards, he went his way: and I went in to the Deanery, and had tea with the Dean, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Foxley Norris, and much talk.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked to the Athenæum, and wrote to Ella and Charles. Then I drove to the Temple, and, after some difficulty in finding the Master's House, reached my destination. I found the new Master, (Rev. S.C. Carpenter) in his study. He is a tall, well&#8211;built man, dark, with strongly&#8211;marked features, and a distinguished air. We talked for an hour, and then went to dress for dinner.</p>
         <p>Judge Tobin, the Treasurer of the Middle Temple dined. He lives in the Temple, almost the last of the Benchers to do so. He is civil, ingratiating, and talkative, but does not attract me. Mine host's "family" consists of his wife, a daughter (aged 15.), a nephew (the son of Duncan Jones, the Dean of Chichester), and a M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Thomas, wife of a Manchester incumbent, who is visiting. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Carpenter appears to be an ardent advocate of "feminism" – a fashionable folly to which I myself am relentlessly opposed. We had much conversation, but I can recall nothing worth remembering. When I went to bed, I discovered that my pyjamas had not been packed! So I slept in borrowed garments!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
