<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A heavy atmosphere with promise of thunder!  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> went off to visit <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Quirk</hi> in order that they might be out of the way of the Ordination candidates.</p>
         <p>I managed to finish the Hereford Sermon, but it was something far indeed from what I had intended. My right hand has lost its cunning.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park which was so wet by reason of the 'fret', which enwrapped the land like a pall, that I had to change when I got home.</p>
         <p>The Ordination candidates arrived in time for dinner, &amp; so did <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>, the Vicar of S. Gabriel's, who is to give the addresses. After dinner I took him to my rooms, &amp; gossiped with him till Compline at 9.45 p.m. when everybody went to their bedrooms.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi> and sent him the Sermon on Privilege which I preached on May 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1913, in Durham Cathedral. He was then in his cradle, &amp; I was Dean of Durham. If all goes well, and such is God's Will, he will come here in five years' time as a candidate, &amp; I shall be looking forward to the pleasure of ordaining him.  Much may happen in five years, &amp; it were rash to count much on any terrestrial projects.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
