<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A mild beautiful morning with much jubilation of nesting birds, and a final disappearance of the snow.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but 6 communicants. The Gospel as history is intolerable: as an interpretation of history luminous &amp; satisfying. Christ could not have actually spoken thus to the Jews: but the Words attributed to Him do sum up most truly the essential meaning of His intercourse with them, &amp; of their rejection of Him.</p>
         <p>I finished and despatched a letter to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>. It occurred to me that it might be judicious for me to inform myself of the facts about this crisis in the College of Medicine from an independent source. So I wrote to Sir <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Marris</hi> suggesting an interview.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> went with me to West Hartlepool, where I preached in S. Paul's Church at Evensong. My text was S. John viii. 46. "<hi rend="underline">Which of you convicteth me of sin? If I say truth, why do you not believe me</hi>?" There was a considerable congregation, and, though there were certainly many bad colds, there was quite a reasonably close attention. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
