<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, Thursday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.: and attended Evensong in the ruins of <hi rend="underline">Finchale Priory</hi> at 6.30 p.m.  There was a considerable congregation which would have been much larger if the weather had been less threatening.  I took the precaution of standing with the wind behind me, when I preached, and by so doing succeeded in making myself audible to most of the assembly.  The sun shone brightly, and illumined a very impressive spectacle.  But the frequent clicking of numerous cameras disturbed me.  On the whole, however, I was well&#8211;pleased, &amp; in an expansive moment said that I would contribute &#x00A3;10 to the S. Oswald's Restoration Fund for which a collection was made.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from Prof. Hutchens a letter asking leave to withdraw his appeal to the Visitor.  I sent him a civil letter indicating my consent</hi>.  This relieves me of a formidable perplexity, but it is not very easy to see how some of these Newcastle academicks can avoid a consumption of their own words on a scale which would shipwreck any ordinary digestion even in these days of rapid &amp; frequent <hi rend="color(202124)">tergiversation</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My letter appears in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> under the heading, "Caste and the Catechism".  It is on the front page, so can hardly escape notice.  I think that it was probably worth writing.</p>
         <p>I received from my Chancellor an approbation of my decision on the meaning of residence, which indicated a certain reluctance to pronounce even so general an "opinion" without having actually seen the Cathedral statutes for himself.  This seemed to me so natural &amp; reasonable that I sent him the volume of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchinson</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">History &amp; Antiquities of Durham</hi>, which contains a faithful &amp; sufficient summary of the said statutes.</p>
         <p>Speaking in the open air is beyond all question far more laborious than speaking within doors. It has, moreover, great disadvantages, for most of the orator's play with his voice is rendered impossible. He must need speak with all possible energy: there can be no variety in his tones. Then, if there be (as was the case this afternoon) any considerable wind, the attention of the congregation will be diverted by the spectacle of the orator's hair being blown wildly about his head, &amp; if he have much hair, the effect may be highly ludicrous.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
