<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fine, rather sunless, &amp; very warm day. I worked at the sermon for the Cathedral and (after a fashion) finished it.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I walked in the Park.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Paine</hi>, who is in charge of the building work here, tells me that the men whom he is employing are far better workers than the men whom he employed in the South, that they are respectful, &amp; do an honest day's work. Moreover, he is able to enforce the rule that there shall be no smoking during work.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The papers give prominence to a Resolution of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">British Legion</hi><hi rend="italic"> at its annual conference affirming the value of Remembrance Day, &amp; ordering </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'that a copy of this resolution be </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough underline">sent</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> forwarded to the Prime Minister and to the Bishop of Durham</hi><hi rend="italic">'. A certain M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Larkins</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Maidstone who proposed the resolution informed the Conference that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'the reference to the Bishop of Durham had been inserted at the instance of a "Padre" who was 100 per cent disabled</hi><hi rend="italic">'.  The Rev. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hugh McMullan</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Norwich said ‘</hi><hi rend="italic underline">that it would be more dignified if the proposal to send the resolution to the Prime Minister &amp; the Bishop of Durham were deleted</hi><hi rend="italic">.'  However the original form of the resolution was adhered to.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
