<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[120]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi> suggesting that it might be advantageous if he and I talked over the situation in the College of Medicine privately and unofficially.</p>
         <p>Also, I wrote to my Chancellor saying that I desired to see him, &amp; proposing that he should come here next week.</p>
         <p>I walked around the Park in the afternoon. The brilliant weather made everything delightful. Falling in with five out–of–work lads, who were all in the C.L.B., we had much converse, &amp; I shewed them the Conservatory &amp;c.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charle</hi>s and I motored to Hartlepool, where I confirmed about 100 persons in the noble parish church.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Paine</hi>, who chose the stone for Car&amp;#x00F6;e's restoration, (who now occupies the rooms at the Gate House while he superintends the work of reconstructing the Stables, went with us in order to see the restored church.  Salter presented 16 of the Boys from the <hi rend="underline">Boys' Brigade</hi> among his male candidates.  Most of them were about 16 years old, an age which he prefers to a younger period: and in this matter I incline to agree with him.  After the Service we looked at the Galilee porch, which The Freemasons have restored, and which is to be dedicated in May.  It is a fine addition to a fine Church.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
