<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930</hi>[sic] <hi rend="bold">[1931]</hi>.</p>
         <p>The frost continues, &amp; there is a tendency to fog.  I read two chapters of Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Quick's</hi> book on the Christian Sacraments<hi rend="underline">, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; was rather surprized to find that he attaches very little importance to the Dominical institution of the Holy Eucharist.  Plainly he is immersed in the sophistries of the "Catholick Modernists</hi>".</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park, where a large number of lads from the Unemployment Training Centre were sliding on the frozen water beyond the goal posts, while others kicked about a football on the hard ground.  There were many pit&#8211;ponies in the park, about 100.  I was told by the two men who were "rounding them up". The beasts feel the cold, &amp; there have been some deaths from chest diseases. They stand about, &amp; take no exercise.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi> arrived about 6 p.m.  He tells me that the Prime Minister is going to appoint a woman to succeed <hi rend="doubleunderline">Middleton</hi> as 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Estates Commissioner!!  Could humiliation be greater for a Church which claims to be Catholick &amp; Apostolick?  To have "Labour" directly concerned with administering the property of the Church of England opens the door to grave trouble. </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
