<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather has become milder, and the snow has nearly vanished. There is much domestic activity about birds in general, and rooks in particular. The mud in the drive is disgraceful &amp; inconvenient.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received from Newcastle a numerously signed letter from the Lecturers of the University supporting the Appeal of the Professors</hi>. I have no notion what to do! I wrote for counsel to my Chancellor, to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi>, and the Master of Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge.</p>
         <p>An Ordination aspirant named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jeffries</hi> came to see me. He was under the impression that "<hi rend="underline">literate</hi>" meant, not a man without a degree, but a man exempt from all examinations: and his disappointment when he learned that an examination was indispensable disclosed both the nakedness of his mind and the strength of his error. I required more personal references.</p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to West Hartlepool, where I confirmed 186 persons in S. Aidan's Church, most of whom were males – an unusual &amp; refreshing spectacle! They came from the two parishes of Stranton and S. Aidan's. The four clergy therein are comparatively young and vigourous.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
