<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 14, 1930</hi>[sic] <hi rend="bold">1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received a very insolent letter from the new Anglo&#8211;Catholic Vicar of S. James, Darlington, <hi rend="doubleunderline">J.C.R.C. Coen</hi>, from whom I had required particulars of the case for sanctioning the confirmation of a number of under&#8211;aged candidates. I returned a mild but, perhaps, sufficient answer.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">William Suthren</hi>, an Ordination candidate, came to lunch. He is one of the band of lads from S. John's, Stockton, who are seeking the Ministry, a good lad enough but not strong.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joyce Jobling</hi> came to lunch.  They have fixed April 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> for their wedding day: &amp; are fussing about furniture etc.</p>
         <p>I paid <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;1051:10:0</hi> on account of income tax and surtax.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Beamish, and there I dedicated the tower, bells, vestries and chancel, which have been added to the parish church.  Colonel <hi rend="doubleunderline">Turnbull</hi> unveiled a tablet to an officer named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Forster</hi>.  I preached a dull sermon.  The Church was crowded.  There was a considerable gathering of clergy, including the Rural Dean, Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi>. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
