<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Atkinson</hi>, the vicar of Silksworth, came to lunch.  He reported to me the actual behaviour which led him to report <hi rend="doubleunderline">Illingworth</hi> to the Rural Dean.  I wrote to the latter, cancelling his permission to officiate in the diocese: &amp; to the Rural Dean informing him of my action.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi> came to say 'Goodbye', before returning to Oxford.  He has been happy at South Shields, but has clearly missed the devotional note to which he has been accustomed.  The rush and hustle of the parish are stimulating up to a point, but then there is a "felt want" which they do not satisfy.  It is a dark shadow on our Church life that there is no security of doctrine or discipline.</p>
         <p>I had a hectic three&#8211;quarters of an hour<hi rend="italic"> with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev. R.A. Jardine</hi><hi rend="italic">, Vicar of S. Paul's, Darlington.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My "indictment" was arranged under 6 heads viz:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">1. His letter in the parochial magazine </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">2. His doctrine about the Resurrection of Christ.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">3. His preaching in Dissenting Churches.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>4. His failure to pay his parochial Quota to the Diocesan Fund.</p>
         <p>
	 <hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>5. Neglect of parochial duty.</p>
         <p>6. Allowing the Church Army Captain to conduct funerals in the cemetery.</p>
         <p>I added some warning words about the local rumours as to his non&#8211;payment of his debts. On the whole, he took my censures, which were severe enough, very meekly, and finally promised amendment. <hi rend="bold underline">He is a poor, unstable creature, with all the faults of his dissenting breeding uncorrected, but linked with the pomposity of the Establishment!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then I had an interview with an Indian medical student from Leeds, who, having failed to obtain his degree in that University, thought he might be able to obtain it in Durham if he had a recommendation of that 'man of God' the Bishop! I had some difficulty in making him understand that neither as Bishop nor as Visitor of the University could I do what he wanted!</p>
         <p>Charles and I walked for 3/4 of an hour in the Park, where the birds were singing their Evensong. Who could grudge the feathered singers their fees in fruit, who has listened to their music in the spring?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
