<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Hodgson</hi> a long and lamentable letter about that hapless <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi>, who hangs about at home without plan or purpose. There is nothing that I can do for him: but it seems horrible to have the wretched youth to the fate of loaferdom.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to West Hartlepool, where I confirmed 75 persons in Christ Church. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Poole</hi> was present though suffering from Influenza: and both the other Incumbents were reported sick. Their curates represented them. There appears to be something like an epidemic of Influenza in the diocese: and many deaths take place from pneumonia.</p>
         <p>The polling for the Durham County Council yesterday confirms the dominance of Labour in this unhappy diocese. I suspect that the General Election will have much the same result. There is, indeed, much discontent in the Labour Party, but that is not because of the recklessness of expenditure which the Government has shown, which is the real justification for turning it out, but because the expenditure has not been reckless enough to answer to the Communist expectations. The disaffected Socialists are not likely to transfer their votes to either of the other parties, which are agreed in preaching the necessity of economy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"Indeed it is said in the book of Job, that the worship of the sun and moon was '<hi rend="underline">an iniquity to be punished by the judge</hi>'(v. Job. xxxi. 26.28). And this, though it is not so much as a precept, much less a general one, is, I think, the only passage of Scripture, which can with any colour be alleged in favour of persecution of any sort: for what the Jews did, and what they were commanded to do, under their theocracy, are both quite out of the case."</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Butler</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Sermons</hi>. p. 263/4.</p>
         <p>I received from old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi> a grateful letter acknowledging my notice of dismissal and announcement of his pension. I signed the document sent by Q.A.B. which enables me to raise a loan of &#x00A3;900 in order to defray my share of the expenditure on the re construction of the stables. It is to bear interest at 4%, and the capital sum is be paid in 25 annual payments of &#x00A3;26. So my income will be reduced by no less than &#x00A3;62. In view of the practically certain increase of Income tax and surtax, I could wish that I had not consented to the re construction of the stables. But something h<hi rend="underline">a</hi>d to be done with Park Gates House.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
