<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip</hi> returned to London, taking with him the papers relating to the Newcastle appeal.  When he has digested them, &amp;, perhaps, taken further advice, he will let me have his considered opinion.</p>
         <p>After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Easington Colliery, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert</hi>, the Vicar, is <hi rend="underline">hors de combat</hi>.  As it appears to be impossible to find a clergyman to take his place, I have authorised the closing of the church on Easter morning, and promised to send <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> to take the Celebration on Low Sunday.</p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to S.Helens Auckland, where I confirmed 85 persons from the two parishes of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's and S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peters, Bishop Auckland.  Males were in a marked majority.  In this parish there is much unemployment, a fact which is generally stated to have an unfavourable effect on everything religious.  The Vicar said that six of his candidates, who had gone into domestic service, were not allowed by their employers to come to the Confirmation, although he had been at the pains of writing to ask for the requisite permissions.  This is equally unusual and deplorable.</p>
         <p>The wind today has been bitterly cold.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
