<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Snow had fallen during the night: and according to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Elland</hi> there were 16 degrees of frost. This menaces the wall flowers, and arrests the crocuses.</p>
         <p>I was driven from my study by a smoking chimney, &amp; took refuge in the smoking&#8211;room. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Lost</hi> came to see me about getting additional aid for the Barrington School from the Eccles.' Com<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi>. I told him that he had better write directly to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Downing</hi>. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilburn</hi> came to lunch, &amp; to talk about his vacant assistant curacy. I fear that from the account he gave of his parish, the Church is a languishing condition. About 15 confirmation candidates out of a population of 7000 tells its own tale. He did not seem to appreciate the gravity of the situation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Stockton, where I confirmed 175 persons in the parish church. In spite of the fact that the organ was out of use, the service was hearty and also reverent. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petrie</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bott</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Champion</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Coen</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gill</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lamb</hi> were the clergy present. Before the service I had a short interview with the ex&#8211;papist woman from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petrie</hi>'s parish, who desires to become an Anglican – a simple poor creature whom any church would suit.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
