<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright warm day, but I felt too ill to enjoy it.  I walked round the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullagh</hi>, but was very exhausted. This indisposition is enigmatic &amp; untimely.</p>
         <p>Charles accompanied me to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, where I was the "principal speaker" at a "circuit rally" of the Wesleyans.  The Chapel was well&#8211;filled; and the proceedings were less repugnant than is generally the case with Sectaries.  The chairman was W. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Doggart</hi>, the owner of many shops in this district, a thriving Baptist. I spoke for 35 minutes on the Sunday question, and probably startled some of the audience by my brusque condemnation of "Sabbatarianism". However they were very attentive, &amp; applauded quite adequately.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Newsom</hi> wrote to say that Selwyn is filled for next term, &amp; that the most he could do for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi> would be to place his name on the waiting list.  This is disappointing.  I wrote forthwith to Keble.  Certainly the impression of that college which I have received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi> has been favourable: but <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth's</hi> lamentable failure has made me doubtful about Oxford, although <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick's</hi> character and training are better suited for the experiences of an University.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
