<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[']It would be as easy to write a poem or a symphony by a committee as to promote the study of human problems by physically arranged groups.  Can really first–rate minds, working in various fields, be artificially and mechanically brought to co-operate in their study, or is anything new likely to be accomplished, if quite ordinary persons mechanically pool their activities in a "clearing–house"?[']</p>
         <p>Flexner 'Universities' p. 118</p>
         <p>But such co-operation as is here justly condemned is the distinctive method of our reforming ecclesiastics, who are now in the seats of ecclesiastical power.  "Copec" was its supreme illustration: and it is 'the way of spiritual renewal', which is now pressed on the clergy <hi rend="underline">ad nauseam</hi>. "Cooperative thinking" is to provide the solution of all our problems: but this, as Swift would say, is 'in the propriety of language', no thinking at all. The "group method" is as futile as it is fashionable.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Budget does not add to direct taxation, but it simply postpones the financial crisis until next year, when probably the whole situation will have worsened.</p>
         <p>I walked around the Park after lunch, to the accompaniment of thunder.</p>
         <p>Old Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Croudace</hi> discussed with me his resignation both of his parish, and of his rural deanery.  The first is in the patronage of the Bishop of Ripon: the last is in mine, &amp; will be hard to fill.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Bruce</hi> and his friend <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jim Crawford</hi> came to see the Chapel, and to return the umbrellas, which we left last Wednesday.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Linnell</hi><persName xml:id="5468"></persName> came to tea.  He had 60 communicants on Easter day out of a population of 750, and thought it good!!! </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi> went with me to Stanley where I confirmed 62 persons, very fairly divided between the sexes.  There was not a large congregation, a circumstance which may perhaps be explicable by the weather.  The Vicar, Tindal, is not much to look at, but he seems to be keen about his work.  Satley, Thornley, and Tow Law sent candidates. The wind was blowing a gale when we left the church.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
