<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull cloudy morning, cold intending to rain, very depressing. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8:00 a.m. We numbered but six communicants including myself.</p>
         <p>I prepared notes for a sermon to Boys and about Boys, which I promise to preach tonight in South Church when, after Evensong, I make a presentation to the Commanding Officer of the local C.L.B. What fellowship can an old man, nearing 70, have with boys, especially when he is one of those unfortunates respecting whom the saying holds that "<hi rend="underline">he never was a boy</hi>"? To be able effectively to address boys, a man ought to be able to draw on the treasury of his own experiences: but this I cannot do, since my own boyhood was nearly destitute of the normal interests. Observation and imagination, even when linked with interest and goodwill, are poor substitutes for experience. Yet when I set myself to interpret Boyhood, I have no other instruments. In these circumstances, I can hardly be edifying or even intelligible.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read the 'Observer' which is filled with Spain and India, &amp; frankly pessimistic about both.  Also, I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>.</p>
         <p>After lunch I walked in the Park for an hour. Nothing seems to have grown during my absence. The daffodils are only beginning to break. It was very cold.</p>
         <p>The evening was woefully wet. Notwithstanding this uncomfortable condition, the C.I.B. boys turned up in fair numbers, &amp; the church was nearly filled with them and the congregation. I preached the sermon which I had prepared from the text 1 Samuel xxi.9 "<hi rend="underline">And David said, there is none like that : give it to me</hi>." I think the boys were interested.  After the sermon, I presented the medal &amp; his major's Commission to Captain <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robinson,</hi> and said a few congratulatory words.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> carried the Staff, and read the lessons.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Clayton</hi>, congratulating him on his appointment as <hi rend="underline">Reader of the Temple</hi>.  If his fantastic scrupulosities don't lead him into some sudden and absurd decision, I think he may well 'make his mark'. His knowledge is exceptional, and his preaching ability above the average: and he is a gentleman.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
