<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ordination</hi>.</p>
         <p>Forty years have passed since I was ordained by Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mackarness</hi> in Cuddesdon Parish Church.  How much was possible then, which is not possible now!  How different has been the course of my life from what then seemed probable!</p>
         <p>The morning was dull and wet: the atmosphere warm &amp; close.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham for the Ordination.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>'s sermon was, perhaps, almost too well delivered, but it was well heard, &amp;, if not particularly illuminating, was not offensive.  There were no untoward incidents, save that there was an excessive amount of the consecrated elements left over after all the communicants had received.  This very unsatisfactory manner of estimating the probable number of communicants is the continuing defeat of the Ordination arrangements in the Cathedral.  I lunched with the Dean, attended Evensong in the Cathedral, had tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Braley</hi>, &amp; preached at Evensong at St. Mary&#8211;le&#8211;Bow.  The little church was well filled, the service was reverently conducted, &amp; the congregation most attentive.  After supper with the Principal, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>, I returned to Auckland.  The weather continued to be dull &amp; rather threatening, certainly promising little that is comfortable for tomorrow.  I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">LII.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>p.87. The Dean of Westminster writes to me with a kindness wh. rather startles me.</p>
         <p>P 92 Justice McCardie on the causes of Crime</p>
         <p>p. 98 S. Martins Review denounces the Bp. of D, &amp; makes an odd ref. to his earlier performances in Victoria Park.</p>
         <p>p. 105 Gladstone's method with his letter tests Miss Muriel Talbot</p>
         
            
         
      </body>
   </text></TEI>

