<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked at the Lenten Sermon, and paid a visit to the dentist. After lunch I walked in the Park, and then prepared notes for a Confirmation address.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> returned home after an absence of 3 weeks. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I went to Eldon, where I confirmed 80 persons from the parishes of Eldon, Shildon &amp; New Shildon. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Browne</hi>, the new vicar of Eldon, is certainly an unattractive fellow enough, and his manner of speaking is deplorably rough. I fear the parishioners are very depressed by his appointment.</p>
         <p>I received from the Deans of Norwich &amp; Rochester replies to my inquiry about the meaning of "residence" in their cathedrals. The latter was rather surprising, &amp; I wrote for further information.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Education Bill</hi> was rejected in the House of Lords by a very large majority &#8211; 168 to 22. I did not think it worth while to go up for the debate, nor was I anxious to be forced to vote one way or the other. Most of the money now expended on the education of the people I suspect to be money thrown away, since most of the children in the schools are not really able to absorb effectively more than 'the three R's".</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
