<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, Sunday, May 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A warm night and a dull morning.  I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  We numbered but 9 communicants including <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Florrie Bryden</hi>. Whitsunday is the least well observed of these great festivals. In spite of the orthodox doctrine, it lacks the personal appeal of Christmas and Easter: and, perhaps, its nearness to Easter has some effect.</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 11.45 a.m. and motored to <hi rend="underline">Scarborough</hi> (72 miles) by way of Stockton, Guisborough, and Whitby. It rained persistently all the way, the country being swathed in a humid mist and its great beauty affectively shrouded from view.  However, the weather cleared up about 5 p.m. when I started on my return journey, and the moors were ravishingly beautiful.  We got home at 7.20 p.m.  I preached to the <hi rend="underline">Oddfellows</hi> of the Manchester Unity Friendly Society who had gathered in force at Scarborough for their annual conference.  The parish church, which was said to seat 1500 people, seemed to be completely filled with men.  I preached from <hi rend="underline">Proverbs viii. 15 &#8211;17. &amp; 1. Cor: XII. 4, 7, 12</hi>. After the service I had tea with the Vicar (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Carter</hi>).</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
