<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 11.45 a.m., and motored to Sunderland. I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Samuel Storey</hi> &amp; his wife in their flat at the Echo Office. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Dawson</hi>, &amp; D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hume</hi> made up the party. After lunch we went to the Hospital where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Dawson</hi> "opened" the additions <hi rend="strikethrough">to the Hospital</hi>, and made an interesting speech. I moved a vote of thanks to him, which was seconded by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Priestman</hi>. After going over the Hospital, I motored to Newcastle, where I visited the hair&#8211;dresser. Then I returned to Sunderland, and had tea at the Rectory. Finally, I motored to S. Cuthbert's, Hebburn, &amp; admitted the Rev. John Walter Harriman to the perpetual curacy. On the whole I was pleased with the service, which was hearty without being irreverent. The clergy present were – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Haltwhistle</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baxter</hi>. After the service we returned to Auckland. There I found awaiting me a long letter from the curate of Winlaton detailing a long list of squalid grievances against his Vicar, the root of which is that ancient &amp; fruitful source of all quarrelling among men – MONEY. And the amounts are as petty as the cause is base.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
