<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">1931</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A white frost and a bright sun led in the New Year.  A long list of Birthday Honours included a Knighthood for <hi rend="doubleunderline">A. F. Dawson</hi>, the late Minister of Education in this County: and my appointment of Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Osborne</hi> as an honorary Chaplain in place of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Fawkes</hi> is reported in the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Times</hi>.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">William </hi>and <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Bryden</hi> communicated, making a total number 7.  I used the collect for New year's Day in the Revised Prayer Book as well as that for the Circumcision.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Article most of the morning.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi> came to lunch, and afterwards walked in the Park with me.  He will be 21 next June.  He said that <hi rend="bold underline">he thought he had gone up to Oxford too young, being then little more than 18.</hi>  I myself matriculated before I was 18.  It is hardly possible to formulate a general rule, since the age of maturity varies so widely.  He speaks of going to Mirfield fro a year after taking his degree, but I do not think that this is very desirable, &amp; shall probably divert him into some other college.  </p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
