<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[45]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Charles accompanied me to Darlington where I caught the early train to London, travelling comfortably without companion.  On the way I read <hi rend="doubleunderline">Plutarch's</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">Moralia</hi>, a treatise full of quaint and permanent wisdom.  After leaving my bags in Park Lane, I went to the hairdresser, and then walked to Westminster, where I attended a very dull session of the Church Assembly.  I came away early, and went to the Club, where I had tea, &amp; some conversation with the Bishop of Birmingham.  Then I walked back to 21 Park Lane, and dined with mine host &amp; hostess.  Lady Shaftsbury was the other member of a pleasant quartett.[sic]  She is the daughter of Lady Grosvenor, and niece of Lord Scarbrough.  The ramifications of relationship among our nobility are so many, that one never knows where one may be trampling into private preserves!  There was some talk about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi>'s illness: &amp; the general impression seemed to be that he was really very ill.  It is, indeed, difficult to see how we can allow ourselves to expect any permanent recovery for the Archbis<hi rend="strikethrough">s</hi>hop.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Lord Scarbrough has adorned his study with a very fine picture of Valette, as it was when still in the possession of the Knights of S. John. A dealer in Paris offered it to the Order, &amp; Lord S. bought it, promising to leave it in his Will thereto. It appears to have been painted about 1740 by an unknown artist and it cost no more than &#x00A3;40. It was an amazing bargain.</p>
         <p>I spoke of the absenteeism of the Durham magnates, and said that in my belief it had an effect on the public opinion of the county.  Mine host was plainly discomposed, and defended himself by the heavy burden of taxation which made residence in Lumley really impossible.  Lady S. added that the staff at Sandbeck was being reduced.  It is, of course, impossible to dispute the cogency of such pleadings.  Nevertheless, the fact remains.  In the absence of those who are their natural leaders, the people fall under the influence of self&#8211;appointed leaders, who are neither disinterested nor intelligent.  "Labour "could never have acquired its present dominance in Durham if the land&#8211;owners and employers had lived in the county.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
