<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A <hi rend="strikethrough">mild</hi> beautiful morning which, though frosty, was almost springlike. I spent the morning in adapting yesterday's sermon for use in Liverpool cathedral next Sunday. It doesn't please me, but it will have to serve.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park in the afternoon.</p>
         <p>Some words of mine in Sunderland when I preached at the consecration of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary Magdalene's Church, &amp; in the course of my sermon referred to Disestablishment as probably not a remote contingency, must have been reported in some Swedish newspapers, for I received from Gothenburg, a long &amp; quite mad communication which jumbled up Disestablishment and the Peace of the World in an absurd mingle&#8211;mangle, &amp; incidentally had an unkind reference to S&amp;#x00F6;derblom as the winner of the Nobel prize.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Shebbeare, the Rector of Stanhope, has become Master of the Beagles.  Ought I to indicate the disgust which I certainly feel at the announcement?  If he were a good parish priest, known to have his heart in his spiritual work, his parishioners &amp; neighbours might condone his action, but as he is quite notoriously a "slacker", they will not take it well.  The growing sentiment against "blood sports" is gratuitously alienated.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
