<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A white frost followed by a very warm day.  The newspapers report the death of Tim Healy,<persName xml:id="373"></persName> the erst‑while Parnellite, who was the first Governor General of the Irish Free State.  He was a quaint creature, very witty.   </p>
         <p>I wrote to Professor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchens</hi> asking him to send me a written statement setting out fully and clearly the reasons why he considered himself to have been wrongfully dismissed. Then, if these were substantial, I would take further steps.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullagh</hi>.</p>
         <p>Charles &amp; I motored to Sunderland, where I instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ridley Barker</hi>, lately the Vicar of Crook, to the Rectory of Southwick in succession to Bolland, who had been transferred to Pittington.  There was a very large congregation: and the service seemed to be edifying.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Allan Ross</hi>, whom I ordained in 1928, &amp; who didn't "hit it off" with Stephenson, who gave him his title, joined us after the service, &amp; came back to Auckland for the night.  He has been at S. George's, Cullercoats, and has not found "Anglo–Catholicism" as attractive as he expected.  He hasn't "hit it off" with Canon Fry.  So once more he is 'at a loose end'.   He might possibly suit Spurrier at Staindrop: and Spurrier might suit him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
