<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A mild, beautiful, springlike day.  The tempest last Friday night brought down the large Spanish chestnut tree, which has made so fine a figure just beyond the gate which separates the Outer from the Inner Park.  It will provide me with much (and much needed) fuel, but its disappearance is a permanent disfigurement of the Park.</p>
         <p>I visited <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi> in the Cottage Hospital.  He was fairly cheerful, but when he will be able to resume his duties remains doubtful.  Meanwhile <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi> carries on, and does so with rather remarkable success.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dr. M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi> has read <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi>'s latest book, &amp; doesn't like it.  <hi rend="bold underline">He is offended by the prominence given to Sex, which, he thinks, is altogether excessive.  His experience does not confirm it.  Plainly he regards our famous Dean as something not very far removed from a 'Sex' fanatic</hi>!</p>
         <p>The Youth at Cambridge want me to oppose "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Jix</hi>" at the Union on the subject of "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Disestablishment</hi>". I don't want to go, but it is not quite easy to find an adequate reason for declining their invitation, especially as they refer to my article on the subject in the <hi rend="underline">Political Quarterly</hi>. Moreover, I should not dislike an opportunity of getting to grips with the said "<hi rend="underline">Jix</hi>".</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
