<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Newcastle evening Paper last night gave great prominence to a sensational account of the crisis in the Medical College, adorning it with a picture of Headlam, which, however was labelled "the Bishop of Durham". It is a curious blunder, and perhaps indicates how little one is personally known in the district. This morning there are paragraphs in the "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>", and "<hi rend="underline">The Times</hi>" referring to the same matter.  Plainly "the fat is in the fire".  Yet I am entirely in the dark on the two essential matters: – </p>
         <p>(1) Whether my visitatorial jurisdiction extends to the case: </p>
         <p>(2) If it does, what is the proper &amp; requisite procedure.</p>
         <p>If I am really required to hear such an appeal as this, the door seems more widely opened than reason could tolerate or even equity justify.  If, however, I refuse to hear it, may I not be acting with a timid apprehension of the ulterior consequences of taking action rather than with a single eye to the performance of my duty?  In either event, whether I act or refuse to act, I must needs make myself odious to important sections of academic opinion in Newcastle.  The one circumstance that is satisfactory is that the appellants are precisely those who w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> normally be anti–bishop!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[139]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I motored to Norton, and read the graveside prayers at the funeral of Sir Frank Brown.</hi>  
<hi rend="bold underline">There was a considerable gathering of mourners although a "memorial service" was proceeding in Stockton Parish at the same hour – 11 a.m.</hi>  After the service I called at Norton Priory, &amp; had some talk with his family.  I was pleased to learn that my letter thanking him for his gift of an additional £<hi rend="doubleunderline">50</hi> as an "<hi rend="underline">Easter egg</hi>", for my Ordination Fund, was read to him, and gave him comfort.  I returned to Auckland, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Carr</hi> was awaiting me.  He holds on at Stanton until the end of May, &amp; will be glad of 'holiday duty' in August &amp; September.</p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Macintosh with their son John, an Eton boy, came to lunch.  She was well known to me once as Mary Sinclair, the only daughter of a Westminster doctor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Charles &amp; I motored to Dunston, where I attended the annual meeting of the Sailor's Institute, &amp; made a speech.  The Lord Mayor of Newcastle presided over a very scanty attendance.  </p>
         <p>We went to Pelton, where I instituted the Rev. R. Richardson to the perpetual curacy in succession to the unspeakable Merryweather. There was a densely crowded church, but everybody was reverent, &amp; on the whole I was pleased with the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
