<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Olivier</hi> replies by suggesting that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Robert Bolam</hi> should come with him, bringing documents.  But this seems to me too formal, &amp; would anticipate the process of an official hearing.  The last will, I fear, be unavoidable.</p>
         <p>Ella and I motored to Durham in order to take part in the reception of Princess Mary, who was to open the Children's Ward, in the County Hospital.  We lunched at the Deanery, and I sate beside <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Boyne</hi>, &amp; had pleasant talk with her.  Then we accompanied H.R.H. to the Hospital, and afterwards to the Town Hall.  Here she was received by the Mayor &amp; Corporation, and afterwards entertained at tea.  I talked with her for something more than my full share of time!  &amp; then she took her departure, &amp; we returned to Auckland.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi>, the Lord Lieutenant, did the honours, &amp; I was glad to get speech with him again.  The brilliant weather made the Royal visit very successful.  </p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to Blackhall, where I confirmed 71 persons from the parishes of Blackhall, Castle Eden, and Monk Hesleden. There was a large congregation and very close attention to my address. Little thanked me afterwards for what I said, a courtesy which surprised as much as it gratified me.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
