<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[126]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have written three letters of condolence today viz. 1. To Jack <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi>, who has lost his mother.  2. To <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joblin</hi>, who has lost his wife.  3. To <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Alfred Palmer</hi>, who has lost his son.  What a sad world!  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and I recorded our votes in the election for the local Urban District Council.</p>
         <p>Two youths &#8211;<hi rend="doubleunderline"> Morrison</hi>, the schoolmaster's son &amp; a friend &#8211; came to see the Castle, and, as I happened to be in, I acted showman myself.</p>
         <p>Two Ordination candidates came to be interviewed, aged 19 and 20.  They will start their academic career in October.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Taylor Hinckley</hi> is the son of a Builder's Foreman, and has been educated in the Bede Collegiate School at Sunderland: <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Portsmouth</hi> is the son of an engine&#8211;driver, &amp; was educated at Gateshead Central School.  Both these youths were well&#8211;grown and promising.  They represent the best type of our future candidates for the Anglican ministry: and, if only we could make sure that they are properly educated, and entrusted for their training to competent clergymen, there is no reason why they should not be fully equal to their predecessors.  But these are difficult conditions to secure.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
