<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>More snow fell during the night, and it was very cold. The morning light disclosed a bleakly wintry aspect of the world.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We were but 6 communicants but, in this high concern, numbers count for nothing.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Somebody sent me "S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Martin's Review" which opens with a denunciation of the Bishop of Durham for having "delivered a widely&#8211;quoted sermon on the subject" of Wireless</hi>. It refers to my sermon in the Temple, which contained an allusion to that subject, but was mainly concerned with graver matters. I suppose that S. Martin's regards itself as the demonstration of the religious value of B.B.C. The writer proceeds to contrast the Bishop of Durham with "D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hensley Henson himself, twenty or thirty years ago" when, apparently, he vanquished the Atheists in Victoria Park [Bethnal Green]:</p>
         <p>"Those who knew Victoria Park in those days still speak with bated breath of his witness there &amp; the fact that, after a time, there were none who would stay to stand up to him."</p>
         <p>Well, well. Thus legend grows. It is 43 years since I <hi rend="bold">[99] </hi>[symbol] contended with infidels in Victoria Park, &amp; certainly I can recall <hi rend="underline">nothing</hi> that justifies such an account of my performances. But this poor fiction is repeated, &amp; with every repetition enlarged, until the tiny fraction of fact is completely submerged. The legend is designed to blacken the Bishop of Durham, not to glorify his earlier Incarnation!</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>" writes very sourly about L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Irwin's argument with Gandhi, which it regards as a complete triumph for the latter. It "damns with faint praise". I have grave &amp; growing doubt about the matter myself.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> &amp; I motored to <hi rend="underline">Witton Park</hi>, where I confirmed 22 persons, of whom but 5 were boys, in the miserable little parish church. The benefice is vacant, for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Birney</hi> took his departure last week. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pearson</hi> acted for him. There were no candidates from Escombe, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi> never sent word. It is all very bad indeed: but only a proegustatis of our fate when "Labour" becomes everywhere dominant!</p>
         <p>We motored to Sunderland in a snow&#8211;storm: &amp; there I preached at Evensong in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's, Hendon: Charles read the service. Considering the weather, there was a fair congregation, but the Church was not much more than half filled. After the service we returned to Auckland. Snow continued to fall, &amp; the road was in a bad state.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
