<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi> suggesting that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> might use his enforced leisure in order to learn shorthand, &amp; thus qualify himself for earning his living as a shorthand reporter. Also, I suggested that he might seek for a post as usher in a school, by writing to the scholastic agents, Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gabbitas &amp; Thring</hi>. I added that I didn't wish to see him until he had shown some evidence of self&#8211;respecting determination to play a man's part in the world.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Bede College Committee: and then went to the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed diocesan business for an hour.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Slack</hi>, the librarian, told me that I figure in the <hi rend="italic">Russian newspapers in some queer variant of my name!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Willingdon where I confirmed 78 persons in the parish church. They came from the parishes of Willingdon, Sunnybrow, and Hunwick. A number of C.L.B. lads in uniform made a fine show. The sexes were about evenly divided. Save for the atmosphere, which was asphyxiating, I was pleased with the service, for the candidates had an appearance of determination &amp; sincerity which was very pleasing, &amp; the congregation was attentive &amp; evidently sympathetic.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
