<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read through Archdeacon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi>'s little "study" "<hi rend="underline">Divorce and Nullity</hi>". It is written with the ardent "cock&#8211;sureness" which marks the more venturous modern critics, but seems to be substantially sound. The latest criticism appears to prefer S. Matthew's version of Christ's words about divorce to S. Mark's, thereby contradicting what had seemed to be the established conclusion of the critics!     </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> motored me to Elwick Hall, where I confirmed 52 persons, &amp; had tea in the Rectory. The parish church of S. Peter is a Gothic Church, which has suffered much from restorers in the last century. Bishop Cosin was once Rector. The Altar Slab of stone is extremely solid, &amp;, at Bishop Westcott's suggestion was raised from the floor, and restored to its original use. This is one of the livings in the gift of the Bishop of Manchester, &amp; is said to be worth &#x00A3;700 per annum. The present Rector, Rev. H. Williamson, has held office for nearly 16 years. He was ordained as long ago as 1884. The Rectory is a substantial house of considerable antiquity, and there is a fine garden. We returned to the Castle by 6.30 p.m.</p>
         
         
            </body></text></TEI>
