<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very wet day, cold but becoming warmer.  I worked at a "Charge" for the Ordinands.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Ralph Wedgwood</hi> and his wife came to lunch, and were shown over the Castle.  She was M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gow's niece, &amp; they were married in S. Margaret's, Westminster, when I was Rector. I walked in the Park in spite of the rain, &amp; there fell in with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullagh</hi> who also insisted on a constitutional.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Morley&#8211;Headlam</hi> brought to tea a young fellow, named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi>, some relation of the Bishop of Gloucester.  Also, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Waldy</hi> and his wife, whom I married in the Temple, came to tea.  I showed the two young men over the Castle, &amp; then resumed labour on the 'Charge'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur</hi> sends me <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Rothermere's</hi> pamphlet on India, together with a letter strongly expressed.  I doubt not that he represents the general opinion of the older Anglo&#8211;Indians, whose investments are hit hard by recent developments in India, &amp; whose estimate of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ghandi</hi> is not unaffected by the fact.  Certainly, it seems highly precarious to build a policy on the verbal assurances of one man, &amp; he an ageing eccentrick, albeit, a man of high character and the most generous enthusiasm.</p>
         
            
        
         </body></text></TEI>
