<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Winter has returned after a few delusive days of seeming Spring. This morning the ground is white with snow, and March "comes in like a lion".</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> communicated, the first time for many weeks. Also, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Elland</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Florrie Bryden</hi>, &amp; 3 maids. Something like a blizzard was in process when I left the Castle after breakfast in order to motor to Newcastle. However things improved as we advanced, &amp; when we reached Jesmond (S. George's) Church, the sun was shining. The service was choral mattins, &amp;, in spite of Lent, we walked round the Church singing a cheerful hymn, &amp; had a "Te Deum". After the service the "Dead March" was played in honour of some parishioner, who had died during the week. The congregation did not much more than half fill the Church, but it was largely composed of men, and was very attentive. My text was Acts xix. 23. After the service Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Woods</hi> took me to lunch with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">White</hi>, as his own house was infected with his children's measles. I returned to Auckland after lunch, &amp; was back in the Castle shortly after 3 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
