<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> motored Ross to Staindrop, where he saw <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spurrier</hi>, and discussed with him the possibility of his becoming the curate&#8211;in&#8211;charge of Cockerton: but the prospect of having to furnish &amp; occupy the rectory&#8211;house was too formidable.  After an early lunch we motored to Dunston, where I dedicated an addition to the Church Hall, and preached a sermon, which I had to concoct during the service, for I had not understood that I was expected to preach.  When this function was ended, I was taken to the Pension Hospital, where I spent some time in visiting the Wards, &amp; talking to the patients.  After this we returned to Auckland.  </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter</hi> offering him appointment to Gateshead Fell in succession to Spencer Wade.  He has been 19 years in Orders, and has held office as Vicar of St. Peter's, Bishop Auckland, for 9 years.  I sent to him for his guidance the letter of the Churchwardens, in which they expound at my request what they conceive to be the type of person which Gateshead Fell requires.  Youth, matrimony, moderation, eloquence and energy are, of course, insisted upon.  It is not without significance that, after nearly a century of Tractarianism &amp; its developments, the English laity retain a profound dislike of celibacy, sacerdotalism, and sacramentalism.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
