<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931</hi>.</p>
         <p>The hard frost continues, &amp; much fog is reported from the South.</p>
         <p>I worked on a sermon for Liverpool.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Elliott</hi>, an Ordination candidate from Chester–le–Street, who is at Selwyn College, Cambridge, came to lunch, and afterwards walked with me in the Park.  <hi rend="bold underline">I was much pleased with his understanding and answers</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Cumming Bruce</hi>, resplendent in his full dress as a Seaforth Highlander, dined here, and afterwards carried off Fearne to the D.L.I. Ball.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robinson</hi>, a very serious &amp; cadaverous young man, predestined to be <hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi><hi rend="underline">'</hi>s partner, &amp; now commissioned to measure the outbuildings which are to be re–cast and destroyed, arrived on time for dinner.  His conversation is limited, and his manner is alarming: but I am assured that his shyness is extreme: so that I am in charity bound to assume that the more attractive aspects of his character have not yet been disclosed. But in these days, the wheels of the world move quickly, &amp; virtues that are not easily exhibited are likely to be permanently obscured!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
