<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> &amp; and two <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brydens</hi> were among the communicants.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> accompanied me to Murton where I preached to a crowded congregation of miners assembled for the annual "Band Service".  Several bands attended, and accompanied the hymns.  Instead of an anthem there was a performance of the Bands.  I preached from 1. Peter I. 3. "<hi rend="underline">Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his great mercy begat us again unto a living hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead.</hi>" The men listened very attentively, and were, I allow myself to think, impressed.</p>
         <p>The population of the parish exceeds 11,000, of whom not less than 3000 <hi rend="strikethrough">were</hi> are men above 18.  There were, perhaps, as many as 300 in church.  <hi rend="bold underline">Nine&#8211; tenths of the industrial population has no other contact with the Church of England than is implied in baptism, marriage, and burial.  The statistics show that to that extent 70% of the Nation is Anglican.  </hi>What is the religious value of this connexion it is impossible to determine, but we must make the most of it.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
