<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi> produced at breakfast a type&#8211;written copy of a letter by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Seeley</hi> discussing some objections which had been waged against <hi rend="underline">'Ecce Homo'</hi>. The skill with which he conceals his own authorship of the volume, while justifying its plan and method, was very remarkable.</p>
         <p>We were taken to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miles</hi> and his wife who lived in a charming house with extensive garden, orchard, and lawn in the village of Grantchester.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miles</hi> and his wife came to lunch.  We had a great discussion (discufsion) of the vexed questions raised by 'birth&#8211;control' and the like.  He spoke of the recent tragical episode of an undergraduate death.  Young <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ellis</hi>, a lad of 19, was a very promising pupil of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miles</hi>.  He tied up himself, or was tied up by others, in such wise that he could not extricate himself from a position, in which he was suffocated.  The official view is that it was a case of unintended self&#8211;slaughter, and this seems to me the best authenticated view.  The psychologists, however, have a fantastical explanation of their own, which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miles</hi> professes to approve.  He did not succeeded in convincing me.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Burkitt showed us "the University", a medieval quadrangle included in the Library, where the divers Faculties once held their "oppositions".  We visited the library.  I saw with keen interest the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Codex Bezae</hi>", and a manuscript of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bede's Ecclesiastical History</hi> which is said to have been written while Bede yet lived.  Then I went to the hairdresser, and received his professional attentions.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi> took me to dine at Trinity.  It being still vacation we dined in the Combination room, &amp; were rather a "scratch" company.  The Vice&#8211;Master, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry</hi>, was at the head of the table, &amp; I sate on his right hand.  Next to me sate <hi rend="doubleunderline">Higgins</hi>, an international lawyer : &amp; opposite was that oaf, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Andrew Gow</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winstanley</hi>, the historian, was beside him.  We talked pleasantly enough, &amp; afterwards in the smoking room, I was introduced to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Houseman</hi>, the Latin professor, who has emerged into literature as the author of "<hi rend="underline">The Shropshire Lad</hi>", &amp; other poems, a strange, furtive, elusive creature of uncertain temper.  However, he was quite civil.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi> and I walked home together through the "Backs" and under a star&#8211;illumined sky.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]<hi rend="italic">Confusion and perplexity in writing is indeed without excuse, because any one may, if he pleases, know whether he understands and sees through what he is about: and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">it is unpardonable for a man to lay his thoughts before others, when he is conscious that he himself does not know whereabouts he is, or how the matter before him stands. It is coming abroad in disorder, which he ought to be dissatisfied to find himself in at home.</hi>["] </p>
         <p>Bishop Butler's Preface to the Sermons at the Rolls.</p>
         <p>Those who accuse <hi rend="doubleunderline">Butler</hi> of obscurity &amp; even crudity of composition argue their own incompetence as judges of style.  The severity &amp; conciseness which mark his writing reflect his sense of the requirements of his subject.  Religion was for him too aweful to be made the occasion of "fine writing".  "<hi rend="bold underline">God is in Heaven, &amp; thou art on earth: Therefore let thy words be few" was his rule.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
