<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>["]History does not stand or fall with historians. From the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century we rely much more on letters than on histories written for the public. I need not add that the history of our Lord which we find in the Epistles is one most valuable testimony in favour of the Gospels. ["]</p>
         <p>Letters of L. Acton to Mary Gladstone, p. 32.</p>
         <p>I despatched the Article to the Secretary of the Theological College Department of the Student Christian Movement.  I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam's</hi> Article on the '<hi rend="underline">Lambeth Conference &amp; Reunion</hi>' in the new issue of '<hi rend="underline">The Church Quarterly Review</hi>'.  <hi rend="bold underline">It is clear, cogent unconvincing and truculent, in a word, highly characteristic of the writer</hi>.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park for an hour and a half. There was nobody but a few boys sliding on the ice beside the goal post.  Everything was ice&#8211;bound, but the sun&#8211;setting  in a calm sky was wonderful.</p>
         <p>Fearne went out to a dance, being transferred thither and returned from thence by the Cecil M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullaghs.</p>
         <p>Charles returned to his duties, and I resumed a measure of mental tranquillity!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
