<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>An overcast, heavy, &amp; rainy day.  I finished the Charge for the Ordinands, wrote letters, and walked round the Park, where I put up a brace of partridges.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> sent me the thesis which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dennis</hi>, the ex&#8211;Baptist minister, had written as part of his examination for Orders. It was entitled "<hi rend="underline">Some thoughts on the Apostolic Succession</hi>", and was quite a creditable piece of work.  But I notice with some concern that, while he frequently quoted the sophist, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moberly</hi>, he never referred to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Lightfoot</hi>. I doubt whether he was personally responsible for so strange an omission.</p>
         <p>I received a note from the Dean thanking me for my letter and memorandum on the subject of Canonical Residence.  He appears to expect that Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Richards</hi> will submit to my ruling without delay, but I should doubt this.  It is difficult to see what he could do, if the Dean &amp; Chapter refuse to pay him his stipend if he continue to absent himself from his prebendal house.  Even if he were to succeed in a legal action, which seems to me wholly improbable, he would draw down upon himself the censure of the public.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
