<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[214]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful day after the mist &amp; rain of yesterday. The world looks alluring enough! I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. All the candidates communicated.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>'s addresses are to have as their subject, the significance of Christ's description of his disciples as the "salt" of the earth. He secured the interest of his hearers, &amp; if he said nothing original or profound, he avoided saying anything foolish or mischievous.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>, &amp; had much talk with him.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wallis</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi> joined us at tea, &amp; held converse with the candidates.  Then for two hours I had interviews, rather depressing, for though worthy &amp; well&#8211;meaning these candidates are a very dull and unlettered set.  The ex&#8211;Baptist minister, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dennis,</hi> is the best of them, and he is quite perceptibly deaf!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi>'s second address was, perhaps, hardly as good as its predecessor.</p>
         <p>For the book which was read at mealtime, I chose the little volume, "<hi rend="underline">Notes on Popular Rationalism</hi>", which I myself wrote more than 20 years ago. It served well enough, and sounded less archaic than I had feared.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Ella.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
