<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Temple Church at 8.30 a.m. The Master served, and there were but 3 communicants beside the two clergy. There was a large congregation at 11 a.m., and a beautifully sung service. The chanting of the psalms was, I think, the best that I have ever heard. <hi rend="bold underline">My sermon was listened to very closely, and I took the impression that my hearers were really interested</hi>: and this was confirmed by the observations which subsequently reached my ears. I brought in allusions to the consecration of the Round Church by the Patriarch Heraclius, on Feb: 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1185, as I had been requested to do. My text was Romans XII. 16. "<hi rend="underline">Set not your mind on high things: but condescend to things that are lowly</hi>". After the service I met several of my friends – Gilbert &amp; "Pip" (whom I had recognised in the Choir), Miss Haldane, Sir John &amp; Lady Barron with their daughter, &amp; Lady Struthers. Then I lunched with the Benchers of the Middle Temple. There was a numerous company, of whom however I knew nobody except Lord Dunedin. I sate beside the Treasurer (Judge Tobin) who was "immense", and Lady M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>All was on my other side.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I called at 81 Albert Hall Mansions, and had tea with Di and Lord Darling. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Clive, a daughter of Lord Muir&#8211;Mackenzie came in: she looks terribly exhausted. I returned to the Temple in time for the evening meal: &amp;, before going to bed, had much talk with the Master. He is, I imagine, a High Churchman, but much affected by Modernism. He tells me that the Benchers have so mean an opinion of the Bishop of London, that when he suggested that his Lordship should be consulted about the appointment to the Readership, they immediately put the suggestion aside. Several of the Benchers lamented to me the inaudibility of the Master when preaching, and said that many of the congregation left the Church when he mounted the pulpit. This fault they lamented the more, since they liked the man, and were persuaded that his sermons were excellent. It occurred to me that it would be a kindly act for me to inform him of this defect, but when it came to sticking point, my courage failed. Moreover, he seemed disastrously convinced that he was admirably heard! It is ever so with us: we are blind as bats to faults in ourselves, which are apparent to all the world.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
