<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received a cheque for fifty pounds on account of rent for a dilapidated cottage in the ‘the Balts' from Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pigg &amp; Son</hi>, the rent–collectors in the market–place, who explained that the head of the firm, who had lately died, have left his accounts in great confusion, &amp; that they would present a complete statement in due course. I had not realised the existence, nor am I clear as to the locality of this cottage, of which the rent, which must be a petty sum, has been accumulating in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pigg's</hi> neglectful hands.</p>
         <p>I instructed the bank manager to purchase £500 worth of war–certificates.  They will cost £400 and remain in his keeping.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Chilton Moor, where I dedicated the new organ, received at the Altar a number of flags from scouts, cubs &amp;c, and preached a sermon.  In spite of the brilliant weather, the Church was nearly full, but there were only 3 clergy besides ourselves, Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Patterson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wolesley</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilkinson</hi>.  The first draws to senectitude, the second is nearly dumb, &amp; the third is deaf! Truly, as the apostle said, "<hi rend="underline">We have the treasure in earthen vessels</hi>"!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
