<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Bitter cold with snow showers at intervals. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi> seeking information about "residence". Christ Church, Oxford, with its professor&#8211;canons is closely parallel to Durham. After lunch I motored to Newcastle, and addressed an audience of less than 70 persons, mostly parsons and women, in the Connaught Hall. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Angus Watson</hi>, a busy <hi rend="italic">secretary very active in good works, presided as Chairman of the Newcastle &amp; Gateshead Vigilance Association. The occasion was the annual meeting of that Society. I spoke for about half an hour, &amp; then, after tea with the Chairman, returned </hi>to Auckland, carrying back with me as far as Durham, the deaconess <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parton</hi>, who had attended the meeting.</p>
         <p>The discussions of <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Irwin</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gandhi</hi> are reported to have reached a successful conclusion. The terms agreed upon are published in the morning's papers, and appear to be reasonable. If we could assume good faith, mutual goodwill, &amp; great patience, we might dare to think that the solution of the Indian problem had been found. At least the effort has been well&#8211;made, &amp; cannot be wholly fruitless. <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Irwin</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gandhi</hi> had much in common, not least a genuine admiration of the Founder of Christianity. And both are really religious men.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
