<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After visiting the hairdresser, I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended the session of the Assembly, but, finding the business of no importance, I called at the Deanery, and had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Foxley Norris</hi>.  Then I walked to Burlington House, &amp; visited the Persian Exhibition, which I found to be more splendid than interesting.  Certainly the carpets &amp; metal work are very astonishing.  <hi rend="underline">I was "offended" at seeing there a cope "loaned by the Soviet Union Government", no doubt part of their loot from some desecrated church</hi>.  After lunching at the Club, where I shared a table with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Ballance</hi> (who sails for U.S.A. next Wednesday), I walked to Westminster, and attended Evensong in the Abbey Church.  As I walked across S. James's Park, I was hailed by a rather youthful looking pair, who introduced themselves to me as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lance Troutbeck</hi> and his wife, whom I knew so well as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nancy Beeching</hi>. He is now an assistant master at Westminster School. She has lost most of her beauty, which in her girlhood was remarkable, but she still retains the sweetness of expression which was perhaps its most distinctive element.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The newspapers give considerable prominence to b<hi rend="underline">ot</hi>h my speeches of yesterday, especially to that in the House of Lords.  <hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" speaks of my "dramatic intervention</hi><hi rend="bold">"</hi>, and refers to me politely in its leading article.  Some of the papers describe my appearance, voice, and manner.  It was an agreeable surprize to know that I have a "fine voice", and spoke in "ringing tones", &amp; that I so stirred their Lordships that, when I sate down, the cheering was "loud &amp; continued".  The "<hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>" has a hostile article headed "<hi rend="underline">The Bishop of Russia</hi>".  I received many congratulations from members in the Club, including Buckle, Macmillan, Fleming, <hi rend="strikethrough">Bridges</hi> Granard, and Ellison.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sankey</hi>,<persName xml:id="3403"></persName> the Lord Chancellor, also congratulated me, &amp; expressed agreement.  He said that the Government were being strongly pressed by leading "industrialists" by no means to break with Russia, as to do so would lose much profitable business, and add largely to the number of the Unemployed.  He is evidently very uncomfortable, as a member of the Government.  Incidentally, he told me that the first sections of the Constitution of the Disestablished Church of Wales were written by himself in Durham castle, when he was staying there as the Judge on Circuit.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles Ballance</hi> spoke of the criminality of Chicago.  On a recent visit to that City he had been consulted by the authorities of the Hospital on the case of a young man, an undergraduate, who, while returning from a base–ball match, had been fired at by "gangsters", &amp; wounded in the back.  The following day an apology was received, explaining that he had been mistaken for another man, and expressing regret.  But the consequence of the error was that a fine young man, six foot tall, &amp; of great promise, has permanently lost the power of movement in his legs.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles</hi> observed on the incompetence of the American surgeons, who had operated on the wrong place, &amp; after a most inadequate investigation!  The youth's parents who had travelled 1000 miles to reach the bedside of their unhappy son, implored <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Charles</hi> to undertake the case himself, but that he could not do, though the offered to assist the American Surgeons with his advice.  </p>
         <p>He was warned not to adventure into the "negro quarter" after sunset: &amp; generally given to understand that the streets were highly unsafe places.  "<hi rend="underline">Would you care to see a murder</hi>?" was a question addressed to him: &amp;, as it fell out, he <hi rend="underline">did</hi> witness one of the frequent shootings of Chicago.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Sankey</hi> assured me that the Labour party would not disestablish the Church. Their view was that the Bishops and clergy ought to be left alone to do their jobs. But this tolerance or acquiescence, based on a complete misunderstanding of the situation, might be brought to an end by some crisis within the Church itself. He thought that Disestablishment was the only remedy for our present confusions, and that it ought to come from within the Church itself. He did not think there was any likelihood that the Church would be drastically disendowed; for the allocation of the ecclesiastical property would be no easy matter. I asked whether he was hopeful about the success of the Indian Experiment, and <hi rend="underline">he replied in the negative</hi>. But in view of the repeated pledges of Great Britain, he held that it was morally impossible for us not to adventure the Experiment. With this I could not but express my agreement.</p>
         <p>I dined quietly in Park Lane with mine host and hostess. We talked discursively, but not very effectively. Then I betook myself to my bedroom, there to write up my record. What conceivable interest the said record will have for anybody, it is impossible to imagine, and yet I write it!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
