<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]                                                                 </hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather was superb in spite of the evil croakings of the prophets.  I had a rather prolonged interview with the Vicar in the Garden, thus mitigating the experience by the sights &amp; sounds of incipient spring.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Rawlinson about Gillett, indicating that I could not myself ordain him to the priesthood, but that, if after learning his history, an American Bishop would do so, the said Bishop must "take him over" completely.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Also, I made a copy of my letter to Eaton Smith, the Secretary of the Church &amp; State Commission, and sent it to Carter for the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Field day of the C.L.B. in the Park was a success (succefs). I motored round to visit the outposts before lunch, and afterwards inspected &amp; addressed the Boys. Then they performed gymnastic feats, had tea, &amp; dispersed. The officers &amp; clergy to the number of about 30 came in to tea afterwards.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Frank Brown</hi> died yesterday.  His daughter called to ask me to take the funeral at Norton on Wednesday.  It is horribly inconvenient but I could not refuse.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
