<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension Day, Thursday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A grey morning, and very warm, with doubtful promise for the day.  </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  We numbered 9 commts, including our two American guests.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Pember</hi>, consenting, though with reluctance, to preach in All Souls on All Souls Day.</p>
         <p>The Americans &amp; Ella went with me to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hartlepool</hi>, where I dedicated the restored Galilee, &amp; preached a sermon.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&amp;oumle;e</hi> was there, &amp; expressed great approval of my speech, but, as it included a compliment to himself, I cannot attach much importance to his opinion.  However, I think the congregation, (which was mostly composed of the Freemasons who had defrayed the cost of the restoration of the Galilee) was interested, &amp; possibly also edified.  I took occasion to emphasise the difference between the Freemasonry of England, &amp; that of the Continent.  Also, I explained the probable meaning of the name ‘Galilee' as applied to a church porch.  After the service we all returned to Auckland, bringing <hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&amp;oumle;e</hi> with us.  The weather was sunless, but fine &amp; warm.  The Church now seen in its full proportions looks magnificent.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
