<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Much snow remains, &amp; there was again a severe frost during the night.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and I voted in the County Council Election. So little interest was apparent in the Election, that no one would have suspected that it was in process. Yet the practical importance of turning out these ruinously wasteful Socialists is generally allowed. But the Nation is "fed up" with elections, &amp; can no longer bring itself to treat them seriously.</p>
         <p>The newspapers announce the resignation of Sir <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles Trevelyan</hi>. In his letter to the Prime Minister, he is not content to offer the defeat of his Education Bill as the cause of his action. <hi rend="bold underline">He has lost confidence in the Government which does not adopt "big Socialist measures" for the relief of the nation in the present crisis</hi>. Every fresh evidence of disintegration brings near the critical Election, which the insensate division of the Conservative Party threatens to lose.</p>
         <p>I gave old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi> a month's notice to leave my service, promising him the use of the little house which William will vacate, when he goes into one of the new cottages, and a pension of 15/&#8211; weekly until his wife also gets the old age pension, &amp; then 10/&#8211;. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[92]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Justice McCardie</hi> in his charge to the Grand Jury at the Surrey Assizes said: &#8211;</p>
         <p>["]Having often analysed the causes of serious crime, I have found that drink has remarkably little to do with it, and, striking though the circumstances might appear, poverty has very little to do with it also. <hi rend="underline">The great causes of crime still remain as they were largely in the past – lust, greed, vanity, and jealousy – just the fundamental weaknesses of mankind and womankind</hi>.["]</p>
         <p>Times. March 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1931.</p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to Hamsterley, where I confirmed 26 persons in the little old parish church. Linnell was the only incumbent present, for Pearson was in bed with influenza, &amp; sent his candidates to be taken charge of by Linnell; and old Wilkinson, the Vicar of Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear had no candidates. Yet he has 2000 parishioners. But he is idle, &amp; without any religious interest. After the service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
