<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Robert Bolam</hi> arrived almost precisely at 10:00 a.m., and for two hours did their best to expound to me the exact state of affairs in Newcastle.  It is obvious that the really determining factors are not those which are apparent, or can be stated.  There is (&#x3B1;) the personal feud between <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchens</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bolam</hi>: (&#x3B2;) the financial resentment caused by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchens'</hi> refusal to economise.  (&#x3B3;) the friction between Armstrong College &amp; the College of Medicine, the former designing to absorb the latter, &amp; to start a separate University for Newcastle. (&#x3B4;) the revolt of the younger men against the elder. It was pointed out to me that all the signatories to the appeal of the Lecturers were juniors.</p>
         <p>It certainly appears to be quite hopeless to arrange the quarrel peaceably.  I am strongly tempted to take refuge in the "line of least resistance", namely, to rule that the matter does not fall within my Visitatorial Jurisdiction.  And this may well be the right course to adopt, for the more I investigate the facts, the more dubious does my position appear.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi> may be able to throw light on it.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie Lillingston</hi> came to lunch.  He is now a man of 24, and looks very frail.  He has been teaching in a preparatory school at Eastbourne, but thinks that he will not continue there.  His mind turns towards Ordination.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Wylie</hi>, a married man of 28, who desires to be ordained, came to see me. He impressed (imprefsed) me well.  I advised him, since he can find the money, to go to Cambridge, and take his degree.  He gave a rather surprising account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bamlett's</hi> "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism", which he has found repugnant.  The people everywhere loathe this folly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Longnewton, where I confirmed 37 persons, mostly males. After the service I went to the rectory and had speech with the rector (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Manning</hi>), who is recovering from pleurisy.  He complained of the fewness of children in his parish.  <hi rend="bold underline">There are only 32 in the church school, and the female teacher is paid &#x00A3;355. per annum</hi>. It is in my opinion certain that the elementary school teachers are overpaid. When it is remembered that the entire cost of their own education, &amp; that of their preparation for their professional work is paid by the State, it must be apparent that the present rates of pay are quite excessive.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
