<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A glorious bright morning, and very warm.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Installation Sermon.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Toomey</hi> came to report progress, and stayed to lunch.</p>
         <p>Professor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchens</hi> came to lunch.  He is a mild little man, with rather a "missing&#8211;link" type of head, &amp; suggestions of obstinacy in his face.  After lunch, I had some talk with him about his 'appeal', and I found him considerably less pugnacious than I had been led to expect.  He certainly had more to say for himself than his antagonists realise.  <hi rend="bold underline">I strongly recommended him to accept a pension and retire. He asked me to postpone further action until he wrote again</hi>, indicating clearly that, if the amount of the pension were satisfactory, he would consent to retire. Certainly, if he should take this course, I should be relieved of a most embarrassing problem. I showed him the Chapel, which he professed to admire. Then we parted with much civility. When combatants consent to negotiate, it is not very easy to get them again into the fighting mood.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi> and I walked round the Park, &amp; had much talk together.  When we returned I lent him <hi rend="doubleunderline">Merejkowski's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Death of the Gods</hi>".  Something had brought Julian the Apostate into our conversation : &amp;, I thought it well to confirm his interest without delay.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi> went with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and me to Frosterley, where I confirmed 49 persons from Frosterley, Stanhope &amp; Muggleswick.  The Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullen</hi>, caused as much confusion as possible by his feckless muddlement, &amp; the candidates, though attentive &amp; well behaved, gave me the impression (imprefsion) of being ill&#8211;prepared. The church was filled, and an unusual feature was the number of men in the congregation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Wolsingham</hi>, with a population of about 3000 persons, sent no candidates at all.  The Rector, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arnold</hi>, is crippled, but the income of the benefice exceeds £<hi rend="doubleunderline">1000</hi> and he ought to have a curate.  If I could find a suitable man, I would insist on his having him; but since I cannot do so, my exhortations are easily and effectively met by a' <hi rend="underline">non possumus'</hi>, none the less hypocritical for being plausible, &amp; even valid. Yet, I cannot pass over without notice so gross an evidence of pastoral failure. I must 'liberate my soul', though the practical result be nil.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
