<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful day, brilliant and calm.  I wrote to the Rev. A.W. Bell, now assistant curate of Heworth, offering him appointment to Dimsdale with Sockburn. He is a poor creature but I can find none else.</p>
         <p>I worked on the Temple sermon all the morning. After lunch I motored to Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Church Building Board. There can be no doubt that the two "Eyes" of the Bishop are not looking in the same direction!  I fear that the dissidence at the centre will be a leaven of disunity in the diocese.</p>
         <p>Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi> arrived about 5 p.m.  He insisted on accompanying me to Sunderland, <hi rend="bold underline">where I instituted </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip Strong</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> to the vicarage of S. Ignatius</hi>.  There was a large muster of the local clergy, and several strangers presumably from Leeds.  There was a large congregation in which, however, young women &amp; girls were formidably present.  I repeated, with substantial additions, the address which I delivered at Pittington on Saturday.  On the whole the service seemed to me very comforting: and I was particularly pleased by the assurances of the churchwardens that they would do their utmost to make the new vicariate successful.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
