<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The hard frost continues, but the bright sun seemed to overcome the cold.  <hi rend="bold underline">I worked at the Letter on the Lambeth Conference</hi>, which I intend to publish in the forthcoming "<hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>".  The difficulty is to say what needs saying without actually breaking the difficult rule of 'secresy'[sic], or being blatantly egotistic.  I desire to indicate my personal dissent from much that was agreed upon; and yet I do not wish to make myself appear as a mere Ishmaelite, which would be false to the facts, and on many accounts undesirable.  I certainly do not share the ardent episcopalianism of my brother bishops.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Watts</hi>, who reached the age of 21 yesterday, addressing him as '<hi rend="underline">Citizen</hi>'.</p>
         <p>I received an excellent and informing letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brilioth</hi> in reply to mine, thanking him for the gift of his book.  He describes the situation in Sweden, which has some striking resemblances to that in England.  "<hi rend="underline">The most serious consequences of the present system of establishment is in my opinion to be found in the province of marriage.</hi>"  But still he clings to the establishment.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
