<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Today I have made two speeches, the one in the Church Assembly on the Party trusts, the other in the House of Lords on the Russian question.  Both speeches were quite impromptu; both were delivered in thin houses; &amp; both were applauded.</hi>  It was probably imprudent to deliver either: for while the one made the Evangelicals very angry, the other exasperated the Labour Government.  I shall certainly hear of them again.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi> was in the house, &amp; told me that Di was in the Gallery, so I sent her a note suggesting that I should call on Sunday afternoon.  She sent down a reply approving the suggestion.</p>
         <p>I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carnegie</hi>. His wife was absent in Italy, but his two younger daughters were at home. The Bishops of Blackburn and Wakefield were there, and we had much pleasant conversation.</p>
         <p>I dined with Lady Struthers. The company were,</p>
         <p>Lord and Lady Askwith.</p>
         <p>A French General and his wife.</p>
         <p>Sir Reginald &amp; Lady Wingate</p>
         <p>Sir Sydney &amp; Lady Waterlow</p>
         <p>Sir Harcourt Butler&amp; Lady Steele–Maitland</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>If I had given but a little more thought to that speech in the H. of L. how much more effective it would have been! But I had no intention whatever of speaking until I was pushed to do so by Lord Newton &amp; others before the debate began, &amp; then I consented just to say a few words associating the Episcopal Bench with the appeal to the Government.  I actually spoke for about 20 minutes.</p>
         <p>Sir Reginald Wingate spoke very interestingly about his experience of Bolshevist propaganda in Egypt, when he was High Commissioner. Under pretence of raising a sunken Russian warship, a Russian Commission secured permission to enter Egypt, then a British Protectorate. The immense quantity of baggage passed in unexamined, until, by accident rather than design, the contents of one box were disclosed, &amp; found to benothing but Bolshevist propagandist pamphlets printed in all languages.  Further investigations revealed the representative character of this box: and the project of infecting the merchant navies of the world with Communism lay unmasked.  The fiction of raising the Warship was quickly abandoned, &amp; the Commission returned to Russia baffled.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
