<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit. Monday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather was fairly fine until 6 p.m. but blustering and threatening.</p>
         <p>I received two invitations from Oxford, neither of which I was able to accept. The first, was from the Secretary of the Stubbs Society, inviting me to dine as its Founder. The next, the Censor of the Non–Collegiate Students inviting me to a quasi–official dinner which is being organised to celebrate the decree of the University authorising the use of the name S. Catherine's. In writing to decline the latter, I asked the Censor to tell me what would be the correct formula with which a preacher might refer to S. Catherine's in the Bidding Prayer.</p>
         <p>Archbishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Söderblom</hi> sends me the notice of his Gifford Lectures, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">says that he owes me the phrase by which he indicates this subject, viz. </hi><hi rend="underline">"Basal forms of Personal Religion"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. But I cannot recall ever having coined, or used, the phrase</hi>.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Peter Green</hi>, acknowledging a reprint of his recent letter to the <hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi> on' <hi rend="underline">Bishops' Palaces and Deans' Houses'</hi>, telling him that the retention of these was integral to the Establishment, &amp; could not survive it.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
