<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">Andrew</hi>'s book, ‘<hi rend="underline">Mahatma Gandhi's Ideas</hi>' in bed, I came across the too&#8211;familiar misquotation of the catechism,' <hi rend="underline">to which it has pleased God to call them'</hi>, in a connexion which suggests that ‘<hi rend="underline">the Church of England Catechism with its feudal background</hi>' provides some kind of a justification for the caste system of India.  I was sufficiently moved to write a short letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> calling attention to this strange blunder.</p>
         <p>The newspapers give prominence to riots in Madrid, which have taken a strongly anti‑clericalist character. Ten churches &amp; convents are said to have been burned, amid dangerous indications of revolt against the cautious &amp; clement procedure of the Republican Government. A royalist was trampled to death, &amp; there were clamours for severe handling of the late ministers. All this is very alarming. It cannot but have an effect in France &amp; Italy where the anti‑clericalist factions are chafing bitterly against the friendly attitude of the Governments towards the Roman Church. Revolution, especially in its excesses, is catching.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bates</hi>, the Vicar of Spennymoor, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Tallents</hi>, the Vicar of Brandon came to lunch, and to "consult" the Bishop. Neither had any business of moment, &amp; both took their leave without illumination! But, probably they feel the better for having "blown off steam". When they had gone, I walked round the Park, which was looking its best in the brilliance of a perfect spring day.</p>
         <p>Then I set myself to put together some notes for my speech tomorrow.  It is not easy to determine beforehand what had best be said, for much turns on what will have been said before one speaks, much on the temper of the meeting, and much on the hour.  <hi rend="bold underline">The secretary sent me a complete type&#8211;written speech to be spoken by the Prince of Wales, and elaborate notes for my own speech</hi>.  The latter seemed sufficiently obvious.  Everything turns for me on how I feel, and how the audience treats me!  If they are frigid and bored, I shall certainly be dull &amp; boring.  On the other hand, if they are genuinely welcoming, I may be able to expand.  There never was a speaker so uncertain as I.  There is no depth of oratorical failure which I cannot sink to &amp; perhaps few heights of subtle oratorical success which I cannot reach!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
