<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A very stormy night followed by a bright morning.  I was much perturbed by receiving, from <hi rend="bold underline">the Bp. of Birmingham a letter about </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Booth</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> with the object of offering him a Trust living in his diocese.</hi>  Now C.B. has been about 18 months in charge of his present parish, Holy trinity, South Shields.  He has made a very good start.  It is bad for him, bad for the parish, bad for the diocese, bad for discipline, that he should be removed so soon.  I told this <hi rend="doubleunderline">to Barnes. This wretched diocese is quickly being stripped of all its able men: and the</hi> appointments to the greatest benefices will be a problem almost incapable of solution.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Pittington, where I instituted the Rev. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest Walter Bolland</hi> to the Vicarage in succession to old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Boddy</hi>. He is the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Vicar whom I have instituted to that parish in the short space of 10 years. The rapidity with which the personnel of the parochial clergy is changed is really astonishing.  After the service we went to Ramside for tea with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pembertons</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Betty</hi> was there, full of her experiences in Switzerland.  She is now a fine young woman, and I baptized her!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
