<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[64]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I frittered away the morning in writing letters, including a long one to Dick in answer to his. He wrote to me on the subject of purity, &amp; so expressed himself as to make me think that he was really perturbed. So I wrote to him at length, and kept a copy of my letter.</p>
         <p>Warwick, the Vicar of S. Jude's, South Shields, lunched here. I talked to him about the implications of "giving a title" for the Ordination of a deacon. He promised well, but what will be his performance? However, I decided to risk it.</p>
         <p>Charles and I started to walk in the Park, &amp; were joined by D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullough. But so violent a storm of sleety rain came on, that we retreated homewards.</p>
         <p>A lay&#8211;reader from Eastgate, named Cartwright, came to see me. I judge him to be sincere, earnest, and – illiterate. However I sanctioned his employment by Canon Crondace.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I received a request from Sir John Reith</hi>, asking for the loan of my Temple Sermon in order that he might see what I did really say about the religious effect of Broadcasting. I sent him the MS. Together with a civil letter.</p>
         <p>A rather boring old parson, named Aldous, came to tea, &amp; afterwards had an interview with me about a silly project for evangelizing the Youth which he had imagined!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
