<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The result of the Election in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's division of Westminster was declared last night:–</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> A. Duff–Cooper (C.)</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>17,242</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Sir E. Potter (Ind.)</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>
<hi rend="underline">11,532</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Majority</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: justify;">5710</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>Not many more than half the electors went to the poll. This, perhaps, is not the least significant fact in the election.</p>
         <p>Minor Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donne</hi> and his Wife came to lunch. He desired also to consider arrangements for the visit of the C.L.B. on Easter Monday.</p>
         <p>Two medical students from Newcastle – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clark–Maxwell</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannerman</hi> – came to see me. They desired to lay before me the indignation &amp; alarm of the students at the dismissal of Professor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutchence</hi>, and to invoke my intervention!!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I were about to start for West Auckland, where a confirmation had been arranged for that parish and S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, when <hi rend="doubleunderline">Walters</hi>, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, arrived in much perturbation, to say that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi> had either forgotten or mistaken the date, that nothing was prepared at West Auckland, and that his candidates, who were already in the omnibus, wanted to know what they should do! <hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi>, the guilty cause of all this confusion, was reported to be in Newcastle!!!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
