<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A calm morning.  There had been a slight fall of snow during the night.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles, Fearne</hi> and I motored to Durham, where I preached and celebrated in the Cathedral.  There was an unusually small congregation, &amp; (an unprecedented circumstance) no reporter came atfter the service to beg for the MS of the sermon.  I was told that there <hi rend="underline">was</hi> a reporter present, so that I may infer that he judged the sermon from <hi rend="underline">his</hi> point of view to be not worth reporting!</p>
         <p>Indeed there was no 'copy' in it, for I preached from S. Matthew vi. 25. "<hi rend="underline">Therefore, I say unto you, Be not anxious for your life</hi>", and I was solely concerned with the true significance of the Lord's words to ourselves.  We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>.</p>
         <p>I finished reading a novel by <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. B. Priestley</hi>, called "<hi rend="underline">Angel Pavement</hi>", which I was induced to read because his previous work, "<hi rend="underline">The Good Companions</hi>" had pleased me much.  But, though the book was not without great merit, I found it tiresome.  Certainly the picture of post&#8211;war society, which it professes to present, with almost photographic fidelity, is extremely repulsive. But I am incorrigibly Victorian!</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
