<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful bright day, almost springlike. I left the Deanery after breakfast, and went to the Athenæum, where I deposited my bags, &amp; visited the hairdresser and the book&#8211;seller. Then I returned to the Club, &amp; wrote to Cecil Fortescue. After this I went to the Temple, and lunched with the Master of the Temple, <hi rend="bold underline">before going to the Temple Church for the marriage of Miss Helen Roche to M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Waldy of Darlington</hi>. The Church appeared to be nearly full of guests. Making my apologies for avoiding the reception I went back to the Athenæum, killed an hour by running through a book on Peter the Great, (who is represented as a homicidal maniac of enormous energy and sheer savagery.) and then proceeded to King's Cross, where I took the Pullman Express, which left at 4.45 p.m. and arrived (theoretically) at 9.37 p.m., and actually about a quarter of an hour later. Leng met me with the car, &amp; carried me to the Castle. There had been another snow storm in the morning, &amp; snow lay on the landscape. Was it wise, reasonable, or anyway defensible that I should waste two days, when I am much pressed by work, expend &#x00A3;5 when I am menaced by poverty, &amp; provoke the resentments of the orthodox by officiating at a wedding in Lent?</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
