<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A cold, comfortless, blustering day. I began an Address for the Diocesan Conference. After lunch I walked in the Park, and later motored to Norton, where I confirmed 104 persons in the parish church. Charles and I dined with the Vicar &amp; his family after the service.</p>
         <p>I received an interesting letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wilson</hi>, the Bishop of Eau Claire. He is evidently not very favourable to attempts at fraternization with "our dissenting brethren":&#8211;</p>
         <p>"Protestantism in its sectarian form is really disintegrating over here. The Fundamentalists are kicking themselves out of everything valid they ever had. <hi rend="underline">The Methodists are burning incense at the altar of Prohibition until their adherents frankly yearn for a fresher breath of Anglican atmosphere</hi>. The Congregationalists have denuded themselves of all convictions until nobody knows what they are any more. <hi rend="underline">Our bishops are besieged by Methodist &amp; Congregational ministers seeking Holy Orders</hi>. Recently a string of German Congregational Churches, numbering 40,000 persons, applied to our National Council to take them over bodily – property, ministers &amp; people – and the matter is now under advisement."</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
