<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1931.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Flexner's</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">Universities American, English, German</hi> is an arresting, thought&#8211;provoking book.  Two thirds of it are given up to the American universities.  This description may well stand alongside of "<hi rend="underline">Al Capone</hi>" as a revelation of braggart &amp; precocious decadence.  Plainly, the intellectual life of the great republic is no rounder than the social.  Commercial life is sufficiently disclosed by the novels of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Upton Sinclair</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sinclair Lewis</hi>. Religion is caricatured but not misrepresented in "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Elmer Gantry</hi>": and sexual morality is darkly displayed in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lindsey's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Revolt of Modern Youth</hi>" and "<hi rend="underline">Compassionate Marriage</hi>". The total effect of all these accounts is quite nauseating. It is still the fashion of "<hi rend="underline">the Protestant Underworld</hi>" to dilate on the moral superiority of Protestant Communities, but in truth that whole contention is utterly obsolete.  'The wheel has gone full circle'; and, now, <hi rend="bold underline">the most demoralised section of Christendom is Protestant America. The antinomianism, always latent in puritan sects, has flamed out irrepressibly since the total failure of sectarian creeds &amp; disciplines. It is this transference of moral superiority from the one side of the great controversy to the other that probably gives the true explanation of the collapse of Protestantism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[Symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">As I review the development of my mind with respect to the subject of Reunion, which interested me deeply 40 years ago, and interests me little now</hi>, I perceive that while my dislike of Rome remains unlessened, my estimate of Protestantism has greatly changed for the worse.  As my knowledge has increased I have discovered that while I was probably unduly severe on the distinctively Roman discipline and devotion, I overrated almost grotesquely the spirituality and moral robustness of Protestantism.  It is difficult to imagine anything farther removed from the Mind of Christ than the supercilious, self&#8211;indulgent rationalism of the Modernists, or the canting commercialism of the Sectaries.  Even the lethargic worldliness of Anglicanism is less irreparably fallen than these.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi> affects to think that the Quakers provide the nearest approach to genuine Christianity: but they seem to me only distinctive in their arrogant aloofness from the general life, &amp; their assumption of a spirituality which their secular prosperity mocks.  Yet somehow the '<hi rend="underline">Holy Catholick Church</hi>' must be able to include all these varieties of the historic fellowship.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]                                                                 </hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Archdeacon </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Swanson</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Lethbridge, Alberta, and sent him a copy of the last issue of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="italic"> since some confused report of what I have written there about the Lambeth Conference had evidently reached him, &amp; caused him to write to me.  In his letter he reminds me that "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">in this little city of the prairies my brother's body lies in the Church cemetery</hi><hi rend="italic">."  That was my oldest brother, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Walter</hi><hi rend="italic">, who left England for Canada, when I was a small boy, &amp; never returned: I scarcely recall him. He fell ill with appendicitis when far from medical assistance, &amp; when at last he was brought to a hospital, he died under the over&#8211;due operation. Such experiences disclose how far removed from civilised conditions much of the great Dominion still is.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked around the Park in the afternoon.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Toomey</hi> came to see me.  I am doubtful whether I did wisely in ordaining him, for though he has an amiable disposition &amp; a genuine desire to serve in the Ministry, his health is very dubious.  However, he is earmarked for foreign <hi rend="strikethrough">service</hi> work, and his service in this diocese will not at longest extend beyond four years.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
