<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="118">Bishop of London</persName> died this day about 1 a.m. The news was brought to me during service by my verger &amp; I sent him to the <persName xml:id="122">minor Canon</persName> to stop the prayer.<hi rend="bold underline"></hi>  <hi rend="bold underline">Then I went to Oxford to take part in the queerest orgy in the world</hi>.  The railway carriage was filled with <term xml:id="1">Socii</term>: &amp; we journeyed merrily enough.  After dinner at 11 p.m. we assembled in the large quadrangle &amp; formed a procession.  The probationer fellows, without gowns led the way, <persName xml:id="132">Liddell</persName> carrying a dead mallard on a pole followed, the <persName xml:id="130">Lord Mallard</persName><note xml:id="11" n="1"></note> was borne on a throne, &amp; the Fellows &amp; <term xml:id="2">quondams</term> carrying torches came after him.  Singing the Mallard Song<note xml:id="12" n="2"></note> most lustily, the procession went round the quadrangles, &amp; then, by the newel staircase in the ante-chapel mounted to the roof.  There the procession was reformed, &amp; proceeded round the roofs.  A halt was made between the twin-towers, &amp; the whole Mallard Song was sung in full.  Then the return to the quadrangle was effected by way of the Library.  A bon-fire was formed with the torches, and we danced about it singing "Auld lang syne".  Then we went to the Buttery, &amp; drank the <hi rend="bold">[7]</hi> Mallard potations.  A silver mallard filled with port-wine was given to the Lord Mallard, and he poured a few drops into the glass of madeira which every one had.  So the solemn common potation was effected.  Then followed sports in the Hall.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
