<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[37]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 29 cts. I preached at Mattins.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On Saturday 18</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> May, I went to Eton &amp; stayed with the <persName xml:id="203">Head-master</persName> until Sunday afternoon. I <listEvent><event xml:id="93" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> to the boys,</hi> <hi rend="italic">but did not make myself well-heard.  <persName xml:id="4">Donaldson</persName> took me for a walk after lunch, &amp; we discussed the new Criticism.<note xml:id="14" n="1"></note>  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I rather alarmed him</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Returned to Westminster, &amp; preached at Evensong.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday there was a clergy-council at which we resolved (&#x3B1;) to start a <orgName xml:id="45">Church Lads Brigade</orgName>.  (&#x3B2;) to start a Club for the Lewisham Street boys. I called on</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1702" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bedford</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">2.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1703">Miss Tomlinson</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">3 Richmond Terrace.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">3.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1704" display="no">Miss Geary</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">11 Victoria St.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">4.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1705">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi></persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1706">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wise</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">11 Victoria Street.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">5.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1707" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Milman</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>				
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p><div type="letter">
         <p>May 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1901.</p>
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="99">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dean</persName>,</p>
         <p>I am not sure whether I rightly understood what you said to me yesterday with reference to the paragraph in my Parochial Magazine for March.  But I rather gathered that <hi rend="underline">somebody</hi> suggested that it involved something of a breach of the obligation to secrecy which protects our capitular discussions, &amp; further that you yourself so far sympathized with that view as to meditate writing to me.</p>
         <p>I do not think you can have read the paragraph, which I, therefore, beg to enclose.  You will observe that absolutely nothing is announced except the fact of our decision, &amp; that my parish Magazine with that announcement did not appear until after the Revised Version was actually being read in the Abbey.  It could not be a breach of confidence to announce a decision which was already being publically acted on.  The offer of the <orgName xml:id="136" display="no"><orgName xml:id="137" display="no">Burgesses</orgName></orgName> was, of course, in no sense private. In the first instance, the proposal was discussed between them and myself, &amp; certainly, publicity was of the essence of the whole transaction. <hi rend="bold">[39] </hi>[symbol] I desired their gift, &amp; the use of the Revised Bible in the Abbey avowedly &amp; obviously because both the one &amp; the other would strengthen my effort to get the Revised Bible generally used in the churches.  Finally, although I had no shadow of doubt as to my liberty in the matter, I was not unobservant of the fact that in a similar instance, when the Chapter requested you to permit, &amp; you did permit a daily Celebration of Holy Communion during Lent, <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="49">Canon Gore</persName> at once wrote to the Church papers announcing the decision</hi>, &amp; I am not aware that anybody in or out of the Chapter objected that he had broken his faith to the Chapter. And, certainly, until I am convinced that my view is mistaken, I shall not hesitate on any future occasion to draw public attention to decisions of the Chapter, which are themselves matters of public concern.  The discussions of the Chapter, of course, are &amp; must be private, but the decisions are sometimes by no means so: &amp; I submit that in the case of the Revised Version it is quite grotesque to support the contrary. You will, I am sure, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dean understand that I write to you <hi rend="bold">[40] </hi>because I conceive the matter to be of the greatest possible importance not merely to my reputation &amp; comfort as a member of the Chapter, but also to my conduct in the future in that capacity.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dean,</p>
         <p>v. faithfully yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Holy Spirit of God have pity on my weakness &amp; misery, and fulfil in me Thine own Ministry of comfort and cleansing.  I know not how to pray as I ought, for memories of sin confound and abash me, and my way is hidden from view. O merciful Spirit of Jesus make intercession for me. I entreat Thee, that I may not altogether fail &amp; fall from grace.  I confess that I have grieved Thee by my persistent rebellion, nevertheless I come back to Thee, driven by my need.  To Thee, henceforth, I would give myself without reserve for discipline, for direction, for renewal.  O Divine Teacher have compassion on my ignorance: O Sanctifying Spirit pity my sinfulness: O Eternal Advocate protect my weakness.  Lead me in the path of righteousness, and guide my steps in the way everlasting, for the sake of Jesus Christ my Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         <p>Evening before Whitsunday. May 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1901</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Whitsunday I celebrated at 8 a.m. and preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 11 a.m.  <persName xml:id="205">Cunliffe</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="206">Baddeley</persName> lunched with me, and <hi rend="bold underline">then I went to Oxford by the afternoon train</hi>. There was a pleasant re-union in <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">College</orgName>. Next day, Whit Monday, a small party from Westminster came to Oxford, &amp; I spent the morning in showing them about. They lunched in the Common Room &amp; had tea in my rooms. They were the following:-</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item><persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1708">Aleck Beeching</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="300">Ellison</persName></item>
            <item>A friend of Ellisons</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="262" display="no">Charles Ramsey</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="263" display="no">Stanley Syms</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="44">Robinson</persName></item>
         </list>
         <p><persName xml:id="170">Perkins</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName>, also, came &amp; helped to entertain them.  On Whit Tuesday I attended the College Meeting, and lunched with <persName xml:id="1710" display="no">Whitmore</persName>.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="919" display="no">Cecil Chapman</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="920" display="no">his wife</persName> were there</hi>.  Then I returned to Westminster, &amp; took the monthly service for the <orgName xml:id="103">S. Margaret's Guild</orgName>.  On Wednesday I dined with <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1384">Bailward</persName></hi> at 1 Princes Mansions, Victoria Street. <hi rend="bold">[43] </hi><persName xml:id="1711">Loch</persName>, <persName xml:id="1712">Champernowne</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1713">Macmillan</persName> formed the party.  <hi rend="bold underline">On Thursday I went again to Oxford. The Canons' Verger, <persName xml:id="1714" display="no">David Waller</persName>, came there, &amp; I showed him about in the morning, gave him lunch, &amp; despatched him</hi>. Later in the day, <persName xml:id="50">Lemare</persName> arrived.  I gave a dinner-party in my rooms to the following.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item><persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName>,</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1772">Allen</persName></item>
            <item><persName xml:id="209">Roland Allen</persName> from Peking</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="210">Urquhart</persName></item>
            <item>Cunliffe</item>
            <item>Lemare.</item>
         </list>
         <p>On Friday I spent the morning in showing Lemare about.  <persName xml:id="41">Davis</persName> took him on the river in the afternoon, &amp; he went away after dining in Hall by the late train.  I attended the meeting of the Council of the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName> in the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>'s rooms, where <hi rend="bold underline">we agreed to offer the Headship to <persName xml:id="211">Henry Woolcombe</persName></hi>. On Saturday I returned to Westminster &amp; in the afternoon showed a party from Barking over the Abbey, &amp; gave them tea.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
