<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended the Celebration in <placeName xml:id="6" display="no">Henry VII<hi rend="superscript underline">th's</hi> Chapel</placeName>, when the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> was the Celebrant, and a number of members of the <orgName xml:id="148">London Diocesan Conference</orgName> communicated.  </p>
         <p>Afterwards I attended the meeting of the Conf: in the <placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName>.  The Bishop presided, and did very well.  There were animated debates both in the morning &amp; in the afternoon. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName> moved the amendment on the proposal to re-translate the Athanasian Creed in a remarkable speech, which made a deep impression on the Conference.<note xml:id="15" n="1"></note></hi> <hi rend="bold">[45]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="italic">I seconded the amendment.  Then the previous question was moved by <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> &amp; seconded by <persName xml:id="213">Riley</persName>, &amp; carried by a great majority.  On the whole we succeeded in effecting our purpose viz: </hi><hi rend="italic underline">discrediting this now fashionable notion of re-translating the Creed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="superscript">^</hi><persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName> and I were temperamentally opposed but we were often in agreement on ecclesiastical matters: while <persName xml:id="49">Charles Gore</persName> and I were almost always opposed on questions of eccles<hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi> policy but attached to one another by genuine affection.<hi rend="superscript">^</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>June 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1901.</p>
         <p>My dear <persName xml:id="50">Lemare</persName>,</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have been thinking over the practical applications of the principles enunciated in my sermon of yesterday morning. It is of evident importance that we should follow up our announcement of purpose by suitable action. Otherwise we shall lie open to the charge of urging people to duties which we obstruct them from performing. I think it convenient to set down in a written statement the course I wish you to pursue in order to secure that congregational worship which I have advocated.  The key of our position is the distinction between the common worship, &amp; such musical performances as we may think desirable.  These, then, are to be the directions, which I desire you to follow for the future.  I set them out quite shortly for the sake of lucidity:-</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">1. There shall be Anthems both at Mattins &amp; at Evensong, but in no case are they to exceed 5 minutes &amp; 10 minutes in length respectively. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">2. The Canticles viz: Te Deum, Benedictus, Magnificat, &amp; Nunc Dimittis are to be sung to chants such as the congregation </hi><hi rend="bold">[47] </hi>can easily sing. Only on Festivals are ‘services' to be used.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">3. The Responses are to be sung with greater vigour &amp; more body of sound: especially those after the Creed. It is most important that these should be sung by everybody.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">4. The whole Choir is to sing throughout the Hymns.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">5.On certain special occasions viz: in Advent, in Lent, &amp; at the Festival in July, there shall be special performance of suitable music e.g. Spohr's Last Judgment, Passion Music, Mendelsohn's Hymn of Praise, rendered on convenient evenings apart from the Church Service</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wish you to consider whether the responses could not wisely be taken on a lower note. It is complained that at present the note is impossibly high for the mass of people.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Believe me, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">ever sincerely yrs.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. HENSLEY HENSON</hi>	
         </p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Sunday, 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> October 1901, <listEvent><event xml:id="6">I preachedp before the University of Cambridge in Great S. Mary's</event></listEvent></hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  The sermon had been prepared in fear &amp; trembling; I never worked with a stronger sense of responsibility.  <hi rend="bold underline">In that sermon I crossed the Rubicon which divides "Catholicism" from "Protestantism"</hi>: I went back on published declarations of my own – I parted company with probably all my oldest clerical friends: I 'burnt my ships' on a burning practical issue.<note xml:id="16" n="2"></note>  The members of the University gathered in force to hear me: &amp; my decision was sufficiently public.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Dean of Ripon, that fluid Latitudinarian <persName xml:id="214">Fremantle</persName>, wrote to ask me to join some scratch crew of religious cranks calling themselves the <orgName xml:id="30">'Christian Conference'</orgName>. I replied in these words.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dean, </p>
         <p>Thank you for your kind suggestion, but I won't join any societies – <hi rend="bold underline">I am sick to death of talk, &amp; reunion talk most of all. Nine-tenths of it is the merest cant, which never will lead, &amp; is never meant to lead to any action</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  After years of thought and self-violence, I have come to think that we ought frankly to recognize the non-Episcopal Ministries, &amp; negociate [sic] a fraternal federation of Churches variously organized but built on the Faith of the Incarnation and linked by Intercommunion in the Eucharist.  <hi rend="bold underline">This is the thesis I am now defending in a series of sermons in the Abbey</hi>. I mean to press this point as the proper preliminary to everything else. But I am not made for conventional talk, &amp; always come to grief when I dabble in it.</p>
         <p>Believe me &amp;c</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>My residence happened to facilitate my design.  I had arranged to take two months consecutively.  <hi rend="bold underline">The idea occurred to me that the Abbey pulpit should become the instrument for the propaganda I was meditating</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  On All Saints Day I struck the note, and on the following Sunday [Nov: 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1901] I pressed home in a long sermon the declaration I had made at Cambridge.  There was a great congregation, and the impression made was confirmed &amp; extended by the publication of the sermon in the <ref xml:id="121">"Church Family"</ref> newspaper, and the <ref xml:id="120">"Christian World Pulpit"</ref>.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="1004" display="no">Mr. Bunting</persName>, the Editor of the Contemporary Review, invited me to write an <ref xml:id="9">article</ref> on the theme of my discourses: and I consented</hi>. On Nov: 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I preached a long sermon in the interest of the <orgName xml:id="145" display="no">East London Church Fund</orgName>; and this also went to the <ref xml:id="122">Christian World Pulpit</ref>.  The Dissenting papers had copious &amp; gushing articles, which gave some opportunity to some characteristically venomous writing in the <ref xml:id="287" display="no">Church Times</ref>.  It seemed to me well to emphasize my position by posting a list of subjects.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="99">The Dean</persName> gave his consent, and I drafted a notice which was duly posted on the boards at the Abbey entrances</hi>.  This notice <hi rend="bold">[51] </hi>[symbol] ran thus.  <hi rend="italic">"Canon Hensley Henson will preach on Sunday afternoons at 3 p.m.  a <listEvent><event xml:id="7">Course of Sermons</event></listEvent> designed to facilitate Intercommunion with the non-Episcopal Churches."</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>The effect of this proceeding was almost nullified by a sudden change of weather. A bitter frost accompanied by fog made church-going difficult. However there was a large congregation on Nov: 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> when I <listEvent><event xml:id="158">preached</event></listEvent> on "Proselytising".  Among others I <hi rend="bold underline">recognized <persName xml:id="215">Mr. Asquith</persName> in the stalls</hi>.  On Monday <hi rend="bold underline">the Dean sent for me, and expressed alarm at what he called the controversial character of the notice. He said Gore had complained, &amp; the <persName xml:id="297">Precentor</persName></hi>.  I at once offered to issue another notice with only the names of the subjects, considering that my object had already been gained when the thesis had been fixed to the Abbey entrances, &amp; that it was plainly important to minimize domestic friction as far as possible.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, the Headmaster of Westminster</hi>, sent me a most friendly note on Sunday evening. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="217" display="no">Lady Wimborne</persName> wrote to ask me to stay at Canford: but I thought this would never do. So I replied in these terms.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Nov: 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1901</p>
         <p>Dear Lady Wimborne,</p>
         <p>I thank you much for your very kind letter, &amp; am glad to have your sympathy in the very difficult effort, to which I conceive myself bound to put my hand.  <hi rend="bold underline">But I am not at all a 'good Protestant' in the conventional sense, &amp; you would find me extraordinarily unsatisfactory</hi>. You must not resent it therefore if I decline your invitation, which, none the less, I am glad to have received &amp; think it extremely kind of you to send.</p>
         <p>Believe me.</p>
         <p>very faithfully yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was a great crowd in the Abbey on Nov: 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> when I <listEvent><event xml:id="80">preached</event></listEvent> on "Superstition".  <hi rend="bold underline">The Dean's Verger informed me that <persName xml:id="218">Lord Roberts</persName> was again present</hi>. He has attended all the sermons so far: &amp; also <persName xml:id="219">Lord Cadogan</persName>.</p>
         <p>There was a larger congregation than ever on Advent Sunday, numbers standing throughout the whole service.  One young man in Poet's Corner fainted &amp; was removed not without disturbing the adjacent listeners.  <hi rend="bold underline">I <listEvent><event xml:id="81">preached</event></listEvent> for 40 minutes</hi> on the Judgement of Christ.  Certain papers say that I was not well heard; on the other hand, I was assured by some of the congregation that they never heard more easily.  The aspect of the congregation was that of a listening crowd, &amp; certainly they were very still &amp; steady.  On Monday I took a chill, &amp; spent most part of the week in bed, preparing my next sermon with immense difficulty.  <hi rend="bold underline">The Article in the Contemporary</hi> - <ref xml:id="209">"Our unhappy Divisions, a Plea for the recognition of Non-Episcopal Churches"</ref> - appeared, &amp; attracted a good bit of notice from the religious press.</p>
         <p>The next Sunday was boisterous and wet, but there was a very large congregation, though rather less than on Advent Sunday. I <listEvent><event xml:id="159">preached</event></listEvent> <hi rend="bold">[54] </hi>on 'the Bible' with much effort.  The sermon was the least 'popular' of the whole course in form and in substance: and must have been difficult to follow for some of the audience.  However there was very good attention on the whole.</p>
         <p>The Dissenting Papers teem with effusive articles: especially the <ref xml:id="288" display="no">"Methodist Times"</ref>. <ref xml:id="289" display="no">The Record</ref> and the <ref xml:id="290" display="no">Rock</ref> are naturally well-pleased. The secular Press is not unfriendly but distinctly puzzled. The Guardian still preserves a threatening silence, &amp; the <ref xml:id="291" display="no">Church Times</ref> is intermittently abusive. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Dec: 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1901.</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I am much obliged to you for your letter, but it is not possible for me to undertake fresh work just now, when I have really more on my hands than I can well carry through.  Even if it were otherwise, however, I could not consent to take part in an inquiry so far-reaching in its inevitable suggestions &amp; consequences, &amp; so arbitrarily &amp; irrationally limited in its scope.  The public apprehensions, to which you refer in your post-script, have their justification, so far as they have any justification, in the whole body of facts relating to the Jesuits.  A complex history in nearly every country under the sun, protracted through 3 centuries, &amp; leaving as its result the relentless suspicion &amp; hatred, which beyond all question attach to the Jesuit Society, not merely or mainly in the Protestant sphere, cannot be the reflection of a blunder as to the formal teaching of the Jesuit canonists.  The blunder, if blunder it was, must be regarded as one effect of the exasperation caused by the Jesuit practice, &amp; the essential question is, precisely, the origin of that sustained &amp; practically universal exasperation.  It is sufficiently well known that I hold a very unfavourable view of <hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>the Jesuits, but I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be extremely sorry if my countrymen were so far to forget their own principles of freedom &amp; equity as to show discourtesy to strangers, who seek the hospitality of Great Britain from the inexorable distrust of their neighbours &amp; compatriots. So long as the French Jesuits &amp; other ecclesiastics respect the laws of this country, I am for receiving them with kindness.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>v. faithfully yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="220">Richard Butler Esq.</persName></p>
         <p>Editor of the Referee</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The last post on Saturday night brought me a very bitter cutting from the Church Review, bitter and base, and a characteristic cutting from the Tablet. The weather conditions on Sunday (Dec. 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>) were extremely unfavourable: a smoky fog developed in the course of the forenoon, and was distinctly unpleasant at the time of service. Moreover many people had left town for the holiday. There were thus explanations in abundance of the very obvious fact, that the congregation was distinctly smaller than on previous occasions.  And it seemed to me that it was more unfriendly.  There was more coughing than is usual when I preach, but this may have been due to the fog: and I noticed a certain amount of whispering.  However I preached my sermon on ‘Holy Communion' </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Christmas Day 1901 was an uncomfortable Festival.  The weather was dreadful, an icy &amp; furious rain in the fore-noon wonderfully thinned the congregations.  There was much coughing during my sermon until I rebuked it.  <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> was down with a chill, &amp; everything was quietly exasperating.  The communicants were 30 at 7 a.m., 104 at 8 a.m., 79 at 11 a.m.: total = 213.  The total number at the Abbey was 212.  </p>
         <p>Christmas Boxes:-</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">[symbol]</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1714" display="no">Canons' Verger</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;1</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">[symbol]</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> policemen</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">10/- apiece</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Gate-keeper</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">10/-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">[symbol]</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="300">Ellison</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;1</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1638" display="no">Miss Clark</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">10/-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1716" display="no">" Irons</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">10/-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1723" display="no">Ward</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">5/-</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1724" display="no">Wood</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">5/-</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather was mild &amp; threatening rain on the 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Dec:, when I delivered the concluding sermon of my course.  There was a great congregation, which included a very large proportion of men.  In spite of some coughing, which worried me at the start, there was very close attention.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="221">Lock</persName>, the Warden of Keble, was my guest from Saturday to Monday. He declined attendance at the sermon</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On New Year's Eve I wrote to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName>, and then went to Church &amp; gave a short address at a special service. <persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName> returned with me to the Rectory, &amp; spent the last two hours of the year in reading through some of the papers I design to publish, Edward Arnold having accepted a series of articles &amp; Essays in satisfaction of my promise made last spring.</p>
         <p>Thus ended my first year at Westminster. </p>
         <p>On New Year's Day, <persName xml:id="222">Albert Saxton</persName> came to lunch, &amp; took me for a walk. I gave him a copy of <ref xml:id="2">"Light &amp; Leaven"</ref>.  He strikes me as a manly &amp; intelligent fellow, &amp; would make a good parson.  </p>
         <p>In the evening I gave a "party" to the Choir boys: and romped madly with them. Kirshbaum, <persName xml:id="170">Perkins</persName>, <persName xml:id="59">Gerald</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="450">Miss Nichol</persName> helped to entertain them.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Contents of <ref xml:id="8">Volume of Essays</ref>.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Church Reform. I. Speech at the S. Alban's Diocesan Conference. Nov 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1897</item>
            <item>[symbol] Church Reform. II.  [1898] </item>
            <item>[symbol] Church Reform. III. Paper read to a private Conference of Clergy. Oct. 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1901</item>
            <item>The Confessional in the Nat. Church. [1898]</item>
            <item>[symbol] The Abp. of Canterbury's Charge. [1899]</item>
            <item>The British Sunday. [1899]</item>
            <item>The Abp's Judgment. [1899]</item>
            <item>The Mivart Episode. [1900]</item>
            <item>Sermons. [1901]</item>
            <item>French of Lahore [1896]</item>
            <item>Foreign Missions [1897]</item>
            <item>[symbol] The Chinese Puzzle of Missions [1900]</item>
            <item>[symbol] History of the Pastoral Ideal within the English Church since the Reformation [1900]</item>
            <item><ref xml:id="11">Cui bono? [1898]</ref></item>
            <item>[symbol] Dissent in England [1900]</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Subscriptions received</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Jan. 6.</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1726" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Humphreys</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;5.5.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">"</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="737">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Erskine</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;10.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">"</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1729">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Swinburne</persName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;10.0.0</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[63]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902</p>
         <p>My dear Churchwarden,</p>
         <p>I need not assure you that nothing is farther from my thought than, in any way, to show discourtesy to my excellent friends &amp; colleagues, the Churchwardens: but the appointment of the organist is my business, &amp; the determining of the type of service, so far of course, as the law does not determine it for me.</p>
         <p>I have satisfied myself that <persName xml:id="121">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Custard</persName> is prepared to carry on his work on the lines which I desire, &amp; which I understood the Churchwardens approved, viz: a reverent congregationalism.</p>
         <p>I do not agree with you about the organ recitals, which give great &amp; wholesome pleasure to many people, &amp; I never meditated considering their cessation, if the organist desired to carry them on, &amp; could do so satisfactorily.</p>
         <p>Believe me</p>
         <p>sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="184">H. H. Montague Smith Esq</persName></p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[64]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Westminster Abbey sermons &amp; others, making up altogether <ref xml:id="8">21 discourses</ref>, were published on Saturday, 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Feb: 1902</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  I directed <persName xml:id="348">Murray</persName> to send copies to all the diocesan bishops, and to a few dissenters &amp; others.  I myself gave away 30 copies.</p>
         <table>
    <row>
        <cell>1.</cell>
        <cell>Raleigh</cell>
		<cell>20.</cell>
		<cell><persName xml:id="32">Bp. of Colchester</persName></cell>
    </row>
    <row>
        <cell>2.</cell>
        <cell>Arthur</cell>
		<cell>21.</cell>
		<cell><persName xml:id="22">Ker</persName></cell>
    </row>
    <row>     
        <cell>3.</cell>
        <cell>Frank</cell>
		<cell>22.</cell>
		<cell><persName xml:id="203">Warre</persName></cell>
    </row>
	<row>
	<cell>4.</cell>
    <cell><persName xml:id="455">Gilbert</persName></cell>
<cell>23.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>5.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="297">Precentor</persName></cell>
<cell>24.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="40">Graham-Harrison</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>6.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="456">Blackmore</persName></cell>
<cell>25.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="222">Albert Saxton</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>7.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName></cell>
<cell>26.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="211">Woolcombe</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>8.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName></cell>
<cell>27.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="457" display="no">Roberts</persName> (<orgName xml:id="32">Choir School</orgName>)</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>9.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="170">Perkins</persName></cell>
<cell>28.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>10.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="458" display="no">Hughes</persName></cell>
<cell>29.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>11.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="459" display="no">Weller</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>12.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="460">Rutherford</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>13.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>14.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="461">Auntie</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>15.</cell>
<cell>The Library at <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">All Souls</orgName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>16.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="237">Benham</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>17.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="59">Gerald</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>18.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="202">Eyre</persName></cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>19.</cell>
<cell><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName></cell>
</row>
</table>


         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Feb: 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> <persName xml:id="240">Edward Arnold</persName> published a vol. of essays &amp;c entitled <ref xml:id="12">"<hi rend="bold underline">Cross-bench views</hi> of current Church Questions"</ref>: and on the next day <hi rend="italic">sent me &#x00A3;100 as agreed on</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> I travelled to Birmingham and <listEvent><event xml:id="94" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> in S. Philip's at 1.15 p.m.</hi>: at 6.30 p.m. I <listEvent><event xml:id="95" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> again at Queen's College.  I stayed until Friday morning preaching both on Thursday &amp; Friday.  Mine host – the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop Suffragan of Coventry</persName> – was very agreeable.  </p>
         <p>I read through <persName xml:id="1733">Benjamin Kidd</persName>'s new book –<ref xml:id="292">"Principles of Western Civilization"</ref>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[66]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Confirmation Candidates. March 21. 1902</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item><persName xml:id="1737" display="no">Davies, John Llewellyn</persName>. 26</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1738">Drowley, George</persName>. 24</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1739">Huckstepp, William John</persName>. 29</item>
         </list>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item><persName xml:id="1740">Atkinson, Marjorie Stopford</persName>. 16</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1741">Cunnington, Mabel Constance</persName>. 14</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1742">Hagger, Edith Anne</persName>. 16</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1743" display="no">Gates, Emma Mary</persName>. 15</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1744">Prestidge, Marion Constance</persName>.  15</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1745" display="no">Wheeler, Margaret Louisa</persName>. 17</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1746">Norris, Ethel Mabel Margaret</persName>.  19</item>
            <item><persName xml:id="1747">Bright, Ada</persName>. 17</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
