<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">. 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The bells are ringing in the new Century.  I am standing on the threshold of new work.  The year, just ended will be always memorable to me, as bringing me this immense opportunity.  When I seemed at the very end of my earthly hopes, this great thing was given me.  <hi rend="bold underline">I had not sought it, it came to me as the most absolute of surprises</hi>.  To this hour, I have no knowledge whose good offices commended me to <persName xml:id="31">Lord S</persName>.  This fact makes me adventure the belief that here I am <term xml:id="51">'<hi rend="underline">missus a Deo'</hi></term>.  And this faith has been strengthened by the extraordinary kindness which on all hands has been shown to me.  Here, I was welcomed most warmly, by everybody from the <persName xml:id="99">Dean</persName> to the Choir-boys.  More than 200 letters of congratulation, from all sorts &amp; conditions of men, were sent to me, many of them expressed in very ardent terms.  The <term xml:id="1">Socii</term>, as usual, were without exception affectionate.  <hi rend="bold underline">The newspapers, with the solitary exception of <ref xml:id="89" display="no">"Truth"</ref>, were friendly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><note xml:id="68" n="1"></note>  All this was very comforting, and in a real measure, strengthening.  Everybody seemed to be accepting me as <hi rend="underline">missus a Deo</hi>.  Thus I face the tremendous responsibilities of this great place with many tokens of confidence, in audience of many voices of encouragement.  Yet I own to a <hi rend="bold">[2]</hi> deep anxiety, almost a fear.  Can I, being what I know myself to be, do this work to which God has sent me?  "<hi rend="underline">The grass withereth: the flower fadeth: but the Word of our God shall stand for ever</hi>." - the confidence which I may have must altogether rest on Him, whose servant I am. With what mind, then, do I dare to put my hand to this plough? I would be a penitent for the past - "<hi rend="underline">I will confess my wickedness, &amp; be sorry for my sin</hi>" - for my amazing &amp; protracted unthankfulness, for my discontent, and egotism, and ambition, and manifold sin.  '<hi rend="underline">God be merciful to me a sinner</hi>'. Then, I would be a Disciple, make an act of personal trust in my living Master &amp; Lord, Jesus Christ, give myself altogether into His keeping. "<hi rend="underline">Lord, I believe: help Thou mine unbelief</hi>".  Finally, I would invoke the Comfort, guidance, purification, strength of the Holy Spirit - '<hi rend="underline">Come, Holy Ghost, my soul inspire</hi>'. Thus I would adventure on this new &amp; difficult enterprize, entirely renouncing confidence in myself, and trusting wholly to the Grace of God. "<hi rend="underline">Shew Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee"</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">Father, into Thy Hands I commend my spirit</hi>."</p>
         <p>[1.a.m.]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My work in the Abbey has begun this New Year's Day, when I began my month's Residence. The Dean being absent I Celebrated after Mattins. There were no less than 72 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, including <persName xml:id="177">Bishop Barry</persName>. </p>
         <p>In the afternoon I attended Evensong: <persName xml:id="73">Bayne</persName> preached very excellently. <persName xml:id="850">Bain</persName> called, and returned later with a picture which he had purchased for me. What an impulsive, affectionate creature he is! My Rural dean, <persName xml:id="407">Northcote</persName>, who is <persName xml:id="187">Farrar</persName>'s son in law called.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>