<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[20]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The <term xml:id="52">Audit Chapter</term> was held in the <placeName xml:id="10">Jerusalem Chamber</placeName>.  The proceedings had to be continued after Evensong, when I moved,</p>
         <p>'That the <persName xml:id="99">Dean</persName> be requested to authorize the use of the Revised Version of the Bible in the Abbey at the option of the Canon in residence.'</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName></hi><hi rend="bold underline"> offered a strenuous &amp; irrational opposition: but he was absolutely alone,</hi> and I had determined to accept no compromise.  Finally we carried the motion by 4 to 1. [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Feb. 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1901</p>
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="184">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Montague Smith</persName></p>
         <p>I know your genuine interest in <orgName xml:id="16">St. Margaret's</orgName>, &amp; I much appreciate your care &amp; work for the Church: but, after carefully considering the situation, I see no reason for alarm, &amp; much for good hope.  There is no ground for thinking (at least I know of none) that the measure of support given to the Parochial organizations will be less in the future than in the past: &amp; on the Choir we are effecting an economy of about &#x00A3;500 per annum.</p>
         <p>We cannot go back to the exact position under <persName xml:id="187">Dean Farrar</persName>, even if we desired to do so, for the interval has materially altered the situation.  It would be really absurd to be the responsible owners, or rather, trustees of a great organ like that in S. Margaret's, &amp; not to use it adequately.  Therefore we must be ready to expend a sufficient sum to secure an organist &amp; Choir worthy of the Church &amp; the Instrument.  I should never have approved the introduction of an organ, so costly &amp; extensive, but there it is, &amp; I must accept it as part of my charge.</p>
         <p>Last year for many reasons was a very <hi rend="bold">[22]</hi> unfavourable year for the finances of S. Margaret's, &amp; yet the total deficit on all the accounts do not amount when justly considered (as far as I can discover) to &#x00A3;150.  We shall face an expenditure reduced by some &#x00A3;500 in the current year. Why should be in doubt [sic] as to our solvency? I ought to say decisively that I am not prepared to reconsider the question of the Choir. We have taken up a position after careful thought: it has been very well accepted by parishioners &amp; congregation: it would be weak, &amp; undignified, &amp; indefensible to abandon it almost immediately. Do not be anxious. All will come right, if we stand firm &amp; work together like men.</p>
         <p>Let me deal with <persName xml:id="50">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lemare</persName>.  His position is a delicate &amp; a difficult one: &amp; he has, so far, acted with great self-suppression, &amp;, in my judgment, very honourably. On all hands I hear satisfaction expressed that he sees his way to remain at S. Margaret's.</p>
         <p>There, my dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Montague Smith, is all I think need be said, except only that I should like to repeat that I value your constant &amp; loyal work very highly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is a great strength &amp; help to me to have Churchwardens like those of S. Margaret's, &amp; as I mean to treat them with the utmost frankness &amp; confidence, as not merely colleagues, but personal friends, so I depend on them for a loyal &amp; constant support in the course which we have decided upon &amp; announced.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Very sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON.</p>
         <p>I think it would be well to let <persName xml:id="98">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hunt</persName> see this letter. </p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]		</p><div type="letter">
         <p>To <persName xml:id="188">Charles M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Arthur Esq. M.P.</persName></p>
         <p>March 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1901</p>
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I thank you for your letter. My practice in S. Margaret's has no connexion whatever with any doctrine, Roman or other, of the Holy Communion.  It is the pious custom which, ever since I have been in Orders, I have followed without offence.  It is our practice in the Abbey, as, I believe, in most, if not all, Cathedral Churches, where I am sure, no suggestions of Roman or other errors are found to be connected with it.  I assume that my congregation understand this, &amp; need no explanation of an accustomed act of reverence, which like bowing at the Name of Jesus, or turning to the East at the Creed, or uncovering the head on entering Church, or kneeling at prayer, &amp; at the reception of the Holy Communion, needs no other explanation than that wh. lies on the surface of every act of accustomed reverence.  This I may rightly add, that I am rather more than ordinarily vigilant about reverent action in S. Margaret's because I find a very lax tradition in that <hi rend="bold">[25]</hi> respect in the Choir, &amp; to some extent in the congregation.  I am sure you will support me in trying to raise the level of the Church in this respect, &amp; as to suggestions of Romanizing sympathies, I must ask you to banish them wholly from your mind.  I do not resent them under all the circumstances of the hour, but I trust that they will not survive my explicit assurance.</p>
         <p>Hoping to have the pleasure of making your personal acquaintance before long.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>v. faithfully yrs,</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On March 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I wrote to <persName xml:id="191">Dr Ince</persName> proposing to write 3 dissertations for the Doctor's Degree on 1.Peter, 1.Cor.XV, Acts II.</p>
         <p>On March 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Churchwardens' meeting was held.  We sat for an hour and a half.  Our unappropriated subscriptions were voted away thus:- <orgName xml:id="26">National Schools</orgName> &#x00A3;15:  <orgName xml:id="28" display="no">Cottage Home</orgName> &#x00A3;10:  Parish Magazine &#x00A3;5: <orgName xml:id="139" display="no">Girls Club</orgName> &#x00A3;5  = <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;35</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                     <placeName xml:id="45">Dartmouth Hall</placeName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="184">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> H. Montague Smith</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                  <orgName xml:id="140" display="no">S. Margaret's Relief Society</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="98">Mr H. A. Hunt</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                     Soup Kitchen.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1558" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Tyler Smith</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Tothill School Institute.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="159">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scholes</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="141" display="no">School Treat Fund</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="758" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rutt</persName>. <persName xml:id="156">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fedarb</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
S. Margaret's Cottage Home.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1560">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lloyd Williams</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="142" display="no">Bandinel Charity</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="76">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Henson</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Girls Club.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="77">Miss Henson</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                  
                  S. Margaret's Nat<hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi> Schools.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rutt.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Parish Magazine.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="62">Rev. S. Kirshbaum</persName>.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Boys Club.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><persName xml:id="1561" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Robinson</persName></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="143" display="no">Fresh Air Fund</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Alms Fund.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                     Church Printing.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"/>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>General Subscriptions</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="144" display="no">Bp. of S. Alban's Fund</orgName></cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">2.2.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName> in Bethnal Green</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">2.2.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="22">Free &amp; Open Church</orgName>.	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="132" display="no">Bp. of London's Fund</orgName>		</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="145" display="no">East London Church Fund</orgName>.	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">2.2.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="23">S.P.G.</orgName>		</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="24" display="no">Oxford Mission to Calcutta</orgName>	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><orgName xml:id="25">Eastern Churches Association</orgName>	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">.10.6</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing"><placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName>		</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">1.1.1</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[29]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Parochial Subscriptions.</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="26">National Schools</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;11.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="27">Westminster Hospital</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;3.3.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
<orgName xml:id="28" display="no">S. Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi> Cottage Home</orgName>.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;5.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
Curates Fund.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;20.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                  Refuge &amp; Rescue Work.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;2.2.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                  Swimming Club.
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">
                  Regatta
               </cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;1.1.0</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>March 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1901.</p>
         <p>My Dear Lemare,</p>
         <p>At the Churchwardens' meeting this afternoon, we had before us an account from Novello for music amounting to over &#x00A3;18 and evidently extending over a considerable period.  We decided to pay it, but thought it right that in future all orders for new Music should be given by the Churchwardens.  Your course will be, when you think some new music is needed, to write to me, &amp; state what you want: then I will lay it before the Churchwardens at our monthly meeting, &amp;, if it is approved, they will give the necessary order.</p>
         <p>It was pointed out that advertisements of the Organ Recitals were appearing weekly in the papers.  I trust you will not forget what I pointed out before, that the Churchwardens are not prepared to pay for more than the posters, the programmes, &amp; one advertisement announcing the beginning of the series of recitals &amp; another announcing its close.  Our finances will not admit of more, &amp; it is essential that decisions once taken are acted upon.</p>
         <p>Further, I have ordered that in future <hi rend="bold">[31] </hi>the lights shall not be turned down at the organ recitals.  A complaint came to me from some ladies who were molested last week by some man, who seems to have been drinking.  Of course, an intruder of that kind argues nothing against the general good order, which is excellent, but this is a case of not letting our good be evil spoken of, &amp; therefore, in future, there will be light.</p>
         <p>I trust you have now quite recovered from your indisposition.  I am myself still rather a poor creature.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
