<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Epiphany, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="169">Bernard Wilson</persName> preached to a large congregation at Mattins.  He made a brief allusion to the <persName xml:id="1228" display="no">Queen</persName>: and also to the <persName xml:id="118">Bishop</persName>.  I celebrated and, before the Prayer for the Church Militant, I asked prayer for the Queen.  <hi rend="italic">It was solemn to think that probably for the last time, I was naming Victoria at the Altar where she had received her crown.  </hi>In the afternoon, there <hi rend="bold">[8]</hi> was an immense throng.  <hi rend="bold underline">I preached for 40 minutes mainly about Bishop Creighton</hi>. The congregation was very attentive, though great part of it had to stand all the sermon through. At Evensong there was again a very large congregation. <persName xml:id="1351">Jones</persName>, Vicar of Petworth preached.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday afternoon about 6.30 the Queen died</hi>.  In the afternoon at the Abbey I asked the Minor Canon, <persName xml:id="122">Hine-Haycock</persName>, to read the prayer in the 'Communion for the Sick' inserting the Queen's name;  Earlier in the day, I had wired to the Bell-ringers postponing the supper which had been arranged for the night.  Then I went round to the Tower with <persName xml:id="170">Perkins</persName>, and spoke to those Bell-ringers who were ringing a muffled peal, &amp; expressed my regret at being compelled to postpone the supper.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
