<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>For the first time in my life I failed at Holy Communion thro' sheer not being up in time.  I had assumed that 8.30 a.m. was the hour of service, &amp; ordered my uprising on that hypothesis.  However, <persName xml:id="170">Perkins</persName> was at the Church &amp; did not wait for me.</p>
         <p>I propose to preach on a very hard text </p>
         <p>"Ye cannot serve God &amp; Mammon" - the truth is as obvious, as its application difficult.  The normal contradiction between the Christian's principle &amp; practice becomes in the Christian Minister an openly aggressive thing, hurting men's consciences.  It is a tough problem.  We are not exempt from the normal anxieties.  The Law resolutely ignores the ministerial character, &amp; 'Society' is not slow to follow in the wake of law.  We live, must live, in the main order &amp; habit of our lives with our class.  So far the exalted language we hold in the pulpits seems a trifle absurd.  But there is not one law for the Minister, another for the laity: he must be normal if he is to set them an example.  Clearly then he is to live on the highest level of the general morality, not on a higher morality - be exemplary in fact, not extraordinary.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[102]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was an unusually large, &amp; very attentive congregation, and 100 communicants at the celebration.  At Evensong, I preached a sermon written as long ago as 1891, for the 'Friendly Societies' of Barking.  It seemed to me more pretentious &amp; rhetorical than my more modern compositions.  It was listened to with close attention.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday October 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902, I journeyed to Northampton for the <orgName xml:id="77">Church Congress</orgName>.  Mine host was <hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> <persName xml:id="278">Cooper</persName> of Delapr&#x00E9; Abbey</hi>, and in him I found much to interest me.  He was (so I was incidentally informed) a wealthy boot-maker: he evidently had been a poor working cobbler.  He retained the language &amp;, in some degree, the habits of his primitive state.  I liked both him &amp; <persName xml:id="1773" display="no">his wife</persName>: their real goodness attracted, their aggressive vulgarity amused me.  Their <persName xml:id="1774" display="no">sons</persName> were public School &amp; University men.</p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="105">Bishop of Rochester</persName>'s sermon in All Saints Church was a really fine effort; it took 50 minutes to deliver.  The acting-President, <persName xml:id="279">Bishop Thicknesse</persName>, struck me as pompous &amp; shallow.  He was also indistinct in his utterance. "Home Reunion" came on immediately after the Presidential address.  The <persName xml:id="280">Bp. of Ripon</persName>, who came first, was windy &amp; futile: the audience was not greatly impressed by him.  <persName xml:id="9" display="no">Collins</persName> followed with a common-place paper of the confident High Church variety, which greatly pleased a large section of the Congress.  Then I came, &amp; was well listened to, even applauded, but clearly did not have the general sense of the Assembly on my side.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[104]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="281">Bishop Montgomery</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="283">his wife</persName>, the <persName xml:id="285">Dean of Peterboro</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="1775" display="no">his son</persName> were guests of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cooper: also my old friend <persName xml:id="289">Anderson</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, the 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I returned to Westminster, &amp;, later in the day, left for Oxford, where the Bodleian Tercentenary was in progress.  I arranged for the removal of my furniture from my college rooms and (on Thursday, the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) again returned to Westminster.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[105]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">As I was reading over my sermon before Evensong on Sunday</hi><hi rend="italic underline">, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the 12</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> October 1902, a note was brought to me from <persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName>.  It was an intimation that on the preceding day, he had received the offer of the Deanery &amp; had accepted it</hi><hi rend="italic">. On the whole it is a good appointment: &amp; we have escaped many things.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
