<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Thanksgiving for Peace attracted great congregations both at Mattins &amp; at Evensong.<note xml:id="17" n="1"></note>  I preached at both services.  The Commons were represented by <persName xml:id="253">Sir Henry Fowler</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="255">Sir Walter Foster</persName>, everybody else had gone to S. Paul's to be with the <persName xml:id="928" display="no">King</persName>.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">In the congregation was the <persName xml:id="257">Abp. of Armagh</persName>, who afterwards observed to Miss L. of my sermon, that it was "Liddon at his best", which seems extravagant even for an Irishman</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> read the first Lesson: &amp; the <persName xml:id="99">Dean</persName> the second.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">In the Evening, the <persName xml:id="259">Bishop of New York</persName> was in the congregation</hi><hi rend="italic">.  He sent me a message to the effect that 'if I would come to New York &amp; preach that sermon, I sh</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have a right royal welcome'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> June, I dined with <persName xml:id="260">Lady Sherbrooke</persName>.  The weather was appalling, &amp; I was extremely indisposed: so I was not particularly happy.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> June, I dined with <persName xml:id="253">Sir Henry Fowler</persName>. I took his brilliant <persName xml:id="265">daughter</persName> down to dinner &amp; exchanged much talk with her. Among others I met <persName xml:id="264">Sir W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Broadbent</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="266">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Robson</persName>.  Also <persName xml:id="255">Sir W. Foster</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O Saviour Christ, I pray Thee to own my ministry this night when in Thy Name, I pray Thy people to help Thy poor.  Save me from the condemnation of those, Who worked unrighteousness even in their preaching of Thy Gospel.  Grant that I may not hear Thee say 'Depart', in the day of judgment. Have mercy upon me, most merciful Redeemer, and forgive all my hypocrisy &amp; self-confidence &amp; lack of love. Give me Thy Spirit of tenderness and sacrifice, that the words which I speak to others may be fruitful in them and in me. Be Thou Thyself, O dear Master, the Preacher this night, and make Thy message known to Thy people. Let none go forth from Thy House untouched by Thy Word, unhelpful to Thy Cause, but bring us all nearer to Thee by our worship this day. Grant this, O saviour, for Thy tender mercy's sake.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The crowds hang about Westminster from morning till evening, and gaze with unflagging delight on the decorations in the streets, the huge erections for spectators, and, above all, on the entrance hall at the Western entrance of the Abbey.  <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, whenever the doors are open, is invaded by visitors.  <hi rend="bold underline">On June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, I preached 3 times on the Coronation.  No other subject was possible</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[92]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>To <persName xml:id="271">Thackeray Turner Esq.</persName></p><div type="letter">
         <p>July 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I have not seen the <ref xml:id="14">statement in the "Daily News"</ref> to which you refer in your letter of the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, but I gather from what you say that it was of a detailed &amp; alarmist character.  I am quite ignorant of the sources of information, from which the author of that statement drew the alleged facts.  There is, so far as I know, nothing to justify any anxiety as to the stability of the East End of S. Margaret's, or as to the preservation of the fabric of the church, or as to the fate of the great window at the East End.  If, on investigation anything seems to be required for the security of the church, no doubt the requisite steps will be taken by its responsible guardians.</p>
         <p>Believe me, </p>
         <p>Faithfully yrs</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
