<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Margaret's Day, July 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m.  There were 44 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>, of whom but 5 were males, &amp; these included <persName xml:id="282">Campbell</persName> &amp; myself.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After the Coronation (August 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902) I preached at a special Thanksgiving Service at which the Abbey Choir sang, and the <persName xml:id="1764">Mayor</persName> &amp; Corporation of Westminster attended in robes.  (August 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1902) On the next day <hi rend="bold underline">I fled to Oxford to avoid the persecution of the American tourists</hi>.  There I remained until Wednesday morning, when I returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> accompanied by <persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName>.  He stayed with me for that night, &amp; then went abroad.  On Friday I went to Scotland by the night train from Euston.  <persName xml:id="1767">Thesiger</persName>, a cousin of <persName xml:id="65">Fred: Thesiger</persName> was my compagnon de voyage as far as Stirling.  I was most hospitably entertained at Balmains, Stanley, Perth, by the <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="284"><persName xml:id="1769">Wolfe-Barrys</persName></persName></hi>, &amp; then went to Helensburgh where I was received by <persName xml:id="286">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Paisley</persName> at 110 East Clyde Street.  Here <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was, &amp; I began the round of Scotch cousins.  On Friday (Aug 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1902) I went on to Artarmon, Row, &amp; was received there by <persName xml:id="287">Col: Gore-Booth</persName>.  On Sunday Aug 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902 I preached in Row Church an old sermon, &amp; in the afternoon I attended a children's service in the Established Church.  The minister - <persName xml:id="288">Webster</persName> - seems a capable man.  On Monday I went with Ella to Fairlie, where <persName xml:id="1547">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Charles Parker</persName> courteously entreated us.  There I continued until Thursday (Aug: 28) when I went on to Dalton Vicarage near to Dumfries where <hi rend="bold">[99]</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I stayed a night with <persName xml:id="227">Murray</persName></hi>.  On Friday, the 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> August, I travelled back to Westminster.  On Saturday I went with <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> house-hunting<hi rend="italic"> to Horley in Surrey, where we decided to rent a small house</hi>.  On Sunday, August 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, I preached twice in S. Margarets.  The rain fell heavily from 8.30 a.m. to 4 p.m.  <hi rend="italic">There was a fair congregation at Mattins, including <persName xml:id="292">Lord Rosebery</persName>: and a large congregation at Evensong.  After service a pleasant faced-young man pursued me in order to thank me for my sermons, &amp; to tell me they had helped him</hi>.  He seemed to be speaking sincerely.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="293">Edwin Saxton</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="294" display="no">Ernest Reynolds</persName> came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Our Saviour Christ, Who hast called us to follow Thee in this difficult life of earth, have mercy on our weakness and pardon our failures.  Show Thou us the way that we should walk in for we lift up our souls unto Thee.  Thou, O Lord, didst bear the sore burden of unkindness &amp; ingratitude: Thou wast misread by jealous eyes, &amp; defamed by envious tongues: and Thou gavest no cause, in Thee was no fault.  Alas, O Master, we are not so: our sufferings have place &amp; title in our own action, &amp; we never wholly undeserve our pain.  Yet we are not patient as Thou wert; we do not forgive like Thee.  Have compassion on us, O Divine Redeemer: by Thy Cross &amp; Passion deliver us from sin.  Pour into our hearts the spirit of self-sacrifice which filled Thine, and stamp on our lives the visible impress of Thy Cross.  Teach us to forgive not seven times, but seventy times seven, and for all the unkindness &amp; calumny of our lives grant us more &amp; more approach to Thee.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
