<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="b">[135]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="b">Thursday, December 4</hi><hi rend="b sup u">th</hi><hi rend="b">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <persName id="331">Archibald S. Routledge</persName> came to see me with reference to my letter about <persName id="113">Knowling</persName>. He, at first, asserted that his intentions and behaviour were excellent, and named many well-known people who were his &amp; friends &amp; relatives, &amp;, © such, vouchers for his character. I was peremptory and severe, requiring his word of honour to break off at once all relations with the boy.  Then he became excited &amp; finally semi-hysterical, weeping &amp; flinging himself on his knees, professing his ardent affection for Knowling &amp;c.  He finally admitted, while asserting constantly the absence of any impurity, that he had been an utter fool, that he had spoken &amp; written to the lad improperly, that he had treated him quite absurdly.  He promised me to have no more to do with him, &amp; asked me to explain matters to him &amp; his (Knowling's) <persName id="327">father</persName>.  I strongly advised him to leave off coming to <orgName id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>: and spoke as solemnly in warning as I could. He thanked me &amp; went away. He strikes me as a feeble, neurotic creature, capable of any collapse.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="b">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In answer to a letter from <persName id="272">M<hi rend="sup u">rs</hi> Routledge</persName>, I wrote as follows.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>December 7<hi rend="sup u">th</hi> 1902.</p>
         <p>My dear Madam,</p>
         <p>You are under a mistake. I make no kind of imputation on your son beyond that of extreme indiscretion. He is a stranger to me: I have no other sentiments towards him than those of goodwill: &amp;, as I told him, his conduct in coming directly to see me predisposed me in his favour. But I cannot permit the kind of acquaintance which he had formed with Harold Knowling. It is not wholesome either for him, or for the lad: &amp; it is clearly incompatible with the discipline &amp; the credit of the Choir. It must cease at once. If M<hi rend="sup u">r</hi>  Archibald Routledge had declined to give me his word, I should at once have dismissed Knowling from the Choir, which, he rightly saw, would have been highly unjust to the lad.  On recalling my interview with your son, I cannot regret the advice which I considered myself entitled to give him, &amp;, as he thanked <hi rend="b">[137] </hi>me at the time, so I feel sure in the future, he will not find reason to be other than thankful.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>faithfully yrs</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="b">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName id="328">M<hi rend="sup u">rs</hi> Knowling</persName> sent to me for my perusal two letters, one from M<hi rend="sup u">r</hi> Archibald Routledge, the other from his mother. I wrote to her, in returning them, thus:-</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Dec: 7<hi rend="sup u">th</hi> 1902.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="sup u">rs</hi> Knowling,</p>
         <p>I thank you for letting me see the enclosed letters. M<hi rend="sup u">r</hi> Archibald Routledge is a stranger to me, &amp; I daresay his intentions may be excellent: but it is wholesome &amp; creditable neither for himself nor for <persName id="113">Harold</persName> that he should form &amp; sustain so intimate an acquaintance.  I cannot permit it in the interest of the credit &amp; discipline of the Choir.  I have pointed this out to M<hi rend="sup u">r</hi> Routledge, &amp; he has pledged his word that his intercourse with <persName id="113">Harold</persName> shall at once cease.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>sincerely yrs,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text>
