<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. in the Abbey, and in the course of the service, asked for prayers on behalf of the <persName xml:id="171">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName>, who is reported to be seriously ill.</p>
         <p>I preached at Mattins in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>: the congregation was small in numbers, &amp; poor in social type. I begged hard for the <orgName xml:id="152" display="no">Rochester Diocesan Society</orgName>, but only raised &#x00A3;24, which was sufficiently disappointing, especially as I left myself little voice for the afternoon sermon in the Abbey.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation at 3 p.m. but not unusually large.  I rather suspect that the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName>'s Saturday afternoon lectures are affecting injuriously my Sunday afternoon congregations. People who have come to the Abbey on Saturday, are disinclined to repeat the process on Sunday. I preached for about 35 minutes on "Judgment by associations". On the whole, the people seemed to be attentive.</p>
         <p>At Evensong in S. Margaret's, <persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName> preached a very good sermon: &amp; afterwards I gave a very short instruction on "Judgment".</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="329">Lyster Jandron</persName> came to church &amp; supper.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
