<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I preached twice in the Abbey, at Mattins and in the afternoon.  In the morning I used an old sermon on the Eucharist, preached as recently as Palm Sunday in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. In the afternoon, I preached on "The Faith that is blessed", the subject naturally suggested by S. Thomas's Day. There was a large congregation, more mingled with restless elements than usual, as, I observe, is the case when holiday seasons approach. My sermon took just 35 minutes to deliver.</p>
         <p>At Evensong I preached in S. Margaret's on the Holy Communion, and afterwards conducted a Preparation Service, which was well attended.  </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="293">Edwin Saxton</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Christmas Eve, I received another letter from <persName xml:id="331">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Routledge</persName>, to which I replied.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Dec. 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1902,</p>
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I am very sure that anyone who cared for your character &amp; reputation, as - though you may not believe it - I do, would approve the course which I have adopted, and, assuredly, nothing will induce me to adopt any other course.  Consult your friends.  You are a Harrovian.  Take counsel with your old Head-master, <persName xml:id="114">Bishop Welldon</persName>, who is again in England, &amp; follow their advice, if you will not follow mine.  I have nothing more to say to you.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>faithfully yrs,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
