<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Innocents' Day, Sunday after Christmas, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m., when, including 3 clergy, there were but 13 cts. Having seen <persName xml:id="321">Carlyle</persName> safely into his place in the procession, &amp; introduced him to the <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName>, I finished my sermon, and then went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> and delivered it.  There was but a moderate congregation, &amp; much coughing.  Also, in the middle of my preaching, I was a little disconcerted by a down-fall of 'blacks', which sprinkled my page, my surplice, &amp; myself in an uncomfortable way. There was an immense congregation in the Abbey at Evensong, many people in the transepts having to stand throughout the service. I preached for 40 minutes, &amp; was listened to with really notable attention, from beginning to end.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the course of my sermon I made an earnest appeal to the Nonconformists to work the Education Act honestly, and I concluded with a brief reference to the late <persName xml:id="171">Archbishop</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Then, on my return to the house, I summoned a District Messenger, &amp; send [sic] my sermon to <persName xml:id="322">Buckle</persName>, with a note.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The <ref xml:id="114">"Times"</ref> on Monday, Dec: 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, reported the concluding part of my sermon<note xml:id="21" n="1"></note>: and on the following day, the "Free Church leaders", <persName xml:id="57">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Clifford</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="323">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Silvester Horne</persName>, made characteristic answer in the <ref xml:id="115">"Daily News"</ref>, in vehement letters.<note xml:id="22" n="2"></note></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The last day of a year more than commonly full of incidents, &amp; for me personally of critical importance, was uneventful enough. I attended my services as Canon in Residence: wrote a sermon; &amp; preached it in S. Margaret's at 8 p.m. Then after supper, I retired to my room, &amp; wrote letters to <persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>January 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1903</p>
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="98">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hunt</persName>, </p>
         <p>I think it is desirable that I should no longer delay to state definitely how I propose to allocate the money received from the contractor for the use of the churchyard on the occasion of the Coronation.  The total sum was &#x00A3;3000.  Of this sum I desire to place one half i.e. &#x00A3;1500 in the hands of the Churchwardens to form the nucleus of a Fund for completing the restoration of S. Margaret's. Of the remainder I have already approved expenditure of the following sums viz:-</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Entertainment &amp;c on the occasion of the Coronation</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">33.17.9</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Charges connected with vaccinating the children of the National Schools</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">26.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Books for S. Margaret's</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">47.2.10</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Balance of account for drainage of the Church</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">110.4.9</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Electric lighting of the Church, say</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">130.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Safe for the Vestry</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">50.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Overdraft on the Parochial account	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">400.0.0</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[148]</hi>
         </p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">Dilapidations of the Rectory	</cell>
               <cell rend="No_Spacing">&#x00A3;300.0.0</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>These sums amount to &#x00A3;1097.5.4, say, &#x00A3;1100, leaving a balance of &#x00A3;400.</p>
         <p>This sum I propose to retain in my own hands &amp; apply to two purposes. (1) (as to &#x00A3;300) the assistance of a poor scholar at Oxford during his academic course.  (2) the formation of an emergency Fund to meet special cases of need, which cannot be fairly met from ordinary sources.</p>
         <p>I desire that this letter be filed for reference, that on a future occasion, if need arise for precedents, it may be accessible.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
