<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1902.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Fourteen years ago on this day I was publicly instituted in Barking Church to the charge of that great parish. <persName xml:id="330">Bishop Blomfield</persName> who instituted me is dead; &amp; the friends who then supported me are widely scattered. Of the enthusiasm which then filled me nothing remains but a mocking memory. Of pastoral purpose there survives but little.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">I notice on turning to my diary that on the following Monday, December 3</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 1888, I <listEvent><event xml:id="101">preached</event></listEvent> for the first time in Westminster Abbey</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><note xml:id="31" n="1"></note>
         </p>
         <p>The weather was hateful: steady rain with high enfeebling temperature. Congregation at Mattins abnormally small. <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> came to lunch.</p>
         <p>At Evensong the congregation, by its smallness, certified the wretchedness of the weather. After Evensong there was a short intercession service for Foreign Missions.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>To <persName xml:id="331">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> A. Routledge</persName>, Coombe Lodge, Combe Lane, Wimbledon.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>December 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1902.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir,</p>
         <p>It has been brought to my notice that you have made the acquaintance of <persName xml:id="113">Harold Knowling</persName>, the solo boy in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> Church, Westminster, &amp; have been in the practice of seeing him frequently, &amp; making him presents. I feel that I ought to tell you that the choirboys are forbidden to accept the invitations &amp; gifts of strangers, &amp; I have, accordingly, warned Knowling that in his case that rule cannot be broken.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>faithfully yrs</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I addressed the following to <persName xml:id="333">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Vacher</persName>, of Chudleigh, Surbiton Hill.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>December 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1902</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Vacher,</p>
         <p>It will give me much pleasure to grant my sanction to your placing a brass to your <persName xml:id="332">Father</persName> in S. Margaret's Church.  He bears a name justly regarded in the parish, &amp; the perpetuation of his name on the Church walls will be welcome.  You will understand that I have to be very watchful as to the introduction of monuments into S. Margaret's, as well because of the great importance of that historic Church, as because persons with no claim at all, either public or local, desire sometimes to set up memorials there. In the case of the brasses set up by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lavie &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hora, I had to settle the question of the Fee to be charged for brasses, &amp; I propose to adopt the same scale as was in their cases, accepted i.e. six guineas for residents &amp; twelve guineas for non-residents.  The fee is substantial in order to discourage frivolous applications, but is not wholly arbitrary, being twice the Fees customary for monuments in the Churchyard, when that was in use. I shall, therefore, have to ask you <hi rend="bold">[134]</hi> (1) to pay a Fee of twelve guineas, (2) to submit to me the exact size of the brass, &amp; the proposed inscription, (3) to meet me in the Church &amp; choose a site for its erection. I think that is all that needs to be said.</p>
         <p>Believe me, 	</p>
         <p>sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson.</p>
         <p>E. F. Vacher, Esq.</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
