<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>O holy &amp; blessed Jesus grant that this day I may not speak one word against the Truth, but only that which shall minister to Thine Honour, &amp; the help of Thy People.  Amen.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="376">Knox Little's</persName> motion was postponed to the afternoon &amp; then, after an abortive effort by the Deans of <persName xml:id="44">Westminster</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="382">Windsor</persName> to carry the ‘previous question', it was debated. A resolution was passed excluding reporters &amp; strangers - a most unusual proceeding.  <hi rend="bold underline">Knox Little moved, <persName xml:id="375">Worlledge</persName> seconded, and <persName xml:id="385">Newbolt</persName> supported the resolution begging the Bps to make a declaration on the Virgin Birth, &amp; the Resurrection</hi>. He incorporated the materialistic language of the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Article in his motion.  <hi rend="bold underline">I opposed in a speech of some length, in the course of which I submitted the following propositions</hi>:-</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>That the language of our doctrinal formularies cannot be pressed in a literal sense.</item>
            <item>That the Christian theology has been from age to age modified by the current science &amp; philosophy of the time</item>
            <item>That this modification has gone to the length <hi rend="bold">[181]</hi> of the total rejection of articles of belief held to be fundamental.</item>
            <item>That the science of Biblical criticism has affected &amp; must affect the belief of the Church.</item>
            <item>That the critical treatment of the N.T. has raised certain questions affecting those <hi rend="italic">articles of the Creed which declare the mode of Christ's Incarnation &amp; Resurrection.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>I asked the House to consider such facts as the following:-</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>&#x3B1;  The Virgin Birth was admittedly not preached by the Apostles.</item>
            <item>&#x3B2;  In the N.T. it is absolutely confined to ‘Supplemental Matter' included in the opening chapter of the first &amp; third Gospels.</item>
            <item>&#x3B3;  These chapters are hard to reconcile with one another.</item>
            <item>&#x3B4;  The great theologians of the N.T. - S. Paul &amp; S. John - who constantly affirm &amp; argue from the Incarnation are quite silent as to the Virgin Birth.</item>
            <item>&#x3B5;   The argument of the Ep. to the Hebrews seems naturally to assume an ordinary birth.</item>
            <item>&#x3B6;   The genealogies are Joseph's.  Christ's <hi rend="bold">[182]</hi> Davidic descent is ‘traced thro' Joseph &amp; not thro' Mary'.</item>
            <item>&#x3B7;   The language of the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> &amp; 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Gospels - apart from the supplemental matter - is quite natural</item>
            <item>&#x3B8;   Very early there was ‘a tendency to emphasize the virginity of Mary, &amp; to remove expressions which seemed in any way to conflict with this <hi rend="bold">[']</hi>.</item>
            <item>&#x3B9; There was a ‘wide-spread tradition that the Apostle Thomas was the twin-brother of Jesus'.</item>
         </list>
         <p>I said that such facts as these did constitute a real question, which ought to be honestly &amp; reverently examined: that with respect to the Resurrection the case was very similar.  The Fact is everywhere affirmed &amp; assumed in the Apostolic writings, but the mode of the mystery is obscure &amp; seems to be apprehended differently by S. Paul, and by the Evangelists.  The language of the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Article is hard to reconcile with 1.Cor.xv.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>That the critical inquiry ought not to be prejudged in the interest of the Christian tradition.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The truth must be defended by argument, not by denunciations.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"I am convinced that a cruel wrong will be inflicted on many good &amp; earnest Christians, who worship Christ with sincerity, &amp; do his work in the world, if we affirm that to doubt the Virgin-Birth implies denial of the Incarnation, &amp; to repudiate the materialism of Article 4, is to deny the Resurrection.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">What are we asking the Bishops to do? We are asking them to attempt a task, which experience often repeated, has shown to be futile viz:- to suppress inquiry by authority.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I submit that this course is not merely tactically mistaken, but morally indefensible.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">One word more: for one person who doubts the Article, there are a hundred who abhor this method of maintaining it.  Why provoke a strike on sympathy?</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Church of England stands for theological liberty.</hi><hi rend="i bold">["]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the discussion that followed an amendment was adopted omitting the quotation from the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Article.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[184]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Dean moved the adjournment, &amp; this was accepted.</p>
         <p>We dined with <persName xml:id="386" display="no">Miss Monk</persName> &amp; found among the guests <persName xml:id="177">Bishop Barry</persName>, &amp; the Dean.</p>
         <p>Afterwards we went on to Lambeth, where was a great crush.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
