<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O Saviour of the World, exalted now in Thy power &amp; majesty, give ear to the prayers of Thy Church, and of me the least and unworthiest of Thy Children.  Break the yoke of the world from off our minds, set free from the bondage of past transgression our wills, and kindle in our hearts the flame of zeal for Thy service.  O reigning &amp; glorious Master make intercession for Thy Children this day, &amp; grant us comfort, courage, and wisdom that we may live in Thy obedience &amp; work in Thy spirit.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Letter to <persName xml:id="307">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Herbert Cox</persName>.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>May 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1903</p>
         <p>My dear Herbert,</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="328">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knowling</persName> has very properly forward to me the letters which you have addressed to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>, &amp; I understand that she has informed you of the rule which prohibits the choirboys of <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> from making the acquaintance of strangers without my permission.  Harold himself reported to me your approaches to him, though I did not know that you were the individual concerned.  You will, please, understand that I will not have that rule broken.  For reasons, which you will readily imagine, the discipline of the Choir will not permit of the kind of friendship you offer.  Nor will the credit of S. Margaret's be served by it.  The Choirboys are entrusted to me by their parents, and they are under my protection so long as they remain in the Choir.  I have very strong objections to their being petted &amp; treated by anybody who has no natural right to be familiar with them.  I do not suspect <hi rend="underline">you</hi> of any intentions except kind ones: but there are too many persons, <hi rend="bold">[191] </hi>[symbol] who would act as you have done, whose purpose is the worst in the world: and you know we, communicants, must ‘take thought for things honourable in the sight of all men'.  I need say no more.</p>
         <p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript">ly</hi>
         </p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> and I attended the reception at the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName> in connexion with the ‘recognition' of the</hi> <persName xml:id="392"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Rev</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> R. J. Campbell</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> as successor to the well-known <persName xml:id="223">Joseph Parker</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>  There was an immense throng, too great for the room underneath the chapel, so it overflowed upstairs; &amp; the proceedings really took place in the Temple itself.  Campbell made a few introductory remarks, and then I spoke for about 20 minutes.  Then a Baptist minister named <persName xml:id="393">Shakspeare</persName> followed; &amp; then the notorious windbag <persName xml:id="323">Silvester Horne</persName>: at the conclusion of his speech, Beeching &amp; I left.</p>
         <p>[192]</p>
         <p>[symbol] [symbol]</p>
         <p>Letter to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName></p><div type="letter">
         <p>May 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1903</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Archbishop,</p>
         <p>I am sure you will not resent, or misunderstand my action in sending you the enclosed account of what took place behind the closed doors of the Lower Convocation House, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">more especially, of the <listEvent><event xml:id="10">Speech</event></listEvent> which I myself addressed to the House</hi>.  From more than one source I learn that very odd versions of what I said have been put into circulation &amp; have even reached some of the Bishops.  I am the better able to give a trustworthy account of that speech, because, being impressed by the unusual importance of the debate, <hi rend="bold underline">I was careful to write out in advance on slips the several propositions which I proposed to submit.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Your Grace knows how earnestly I deprecate any doctrinal pronouncement from the Episcopal Bench at this juncture. The certain ill effects of such a pronouncement I can the more clearly see as I the more carefully reflect. The good effects I cannot imagine.</p>
         <p>It cannot be too strongly pressed on your Grace's attention that the practically unanimous <hi rend="bold">[193]</hi> [symbol] sense of the Lower Convocation House with respect to <persName xml:id="376">Canon Knox Little's</persName> <term xml:id="7">gravamen</term> was one of regret at its introduction.  Once a question of the Creed had been raised, many members felt themselves bound to take action, but all - as far as I could discover - saving a knot of extreme High Churchmen deprecated the raising of the question.  The fanatical spirit in which the gravamen was conceived, moved, &amp; pressed may be sufficiently indicated by the fact that the mover quoted, endorsed, &amp; dilated upon the grotesque declaration of the late <persName xml:id="395">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Liddon</persName> that <ref xml:id="276" display="no">'Modern Oxford was the 'world' as conceived by S. John'</ref>. It will be within your Grace's recollection that D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Liddon's censures fell nowhere more heavily than on that very distinguished representative of modern Oxford, the <persName xml:id="49">Bishop of Worcester.</persName></p>
         <p>Apologizing most sincerely for troubling you when your weight of cares is so great,</p>
         <p>I am, my dear Lord Archbishop,</p>
         <p>Sincerely &amp; dutifully yrs,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
