<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[226]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m: feeling very sad at the thought of <persName xml:id="1839" display="no">Giffin</persName>'s sudden death. He was a good &amp; religious man, the best &amp; most serviceable of the sidesmen.</p>
         <p>There was a fair congregation at 11 a.m. There was no choir, but the congregation managed very well by itself. I preached on Holidays. At the Celebration after the service: there were 91 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>In the course of the afternoon I called on <persName xml:id="1840" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Giffen</persName> [sic], &amp; offered such condolence as I could. On my way home, I encountered <persName xml:id="459" display="no">Weller</persName>, &amp; spoke to him. He is a genuine, good fellow.</p>
         <p>At Evensong was a moderate congregation: I preached what might fairly be called a Funeral Sermon for Giffen. Another American parson came into the Vestry after service.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[227]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Letter to <persName xml:id="465">Canon Wirgman</persName>.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>[symbol] My dear Sir, </p>
         <p>I am in doubt whether you expect or desire any answer to your letter of August 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, and, indeed, to speak frankly, it is couched in terms which almost prohibit answer.  I do not understand the precise complaint you make.  Is it that I have altered my opinion on some points of current belief?  But I could do no otherwise when that opinion seemed to me, in the light of fuller knowledge &amp; more careful thought, to be no longer tenable.  Would you have had me continue to profess opinions which I had ceased to hold?  You blame me for desiring better relations with non-Episcopalian Christians, &amp; for attaching value to the constitutional relation with the State which the Church of England still retains.  I really am at a loss to know how I can meet your wishes without doing violence to my own convictions.  I regret &amp; disapprove the attitude of the Nonconformists with respect to Education as much as you do: though, perhaps, I should allow something <hi rend="bold">[228]</hi> more in excuse for it from historical causes than you would. But can we not differ without anger or insult?</p>
         <p>Believe me, </p>
         <p>faithfully yours</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
