<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 23 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  Then I drove to <orgName xml:id="34">Lock Hospital</orgName>, &amp; <listEvent><event xml:id="112" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> the Annual Sermon for the Refuge, connected with it. <persName xml:id="345">Lord Kinnaird</persName>, the Chairman, took me back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>: and I diagnosed him on the way.  In the afternoon, <hi rend="bold underline">accompanied by <persName xml:id="346">Alan Henderson</persName></hi>, I went to <orgName xml:id="15">Bethnal Green</orgName>, &amp; gave the <listEvent><event xml:id="9" display="no">2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> lecture of my course</event></listEvent>.  The room was well filled with men. I spoke for a full hour: &amp; afterwards answered diverse questions, &amp; a rambling atheist's speech.  Then I returned to Westminster, and preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> to a large congregation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="502">Alwyn Parker</persName> came to supper.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
		 <div type="letter">
         <p>To the <persName xml:id="347">Rev. Ensor Walters</persName></p>
         <p>13th Feb. 1903</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ensor Walters,</p>
         <p>I have been thinking over the invitation which you so kindly brought me to preach in St: James Hall, the annual sermon of the <orgName xml:id="35">West London Mission</orgName>, and I have consulted one or two friends in whose judgement I have confidence.  <hi rend="bold underline">The result is that I must very regretfully say No</hi>.  You will need no assurance from me that if I consulted only my own personal feelings, I should have no hesitation whatever in coming to you, but I feel that the position in which I stand, and the great importance of the cause to which I have addressed myself, make it extremely requisite that I should, as far as possible, avoid anything which might have the effect of hindering moderate Anglicans from listening to my case. In the main, and for a long time to come, my duty is with my fellow Churchmen, whom I have to persuade <hi rend="bold">[159] </hi>[symbol] to accept a standpoint to which, for the most part, they are quite unaccustomed, and which can hardly fail to be, at first sight, extremely unpalatable.  I am quite clear in my own mind as to the essential rightness of that standpoint, and it is a matter of faith with me that it is sound policy resolutely to follow in all their practical consequences, principles, which are seen to be just.  But there is need to remember the Pauline counsel not to let our good be evil spoken of, and, therefore, I accept a limitation of my proper liberty in order not to offend prejudices which however irrational, cannot be justly described as unnatural.</p>
         <p>With many thanks for your kindness in asking me to come, with much regret that I must decline to come, and with earnest hope that the day may be not far distant when an interchange of Pulpits between the ordained Ministers of different branches <hi rend="bold">[160]</hi> [symbol] of Christ's Church (variously organised as the circumstances of History, which are the guidings of Providence, have determined, but none the less fundamentally united in the faith and worship of the one Lord) may seem the most natural thing in the world.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
