<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I <listEvent><event xml:id="114" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> at Christ Church, Lancaster Gate, on behalf of the Diocesan Seaside Camp for Boys: but the weather was desperate, &amp; the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> was preaching next door. <persName xml:id="463">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> DeCourcy Laffan</persName> preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> to the smallest congregation ever seen there on a Sunday morning in July. At Evensong I preached in S. Margaret's, &amp; for the first time on record, the evening collection was larger than the morning.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[222]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Letter to the <persName xml:id="465"> Bishop of Hokkaido</persName></p><div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Lord Bishop,</p>
         <p>I must begin by asking your pardon for having left your letter so long unanswered but you will understand that I was reluctant to answer it hastily, and, for the rest, I must ask you to make allowance for the numerous and always multiplying claims upon such leisure as I have.</p>
         <p>With respect to the question you raise, I would point out that there are two general considerations which might be thought to determine the answer which one holding the responsible position of a bishop and required to give answer, might return.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>The organisation of the Church of Christ is not <hi rend="underline">de fide</hi>. The episcopal r&#x00E9;gime is historically only one among many forms of ecclesiastical order, which the Christian Society has received. The fact that any local church, or association of Christians is not episcopally organised <hi rend="bold">[223] </hi>does not <hi rend="underline">ipso facto</hi> destroy its ecclesiastical character.</item>
            <item>There are certain conditions which must be fulfilled in any Society, however organised, which can claim recognition as a Christian Church.  I do not know that the definition of the XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Article can be improved upon.  I apprehend that a bishop would have to satisfy himself that any congregation which he recognised, fulfilled the conditions there laid down viz:-</item>
            <item>That it consisted of faithful men</item>
            <item>That the pure word of God was preached therein.</item>
            <item>That the Sacraments were duly ministered according to Christ's ordinance</item>
         </list>
         <p>The origin of any ministry is not, I venture to think, of primary importance. The essential thing is the acceptance of the Christian congregation, which is the organ of the governing Spirit, and the indispensable evidence of character which every ministry must be required to give is that which our Lord authorised us to demand. I mean, the evidence of moral <hi rend="bold">[224]</hi> results. "<hi rend="underline">By their fruits ye shall know them</hi>". With these broad considerations in mind<hi rend="italic">, I should hold that every bishop was under the most solemn obligation to determine how far he could recognise the congregations of non-episcopalian Christians as truly churches of Christ.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I must add my conviction that, if he honestly accepts his obligation, and resolutely setting on one side all questions of professional, or denominational character, looks only to the glory of God and the well being of His church, he will find himself conscientiously compelled to acknowledge fellowship with the non-episcopalian congregations &amp; moreover to do this, as alone it can be done by joining in the act of Holy Communion.</p>
         <p>Even allowing that the origin of the Wesleyan ministry, for example, was altogether irregular, I should maintain that, in view of the spiritual &amp; moral authentications which the Holy Ghost has added to that ministry, we cannot, without incurring <hi rend="bold">[225]</hi> the gravest guilt, exclude it from our fraternal acknowledgment. It comes under the principle enunciated by S. Peter in the house of Cornelius "Can any man forbid the water that these should not be baptised which have received the Holy Ghost as well as we."</p>
         <p>Mere individualism, of course, is the very temper of schism, and cannot possibly be owned of God, or acknowledged by us, but, the more closely I examine the actual facts, the slower I become to attribute <hi rend="underline">that</hi> character to organised Christian churches.  I pray God that He will guide you with respect to this matter.  A very special responsibility appears to rest upon the missionary churches.  I think the restoration of visible unity will come from them.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>most sincerely yours</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
