<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[268]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">New Year's Eve, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Almighty God I beseech Thee to forgive my sins, known &amp; unknown, to remedy my blunders, unsuspected and apparent, to purge my character &amp; my motives, to direct my action, to govern my life through Jesus Christ Thy Son.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>In my personal life justice, simplicity, &amp; love.</item>
            <item>In my parochial life insight, candour, &amp; sympathy</item>
            <item>In my public life, courage, wisdom, &amp; sincerity.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[269]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Last year on review seems to have been beyond all precedent contentious. In 1902 I broke with the<hi rend="bold underline"> Catholics</hi> in point of organisation: in 1903 I have broken with the <hi rend="bold underline">Orthodox</hi> in point of doctrine.  To the perilous Protestantism of <ref xml:id="8">"Godly Union &amp; Concord"</ref> is now added the still more perilous latitudinarianism of <ref xml:id="18">"Sincerity &amp; Subscription"</ref>.  <hi rend="bold underline">Gradually I am moving without the camp as all the rest have had to do.</hi>  Undoubtedly I move with much more liberty in the lightening harness, but the professional outlook has, perhaps, taken a settled gloom. That don't [sic] much matter, so long as I have strength &amp; courage for the war: but the strain on these qualities has become extremely severe, &amp; I hardly know how long I can stand it. Like the page in ‘Good King Wenceslas', I am disposed to say, "I can go no longer": and yet just ahead are heavier tasks &amp; fiercer fights than any, under which I have hitherto had to stand.  Well, well: the cause is a good one, &amp; I must do out the duty in the Name of the Lord.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
