<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[243]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1903.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dark, wet day: and the dark fit of depression which has lain on my spirit for some days past remains. I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8.a.m. Among the communicants were the two brothers – <persName xml:id="222">Albert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="293">Edwin Saxton</persName>. It is some joy to see consecrated fraternity still lingering among us. In the main, natural relationships are the true pillars of character.  Sonship &amp; fraternity are the ‘Jachim' and ‘Boaz' of the spiritual temple: &amp; that life, from which they are cut out, or have never been, is a broken, tottering thing.  And, as I review my own spoiled &amp; miserable course, I can see that that was my case: &amp; now I seem to be bankrupt in heart, a weariness to myself, &amp; an enigma to others.</p>
         <p>The rain continued far into the afternoon, and the congregation was at Mattins the smallest I can remember having preached to in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. I had taken more than ordinary pains with the sermon.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[244] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Rector to <persName xml:id="487">Mr Longman</persName>. </p><div type="letter"><p>Oct. 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1903.</p>
         <p>Dear Mr Longman,</p>
         <p>It has been arranged that I shall be in residence in the Abbey throughout next Lent, and probably I shall be urged to undertake in addition to the Lenten preaching the course of Friday afternoon lectures which, for some years past, have been an important feature of our arrangements for that season. In that case I feel increasingly doubtful whether it will be possible for me to give the large amount of time which I intended to give to the <ref xml:id="25" display="no">historical work</ref> for which I stand pledged to you. I meditate giving in the Abbey (assuming that I lecture on Fridays) a course on <ref xml:id="27">"Moral Discipline in the Christian Church"</ref>. I should follow substantially the scheme which I crafted four years ago when I stood for the Bampton Lecture against the present <persName xml:id="358">Bishop of Exeter</persName>, who was on that occasion, elected. I enclose a draft of the scheme that you may form an opinion upon it. Of course, I should, in the Abbey pulpit, adopt a less academic style than would have been proper in the university pulpit. I should appeal to the general body of English Churchmen rather than to the learned class. And therefore you will understand that the enclosed scheme is not designed to be more than a general indication of the range, character, drift &amp; method of the lectures I should <hi rend="bold">[245]</hi> deliver in the Abbey.</p>
         <p>In this case, would you be willing, first, to postpone the Savoy Conference to next year, and next, to accept for publication the Abbey Lectures?</p>
         <p>Very faithfully yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson.</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[246] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>To the Head of the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName>.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>Oct. 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1903</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="211">Woolcombe</persName>,</p>
         <p>I have delayed answering your letter, not because I had forgotten it, but because I really desired to be able to do what you ask: but, after much turning it over in my mind, I feel that I must say, No.  And I will tell you briefly why this is the case.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>I am seriously thinking over the line of defence which ought to be taken up by the Christian apologist who doesn't wish <hi rend="underline">only</hi> to score an immediate victory but abidingly to help the cause of truth - and I haven't yet come to any decision on the matter.</item>
            <item>I <hi rend="underline">know</hi> that at least I have reached so much of a conclusion on the subject that I am sure I should make concessions, &amp; take up positions which the most part of Anglicans would consider respectively treasonable &amp; dangerous.</item>
            <item>It would put the <persName xml:id="130">Bishop of Stepney</persName>, or any other clergyman who happened to be the chairman in rather an uncomfortable <hi rend="bold">[247]</hi> dilemma.  <hi rend="underline">Either</hi> they must publicly throw me over, which wouldn't assist the main purpose of the meeting, <hi rend="underline">or</hi> they would have to seem to acquiesce in what they really disliked &amp; disallowed.</item>
         </list>
         <p>You will allow, I think, the force of these considerations, &amp; believe me when I say that I decline with reluctance the proposal you are good enough to make to me.</p>
         <p>Sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
