<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>[305]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904</hi>.</p>
         <p>A cold day threatening rain!</p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 72 comm<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>. At the choral celebration there was by no means a large congregation, which however was perhaps not unconnected with the darkening aspect of the sky. I preached depressingly: there were 136 communicants.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">An American clergyman, named <persName xml:id="569" display="no">Lloyd</persName>, who hails from Seattle</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the state of Washington, came into the Vestry after the early celebration, and afterwards lunched with me.  He was an interesting &amp; intelligent man.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked down the Embankment, &amp; left some portion of my discourse at the Times Office. </p>
         <p>At Evensong there was a fair congregation.  I preached a sermon written as long ago as 1898.  <persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName> took his place in the Churchwarden's seat.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="570">Edith Bruce</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="571">Geordie Gore</persName> came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[306]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday, May 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to Cambridge to visit the <persName xml:id="574"><persName xml:id="573">Burkitts</persName></persName>, and stayed until Friday night, when we returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>; having enjoyed a pleasant visit with very hospitable, kind hosts.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was interested to meet again <persName xml:id="572">Kennett</persName>, now Regius Prof. of Hebrew, and Canon of Ely. I had not seen him for at least 21 years, and he had become, in the interval, unrecognizable.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday <persName xml:id="574">Burkitt</persName> took me to dine in Trinity; there I renewed acquaintance with <persName xml:id="575">Jackson</persName>, one of the senior fellows. The Romans are much in evidence at Cambridge. I met <persName xml:id="576">Dom: Butler</persName>, <persName xml:id="577">Father Sutcliffe</persName>, <persName xml:id="578">Father Nolan</persName>, and Ella met also <persName xml:id="579">Father Barnes</persName>.  </p>
         <p>On Friday afternoon we went for a picnic up the river very pleasantly.</p>
         <p>

            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
