<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[283]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I Celebrated in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m. After breakfast I revised a sermon on "<hi rend="underline">Honour in times of Religious Transition</hi>", and walked to the <orgName xml:id="79" display="no">Temple</orgName>, where I <listEvent><event xml:id="117">delivered</event></listEvent> it to a congregation by no means crowded: that may have been in some degree owing to the raw &amp; unpromising weather.  I was hospitably entertained at lunch in the <orgName xml:id="49" display="no">Inner Temple</orgName>.  The aged Treasurer, <persName xml:id="538">Judge Baylis</persName>, insisted on showing me about the building, and the curious silver-gilt ships of great age, which are the glory of the Temple plate.  <persName xml:id="539">Alfred Lyttelton</persName> &amp; his family were in church &amp; at lunch.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[284]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>[symbol] To the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of Canterbury</persName></p><div type="letter">
         <p>Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1904</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Abp,</p>
         <p>I shall ask you to allow me to send you the enclosed letters to read, &amp; (if you will be so good) to return to me. My own view was that <persName xml:id="496">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Beeby</persName> ought to have made a frank statement of his case in the "<hi rend="italic">Times</hi>", letting the public know the harsh treatment he has received, appealing against the hateful slanders which have been moved against his character, &amp;, if the consent of <persName xml:id="497">Bishop Perowne</persName> could be obtained, publishing the remarkable letters which he received from that prelate some years ago when the same unscrupulous faction, which has now triumphed, vainly tried to force the action of his diocesan. I think there is enough generosity left in the public mind to have responded to such an appeal, as he undoubtedly has the power to make. But he declines this counsel, &amp; prefers to retire from conflict. I think he is mistaken, but of course, he must choose his own procedure.</p>
         <p>Your Grace will understand why I feel that these letters should be sent for your perusal. <hi rend="bold">[285]</hi> They will help you to form an opinion of the man.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Always your Grace's sincerely,</p>
         <p>&amp; dutifully</p>
         <p>H. H. H.</p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[286]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday the 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 1904, we went to Eton through floods of rain.  A pleasant dinner-party at the <persName xml:id="203">Headmaster</persName>'s. Sunday, the 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, was very wet until 3 p.m., but one's congregation was for cogent reasons "independent of the weather". A grand congregation it is: the great chapel filled with the finest lads in the world. I <listEvent><event xml:id="118" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> on "<hi rend="underline">Christianity &amp; Youthful ambitions</hi>", and was very well listened to, a circumstance the more gratifying since Etonians are quite able &amp; willing to make their inattention known to the preacher.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="379">Ernald</persName> &amp; Edmond took me for a walk about the castle &amp; Park: and afterwards we went to Evensong in the School Chapel.  <persName xml:id="541">Alington</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
