<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[317]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dark &amp; thunderous day which began with a deluge.  I celebrated in much physical discomfort, being nearly voiceless &amp; my head aching badly, at 8 a.m.  There were 27 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  I preached with husky fervour to a congregation by no means large.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="268">Principal Rainy</persName> was sitting under my pulpit</hi>. During the Celebration (at which were 90 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>) there was a tremendous downpour.</p>
         <p>At Evensong I preached again with a voice like a raven.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[318]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday &amp; Wednesday the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> of Canterbury</hi> held sessions, &amp; I wasted in attending them those days.  Beyond a short speech in favour of vesting <persName xml:id="589" display="no">Glebes</persName> in the <orgName xml:id="156" display="no">Eccl<hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi> Comm<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi></orgName>, I took no part in the proceedings.  On Thursday &amp; Friday were the meetings of what called itself the <orgName xml:id="57">"Representative Church Council"</orgName>.  Here also I showed up &amp; wasted two days, but took no part in the business.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The members, so far as I could judge, regarded me with kindness.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">There was no Disinclination to receive my hospitality, (21 members lunched here) and no reluctance to acknowledge acquaintance.</hi>  <hi rend="i bold doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon Watkins</persName></hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> of Durham volunteered to thank me for my book</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; several members were very complimentary on my speech.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">Moreover the fanaticks were either absent, or silent, and wore a sulky &amp; baffled aspect, as men who dimly saw that they were disapproved.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Friday's Literary Supplement of the 'Times' had more than a column on <ref xml:id="40">"Canon Henson's Answer"</ref>: &amp; there were 3 columns of hostile <ref xml:id="41" display="no">"review"</ref> in the "Church Times" of the same date.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
