<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[297]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This day is set for the celebration of the 1300</hi><hi rend="i superscript">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> anniversary of the Bishop</hi><hi rend="i bold">^rick^</hi><hi rend="italic"> of London[</hi><hi rend="i bold strikethrough">'s Fund</hi><hi rend="italic">], and also for the annual collections for the Bishop's <orgName xml:id="132" display="no">Fund</orgName>.  I have prepared a long </hi><hi rend="italic underline">historical</hi><hi rend="italic"> sermon for the morning, and a more directly </hi><hi rend="italic underline">mendicant</hi><hi rend="italic"> discourse for the evening.  It is the first occasion on which I myself have preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> on this Sunday: and now </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I do so heavily suspected of all kinds of fatal heresies</hi><hi rend="italic">, and, for some weeks past, the object of insult &amp; denunciation, public &amp; private. It is strange to what fortunes we are surrendered, &amp; to what unexpected ends we move.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">More &amp; more I am persuaded that my life is governed by a Higher Power, and that I move along pre-ordained lines towards pre-determined ends: &amp; yet I am not fatalist because, along with this, I am more &amp; more impressed with a haunting fear of personal failure to answer to the calls &amp; plans of God</hi><hi rend="italic">.  Yet can I in no way reconcile these conflicting convictions.  To be a Man of destiny, a straw on the stream of Divine Purpose, is one thing: to be a disobedient &amp; self-willed servant, is another.  Yet I know myself to be </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">both</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
