<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I did not get up for the early service. At 11 a.m. I preached and Celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 95 communicants.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName> came to see me during the afternoon, and stayed on to service in the Abbey, when I <listEvent><event xml:id="116" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> again. It was a horrid wet night, but, in spite of the weather, there was a considerable congregation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[271]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>To the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. Of Canterbury</persName>.</p><div type="letter">
         <p>[symbol] Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1904</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Archbishop,</p>
         <p>You will, I know, understand how greatly troubled I am at the situation in which I find myself with respect to <persName xml:id="496">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Beeby</persName>.  Much has been told me &amp; written to me about him during the last few days, and (save for a letter from a Birmingham incumbent clearly adverting to the same matter as that referred to by your Grace) everything is most creditable to him. <persName xml:id="497">Bishop Perowne</persName> described him recently to one of my correspondents as ‘one of the saintliest men in the diocese'. He is said by those who know him well to be a good husband &amp; a very affectionate father. I see that it is stated in the <ref xml:id="28">"Times"</ref> this morning that his parishioners are getting up some memorial or testimonial to him.</p>
         <p>Several persons have written to me with the design to make some effort to find M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Beeby another sphere of work: &amp; my necessary answer, dissociating myself from him as a stranger, &amp; emphasizing his expressed desire to have his resignation undiscussed must injure his interests, &amp; can, I fear, hardly fail to suggest something <hi rend="bold">[272]</hi> vaguely unsatisfactory about him. It tortures me to think that I may be further wronging a man, who has already been wronged.</p>
         <p>I shall ask your Grace, therefore, to add to your kindness this also, to let me know at once what conclusion you may come to on the matter submitted to investigation.</p>
         <p>It is a curious &amp; sinister coincidence that the Holy Office should have condemned L'Abb&#x00E9; Loriz just at this time.</p>
         <p>With all good wishes for your Grace, personal &amp; official, in the New Year.</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>always sincerely &amp; dutifully,</p>
         <p>H. HENSLEY HENSON</p>
         <p>(This letter was marked within &amp; without ‘private')</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
