<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[303]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I attended the Prize distribution in S. Margaret's Schools. After which there was a meeting of managers at which <persName xml:id="565" display="no">Rute</persName> announced that we ended the final year of "voluntaryism" with a balance of &#x00A3;7: which would be increased presently by about &#x00A3;40, the amount of the Government grant for the month of April.</p>
         <p>This afternoon E. made an interesting communication to me.<note xml:id="30" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="491">Lady F. Balfour</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> wired for me to dine, which I was able to do.  <persName xml:id="314">Hugh Cecil</persName>, <persName xml:id="566">Fleming</persName>, </hi><persName xml:id="567"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">r</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="1842"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Saintsbury</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; <persName xml:id="568">Eustace Balfour</persName> made up the party.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[304]</hi>
         </p><div type="verse">
         <p>O Spirit of Jesus guide my way in the world,<lb/>
         and make me a witness of Thine own Love.<lb/>
         O Spirit of Truth govern my thoughts, and <lb/>
         direct my speech, and inspire my teaching<lb/>
         O Spirit of Wisdom illumine my understanding, <lb/>
         and choose for me my course.<lb/>
         O Comforter stay the wasting sorrows of my <lb/>
         heart, and console my loneliness.<lb/>
         O Holy Spirit of God purge my heart, and <lb/>
         cleanse my way.<lb/>
         O Helper of Christian Souls grant help to <lb/>
         me, &amp; make for me Thy sweet, prevailing intercession.<lb/>
         O Spirit of Joy pierce the clouds of depression <lb/>
         which enfold me, and make me glad with Thy Presence.<lb/>
         O Spirit of Prayer teach me to pray.<lb/>
         O Sprit of Fellowship teach me to serve.<lb/>
         "With hearts so vile, how dare we venture,<lb/>
         Holy Ghost! to love Thee so? <lb/>
         And how canst Thou, with such compassion,<lb/>
         Bear so long with things so low?<lb/>
         Holy Ghost! come down upon Thy children,<lb/>
         Give us grace, &amp; make us Thine;<lb/>
         Thy tender fires within us kindle,<lb/>
         Blessed Spirit! Dove Divine!</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
