<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[344]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished one sermon, &amp; nearly finished the other; corrected &amp; returned to the publishers the remaining proofs of <ref xml:id="53">"Notes on popular Rationalism"</ref>. Showed a party of S.S. Teachers over the Abbey, walked with <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> on the Embankment, &amp; met <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>: attended the Organ Recital.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="113">Harold Knowling</persName> had a long conversation with me, which greatly surprised me.</p>
         <p>Reading:-</p>
         <p>Nil</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[345]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Almighty and All Holy God, Whose Will is prevailing through all the chaos &amp; crime of our life on earth, to Whom we are servants when we know it not, have mercy on us, as we fail &amp; stumble under the over-heavy burden of our sin.  Thou Who dost call us to Thy Work must Thyself create us for it: for, O God, we are not able of ourselves to make answer to Thy Call.  Therefore, have mercy upon us, &amp; fashion us according to Thy Will.  Send into our hearts the purging fires of Thy Holy Spirit: let the Divine Light shine in our sin-darkened understandings.  O Righteous &amp; Terrible God, Whose eye sees all the long course of our past years, seamed &amp; stained with wilful sin, pity our weakness, &amp; lift us from our shame.  Thou knowest all we have been, and all we have longed &amp; striven &amp; failed to be.  Thou knowest all, and, therefore, we dare to pray Thee save Thy servants from their sin.  <hi rend="underline">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee</hi>.  O God I love Thee, and dare to confess my love - I, who merit nought but the stroke of Thy judgment.  I am Thine, help Thy servant who putteth his trust in Thee.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
