<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[362]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1904.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This day has been altogether frittered away in letter-writing &amp; interviews. Perhaps the most important letter was that copied into this journal which I addressed to <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName>'s father, &amp; sent to him by the hand of his son.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[363]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>Dear <persName xml:id="327">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Knowling</persName>,</p>
         <p>I understand that Harold has a great desire to make music his profession in life, &amp; I think our experience of him as a chorister in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> provides sufficient reason for making an attempt to allow him the opportunity of showing how far his aptitudes justify his ambition. It would certainly be no slight satisfaction to me if I could assist him towards a career into which he could throw his heart; but of course it would be both wrong &amp; foolish to encourage him to look forward to a musical career, if his natural powers are inadequate: &amp; it is certainly too soon to be sure that this is not the case. An opportunity, however, has offered itself which may perhaps give him the chance of shewing his metal.</p>
         <p>At the beginning of next year, the Churchwardens of S. Margaret's will require the services of a clerk, and I have asked them to allow me to offer the position to Harold on certain conditions.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">They are willing to appoint him for one year</hi>, provided of course that he behaves well &amp; does his work to their satisfaction.  <hi rend="underline">The work is light but responsible, &amp; they will appoint so young a clerk on the express understanding that he devotes himself in his leisure to the study of music</hi>, &amp; they are prepared to arrange that <persName xml:id="121">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss-Custard</persName> <hi rend="bold">[364] </hi>the Organist of S. Margaret's shall undertake the direction of his musical training.  They will pay him a stipend of &#x00A3;30: and I myself will add &#x00A3;9, in return for such occasional assistance, outside his duties, as I may require from him in the course of the year. Thus he will receive fifteen shillings a week, and gratuitous instruction from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss-Custard.  At the end of the experimental year, if everything goes well, we shall be in a position to determine whether or not it is worth while to encourage Harold to persist in his design of a musical career: and, in the event of our deciding, after consultation with M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Goss-Custard, that he has no fair prospect of success in that direction, he will be nowise injured - always provided that he has behaved well &amp; done his duty - in the alternative career of a clerk.</p>
         <p>You will understand that, in yielding to my wishes, the Churchwardens are mainly influenced by the desire to give a fair opportunity to a lad who for six years past has done good service in the Choir, &amp; whose success in the career which he desires for himself would give them unfeigned satisfaction.</p>
         <p>If you approve of this proposal, and are willing to make this experiment, I should <hi rend="bold">[365]</hi> expect Harold to place himself completely under the orders of the Churchwardens, and to enter on his duties from January 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1905.</p>
         <p>Let me add my personal assurance that I should rejoice greatly if he were able to make such good use of this opportunity as to succeed in the beautiful art, which he admires so much.  I have watched Harold closely for the past four years, &amp; have taken note of his enthusiasm for music.  I prepared him for Confirmation, and, as indeed you know, have a genuine concern for his welfare, and also − what will please you to hear − an increasing confidence in his character.</p>
         <p>You will let me know your decision that I may be able to tell the Churchwardens whether their proposal is accepted.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours very sincerely</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson.</p>
         <p>Nov: 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1904</p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
