<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[423]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant day becoming warm to the point of sultriness.  I celebrated at 8 a.m., when there were 37 communicants.  At Mattins <persName xml:id="692">Carlile</persName>, the Founder &amp; Chief of the <orgName xml:id="50">Church Army</orgName>, preached for his work, &amp; plates were held at the doors in his interest, the regularly-collected offertory being as usual for the <orgName xml:id="159">Churchwardens' Fund</orgName>.  The sermon consisted largely of anecdotes of the serio-comic, or comic-tragic type customary in the circles of "social work": but they were probably true in substance if not in detail, &amp; the preacher was evidently earnest &amp; sincere.  I added a few observations in support of the appeal, &amp; no less than &#x00A3;40 odd was collected at the doors.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">After lunch <persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> &amp; I went to Paddington to <listEvent><event xml:id="134" display="no">preach</event></listEvent> at a Welsh Church.</hi>  After waiting in the Vestry for a considerable time, a boy &amp; a man turned up, to be followed afterwards by the Parson. When expressing some annoyance at being kept waiting, he informed us that they usually came about 10 minutes late. On the whole it was a bright service, &amp; the singing was quite good. The Sermon which I had taken a lot of time &amp; pains to be preached to a learned <hi rend="bold">[424]</hi> congregation, was eventually read to a number of milkman [sic], However, they seemed to pay great attention. The service was all in welsh except the Sermon. A notice was given out that tea would be supplied in the School room, underneath the Church, at nominal prices.</p>
         <p>At Evensong there was a large congregation.  I preached on 1 Thess. IV. 12.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
