<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[406]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A cold and brilliant day.  I celebrated at 8 a.m. there were 20 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  At Mattins there was a large congregation.  I <hi rend="bold underline">noticed <persName xml:id="368">Victor Cavendish</persName></hi> &amp; <persName xml:id="747" display="no">Capt<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> Butler</persName> among the rest.  The sermon was a dull &amp; lengthy disquisition on <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName>'s Appeal to the first Six Centuries.<note xml:id="40" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>At Evensong I preached an old sermon on the Rich Fool.  There was a fair congregation, &amp; it was very attentive.  The Offertories throughout the day amounted to nearly &#x00A3;22.0.0.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[407] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]			</p>
         <p>Convocation met on Wednesday. Feb: 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905; I attended the Holy Communion in <placeName xml:id="6" display="no">Henry VII<hi rend="superscript underline">th's</hi> Chapel</placeName>. We spent the day in discussing a lengthy motion about the Constitution of the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName>, moved by the Ritualists (<persName xml:id="748">Canon Sanderson</persName> moved; <persName xml:id="749">Preb: Villiers</persName> seconded)[.]  I was about to speak, when the adjournment cut me short, &amp; I was 'in possession' of the House for the following day.  Accordingly, on Thursday, I opened the debate with a <listEvent><event xml:id="15">short speech</event></listEvent> which was ill-delivered &amp; coldly received.  The subject was not disposed of until lunch-time, when the Ritualists carried much-mutilated motions by the miserable majority of 4 votes in a thin house – 36 to 32.</p>
         <p>After lunch the main battle was joined on the <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName>'s motion with respect to the first six centuries. He spoke well, &amp; was seconded by the <persName xml:id="374">Dean of Salisbury</persName> in a speech of the most incoherent and rambling description. Then <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> made an effective speech, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">finally, I <listEvent><event xml:id="16">spoke</event></listEvent> for more than half an hour</hi>. The House listened well, &amp; was, I think, impressed.  Our <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> made a brief mediating speech, &amp; then we adjourned leaving Preb. Villiers in possession of the House.  On Friday it was immediately apparent that the Dean of Canterbury had accepted a drastic remodelling of his motion, which now emerged as a <hi rend="bold">[408]</hi> quite harmless platitude. Everybody wanted to save the Dean's face, &amp;, accordingly, it was suffered to pass without a division, but, in truth, the "the appeal to the first six centuries" had perished in the debate.  The motion as adopted by the House ran as follows:-</p>
         
		 <p><div type="quote">That the appeal to Antiquity may rightly be interpreted as an appeal to the general practice of the Catholic Church in the first six centuries, and that amidst present controversies a fuller recognition of this principle is much to be desired.</div></p>
         
         <p>Thus all the objectionable features had disappeared – the reference to ‘the principle of the English Reformation', the inclusion of doctrine, the definition of ‘Catholicity'</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
