<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[442]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The altar had been arranged in front of the scaffolding, as the workmen had not succeeded in finishing the temporary screen.  The effect architecturally was surprisingly good.  <persName xml:id="282">Frank Campbell</persName> celebrated at 8 a.m.  There were 29 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  At Mattins there was a considerable congregation, and no less than 95 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  I preached from the "parable" of the Feeding of the 4000 <hi rend="bold">[sic]</hi>, which happened to be the Gospel for the day.  We all had tea on the roof, a circumstance which indicates <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>'s progress towards recovery.  I wrote at some length to the <persName xml:id="560">Admiral</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">There was again a considerable congregation at Evensong, when I preached an old sermon.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">A Canadian clergyman came into the Vestry to shake hands afterwards.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">This seems to minister much comfort to the Transatlantic mind.</hi>  <hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName>'s voluntary choir was on duty.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">In the morning 'twas a horrid failure, but at Evensong when we made them sing "full", and read the prayers and versicles they did better;  but I was amazed that so little sound could issue from 14 young men evidently making considerable exertions!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="502">Alwyn Parker</persName> &amp; his Russian friend came to supper.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">The latter was a very entertaining &amp; attractive fellow.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">He talked freely of the war, &amp; seemed to have much</hi><hi rend="bold"> [443] </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">knowledge of the subject.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">He described <persName xml:id="812">Stőssel</persName>, the "hero" of Port Arthur as hen-pecked and effete.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">Private letters from the Russian army, which he had seen, were full of complaints against the incompetent generals, but said little of the Japanese.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">He was an enthusiastic sportsman, and described with much humour the hunting of bears &amp; wolves</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">The latter, indeed, seem to interest him greatly.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">They are in his view extremely intelligent beasts, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">neither numerous nor dangerous</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">Elks are plentiful even close to S. Petersburgh, and boars on the frontier of Poland.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">His account of the Russian Clergy was not flattering, they are ignorant and depraved.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">The monasteries have ceased to civilize.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">There is little preaching in the churches, &amp; what there is, is bad.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">No educated or well-born man would dream of taking Orders.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">He was, he said, more impressed by Westminster Abbey than by anything else he had seen.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">S. Paul's did not attract him.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">Everywhere you found churches of that kind, but the Abbey was unexampled.  This shewed his good taste.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">He repeatedly pressed me to visit him in Russia.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[444]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1905 I <listEvent><event xml:id="139" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> to the Extension Students in <orgName xml:id="61">S. Mary's</orgName>, Oxford</hi>: &amp; in the evening I <listEvent><event xml:id="140" display="no">addressed</event></listEvent> a meeting on the subject of University Settlements: but I was far from well: &amp; on Monday morning felt dismally ill.  However I was able to pull myself together &amp; leave the Deanery, (where <persName xml:id="120">Strong</persName> has hospitably entertained me).  I travelled back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and collapsed on my arrival.  After 4 days in bed I revived sufficiently to leave Westminster, &amp; go with <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> to Frant, where I visited <persName xml:id="642">Sir Peile Thompson</persName>, a quaint Yorkshire baronet who had started as a barrister, &amp;, on the failure of his health, became a parson.  Here we stayed until Wednesday, 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Aug:, when we returned to Dean's Yard.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">The next day, I went to Sutton to visit <persName xml:id="813">Mr Arthur Rawle</persName>, a cousin of mine, with whom I stayed until Saturday, when I journeyed to Horley</hi><hi rend="i bold"> with my <persName xml:id="76">mother</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="77">sister</persName>.</hi>  <hi rend="i bold">Here I continued until </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Monday 4</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Sept: when I returned to Westminster, &amp; the next day married in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> an American millionaire, <persName xml:id="814">Mr Marshall Field</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>  After the service I went again to Horley, &amp; continued there until Sept 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when I journeyed to Dunsfold in order to visit <persName xml:id="560">Admiral Rolfe</persName>.  With him I stayed until Thursday, Sept. 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when I went to Westminster, &amp; the next day to Oxford.  Here I remained in <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">college</orgName> until Saturday 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Sept., when I went out to Pusey to spend Sunday with the <persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName>.  On Monday, 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept: I returned to Westminster, &amp;  rejoined <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>, <hi rend="bold underline">who</hi><hi rend="bold"> [445] </hi><hi rend="bold underline">had been meanwhile in Switzerland with her <persName xml:id="584">father</persName></hi>.  On the 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sept. we travelled together to Wells, where I had promised to preach in the Cathedral.  <hi rend="bold underline">But I had taken a chill, &amp; had no voice: so </hi><persName xml:id="815"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Goudge</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the Principal of the <orgName xml:id="62">Theological College</orgName>, read my sermon for me</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi>  I had promised to preach at Nottingham on the 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, but, under the circumstances, preferred to forward my MS. with an apology, &amp; to go direct to Glasgow.  We broke the journey at Carlisle, &amp; the same day when we were dining in the Hotel, the Bps. Of <persName xml:id="720">Carlisle</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="130">Stepney</persName> fell in with me, &amp; constrained me to address the meeting, which they had convened in the Hall adjoining the Hotel.  On the next day we continued our journey to Glasgow.  We were hospitably entertained at Jordanhill.  <hi rend="bold underline">On Sunday Oct: 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, I <listEvent><event xml:id="17">preached in Glasgow Cathedral</event></listEvent> to crowded congregations.</hi>  We stayed at Jordanhill until Tuesday, Oct. 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, &amp; then went to Fairlie to visit <persName xml:id="1547">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> C. S. Parker</persName>, with whom we continued until the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, when we travelled back to Westminster.  <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> returned in consequence of a vehement toothache which claimed the dentist's ministry: &amp; I returned to my work.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
