<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<hi rend="bold">[410]</hi>
                 <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather was uncomfortable, &amp; hostile to the assembling of ourselves together as the manner of some is.  I celebrated at 8 a.m., when there were but 20 communicants.  At Mattins the church was but half full. Among the congregation I noticed <persName xml:id="672">Lord Rayleigh</persName>, <persName xml:id="193">Sir Michael Hicks Beach</persName>, <persName xml:id="253">Sir Henry Fowler</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="419">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Craig</persName>.  A reporter carried off my sermon.</p>
         <p>I went to the Abbey, and heard (imperfectly, because of the coughing) the <persName xml:id="475">Bishop of Hereford</persName> preach from Mical VI. 6.  One of the choirboys was prayed for: the child is very ill with heart-failure.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[411]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O God, grant that the effect I desire to follow from my preaching tonight may be secured in so far as it is according to Thy Will, and that I myself may be reached by my own message. Suffer me not, after having preached to others, to be myself a castaway.  Thine is the Word, be Thine also the manner of its preaching. Send Thy Holy Spirit among us tonight, O God, in power &amp; mercy: and make us feel Thy Presence. Apart from Thee we can do nothing.  Cleanse my heart, &amp; raise my thoughts:  liberate me form the chains of sin, and 'set my feet in a large place'. Grant the comfort &amp; strength of Thy Forgiveness, O Lord, I beseech Thee for Christ's Sake.
          Amen
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[412]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On Friday, March 11</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 1905, I received a note from the <persName xml:id="192">Speaker</persName> asking me to act as Chaplain at his Official dinner held that night</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, as <persName xml:id="109">Archdeacon Wilberforce</persName> was ill.</hi>  So I clothed myself in cassock, gown, and bands; and went across to Speaker's Court.  This was the third of the series of Official Dinners, and was given to the Privy Councillors of the House, who were neither Ministers nor ex-Ministers.  It was a pleasant enough gathering.  I had speech with the following:-</p>
         <table rend="rules">
            <row>
               <cell><persName xml:id="755">Lord George Hamilton</persName></cell>
              
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>Sir Michael Hicks Beach</cell>
             
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell><persName xml:id="763">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ja<hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi> Round</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="232">J. G. Talbot</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="412">J. Parker Smith</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell><persName xml:id="764">Sir John Kennaway</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="696">John Dorington</persName></cell>
              
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="766">F. Milner</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell><persName xml:id="768">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jesse Collings</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="769">Halsey</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="770">Chapman</persName></cell>
               
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>" <persName xml:id="341">John Morley</persName>.</cell>
               <cell/>
            </row>
         </table>
		 
		 <p><persName xml:id="508">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Balfour</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="539">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Alf. Lyttelton</persName> arrived as I was departing, and I had a few words with the latter. <persName xml:id="771">Mowbray</persName> and <persName xml:id="368">Victor Cavendish</persName> also arrived &amp; exchanged speech with me. I had a little conversation with <persName xml:id="339">Sir R. Finlay</persName>.</p>
         <p>There was a Levée afterwards  	</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
