<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[389]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Christmas, January 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>The air was clear &amp; keen when I went to Church for the early Celebration.  The sky was cloudless, and the new moon shone benignantly.  All the buildings of Westminster had an unearthly, spectral look.  There were 39 communic<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> at 8 a.m. </p>
         <p>At Mattins there was a fair congregation, among whom I recognised the <persName xml:id="192">speaker</persName>, <persName xml:id="255">Sir Walter Foster</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="419">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Craig</persName>.  There were 110 communicants at the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> celebration.  I preached a New Year's Day Sermon from the two passages, Psalm XLVI.I, &amp; Romans VIII. 35.  Among the communicants I noticed <persName xml:id="743">Lord Onslow</persName>, <persName xml:id="744">Coleridge</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>.  <persName xml:id="795">Nixon</persName>, the deputy Minor Canon came to lunch. </p>
         <p>At Evensong there was a large congregation.  I preached an old sermon with an appendix. After service we sang five carols. <persName xml:id="300">Ellison</persName>, whose tenure of office ends today, came in to supper. </p>
         <p>So ends the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> New Year's Day which I have passed at Westminster, not altogether without encouragement. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[390]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>To <persName xml:id="745">Edward Frampton Esq</persName>. </p><div type="letter">
         <p>Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905. </p>
         <p>Dear Sir, </p>
         <p>I am greatly obliged for your letter.  The Committee felt that they were bound in duty to the public to entrust the handling of the great East Window to one who might fairly be regarded as an expert in medieval stained glass.  Accordingly, they have invited <persName xml:id="104">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kemp</persName> to prepare designs, &amp; are hoping shortly to receive them from him. </p>
         <p>With many thanks for your kind willingness to assist us.</p>
         <p>I am, most faithfully yours,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson. </p></div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[391] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>To <persName xml:id="746">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> J Aubrey Rees</persName>, Secretary</p><div type="letter">
         <p>National Association of Grocer's Assistants</p>
         <p>Jan 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905 </p>
         <p>Dear Sir, </p>
         <p>I find that your letter of Dec 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1904 has been overlooked &amp; left unanswered.  I am sorry that this should have been the case, because the shortening of hours of work for shop assistants seems to me a cause so excellent in itself, &amp; so important at the present time, that it would distress me even in appearance to treat it lightly.  I think on many grounds, that it would be very advantageous to the public interest that the attention of parliament should again be directed to this subject; &amp; if the addition of my name to your Committee would be of any service towards that end, I shall be very pleased to grant you permission to use it.  With all good wishes for your excellent work. </p>
         <p>I am, very faithfully yours</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson. </p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
