<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[395]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="62">Kirschbaum</persName> accompanied me to Norwood, where the poor little body of my dead child was buried without other liturgy than its father's grief</hi>.<note xml:id="33" display="no" n="1"></note>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[396]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>To the <persName xml:id="44">Dean of Westminster</persName></p><div type="letter">
         <p>January 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905</p>
         <p>Dear Dean,</p>
         <p>I am re-considering the passage in <persName xml:id="656" display="no">Pliny</persName>'s <ref xml:id="60" display="no">Letter</ref>, with respect to which you were good enough to point out what you conceived to be the error of the common rendering, which I adopted in my lectures last Lent.  You will have it that ‘quod ipsum' refers to the whole statement of the renegades, and not merely to the last clause.  But would it not have been ‘quae ipsa'?  Ought we not to suppose, in any case, that the renegades are not speaking in that character, but as witnesses to Christian practice?  The statement is that ‘they' had given up something ‘post edictum meum'.  Pliny had been probably about a year in office at the time he wrote to <persName xml:id="657" display="no">Trajan</persName>, so that his promulgation of the edict against ‘<hi rend="underline">hetaeriae'</hi> could not have affected the action of men who declared that they had abandoned Christianity ‘quidam ante triennium, quidam ante plures annos, non nemo etiam ante viginti'.  I incline therefore to revert to the common view that the Christians did surrender their agapai <hi rend="bold">[397]</hi> in deference to the State. But I would be grateful for an expression of your views before I finally make up my mind.</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>H. Hensley Henson<hi rend="italic">.</hi>	
         </p></div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
