<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[437]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A hot, sultry day marked by two violent thunderstorms.  I preached twice on the Work of Restoration contemplated at the East End.<note xml:id="66" n="1"></note>  Papers were circulated in the seats, and after service plates were held at the doors in order to give visitors an opportunity of contributing.  In this way more than &#x00A3;16 was collected.  <persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> was troubled by no less than 3 telegrams of an alarming character as to her <persName xml:id="828">mother</persName>'s health.</p>
         <p>A new Choir boy was admitted to the Choir viz. –</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item><persName xml:id="826" display="no">Ernest John Bennett</persName></item>
            <item>aged 12 (born Nov: 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1892)</item>
            <item>son of <persName xml:id="827" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> J. Bennett</persName></item>
            <item>92 Chestnut Gove </item>
            <item>Balham. S.W.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[438]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, July 15, 1905, my wife who had been in bed by the doctor's orders most part of the week, found herself worse, and about 2 a.m. on Sunday morning I had to go across to the <orgName xml:id="27">Westminster Hospital</orgName> and telephone <hi rend="italic">for doctor &amp; nurse.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It was a dolorous rehearsal of the wretched experience of Jan</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript">y</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> 8</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, but unlightened by any hope to compensate for pain &amp; anxiety.  Before long I was duly informed that my wife had passed through the futile disaster of "miscarriage", and could now recover at leisure! What a second holocaust of hopes &amp; loves within half a year!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I hastened to catch the 9.30 a.m. train from Waterloo to Brookwood in order to go to <placeName xml:id="17">Bisley Camp</placeName>, and <listEvent><event xml:id="137" display="no">preach</event></listEvent> to the <orgName xml:id="63" display="no">Rifle Association</orgName>.  <persName xml:id="830">Lord Cheylesmore</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="39">Doyle</persName> met me, &amp; everybody was most kind; but I was heart-sick, &amp; thankful to get back to my dreary &amp; darkened house.  The congregation at Evensong was greatly swollen by an overflow from the Abbey, where the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> was the Preacher.  Offertory = &#x00A3;8.19.9.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[439]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Monday, </hi><persName xml:id="828"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Dennistoun</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> died</hi>, and on Tuesday morning I asked <persName xml:id="542">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gow</persName> to tell my wife.  On Wednesday night I travelled to Helensburgh by the night express in order to attend the funeral, returning on Thursday night.  On Saturday, July 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1905, I entertained at tea a party of 23 men from the <orgName xml:id="15">Oxford House</orgName>, and after tea, I shewed them the Abbey. In spite of the extreme heat, they appeared to enjoy themselves.</p>
         <p>On the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sunday after Trinity, July 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1905, there were heavy downpourings of rain.  I celebrated at <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, and attended the service at 10 a.m. in the Abbey.  <hi rend="bold underline">After this, I went to S. Margaret's and heard the conclusion of <persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>'s sermon</hi>. The rain fell heavily just in front of the 3 o' clock Service in the Abbey, and the fact was sufficiently reflected in the congregation, which, though large, was not crowded. I <listEvent><event xml:id="138" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> an old sermon wearily. At Evensong in S. Margaret's, I preached again. There was a fair congregation.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
