<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[429]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>         
</p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 26 communicants. In the course of the service I asked prayers ‘on behalf of a family connected with the parish in deep affliction'. <hi rend="italic">This had been asked of me by </hi><persName xml:id="232"><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Talbot</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, whose youngest son, <persName xml:id="693">Eustace</persName>, died last week under an operation for appendicitis within a few days of announcing his engagement to be married.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At Mattins I preached to a very small congregation almost wholly in petticoats.  At 2 p.m. I assisted at a wedding: and then attended Evensong in the Abbey.  The <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> preached an excellent sermon on behalf of the Fund for Restoring Bell Harry Tower.<note xml:id="36" n="1"></note>  I went to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> for the Choral Service at 8 p.m, &amp; listened to a characteristic sermon from <persName xml:id="282">F. C.</persName></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[430]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O risen and reigning Lord, look down with pity on us Thy servants who are called to fight Thy Battle here on Earth: we are sore let and hindered by our own sins, and truly the enemy presses us sore.  Come and help us, O Christ, as Thou didst help Thine own in the times past; &amp; grant us in this warfare the comfort of Thy Presence, for Thy tender mercy's sake.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
