<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[449]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull, windy day threatening rain.  I celebrated at 8 a.m. Among the communicants was <persName xml:id="413">Reichel</persName>, who came in to breakfast.</p>
         <p>Congregations were unsatisfactory both at Mattins and at Evensong.  The evening turned out wet, &amp; this may explain the latter, but the morning remains unexplained.  I was told that it was "Temperance Sunday", &amp; – as it is fairly well known that I ignore all "fancy calendars" – it is possible that there was a secession to S. John's, where the <persName xml:id="109">Archdeacon</persName> preached twice.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="661" display="no">Waddell</persName>, <persName xml:id="756" display="no">Gage</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="28">Dick Rosser</persName> came in to supper. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[450]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended the consecration of <persName xml:id="532">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Chase</persName> as the new Bishop of Ely on S. Luke's day. The <persName xml:id="757">Master of Trinity</persName> preached a fine sermon.</p>
         <p>On Friday, the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Oct: 1905, <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="754">Sir Henry Irving</persName></hi> was buried in Poet's Corner, with much ceremony.  The <persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> emerged at the beginning &amp; at the ending of the service. The <persName xml:id="296">Sub-Dean</persName> read the Lesson &amp; the Committal; &amp; the Archdeacon read the concluding prayers.  When the procession was returning, &amp; the ‘Dead March' had just ceased on the organ<hi rend="bold underline">, there was heard a cry of some Fanatical Anti-Dramatist, "Whatever a man soweth that shall he also reap".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This is the anniversary of my marriage.  Three years have passed since in the Abbey I took that gravest of all decisive acts, &amp; am still wondering dismally whether it was for me in any respect a legitimate action.</p>
         <p>Note:- My <persName xml:id="112">wife</persName> went off again to Scotland on the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> October.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
