<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[451]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright autumn morning with a white frost on the ground and its bite, the first kiss of winter, in the air.</p>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m.: there were 25 Communicants.</p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation at Mattins, among the rest I noticed the <persName xml:id="125">Duke</persName> and <persName xml:id="820">Duchess of Buccleugh</persName>.</p>
         <p>It was plain enough that there was an expectation that I should make references to <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="754">Irving</persName></hi> and to <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="821" display="no">Nelson</persName></hi>:<note xml:id="41" n="1"></note> but this, on particular grounds of principle and of policy, I would not do. Accordingly I preached on the words, "<hi rend="underline">Where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty</hi>".  The collection was disappointing, something over &#x00A3;13.0.0.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName></hi> came to tea.  As a Birthday present I gave him <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="355">Fletcher's</persName></hi> fascinating <ref xml:id="74">History of England</ref>.</p>
         <p>As the 109<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Psalm came into the Psalms for the day at Evensong, I seized the opportunity of preaching plainly on the "<hi rend="underline">Imprecatory Psalms in Christian Worship</hi>", combining in my text some of the Imprecations with S. Matt. V. 43-46.  There was a large &amp; attentive congregation.  The collection amounted to &#x00A3;6.16.5.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="823" display="no">Lake</persName>, the usher of the <orgName xml:id="32">Abbey Choir School</orgName> came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[452]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, October 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905, I travelled to Aberdeen, leaving King's Cross at 10 a.m. and arriving in Aberdeen at 10.5 p.m.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="824">General Booth</persName> was on the train, &amp;, accordingly, crowds of devotees attended at the stations.</hi>  At Edinburgh <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> kindly way-laid the train &amp; exchanged greetings.</p>
         <p>On the next day, Sunday 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I <listEvent><event xml:id="142" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> in the University chapel to a congregation which crowded it, &amp; over-flowed into the Ante-chapel.  It was a picturesque scene.  The Arts-students of both sexes wear brilliant scarlet gowns.  The professors, with the <persName xml:id="825">Rector</persName> in the centre, occupy a semi-circle of seats behind the Holy Table.  The service was of the now-customary Presbyterian type – semi-liturgical.  I wore my black-silk gown &amp; bands.  I preached on ‘Didactic Reserve'  &amp; my sermon occupied about 40 minutes in delivery.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">In the afternoon I delivered the <listEvent><event xml:id="18">Murtle Lecture</event></listEvent> in the Hall of Marischal College</hi>.  There were more than 1000 people present: indeed the Hall was filled from end to end, &amp; it is said at the utmost to seat 1200.  My lecture on "Christianity in Politics" took an hour and ten minutes to deliver.  Everybody seemed immensely well-pleased, &amp; all were very kind.  At dinner afterwards I met Profs <persName xml:id="829">Nichol</persName> (Pastoral &amp; Exegetic), <persName xml:id="831">Baillie</persName> (Moral Philosophy), <persName xml:id="832">Davidson</persName> (Logic), <persName xml:id="833">Cowan</persName> (Eccl. Hist.), <persName xml:id="834">Curtis</persName> (Theology).</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[453]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The next day – Monday. Oct. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> – I found time before leaving Aberdeen to visit again the Chapel, &amp; look at the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century stalls, the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century pulpit, &amp; the tomb of <persName xml:id="835">Bishop Elphinstone</persName>.  Also I was shewn the library – a very fine room.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The train left Aberdeen at 10.20 a.m. and arrived at King's Cross at 10.45 p.m.</hi>
            
<hi rend="italic">At Edinburgh I saw <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> for a few minutes.</hi>
            
<hi rend="italic bold underline"><persName xml:id="508">Mr Balfour</persName> was on board, a fact which I discovered in the dining car.</hi>
            
<hi rend="italic bold underline">He recognized me at once, &amp; we had some very interesting conversation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On all Saints Day, Nov. 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1905, I celebrated in the Abbey after Mattins; in the afternoon I left a <ref xml:id="75">letter</ref> at the 'Times Office' on 'Religious Education'; and then went to the <placeName xml:id="18">Mansion House</placeName>, &amp; spoke at a very small meeting in support of a project for buying 40 acres near Ilford as a cricket – ground.  <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="838">Col. Lockwood</persName>,</hi> fresh from the glory of entertaining the King at Epping, was there, &amp; gave me a lift homewards in his brougham.</p>
         <p>On Thursday. Nov. 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, I took <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="847" display="no">Lord Litchfield</persName></hi>, aged 12, with <persName xml:id="848" display="no">Maclagan</persName> his tutor to the roofs of the Abbey.  He is a simple &amp; well-mannered boy, not brilliant.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
