<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[459]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A cold day but without wind or rain. <persName xml:id="282">Frank Campbell</persName> was reported seriously ill.  A note from his <persName xml:id="767" display="no">sister</persName> begged for prayers; &amp; he was prayed for by name at Mattins in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.  I <listEvent><event xml:id="146" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> in the Abbey at Mattins, a begging sermon for the <orgName xml:id="145" display="no">East London Church Fund</orgName>.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I preached again for the Fund.  There was a very large congregation, but a large part of it probably consisted of <term xml:id="14">Nonconformists</term>.  The Church-going public abstains from the heretick.</p>
         <p>In the evening I preached in S. Margaret's to a large congregation.  <persName xml:id="489">Sherwood</persName> took the service.</p>
         <p>On Monday, Nov: 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, <hi rend="bold underline">I baptized in S. Margaret's, <persName xml:id="760">Margaret Hermione Millicent</persName>, the daughter of the <persName xml:id="759">Earl of Lytton</persName></hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  <hi rend="italic">In the afternoon I opened a Sale of Work in the Cannon Street Hotel for the <orgName xml:id="56">Salvation Army</orgName>.</hi>  <persName xml:id="762">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bramwell Booth</persName> spoke very effectively.  <persName xml:id="566">Fleming</persName> of S. Columba's was present, &amp; read prayers.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> came to dinner, &amp; we discussed the Report on the Constitutional question.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[460]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday. Nov: 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1905 I delivered the second <listEvent><event xml:id="14" display="no">"Golden Lecture"</event></listEvent>.  There was a fair congregation.</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">On Wednesday, Nov: 22</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1905, I attended the meeting of the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName>, and made a short speech opposing the attribution of 'inherent powers and functions' to the Episcopate.</hi></p>
         <p>On Thursday, Nov: 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1905 I again attended the meeting of the Representative Church Council but made no speech.  In the evening I lectured on Westminster Abbey to the young men connected with the <orgName xml:id="37">City Temple</orgName>.</p>
         <p>On Friday, Nov: 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1905 I attended the final meetings of the aforesaid Council, &amp; made a speech, seconding a motion by <persName xml:id="765">Chancellor Vernon Smith</persName>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
