<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[447]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1905.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I returned to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> after an unprecedented absence of no less than 8 weeks; it was a dull day minatory of rain.  I celebrated at 8 a.m. There were 17 communicants.</p>
         <p>There were considerable congregations both at Mattins, and at Evensong.  I preached on "Faction &amp; vainglory" in the morning; and on the "Healing of the Gadarene demoniac" in the evening. The last was a frankly heretical sermon</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[448]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Wednesday, the 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Oct: 1905, I travelled to Portsea, and <listEvent><event xml:id="141" display="no">preached</event></listEvent> in the Parish Church, where the celebration of the Dedication Festival was beginning.</hi>  There was a large congregation &amp; an immense choir of men &amp; boys.  I put up for the night at the Vicarage or Clergy-house; &amp; was much pleased with the general aspect of enthusiasm &amp; effort, which marked the place.  <hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="169">Bernard Wilson</persName> is certainly an excellent fellow</hi>, &amp; under his leading the parochial system shews up well.  I returned to town on Thursday morning <hi rend="bold underline">in time to officiate at S. Margaret's at the wedding of <persName xml:id="750">Miss Gorst</persName> and <persName xml:id="751">Major Herbert</persName>.</hi>  My <persName xml:id="112">wife</persName> &amp; I attended the reception afterwards, &amp; there I met <persName xml:id="752">Canon</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="753">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Barnett</persName>, whom I had not seen for nearly 20 years.  On Thursday evening I wrote a letter to the Westminster Gazette; it appeared in that paper under the heading, <ref xml:id="71">‘The Clergyman in Politics'</ref>, on Saturday the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.<note xml:id="60" display="no" n="1"></note>  The death of <persName xml:id="754">Sir Henry Irving</persName> is announced.  A reporter attempted to obtain from me an opinion on the subject of his burial in the Abbey!  The day before, he had sought a decision from me on the "Sex of the Angels">!!!</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
