<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Baptist Minister, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. Herbert Dunnico M.P</hi><hi>.,<persName xml:id="5491"></persName> who sits as Labour Member for Consett, sends me the Official Report of his speech on the Prayer Book Measure in the House of Commons on December 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. It is excellent. He spoke 'as a free Church Minister' and claimed 'that in expressing his opinions, he was expressing also the opinions of some of the great leaders of the Free Churches'. He prefers the New Book to the Old, &amp; refuses to see anything objectionable in Reservation. I sent him a short letter of acknowledgement &amp; appreciation.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Kenneth took me for a walk round the Park. We discussed the origin of the Holy Roman Empire, a subject which he is reading about in Bryce. He is certainly keen, but how far he is intelligent is not yet disclosed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent most of the day on the preparation of my sermon for New Year's Day, when I preach in the Cathedral. It is less a sermon that I project than a pronouncement: &amp; the more I attempt to frame it, the more difficult it seems to be to say what I really mean. The temptation is very strong to say nothing, but to 'wait &amp; see', that is, to accept the defeat, &amp; 'take it lying down'!!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
