<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Mass of Bolensa, Thursday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>What </hi><hi rend="underline">Transubstantiation</hi><hi> was understood to mean in the XVI</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century is well shown by the legend of Bolensa, which is pourtrayed [sic] by Raphael in the Vatican, and had a special attraction for his patron, Julius ii. For the whole story see </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pastor</hi><hi>'s </hi><hi rend="underline">History of the Popes vol vi. p 594&#8211;599</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"A German priest had been greatly tormented with doubts as to the truth of the doctrine of Transubstantiation, and had earnestly prayed for a sign that should dispel them. His prayer was granted in eh Church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ta</hi><hi> Christina at Bolensa, where he had stopped in the course of a pilgrimage to Rome. While he was saying Mass there, at the moment of consecration, drops of Blood oozed from the Sacred Heart in sufficient quantity to stain the Corporal. This miracle constituted one of the motives which had determined Urban IV to institute the Feast of Corpus Christi. By his orders the relic was brought to Orvieto, &amp; the splendid cathedral there was built mainly for it... Julius II when staying at Orvieto on his first expedition against Bologna had manifested great reverence for this relic " Probably this gross understanding of the scholastic dogma still governs the multitude of Papists.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning in preparing notes for a speech tonight, and a little address for the function tomorrow. After lunch I walked for an hour and a half. Then I motored to Newcastle, &amp; dined out with the Newcastle and Northern Counties Medical Society. The company numbered about 120 doctors, &amp; was presided over by the President ^of the Society^. I sate beside a Glasgow surgeon named M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Clelland, who had been lecturing in the afternoon. I found the proceedings intolerably dull, but I could not get away as my toast was the last on the list. About 10.30 p.m. I escaped and was back in the Castle before 11.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The general appearance of the doctors rather surprised me. They are certainly a rough lot, possibly well equipped for their particular work, but uncultured &amp; perhaps even illiterate. Of course this was no more than an impression, but it was a strong one. My speech only took about 12 minutes, for I omitted much, and, as there were no reporters present, there was no public importance in the speaking. The older I grow the more odious becomes the smell of tobacco, &amp; the pointless talk which passes for conversation at public dinner!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
