<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Boxing Day, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>More snow during the night, and sudden snow falls during the day. I declined the suggestion of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Marchant</hi><hi> that I should write something on '</hi><hi rend="underline">Spiritual Independence for the Church of England</hi><hi>', but I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hird</hi><hi> inquiring whether </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder and Stoughton</hi><hi> would publish 'at short notice and at headlong pace' something to be entitled "</hi><hi rend="underline">Thinking aloud; reflections on the Crisis</hi><hi>", or something of that kind. Some pronouncement from me seems to be required, but I find it extraordinarily difficult to determine what it ought to be. If I were a thorough–going advocate for "autonomy", it would be easy enough; and, if I were a thorough–going "Erastian", there would be little doubt of my course: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">but as it is, distrusting Autotomy and loving the Nation, I am in a 'tight place'. Nor am I quite independent. My writings and speeches must be held to limit my liberty. Especially what I said in the H. of L., and in my 'Open Letter' prohibits my attempting to belittle the sinister significance of the episode. Even if the vote itself be reversed, the light cast on the actual situation of the Church at present is too illuminating</hi><hi>! </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
