<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
<p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I spent the day at Lambeth in conference with my fellow bishops. All the four rebels were present, and all spoke. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Exeter</hi><hi rend="italic"> excelled himself in muddle&#8211;headed irrelevance. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Worcester </hi><hi rend="italic">was meticulously didactic. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Birmingham</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">plaintively egotistical. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Norwich</hi><hi rend="italic"> 'The sparrow that sittest alone upon the housetop'. There were, I thought, ominous signs that the Evangelical bishops were 'weakening'. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">St Edmondsbury and Ipswich</hi><hi rend="italic"> almost hung out the white flag. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Coventry</hi><hi rend="italic"> all but expressed satisfaction at the loss of the Prayer Book. Even </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Chelmsford</hi><hi rend="italic"> pleaded for conciliation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There is not much substance in the vaunted unity of the episcopate. But the most part of the bishops stood firm, and some, notably </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Chester</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">St Alban's, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">and </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Southwark</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, were almost bellicose. </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Manchester's</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> attitude interested me most. I carried on a conversation in writing with him and retained the manuscript</hi><hi rend="italic">. It runs thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Durham</hi><hi rend="italic"> Should we carry the Revised Book through Church Assembly and Convocations again?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Manchester </hi><hi rend="italic">Certainly through Convocations, not so certainly through Assembly, but I think so.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Durham</hi><hi rend="italic"> The real scandal of the situation is that such a decision could be reached by such an assembly after such a debate.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[26] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Manchester </hi><hi rend="italic">Yes; and we shall have to consider how far we can in future put such matters before Parliament. But we </hi><hi rend="italic underline">have</hi><hi rend="italic"> put this forward to Parliament, and to go round some corner </hi><hi rend="italic underline">now</hi><hi rend="italic"> would be (in justice) to flout the State, not merely to declare independence in action.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Durham </hi><hi rend="italic">But isn't this (perhaps) a God&#8211;given opportunity for stating the aforesaid principle at stake without party or personal complications such as would inevitably exist when the issue is next raised? Hadn't we better seize it?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I can see a real wisdom in this, but the ramifications of Disestablishment are so great that I feel (at present) unable to embark on this course until I </hi><hi rend="italic underline">know</hi><hi rend="italic"> that the Church cannot have freedom of worship under the existing system.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">As I was leaving</hi><hi rend="i bold">, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Archbishop called me back and begged me to dine &amp; discuss the wording of the Archiepiscopal letter which we decided to put out</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">So rather ruefully I wrote a note to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi><hi rend="italic"> cancelling my appointment to dine with her, promising to get away from Lambeth as soon as I decently could</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner the two archbishops and I laboured for an hour on the letter which should be sent to the peers</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Then I got back to Londonderry House, and found beside mine host &amp; hostess, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Salisbury</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Chaplin</hi><hi rend="italic">, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Carlisle</hi><hi rend="italic">. We talked briskly for an hour, &amp; then I went to bed being sufficiently tired.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Sir Vincent Baddely</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> told me that he had heard my speech throughout, &amp; congratulated me on it warmly</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> publishes a vigorous letter from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Birkenhead</hi><hi rend="italic"> criticising severely the action of the House of Commons, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">exhorting the clergy to proceed forthwith to use the Revised Prayer Book as if it had been legalized, and plainly castigating "</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jix</hi><hi rend="italic">". This letter, expressed with much humour, is bound to have a considerable effect, but it is less helpful than embarrassing to the Bishops. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Birkenhead</hi><hi rend="italic">'s </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">notorious laxity of morals</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> disqualifies him for any considerable rôle in the ecclesiastical sphere, whereas </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inskip </hi><hi rend="italic">and "</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jix</hi><hi rend="italic">", dour fanaticks as they are, do command respect as evidently governed by real religious conviction.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
