<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">By 248 votes to 205 the Revised Prayer Book Resolution was rejected in the House of Commons last night. It is an untoward event, and for me as unexpected as it is untoward</hi><hi>. The case seems to have been badly presented to the House, and the combination of religious fervour &amp; legal acumen in the attack was irresistible. Neither </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridgman,</hi><hi> who introduced the Resolution nor </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Cecil</hi><hi>, who was depended on to be its principal defender was effective, while </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Joynson Hicks</hi><hi> made the speech of his life. A fervent Presbyterian named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rosslyn Mitchell</hi><hi> made a vehement speech, which is said to have been very effective. It is, perhaps, rather difficult to understand the process of reasoning by which he engaged in the effort to Erastianize an alien church; but the logic of fanaticism is quite unfathomable. The Prime Minister seems to have spoken well, but he was unable to stay the tide of anti&#8211;episcopal feeling. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi> voted against the Resolution, and, rather to my surprise, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Simon</hi><hi> spoke energetically against it. The Archbishop of Canterbury, witnessing the ruin of his hopes, is reported to have wept It was for him a cruel experience.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>N.B. His Grace denies this.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[16] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The situation which has been created is difficult. On the whole I do not envy the position of the Bishops of Norwich, Worcester, and Birmingham. </hi><hi rend="underline">They have invited the barbarians into Italy</hi><hi>! It is hard to see what course they can take. The so&#8211;called compromise of passing a fresh measure incorporating everything except the provisions affecting the Communion Office is wholly unacceptable. </hi><hi rend="underline">The Episcopate can hardly sink so low as to accept a policy from a majority of the House of Commons</hi><hi>. Perhaps the best and most dignified course would be for the Primate to give notice that he would himself introduce a measure for </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Disestablishment</hi><hi>. But at fourscore a man may well hesitate to initiate an angry and protracted conflict in order to attain an object which be loathes! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Perhaps this humiliating defeat may turn out to be a blessing in disguise, for it has forced Disestablishment into prominence on a clear&#8211;cut and adequate issue. If the Resolution had gone through Parliament successfully, the same question would have had to be faced as soon as a Labour Government came into power, probably on some petty issue of Crown patronage! </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Durham, and confirmed in the Cathedral 54 boys from the Grammar School and 4 Choristers. Derek Elliott was one of the boys confirmed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I returned to Auckland and wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Marchant</hi><hi> basely crying off my promise to write a "Swan&#8211;song" sermon for his book, &amp; suggesting that, if he really </hi><hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> have one of my discourses, he had better make use of the Congress sermon. Then I visited the dentist; after which I went again into Durham taking </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Perry&#8211;Evans</hi><hi> with me. I interviewed the following 8 candidates:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Priests.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Oswald Noel Garilliam. B.A. (Durham)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>John S. G. Llewelyn. B.A. (Oxford).</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Robert W. B. Richards. B.A. (Oxford)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Deacons.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>George Bailey.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Nigel Edmund Cornwall.</hi><hi> B.A. (Oxford)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>William Burdon Frazer. B.A. (Cambridge)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Harold Grayson. B.A. (Leeds)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>William E. Wright. B.A. (Durham)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Parry&#8211;Evans gave an address at Evensong, which was evidently prepared with much care. It was rather long, but evidently sincere: I think the men were impressed.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
