<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1927.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 11 communicants, including the 3 Brydens, and our 2 guests.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I revised my sermon for Shildon, and made some notes for the debate in the House of Lords.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and Linetta accompanied me to Shildon, where I preached at Evensong from S. John i.35. The centre of the church was well filled, but the aisles were empty. I was pleased with the service, save for the illegal substitution of "special" psalms for those appointed in the Prayer Book, and of an 'omnibus' prayer for the King &amp; others in authority for the prayers for His Majesty and the Royal Family. Why will the clergy break the law so needlessly? The lessons were read by two young laymen, of whom I recognized one as an Ordination Candidate to whom the diocese makes a grant. There was a choir of men, women, and boys, which sang well. Evidently </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watts</hi><hi> has a hold over them, though I suspect that they find him rather fussy. </hi><hi rend="underline">He told me that he had withdrawn from his connexion with the Labour Party</hi><hi>. We returned to Auckland immediately after the service.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[7] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Streeter sent me last week his latest composite volume – 'Adventures, the Faith of Science and the Science of Faith'. It is the work of three others besides himself – Catherine M. Chilcott, John Macmurray, and Alexander S. Russell. I read through the first three chapters.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">The Protestant Underworld</hi><hi>", the noble and learned Lord said that the phrase w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> never be forgotten. I rejoice to hear it. I hope it will be remembered and repeated as long as that 'underworld' is allowed to be a factor in our public life, &amp;, I will take leave to add, as long as eminent lawyers &amp; ecclesiastics are found to utilize its services &amp; accept its dishonouring homage."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>N.B. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I did actually say this in my speech in the House of Lords: when I produced and read aloud a scurrilous paper, as illustrative of what I meant by 'the Protestant Underworld', a phrase which has been hotly resented by the Evangelicals, who have generally assumed that I intended it as a description of their immaculate selves!]</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
