<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Anima vagula blandula</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>hospes comesque corporis</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>quae nunc abibis in loca</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>pallidula rigida nudula</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>nec ut soles dabis locos!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Soul of mine, pretty one, flitting one,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Guest and partner of my clay,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Whither wilt thou hie away, – </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Pallid one, rigid one, naked one – </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Never to play again, never to play.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Emperor Hadrian as he lay dying is said to have composed these lines (v. Scriptores Historiae Augustae. Hadrian. 25).</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The papers report the murder of a young bank–clerk named Abbey by a burglar, who robbed the bank at Ferryhill. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Abbey</hi><hi rend="italic"> was a chorister in Durham, when I was first Dean, &amp; seems to have been an estimable fellow. Taken together with the recent series of burglaries in Bishop Auckland, &amp; the increasing audacity of the coal–stealers in the Park, this shocking crime must be taken to disclose a notable weakening of elementary morals in the population. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[125] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p>["]<hi>Now there is an apprehension &amp; presentiment, natural to mankind, that we ourselves shall one time or another be dealt with as we deal with others: and a peculiar acquiescence in, and feeling of, the equity and justice of this equal distribution.</hi>["]
         </p>
<p><hi>Bishop Butler 'Upon Forgiveness of Injuries'</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This 'apprehension and presentiment' are explicitly authenticated by our Blessed Saviour: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Judge not, that ye be not judged. For with what judgement ye judge, ye shall be judged; and with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured unto you</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Selbie</hi><hi>, speaking in Oxford yesterday, is reported to have said:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"The discussions on the Prayer Book had led to a good deal of hardening of opinion among Free Church people. In the course of recent conversations </hi><hi rend="underline">he had been surprised at the extreme &amp; obsolete Protestantism held by many prominent laymen of the Anglican Church</hi><hi>".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This is certainly illuminating.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
