<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">A woefully wet day. Ella went with me to Darlington where she had to attend a Committee and I caught the 11.21 a.m. express to King's Cross. I had a carriage to myself, &amp; killed the time with the newspapers &amp; my own thoughts. On arriving in London, I drove to Lambeth, where I found M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="italic">Davidson at tea, and the Archbishop in bed with a chill. Lord Hugh Cecil was in the drawing&#8211;room, but went off immediately. I had a long talk with Sir Lewis Dibdin, who is strongly in favour of meeting the House of Commons by substantial concessions. Indeed, he comes pretty nearly to urging a surrender. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He spoke with much frankness of the Bishop of Worcester, whom he regarded as 'essentially shallow'</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He said that the Bishop made no impression of capacity on his fellow&#8211;directors of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Clergy Mutual</hi><hi rend="italic">: that he was 'a journalist &amp; nothing more', and that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">his appointment to the episcopate evoked Homeric laughter from his colleagues in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi> 
<hi rend="italic bold underline">office. It argues some mental power to be a journalist and an antiquarian, and Ernest Pearce is both, but he does not transcend either</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[57] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The floods in London must have been very terrible. Lord Desborough, the Chairman of the Thames Conservancy, is reported to ascribe them to a tidal wave, and says that no effective precaution can be taken against them. The waters rushed into Lambeth Palace, and flooded all the basements.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir Thomas Barlow and his daughter were at dinner. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The old man said something flatterous about my article on the Quakers in the</hi> 
<hi rend="italic underline">Edinburgh</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">We had a considerable talk on the Situation after dinner. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi><hi rend="italic">, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">I</hi><hi rend="italic"> were for standing firm, &amp; conceding nothing but explanatory amendments. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dibdin</hi><hi rend="italic"> was as strong for substantial concession. If we had behind us a genuinely united church, our course would be comparatively simple, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Revised Prayer Book is a most delicately balanced compromise, &amp; any alteration so disorders the balance that the whole structure may collapse</hi><hi rend="italic">. Our brave front in the House of Lords was largely a piece of inevitable bluff. We assumed an agreement which we could not but know does not exist: &amp; when we are required to reproduce it, the chances are heavy against our being able to do so.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
