<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The really trying thing about episcopal office is the inevitable acquiescence in the make–belief involved in administering a system which is altogether obsolete, not so much in its actual requirements as in its pre–supposition and underlying ideas. Today an incumbent writes "in accordance with the Rubrics for Adult Baptism" to "inform me "that he has "three candidates for Confirmation who are to receive the Holy Sacrament of Baptism". The Rubrick throws on the Bishop an ampler obligation than the good man seems to realize; and the notice must be given "by the Parents, or some other discreet persons', a description which hardly suggests the parish priest. And the object of this notice to the Bishop is thus stated, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">that so due care may be taken for their examination, whether they be sufficiently instructed in the principles of the Christian Religion; &amp; that they may be exhorted to prepared themselves with Prayers &amp; Fasting for the receiving of this Holy Sacrament". I sent a note to the Incumbent authorising him to act as my deputy, and dispensing from the Fast</hi><hi rend="italic">. I wonder whether the Rubric ever was seriously enforced even in the generation which witnessed its enactment.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[203]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Hodgson</hi><hi>, a lad of 17, the son of a market gardener at Heighington, who aspires to become a clergyman came to lunch. I asked him what had put it into his head to want to be ordained, &amp; he replied, "</hi><hi rend="underline">From reading Ibsen's Brandt</hi><hi>". This is, perhaps, an unusual consequence of reading Ibsen. The lad was painfully shy, but not lacking in modesty and intelligence. On the whole, he impressed me well, but whether he has a definite purpose in the matter of Ordination I have my doubts.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We all motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Houghton–le–Spring</hi><hi>, where I dedicated the bells in the parish church, &amp; gave an address. There was a large congregation. After the service we had tea in the Rectory.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>On returning to the Castle, I interviewed M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Isaac Elland,</hi><hi> an applicant for the position which Laws will vacate on May 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. He is a decent looking man, and has good references, but he is 58, which is rather older than I like: yet these older men are often worth more than the younger, since they still retain the old–fashioned pride in their work, which the others have long since ceased even to understand, still less to possess. "Ca canny" is an atmosphere, even where it is not a policy.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
