<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella with her party returned from Raby at 4.25 a.m. </hi><hi rend="italic">I spent the morning in writing letters, among which was one to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Will Spens</hi><hi rend="italic"> in answer to a suggestion that he might have an interview in order to discuss with me some proposals which Streeter, Storr, Rawlinson, and he have drafted with a view to finding a way out of the impasse on Prayer Book Revision. I replied amiably but pointed out that we could hardly make fresh proposals without appearing to accept the situation created by the House of Commons.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">In the afternoon I walked with the Park&#8211;keeper who showed me a new coal&#8211;stealing boring&#8211;place. We visited the usual "mine", and captured two men, who were actually getting coal. One of them had served in the Gordon Highlanders as Sergeant Major. I said that for that reason, he should be let off.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I have read through </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dick Shepphard</hi><hi rend="italic">'s book &#8211; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Impatience of a Parson</hi><hi rend="italic"> &#8211; a second time, and my ill impression of it is confirmed. There is in it </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">nothing</hi><hi rend="italic"> of value, and much that is extremely mischievous. What a light it casts on the quality of modern preaching that flimsy extravagances of this kind should be hailed with enthusiasm as 'prophecy'!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
