<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I would beg the clergy to abstain from using the word Mass for the service of celebrating the Holy Sacrament …. The Reformers in the first Prayer Book retained the word, but when they realised the state of the case they gave it up. Even if the "Mass" were identical with the Order of the Administration of the Lord's Supper, the use of the name would be offensive &#8211; but as certainly it is not, it is false &amp; suggestive of more falsehood &amp; more insincerity. Of the silliness of this I prefer not to speak. On this point I would peremptorily insist; &amp; would forbid the employment of the term absolutely, were I not apprehensive that those who are so foolish as to use it would not be wise enough to obey my h ^[remaining sentence missing]^</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Bishop Stubbs. Charge. 1899. (p. 325&#8211;6)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The word "Mass" is used habitually by Anglo&#8211;Catholics, who express a pained astonishment when a Bishop objects to it use. Bishop Stubbs was a rigid Tractarian, but he would have been entirely out of harmony with our Anglo&#8211;Catholics. His type of English Churchmanship is probably limited to clergymen over seventy!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I read through Bunyan's interesting tract published in the very year of his death, 1688, &amp; quaintly entitled "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Heavenly Footman</hi><hi>". Then I read '</hi><hi rend="underline">Grace Abounding</hi><hi>', and was more than ever impressed by its power &amp; sincerity. But what a Christianity this is which the tinker exhibits! It has no use for sacraments, or an ordained ministry. The English Bible &amp; the ability to read it suffice.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> came to see me. He is on the brink of a nervous breakdown. It is the usual story. The lad has been reading absurdly, worrying himself excessively, &amp; made himself ill. I took him for a walk in the Park, &amp; poured out the experienced wisdom which youth always receives, &amp; never heeds!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lake</hi><hi> came to lunch. I proposed to him appointment to the School Mission in Gateshead. He was certainly by no means enthusiastic, but promised to consider it! </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> &amp; I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Herrington</hi><hi>, where I confirmed 83 persons. The church was filled by an attentive congregation, &amp; the candidates were devout in their demeanour, &amp; seemed to be impressed. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lockyer</hi><hi> of Newbottle brought candidates, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Renwick</hi><hi> of Shiney Row brought 3 "oddments". After the service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
