<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This visit to Lambeth has been less pleasing than former visits, mainly </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">because there has been a change for the worse in my relations with the Archbishop</hi><hi rend="italic">. Partly, this arises from his Grace's perception that I regard the present untoward situation as the outcome of the Enabling Act, which he has accustomed himself to regard as the monument of his statesmanship: and, partly, because he wants to patch up the quarrel with the House of Commons, &amp; finds me far less conveniently "Erastian" than he had allowed himself to expect. It is the old story of disappointing expectations which are both natural and unfounded! </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Davidson</hi><hi rend="italic">, who is 'wrapped up' in her husband, inevitably reflects his mood: and, therefore, regards me with a disappointing eye. Their extraordinary amiability last night confessed as much as concealed their mood of disapprobation. I fear this unhappy action of the House of Commons will affect private as well as public relations. It has severed </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi rend="italic"> and me, &amp; must necessarily do so as much with my friendships with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pearce</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; others. We disclaim the alienation, &amp; use the old terms of affection, but the friendship itself has expired.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi><hi> has an extremely hostile paragraph about the Bishop of Durham, to whose sermons and speeches the loss of the Revised Prayer Book is mainly to be ascribed!!! The reference to 'the Protestant underworld' was apparently too much for the House of Commons to stand! The </hi><hi rend="underline">Church Family Newspaper</hi><hi> has a letter from Guy Rogers on the situation in which it says "The Protestant underworld has smitten the Bishop of Durham hip and thigh". I suppose that is that is the way in which that phrase passes in Evangelical circles. The world is an absurder place than I had thought.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ I left the Palace after breakfast, and attended the Meeting of the Home Office Committee at 10.30 a.m. We had witnesses from Birmingham and Manchester. The extraordinary feature of Their evidence is the recent, rapid diminution of arrests for prostitution. I asked to what this fact was attributable, &amp; was told that it was mainly due to the advent of the motor&#8211;car and motor&#8211;cycle, which distributes prostitution over a very wide area. There appears to be practically no unnatural vice in these provincial cities.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ </hi><hi rend="italic">I dined with mine host and hostess in Park Lane, and had much talk with them. S. expressed himself with decision on the unwisdom of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic">'s performance in York Minster on New Year's Eve. He thought the photograph of the Archbishop in full pontificals, which appeared in the newspapers was likely to confirm all the Protestant apprehensions, which defeated the Prayer Book in the House of Commons. I think so too, but I was surprised to hear him say it also.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ The papers report a rather squalid suit, in which a money&#8211;lender brings an action against </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Hardinge's</hi><hi> wife. Incidentally, it was mentioned that he was ill, and had lost his memory. What a tragedy his life has become! Both his sons have been killed in bicycling accidents: &amp; now he is a helpless derelict, &amp; his wife is bringing his name into discredit. How differently I remember him when first I made his acquaintance at All Souls in 1884 &#8211; forty three years ago. He was bubbling over with high spirits. We took to one another, and, I suppose, must have had some resemblance, for I well remember that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Forbes</hi><hi> of Balliol mistook me for him, and talked through a whole evening on the mistaken hypothesis. And now ___ ?</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
