<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928. Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The sermon I propose to preach to the University this afternoon must affect my reputation, and may affect my fortune. Any one who even seems to assist the disastrous policy of Disestablishment and Disendowment will certainly arouse against himself the bitter resentment of all who stand to lose, or think they stand to lose by it. If the policy shall actually be carried through, one thing at least is certain viz. that the latest years of my career like the earliest will be shadowed by poverty. Not, indeed the squalid indigence which is commonly understood by poverty, but a privation of all that gives social importance, refinement, and freedom of movement. This would be unacceptable in any case, but when it must be extended to the case of another, unresponsive, unconvinced, perhaps resentful: it will bring to one's life a degree of bitterness which will be hard to bear. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">A man's foes shall be they of his own household</hi><hi rend="italic">" said Christ. S. Paul: "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">He that is married careth for the things of the world; how he may please his wife".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I attended the Celebration in the College Chapel at 8.15 a.m., &amp; received Holy Communion.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I preached in </hi><hi rend="underline">Trinity College Chapel</hi><hi> at 11 a.m. There were about 120 persons in the Chapel, of whom perhaps as many as a dozen were ladies. The service consisted of abbreviated morning prayer. I preached the sermon on </hi><hi rend="underline">Tolerance</hi><hi>, which has already done duty in Durham &amp; Leeds. The youth were really attentive: indeed, the Master told me that he /had never before seen them so much so. And </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stewart</hi><hi> was very appreciative. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Xan Wynne–Wilson</hi><hi>, and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Garth Moore</hi><hi> were awaiting me in the Great Court. This was more pleasant than I had ventured to hope.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I lunched with mine host &amp; hostess. The new Dean of Norwich &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cranage</hi><hi> were there: and lady who explained to me that she was the sister of Dorothy's husband, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Low</hi><hi>, the ornithologist. Also, there was also a well–looking young clergyman, who was introduced to me as the Chaplain of Magdalene College. Another lady was present, but she made no impression on me.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">There was a large congregation in Great S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Mary's at 2.30 p.m. when I preached to the University. The floor was completely filled, and both galleries looked full of undergraduates. Among my hearers were the Bishop of London, who had come up to preach to undergraduates, and the Editor of the Tablet. My sermon took about 45 minutes to deliver, and was listened to with the closest attention. Once or twice a ripple of amusement passed over the congregation but mostly it was as sedate as it was attentive. I think everyone realized that the occasion was critical, and the pronouncement both deliberate and important.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I had tea with Cunningham in Westcott House, i.e. with the Vice–Principal, an Anglo–Catholick, but attractive &amp; in appearance candid. Two young men who aspire to work in the diocese of Durham joined us, &amp; we had a great talk. One of them, Harding of Queen's, walked back with me to Sidney Sussex, &amp; gave me an informing account of the diverse religious agencies in the University.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
