<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
<p><hi>[</hi><hi rend="bold">45]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">New Year's Day, January 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The cold continues, but there is a 'feeling' of thaw in the air. But the country is still snow shrouded</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but 8 communicants. Before the prayer for the Church Militant I called for special prayer that God would guide &amp; strengthen us in the new year.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">We motored to Durham, &amp; attended the morning service in the cathedral. I preached from Exodus xiv.15 "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Speak unto the children of Israel, that they go forward</hi><hi rend="italic">'. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My sermon was a 'pronouncement'</hi><hi rend="italic"> on the crisis so suddenly induced by the action, as reckless as it was unexpected, of the House of Commons</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Headlam</hi><hi> was in the congregation, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Castlereagh</hi><hi> with a party from Wynyard. They approved, but their approval doesn't carry far. I celebrated the Holy Communion, &amp; then lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson Walker</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">On our way back to Auckland we called on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Colonel Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; received the parcel of prints of Auckland Castle, which </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Barrington</hi><hi rend="italic">, a descendent of the Bishop, presented.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Great Stainton, &amp; preached at Evensong to a congregation of about 50 persons. This little parish, with a population of 156 has just been united to </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishopton</hi><hi> with 424. The parson of the united parishes, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> R. H. Reilly</hi><hi>, is a good fellow with failing eyesight. He made some rather disconcerting blunders in reading the service. I read the lessons myself, &amp; so avoided the disclosure of his weakness at the lectern: but I augured ill from the fact that he found it necessary to assist his eyes with a flash lamp! He was ordained in 1887, the year of my own ordination, &amp; he has been 20 years at </hi><hi rend="underline">Bishopton</hi><hi>. The increasing decrepitude of the aging clergy is becoming a very serious feature of the situation. In the old days there was a continual supply of young assistant curates, &amp; these relieved the weakness of their old incumbents: but now the poor things have to go on without help &amp; gradually one piece of parochial work is given up, &amp; then another, until everything shrinks to the petty measure of the legal obligation. The standards of work are lowering everywhere in this diocese.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
