<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Maundy Thursday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wasted the morning in writing a sermon, and the evening in going to Lynesack, and delivering it. The afternoon was wasted in going to Durham, and presiding at a meeting of the Training &amp; Maintenance Committee.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Canon Bothamly collapsed yesterday by reason of a sudden heart&#8211;failure, &amp; is now in Durham Hospital. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Merrifield of Etherley seems to be nearing his end. I saw him for a few minutes, as I went to Lynesack. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Heselton came to lunch by appointment. I offered him the living of Rainton, from which the present Vicar, Rawlins, retires; his resignation takes effect on May 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, &amp; he has been allotted a pension of &#x00A3;100. Out of the income of the benefice, which is thus reduced to little more than poundisgn300. Per annum.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Evangelical press rages against me, denouncing me as 'a mutable Bishop', referring to me in terms of calculated insult, &amp; belittling everything I say or write. I have had much experience of religious hostility in the course of my life: &amp; I don't think there is much to choose between the venom of Evangelicalism, and that of Anglo&#8211;Catholicism. Perhaps, the first is the more nauseous, &amp; the last, more malicious!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
