<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ We motored to Durham, and lunched in the Castle. The party consisted besides ourselves of Lord Londonderry and his daughter Helen, the Master &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Ellershaw, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jones, the architect. After lunch, the last&#8211;named showed the males of the party over the building, and explained the work which was necessary to preserve it from what looks like imminent destruction. Certainly the tokens of danger are alarmingly apparent, great fissures in he walls, disintegrated masonry, and walls out of the perpendicular. We returned to Auckland after our inspection was finished.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ Tony Chute arrived on a short visit: and Lionel returned.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Servant's Party took place, &amp; was attended by a company of about 40 persons. We joined them for the acting which was extremely amusing. There is an astonishing amount of dramatic capacity about the humble English folk, &amp; this was stimulated and directed by the professional skill &amp; enthusiasm of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Smith. I cannot but think such a domestic </hi><hi rend="underline">saturnalia</hi><hi> has an excellent effect on the course &amp; temper of household life. It draws us together, and does something to mitigate the sharpness of class&#8211;divisions.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
