<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I weeded out from the shelves in my dressing room and placed on the floor for transference to a kind of 'indeterminate state' between recognition &amp; destruction a number of small books, sent to me by author and publishers for the most part, which have no interest for me, &amp; have no permanent value at all. They will be placed demurely in the less–used bedrooms, until when the final dispensing of my goods takes place, they will be consigned to the flames, from which only my good feeling has rescued them. We speak of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ephemeral</hi><hi rend="italic"> and permanent books: but the terms are relative. The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ephemeral</hi><hi rend="italic"> only differ in degree from the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">permanent</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; both are less than ephemeral in reality. Even the books which are comparatively important are more often than not rendered (i.e. the volumes one possesses) valueless by new editions. And the older books, which one exulted in acquiring &amp; exhibited to one's friends with something of a bibliophile's enthusiasm, are all being stripped of any special worth, &amp; of all their mysterious charm, by the modern fashion of re–printing &amp; even re–producing in actual type &amp; shape everything of interest. There is no longer any significant reason why anyone should be at all cast of purchasing, and the inconvenience of housing, a library of his own.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella and I left the Castle with the intention of staying the night with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Baker–Wilbrahams</hi><hi> at Rode Hall in Cheshire. We travelled easily to Healaugh Manor, Tadcaster, where we lunched pleasantly with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Edward and Lady Brooksbank</hi><hi>. We were looking at the flowers in the conservatory when a message from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Leng</hi><hi> summoned me to the garage. Something had gone wrong with the car: a broken screw emerged from its entrails: &amp; Leng advised a return to Auckland. This counsel prevailed, and we travelled home without incident or delay, arriving at 5.30 p.m. to the surprise, &amp; perhaps the consternation, of our household. This was a rather absurd start for a holiday.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I was rather perturbed at being given plover's eggs at lunch: but mine host assured me that the birds were plentiful on his moor, and that while </hi><hi rend="underline">selling</hi><hi> the eggs was illegal, the taking &amp; eating of them was not. He said also that there had been a notable increase in the birds since the sale of their eggs had been prohibited. In the whole drive to &amp; from Tadcaster I only saw two plovers.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[209] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> reports the passing in Alberta of '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Sexual Sterilization Bill'</hi><hi rend="italic"> which 'provides for the sterilization of all feeble–minded persons whom it is proposed to release from the provincial asylums &amp; mental hospitals'. How far is this law consonant with the principle of Christ's Gospel? The plea that sterilization is required in the interest of the community has obvious congruity with the Christian insistence on self–sacrifice for the sake of others. The inflicting of the death penalty on criminals, &amp; the acceptance of military service as legitimate for a Christian man – both of which have always been held to be consonant with Christian duty seem to establish the right of the State for sufficient cause to castrate or sterilize individuals. Nevertheless, Christian Sentiment is revolted by such treatment of the human body. It seems to violate the self–respect of humanity, &amp; to restore the long–repudiated penal method of mutilation. The circumstance that feeble–mindedness argues no moral fault, but must be regarded as sheer misfortune differentiates the case of the feeble–minded from the criminal. This, indeed, is recognised by the provisions of the Bill which make the consent of relations requisite before sterilization can take place.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
