<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Some anonymous correspondent sent me a cutting from the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Daily Express</hi><hi>', which is not without interest:</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>'Hundreds of M.P.s yesterday received a Bible each, beautifully bound, with gilt edges, &amp; a golden illustration of the Houses of Parliament on the cover. They were at first astonished.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>An accompanying letter showed that the Bibles came from the Rev. H. Anton, Vicar, &amp; Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs.</hi><hi> W.J. Grimes &amp; E. Bricknell, Churchwardens, and the congregation of Christ Church, Coventry, to commemorate December 15, when the revised Prayer book measure was defeated in the House of Commons.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Every member who voted against the Prayer–book received a Bible in appreciation of his "stand for the truth".' </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The M.P.s may well have been astonished. The Vicar, who was no doubt the originator of this singular demonstration, is a Cambridge man, took a 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd </hi><hi>class in the Classical Tripos in in 1906, and was ordained in 1909. He holds a benefice which is in the patronage of Trustees. We know what that means.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered but 7 communicants. After breakfast I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><hi>. Also, I wrote to the Archbishop of York reporting this lamentable business of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sinnamon</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">South Hylton</hi><hi>, where I confirmed 65 persons. After having tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Fuller</hi><hi> in the Vicarage, where he lives rather forlornly in 2 rooms, we went on to </hi><hi rend="underline">Gateshead</hi><hi>, where I confirmed 75 persons in the parish church. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephenson</hi><hi>, with his colleagues, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Heselton</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Welch</hi><hi>, were there. There was a large congregation which, though mainly composed of 'slummites', was very attentive &amp; well–behaved. The four churchwardens preceded me with their wands. I was surprised at the excellence of the singing. There is much to be said for having Confirmations on Sundays. After service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote up my journal, and made my preparations for a day in town tomorrow before going to bed. Only my desire to assist the Fund for Durham Castle could justify the waste of time, money, &amp; strength involved in a journey to London.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
