<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[219]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I slept badly, and "deceived" the wakeful hours bys reading </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ronaldshay</hi><hi rend="italic">'s '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Life of Curzon</hi><hi rend="italic">', which I found both illuminating and full of interest. The reflection crossed my mind, how great the loss, and how grievous the disadvantage which attach to the absence of the normal training for public life, which in </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Curzon'</hi><hi rend="italic">s case was present in fullest measure. What in later years can make up for the handicap implied by lack of the disciplines, emulations, cultures, enthusiasms, &amp; friendships which a public school brings to the well–born young Englishman? </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Curzon </hi><hi rend="italic">had every factor of success except one, physical robustness, and even this disadvantage probably assisted rather than retarded his career. For not only did his character benefit by the necessity of self–control &amp; determination, but also, he was protected from many distractions which perfect physical health must have brought. Apart from this single hindrance, how magnificent was his equipment for the battle of life – ancestry, a good home, beautiful environment, good looks, brilliant intellectual powers, perfect training, troops of friends, early &amp; rich opportunities. And every opportunity was seized, every faculty developed, every power exercized. He was a "good &amp; faithful servant".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[220]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Another dark and rainy day, withal bitterly cold. We left Broncroft Castle at 10.20 a.m., &amp; motored to Craven Arms where we took train to Hereford. Alan Smith met us at the station, &amp; drove us to the Palace. There we lunched with the Bishop &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Linton Smith. The Dean of Hereford (Waterfield) came to lunch. Afterwards I had much talk with the Bishop, mainly depressing. We left Hereford at 4.5 p.m, &amp; travelled to Gloucester. The Dean met us at the station, &amp; drove us to the Deanery. The Soltau–Simmons [Symons] failed to come to dinner, pleading an invasion of mumps! So we dined with our host pleasantly enough. A telegram from Fearne informed us that Leng had returned to Auckland, reporting that the date of the car's return to duty was uncertain.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Froggatt writes to announce his acceptance of the Stockton Vicarage.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Lord Mayor of London writes to consent to a meeting in the Mansion House in aid of the Durham Castle Preservation Fund, suggesting that it should be postponed for a while to avoid clashing with the Appeal fund.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
