<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Justice Roche</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to me about possible methods of raising funds for the Durham Castle Fund. He assumes very justly that the public appeal has failed, and suggests personal appeals. He indicates what is indeed apparent that the academic authorities carry no weight with anybody, &amp; wonders how much time I can myself devote to mendicancy!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold underline">Lionel and I motored into Durham, where I presided at the meeting of the Diocesan Conference in the Chapter House. There was a fairly large gathering &amp; my address on the question of Ordaining Women in orders to remedy the shortage of clergy, was well received</hi><hi>. The business was transacted with expedition, which was only interrupted by the rambling speeches of the foolish &amp; irrepressible Lomax. I gave lunch in the Castle to Shaddick, Haworth, Patterson, Wynne Willson, Greenway, and Morvis Young. I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed with him much diocesan business. Then we motored to Gateshead Fell, picking up Cecil Ferens on the way. There I instituted </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi> to the Rectory, and gave an address.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After the service we returned to Auckland arriving at the Castle at 9.40 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
