<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My picture as one of "</hi><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Punch's Personalities</hi><hi>" appears in Punch, accompanied by some effective references to the appeal for Durham Castle. I cannot say that the picture is attractive, but it may well be faithful none the less!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the morning in writing a sermon for next Sunday morning when I when I must preach to the Mayor &amp; Corporation of Sunderland in Southwick Church.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After lunch I motored to Newcastle, &amp; attended a meeting of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Durham Castle Fund</hi><hi>. So far we have only received in cash &amp; promises about &#x00A3;10,000. The wealthy men have done very meanly, so far.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Master of the Temple</hi><hi> arrived during my absence. He is as discursively garrulous as ever, &amp; retails a vast amount of gossip, which is more interesting than trustworthy. </hi><hi rend="italic">He said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic">'s last sermon at the Temple, was flatly Unitarian in its teaching about our Saviour, &amp; that the graver Benchers were offended at it.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I gave </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Laws</hi><hi> &amp; his son formal notice to quit my service at the end of April, the month's notice to run from the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> of April. This ought to have the effect of galvanising him into some decision as to his future. A natural vanity &amp; the disintegrating effect of Spiritualism have brought him to an ill pass.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
