<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Creighton</hi><hi> having written to me critically about my address to the Diocesan Conference of which she had seen no more than the extracts which appeared in the newspapers, I was at pains to reply to her very civilly, sending an extract of the salient passage.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">The Master of the Temple</hi><hi> stayed until shortly after 3p.m. He talks volubly and discursively but not very intelligently, though he has a considerable knowledge of English Literature.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After his departure, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I walked in the Park, but got very wet. The rain fell most of the day with considerable violence.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> returned from Scotland, attending a meeting in Durham on the way from Newcastle.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I read through a vehement attack on the modern nonsense of Sex equality by a Norwegian Professor, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">K.A. Wieth&#8211;Knudsen</hi><hi> &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">Feminism, a sociological Study of the Woman question from Ancient Times to the Present Day</hi><hi>". The author makes it very clear that he is neither a Christian nor a Darwinian. He makes out a good case against ignoring the physiological difference between the sexes.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
