<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi><hi> writes, "I am rather inclined to think that the House will pass the Book this time. The last thing they want is a row between Church and State". On the other hand, the Archbishop of Canterbury writes in the opposite sense:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"I have been having interviews with all sorts and conditions of public men, lay &amp; clerical, &amp; I find a very firm conviction on the part of those who were led by the Home Secretary in the House of Commons that they are going to have a larger majority than before when the Commons consider our proposals afresh. But we have learned the fallibility of prophets in this matter to a more than usual degree."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I incline myself to think that the House will not reject the Book a second time.["]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ I spent the morning in writing letters, and preparing notes for an Oration on the League of Nations. The bother of these occasional speeches is the uncertainty what may be made of them by the reporters, &amp; what may grow from their reports. They almost always miss your point in order to provide their own 'copy'!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I motored to Sunderland, &amp; had tea in Bishopwearmouth Rectory. Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Plummer</hi><hi>, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Hilda's, came to expound his objections to the proposed re–arrangement of his parochial boundaries. He was vehement, persistent, and irrational; indeed almost incoherent. After he had taken his grumbling departure, we went to the Town Hall for the meeting of the League of Nations there. The Mayor of Sunderland presided, &amp; there were about 100 persons present. I delivered the oration which I had prepared, gave my notes to the reporters, &amp; returned to Auckland, where we arrived about 9.45 p.m. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Mayor of Sunderland asked me to preach to his Corporation in Southwick Church on April 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> in order that the incorporation of a larger area in the area of the borough might be inaugurated by an act of corporate religion. He expressed himself so nicely that I could not refuse his request, though on that Sunday (Palm Sunday) I have the Confirmation in South Church at 3 p.m. I am informed that the mayor is a nonconformist, &amp; this circumstance also is a reason for doing what he wants.</hi>
         </p>
<p>
            </body></text></TEI>
