<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A grey fog lies on the land like a pall. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants including John.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I completed the sermon for the S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's College students, and then wrote a letter to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> under </hi><hi rend="italic">the heading '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Cardinal Bourne's Fallacy</hi><hi rend="italic">'. This was a criticism of his Eminence's Pastoral Letter, in which he advances the proposition that the "martyrdom" of Papists under the Penal Laws "is the most complete disproof of that imaginary continuity to which some members of the Established Church lay claim".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I walked round the Park during the afternoon. The sun shone brightly from a cloudless sky &amp; the faint haze which over&#8211;spread the country and added to it an almost mystical beauty was the only relic of the morning's fog.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I motored into Durham, where he preached to the C. L. B. in S. Cuthbert's, and I preached to the students of S. John's in Little Bow church, which is now definitely assigned for the College Chapel. After the service I saw Ainsworth, one of the students who wishes to be ordained: &amp; then we had supper with the Principal, &amp; returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
