<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Copies of "The Book &amp; the Vote" were sent to:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>The Duke of Northumberland.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Lord Danesfort.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The Rev. F. E. Warren D.D.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>The Rev. F. C. Tymms.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Cullagh</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Rev. J. C. S. Daly.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
<p><hi rend="italic">I received a pleasant letter from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Abp. D'Arcy</hi><hi rend="italic">. He says of my little book, "It has the charm of being eminently readable, as well as pre&#8211;eminently timely.' His anxiety about Disestablishment is deep. "I was in London lately, &amp; met quite a number of important laymen. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Bridgeman seemed confident that the Book will pass when it comes before Parliament again: others took very decidedly and opposite view. I dreads disestablishment. A second rejection would be a terrible event." He suggests postponing the whole matter for two or even for five years.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Danesfort</hi><hi> writes to ask what on my view Parliament ought to do if the Church definitely adopted Roman catholic doctrines. I could but reply that, in that case, the Church ought to be disestablished: &amp; I sent him " The Book &amp; the Vote".</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Macmillan</hi><hi> sends me a letter of thanks, which opens thus:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>'</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Samuel Johnson</hi><hi> says, "People seldom read a book which is given to them"! But I have waited to thank you for '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Book &amp; the Vote</hi><hi>' until I had read every word of it. Your statement of the problems was profoundly interesting &amp; illuminating to one brought up like myself in the barbarous North &amp; to my lawyer. Soul &#8211; if lawyers have a soul _ the development of your thesis was an intellectual joy.'</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Daly, from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Mary's, Tynedock, came to consult me about a proposal that he should go to Persia for some rather nebulous work for the employe's [sic] of an Oil Company. I told him to stay where he is.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I walked round the Park, calling on the way at Byden's house to inquire for William who has been off duty.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>J. G. Wilson came to tea, &amp; returned to Durham with me &amp; Lionel. We went on to Beamish, where I confirmed 96 persons in the parish church. There was a good deal of fog which made motoring slow &amp; dangerous. However we got back to the Castle about 9.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
