<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I repeated the lazy rôle of yesterday, only getting up after lunch.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The House of Laity finished its revision with no great harm done. The House of Clergy has adjourned until Wednesday. Probably as a result of this adjournment, the Meeting of the House of Bishops is cancelled for next week. It is to take place on March 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> to 7</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. This means that no less than 3 confirmations must be cancelled.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to Kenneth, and sent him the cutting from the </hi><hi rend="underline">Cambridge Review</hi><hi> which has the Sermon preached to the University on the 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Jan</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ry</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I read much of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rostovtzeff's</hi><hi> book, which is quite fascinating. The parallel between the ancient world and the modern is arresting, &amp; far closer than I had imagined. His description of the Greeks in Egypt, and the Romans in Asia hardly requires more than a change of names to make it hold of the English in India. The treatment of their North African possessions by the Romans bears a suggestive resemblance to that our East African colonies by ourselves. And he never seems to find a place for any influence of Christianity!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Julius Mansuctus, a Spaniard, enlisting in the legion Rapax, had left at home a son of tender age. The lad grew up to manhood, &amp; was enrolled by Galba in the 7</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> legion. Now chancing to meet his father, he brought him to the ground with a wound, and, as he rifled his dying foe, recognized him, &amp; was himself recognized. Clasping the expiring man in his arms, in piteous accents he implored the spirit of his father to be propitious to him, &amp; not to turn from him in loathing as from a parricide. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">This guilt", he said is shared by all: how small a part of a civil war is a single soldier!</hi><hi rend="italic">" With these words he raised the body, opened a grave, and discharged the last duties for his father. This was noticed by those who were on the spot, then by many others: astonishment &amp; indignation ran though the whole army, and they cursed this most horrible war. Yet as eagerly as ever they stripped the bodies of slaughtered kinsfolk, connexions, and brothers. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">They talk of an impious act having been done, and they do it themselves</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Tacitus. Histories iii, 25.</hi>
         
<p></body></text></TEI>
