<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I was unpleasantly impressed by young Harding (only 20 years old) speaking glibly about 'preaching at Evensong' when on one of these undergraduate missions, which are so popular &amp; so doubtful.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I left Cambridge by the 9.5 a.m. train which brought me into Liverpool Street at 10.23 a.m. I drove at once to King's Cross where I caught the 11.20 a.m. express. At Darlington I was met by Ella and the car.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Among the letters awaiting me was one from the Archbishop of York asking my counsel as to our course of action in the Assembly which meets in a week's time. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is evident that a serious effort will be made to amend the book in a Protestant direction, &amp; that it will probably succeed. In that event, I incline to think that the measure ought to be withdrawn</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Headmaster of Westminster writes to ask me to confirm the boys of his school. The Warden of New College invites me to preach to his undergraduates. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Lunn</hi><hi> begs me to write an article on "Bunyan" for 'The Review of the Churches'. It is well enough, but the frittering away of one's time &amp; energy on these 'side&#8211;shows' tends to lower the quality of one's proper work.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
