<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Would it be worthwhile to write a small book on the situation which the untoward vote of December 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> has created? Such topics as the following might be relevant:–</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>1. The Via Media, what it has come to mean.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>2. The 'No Popery' cry.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>3. Erastianism, Erastus &amp; Hobbes.</hi><persName xml:id="2150"></persName>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>4. Non–Roman Catholicism.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>5. Reservation.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>6. Transubstantiation.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>7. The Bishops.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>8. The Protestant Religion.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>9. The new factors in the ecclesiastical Situation.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>10. The Anglican Communion.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>11. Modernism.</hi>
         </p>
<p rend="List Paragraph">
<hi>12. Establishment.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I succeeded in completing the sermon for Cambridge, but was unable to rid it of the militant character which at once I approve and regret. My instincts &amp; all the precedents of my life dictate the policy of conciliation and compromise, but the world has changed so wonderfully, &amp; the outlook, political &amp; economical, has become so doubtful and menacing, that I feel we have reached the point of 'clearing the deck for action'.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Hodgson</hi><hi> came to lunch, &amp; afterwards walked with me round the Park. We were joined by old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi><hi>. He expressed himself rather strongly in condemnation of the 'conversations' at Malines, of which the report has a prominent place in this morning's newspapers. I was interested by his opinions which are probably those of the main body of good lay Churchmen. That foolish business at Malines, into which the Archbishop was drawn by Lord Halifax against (as I feel sure) his own better judgement, cannot but have the effect of increasing suspicion, and strengthening the opposition to the Revised Prayer Book. It is astonishing to observe the lengths to which the Anglican representatives at Malines were induced to go in their eagerness to propitiate the Papists. Frere, Gore, Kidd, Armitage Robinson, &amp; Halifax are hardly average specimens of Anglican clergymen. They are all advanced Anglo–Catholicks.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I "cockered up" a sermon for use in Trinity, where I foolishly promised to preach on January 29</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. Thus I shall wear out my voice before the sermon to the University in the afternoon, which alone is important.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
