<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I finished the 'Preface', and decided to include in the volume divers articles which have already seen the light as well as the Cambridge Sermon, the whole sufficing to make up a small volume. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi><hi> proposing that they should publish the said volume forthwith, and also to the Editor of '</hi><hi rend="underline">The Nineteenth Century &amp; After'</hi><hi> asking permission to use the article headed '</hi><hi rend="underline">The passing of National Churches'</hi><hi> which was originally composed as a Lecture, &amp; then made into an article in that Journal.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon I motored to Durham, and attended a meeting of the small executive Committee for the Durham Castle preservation Fund. I said that I would myself subscribe &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">500.00</hi><hi>, which is vastly more than I can afford. Lord Durham did not appear, pleading illness, but he sent the gratifying information that His Majesty had contributed &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">100.00</hi><hi>: and the Queen &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">50.00</hi><hi>. This is important.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I returned to Auckland. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Linnell</hi><hi> and his wife arrived to stay the night. I had some talk with him about his own situation. he evidently chafes under the incessant polemic of his incumbent, who had the '</hi><hi rend="underline">No Popery'</hi><hi> craze on the brain.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
