<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lionel and I left the Castle at 10 a.m., and motored to Newcastle. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I attended a scantily attended meeting of the Chamber of Commerce in the Exchange. Sir Arthur Sutherland presided, and I addressed the members on the Durham Castle Appeal.</hi><hi rend="italic"> After the meeting M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Shaw showed me over the building which is extremely interesting. The Board Room of the Merchant Adventurers' Company, which received its Charter from Queen Elizabeth contains a noble fire&#8211;place elaborately carved by Grinling Gibbons. Sir Thomas Oliver showed me the Trinity House with a fascinating little Chapel. This Corporation dating from Henry VIII, has control of buoys &amp; pilots from Whitby to Holy Island. Sir A. Sutherland showed me his office </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">which was a 17</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> century house, from which Lord Eldon eloped with his bride!</hi><hi rend="italic"> He entertained me, &amp; a company to lunch in the Club. The Lord Mayor was there, and I catechized him about the Appeal for the Miners. He told me that it originated in London, &amp; apparently the Lord Mayor of London was moved to action by a suggestion from the Queen and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Baldwin. Anyway, it is a foolish business.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Sir Arthur told me that he would contribute &#x00A3;500, little enough if he be as wealthy as he is said to be! After lunch I rejoined Lionel and the Car. We motored to Hetton&#8211;le&#8211;Hole, where I confirmed 83 persons. Then we proceeded to Sunderland, where I had tea with Canon &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Cullagh, and rested for an hour. Then I went to the Infirmary, and confirmed a paralyzed man in his bed. After this, I returned to Christ Church, and confirmed 97 persons, among whom was a town&#8211;councillor &amp; his wife. Wynne&#8211;Willson brought his candidates there, &amp; with them came Noel Gwilliam, &amp; ^[word missing]^. The last presented 3 candidates from his district. He certainly ought to have presented more, but he is a poor lethargic creature. After the service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The doubling of the electric light charges appears to be general, &amp; to have evoked general complaints. The urban district council is reported to be addressing inquiries to the Electrical Supply Association, but there seems to be no suggestion of any remedy if the charge is thus arbitrarily raised. </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
