<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Ten years ago I was consecrated as Bishop of Hereford in Westminster Abbey. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The recantation of the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Edmundsbury and Ipswich is announced in this morning's papers</hi><hi rend="italic">. He now ranges himself openly with the H. of Commons.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burkitt </hi><hi rend="italic">writes me a rather aggressive letter enclosing a communication he had received ascribing the reference to Disestablishment as arising from "pique". I wrote to him a mild reply, though indeed I think his article in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Cambridge Review</hi><hi rend="italic"> was a base performance.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi rend="italic"> and I walked round the Park in the rain, and then I had an interview with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Richardson,</hi><hi rend="italic"> the assistant Curate of S. Cuthbert's, Darlington. He is 'wearying' to get away from that parish though he has been there little more than six months. He complains that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">his Vicar is for ever denouncing the Revised Prayer Book; that he (the Vicar) urged the congregation to sign a petition against it; and that he resented his (the Curate's) refusing to sign with the rest. Certainly these Protestants are a fanatical crew, and their Victory in the House of Commons has puffed them up wonderfully.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
