<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">No man can serve two masters</hi><hi>" i.e. no man (or institution) can order life permanently on conflicting principles. A church which owns a double allegiance, can only hold on its course when the two authorities to which it yields accord, or, at least, don't come into opposition: but when the agreement ceases, &amp; the battle is joined, the Church is brought up sharply to the alternatives, Caesar or God, Mammon or God. In coming to the unavoidable decision the Church may not urge that to assent to God's right against Caesar's claim will hamper, even prohibit, some desirable activities in God's Cause: for, indeed, to carry on God's work under the condition of surrendering God's right is to join that woeful company of professors whose whole pompous parade of various &amp; successful religious effort is summed up shortly by the Divine Lord, in whose name it was all undertaken, as just '</hi><hi rend="underline">working iniquity'</hi><hi>. The claim of the Church of England, uttering its mind through such instruments of corporate expression as it possesses here and now, is a very inadequate embodiment of God's Right against Caesar's; and yet?</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I spent the day at the Committee, where we heard the evidence of Scottish witnesses. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Macpherson from Edinburgh, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Smith from Glasgow impressed me well. On the whole, my mind tends to the conclusion that the existing system works sufficiently well, and needs no substantial change. Even if it were otherwise, prostitution in the streets is diminishing so rapidly that it is hardly worth while to improve the machinery of the law which has to deal with it.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I dined in the Club, wrote to Ella, and read through a little book on Holy Communion by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Armitage Robinson</hi><hi>. He has travelled far from the rather extreme Evangelicalism in which he was bred. Yet he retains something of the old Evangelical unction; and it is odd to think of him as one of the five Anglicans who 'flirted with the scarlet woman' at Malines.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I had some talk with Lord Sumner in the Club, but (by tacit agreement) we avoided the vexed question of the P. B.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Revised Prayer Book represents a delicately adjusted compromise between the various sections of the Church of England. This indeed is its principal merit, for the Church of England cannot afford to lose from its membership any one of them, though to reconcile them all to a single system is to give complete satisfaction to none. But this character of a balanced compromise implies extreme controversial disadvantage. The thorough going representatives of Modernism, Protestantism, and Anglo–Catholicism have an easy task when they attack the Revised Book, which is so apparently incoherent &amp; halts so painfully in its logic. Of these partisans only one has an extensive following in the non–Anglican public, for Protestantism has behind it the strength &amp; prestige of aa patriotic tradition. The Modernist is suspect: the Anglo–Catholic disliked: but Protestantism, in this respect like Charity, covers a multitude of sins. Nonconformity is Protestant to the backbone: and 'corybantic Christianity' adds a certain fervour to its unarguing Fundamentalism. Thus Protestantism is strong </hi><hi rend="bold">[90] </hi><hi>in the constituencies, &amp; vocal in the House of Commons. The principal attack is directed against the alternative Order of Holy Communion and Reservation, that is, against precisely those parts of the Revised Books which are welcomed by Anglo–Catholics. Unless the Bishops are willing to accept a partisan character, they cannot possibly consent to abandon the compromise–character of the Book. Thus a rift has opened between the Church of England and the general sentiment of the Nation, and it may even engulf the Establishment itself. While the popular notion of Revision, which found such vehement expression in the House of Commons, never went beyond 'a short and easy way' with "Ritualists", the Church of England has all along aimed at making its formularies &amp; ceremonial as genuinely Catholic as an unfaltering allegiance to its constitutive principles would permit. Catholic, I say, not in the pinched meaning which the hyphenated claimants of the famous name advocate, but in the generous amplitude </hi><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi><hi> with which the [Lambeth Conference charged it] [struck through] ^Prayer Book uses it, and^ which the Lambeth Conference has affirmed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">A telegram from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hodder &amp; Stoughton</hi><hi rend="italic"> replies to my proposal of a small book on the Crisis:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Most readily agree your proposal please forward manuscript today.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic underline">This means that the 'die is cast'. and any decision to abandon the Establishment becomes definitive</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is a formidable step to take, and will immerse me in fresh odium. All the influences that make for compromise, and even for surrender are coming into play, secretly encouraged by old Cantuar: who cannot bring himself at this late hour to abandon the accommodating habit of a life–time. Then great prominence is being given to the Dean of Westminster's 'discovery' that Disestablishment would only mean a dispersed bondage, unless the Disestablished church renounced all the endowments, &amp; consented to purchase freedom at the heavy cost of Apostolic poverty. The women will have something to say on that!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
