<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>A still, dull morning with mild temperature and a cloud wrapped sky. The birds sing but without the enthusiasm, born of sunlight, which distinguishes their singing on a fine day.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 7 communicants.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lione</hi><hi>l and I motored to Southwick, where I preached to a large congregation which included the mayor &amp; Corporation of Sunderland, &amp; both the local M.P.s. The inclusion of Southwick within the Borough of Sunderland takes place today, &amp; the Mayor desired to inaugurate the new stage of municipal history by an act of religion. This pious aspiration accorded altogether with my own views. Therefore, when he asked me to preach, I made no objection. The service was reverent &amp; appropriate. An enterprising photographer took a picture of the Mayor &amp; me afterwards. We returned to Auckland immediately.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>In the afternoon I confirmed 149 persons in South Church, among them was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi>'s sister.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The weather, which began with dullness, became rainy as the day advanced; effectively destroying the impressiveness of the Mayor's procession in Sunderland, &amp; the comfort of the female candidates in Bishop Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
