<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
<p><hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> publishes an article on Durham Castle by Hamilton Thompson.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We all, except Fearne, motored to Durham. There I licenced five clergy, and lunched in the Castle. Then we motored to Newcastle, picking up Lord Scarbrough at Lumley on the way. The Mayor's chamber was comfortably filled for the </hi><hi rend="underline">Durham Castle Meeting</hi><hi>. The Lord Mayor presided. The Duke of Northumberland and I were the orators: Sir Thomas Oliver &amp; Prof. Heewood expounded procedure. I announced the contribution of &#x00A3;5000 by the Eccles: Com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m </hi><hi>&amp; the announcement was better received than it deserved. I also read out Lord Londonderry's letter announcing a subscription of &#x00A3;500. After having tea with the ladies at the Railway Hotel, we motored to Sunderland. After calling at Bishopwearmouth Rectory, we went to Venerable Bede Vicarage. The Vicar took us to the dwelling of a poor man, whom I confirmed in his bed. Then I confirmed 98 persons in the Church. Hawke presented 6 candidates from Monkwearmouth, a parishing containing more than 9000 people! He seemed to attribute the absence of confirmation candidates to the slackness of his predecessor, but I find this explanation difficult to understand.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
