<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The numbers of the voting in the House of Clergy were, For the General Approval 247, against 35. The House of Laity not having completed its debate the Assembly was unable to meet before the afternoon. I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; had a long talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bell</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the Dean of Canterbury</hi><hi rend="italic">, who seems to take a very sensible view of the situation. Then I went back to the Deanery for lunch, after which I attended the meeting of the Church Assembly. The numbers of the voting in the House of Laity were announced by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Selborne</hi><hi rend="italic">. For, 196: against, 80. So far, so good: but the real fight comes at the Revision stage &amp; to judge by the notices of amendments, it will be lengthy. I sate for an hour &amp; a half in the Assembly listening to the worst bores in its membership, and then went over to the House of Lords, and listened to three admirable eulogies on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Earl Haig</hi><hi rend="italic">, pronounced by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Salisbury</hi><hi rend="italic">, as Leader of the House, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lords Haldane</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Beauchamp</hi><hi rend="italic"> as leaders of the two opposition parties. Then I had tea with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Exeter</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; his son Victor, &amp; returned to the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[109] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Ernle</hi><hi rend="italic">, (</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">formerly R. E. Prothero</hi><hi rend="italic">) had some talk with me in the Athenaeum about the ecclesiastical situation. He was a member of the Ecclesiastical Committee, &amp; had observed with wonder the quantity &amp; squalor of the literature with which he and his colleagues had been overwhelmed by the opponents of the Revised Book. Practically no literature came from the other side. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">He hoped the Bishops would keep a stiff back: &amp; thought that if they did, the House of Commons would not reject the Book again. "I had been astonished that no attention has been directed to one feature of the Revised Book, which seems to me both very important and very surprising, I mean, its literary excellence. I examined the book with considerable trepidation on this point, but my anxiety quickly gave place to admiration</hi><hi rend="italic">". In view of Lord Ernle's recognized distinction as a man of letters, this unsolicited testimonial to the Revised Book is worth recording. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But the Dervishes of the House of Commons care nothing for literary excellence!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[110]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">While talking with Bell in the Athenaeum, I contracted a chill. The club, after so long disuse, is damp and the smell of new paint is murderous. Nevertheless, I dined at Grillions, where the</hi><hi rend="italic"> company was composed of the following: –</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi>
         </p>
<p> 
<hi rend="italic">" " York</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Bishop of Durham</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lord Sumner</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Lytton</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" Dawson</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"Crawford and Balcarres</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Sir George Murray</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Edmund Gorse</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The Editor of the Times</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">" " " Punch</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lord Eustace Percy</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I came away early as I felt ill: but I had some interesting talk with Geoffrey &amp; Eustace Percy. I really think the latter is a good fellow. He said that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the really impressive character of American Society was its godlessness</hi><hi rend="italic">. He has some (real) knowledge of America.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
