<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The snow vanished almost completely during the night: &amp; the wind &amp; rain of the day finished it.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I consecrated an addition to the churchyard at Coundon in the afternoon. The weather was villainous, and in spite of driving rain we circumambulated the ground accompanied by a considerable company of boy&#8211;scouts and girl guides, organized by the zeal of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Hedley. I went to the schoolroom, and spoke to the people about the importance of keeping glass&#8211;globes out of the churchyard.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I motored to Newcastle in order to broadcast the appeal for Durham Castle. The allusions to the German shells etc. were cut out by the B.B.C. critic, rather to my disgust.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archbishop of York</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"I communicated your views about a doctrinal declaration to the House of Bishops, and you will be relieved to hear that after a long &amp; rather difficult discussion we decided that we could not undertake the responsibility of any such declaration."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This relieves my mind of a considerable anxiety. I wish more than ever that the Bishops had not agreed to introduce a declaration on Fasting.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
