<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Still more snow. There are considerable drifts, and motoring is uncomfortable.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Londonderry</hi><hi> writes to say that he will contribute £500 to the Castle fund! Now did you </hi><hi rend="underline">ever</hi><hi>! I would have thought pride, if not public spirit, would have carried him to four figures!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lionel and I motored to Durham, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">where I entertained the Editors of the local Press at lunch</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sir Thomas Oliver, Ellershaw, Macfarlane Grieve, James the Architect, < &amp; Lionel together with 13 editors made a party (with myself) of 19. After lunch James expounded the case for the Castle. I hope the press–men were usefully impressed. Among them was Bex, formerly Editor of the Hereford Times, and now editor of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Herald</hi><hi rend="italic"> – a dingy Anglo–Catholic! After this function, we motored to Jarrow, where I had</hi><hi> tea with the Rector of Jarrow Grange (Williams), and there confirmed in his Church 88 candidates. The roads were heavily encumbered by snow, but we travelled without accident, and with at a fair speed, getting back to Auckland Castle about 9.40 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The publishers send me a book by James Raven entitled, "Women and Holy Orders. A plea to the Church of England".</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
