<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 18 communicants, but there were several absentees, – Ashton, Harry Leng, Harold Bryden, and George Laws. Work may perhaps explain Harry's absence but not the absence of the others. Lionel was taking the celebration at Etherley, where the Vicar nears his end.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After breakfast I motored to Sunderland, where I preached &amp; celebrated in Bishopwearmouth Church, and afterwards lunched at the Rectory. I returned to Durham in time to attend Evensong in the Cathedral. After the service I had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lillington</hi><hi> and his two boys. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie</hi><hi> attained his majority last week. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><hi> joined me at tea, &amp; we all returned to Auckland afterwards.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cunningham</hi><hi><persName xml:id="5607"></persName> of Westcott House, trying to disabuse him of the notion that the projected Mission of Undergraduates in Sunderland was declined by the clergy because of its inter–denominational character. I pointed out that the reason given to me was the fact that Missions have been held in the Sunderland Parishes during the last 2 years, &amp; that another Mission was undesirable so soon.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[205] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Anonymous letters, of which I receive many, are almost always abusive &amp; scurrilous: but there are exceptions, an example of which is the following which reached me a few weeks ago, &amp; which merits a better fate than the w.p.b.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">My Lord,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I write to thank you from the bottom of my heart for all that you are doing and have done for the Church of England in days which are bringing such perplexity to all in or under authority.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I do so partly out of sheer gratitude: partly for conscience sake. I confess that ten years ago I felt you stood for very much that I disliked. I hated your opposition to 'Life and Liberty', and I think I rather hated you! I still thank God for 'Life &amp; Liberty', but I can also thank Him for your leadership, courage, scholarship, &amp; above all your devotion to the Church of England as a spiritual Society.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Your 'Book &amp; the Vote', your correspondence in the Times on "continuity", &amp; much else, make me thank God &amp; take courage.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[206] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Lest this letter appear to have an interested purpose, you will forgive me if I do not sign my name. I have been a silent and humble member of the Assembly from its beginning.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This letter has an honest sound: &amp; it may be representative of others who joined in the violent denunciations of the Bishop designate of Hereford.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to MacMunn inviting him to give the two addresses on Pastoral work which it is usual to include in the "retreat" which the candidates are required to traverse before their Ordination. He is a pronounced "Anglo–Catholic", but not, if report be trustworthy, an extreme example of the type. He is certainly well–regarded by his brethren, &amp; appears to be a good enough person of the conventional sort.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Kenneth was to have come to dinner, but he failed to appear. I </hi><hi rend="italic underline">hope</hi><hi rend="italic"> he will be able to offer me some reasonable explanation, but such careless treatment of the Bishop requires explaining. We have come to such a state of social anarchy, that one may not safely resent any neglect or discourtesy.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
