<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I decided to address the Diocesan Conference on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Raven's</hi><hi> plea for a Female Ministry.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The whole morning was wasted in writing an article on </hi><hi rend="underline">'King &amp; Count Palatine'</hi><hi> for the Evening Standard. It occurred to me that an account of the Palatinate would assist to keep the appeal for the Castle before the public mind.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I walked in the Park. The snow was thawing at a great pace: the Gaunless &amp; its tributaries were in spate, &amp; everything was dripping.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We motored to Dawdon, where I confirmed 130 persons. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Duncan</hi><hi>'s churchmanship is steadily rising: the aspect of the church was quite markedly ''Anglo&#8211;Catholick'', and the congregation was quite markedly of the 'weaker sex'! The quaint little curate, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cross</hi><hi>, who looks like a shy and undersized lad of 18, assured me that he was happy, active, and loved the people. So far, so good. It is a fortunate thing for some of us that '</hi><hi rend="underline">'the Lord looketh not at the outward appearance</hi><hi>'', for if He did, we should stand a poor chance of being accepted!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>After the service we returned to Auckland in a high wind. The snow has vanished from the roads, but there are considerable banks by the road side.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
