<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I finished the Conference Address. My post contained nothing of interest or of importance, which bodes ill for the Durham Castle Fund, but left me free to work.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Kidd</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">' join </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Frere</hi><hi rend="italic">: but </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gore</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Alban's</hi><hi rend="italic"> adhere to the Book, though with scruple &amp; sorrow. Meanwhile all the Protestant associations proclaim their unaltered opposition. I strongly suspect that we have lost the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks without placating anybody!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Barnard Castle, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Governors of the School. We had an amiable but melancholy meeting. The decline of the School continues, &amp; last year there was a deficit of &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="underline">900</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and I motored to Burnmoor, where I confirmed 94 persons in the parish church. They came from the three parishes of Burnmoor, Shiney Row, and Penshaw. I was pleased to notice that the number of males was about equal to that of females. It seems to be evident that the gross dis&#8211;proportion in number between the sexes is almost limited to "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" parishes. There is something in the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" version of Christianity which is distasteful to normal boyhood. Women take to sacramentalism like ducks to water! </hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
