<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
        
<p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, January 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>While I was dressing, the right text for my Cambridge sermon flashed on my mind &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">Shall two walk together except they have agreed?</hi><hi>" Amos iii, 3. That will suggest immediately the subject I am going to handle viz: the sudden discord between Church and State, and so prepare the congregation for the unusual kind of sermon which is to follow.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 11 communicants, including </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi> and the dear </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brydons</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The '</hi><hi rend="underline">Observer</hi><hi>' takes a rather gloomy view of the ecclesiastical situation, which, it sees clearly, threatens to raise the question of Establishment. It seems to think that the Archbishop will make some public answer to the Bishop of Birmingham. I cannot think this likely: in any case the answer could only take fitting form as a rebuke. But I suspect that Cantuar. has 'got the wind up', and is not in the mood to stand on his dignity.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored to Burnopfield, &amp; after having tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wilson</hi><hi>, I went to a house in Tanfield &amp; confirmed a consumptive girl in bed. Then I returned to Burnopfield &amp; preached in the parish church at Evensong. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionell</hi><hi> [sic] read the prayers. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
