<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">A most beautiful day. The Chapel illumined by the brilliant morning sun was wonderful. I spent the morning in preparing sermons. It is 'hand&#8211;to&#8211;mouth' work, and has in abundance all the faults distinctive of that kind of unprincipled labour.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to James Parker Smith thanking him for an excellent letter on the Prayer Book, which is given a prominent place in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Glasgow Herald.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">At 4 p.m. we &#8211; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lionel</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi><hi rend="italic"> and I &#8211; left the castle, &amp; motored to Sunderland, stopping at Durham on the way to enquire after </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Bothamly</hi><hi rend="italic"> who collapsed with heart&#8211;failure rather startlingly while driving his car, and now lies at the County Hospital. We had tea at Bishopwearmouth Rectory, &amp; then went to the Victoria Hall, from which the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">'Procession of Witness</hi><hi rend="italic">' was to start. The procession was limited to men above 18, &amp; was an imposing one. The Mayor &amp; I with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Lillington</hi><hi rend="italic"> (representing the Rural Dean, whose walking powers, [thanks to arthritis, were inadequate for so long a walk,) &amp; a se??bly little sectary who is President of the Free Church Council, led the precession. On returning to the Victoria Hall, there was a service, at which I preached. After this we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[201] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">What do I really think about this Procession of Witness?</hi><hi rend="italic"> It was impossible not to be impressed by the spectacle of such a company of men traversing the streets singing hymns: &amp;, indeed, the multitudes that lined the route were evidently impressed. The composition of the procession was certainly significant. That the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Salvation Army Band</hi><hi rend="italic"> should have led the procession, and that the Bishop &amp; Mayor with the representative of Nonconformity &amp; the Member of Parliament should have headed the long succession of surpliced Choirmen &amp; boys, &amp; been followed by perhaps 1500 men, was notable &amp; suggestive. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Per contra</hi><hi rend="italic">, the procession has established itself as pleasing to the townsfolk, for whom it provides a welcome relief to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">tedium</hi><hi rend="italic"> of a holiday. The advertising motive will probably compete with the religious in bringing "leading citizens" into willing cooperation. I did not like the introduction of sentimental anthems sung by the Sunderland orchestra into the service which followed the procession: &amp; the extemporaneous prayer by a local [sectary] was what such an effusion would naturally be. Still, when all these considerations are weighed, there remains enough to make one thankful.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
