<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I had a comfortless night, &amp; felt miserable. Nevertheless, I resisted the kind urgency of mine hostess, and returned to Auckland by the corridor express. </hi><hi rend="italic">The engine broke down outside Doncaster, &amp; delayed the train 45 minutes. On arriving at the Castle, I retired to bed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">On the way I read through the proof of the little book which is immediately to be published by Hodder &amp; Stoughton. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Book and the Vote</hi><hi rend="italic">". The worst of all proof–readers is the Author, for his intimate familiarity with the text leads him to pass over the little errors which it is the proof–reader's duty to detect. If the course of events in the Assembly is adverse, and the Revised Prayer Book is ship–wrecked by Anglican hands, the result will certainly be a great perversion of the popular judgement. The House of Commons will be generally presented as having proved itself a better exponent of the Church's mind than the Bishops &amp; Clergy, though, of course, the true inference from </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the facts would be that the House of Laity prefers Establishment to Spiritual Independence</hi><hi rend="italic">. In any case, my poor little book will have a forlorn and superannuated aspect!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
