<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Almighty God, by whose appointment the children of men dwell together in order &amp; fellowship, look down with mercy upon this great community of Sunderland, &amp; prosper all who labour therin to set up on earth thy kingdom of righteousness &amp; love. Give wisdom to the Mayor and Corporation, &amp; to all who are called to bear office in this place, that they may fulfil their several tasks with courage &amp; faithfulness to thy glory &amp; the welfare of thy people. Pour out on all the citizens the spirit of brotherly goodwill, that they may bear one another's burdens, &amp; so fulfil the law of Christ. Strengthen in them habits of industry, temperance, &amp; pureness of living. Let thine especial blessing rest on all schools for the training of the young, &amp; on all places set apart for the comfort of the afflicted &amp; the relief of the sick. Be with us in all our undertakings for the common good, &amp; make us to be of one heart and one mind in thy service. Grant these our petitions, we beseech thee, for the sake of thy Blessed Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Amen</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>At the Vicar's request I wrote this prayer for use at the special service on April 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>, when the Mayor and</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Corporation attend Divine Service in Southwick Church in order, as the Mayor says, to start the enlarged city with God's Blessing. Sunderland is absorbing Southwick. On the whole these people mean well, so I undertook to preach to them.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The papers give much prominence to Durham Castle. Both the Times and the Yorkshire Post have leaders &amp; photographs. Unfortunately the first contained no mention of the fact that their Majesties had contributed to the Fund. This was entirely due to the fussy meddlesomeness of 'Pussy&#8211;cat' &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi><hi>. who must needs abbreviate the précis I sent them.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I walked in the Park. The snow was melting, and the streams consequently in spate. We motored to Sunderland, where I confirm 50 persons in S. Mary Magdalene's Church. Before the service I confirmed 2 men privately, the one in his room in a horrible dark slum: the others in the Infirmary.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I was taken to a gathering of small children, &amp; gave them a brief address. "Father" Wright is my most pronounced "Anglo&#8211;Catholic": but it is impossible not to like the fellow, &amp; to admire the order in which he keeps his slum dwellers.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
