<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[137]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>When Bishop Lightfoot's predecessor died, the Dean &amp; Chapter treated the Archbishop's inhibition as so much waste paper, &amp; they are preparing to do ^the same^ now. So strained, indeed, are the relations between York &amp; Durham that the Archbishop did not go to Durham Cathedral on Friday, but waited at Bishop Auckland, where he officiated. The Dean of Durham, on his part, did not go to Bishop Auckland, the members of the Chapter attending as individuals, &amp; not in their official capacity.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>v. </hi><hi rend="underline">Daily Telegraph</hi><hi> in connexion with its account of Bishop Lightfoot's Funeral.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>From the Christian point of view, which of the parties ought to have yielded? The actual importance of the point at issue, (whether the Archbishop of York, or the Dean &amp; Chapter of Durham were guardians of the see during a vacancy,) was petty enough, a matter for the antiquaries to talk about: but some aroma of pre–eminence attached to it, &amp; hence the resolute determination which both parties displayed even by the graveside of one whom both desired to honour!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella went with me into Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the Committee of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Catherine's House. Then we went to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Giles's Church, where I baptized Jane Braley, the infant daughter of the Principal of Bede College.<persName xml:id="5464"></persName> After the service we went to the College and had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Braley. The staff were there, &amp; were presented to me. I was impressed by their comparative youth. Evidently, the Principal has achieved his purpose of making "a clean sweep" of the old lot, &amp; substituting men more to his own mind. He has secured the enlargement &amp; renovation of the College itself. Evidently he is a man of energy, ideas, &amp; persistence.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I went to Winlaton, where I confirmed 187 persons in the parish church. Old Canon Jones seems to have renewed his youth. 22 boys were presented from some Industrial School in the district. The Headmaster is also a churchwarden. I was well impressed by the wholesome aspect, and quite natural piety of these boys. They compared well in these respects with the other candidates.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We returned to Auckland Castle by way of Newcastle, &amp; arrived there at 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
