<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Guillaume</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Shebbeare</hi><hi rend="italic"> send me a combined request that I will allow them to move a resolution at the Diocesan Conference, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">urging the unwisdom of presenting the re&#8211;revised Prayer Book to the House of Commons this year!</hi><hi rend="italic"> Now did you ever? I returned a polite but decisive refusal. The merest whisper of possible Disendowment strikes terror into most Anglican bosoms, &amp; brings the whole fabric of ecclesiastical theory down with a rush! This is hardly an age of martyrs.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><hi> came to lunch, &amp; walked with me in the Park. On returning to the Castle, I confirmed M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi>Low, two South Africans, who shewed kindness to William &amp; Frank, when first they came to Johannesburg. They desired to receive Confirmation in order that they might receive the Holy Communion with their boy, now at Dover College, who is to be confirmed immediately. This intermingling of natural affection and religious motive cannot be displeasing to the Author of both.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The fanatical papers now pouring from the Protestant party make great play with an assumed connexion between the 'conversations' at Malines and the re&#8211;revised Prayer Book.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[178] </hi><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I motored to Gateshead, where I confirmed 162 persons in S. Chad's Church. This is the Anglo&#8211;Catholick citadel of Gateshead, and there was abundant evidence of the fact. Nevertheless, it was a good service, &amp; I was pleased. The young men clothed in red with cottas, who carried lighted candles, were less supercilious &amp; patronising than is usual with their kind. I noticed that the Sacrament was reserved in a Chapel, &amp; was told by the Vicar (Elwood) that it had been so reserved for 20 years. He told me that his morning congregation was larger than in the evening. No doubt, he has succeeded in bringing the people to accept the Roman practice. They regard attendance at "Mass" as obligatory: but, when they have fulfilled that obligation, they are free to take their pleasure.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">There are indications in this morning's papers that Frere's defection will have considerable effect on the whole Anglo&#8211;Catholick, which has been induced to accept the Revised Prayer Book mainly by his influence. It is an ill outlook.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
