<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Ash Wednesday, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p>["]<hi>Self–denial was the law of his life, yet the word never crossed his lips. He revelled in doing kindness, never more than when the recipient was a little child, or an overworked school–mistress, or a struggling author. He taxed his ingenuity to find words of encouragement and praise for the most immature &amp; unpromising efforts. He was even passionately loyal to old association, and to have helped or cared for those who were dear to him was a sure passport to his affection. The magnificent serenity of his demeanour concealed from the outside world, but never from his friends, his boyish appreciation of kindness, of admiration, of courteous attention.</hi>["]
         </p>
<p><hi>George Russell on Matthew Arnold v. Prefatory note to "Letters of M. A.".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>This is not the conception of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Matthew Arnold</hi><hi> which is generally received, but it may be true none the less. We are impenetrable secrets all of us, and only our Maker knows the whole truth about us. To Him alone, '</hi><hi rend="underline">We are naked and laid open'</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[134]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 11 communicants including </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Smith</hi><hi> and John.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Various acknowledgements of early copies of "The Book of the Vote" informed me that it had actually been published.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel and I walked round the park, &amp; 'looked in' on the Football and Hockey matches which were in progress there.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then we motored to Norton, where I instituted the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Maurice Woolley to the Vicarage of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Michael &amp; All Angels. There was a large congregation. After the service we dined with old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Kirk, with whom was his son–in–law Nigel Harrison, &amp; J. G. Wilson. </hi><hi rend="italic">I took occasion to hold forth on the claim of Durham Castle, hinting with brutal obviousness that M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Kirk might himself do something considerable! The old gentleman invited me to come apart in order that he might suggest that I should appoint M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Purvis, the Vicar of Holy Trinity, to succeed Douglas at the Parish Church. But I told him that is was my settled rule never to appoint 'from one side of the street to the other'</hi><hi>. We returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
