<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[147]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday. March 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The '</hi><hi rend="underline">Church Family Newspaper</hi><hi>' has a leader by Ralph headed "</hi><hi rend="underline">Quantam matatus!" The Bishop of Durham's Volte face</hi><hi>." Its personal references to me are expressed in a kindly fashion, but it accuses me of an "apparently total </hi><hi rend="underline">volte face</hi><hi>' in the sphere of my '</hi><hi rend="underline">deepest convictions</hi><hi>'.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The substance of the article is a series of extracts from my books, exhibited in what purport to be contrasts. They do not seem to me particularly well&#8211;chosen for their purpose, and are all easily capable of reconciliation, but I doubt not that they will suffice for their purpose with the public to whom they are addressed. </hi><hi rend="underline">The Editor of the C.of E.N. wrote to offer me the front page for a reply: &amp; I wasted the morning in writing something</hi><hi>. I am sorry </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi> allowed his prejudices so completely to submerge his friendship as to make a public onslaught on me: but what would one have? The by&#8211;products of religious controversy are often very disagreeable, &amp; even extremely painful.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Blaydon, where I confirmed 78 persons. On the way, I called at Lambton, &amp; saw Lord Durham, who has been ill. There was much fog at intervals, which made us 10 minutes late at Blaydon. We arrived back at the Castle at 9.50 p.m.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
