<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> February, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I received from Ralph the following brief note:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My dear Herbert,</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Upward wanted me to write on your new book. The result would only be a deep groan. But I cannot help it, and must hope to be forgiven.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Yours ever</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>W. R. Inge</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The worst effect of these accursed religious controversies is their destruction of personal friendship. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ralph</hi><hi rend="italic"> is terribly remote from the facts of ecclesiastical life: his deafness isolates him: &amp; the adoring crew which acclaims him is barely Christian. His brilliance &amp; versatility make him the prince of journalists: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">he is exchanging the respect of his equals for the clamourous homage of his inferiors</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The Editor of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Ninteenth Century and After</hi><hi>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Carrol Romer</hi><hi>, has been moved by my </hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> letter – which he says is 'perfectly splendid' – to write to me at length. He is apparently immersed in a libel action with the Papists, whom he has criticised in his journal with imprudent candour. "Look at America where </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Theodore Dreiser</hi><hi> tells me that he believes it (i.e. the Roman propaganda) will cause civil war within 20 years".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I motored with Lionel to Newcastle. There I attended a meeting of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Riddell Trustees</hi><hi>. We chose </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Professor Eddington</hi><hi> to give the first course of lectures on their foundation. Then I attended a meeting of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Durham Castle Preservation Fund</hi><hi>. My suggestion of a ^lunch^ to the Editors of the local press in order to expound the situation of Durham Castle was welcomed.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Then I went to </hi><hi rend="underline">Gateshead Rectory</hi><hi>, &amp; had tea. Lionel rejoined me, &amp; we motored to </hi><hi rend="underline">Whickham</hi><hi>, where I confirmed 96 persons in the parish church. Among them was the Rector's daughter. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>On our way home we called at Gateshead Rectory in order that I might see </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephenson</hi><hi>, who had been absent during the afternoon. I told him of the distressing situation which had developed in Bishopwearmouth: &amp; he undertook with the utmost willingness to get into communication with Wynne–Willson &amp; offer to lend him the services of one of his colleagues. He really is a thoroughly good fellow.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">John M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitterick</hi><hi> sent me a telegram telling me of his father's death. I fear that the wife and family are very ill provided for.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
