<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The great secret I out, &amp; the world knows now what are the concessions which the Bishops feel free to make to the House of Commons. They certainly do not amount to much, and if the majority in the Commons desire to quarrel, they do not lack occasion. Nor will they be without episcopal encouragement, for the Bishop of Birmingham has a truculently worded commentary on the proposals of his brethren. He is certainly a difficult problem to solve, for he doesn't observe the ordinary conventions. Thus he allows himself to make disclosures of our proceedings in secret session, apparently concluding that because he objects to the secresy [sic] he is free to violate it! He seems to recognize no obligation to the Episcopate of the Church, but carries himself with the reckless freedom of a private adventurer. The '</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>' refers to him with some severity, implying that his objection to meeting in private is that the is thus hindered from being known openly! It notes with censure his ill conduct in revealing secrets. But, of course, the worse he behaves, the more he will endear himself to the "army of illiterates" which he (without the excuse of being an 'octogenarian') is apparently eager to 'general'.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
