<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>We left the Castle at 9.45 a.m., and arrived at Broncroft at 8.15 p.m., having travelled 237 miles. We came by way of Wetherby, Doncaster, Derby, Uttoxeter, and Bridgnorth, and stopped for luncheon at Doncaster, and for tea at Uttoxeter. In the later stage of the journey we lost time by frequent inquiries as to our route, but even so we travelled at an average rate of something over 26 miles in the hour. The car, in spite of its damaged condition, gave us no trouble. The weather was fine until 4.30 p.m., when it became wet. We ended our journey in rain &amp; mist.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Broncroft Castle is situated in the depths of the country, and is not very easy to find. It has a considerable historical interest. The older part dates from the 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century, and latest from the 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. It seems to have been possessed by a succession of interesting families, mostly connected with the law. Of these the most famous was the Littleton who wrote the book on Tenures. The place was held as a fortress during the Civil War: but there is no moat, and it is not large enough to hold any considerable garrison. Frank &amp; his wife have adapted it with skill and taste to the aspect &amp; uses of a country mansion.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
