<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, Sunday, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">This beautiful collect for '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">that most excellent gift of charity the very bond of peace and of all virtues</hi><hi rend="italic">' was composed in the XVI</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> century, presumably by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cranmer</hi><hi rend="italic">. It utters the longing of genuine disciples in an age which had forgotten the meaning of discipleship. Of all the praises bestowed on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Oxford</hi><hi rend="italic"> perhaps the most sincere was that which dwelt on '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">his genius for forgiveness</hi><hi rend="italic">': and yet it is difficult not to connect this with his placable complaisant disposition, which was rather a natural endowment than a virtue. And, indeed, it is apparent that character, as seen and appraised in human intercourse, is very largely temperamental, and to that extent not reasonably either praised or blamed. The charity for which the Collect prays, &amp; concerning which it declares that God has '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">taught all our doings without it are nothing worth</hi><hi rend="italic">' must be much more than such an endowment of nature. S. Paul's description of Charity includes much (e. g. '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rejoiceth not in iniquity but rejoiceth in the truth</hi><hi rend="italic">.') which is hard to reconcile with the easy&#8211;going unresentful temper which is the gift of nature. Zeal enters into the picture as well as meekness. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cranmer</hi><hi rend="italic"> too was a martyr in the end.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>If it were done when 'tis done, then 'twere well<lb/>If it were done quickly: if the assassination<lb/>Could trammel up the consequence, and catch<lb/>With his surcease success: </hi><hi rend="underline">that but this blow<lb/>Might be the be&#8211;all and the end&#8211;all here,<lb/>But here, upon this bank &amp; shoal of time,<lb/>W'd jump the life to come. But in these cases<lb/>We still have judgement here</hi><hi>: that we but teach<lb/>Bloody instructions, which, being taught, return<lb/>To plague the inventor: </hi><hi rend="underline">this even&#8211;handed justice<lb/>Commends the ingredients of our poison'd chalice<lb/>To our own lips</hi><hi>. </hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>(Macbeth)</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 8 communicants including Peter Richardson, who is week&#8211;ending here. After breakfast I completed the sermon for Pittington, &amp; walked in the Park with Peter. The exquisite fairness of the day and the mildness of the air were most enjoyable.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella &amp; Peter accompanied me to Pittington where I read the lessons &amp; preached at Evensong. Then we dropped Peter at his lodgings, and ourselves returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
