<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Carnegie Simpson</hi><hi rend="italic"> has an article in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">British Weekly</hi><hi rend="italic"> headed "The Anglican Church &amp; Spiritual Freedom, a comment on the Bishop of Durham's Sermon." It is, perhaps, most interesting as an indication of the reluctance of the Nonconformists to raise the issue of Disestablishment. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir James Marchant</hi><hi rend="italic"> writes to ask me whether I intend to answer this article, to which I replied in the negative.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 9 communicants including Lionel, Lady Eden, &amp; John.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I wrote to William, Jack Clayton, and James Parker Smith, and walked round the Park in the afternoon. The sunshine &amp; mild air were delectable.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Lionel &amp; I motored to Etherley for Evensong at 6.15 p.m. Before service I went in to the Rectory, and said prayers with the Rector (Rev. L.S. Merrefield) who has been at death's door with pneumonia, &amp; is still very ill. There was a very small congregation for there are nearly 2000 people in the parish, but there is much sickness and hosts of sectaries! The parish church is a mean building, a barn tacked on to a tower! After service we returned to Auckland.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
