<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> January, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>That very quaint person, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Chesney, whom I have not seen for 30 years, writes to me characteristically recalling the time when he was a choirboy in S. Margaret's, Westminster:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>"It seems so long ago since your last annual party for us boys. Always shall I remember Fatty Reynolds stuffing himself with chocolates, and myself refusing to take off my shoes for the Cockfighting, owning to my socks possessing more darns than the original wool."</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Memories are odd things, and a small boy's memories the oddest of all. He was a very queer, naughty boy, but I never suspected that the reason why he stuck to his boots was to hide the darns!</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Fred Gray writes to introduce herself as the wife of Fred Gray, who was a choir&#8211;boy at Barking when I was Vicar 1888&#8211;1895. She was living in Barking then. She refers with extraordinary affection to those "dear old days". The tenacity of their personal loyalties is a very attractive &amp; impressive quality of humble English folk.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>I also received a very pleasantly worded letter from William.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Arthur Hird</hi><hi rend="italic">, the theological manager of Hodder &amp; Stoughton, came about 4 p.m. and readily agreed in my suggestion that he should stay the night. We had a prolonged talk together, in the course of which he told me a good deal about himself. He was the son of a Lancashire ^artisan^ and was working in a mill when no more than 11 years old. He must have been possessed with uncommon determination and ability, for he was a preacher at 16, a student of theology at 19, and is now quite an important person. He spoke much of the account of the Prime Minister, which he had received from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Oliver Baldwin</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">He ^(O. B.)^ had never known his father have a friend save only </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bonar Law</hi><hi rend="italic">. He never remembered his father ever playing with him ^in his childhood^.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi><hi rend="italic"> He ^(the P. M.)^ would never quite succeed in anything, &amp; so forth.) This is curiously contrary to the impression which the P. M. makes on me.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic bold underline">We talked much of </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Dick Sheppard</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">'s book. He said that 90,000 copies were printed, &amp; 80,000 had already been sold</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Miss Macdonald, who is to be a Rescue Worker in this parish, stayed here. She looks the last conceivable person for that sort of job, but in these demented days anything is possible, &amp; probably she could abash me by her acquaintance with </hi><hi>^[phrase written in Greek]^</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
