<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>^[paragraph strikethrough]^ </hi><hi rend="italic">I remained in bed until the afternoon. Lionel came to my room, &amp; we went through the letters.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The House of Laity appears to have approved perpetual Reservation by a substantial majority, 162 to 108. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Dibdin</hi><hi rend="italic"> made a most mischievous speech in the course of which he said:–</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">"It w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be better that the Measures should break down in the Assembly rather than that they should fail again in Parl</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic">. If there were a second rejection, the consequences c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> hardly fail to be disastrous. He hoped they would support the deletion of the second rubric".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">His defeat in the division is consoling, and may be significant. It will hardly be doubted that whatever course he takes expresses the wish of the Archbishop.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">In the House of Clergy an Amendment ruling out the second rubric moved by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Guy Rogers</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; supported by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon H. A. Wilson</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; the Bishop of Barking was rejected by 108 to 46. This is re–assuring. The Dean of Canterbury (Bell) seems to have made an excellent speech. He also is thought to be the mouthpiece of the Archbishop.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I corrected, and despatched, the proofs of '</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">The Book and the Vote</hi><hi rend="italic">', directing the publishers to send copies to several members of the Cabinet, and to all the Bishops.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank</hi><hi> writes to ask me to preach in the College Chapel on All Souls Day: but I had to refuse, as I cannot kick my heels in the South before the Meeting of the Church Assembly on November 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and have promised to preach in New College Chapel on the 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">The election at Lancaster has resulted in a victory for the Liberal with a very large majority. Lord Ashton's letter repudiating </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi rend="italic"> has had the opposite effect to what the writer intended: for it has given </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi rend="italic"> the opportunity of striking an effective attitude, &amp; securing a resounding triumph. Probably the attempt of a great employer to dictate to his work–people in the matter of their political action was resented by the electors: and the "wizardry" of the little Welshman did the rest. His attempt to rebut the actual charges preferred against him was lame enough: but they counted for nothing. It was the personal duel that mattered.</hi>
         </p>
<p>
            </body></text></TEI>
