<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
<p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1928.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>Ella went with me to Darlington where I took the early train for London, and she went by a later train to Scotland. </hi><hi rend="italic">The newspapers were full of the re&#8211;revised Prayer Book, to which they give a distinctly chilling reception. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Frere</hi><hi rend="italic"> has a correspondence with an Anglo&#8211;Catholic clergyman in his diocese named </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cooper</hi><hi rend="italic">, the gist of which is that he repudiates the book in its latest form, &amp; announces his intention of opposing it in Convocation. This is grave news indeed, for it </hi><hi rend="italic underline">may</hi><hi rend="italic"> indicate a general 'break&#8211;away' of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks, a contingency which might bring about the defeat of the Book in Convocation, or such an increase of the dissentient minority as would strengthen the case for rejection in the House of Commons. The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop of Norwich</hi><hi rend="italic">, of course, announces implacable opposition. Colonel Headlam came into my carriage, &amp; talked gloomily of the parliamentary prospects of the Book.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="italic">I went to the hair&#8211;dresser, &amp; then to 6 William St: Knightsbridge, where for 2 hours I posed to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Belcher</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">who made a 'personality' sketch of me for Punch</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is extraordinary how fatiguing this business of posing can be. However I succeeded in catching the 5.30 p.m. express to Darlington.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>My travelling companion was a young lady with whom I had some interesting conversation. Her name was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mabel Marchbank</hi><hi>, &amp; she lived at Brinkburn, Elmsfield Road, Gosforth. She evidently recognized me, and, though herself a Presbyterian, had heard me preach several times. We dined together, &amp; I promised to send her a copy of "The Book &amp; the Vote".</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Guy Wrightson</hi><hi> came into my carriage to explain that a bereavment had prevented him from attending the meeting about the Castle. He discussed at length &amp; more hopefully than I expected about the economic outlook of Durham.</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>The old 'Scapa' enthusiast Richardson Evans sends &#x00A3;50 to the Preservation Fund, accompanying the cheque with a very civil letter, in which he says:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>'Apart from my interest in this question of Durham, I have a very grateful recollection of many of your sermons in Westminster Abbey, when I was still able to live and move in London.'</hi>
         </p>
<p><hi>It is now more than 15 years since I was Canon of Westminster.</hi>
         </p>

            </body></text></TEI>
