<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Winnipeg</hi>:&#8211; </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wrote to Miss Markham<persName xml:id="1261"></persName>.<note xml:id="538" n="1"></note> I had some conversation with the Abp. of Rupertsland (Mathieson). Of course we got on to the subject of Reunion.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He said that Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> wrecked everything at Lambeth</hi><hi rend="italic">. When he appeared, there was a general rally of the obscurantists, who clustered about him like a swarm of bees.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He seemed greatly impressed by Lang, who apparently posed in the Conference as the exponent of liberal ideas</hi><hi rend="italic">! I suggested that the reference to 1610 could hardly have been reasonably thought conciliatory to Scotsmen. He replied that he agreed, &amp; had said as much at Lambeth. Generally he was despondent on the whole subject. He was reluctant to play the prophet, but he could not avoid the belief that within a short space there would be a schism in the Church of England. The Ritualist faction might patch up some kind of an union with the Greek Church, or even with the Roman Catholics: the mass of Anglicans might get into alliance with Presbyterians. As I looked at the Bishops, &amp; listened to the debates, I felt that there were really two Churches represented in the Conference. This is entirely accordant with what I learned from the American Bishops.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p>Then we lunched at the Deanery. The Dean (Coombes) is a pleasant, rather sleek little man about to celebrate his silver wedding, &amp; proud of the fact! He &amp; his canons have their main sphere of work in connection with the Theological College, where they are <hi rend="underline">ex officio</hi> professors. S. John's Cathedral is a humble little building dated from a comparatively remote period, perhaps 60 years!, and already tending to fall by reason of doubtful building &amp; bad foundation. It has a rather fine carved wooden pulpit.</p>
         <p>Later we had tea with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Jones. After dinner another of the Cathedral clergy called on us, Canon Jeffries, the diocesan Missioner. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Oldfield, a friend of Aubrey's<persName xml:id="1095"></persName>, called also. He is a successful <hi rend="underline">English</hi> colonist, almost everybody else is Scotch, who can be so described.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">He gives a very unfavourable account of the political morality of Canada. "Graft" is universal; &amp; there is no public conscience on the subject. The newspaper contains a terrible account of the social morality of Winnipeg. I fear the general effect of what I have seen &amp; heard in this city is distinctly depressing.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>