<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Winnipeg</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>The telephone brought us an invitation to dine at Government House, which of course we had to decline.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Oldfield called at 10.30; and took me a drive round the city, and into S. Boniface. It is impossible not to notice that the fine stone churches are almost without exception non&#8211;Anglican. The Roman Catholic institutions are very prominent. The chief centre of the R. Church is, of course, among the French Canadians in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Boniface.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic">O. gives an unfavourable account of the C. of England. The clergy are </hi><hi rend="italic underline">relatively</hi><hi rend="italic"> inferior both intellectually &amp; spiritually. Why is this? In the States I found the Anglican Church aggressive, hopeful, and apparently advancing. Here it is nothing of the kind. Why?</hi></p>
         <p>Last night Canon Jeffries made the statement, giving a Canadian farmer as his authority, that the wolves (i.e. cayotes) would not jump wire netting. A low fence, 3 or 4 feet high, sufficed for the protection of sheep. If this be true, the fact should be made known as widely as possible, for we hear of sheep&#8211;growing abandoned by reason of wolves.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p>We packed miserably, bade farewell to Aubrey<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> &amp; Lois<persName xml:id="2672"></persName> who had accompanied us to the station, joined Max Dennistoun<persName xml:id="2743"></persName> &amp; D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jones there, &amp; so went off to Keewatin on the Lake of the Woods. We reached our destination in 4¼ hours: the latter part of the journey was relieved by a fine series of Lake views. At Keewatin the train ran by the lake&#8211;side: here waited to receive us Max Dennistoun's sons James &amp; John<persName xml:id="2745"></persName>, &amp; the boat which quickly brought us to his cottage.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Jones </hi><hi rend="italic underline">en route</hi><hi rend="italic"> told me this story, which he said he had himself received first&#8211;hand. When the C.P.R. line was in making, two gangs of men &amp; horses of equal number went to work on adjacent sections, precisely similar in quality. One of them was Sabbatarian, the other was not. At the end of a few weeks the first were somewhat behind&#8211;hand; at the end of the summer the position had been altogether reversed. The Sabbatarians had done more work, &amp; came away with cattle in good condition: their neighbours had ruined their cattle &amp; failed to finish their work.</hi></p>
         <p>After dinner Dennistoun &amp; I talked politics on the verandah, watching the while the fire&#8211;flies, gleaming like electric sparks to &amp; fro. </p></body></text></TEI>