<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Seattle:&#8211; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Josiah Collins &amp; D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Lloyd came to meet us at the station</hi>. We were taken in the motor to a very pleasant house, with a noble fire&#8211;place in which a whole household could gather. The walls were adorned with trophies of the chase. An immense moose's head was particularly noteworthy.</p>
         <p>After lunch we went with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Collins to the Exposition. It is finely situated, having a noble view over the bay &amp; lake, with the mountains beyond. The arrangement of the grounds is excellent. Flowers are prominent &amp; beautiful. We looked at the exhibits from Alaska, which appears to be a habitable &amp; fertile country, extraordinarily rich in minerals. <hi rend="italic">The Forestry exhibition was most striking. It is housed in a noble log&#8211;built structure, destined to be a permanent possession of the State University. There was a beam of wood 18 inches square &amp; no less than 156 1/2 feet long, cut out of a single tree. Another beam 4 1/2 feet square was 76 feet long.</hi></p>
         <p>The Exhibition is held under conditions which might well compromise its financial success. It has received no grant from the Federal Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>: it has been required to have no alcohol sold within its confines: &amp; some of its buildings have been built with a view to the permanent needs of the State University.</p></body></text></TEI>