<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A brilliant day but still cold. We were fetched in good time for the service in Trinity Church at 10.30. It consisted of the Litany &amp; Holy Communion with Sermon. There was large, but not a crowded congregation. I preached a sermon on 'The criticism of scruples'. In giving out the notices the Rector observed that it was 31 years since Dean Stanley coming to America preached his first sermon in Trinity Church &amp; added that this was my first sermon in an Episcopal Church.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We looked at some impressionist daubs by a Spanish artist, Saroka, over whom the Americans are raving: &amp; then returned to Harvard, where I betook myself to slumber by way of preparing for the evening.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The President (Elliott) and his wife came to "High Tea". He is a tall &amp; impressive looking man with a look of great nobility and strength</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> An ugly discolourment of the face, which would ruin most men's appearance, is discounted by the moral &amp; mental force which his countenance expresses.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There was a great congregation in the Appleton Chapel, mostly students &amp; others from the university. I preached substantially the sermon which I had preached in Cambridge last November. Dr. Moore conducted the service save for the lesson (S. Matt. VII) which I read. The attention was close and sustained. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The President thanked me afterwards in very kind terms. "It was a real University sermon" he said in his grave way.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Afterwards we met Prof. &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Joy, Prof. &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Scofield, M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Neilson. The last named said that he had met me at Bonskeid in 1890. I had quite forgotten him.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I was much impressed by the mode of administering the Holy Communion in Trinity Church. The Communion rail round the Altar forming a half&#8211;circle. There were about 400 communicants: but the administration very quickly effected as chalice was administered with the formula addressed to couples.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>