<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Bismarck</hi>: This is the State capital, named after the Blood&#8211;&amp;&#8211;Iron Statesman with a view to "booming" Dakota in Germany. The reasons why towns get their names are various: hardly any could be more squalid. There had been heavy rain during the night &amp; the fact was evidenced by the condition of the streets which had the aspect &amp; quality of a ploughed field. Yet this miserable road, which w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> disgrace barbarians, sustained down its centre a line of electric cars. We visited the Capitol, a square tasteless building where the State Legislature holds its sessions. Here we were shown everything by an obliging official. A very small collection of Indian trophies &amp; relics, &amp; many specimens of Dakotan Corn &amp;c were exhibited.</p>
         <p>After lunch we were driven to the State Penitentiary, where the Warden courteously showed us over his melancholy domain. We admired the arrangements of the cells, &amp; observed with natural depression the prisoners. Mostly they are employed in rope&#8211;making &amp; in the work of the institution. We saw the dogs kept to pursue fugitives, but rarely needed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Then we visited an Indian School</hi> nobly placed on the bank of the Missouri River, a splendid stream now swollen by the rains &amp; rushing along with a swift &amp; dangerous current. There are about 60 boys &amp; gals sent by their parents, mostly prosperous farmers, &amp; educated at the cost of the Govt of USA. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p>The strongly marked type of face &amp; the taciturn mysterious manner sufficiently indicated the race.</p>
         <p>We dined with some friends of the Bishop, named Jewell, very courteous &amp; hospitable people.</p>
         <p>There had been much uncertainty as to the chance of our getting sleeping accommodation on the Western trains, so that we brought anxious minds to the station. Happily our fears were disproved by the event, for the conductor housed us must comfortably – using the word with that depraved significance which it bears in such circumstances.</p></body></text></TEI>