<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>The violent rains of yesterday and last night muddied the water from which the hotel draws its supplies: we had to make shift with washing with a coffee&#8211;coloured liquid which suggest rather ablutions finished than about to be. The morning is bright but the sky is still threatening, and the temperature has fallen.</p>
         <p>Our train was no less than 2 1/2 hours late: we did not arrive at Calgary until past 3 p.m. There we were met by Edith Ripley, Harold &amp; their mother. We spent the time before dinner in visiting the Exposition. Here the ground was bright with elaborately dressed Indians, &amp; there was a fine display of dogs, horses, cattle, &amp; poultry. We dined in the Alberta Hotel: &amp; then sate &amp; talked until nearly 11 p.m. when we went to the station &amp; waited our train.</p>
         <p>Pacific Time…… To Loggan</p>
         <p>Mountain "…… " Broadview</p>
         <p>Central "……… " Fort William</p>
         <p>Eastern " ……… </p>
         <p>Atlantic " ……..</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi></p>
         <p>The station at Calgary presented a curious spectacle. It was crowded with men, women, &amp; children, even infants. As train after train passed out, &amp; yet these people remained, it became evident that a large proportion of them were spending the night in the <hi rend="italic">waiting rooms. A railway official told me that they were the new colonists who are 'taking up' the lands in Alberta. Some of them had come from far, &amp; seemed extremely fatigued.</hi></p>
         <p>At 2.30 a.m. on July 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> our train drew up at the platform : we were relieved to find that the conductor had a drawing room for us, (for which we paid 18 dollars) and at last we were able to get to bed. All Thursday we traversed an immense level plain, treeless &amp; unvarying, the most dreary country in the world. The little settlements have a forlorn aspect from a distance, a squalid appearance at close view. Hideous 'elevators' are the chief public buildings. No one yet has managed to plant trees. It is impossible to imagine a more desolate setting for human life. At 7.15 a.m. on Friday July 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> we reached Winnipeg, &amp; found Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> &amp; Lois<persName xml:id="2672"></persName> waiting to receive us on the platform.</p></body></text></TEI>