<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>Sicamous Hotel is a modest guest&#8211;house built on the edge of a small &amp; beautiful lake, engirdled with the mountains. It had one grave draw&#8211;back – <hi rend="underline">mosquitoes</hi>. These pests swarmed on the platform as we waited for the train, &amp; stung us all comfortably before starting! We started about  1/2 an hour after the advertised time.</p>
         <p>The line ran through the grandest mountain scenery. On the lower slopes &amp; by the side of the railway was a profusion of wild&#8211;flowers. Abundant evidence of recent forest fires were painfully manifest. We passed a succession of notable waterfalls, and canyons. At one point a picturesque group of Hindoos encamping under the trees arrested our notice. These aliens were working on the line. As we approached the "great Divide" the train mounted with laborious effort, and for a considerable space accompanied a foaming stream, which made a grand figure in the retrospect. In the evening lights the mountains looked strangely beautiful. There were three locomotives engaged in pulling &amp; pushing the train up the ascent. We arrived at Loggan about 9.15, and then had a long drive to the "Lake Louise Hotel", where we put up for the night. It was nearly midnight before our luggage arrived, and we were able to carry ourselves to bed.</p></body></text></TEI>