<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[166]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Empress of Ireland</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>There was some sun in the earlier part of the day: but after noon the grey aspect was restored.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I walked much &amp; talked much with D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Denny<persName xml:id="4198"></persName>, whom I find a pleasant companion. His enthusiasm for poetry is admirable. Just now he is full of Homer, having just re&#8211;read the Iliad. Of English poets he is clearly most devoted to Milton. Lycidas he considers the master's chef d'oeuvre. He is convinced that English literature is of all literatures the greatest, &amp; in the fact he would find one more evidence of Divine purpose in the history of the English race.</hi></p>
         <p>We had some conversation on pastoral work. He told me that, in the whole of his ministry, no one had ever come to him with desire to ease his conscience by confession of sin. How different has been my experience! Pascal's Provinciales had been for him, as for me, a book of abiding impressiveness, the reading of which had been an event in the development of mind.</p>
         <p>After lunch I walked for an hour with an elderly man, whose name I cannot discover. He is a member of the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>: he has been much in the East: knows Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> well: &amp; was with him during the last fortnight of his stay in India: is now a director of the Times. His conversation was most interesting, for he has <hi rend="bold">[167]</hi> travelled far, &amp; seen many important men. He told me that the opposition to the partition of Bengal mainly proceeded from lawyers &amp; absentee landlords, who dreaded the superior efficiency of a government in Dacca, &amp; its inconvenience to themselves! He thought that Sir Bampfeld Fuller had been very badly treated, but he had ruined his chances by writing the sensational letter, headed '<hi rend="underline">J'accuse</hi>'. In point of fact, Lord Morley had actually arranged to place him suitably, when that unfortunate epistle appeared, &amp; spoiled all. Lord Morley is admirable &amp; very skillful, but he takes no counsel that he doesn't like, &amp; plays the Jesuit in politics. Lord Minto was not supported by the Council in India when he supported the Reform scheme.</p>
         <p>Yesterday we made 431 miles – a record. I started reading Fogazzaro's famous novel, 'The Saint', which I borrowed from the ship's library. It is a very disappointing book, &amp; if it really expresses the mind of the Italian Modernists one can have little confidence in their success. For the central conceptions are frankly ascetic &amp; medieval. 'The Saint' is only S. Francis restored to life again. As another indication of the squalid &amp; ceaseless tyranny of the ecclesiastical system, the book has a melancholy interest of its own, but it is futile as a programme of religious reform.</p></body></text></TEI>