<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[102]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Victoria</hi><hi rend="bold">:</hi> Another glorious day. The view of the harbour and the straits, girt with hills &amp; besprinkled with islets was superb. I was reminded of Stockholm. This is a public holiday – Dominion Day – and the steamers are dressed with flags. Today we begin our return journey. Henceforward our faces are turned homewards. </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>I travell'd among unknown men,</p>
         <p>In lands beyond the sea;</p>
         <p>Nor, England! Did I know till then</p>
         <p>What love I bore to thee.</p>
         </div>
         <p>These colonists, however, are not fairly to be described as "unknown men", and <hi rend="underline">their</hi> love of England is perhaps hardly less than one's own.</p>
         <p>The "Victoria Colonist" has quite a respectable report of my speech to the Canadian Club, and also a short and well&#8211;written leader on the same.</p>
         <p>We packed our bags, &amp; "checked" the heaviest of them to Winnipeg. Then we lunched, paid our reckoning (16 1/2 dollars for the room for 3 nights), &amp; went on board the steamer for Vancouver. The weather was superb, and as the steamer made its way through the wooded island, the scenes of natural beauty which disclosed themselves were marvellous. The snowy summit of M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Baker accompanied us throughout – a most rare &amp; lovely spectacle. Though scarcely 11000 feet high this mountain <hi rend="bold">[103] </hi>stands out in solitary pre&#8211;eminence which suggests a much greater height. The colouring of the sea, mountains, and islands was a great addition to the beauty of the scene. Everything seemed steeped in a blue brilliance. I was interested in watching a large salmon jumping in mere wantouness of natural liberty from the water. One thing, indeed, which offended me – there was <hi rend="bold underline">a long succession of vulgar advertisements set up on the lovely islands where the narrowness of the passages compels the steamer to go within reading distance of the shore</hi>. As we drew near to Vancouver the mountains had a grand aspect, as of a mighty gateway into the mainland: the steamer changed its course, however, just when it seemed about to enter, &amp; steamed into the city leaving the mountains to the left. On our right was the dense wood of Stanley Park. Taken altogether the entrance to Vancouver is very fine.</p>
         <p>After dinner I write letters to Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> and Robertson.</p></body></text></TEI>