<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>A bright morning after the rain. I wrote letters to Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> and <hi rend="underline">Buff</hi>. At 10 a.m. Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Benson arrived to take us over the Terraces. We had two hours of most interesting inspection &amp; most agreeable conversation. These terraces are really a collection of dead, moribund, &amp; dying geysers. A time will come when "Old Faithful" will have smothered himself in his own deposits. He, &amp; every other active geyser, is engaged in building &amp; decorating his own tomb. We admired especially the "orange" geyser, about which trees &amp; flowers are growing freely. We drank the tepid disagreeable water of the Soda Spring: descended the sulphurous cavity of the "Devil's Kitchen": and gazed on the green&#8211;tinged water of the pool in which the bather may swim from cold water to hot.</p>
         <p>We returned to the hotel for lunch; and then went through again the dolorous task of packing. We went to the Bensons for a farewell cup of tea. The Major had got out his views of the Yosemite valley.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then we dined in the hotel, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">paid our reckoning</hi><hi rend="italic">, and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">went off to Gardiner</hi><hi rend="italic">. Our coach drive to the station was cheered by a beautiful double rainbow.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p>We left Gardiner at 7.15 p.m. on Monday, and arrived at Seattle at 8.30 a.m. on Wednesday. The train was filled with an inferior class of tourists.</p>
         <p>One tragic incident marked our journey. One of the tourists – a young woman – died on the journey, &amp; was removed from the train at the first convenient station.</p></body></text></TEI>