<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>Our host called me at 6 a.m. Reluctantly but punctually we rose, dressed, completed our packing (a hideous process) and breakfasted. Then bidding farewell to our hostess, we went off with our host to the railway station. We journeyed by an 'accommodation' train to <hi rend="underline">Boston</hi> via Springfield, where we had a wait for 40 min: which I utilized by getting my <hi rend="italic">boots cleaned (10 cents). On the road we bought a Hartford paper, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; found in it a leader on "The Inhibition of Canon Henson". From this I gathered that a Chicago paper had been also writing on that theme</hi><hi rend="italic underline">.</hi></p>
         <p>We arrived in Boston in pouring rain, &amp; were met at the Station by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Chandler, the Secretary of the Twentieth Century Club. We were driven to the Club premises, &amp; incontinently introduced to a mingled company of men &amp; women, who were lunching. After the meal, which was of a very simple description, we started speechifying. I led off with half an hour's disquisition on the educational situation in England. I was followed <hi rend="bold">[18]</hi> by a lady connected with the American Lady's College at Constantinople. She was an enthusiastic advocate for the Young Turks, &amp; had no mercy for Abdul Hamid.</p>
         <p>This function ended we were driven to 21 Kirkland Street, Cambridge. Mass, the residence of the Rev. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Moore. Here we were most hospitably received. At dinner were Dean Hodges &amp; his wife, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mann &amp; his wife, and a local lawyer whose name escapes me. The subtle &amp; persuasive Rector of Trinity Church pledged me to preach for him on the morrow.</p></body></text></TEI>