<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>We were called at 5.30 a.m. The Bishop &amp; I went out to take a farewell view of the Cañon &amp; Waterfall before breakfast. <hi rend="bold underline">Here a disaster happened to my camera</hi>. I had taken out the spool of films which had been used, &amp; aspired to replace it with an unused spool: by an act of incredible stupidity I actually took the spool which had just been taken out, &amp;, of course, the thing didn't act. Finally I got it so unrolled &amp; messed about that I judged it irreparably injured. So the 12 photographs taken of the geysers went into the cataract, &amp; I went back to the hotel mightily ill&#8211;pleased.</p>
         <p>The drive back to Mammoth Hot Springs Hotel was mainly over old ground. We suffered considerably from the dust; &amp; from the melancholy consciousness that we were leaving the Yellowstone behind us. Our circumstance, however, gave distinction to the drive: we saw a bear moving about quite close to the road. The Bishop asserted that he saw a beaver leap into a stream by the way&#8211;side: &amp; this statement was confirmed by a tourist in another coach. A curious growth of 'twin trees' counts also as a curiosity of this drive.</p>
         <p>We arrived in the Hotel about 4 p.m. simply covered with dust. Then, after an interval, the Manns went off to Fargo. </p></body></text></TEI>