<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Empress of Ireland</hi></p>
         <p>The stewardess brought us some excellent tea at 7 a.m., &amp; half an hour later I was called for my bath. We found ourselves anchored outside Rimouski, waiting for the mails. The delay at this point varies from 8 to 12 hours. Breakfast was successful in all respects – the viands were good, &amp; our companions disposed to talk. It must, indeed, be admitted that our conversation did not range far, or attempt any adequate subject, such as it was, however, it relieved the tedium of the voyage, and improved the atmosphere.</p>
         <p>I read in the 'Times' the record of the debate in Parliament raised by the Labour members on the subject of the Czar's visit to the King. Sir Edward Grey rebuked them with unusual severity, &amp; of course the 'Times' is stern &amp; sarcastic. Doubtless they are mistaken &amp; ignorant, but when I recall the sentiments with which we were all filled, &amp; which most of us professed a few years ago on the subject of Russian autocracy, I cannot condemn very severely these Labour men, who only differ from the rest in being somewhat slower in changing their prejudices. Nor do I think Sir Edward would be able to show that the duty of non–interference in the domestic politics of other nations has been consistently, or could be rightly, recognized by this country.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi></p>
         <p>The day was wasted in waiting for the mails. We were altogether something more than 14 hours at anchor off Rimouski. About 5.30 p.m. we resumed our journey. The river grows wider, &amp; the banks more monotonous. After dinner we paraded the deck enjoying the moon–light on the water, &amp; the afterglow of the sunset.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> James Denny</hi><persName xml:id="4198"></persName> introduced himself to me, &amp; for more than an hour we paced the deck discussing theology and the relations of churches. He assures me that D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cooper has no following in Scotland. <hi rend="underline">Prof. Orr</hi>, his colleague in Glasgow, who has taken up the rôle of orthodox champion, is, he says, essentially a philosopher, little able to understand &amp; less able to sympathize with the standpoints &amp; methods of historians &amp; critics. <hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="underline">Denny</hi> said that he had read carefully <hi rend="underline">Loisy's</hi> "Les Evangiles Synoptiques", and had come to the conclusion that the author had really parted with Christianity itself. "Looked at from the lowest point of view, Christianity is a great business, &amp; cannot be run on an infinitesimal capital of conviction". He could not censure the Pope for condemning <hi rend="underline">Loisy</hi>. I suggested that he would find himself in general agreement with <hi rend="underline">Inge's</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName> article on 'Modernism' in the jubilee number of the 'Quarterly'. Generally I found myself in agreement with <hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Denny's</hi> opinions, both theological &amp; ecclesiastical. He says that his last book has been received in Scotland with much acceptance. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi></p>
         <p>My vis–à–vis at the Captains table is a much travelled man, who having served as an army–doctor in many parts of the British Empire, has now retired on a pension. He has a grievance against Westminster Abbey. An ancestor of his was Wyatt, the architect who is buried in Poet's corner (as he avers). In the Deanery Guide book this good man is mentioned as <hi rend="underline">'well–known as the Destroyer'</hi>, an opprobrious description earned by his <hi rend="underline">'restorations'</hi> at Durham &amp; elsewhere. He thought it a hard thing that his relative's architectural distinction should be buried in a contemporary gibe!</p>
         <p>I have been reading an historical novel by an author, whose name &amp; fame have hitherto been unknown to me:– "The Golden Dog (de Chien d'Or) A romance of the Days of Louis Quinze in Quebec, by William Kirby F.R.C.S.. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>The Montreal New Co. Lim<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Publishers.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p></body></text></TEI>