<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>We were running through a pretty &amp; varied country when we looked out of our "State&#8211;room" window. Rather to our surprise the negro informed us that breakfast was not obtainable on the train. We reached Minneapolis at 9.50 or thereabouts. On the platform were M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Mann &amp; M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Clark. We were motored to the latter's house, &amp; given breakfast. After this we were taken [on] a delightful drive in the motor round the lovely lakes which are the special glory of this city. Here again we admired the enterprize &amp; public spirit of the citizens in the securing for their community ample means of healthy recreation. In the course of our drive we saw a number of birds, and also a turtle. I recall the following:&#8211; the oriole, the blue bird, the cat bird, the blue jay, the American robin, the yellow&#8211;hammer, the red&#8211;winged black&#8211;bird, the crane, &amp; several others. We lunched at a pleasant club&#8211;house: &amp; then resumed our drive. We visited S. Paul, and admired the sleep&#8211;banked Mississippi. Here also were more admirable parks; a fine State&#8211;House, &amp; a commodious University. Having bade farewell to M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Clark, we dined at the West Hotel; and then <hi rend="bold">[58] </hi>having yet some hours to dispose of before our train left, we went out to the Minihaha Falls on the trolly car. The falls are really worth seeing; the volume of water is considerable, and the entourage of the water&#8211;fall beautiful. Few cities can boast of so notable a feature in their public parks.</p>
         <p>At 11.5 p.m. we left Minneapolis, and arrived at Fargo at 7.15 on the next morning.</p></body></text></TEI>