<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant day. I made a start by visiting an adjacent dentist. Then mine host took me to the Spanish Museum, where we found D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Huntingdon the benevolent millionaire who finances it. An interesting man, tall, handsome, and conversational. He spoke with the usual scorn of the Y.M.C.A. young man, &amp; said that he would not care to take him into his service. All the ability of America was in finance. I was interested in hearing him talk.</p>
         <p>We lunched at the Railroad Club on the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> floor of the Hudson Terminal Bldg, a monstrous sky&#8211;scraper. The view over the city and river was very fine. After luncheon we went over the club, and descended into depths where the new Hudson and Maine Railway is in construction below the other underground railways. We were introduced to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Macadoo, the famous subterranean engineer, whom the New Yorkers regard with veneration, as the enterprising spirit to whom an undertaking accounted impossible was due.</p>
         <p>After lunch we called at the C.P.R. office, and then went in the elevated R<hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi> to have tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fisher. Then mine host &amp; I went to the Alumni dinner of the General Seminary, but came away in some disgust at the speeches. My toothache was violent.</p></body></text></TEI>