<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Winnipeg</hi><hi rend="bold">:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p>I am pledged to address the Canadian Club on "<hi rend="bold underline">A cross&#8211;bench view of Imperial Defence</hi>". It is not easy to keep the bounds of prudence: &amp;, when one has done one's best, there is always the head&#8211;line to be reckoned with. I wrote out a short speech, having learned by experience that the American reporter is quite unable to report anything. There were about 250 people present, both men &amp; women, but mainly men. The lunch was the meagre&#8211;est in the world, &amp; then came a few words from the chairman introducing me, &amp; then I spoke for about 25 minutes. The audience listened closely, &amp; applauded loudly at the end. Then we sang "God save the King" fervently: &amp; so departed. In the company were the leading citizens of Winnipeg including the Archbishop, the Lord Chief Justice, the Attorney General, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Whyte. The last sate next to me, &amp; I found him again very interesting. He says that the influx of Americans is bringing the "graft" mischief into Canada.</p>
         <p>Max Dennistoun<persName xml:id="2743"></persName> took me to the Manitoba Club, &amp; there I wrote a letter to Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> &amp; read the papers, while he transacted some business. Then we had tea, &amp; rejoined the ladies, in order to go out to the Country Club, where he entertained us to dinner very pleasantly. <hi rend="bold">[120]</hi> The Fishery Commissioners whom we met in Washington – Professors Jordan &amp; a Canadian professor – were in the Club, &amp; claimed acquaintance. The former with his secretary called on me in the morning, &amp; had a brief conversation.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">It is evident that much money may be made in this country by money&#8211;lending to the farmers. Money may be borrowed at a cheap rate in the East or in Europe, and lent out at no less than 6 or even 8 per cent interest. Everybody is mortgaging in order to raise funds to lend out at this rate.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>