<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Seattle:&#8211;</hi><hi rend="italic">We received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in S. Mark's Church. I carried my robes round, and wore them at the 11 a.m. service, when I read the lessons, by way of showing that there was 'no malice'.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lloyd made an elaborate &amp; excessively grandiloquent statement about the incident which had induced me to cancel my promise to preach: &amp; then enlarged on a 'moonlight party', tickets 50 cents, including food, which the parish was arranging! The bathos was extreme. The sermon on the text, 'Bless them that curse you etc', was so ludicrously connected with the episode on which the preacher had been dilating, that I could hardly conceal my amusement. There can be no doubt about the good man's disturbance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There was a considerable attendance in the 'Auditorium' for my lecture on 'Westminster Abbey'. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic">Collins says there were about 1200 people, &amp; that this was the largest concourse they had yet collected on Sunday afternoon. The lecture was as well received as I had any right to expect.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lloyd sent me an Indian totem as a peace&#8211;offering!! The poor fellow looks quite exhausted with his emotions!!!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>