<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>The day was dull &amp; threatening at the start, wet in most of its course, and reluctantly fine at its close, i.e. the setting sun showed a few gleams across the lake.</p>
         <p>We caught the 9 a.m. steamer from Toronto, and reached Lewiston, seven miles up the Niagara river on the American side, at 11.55: then we were carried by the electric railway to the Niagara Falls. The train runs along the river&#8211;side, almost at the level of the water, enabling us to view the Rapids to advantage.</p>
         <p>These are, indeed wonderful. I was not prepared for the beauty, or the volume, or the violence of the River.</p>
         <p>On arriving at Niagara we went to look at the American Fall, which is extremely beautiful, but, by comparison with the Horse&#8211;shoe Falls on the Canadian side almost pretty. Then we crossed the bridge, and lunched in the Clifton Hotel, of which the dining room commanded a noble prospect of the Falls. After lunch we charted a carriage, and were driven to the Horse Shoe Fall. We looked at it from above, &amp; from below. We were clothed in oil&#8211;skins, and sent through a tunnel cut in the rock, until we were able to stand under the mighty cataract, &amp; feel its water splashing in our faces. We looked at the wide expanse of foaming waters, tumbling over great ridges of rock, before <hi rend="bold">[136] </hi>taking the great leap into the abyss. The scene above the Falls, looking away from the hideous power&#8211;houses on the American side, is extraordinarily impressive. I was not prepared for so great a width of the river, or for the long series of foam&#8211;crashed ridges. We went on to the island which separates the Falls, and as we returned, we encountered a drunken man, supported with difficulty by a lady, presumably his wife, and going down to see with his drink blurred vision the same amazing spectacle as we had gazed upon. What a theme for a moralist! The physical force of Nature &amp; the moral weakness of man united in a single picture. We returned by the Canadian bank, where the line runs on the top of the river&#8211;bank. I observed numerous vine yards &amp; fruit orchards. This district is renowned for its production of peaches.</p>
         <p>A numerous excursion returning to Toronto crowded the steamer, filling everything with their chatter &amp; laughter. Humanity in the gross is strangely repulsive. American varieties, perhaps , more repulsive than the rest. There is a strident vulgarity in the voices, and aggressive self&#8211;assertiveness in the gestures of Americans which, I hope &amp; believe, have no terrestrial parallels. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Donaldson met us at the station, and we were all safely under cover again by 9.15 p.m.</p>
         <p>N.B. The paper reports D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Huntingdon to be dying.</p></body></text></TEI>