<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant day but the wind still cold. After breakfast I revised my lecture &amp; then went out for 2 hours. <hi rend="underline">The grey squirrels are fascinating – so tame that they will offer you to come within a few feet of them</hi>. The robin is a fine bird as large as a thrush. Returning to the house I wrote a letter to Reggie Still<persName xml:id="1259"></persName>: &amp; then we went to lunch.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">President &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic">Hadley were of the company, very pleasant &amp; intelligent people. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">My 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> lecture </hi><hi rend="italic">was well&#8211;attended, &amp; seemed to be well&#8211;liked. Then we had tea with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Hadley, &amp; made preparations for our next function, which was of an unusual &amp; amusing character.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We attended the "Fellowship Meeting" of the New Haven Congregational Club. The proceedings began with a 'Reception to Canon Henson'. I stood on the platform of a large and hideous chapel with my 'bear&#8211;leader' Prof. Walker, and shook hands with a multitude of plain men &amp; plainer women. Then we went to 'dinner &amp; table&#8211;talks'. I was told that 490 sat down to feed: the victuals &amp; the waiting being provided by the ladies of the congregation. After dinner followed the speeches from representatives of the different churches. The President of the University led off: then followed a Baptist, a Presbyterian, an Episcopalian, a Methodist, &amp; a Congregationalist. After this performance we all returned to the Chapel, &amp; listened to an Anthem</hi>, <hi rend="bold">[13] </hi><hi rend="italic">&amp; then I made a speech on 'Fellowship' of about 35 minutes length. The singing of two verses of 'Onward Christian soldiers' brought this strange function to an end. A secretary thrust a cheque for twenty five dollars into my hand.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>