<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p> A beautiful, bright morning. I awoke with a depressing consciousness that I was committed to some formidable engagements, for which I had but little competence. First there was the service for the youth at 10.30. I chose from my travelling stock of old sermons the discourse onn Eph. VI. 17, 'The Sword of the Spirit which is the Word of God', preached last Whitsunday in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. It has an aspect of deadly dullness, but must serve. Still more alarming is the conduct of the service, which includes 'extemporaneous' prayer! <hi rend="bold underline">Of all men I am surely the most 'Liturgy&#8211;bound'. Impromptu prayer seems impossible: it can only be an indirect speech interlarded with liturgical reminiscences</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>There was a great gathering of students – 1500 was said to be the number of the congregation, &amp; of these most were academic – and I conducted the service &amp; preached. As I had anticipated, the sermon was a failure, never gripped the boys once, being indeed a tiresome production altogether. The 'extempore' prayer passed muster better than the discourse. After the service, which occupied about an hour, I was carried to the club, &amp; given a cup of tea. Then I addressed about 70 'Sheffield' students. These are said to study science, mostly engineering. The address was an extemporaneous sermonette lasting about 20 minutes. After this we returned home, &amp; lunched. At 3 p.m. I was brought down to a Y.M.C.A. (or something equivalent) <hi rend="bold">[10]</hi> <hi rend="italic">building, &amp; established in a room by myself to confer with anybody who should desire that privilege! It was indicated to me that the young men would probably have the good sense to prefer the country &amp; the fresh air!! Behold me, then – like a holy spider with out&#8211;spread net, on the watch for spiritual flies – sitting solitary, &amp; writing cynically. Tonight I understand that I shall have a further opportunity of illumining the youth of Yale: but there seems much question whether they will wish any further illumination. Certainly the provision for their edification is ample, frequent, &amp; varied! At least, I may utilize the interval to prepare some observations for the prospective Nicodemuses!!</hi></p>
         <p>Perhaps one might with advantage talk about the practical significance of Christianity in present circumstances. A sufficient skeleton might, perhaps, be the Scriptural designations of Christ's followers:&#8211; 1. disciples. 2. brethren. 3. Christians. 4. Saints. These indicate the stages of the process of self&#8211;realisation which the church traversed: nor may this be reversed. All must be combined in the Christianity which is healthy and whole. The undue or even exclusive emphasizing of any one leads directly to spiritual error &amp; defeat. The ascetic fastens on that aspect of his religion in which he is required to be a saint: the "Christian" <hi rend="underline">eo nomine</hi> may subordinate everything to formal definitions of belief &amp; rules of profession: the 'brother' <hi rend="bold">[11] </hi>may place social service of denomination zeal in the stead of saint&#8211;hood on personal allegiance, or external witness. Even the 'disciple' may so isolate his discipleship from its ecclesiastical &amp; secular bearings as to become dangerously individualistic.</p>
         <p>The monk, the Erastian [sic], the clerical, the sectary – may sufficiently illustrate these lop&#8211;sided versions of Christianity.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">S. Luke X14.25f </hi>'If any man cometh unto me &amp; hateth not his own father &amp;c. he cannot be my disciple'. To be a 'disciple' is to realize the sterner side of X<hi rend="superscript underline">ity</hi>: and to face the full demand of X<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. It implies obedience and belief. "Follow me." "Lovest thou Me?"</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">S.Matt. Xxiii.8</hi>. 'Be not ye called 'Rabbi': for one is your Teacher &amp; all ye are brethren. cf. S.John. X.16. "They shall become one flock, one shepherd".</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Mine host has just come to take me home, my hour of solitary expectancy being exhausted. That was a curious and even comical incident!</hi> At 6.40 I was again on the same scene addressing a collection of about 60 or 70 pious youth. The lucubrations of the afternoon provided material for a 20 minute talk. Finally we went to the Holy Trinity (Episcopal) Church, where one D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Peabody, a schoolmaster of some repute in these parts, delivered a "Berkeley Sermon". 'Twas a poor performance enough, mostly extemporaneous, and attended by a small congregation including about 50 of the students. Then home to bed about 11 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>