<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">dies fatalis</hi> of departure arrived at last. Our packing was completed, &amp; we went off to the station in Jim's motor: the luggage going on before with Mother<persName xml:id="76"></persName> &amp; Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>. At Euston Mary<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> &amp; Signorina<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> arrived to see us off: &amp; the absurd young man Townshend whom I knew as a lad in Ilford ten years ago. Canon Walpole was in the train: he is to be our fellow&#8211;traveller as far as New York. We lunched comfortably on the train, &amp; went on to the 'Carmania' under a heavy rain. Here we were at once seized upon by the Dock Chaplain, &amp; the Superintendent from the Cunard C<hi rend="superscript">y</hi>. He offered us a change of cabin: so we found ourselves comfortably established in a cabin with private bath&#8211;room etc.: &amp; quite respectable space. When we went to prepare for dinner we found several telegrams from well&#8211;wishers, including one from Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName>. A reporter from the Liverpool Daily Post caught me as I was entering my cabin, &amp; started on the Birmingham episode, but I had little to say to him. We sate at the Captain's table during dinner, together with Canon Walpole, &amp; another guest, whose name we knew not. Afterwards we wrote letters, &amp; then retired to bed.</p></body></text></TEI>








