<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The rain was falling heavily when we took our departure. In the train we found ourselves next to Colonel Dudley, one of the West Point authorities. He assisted us to a safe arrival at our destination.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Travers, the Chaplain, met us, and drove us to the house of the superintendent, Col: Scott, by whom we were to be entertained</hi><hi rend="italic">. After lunch we motored round the place, which even under a falling rain, has an attractive aspect. At dinner several of the officers with their wives dined. All were very agreeable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Col: Scott is exceptionally interesting</hi><hi rend="italic">. He has served among the Red Indians, in Cuba, &amp; in the Philippines, where for 3 years he bore the sceptre of rule among the Mohammedans. He is clearly a man of parts, concerning himself in the populations with which he has come into contact. He gave me a most interesting account of the Indians, &amp; of the buffalo. In 1877 the latter were still very numerous. He himself had seen thousands, &amp; had witnessed their destruction. The railway brought death to the bison: when his hide was worth a dollar, he was ruthlessly slaughtered. He himself had seen 25 or 30 of the great beasts shot at once; the wind carrying away the sound of the discharges, so that beast after beast fell without arresting the notice of the herd. The wolves were numerous; &amp; since the bison has gone, are attacking the cattle on the ranches.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>