<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Montreal:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> John Bassett (655 St. Urbain St., Montreal) duly came to breakfast, and, when the meal was over, he had some conversation with me. He is 22 years old; an Irishman with all his countryman's fluency &amp; courage: he was educated in a seminary, &amp; then in the royal University, Dublin: he has a degree, having read law. His father died last year; &amp; he has come out to seek his fortunes in the New World. He spoke freely &amp; with a boy's frankness. For some reason or other he has evidently formed an exalted notion of me; &amp; was really much pleased at finding himself t&#x00EA;te&#8211;&#x00E0;&#8211;t&#x00EA;te with his hero. Our conversation took a grave turn; &amp; I listened with pleasure to sentiments which indicated a good up&#8211;bringing &amp; a genuine disposition to be religious. He has evidently been influenced for good by the apologetic writings of Frank Ballard<persName xml:id="5360"></persName>, the opponent of the notorious Blatchford<persName xml:id="5361"></persName>. We parted with many expressions of mutual regard. I advised him to join D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Symond's congregation, &amp; promised to write to the latter about him.</p>
         <p>Prof. Adams shewed us over the buildings of the McGill University. We admired their size, convenience, &amp; completeness of equipment. Especially the departments of mining &amp; metallurgy are admirably provided for. He explained to us divers experiments of his own in measuring the 'flow' of rocks. We saw also the 'Peter Redpath <hi rend="bold">[146]</hi> Library which we were told now contains 125,000 volumes.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went back to the house to lunch with Miss Blackadder. I went to the club to lunch with Mr. Greenfield &amp; mine host. The former is an interesting man who has a turn for philosophy. He is a Presbyterian by profession, &amp; delights to vex the souls of the orthodox by starting wild &amp; searching discussions on theological matters! Here I met Mr. Macpherson of Quebec, who expressed himself kindly anxious to show us civility there.</p>
         <p>After lunch Mr. Abbott, a son of a former Prime Minister of the colony, took me to two private houses in order to show me the pictures with which they were adorned. The first, that of Sir William van Horn, contained a number of interesting, &amp; some valuable pictures by Flemish, Spanish, English (inserted), modern Dutch, &amp; French painters. He is an artist himself, &amp; has on his walls many productions of his own. He is evidently a great collector. Among other objects of interest he has a number of old models of ships, mostly from Germany &amp; Holland. His studio is filled with Japanese pottery, etc., &amp; he amuses himself after finishing his work before going to bed, by painting a picture of every piece, &amp; making careful description of it. I was shown scores of these sketches, which amazed me by their excellence. Here is an astonishing exhibition of rigour &amp; versatility in a man whose age approaches three score &amp; ten years. He is 'adviser' to the C.P. Railway, &amp; has been engaged in railway work all his life, having worked himself up from the humblest beginnings.</p>
         <p>The second house, which I visited, was that of Sir George Drummond. Here were some magnificent pictures, notably <hi rend="bold">[147] </hi>three fine Vandycks, &amp; several Constables &amp; Chromes. It is a hopeful thing that the successful Canadians are thus aspiring to become patrons of the arts.</p>
         <p>Leaving my guide Mr. Abbott, I returned to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fleet's house &amp; there rejoined <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. We had tea, &amp; then went off to see the Lachine Rapids. These are certainly well&#8211;worth seeing. The S. Lawrence which here is a noble stream, two miles or more across, descends with much foam &amp; fury over a series of great ledges of rock, between which the steamer directs its course. Opposite to Montreal is a small Indian Reservation, largely occupied by French half&#8211;breeds.</p>
         <p>Montreal is growing rapidly. The population which is coming into the city is largely foreign, i.e. non&#8211;British. The Jews now number 40,000. Their children form 40% of the scholars in the Protestant schools. Italians &amp; Greeks in considerable numbers are also arriving. The natural increase of the French greatly exceeds that of the English. Thus the position of the latter does not improve: and the strength of the Roman Catholic Church on the whole is something more than maintained.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fleet went off to Little Metis. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McDougal, the editor of 'The Witness' &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Grenfell, mother of the Missionary, dined here. Also Wilfrid Bovey &amp; another.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McDougall is a strong Free&#8211;trader, and an opponent of Socialism. Mainly I find myself in agreement with his opinions on these subjects.</p></body></text></TEI>