<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1513</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The railway strike has ended. In front of the combination of firmness on the part of the government, and open anger on the part of the public, the strikers found themselves compelled to give in</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Of course there is to be no "victimisation" of the leaders, which means that treason in the ranks of "Labour" is to enjoy absolute impunity. We are treating "Labour" as we have long treated "Ireland", and we shall have the same consequences. Probably the dislocation of the railways for the last few days has inflicted on the Nation losses equivalent to a considerable German victory.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> and Crawfurd<persName xml:id="4909"></persName> went off by the midday train. There came to lunch a "melancholy humbug",</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">the Rev. G. H. E. Howell<persName xml:id="4592"></persName>, the Vicar of Ewyas Harold</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He came to ask to be transferred to another living, because, after five years experience of his present parishioners, he has reached the conclusion that he can do nothing with them. He is a well&#8211;grown man with a fairly good&#8211;looking countenance, rather "given away" by a nagging hopeless voice, like that of "a contentious woman". I felt that the parishioners may have had something to say on their side of the question.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> motored with me to Ross, where we are to be the guests of the Rector<persName xml:id="4330"></persName> &amp; his wife for the week&#8211;end. The weather was unfriendly again. We arrived in a rain storm. However, it cleared sufficiently for me to take a short walk with mine host before Evensong. At dinner our conversation turned on to ecclesiastical matters, &amp; I observed with some surprise that the conventional clap&#8211;trap against the Established system had made more way here than could have been expected.</hi>    
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
