<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[33]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Tuesday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1387</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I sent M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Paulin's letter (Bedwyn, Combe Down, Bath) about her unpaid Harley Pension to the solicitors of the Harley Trust<orgName xml:id="308"></orgName> (Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Harrison, Pollock, &amp; Harrison, Vernon House, Sicilian Ave. Bloomsbury Sq. W.C.1).</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Post brought a letter from the Dean of Christ Church<persName xml:id="120"></persName> stating that the Governing Body will not return Barnard's music.<note xml:id="388" n="1"></note> So my labours are vain.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 10 a.m. we started in the motor for </hi><hi rend="underline">Rock</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="underline">Beardley</hi><hi> in the Worcestershire part of the diocese, where I had undertaken to confirm. We travelled without any untoward incident, and reached Hereford shortly before 7 p.m. The heat was great, and the country looked most beautiful. Rock Parish Church is a noble building, mainly Norman, with a Perpendicular tower. The elaborately ornamented chancel arch, and the North&#8211;western porch are unusually fine examples of late Norman work. Here I confirmed 46 candidates, among whom was Hilda Jenkins, the Vicar's<persName xml:id="4598"></persName> younger daughter. After lunching at the Vicarage, we went on to Beardley, and here I confirmed 34 candidates. This church is architecturally beneath contempt, and I was not well&#8211;impressed by anything. We had tea at the Vicarage before starting for our return ourney.</hi>        
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The papers report an air&#8211;raid of unusual scale &amp; severity which took place in London on Sunday night. There was little damage done, but great loss of life &amp; limb. Exasperation rises ever, &amp; makes peace ever more unthinkable.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
