<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1381</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Edgar Dobbie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> before breakfast, thinking it well not to leave unanswered his caustic question about the Band, whether he ought to leave it because of the foul language of the members, or not? After breakfasting at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; visiting the barber, I walked to Lambeth, &amp; continued in the Bishops' Meeting all day, from 10 a.m. to 6.30 p.m., with brief intervals for lunch &amp; tea. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The subject of "Reunion" was brought forward by the Bishop of Sodor &amp; Man<persName xml:id="3229"></persName>, &amp; the discussion developed into a trial of strength between the Tractarians and the moderates. I spoke with frankness, and courtesy, setting forward my notion that the Bishops ought to regularize "interchange of pulpits" by granting requests from the Incumbent &amp; Churchwardens for permission to have a Nonconformist Preacher in their Parish Church. The Bishops of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> &amp; Oxford<persName xml:id="49"></persName> opposed, &amp; were defeated on a motion asking the Abp.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> to appoint a Committee to consider how far Non&#8211;Anglicans c</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">officiate in the churches. But I was myself defeated on the question of hurrying forw</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Revision of the P.B.</hi><hi rend="italic"> It was decided, on the motion of the Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, to pubish the Resolution on Reservation adopted by the Bishops in July 1917. I expressed my personal dissent.</hi><hi> After the meeting I walked with the Bishop of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName>, &amp; then dined at the Athenaeum with the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName>. The Death of the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="3129"></persName> is announced in the evening papers – a conscientious, dull, hardworking good man, much respected &amp; nowhere loved.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
