<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1412</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote [to] the Ecclesiastical Secretary of the Lord Chancellor setting forth the reasons why I desire to exchange the patronage of Kimbolton for that of Leominster. It hardly seems to me probable that will seem convincing from the Lord Chancellor's point of view. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I attended a meeting of the Higher Education Committee of the Hertfordshire County Council at 1 p.m. It sate on until 2.15 p.m. There was a question of appointing a Governor of the High School in place of the late Bishop, &amp; Sir John Cotterill<persName xml:id="4535"></persName> proposed Sir Geoffrey Cornwall<persName xml:id="4534"></persName>. Somebody however, proposed me &amp; this seemed generally agreeable so that Sir John withdrew his motion. Afterwards he make a kind of explanation or apology to me, which was quite superfluous. <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> walked with me by the river&#8211;bank &amp; afterwards had tea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Church Family Newspaper has a friendly notice of my volume of sermons: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the Westminster Gazette had a short and unfriendly note</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi> Save for these petty exceptions, the poor thing seems to have been still&#8211;born! After dinner I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>: &amp; wound up a week which has been fussily busy and substantially barren.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
