<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1436</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Warre<persName xml:id="203"></persName> and Jevons<persName xml:id="3455"></persName> were breakfasting in the Athanaeum. The latter asked me whether I could assist him to answer a correspondent who had applied to him for information on the "Bibliography of partings from the time of S. Paul". I said that in my opinion the good man probably meant "partings in literature", and that only a good memory linked with a wide range of reading would serve his turn.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I walked to Westminster for the meeting of the Convocation, and read the Latin Litany. The Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> read the petition which has been circulated throughout the country on the subject of the Virgin&#8211;birth. He told us that in the Province of Canterbury alone no less than 54,000 signatures had been obtained. Considering that the said province contains more than 20,000,000 people, this hardly seems very impressive. I asked whether, when the matter comes on for discussion, I should be in order in moving that the debate be postponed to the next session: the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> replied in the affirmative. There is, I suspect, a general desire to avoid a doctrinal debate, but it may not be easy to do this. I lunched with the Gows<persName xml:id="216"><persName xml:id="542"></persName></persName>. In the afternoon we were mainly concerned with the draft Bill on the Union of Benefices, which the Bishop of Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName> has introduced into the House of Lords. I had tea with the Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, and walked for an hour with him. It is a pity everybody is so appallingly timid.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined with Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName>. It was a pleasant party. There were </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arthur Balfour</hi><persName xml:id="508"></persName><hi rend="italic">, Sir Brian Mahon<persName xml:id="4622"></persName>, Sir C. Craig<persName xml:id="419"></persName>, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Edmund Gosse</hi><persName xml:id="2083"></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Duchess of Abercorn<persName xml:id="4494"></persName>, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Edward<persName xml:id="2052"></persName> &amp; Lady Carson</hi><persName xml:id="4526"></persName><hi rend="italic">, Lady Craig, Lady Cunard, and some other – 14 in all. We all went in promiscuously, ladies leading. I sate between the Duchess of Abercorn &amp; Lady Carson. Both were pleasant, the last delightful. After the ladies had withdrawn, I had some talk with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arthur Balfour</hi><hi rend="italic">. He gave me a racy account of the behaviour of Joffre<persName xml:id="3785"></persName> &amp; Viviani<persName xml:id="4431"></persName> in America. Viviani was unknown, though an ex&#8211;Prime Minister, &amp; a great orator. Joffre was dumb but famous. The relations between the two became so strained that at last they travelled by separate trains. In the Drawing Room I had some conversation with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gosse</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was an eye&#8211;witness of the violent scenes in the Billing<persName xml:id="4655"></persName> trial.<note xml:id="442" n="1"></note> He said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Darling</hi><persName xml:id="4032"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was completely cowed by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Billing</hi><hi rend="italic">. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Villiers&#8211;Stuart<persName xml:id="4694"></persName> is Billing's sister. It was odd to hear </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lady Carson</hi><hi rend="italic"> speaking with such enthusiasm of the bungalow at Birchington. She said her brother &amp; his wife were living at Hereford. He has some occupation in connexion with the munitions factory. If I caught the name correctly, he is called </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Frewer</hi><hi rend="italic">. The world is certainly a much smaller place than we know! I was back in my room shortly after 11 p.m..</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arthur Balfour</hi><hi rend="italic"> looks amazingly well. He has filled out considerably since the days when he was Prime Minister, &amp; he is an admirable talker.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
