<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1361</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather was perfect from beginning to end – the air mild, the sky cloudless, the sun bright &amp; warm. After writing my letters, I motored to Lambton, &amp; spent more than an hour sauntering on the terrace &amp; in the grounds with Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> and Lady Anne<persName xml:id="3504"></persName>.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I never felt more strongly the personal charm of that unfortunate and enigmatic nobleman</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Both adjectives are fitly applied to him, for what misfortune could be greater than that which bound an affectionate man to a wife who, almost from her marriage day, was a hopeless lunatick?<note xml:id="259" n="1"></note> And </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">what enigma could be more baffling than that presented by the combination of so much natural ability and so many inherited advantages with a career so futile &amp; barren</hi><hi rend="i bold">?</hi> <hi rend="italic">I told him that he ought to use his leisure by writing some record of these times. He seemed struck by the idea, &amp; thanked me for the suggestion: but I fear that he is a creature of impulse, of 'fits &amp; starts', never continuing in one stay.</hi><hi> In the afternoon I went to Newcastle, and visited the dentist.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">On my way home, I ran into Morant<persName xml:id="4333"></persName>, whose only son<persName xml:id="4635"></persName> has just been killed in France. He has the aspect of a man who bleeds inwardly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Rogersons<persName xml:id="3438"><persName xml:id="3439"></persName></persName> came to dinner. "Fuzzy" acts as chauffeur. In the "Times" I see the announcement that young Addis<persName xml:id="4495"></persName> has been killed. This news would have been too much for his old father<persName xml:id="1089"></persName>. It is well that he has been taken away in advance of the disaster. There is a brief account of yesterday's proceedings in Durham, and just the truculent piece of my speech!<ref xml:id="1052"></ref><note xml:id="436" n="1"></note></hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
