<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1356</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fair morning, though cold, and a wet afternoon. I wrote a few letters, &amp; then was interviewed by the Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName>, and the Dean<persName xml:id="3741"></persName>. After these prosy magnates had taken their departure,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I walked out &amp; fell in with Sir John Cotterill<persName xml:id="4535"></persName>, who introduced himself &amp; walked with me to the Club<orgName xml:id="318"></orgName>, of which I have just been elected a member</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Then I went to the Palace, where I found the 3 soldiers engaged in mowing the lawn, which they oughtn't to do. I went to Ross, &amp; was there met by the <persName xml:id="4450">Archdeacon's</persName> brougham, &amp; driven to Bridstow. There were a good many matters of diocesan business to talk over with mine host. He opened out beyond my expectations in conversation, and gave expression to more liberal opinions than I had expected to hear from his lips. He even repudiated the description of "High Churchman", which I applied to him. Another <persName xml:id="4701">daughter</persName> of the Archdeacon arrived after dinner with her</hi> <hi rend="underline">fianc&#x00E9;e</hi><hi>, an officer named </hi><persName xml:id="4700"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Westmacott</hi></persName><hi>, who had been slightly wounded in the recent offensive. Both these young women are "strong feminists", and both might be described by an impartial observer as "hard featured". I prefer the older type of girl which belonged to neither category.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I mentioned to mine host, the question of appointing to the vacant Prebend, and I found him well disposed towards my notion of offering it to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi rend="italic">, the Vicar of All Saints, who took a prominent share in organizing opposition to my appointment as Bishop.</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> was not so ready to approve my chivalry.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
