<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[164]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1501</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I breakfasted at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and had much conversation with Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName>. Then I wrote to Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> and <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName>. I walked into the City, &amp; changed a cheque: then I called at the Deanery, &amp; saw Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">He was more than usually gloomy about the war, &amp; foretells revolution at its certain result</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">It certainly is hard to avoid pessimism, when one reads daily of strikes. I bought a few books in Paternoster Row, and went back to the Athanaeum by way of the Embankment. Here I lunched, having as my table comrades Percy Matheson<persName xml:id="2084"></persName> and the Bishop of Sheffield<persName xml:id="3533"></persName>. Then I returned to the Hotel, paid my reckoning, "took up my carriages", and went to Paddington. My journey to Hereford was relieved by the conversation of a young officer of the Naval Brigade, named Price. He told me that he had been educated at Tenbury Musical College (where he had been solo&#8211;boy), &amp; Hereford Cathedral School. He had been a solicitor, &amp; got into the Army from the Inns of Court Territorials. He was now 26 years old. We discussed life in the Army. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He was very frank, said that 80% of the officers "went to pieces" with drink &amp; women, that of these 20% contracted disease. I asked him whether the minority were also those who made some religious profession</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He said this was so but that religion was a less powerful restraining force than fear of disease, &amp; a feeling that one could never ask a decent girl in marriage if one had taken up with the baser sort. I arrived in Hereford about 8 p.m. Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> &amp; Crawford<persName xml:id="4597"></persName> had arrived, &amp; also Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>. The weather was quite cold.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
