<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1425</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, walked into the city and changed a cheque, lunched, walked to Westminster &amp; attended the Bishops' Committee on relations with Nonconformity, returned to the Club, walked with Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> to Brookes &amp; had tea there, then walked to 35 Eaton Sq., and found <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, walked with her, went to the Club, dined, wrote letters, &amp; went to my hotel. Voila tout!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishops of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> and Oxford<persName xml:id="49"></persName> declined to sit on the Committee, the one alleging the excuses of health, the other that of over&#8211;work! Thus the C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> was reduced to four members – the bishops of Ely<persName xml:id="532"></persName>, Ripon<persName xml:id="2074"></persName>, Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, &amp; myself. It was sufficiently obvious that nothing effective could be done &amp; nothing was done.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was surprised, and perhaps a little annoyed, that there was no report of the meeting in Caxton Hall last night. Nor do I think that this was undesigned, for</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName></hi><hi>, whom I met in the Club, said something cryptic about regretting the "polemical" note at the conclusion of my speech! And this was only that I designed to exercise my episcopal power of dispensing with the law impartially! The truth is that the Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName> had its silly head turned by a visit to Lambeth.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName><hi>, whom I met in the Club, &amp; who was himself a member of the deputation, admitted as much. It is clear that the Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> intend that nothing shall be done, but everything evaporate in talk!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
