<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1453</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I began by writing another nonsense&#8211;letter to Adrian</hi><persName xml:id="4831" display="no"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> came to see me, &amp; I took occasion to gather from him as much information as possible. On the whole, what he said was re&#8211;assuring. He described the Vicar of All Saints as a "very High Chairman", extreme "for Hereford", which, perhaps would not be so regarded elsewhere. He thought the said Vicar a fairly straightforward man, and mainly absorbed in the work of his parish. At 3 p.m. Treherne<persName xml:id="4426"></persName> appeared, and talked with me for more than an hour. He told me incidentally that</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hermitage Day</hi><persName xml:id="4190"></persName><hi> had ceased to assist him since my arrival. He has evidently had difficulties of his own with the extremer members of the "Catholic" following. He has no desire to re&#8211;open "S</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Barnabas" at present. It had collected a small clique of none&#8211;too&#8211;loyal "spikes", and become a kind of rival to the parish church. I inquired whether there was any real prospect of such a population growing up in the district as to justify the hope that in process of time a new parish would have to be formed. His answer was in the negative. The Durham paper arrived. It contains an account of Welldon's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> Installation as Dean of Durham. I shall not soon or easily escape a proprietary interest in that description! My appointment to Hereford was gazetted on December 13</hi>               
<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1917. My successor was not installed at Durham until July 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1918 – an interval of more than 7 months. This must be unprecedented for a very long period.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
