<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1386</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A really hot day, befitting July more than May. But truly the world looked beautiful under the sun: &amp; only a resolute effort could keep its profound and continuing misery in mind. I spent the day mostly in the Palace, where the garden is glorious.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> about the restoration of Barnard's music, insisting that it should be effected without delay.<note xml:id="388" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> James Wright came to see me about Ordination. He is 25, has little Latin &amp; no Greek, teaches in a school &amp; has been invalided from the Army for a weak heart – a poor specimen enough. I advised him to get his degree at T.C.D. as a non&#8211;resident student (he has already matriculated), and then approach me again.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Treherne<persName xml:id="4426"></persName>, the Vicar of All Saints, made his statutory declaration &amp; took his oaths as a Prebendary.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> assisted me in arranging the books. They are truly in a wonderful &amp; almost inextricable confusion.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After dinner the Archdeacon of Hereford<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came in to see me about various items of business. I wrote to the Eccles</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi><hi> Comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi> approving the proposed exchange of patronage between the Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="2047"></persName> and the owners of Moreton Court: and also to L. Percival<persName xml:id="4358"></persName> asking that the "Bishop's Charities" might be handed over. The cries of divers widows who cannot get their accustomed pensions pursue me. Indeed it is high time that these business arrangements were completed.</hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
