<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1427</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautifully fine day, and neither hot nor heavy. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Berry<persName xml:id="4130"></persName> fetched me in a taxi soon after breakfast. He is a tall man, goodlooking, with an alert intelligent look, and a pleasant manner. I was told that he is about 36 years old. He wore the hood of an Oxford M.A. and belongs evidently to the "progressive" section of his Church. I suspect that he regrets the collapse of the "new theology" movement. There was a large &amp; attentive congregation in the morning, where I preached on "Reunion", taking for my text: the closing sentence of S. John's first epistle: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Little children, guard yourselves from the idols</hi><hi>". I lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Keape, who entertained me when I made my memorable visit to the Digbeth Institute in 1909. At 3 p.m. I went to a meeting of the Soho Brotherhood, and gave an address to about 300 men. At 6.30 p.m. I preached again at Carr's Lane to a very large congregation. My text was: "</hi><hi rend="underline">If thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord: &amp; shalt believe in thine heart that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved"</hi><hi>. After the service I was taken to an open&#8211;air service for the Navy Mission, and gave a short address. This was rather a poor performance, &amp; confirmed me in my dislike of such services. The taxi that had been ordered failed to turn up, &amp; I kicked my heels outside the parish church for ½ an hour while another was fetched. At last I got home, tired but not wholly discontented with the day's experiences.</hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
