<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1360</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a thick mist before 10 a.m., and after 6 p.m., but the rest of the day was fine, &amp; much warmer. Lord Zetland<persName xml:id="4549"></persName> went away soon after breakfast. I wrote letters until midday, when I strolled with mine hostess until lunch&#8211;time.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">We motored into Durham for the function of the conferring of the Freedom of the City</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> There seemed to be a full gathering of the civic fathers, but the Town Hall was barely half&#8211;full. No attempt had been made to interest the public. Addresses were read of the usual type – verbose &amp; fatuous. I spoke briefly &amp; very badly. Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> was longer &amp; far happier. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> made a short speech. Then some medals were distributed in the market&#8211;place: &amp; I came away to have tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Afterwards I called on Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName>, &amp; the <persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Culley<persName xml:id="3448"></persName> walked with me to the station. I said that I would henceforward call her "Flora" to remind myself of her garden! Then I returned to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, &amp; walked to Lumley<placeName xml:id="62"></placeName>. Lady L.<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> &amp; I dined together very pleasantly, and talked a great deal, mainly about persons &amp;, perhaps, not very charitably. She knows a vast deal of a world into which I have but peeped from over the wall: and I strengthen myself against the blunders of sheer ignorance by listening to her conversation. She has considerable experience of many kinds of war&#8211;work, and her judgment is sound on most practical matters. Nor does her severe &amp; cynical speech give any trustworthy indication of her real mind, which is essentially kind.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
