<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1479</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After a very hot night (hostile to sleep) another hot &amp; brilliant day followed.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote to <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName> thanking him for his volume of essays and pointing out that in my judgement the writers had given too great importance to the tendencies &amp; emotions created by the War, and that they had not realized sufficiently the difference between the physical and the spiritual spheres. For my part I preferred the frankly agnostic position with respect to those high themes rather than speculations which owed their authority to their congruity with emotions and aspiration which perhaps needed discipline rather than indulgence</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi>"The Times" contains two letters on "Reunion" both on my side, the one from the Dean of Worcester<persName xml:id="1814"></persName>, the other from a Methodist minister named Harlow.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">T. A. Lacey</hi><persName xml:id="1936"></persName><hi> has been appointed Canon of Worcester in succession to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knox Little</hi><persName xml:id="376"></persName><hi>. </hi><hi rend="italic">He is a member of the Council of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName>, and can hardly be acceptable to the Dean and Canons. He has a vein of eccentricity in his character which tends to mitigate the rigidity of his orthodoxy</hi><hi>, &amp; latterly </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>he has professed a mighty affection for the Nonconformists.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Harold<persName xml:id="1097"></persName> went to Canterbury in the motor omnibus. I sate in the garden &amp; wrote letter to Archdeacon Winnington Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName>, Canon James<persName xml:id="2619"></persName>, and Fleming<persName xml:id="566"></persName>. </hi><hi rend="italic">I worked after tea at the Warden's<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Journal. He records a story told at a dinner of "the Club" of a Quaker at a teetotal meeting who said he agreed with all the speakers, but would ask them to explain why he so liked his glass of beer!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Carson</hi><persName xml:id="4526"></persName><hi> asking us to tea this afternoon arrived about 7 o'clock. Ella wrote a note explaining the situation, and we walked round with it under the fullest &amp; yellowest moon ever seen!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
