<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1477</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather today has been fine, but not unduly hot. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked out both before lunch and after tea. We noticed that harvesting proceeds steadily in the fields but not rapidly. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tommie Hall</hi><persName xml:id="75"></persName><hi> brought his wife<persName xml:id="1417"></persName> and children to tea. Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> and I cut out paper animals for the amusement of the little girls. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName> sends me the volume which he edited last year, "Immortality an essay in discovery coordinating scientific, psychical, and Biblical Research"<ref xml:id="1019"></ref>. He inserts an inscription in which he calls me "ecclesiæ libertatis propugnatori"</hi><hi> [defender of ecclesiastical liberty]. I could accept the description with more confidence if I could agree with myself upon an understanding of the two words "libertas" and "ecclesia".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
         <hi rend="bold">[129]</hi> [Second entry for date]
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1477</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An over–clouded day but without rain. The post brought me two letters thanking me for my pronouncement in "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Times</hi><hi>", the one from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fleming</hi><persName xml:id="566"></persName><hi>, the other from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon James</hi><persName xml:id="2619"></persName><hi>. "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Times</hi><hi>" itself contained letters from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName></hi><hi> &amp; from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Robinson</hi><persName xml:id="2288"></persName><hi>, neither hostile to me. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName><hi>, and to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Whitehouse</hi><persName xml:id="4704"></persName><hi>, the Vicar of Sellack, whose son </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Whitehouse</hi><persName xml:id="4703"></persName><hi> is reported to have been killed in France. I started reading "</hi><hi rend="underline">Immortality</hi><hi>", judging it best to finish the volume before thanking the donor. The opening essay by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clutton–Brock</hi><persName xml:id="4169"></persName><hi> did not impress me save as wordy &amp; pretentious: but the next essay "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Mind and the Brain</hi><hi>" by a surgeon named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadfield</hi><persName xml:id="4576"></persName><hi> was suggestive &amp; informing. It opens up new ground, and brings together much little known but relevant matter.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the afternoon we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> &amp; I) drove to Minster, &amp; there were joined by Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> &amp; Edward, who came by train from Canterbury. We visited the glorious parish church (</hi><hi rend="bold underline">always interesting to me as the place in which I was baptized,</hi><hi>) and then had tea very pleasantly in a tea–garden, "Rose–dene". Our meal was enlivened by the discovery and destruction of a swarm of winged ants which emerged in the garden–path hard by the place where our tea–table was spread. Petrol was poured upon the creatures &amp; then ignited – a barbarous proceeding. After tea</hi> <hi rend="underline">Ralph</hi><hi> and I walked &amp; talked for an hour, while our wives visited the curiosity shop, and Carissima sate with Edward in the carriage. I was pleased to learn from Ralph that he would have no more dealings with the Peace movement inaugurated by Lord Lansdowne<persName xml:id="1591"></persName>. He said that it had got into the wrong hands, &amp; mentioned Ramsay Macdonald<persName xml:id="891"></persName>. A reference to Sinn Fein at the recent meeting had been received with cheers. We drove back to Birchington under a cloudless sky &amp; through fields from which rich crops of grain were being gathered. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Ralph thinks the philosophical work in Streeter's volume is inadequate. I read most of Streeter's Essay on the Resurrection<ref xml:id="1019"></ref>, and was rather alarmed at his evident inclination to take up with the Psychical Research Society's<orgName xml:id="311"></orgName> attitude, which seems to me essentially materialistic, &amp; to open the door to all the old debasing superstitions. On the whole, I prefer a frankly agnostic position, which seems to me both more reasonable and less perilous. Once allow free speculation in a sphere so charged with estranging emotions, &amp; failure is almost inevitable</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
