<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1514</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The day was generally fair, but cold with occasional showers. I discovered to my horror that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bateman</hi><persName xml:id="4471"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had forgotten to pack my shaving brush! I dressed hastily, and went forth into the town, where, however, every shop was shut, the hour being too early for business. So I was trying to reconcile myself to facing mine hostess in a hirsute condition, when I came upon a chemist's shop which was in the very process of opening. Here at an expenditure of 9/&#8211; I bought a shaving brush, &amp;, returning to the Rectory, completed my toilet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I had much talk with mine host walking in the fine garden. Then I settled down to letter&#8211;writing, &amp; was so engaged until lunch&#8211;time. After a short walk with the Rector<persName xml:id="4330"></persName>, I came back for a garden party, to which the magnates of the church had been invited to meet me, the clergy from the rural deanery &amp; the leading lay&#8211;folk. This went off pleasantly, &amp; I wrote more letters. Then after an early dinner we went to the school&#8211;room where a reception of church&#8211;workers had been arranged, all very kindly. The Rector "introduced" me, &amp; I made a short speech, rambling and foolish! However, it all went off well enough.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">But the broad impression made on my mind was not wholly pleasing.</hi> <hi rend="italic">For this is a parish of 5000 souls, well&#8211;endowed, and, as I am assured, well&#8211;worked: and this little company of perhaps 120 folks, mostly women &amp; girls, represents the Church! There are chapels in the town, which saved religion in the first decade of the XIXth century, when the Rector was an absentee for half the year. And the Church only holds 700 people, yet, as the Churchwarden informed me, it was rarely filled. All this gives much food for thought.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
