<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1512</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Government announces strong measures against the strikers, and undertakes to keep the necessary trains running by using the soldiers</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> It remains to be seen how the rebels will take this unaccustomed rigour.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished the King's College Lecture, &amp; prepared sermon notes. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me in the motor to</hi> <hi rend="underline">Norton</hi><hi>, where I was rather late for the service. I preached to a church full of folks, &amp; afterwards had tea with the Rector, Rev. P. J. Simpson<persName xml:id="4640"></persName>. This parish is doomed to go into Wales so soon as the Welsh Disest</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Act comes into operation. Everybody seems disgusted at the prospect.</hi> <hi rend="italic">We went to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Pembridge</hi><hi rend="italic">, and there I preached to a considerable congregation in one of the noblest parish churches in the diocese. The detached bell&#8211;tower, mostly of timber, is very curious. In the parish church are many features of interest, including an unusually fine font. We had supper with the Vicar (Rev. H. C. Green&#8211;Price<persName xml:id="4237"></persName>). His churchwarden, Gen. Sir Elliott Wood<persName xml:id="4493"></persName>, also came to supper.</hi><hi> We arrived back at the Palace about 10.30 p.m. I found a budget of letters, and a note from <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> saying that the Railway men thought no good purpose would be served by a meeting, at which I would attend &amp; speak. This accorded with my own view, for really there is nothing to discuss. The men have got to give in.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> writes from Canada to say that he has resigned his connexion with the Winnipeg Street Railways C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">y</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
