<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[12]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1367</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Another day spent, and ill&#8211;spent, in Convocation</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> The morning was filled with tiresome talk about the marriages of colonial soldiers to English girls, and with the completion of the debate on the Bishop of Peterborough's<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> resolution. I sate through most of it, but was absent at the end,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">when the Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> "went for" me</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> After lunching with Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, I returned to the Convocation House, where in the course of the afternoon </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I came into sharp collision with the Bishop of Oxford</hi><persName xml:id="49"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">It happened on this wise. The aforesaid Bishop moved a resolution asking the Abp.<persName xml:id="128"></persName> to appoint a Committee to consider a reform of the method of appointing bishops. He disclaimed any reference to my appointment to Hereford. But </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">this seemed to me a gratuitous piece of hypocrisy: and I replied in a fierce speech</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I spoke with brutal frankness about the recent agitation, &amp; let their Lordships know the mingled scorn and resentment which had been moved in me. It was probably a foolish proceeding on my part.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> carried his motion by 13 votes to 6. The last were: Exeter<persName xml:id="31"></persName>, Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName>, Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, LLandaff<persName xml:id="3489"></persName>, S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName>, &amp; Hereford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After the meeting, I walked to the Temple, &amp; had an interview with my Chancellor, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Ernest Charles<persName xml:id="4529"></persName>, at his chambers, 2 Mitre Court Buildings. He seems an amiable &amp; intelligent person. I asked him about the legal aspect of the sale of the music by the Hereford Chapter: &amp; he said that it was illegal.<note xml:id="388" n="1"></note> Then I walked back to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; there dined. I wrote letters after dinner.</hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
