<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1473</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi> <hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Before getting up I read aloud to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> Cowper's<persName xml:id="4537"></persName> "Expostulation"<ref xml:id="1015"></ref>. It would be difficult to improve upon the following as a description of our "Ritualists": it is by the Poet himself applied generally, though suggested by the religious decay of ancient Israel: &#8211;</hi>   
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Then Ceremony leads her bigots forth,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Prepar'd to flight for shadows of no worth;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>While truths, on which eternal things depends,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Find not, or hardly find, a single friend: </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As soldiers watch the signal of command,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>They learn to bow, to kneel, to sit, to stand;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Happy to fill religion's vacant place, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>With hollow form, and gesture, and grimace. </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>It is in this poem that the famous denunciation of the Test Act<note xml:id="448" n="1"></note> occurs. It follows a remarkable description of the "nabob's" career: The poet addresses Britain thus unflatteringly: &#8211; </hi>  
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Hast thou, though suckled at fair Freedom's breast,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Exported slavery to the conquer'd east?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Pull'd down the tyrants India served with dread,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And raised thyself a greater, in their stead?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Gone thither arm'd and hungry, return'd full,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Fed from the richest veins of the Mogul,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A despot big with power obtained by wealth,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And that obtained by rapine and by stealth? </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>With Asiatic vices stored thy mind, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But left their virtues and thine own behind? </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And, having truck'd thy soul, brought home the fee,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To tempt the poor to sell himself to thee? </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>[ All this might be applied not unfairly to our Rand millionaires, and rubber speculators, who have shone in Park Lane of late years. ]</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Hast thou by statute shoved from its design</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Saviour's Feast, his own bless'd bread and wine,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And made the symbols of atoning grace</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An office&#8211;key, a picklock to a place,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That infidels may prove their title good</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>By an oath dipp'd in sacramental blood?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A blot that will be still a blot, in spite </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Of all that brave apologists may write:</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And though a bishop toil to cleanse the stains,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He wipes and scours the silver cup in vain. </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>[The bishop presumably was the braggart, carnal, paradoxical Warburton<persName xml:id="3959"></persName> who represented the Test Act as the essential feature of Establishment.]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In 1785 Cooper published "Tirocinium; or a Review of Schools"<ref xml:id="1016"></ref>, in which he drew a dark picture of the public schools of the time, &amp; denounced them as morally contaminating and intellectually sterilizing. It is gloomily suggestive that precisely the same picture has recently been drawn by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Aleck Waugh</hi><persName xml:id="4435"></persName><hi>, a Sherborne boy, in "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Loom of Youth</hi><hi>". Probably in 1917 as in 1785 there was exaggeration, but, as probably, the broad impression conveyed is not unjust.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
