<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[152]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1490</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful autumnal morning. Water wagtails make great sport on the lawn: and a pair of thrushes showed themselves, but the fewness of these beautiful birds distresses me. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> says that a brace of owls are haunting the garden, and thinks that their presence scares the thrushes. It may be so, yet a thrush ought to stand up to an owl! I celebrated in the Lady Chapel, or (as it is called) S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's. I preached at S. Nicholas to a scanty congregation (many being absent on holiday, and nobody having had notice of my coming) on Jacob's Vision – being the 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> repetition of a sermon originally written for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret's Westminster in 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Instead of going to the Cathedral at Evensong I stayed in my study, and wrote letters. It appears that at the last meeting of the Church &amp; State Committee, when I was absent on account of illness, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the clause reserving "the powers &amp; functions inherent in the Episcopate" was adopted</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> tells me that there was but a scanty attendance of the members, when this momentous step was taken. I suspect that Lords Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> and Wolmer<persName xml:id="1028"></persName> with Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> have been putting great pressure on their Graces, who (like all Scots) are extremely deferential to the "lords of the congregation"! The pressure has not been ineffectual. A "time&#8211;limit" has been imposed on our Committee's discussions by the convening of the Representative Church Council in November. We </hi><hi rend="italic underline">must</hi><hi rend="italic"> be ready with our Report against that meeting!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[153]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Bishop of Manchester</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>September 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>, 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I had been assured by the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> there was in his judgement no likelihood of the clause reserving "the powers &amp; functions </hi><hi rend="underline">inherent in</hi><hi> the Episcopate" being discussed, &amp; therefore, I was startled to learn that the clause had been adopted. To my thinking that clause is of supreme and fatal significance. It takes what has hitherto been the "pious opinion" of a party and incorporates it into the constitution of the Church of England. It gives official endorsement to the episcopalian doctrine of Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> and repudiates that of Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName>: it closes the door on any honest negotiation with non&#8211;episcopalians: and it categorically repudiates the principle &amp; method of the English Reformation. Evangelicals may as well admit at once that they have no place in the Church of England. On merely practical grounds, it would seam indispensable that the "inherent powers &amp; function" should be stated, defined, &amp; conditioned. Not to do this is to leave the whole settlement at the mercy of any "highflying" bishop who chooses to think that his "inherent" authority ("jus liturgicum" [law of the liturgy], "donum veritatis" [gift of truth], what you will of obsolete folly) covers the matters with which the Church Council deals. Is Ordination an "inherent" function of the Episcoate? Then all non&#8211;episcopal ministries</hi>           
<hi rend="bold">[154]</hi><hi> are disallowed. Are Evangelicals prepared for that?</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Is Confirmation? Then the Eastern Churches &amp; the Lutherans are ruled out. Is doctrinal definition? Then the English system is condemned. I am amazed at the frivolity which has marked the action of the Committee: &amp; I doubt whether the vote was carried by half the members. This point seems to me so far more considerable than all the others that they hardly seem important. I agree that there should be a meeting of those who cannot accept the majority decisions: and I will make a point of attending on Monday, the 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> at 5.15 p.m. if you arrange a meeting.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I cannot help feeling that this whole matter is being dealt with behind our backs. Their Graces are playing a double part, in the seat of impartial authority</hi> <hi rend="underline">and</hi><hi> in the counsels of the minority faction.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, ever sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Wolmer's amendment would involve the stultification of the whole scheme.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
