<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1446</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My infirmities grow upon me, so that work is impossible. I crawl through the indispensable things, and attempt nothing else. We motored to Ledbury, and lunched with</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Biddulph</hi><persName xml:id="4134"></persName><hi> who lives in a large timbered house, of which a considerable portion runs back to 1590. Prince Rupert<persName xml:id="4666"></persName> slept there during the Civil War, when Ledbury was the scene of a smart skirmish. There was a garden party in aid of the Church Army<orgName xml:id="50"></orgName> Hut Fund. The meeting was incommoded by rain. I made a speech, &amp; was followed by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Claud Lighton</hi><persName xml:id="4612"></persName><hi>. Over &#x00A3;25 was collected. On our way home we called at Tarrington Vicarage, and had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Green&#8211;Price<persName xml:id="4572"></persName>, the Rector, &amp; his wife. This is a pretty parish with an attractive &amp; well&#8211;kept Church, dedicated to S. Philip &amp; S. James. The Vicar told me that among his 476 parishioners there are no dissenters. He bewailed his ill&#8211;success in getting his parishioners to receive the Holy Communion, though they attended church well. He had arranged a choral Celebration on the 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> Sunday of the month at 10 a.m., which he hoped might tend to increase the number of communicants. On the whole I was favourably impressed by this clergyman. We called also at the Rectory, Stoke Edith, but the Onslows<persName xml:id="4643"></persName> were not at home.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">After dinner D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Pattison<persName xml:id="4893" display="no"></persName> came &amp; inspected my state</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He injected carbolic acid into the boil on my neck, &amp; gave me various instructions. But my condition was woefully uncomfortable, &amp; I decided to adopt the Leech's counsel to cancel my engagements in London next week.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
