<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1396</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Germans continue to advance, &amp; have taken Soissons. Tanks &amp; machine&#8211;guns assist their progress. It is very disconcerting.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in the Committee. My speech on the position assigned to the bishops provoked a considerable debate. I did not get my way, but I think the episode was educationally useful. I lunched with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, who is becoming a power through is work on the "Times". Then I attended the annual meeting of the Harley Trustees<orgName xml:id="308"></orgName> in Sicilian Avenue, Bloomsbury Square. Then I walked to Palace Street &amp; called on Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, with whom I talked for nearly an hour. On returning to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I found Asquith<persName xml:id="215"></persName> reading the telegrams, &amp; spoke to him. He was rather gloomy about the situation at the Front, and spoke of the danger of the French 'breaking'. But one must always discount the vaticinations of Opposition statesmen!</hi>        
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The papers are filled with reports of a nauseous libel action brought by the notorious dancer, Maud Allan<persName xml:id="4496"></persName>, against the self&#8211;advertizing quack, Pemberton&#8211;Billing<persName xml:id="4655"></persName>.<note xml:id="442" n="1"></note> It is a strange and melancholy thing, not without a certain suggestiveness, that at this solemn juncture, when the fate of the world hangs in the balance, &amp; every hour witnesses the death of our youth, the public interest should be diverted to so squalid &amp; depraving a spectacle. The names of public men &amp; women are bandied about in the most infamous connexions to the exceeding disgrace of society.</hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
