<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[13]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1368</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather became milder. I spent the day in Convocation, and lunched with Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName>. Just before the afternoon session began, the</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> stepped up to my seat, and said: "On the balance of the two speeches, yours &amp; Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, I think you were in the right". I replied that I was glad to know that his Grace thought so, but that I myself on the whole was disposed to regret having spoken at all. "Well, since you say that", said the Archbishop, "I will say that I wish you hadn't". So it stands at that. Everybody feels that I had great provocation: &amp; everybody wishes that I had not yielded to it. And that is substantially my own view of the episode</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Bishop of Bristol<persName xml:id="2533"></persName> moved a resolution, the effect of which was to "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">call a halt</hi><hi>" in the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">process of treating the decisions of Convocation as if they possessed statutory authority</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Gore supported this in a speech of characteristic extravagance. The Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> was opposed, &amp; spoke with much sophistical acuteness, though at the end he acquiesced in the vote. I spoke in support of the motion,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">criticising both Gore &amp; Talbot with some freedom</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> In the end the motion was adopted </hi><hi rend="underline">nem. con.</hi><hi> Then I went with the Bishop of Bristol to have tea with Colonel<persName xml:id="1659"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Burdon<persName xml:id="2981"></persName>. I returned to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> for dinner, &amp; was there joined by Mead&#8211;Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>, who induced me to enlarge my meal to the utmost limits of this frugal time! But it is a rare &amp; notable thing to meet a friend in these strenuous days, and we may well be pardoned if we make of it a festival.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
