<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[89]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1442</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote a cheque (&#x00A3;250) for Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Robson &amp; Sons to pay for their charges in removing my furniture from Durham to Hereford. Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName> went back to London after breakfast. Beyond writing a number of letters, and having an interview with the Bishop of Sodor &amp; Man<persName xml:id="3229"></persName>, I did nothing worth speaking of. After lunch I wrote more letters, and rolled the lawn. The rain which had threatened all day came on to fall heavily at eventide. At 8 p.m. I presided at a lecture in the interest of S.P.C.K. in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's Institute. The lecturer, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Goodchild, railed at the Germans in the popular style. His concluding slide was one of the Crucifixion which seemed to jar violently with his speech.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I could not refrain from dissociating myself from the tone &amp; tendency of the lecture</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> But in the present fever it is little use to make an effort to call people to sanity. One only draws suspicion upon one's own self.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This morning I sent a cheque of one hundred pounds (&#x00A3;100) to Prebendary Hopton<persName xml:id="4280"></persName> as my subscription to the Diocesan Finance. The evening paper reports the resumption of the German Offensive, &amp; the usual initial successes. The enemy will not be assisted by the weather as heretofore; &amp; Foch<persName xml:id="4563"></persName> can hardly be taken by surprise. Nor can the numbers of the opposing armies be so unequal. More than a million Americans must make a great difference even though most of them are comparatively half&#8211;trained. If the statistics of the destruction of aeroplanes are trustworthy, our flying men are overwhelmingly superior.</hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
