<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1428</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The singular project of concurrent re&#8211;ordination in the interest of ecclesiastical reunion, which the fertile mind of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamilton Baynes</hi><persName xml:id="4124"></persName><hi> has suggested, does not appear to have made progress. It seems to be essentially identical with the plan which Briggs<persName xml:id="2044"></persName> of the Union Seminary, New York, expounded to me. But it could not possibly succeed because it must needs arouse against itself precisely those in every church who take the most spiritual view of the ministry. Their scruples can hardly be removed by a proposition which implies that Ordination is no more than a ceremonial or legal preliminary to ministry. No: we must approach the practical problem from the opposite point of view. Ministry is so essentially a Divinely ordered, Divinely enabled thing, that where it is found, it </hi> <hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> be owned and honoured. And the evidence of Ministry must be its fruits in the holiness of the minister, and the results of his work. "</hi><hi rend="underline">By their fruits ye shall know them</hi><hi>". But who shall guarantee holiness in anyone? And who shall measure the spiritual quality of any man's ministry? Inevitably we are brought back to the prosaic question of formal credentials: and this raises the more difficult question of the right to grant them: and this the whole tiresome interminable wrangle about "Apostolic Succession". At least we know that Apostolic succession, where it is most confidently claimed, </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">secures</hi><hi> to the ordained minister </hi><hi rend="underline">neither</hi><hi> personal holiness, </hi><hi rend="underline">nor</hi><hi> ministerial success.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">It</hi><hi> cannot enable any man to pass Christ's test of a true prophet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent some time in the garden after breakfast talking with a young man, staying in the house, named Vincent, a relation (grandson, I think) of old Sir William Vincent<persName xml:id="2181"></persName>. After depositing my bags at the station, I lunched with</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Hamilton Baynes</hi><hi>, and heard from him a full account of his reunion&#8211;project. He had been to Farnham to talk it over with the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName>, &amp; had not received much encouragement. He thought the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> was timorous, &amp; disinclined for anything that might provoke discussion.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I travelled to Hereford by a train which left Birmingham at 3.50 p.m., and arrived at 6.3 p.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived from London about dinner&#8211;time.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "</hi><hi rend="underline">Westminster Gazette</hi><hi>" prints the following lines of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Crashaw</hi><persName xml:id="4539"></persName><hi>, under the heading </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>"Thought for the day":</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Days, that in spite</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Of darkness, by the light</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Of a clear mind, are day all night.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Life that dares send</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A challenge to his end,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And, when it comes, say, Welcome, friend.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I found a package awaiting me. It contained a little silver cup with an inscription: "H. H. H. d.d. J. G. W.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Sis memor nostri</hi><hi>". A kind letter from Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> explained that it was an acknowledgment of much kind hospitality. It is pleasant to be thus remembered. I wonder whether they will all take to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName><hi> as heartily as they seem to have taken to me.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
