<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1485</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Cowper<persName xml:id="4537"></persName>, in "Conversation"<ref xml:id="1024"></ref>, dwells feelingly on the taciturnity of ordinary Englishmen:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>Few Frenchmen of this evil have complained;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It seems as if we Britons were ordained,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>By way of wholesome curb upon our pride,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To fear each other, fearing none beside.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>He describes vividly the portentous dullness of conventional society:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>The circle form'd, we sit in silent state,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Like figures drawn upon a dial–plate;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yes, ma'am, and no, ma'am, uttered softly, show</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Every five minutes how the minutes go;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Each individual, suffering a constraint</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Poetry may, but colours cannot, paint.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The sense of relief when the boring duty has at length been achieved could not be pictured more justly than in these lines:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>The visit paid, with ecstasy we come,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As from a seven years' transportation, home,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And there resume an unembarrass'd brow,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Recovering what we lost we know not how,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The faculties, that seem'd reduced to naught,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Expression, and the privilege of thought.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>On the experience of acute personal suffering could have inspired such lines. I am free to endorse them as nowise exaggerated when applied to the "social duties" of the 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Century.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He describes a curious revival of paganism among his contemporaries which could hardly have been more than an affectation like the sham Gothic of the period:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>It has indeed been told me (with what weight,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>How credibly, 'tis hard for me to state),</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That fables old, that seem'd for ever mute,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Revived, are hastening into fresh repute, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And gods and goddesses discarded long,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Like useless lumber, or a stroller's song.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Are bringing into vogue their heathen train,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And Jupiter bids fair to rule again;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That certain feasts are instituted now,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Where Venus hears the lover's tender vow;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That all Olympus through the country roves,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To consecrate our few remaining groves.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And Echo learns politely to repeat</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The praise of names for ages obsolete;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>That having proved the weakness, it should seem</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Of Revelation's ineffectual beam,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>To bring the passions under sober sway,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And give the moral springs their proper play,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>They mean to try what may at last be done</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>By stout substantial gods of wood and stone,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>And whether Roman rites may not produce</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The virtues of old Rome for English use.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This morning I received the following epistle:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Aug. 21</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">B.E.F. France</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Your Grace,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My bâtman, a very nice boy, comes from Durham, and he was talking to me today about his home. He told me that Durham was "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">only a small place, Sir, but it's become quite famous lately because of its Dean.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He has just been made a Bishop. You may have heard of him, Sir, his name is Henson".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I feel sure that your Grace's sense of humour will rejoice to hear the origin of the fame of the little place called Durham.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I am, Your Grace's obedient Servant,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">E. H. Welby</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Rt. Reverend the Bishop of Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I called on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Serres<persName xml:id="4066"></persName>, the Vicar. He told me that some weeks since he had written to the Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, asking permission to invite a Nonconformist Minister to read the lesson &amp; some of the prayers on August 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, at the special service, &amp; that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">his Grace had replied, expressing sympathy with his desire, but advising him against carrying out his plan! A fortnight later the service in Canterbury took place "with his grace's approval", &amp; there dissenting ministers both prayed &amp; preached. I must needs suspect the Archbishop of a certain incorrigible habit of worshipping "the jumping cat"</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I called on the Matron at Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> Hospital, and had some talk with her patients.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
