<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1510</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fine but chilly day. The Archdeacon of Hereford<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came for me, and at noon we started in the car for a little round of visitations. We visited the following:</hi>  
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item> 
<hi rend="underline">Much Dewchurch</hi><hi>, a fine church with a Jacobean pulpit, and a very fine monument to the Pye family. Here we lunched with the Vicar (Rev. E. Brooke Bradley<persName xml:id="4518"></persName>), a strong but not very amiable looking parson, who hailed from the Gloucester Diocese.</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline">S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Weonard's</hi><hi>, This is an unusually interesting church with fine wooden screens, a 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century window, a huge old chest, a Jacobean pulpit, &amp; a fine tower. The parson, Rev. G. H. Davis<persName xml:id="4543"></persName>, is a Christian Socialist, at cross&#8211;purposes with his people, once a curate of Jimmy <persName xml:id="88">Adderley</persName>, &amp; now more than usually sad for the loss of his son in France. I was touched by his miserable look.</hi>  
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline">Tretire</hi><hi>, a squalid modern church without redeeming feature.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline">Whitchurch</hi><hi>, a fairly interesting church. The font (Norman) very fine. The parson, Rev. D. O. Thomas<persName xml:id="4912"></persName>, had had an American Baptist minister to preach for him at his Harvest Thanksgiving yesterday.</hi>  
            </item>
            <item>
<hi rend="underline">Goodrich</hi><hi>, a squalid church. We had tea with Prebendary Seaton<persName xml:id="4672"></persName> &amp; his wife.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He showed me a beautiful chalice presented to the Church by Dean Swift<persName xml:id="4012"></persName>, and bearing a inscription to the effect that it had been used for private celebrations by his grandfather, Thomas Swift<persName xml:id="4686"></persName>, who was Vicar of the parish.</hi> 
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>I got home shortly before 7 p.m., &amp; learned that </hi><hi rend="bold underline">a railway strike was imminent at Hereford</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The times are out of joint.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At Goodrich a brother<persName xml:id="4604"></persName> of Lord Knollys<persName xml:id="1313"></persName>, lately the Vicar of Folkestone, and now a resident in Goodrich, has undertaken the office of churchwarden. He is a tall &amp; fine&#8211;looking man, whose conversation did not bear out the promise of his appearance. I was, however, told that he had but recently lost his daughter, &amp; this may explain his conversational ineptitude. Prebendary Seaton has been Vicar of Goodrich since 1875, a period of 43 years. He had previously been Curate of the same parish for 9 years. Thus his ministry in that place has continued for 52 years without a break. His wife told me that they observed but small change in the parish.</hi>      
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
