<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1406</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The sky is overcast, the glass has fallen: there is a sound of rain in the air. I went to the Cathedral, and received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m.: and then set my face towards the troubled &amp; troublesome parish of</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bredwardine</hi><hi>, which still lies vicar&#8211;less after many months. The dilapidated state of the vicarage deters men from coming. Add that the churchwardens are quarrelling, &amp; that one of them is of the gentler sex! I had a pleasant day on the whole. There was a fair congregation at Mattins, and quite a large one at Evensong. I lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Willliams</hi><hi>, the Vicar's warden, and had tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Philipson</hi><persName xml:id="4363"></persName><hi>, the People's Warden.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">My sermons were designed to promote peace in the parish, &amp; were listened to very closely</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> In the afternoon I took the service in Brobury, where the chancel of the church, destroyed by faculty in 1873, has survived as a mortuary chapel. Thus I preached 3 extempore sermons in one day, besides reading the service. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Turner</hi><persName xml:id="4691"></persName><hi>, the parson to whom at my request the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> offered Bredwardine, motored over to see me, &amp; caught me just as I was leaving the church at Brobury. He is a vacillating kind of man, given to procrastination, &amp; he "funks" the vicarage house. I told him he ought to accept the living.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Sunday paper reports the appointment of Bishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName><hi rend="italic"> as Dean of Durham. He is 64 years old, the right age for a Dean. He has a high record, academic &amp; educational, &amp; so far he will satisfy the conditions of that Deanery.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">But he is fundamentally, a wind&#8211;bag, &amp; has just signed an "orthodox" petition</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
