<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1402</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The most scandalous law&#8211;suit within living memory ended yesterday with the acquittal of the most impudent libeller since Titus Oates<persName xml:id="4642"></persName>.<note xml:id="442" n="1"></note> We are manufacturing the "psychological climate" of revolution at a great pace. Proeter&#8211;natural </hi><hi> [sic]</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">suspicion is in the air, &amp; no lie is too monstrous for public acceptance. Pemberton&#8211;Billing</hi><persName xml:id="4655"></persName><hi> is one of those sinister figures which presage disaster to the society which they disturb and exploit.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Maud Allan</hi><persName xml:id="4496"></persName><hi> is, of course, merely a fragment of the garbage which accumulates in our modern world, infecting and exhausting it. The worst feature of the whole miserable case is that there does exist just enough truth in the vast lie to paralyze those who would punish the brazen Liar. "We are betrayed by what is false within".</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">While the nation has been absorbed in its Scandal, the critical battle of the War proceeds in France</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I motored to Ganarew, a little parish near Monmouth on the edge of the diocese, &amp; lunched in an extremely beautiful place with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Levett, who is purchasing the property which he has been renting for 4 years past. He &amp; his wife are full of complaints of their parson, the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> W. O. Jones<persName xml:id="4600"></persName>, who resides in Monmouth. The whole population of the parish is but 137, and there is no vicarage house. The patronage belongs to Oriel College. I half&#8211;promised to spend a Sunday at Ganarew, and to bring <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> with me. The Levetts strike me as kindly folk, who are not very "churchy", but disposed to be helpful. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> recommends a gardener, but he wants 45/&#8211; per week, which is a larger sum than I have contemplated. However – [sic, end of entry]</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
