<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1362</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Again, a perfect day. I spent most of it in the open air. After writing to Olaf Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="2128"></persName> and Bishop Lawrence<persName xml:id="931"></persName>, I sate on the south side of the castle for two hours before lunch, and after lunch accompanied her in the motor to Seaham, where we visited the convalescent home for soldiers in Seaham house, visited two churches, one quite modern &amp; the other very ancient, and had tea. Lady L.<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> presented a military medal with a clasp to a soldier named Barrow. The whole company were then photographed. The little church hard by Seaham Hall is extremely interesting. It belongs to the earliest period of our ecclesiastical history, and presents many points of challenging distinctiveness. Thus, in the recess on the south wall of the chancel, which is</hi> <hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi> a piscina, &amp; may be a quasi&#8211;credence table, there is carved a hand in benediction. I have never seen that in any other church. This church was the scene of</hi> <hi rend="italic"> Byron's ill&#8211;fated marriage with Miss Milbank<persName xml:id="4639"></persName>, who then lived in Seaham Hall. The old parson, hopelessly deaf, offered to shew me the marriage&#8211;register. Lady L. and I dined together very pleasantly. I was again impressed with the violence of her language, and the goodness of her heart! Our conversation became very intimate, and we were deeply pledged to the secresies of friendship. It is well enough. I would not betray a friend: &amp; I could not if I would, for such is the weakness of my memory, that I never retain in my mind for more than a few hours even the most interesting communications!!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
