<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1404</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have chosen my text for the sermon at Oxford: it will fit in well enough with the historical retrospect suggested by the Commemoration, &amp; will lend itself properly to some reflections on the situation which the War is creating. It is, moreover, a text which has always appealed to me strangely: "</hi><hi rend="underline">The world passeth away, &amp; the lust thereof, but he that doeth the Will of God abideth for ever</hi><hi>". I spent the morning in making notes for a sermon on this text, but my progress was not encouraging. After lunch I motored to Bishop Eaton, or rather</hi> <hi rend="underline">Eaton Bishop</hi><hi>, and called on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> O'Neil</hi><persName xml:id="4641"></persName><hi> the parson, a cheerful man, who received me with kindness, &amp; showed me his church. This has two very notable features – a squat, square Norman tower, and some wonderful 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century painted glass in the chancel. I called also on the</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Right Hon</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">ble</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> William Crooks</hi><persName xml:id="857"></persName><hi>, who has been visiting his niece, a farmer's wife in this parish. I was distressed to notice how ill the good man looked, &amp; gratified by the warmth of his welcome. The farmer,</hi> <hi rend="underline">Mutlow</hi><hi>, shewed me some very fine Herefords. One bull was a truly formidable beast to look at. I caused Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> to pack &amp; send off copies of my new volume to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; to Lawrence Holt<persName xml:id="3655"></persName>. Also I wrote to Major<persName xml:id="3660"></persName></hi> <hi rend="bold underline">offering him the sermon on Reunion which was preached in S. Martin's last Sunday</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Bonar–Law<persName xml:id="2278"></persName>, in answer to a question in the House, said that the Deanery of Durham had been offered to somebody. I suppose this must mean that Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> will exchange Manchester for Durham.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
