<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1504</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A wet morning succeeded a wet night and presented to view the melancholy spectacle of sodden Nature. I revised the sermon which I propose to preach at Holmer. It was written originally for Westminster Abbey, &amp; was there preached on April 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1910. Its subject is "Christ's Treatment of Questioners", and its text, S. Luke XIII. 23, 24. "</hi><hi rend="underline">And one said unto Him, Lord, are there few that be saved? And He said unto them, Strive to enter in by the Narrow Door: for many, I say unto you, shall seek to enter in, &amp; shall not be able".</hi><hi> We (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, &amp; I with Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> on the box) drove to Holmer, and there I peached, and celebrated the Holy Communion. The little church (S. Batholomew's) was fairly filled. It is an aisle&#8211;less building with two interesting features – a timbered tower, and a 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century roof transferred from one of the episcopal residences to the chancel, which it doesn't fit. After lunch I went with Ella to the Union, &amp; there preached to the "inmates" and their "Guardians", who were keeping a Harvest festival. The service ended, we walked round the wards. At tea&#8211;time Miss Squire from the Munitions central office came to see me, and talked much of the necessity of "doing something" for the munitions workers: but I hardly see what there is to do, or who is to do it. The difficulties mainly arise from the smallness of the city, these excellent officials wonder why Hereford cannot do what Manchester, &amp; towns of that sort succeed in doing. The answer lies on the face of the question.</hi>      
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
