<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[120]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1470</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The brilliant weather continues, &amp; the good news from France. Sounds of gun&#8211;firing went along with the rattle of the aeroplanes to keep the War always in our minds. I wrote to Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> suggesting a possible scheme of my lecture on "The Anglican Version of X</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ty</hi><hi>" for King's College in October. I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> start by picturing the ordinary Englishman's religion in the year 1500, and comparing it with what it had become in 1600, in 1700, in 1800, and in 1900. I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> then distinguish the salient notes of the new "Anglicanism". It was insular, Biblical, secular, individualistic. Severally these "notes" were most apparent at the several dates. Then I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> inquire whether any, and if so what, principles were implicit in these "notes": &amp;, finally, ask what future lay before this version of Christianity.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Philip le Mesurier</hi><persName xml:id="3919"></persName><hi> writes in reply to a letter in which I had asked, half playfully, how he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to be a bishop's chaplain, and had mentioned the probable acceptance of Almeley by Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName>. He takes the suggestion most seriously, and exults in the half&#8211;disclosed prospect of</hi> <hi rend="underline">his</hi><hi> becoming Norcock's successor. As he is still a good way from being qualified to take Holy Orders, the matter can hardly be called urgent, but I am compelled to ask myself whether he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> really be well&#8211;suited for my purpose, and I am equally compelled at present to answer that I have no adequate reason for thinking that he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> make a good chaplain.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
