<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1403</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day has been wasted. The heavy state of the atmosphere would in any case have made effort very difficult, but I have the further disadvantage of finding myself quite unable to make up my mind what to do. The sermon at Oxford on the 23</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> haunts me. What shall I preach about? In the afternoon I visited the Industrial Boys' Home<orgName xml:id="309"></orgName>. There are more than a hundred boys, mostly sent from London Unions, being taught useful trades. They looked a low type, such as the slums evolve. The institution did not wholly please me, though the object is unquestionably excellent. I presided at the annual meeting which was very thinly attended.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Admiral Sir Day Bosanquet</hi><persName xml:id="4515"></persName><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Elliott Wood</hi><persName xml:id="4493"></persName><hi> were among the speakers. Rather grim old boys both of them, but civil to me.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moore</hi><persName xml:id="4331"></persName><hi> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Peter's is the Chaplain of the Home.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He walked back with me to the Close, &amp; told me that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hermitage Day</hi><persName xml:id="4190"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had entreated</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi rend="italic"> to refuse the Prebend! I went through my letters with Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName></hi><hi>. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came in with a long face to say that about 80 clergy from his archdeaconery had not returned the papers about military service.<note xml:id="415" n="1"></note> Is this the beginnings of the clercial boycott with which I have been threatened? More probably, it is sheer slackness, but anything is possible, &amp; </hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I move in an atmosphere of treason in an unknown land</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> The outlook has an uncommonly black look today: Why?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
