<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1424</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The proceedings in the Committee were of no great interest or importance. Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> and I united in a vigorous protest against reporting to the Representative Church Council in October. The session ended at 1.30 p.m. I lunched with Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName>.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">At 5.30 p.m. I attended a meeting of the Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName> at the Caxton hall, and made a speech on Exchange of pulpits. The Bishop of Carlisle<persName xml:id="720"></persName> was there</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> An excellent paper on the "Liberty of Prophesying"<ref xml:id="1008"></ref> was read by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macan</hi><persName xml:id="4619"></persName><hi>, the Master of University. He thanked me for my Commem. sermon, which, he said, had impressed everybody as "entirely adequate" to the occasion. A young clergyman asked to be introduced to me. He said that a sermon of mine in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret's, which he had heard one Easter day, had converted him from agnosticism to faith. He expressed himself with some ardour. I dined with</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Mundella</hi><persName xml:id="2712"></persName><hi>. The party consisted of Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName>, Sir J. Murray, ^Lady Murray^, Admiral Paget<persName xml:id="4894"></persName>, Lady Paget, Lady Cromer<persName xml:id="1144"></persName>, Lady Romer<persName xml:id="4663"></persName>, Sir Robert Younger<persName xml:id="4071"></persName>, myself, &amp; Miss M<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>. For some reason or other, I found the evening dull, &amp; indeed was positively bored. Probably the fault was wholly in myself. Lady Romer drove me to Gloucester Road Station, from whence I got a train to Charing Cross &amp; so home shortly after 11 p.m. Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> offers "chapter &amp; verse" for his accusation against the Roman Catholic clergy in Ireland by publishing a sheaf of extracts from sermons by Irish priests. Nothing could be more treasonable, &amp; wicked. Yet the Irish bishops pretend to be injured by the charge!</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
