<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[5]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1359</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I paid my reckoning, &amp; caught the 10 a.m. express to York: there I changed into another train, &amp; so got to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street about 4.45 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Lord Zetland<persName xml:id="4549"></persName> was in the train; &amp; we proceeded together to Lumley</hi><placeName xml:id="62"></placeName><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> On the journey I read and reflected upon the Budget proposals. They are sufficiently alarming. The income tax and super tax together will sweep away nearly half my income! I bought at King's Cross, &amp; read through in the train, the translation of <persName xml:id="1527">Licknowski's</persName> revelations. They ought to open the eyes of the German people, and, as they are allowed to be sold everywhere in Germany, there is no reason why they sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not do so, unless it be indeed the case that the German Government has succeeded in perverting the popular understanding so effectually that no truth can find entrance into the popular mind. Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> received me with much kindness: we walked together in the grounds before dinner. It was "pretty" to see her Ladyship feed the pigeons. The birds have become so familiar that they settle on her hands, and feed therefrom. One, more audacious than the rest, actually perched on my hat! We had much conversation at dinner, &amp; afterwards Lady L professes the most ferocious sentiments against the Germans; but she has too kind a heart to ever allow her sentiments to find expression in practice. Lord Zetland told me what I had quite forgotten, that he was once Lord Lieutenant of Ireland. He takes a gloomy view of the present situation in that intractable &amp; unintelligible island.</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
