<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1441</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Collect for this Sunday is impressed on my mind more deeply than the rest because it was a favourite of my Father<persName xml:id="83"></persName>, &amp; entered frequently into the m</hi><hi rend="italic">&#x00E9;</hi><hi rend="italic">lange of prayers read and improvised which made up the daily worship of the household. It is a very perfect example of the Prayer&#8211;Book style – dignified, vague, easy to remember, impossible wholly to forget:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"Lord of all power &amp; might, who art the author &amp; giver of all good things; Graft in our hearts the love of thy Name, increase in us true religion, nourish us with all goodness, &amp; of thy great mercy keep us in the same; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen"</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">That is not the kind of prayer which could satisfy the demands of that materialised multitude of whom the Duke of Rutland<persName xml:id="2517"></persName> has made himself the unexpected but not unsuitable mouthpiece.<note xml:id="443" n="1"></note> The papers are dubbing his Grace "the new Elijah"!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>By an odd coincidence rain did follow the Duke's appeal to the Bishops for prayers. The following appeared in last Friday's issue of the "Times":&#8211;</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>Sir,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Heartiest congratulations to the Duke of Rutland and to </hi><hi rend="underline">The Times</hi><hi>. I hope the rainfall has not been too excessive in the neighbourhood of Belvoir Castle.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Archbishops<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> prayed for wet: their prayers were in vain:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Rutland wrote to </hi><hi rend="underline">The Times</hi><hi> – and there was rain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, Sir, Your obedient servant,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>G. Stuart Robertson<persName xml:id="4661"></persName>.<note xml:id="444" n="2"></note></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Yesterday, under the same heading "The New Elijah" appeared this:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>Sir,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Imbris egent agri: fit epistula, decidit imber:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Tempora nimirum ducit ut ante Ionans.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your obedient servant,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Boanerges.<note xml:id="445" n="3"></note></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The magic of the ducal invocation is not yet exhausted, for the rain is still falling on a yet unsatisfied land.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName><hi> writes to tell me that "a French friend tells him that Lord Halifax<persName xml:id="1748"></persName> has "</hi><hi rend="underline">un naif article sur l'&#x00E9;veque Henson</hi><hi>"[a naïve article on the Bishop Henson] in the Correspondent of May 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He suggests that he should write a reply to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lake's</hi><persName xml:id="38"></persName><hi> article in the "Hibbert Journal"<ref xml:id="1011"></ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 9.30 a.m. I addressed the members of the "Friends First Day Adult School" on Christian Unity &amp; Industrial Peace". About 130 men attended &amp; listened with patience to an extemporaneous address from notes, which lasted 45 minutes. The time until lunch was spent in my study, writing letters, &amp; preparing notes for this afternoon. After lunch <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> and I together with Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> motored to Brampton Bryan where a "United Service" in the open air had been arranged. The rain, however, caused the service to be held in the parish church, which was crowded. Divers sectaries prayed; there were several hymns, &amp; I gave another extemporaneous address on "Christian Unity &amp; International Peace". There was a collection for Blinded Soldiers (S</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Dunstan's) and Lord Roberts's Home for Wounded Men. After service we had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Beavan, the tenant of Harley House. The ruin of the old castle is in front of the modern House. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4916"></persName><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Harley were there, &amp; others whose names I cannot recall. All were very civil.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Vicar, Hastings<persName xml:id="4583"></persName>, is a rough type of man, but his face is not unpleasing, &amp; he impressed me as honest. His house was burned down last year, &amp; the new one was not yet completed. We motored back to Hereford by way of Presteign, Eardisley &amp; Bredwardine; where we picked up Compston<persName xml:id="2010"></persName>, who had pernoctated at the village inn. The heavy masses of vapours gave very remarkable effects in the intervals of sunshine. It would be difficult to imagine a more beautiful country.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Everywhere is being defaced by the felling of the woods</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We reached home about 7.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
