<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1426</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I finished "Eminent Victorians"<ref xml:id="1007"></ref>. It appears that Gordon was addicted to brandy&#8211;soaking, as well as to mysticism. Is there ever the faintest allusion to this squalid vice in the voluminous self&#8211;revelations which he has left behind him? Saints (e.g. S. Augustine) will dilate on sins which they have renounced, but they cannot bring themselves to speak of those which they fail to conquer. Was S. Paul's mention of the "thorn in the flesh, a messenger of Satan", against which he prayed in vain, an exception to this rule?</hi>     
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfasting in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I went through with care the sermons I propose to preach tomorrow, wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and packed my bag. I came away in very good time, &amp; caught the 2 p.m. express at Paddington.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon Arbuthnot</hi><persName xml:id="4498"></persName><hi> was on the platform with his wife. They had been in the Albert Hall at the meeting on May 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Willink</hi><persName xml:id="2716"></persName><hi> met me at the station in Birmingham. He said that this city has become the centre from which the American mail is distributed. With a million soldiers on this side of the Atlantic the mass of letters must be gigantic. I was much interested by the photographs, both plain and coloured, which had been taken by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lieut: Willink</hi><persName xml:id="4706"></persName><hi>, who has been invalided home from Salonika. He was a choral scholar at King's College, Cambridge, and has many photographs of the chapel. Photography is, however, for the present almost entirely suspended save for military purposes: for the materials, thanks to the War, are no longer to be purchased.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
