<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1393</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I cleared off as much of the business letters as I could with the Archdeacon's<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> assistance, and then </hi><hi rend="bold underline">went off to London</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> On the platform was M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Shaw, with whom I travelled a stage of my journey. I put up at Garland's Hotel, and dined at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, having Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName> as my table&#8211;companion. The renewal of the German offensive, expected for so long, is at length announced, and appears to have had some initial success. After dinner, I walked to Westminster, and called on Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. He thinks that the extraordinary delay in filling up the Deanery of Durham is perhaps not unconnected with the pressure being placed on the Prime Minister to get him to accept some kind of a Committee to review ecclesiastical appointments. Unfortunately Lloyd George<persName xml:id="234"></persName> has no real understanding of the ecclesiastical system, &amp; is but too much inclined to yield anything for a little popularity.</hi>     
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I took up the "Tablet", &amp; noticed that it is engaged in "rubbing in" the moral of the correspondence between Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName> &amp; the Bishop of Ely<persName xml:id="532"></persName>.<note xml:id="440" n="1"></note> Certainly the authority of the episcopate has a futile appearance. Its immense claim and its practical impotence form a contrast which arrests attention.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I understand that General Maurice<persName xml:id="4627"></persName> maintains to his friends that he has been "done in by the politicians", &amp; that his statements were true, &amp; capable of being proved, if he had the chance of presenting his case!</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
