<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1448</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in Holy Trinity with effort and pain, but without a collar, my throat being swathed in a kind of stock, composed of pocket&#8211;handkerchief &amp;c. secured by "safety pins". I must have looked rather a terrifying guy, not to say even an episcopal scare&#8211;crow!</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We lunched with the Moores<persName xml:id="4331"></persName>, with whom was the Bishop of Birmingham<persName xml:id="421"></persName>. His Lordship was in a physically dilapidated state. He gave an ill account of his lawless clergy, some of whom w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> appear to be introducing "Benediction".</hi> <hi rend="italic">The doctor was rather alarming about this abominable evil in my neck, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">which he now describes as a carbuncle, and suggests may require surgical treatment</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Besides the personal inconvenience there is the dislocation of my engagements for the next month. He says this indicates that I have "run down" badly, &amp; been working for some while past under condition. It is, I suppose, the aftermath of all the bother since the outbreak a "Catholick" hostilities!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The only consolation is the news from France, which continues to be good. Foch's<persName xml:id="4563"></persName> stroke has compelled the Germans to withdraw across the Marne; &amp; he claims besides 20,000 prisoners, and about 400 guns. It is evident that the Americans, young, keen men, are having a notable effect in a campaign in which all the other armies are "stale" and largely middle&#8211;aged. The effect in Germany itself can hardly be unimportant, &amp; may even be critical.</hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
