<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[37]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1391</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I completed the Abbey Sermon, and had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Wright<persName xml:id="4457"></persName> &amp; the Vicar of Humber respecting the union of Stoke Prior and Humber. The scheme is held up by the opposition of Nelson<persName xml:id="4341"></persName>, the Vicar of Leominster. I undertook to speak to him on the subject when I go to Leominster for a confirmation. In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I drove out to return calls. Lady Croft<persName xml:id="4541"></persName> was not at home: M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Lea &amp; his sister received us pleasantly, &amp; as much may be said for Lady Hopton<persName xml:id="4590"></persName>. After tea I went again to the Palace, &amp; revised a sermon for use tomorrow. Also I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, to Kathleen<persName xml:id="2658"></persName>, to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; to Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName>. From the last I received two books as a parting gift.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Archdeacon Pelham<persName xml:id="4653"></persName> sends me a paper "Towards Reunion" drawn up by a company of Anglicans &amp; Nonconformists, which included, until his recent death, Archdeacon Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="3997"></persName><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The proposals are rather vague, but otherwise unobjectionable. One appears to design something specific:&#8211; "By seeking to do away with any legal barriers that may exist to the permissive interchange of pulpits". The Archdeacon accompanies the paper in which he asks me "to refer him to any modern book, or individual, who w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> help me to understand the legal difficulties in the way of a permissive interchange of pulpits". He adds, </hi><hi rend="i bold">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I cannot say with what pleasure I heard of your appointment to the See of Hereford: &amp; with what indignation I read of the opposition of the foolish</hi><hi rend="i bold">".</hi> <hi rend="italic">It remains to be seen how far the good man is representative of the Evangelicals. Will they support, or ignore, the appeal to the Bishops?</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
