<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[150]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1489</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Grant, Lord, Thy Blessing upon our life in this House. Give us the mind to understand, and the will to work. Guard our hospitality from frivolity &amp; self&#8211;indulgence, and inspire our labour with the spirit of true service. Cleanse our hearts, and keep the door of our lips. Pour out upon our Family the spirit of fellowship and discipline, and make our home a little church, ordered according to Thy Will, and serviceable to Thy Purpose, through Jesus Christ Thy Son. Amen</hi>     
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I spent the whole day in writing letters, and trying to arrange my study on a "workable" basis. How I covet the methodical skill and orderly habit of the professional secretary! <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> had tea. He has been down with influenza, and has been ordered to slacken work. I offered to preach for him tomorrow morning. <persName xml:id="3230">Streeter</persName> came in after dinner, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; I consulted him about the wisdom of getting up a public meeting to advocate the "League of Nations". He did not seem very enthusiastic, but agreed that we ought to keep the idea out of the monopolizing hands of the avowed Pacifists</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Finally I wrote to the Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName> inviting his opinion on the subject. I wrote to Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName> conveying the joint opinion of W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> and me on the subject of her MS., expressing myself considerately in order to minimize the inevitable disagreeableness of the message. But her MS. is really inadmissible to such a Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> as I project.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[151]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My predecessor, Bishop Herbert </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Croft</hi><persName xml:id="4540"></persName><hi> (1603&#8211;1691) was an interesting person. As a young man, he, like the more famous</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Chillingworth</hi><persName xml:id="551"></persName><hi>, was seduced into popery, but "on the occasion of a visit to England, he was induced by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Morton</hi><persName xml:id="4636"></persName><hi>, Bishop of Durham, to conform to the established church".</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Laud</hi><persName xml:id="3468"></persName><hi> was interested in him, &amp; caused him to go to Oxford. He became chaplain to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles I</hi><hi>"who employed him in conveying his secret commands to several of the great officers of the royal army". In 1644 he was installed Dean of Hereford, where his valiant loyalty almost secured his destruction in the Cathedral by the exasperated soldiers whom he denounced! In 1661 he was nominated by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles II</hi><hi> to the bishoprick of Hereford.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burnet</hi><persName xml:id="1435"></persName><hi> says "Croft was a warm devout man, but of no discretion in his conduct; so he lost ground quickly. He used much freedom with the king: but it was in the wrong place, not in private, but in the pulpit". As a bishop he seems to have been popular and effective. "He laid down strict rules for admission to holy orders, &amp; dissatisfied some of the clergy by invariably refusing to admit any to be prebendaries of his church except those who resided in the diocese". In 1675 he published "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Naked Truth, or the True State of the Primitive Church by an Humble Moderator</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref>. 'The author endeavours to show that protestants differ about nothing essential to religion, and that, for the sake of union, compliances would be more becoming, as well as more effectual, than enforcing uniformity by penalties and persecution".</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
