<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[65]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1420</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A day alternately bright and clouded, with a chill in the wind which made an overcoat pleasant, and changing lights &amp; shadows which showed Oxford to perfection. I went to chapel, and joined in Morning Prayer with Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName>, Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>, Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>, Grant Robertson<persName xml:id="251"></persName>, Johnson<persName xml:id="2407"></persName>, &amp; a Bible clerk.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Then I vested myself in "purple &amp; fine linen", and went to S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Mary's for the University Sermon. There was a considerable congregation</hi><hi>, of which the academic element was not the largest constituent, though it was much larger than I had expected. The heads of Trinity<persName xml:id="4136"></persName>, Oriel, All Souls, Magdalen, University<persName xml:id="4619"></persName>, &amp; S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> John's represented the "houses".</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I preached a sermon more or less congruous with the Commemoration, taking</hi><hi> as my text 1. John V.21.</hi> <hi rend="underline">"The world passeth away, &amp; the lust thereof, but he that doeth the Will of God abideth for ever"</hi><hi>. If any had come expecting a polemical discourse, they went away disappointed. The attention throughout was close and sustained. I must needs conclude from what various persons said to me afterwards that the sermon was appreciated. It is always difficult to distinguish the message of truth which is carried</hi> <hi rend="bold">[66] </hi><hi> by words of compliment, &amp; certainly the man to whom they are addressed is of all men the least competent to essay the task. Nevertheless, I cannot think that men so different as Ker, Johnson, Robertson, Holland<persName xml:id="776"></persName>, Marriott<persName xml:id="4624"></persName>, and Phelps<persName xml:id="2145"></persName> would wholly sink their real sentiments when undertaking the gratuitous &amp; unexpected r&#x00F4;le of those who applaud. I suspect there was an element of relief in their approval. They were glad to have escaped a fresh episode of controversy.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I called on the President of Magdalen<persName xml:id="2521"></persName>, and talked with him for an hour, partly about his contribution to the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>, &amp; partly about "Life &amp; Liberty".<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note> He expressed decided disapprobation of the views of Canon Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName>, who is a connexion of his. From Magdalen I walked to 64 Banbury Road, and called on the Bishop<persName xml:id="475"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Percival. The poor old man is in the last stage of physical wreckage, &amp; I am nowise assured that he was quite clear as to who I was, and what I said. Phelps<persName xml:id="2145"></persName> was there, and afterwards walked back with me as far as the College. He was as ever cheerful and friendly. I told him much of the inner history of the agitation against me, which surprised him a good deal. It appears that he has personal connections with Hereford. I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, attended service in Chapel, and dined in Hall. It was a pleasant party of friends. The Dean of Christ Church<persName xml:id="120"></persName> was there as a guest: &amp; Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, who is coming to look quite patriarchal, &amp; Holland. Also Radcliffe<persName xml:id="4657"></persName> and Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName>. I seemed to be carried back more than 30 years to my first days in college. We are all getting old: mine is still the youngest&#8211;looking head, though that is grey.</hi>             
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
