<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[19]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1374</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was interrupted by Lady Lawrence &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Warburton who came to see me about the clubs. They are evidently "up against" the county authorities. I told them to be placable.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Then came Moore<persName xml:id="4331"></persName> of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Peter's who is "up against" his rural dean, &amp; quite extraordinarily hard to bring into a Christian temper!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We started in the motor about noon, and travelled as far as Ludlow. Here we lunched at the "Feathers", a wonderful old timbered house where but a little imagination re&#8211;created the society of Tudors and Stuarts. We resumed our journey shortly after 2 p.m. and motored vi&#x00E2; Craven Arms to Bishop's Castle, passing through Stokesay &amp; admiring the group of buildings which give it distinction &#8211; the moated Manor house &amp; the church. At</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop's Castle</hi><hi> I first confirmed a poor sick woman in her house, and then went to the parish church (a new structure) &amp; confirmed 26 candidates. My address was based on the words &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">So speak ye &amp; so do as men who are to be judged by a law of liberty"</hi><hi>. We had tea in the Vicarage. The Vicar, Warner<persName xml:id="4698"></persName>, afterwards explained to me "</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wrights Charity</hi><hi>" of which the Bishop of the Diocese is the sole trustee. We motored back to Hereford with no worse mishap than losing our way once. The weather was brilliantly fine, and the country beautiful beyond description. After dinner Archdeacon Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> came in to see me. He designs some changes in the order of the services tomorrow, but I disclaimed all concern with that matter as being a domestic concern of the Dean &amp; Chapter. I undertook to celebrate at 8 a.m.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
