<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1398</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The news from the Front continues to be bad. The Germans are now back to the Marne, and have cut the main line between Paris and Chalons. Foch<persName xml:id="4563"></persName> seems to have been hopelessly out&#8211;numbered.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Before getting up I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">and to Ernest Rudling</hi><persName xml:id="600"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Radcliffe<persName xml:id="4657"></persName> was breakfasting in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; I joined him. It appears that he also makes Garland's his halting place. After breakfast I answered Lieut&#8211;Colonel Le Mesurier's<persName xml:id="4608"></persName> important letter about Ordination.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I walked to Westminster, and called on Gow<persName xml:id="216"></persName>, who is aging &amp; melancholy. As I walked back to the Club,</hi> <hi rend="italic">I was accosted in the Park by an officer in khaki, who desired my counsel on the vexed question how, being a divorced man, the "innocent party", he could get married in church. I advised the registry office. He evidently is pressed by the lady's desire for a marriage in church. I assured him that a registry marriage was fully valid both by the law of the land, &amp; by the law of the Church. After lunching I ran through a disgusting story – "Pretty Woman"<ref xml:id="1001"></ref> by Arnold Bennet<persName xml:id="4508"></persName></hi><hi> – a study in harlotry under war&#8211;conditions. I wrote to Ernest. When walking to Westminster to dine with Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, I overtook the Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName>, and walked with him. He is evidently much exercised by these Romanizing Ritualists, but his desire to keep all things pleasant paralyzes him. Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="793"></persName> dined. We sate in the Garden, &amp; talked pleasantly enough. I walked back to my Hotel about 10 p.m.</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
