<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fine morning after the rain, but with heavy clouds in the sky, portending a renewal of showers. I wrote to Ernest. After breakfast I started in the motor for Staunton on the Wye, but scarcely a mile beyond the City, there was a loud report, which brought us sharply to a standstill. <persName xml:id="4501">William</persName> went back to Hereford to fetch out another motor, while I kept watch over the damaged car, &amp; read the book on Leominster, which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Nield lent me. (The name is properly Leofric's minster,</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">not</hi><hi> Leonis monasteruim as the medieval legend affirms.) William arrived with the relief car, &amp; carried us out to the Jarvis meeting in time to preside over the meeting of the Trustees<orgName xml:id="313"></orgName>. Both Sir John Cotteril<persName xml:id="4535"></persName>, and Sir Geoffrey Cornwall<persName xml:id="4534"></persName> were present. The latter has rather a severe aspect : he is practically the owner of Bredwardine. (William told me that his father was dead : that his mother kept lodgings : that he had a younger brother &amp; sister : that they were all Baptists. Why is it that, whenever I am impressed by a young man as rather more than usually trustworthy &amp; intelligent, he almost always turns out to be a Dissenter of one sort or another?)</hi>    
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch I went back to the Palace &amp; wrote letters. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked together as far as S. Martin's. I wrote to my Godson Alfred<persName xml:id="7"></persName>, &amp; to Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>. The news from the battle&#8211;field is on the whole re&#8211;assuring. Especially the Americans have acquitted themselves well; &amp; the Germans have nowhere had any very conspicuous success.</hi>    
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
