<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[106]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1456</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started the day by wasting the time required for reading through an absurd little book – "The New Revelation" by Arthur Conan Doyle<persName xml:id="4548"></persName>. The author professes himself a convert to spiritualism, of which he speaks in the most extravagant terms, as if it were a Revelation of Truth not inferior to Christianity itself. His concept of religion is totally divorced form morality: and he imagines the "spiritual" world as a crude replica of this "material" life. The book is one more depressing indication of the intellectual decline induced by the War.</hi>    
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I offered Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> the living of Almeley, which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Matthews<persName xml:id="4811"></persName> had declined. He said that he would like to consult his</hi> <hi rend="underline">fianc&#x00E9;e</hi><hi>. If, as seems to me probable, they decide to accept preferment and get married, I must set about the rather difficult task of finding a new Chaplain. Clarence Stock<persName xml:id="1178"></persName> came to see me, &amp; sate for an hour talking about the various crotchets which interest him.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">I wrote to the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName>, accepting nomination to the Conference on Prayer Book Revision</hi><hi> : to Arnold Culley<persName xml:id="2800"></persName>: &amp; to the Dean of West</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="325"></persName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> spent the day with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Burgess in an expedition on the Wye. They went by train to Ross, and from thence boated as far as Monmouth. The fineness of the weather displayed the beauty of the river to great advantage. They got home shortly after 8 p.m. well&#8211;pleased with themselves. I made a rather unsuccessful attempt to compose something on the War to be read in the Cathedral next Sunday in lieu of the Sermon which I had undertaken to preach there, and to repeat at Ledbury.</hi>    
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
