<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[23]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1378</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Glorious sunshine. The close with its carefully mown turf, and fresh young foliage, gathered around the Cathedral, like a garland about a May Queen's face, is amazingly beautiful. Last night the setting sun illuminated the tinted sandstone with the colour effect which we wondered at in the Dolomites before this abominable War shut the Tyrol, &amp; so much else out of our reach. This morning the milder morning sun creates an effect less astonishing but more alluringly fair. What a limitless distance parts this beauty from the infamous conflict in France! How long, O Lord, how long!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. &amp; received the Holy Communion. The two Archdeacons<persName xml:id="4450"><persName xml:id="3618"></persName></persName> were present. Ingram celebrated. After breakfast I went to the Palace, &amp; spent the morning quietly in my study preparing an address for the Confirmation, and writing letters. After lunch we motored to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colwall </hi><hi> where I confirmed 50 candidates. The Vicar is a learned man, but speaks with a rank vulgar accent. His name is D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Harris<persName xml:id="4581"></persName>: he was a lecturer at Lampeter, then Rector of Claverley, where I dedicated a tablet to Gen</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">l</hi><hi> Gatacre<persName xml:id="23"></persName>, finally, 9 years ago, he came to Colwall. He is an author of merit. An unusual feature of this Confirmation was the answering of the Question by every candidate separately, instead of all together. The Vicar called out the names. It was not unimpressive, but might, I imagine, become so. Anyway the risk is considerable. The church was filled with the congregation of friends, neighbours, &amp; relatives. We had a pleasant drive back to Hereford, the evening sun showing the fair country to great advantage.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
