<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1413</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A cool beautiful morning, but the turf is assuming a brown burnt up aspect, and the crops cry out for rain.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The collect for this Sunday is very consoling &#8211; "we, to whom Thou hast given an hearty desire to pray" is a description which fits the worst &amp; least of us. The "desire to pray" is ours though the power &amp; the comfort of prayer are not. I celebrated in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. There were 30 com</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi><hi> besides myself: and these were all women except some boys from the school in khaki, 2 vergers, &amp; Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName>. After breakfast I went to the Palace, &amp; spent the morning in making some notes for the Birmingham Sermon. I lunched at the Deanery, &amp; then went to the cathedral where the annual service in support of the Herefordshire General Hospital had been arranged. There was a very large congregation composed of many societies from the Corporation to Boy Scouts and Girl Guides. I preached the sermon, and gave the Benediction. The collection amounted to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;36.15.9</hi><hi>. which was said to be very good.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I attended Evensong, when Winnington&#8211;Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> preached to a rather scanty congregation. I read the 2</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> Lesson, &amp; gave the Benediction. At the afternoon service the pastoral staff was carried by the new Prebendary </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It was a curious reflection that less than six months ago he was leading the agitation against my consecration, and organizing the distribution of all kinds of calumnies against me. I think the oddness of the contrast must have suggested itself to a good many persons; for </hi><hi rend="italic underline">"these things were not done in a corner"</hi><hi rend="italic">. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> commented on the fact.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
