<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[30]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1385</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Most difficult, nay altogether unattainable, is any clear understanding of the orthodox doctrine respecting the Holy Ghost – His Personality, His Equality with the Father &amp; the Son within the unity of the undivided Godhead, His “double Procession – and yet no part of the Christian System appeals more potently to the mind. For here at least we have God with us, not severed by a waste of centuries, not awfully remote in Power, but within ourselves, &amp; audible to us there.</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="verse">
         <p>
<hi>For God is never far off</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>As even to be near</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>He is within: our spirit is</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Home He holds most dear.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>No Festival is more exalting; none more consolatory. The Creed may be to us no more than a tiresome and perplexing logomachy, but the "Veni Creator" moves us as nothing else can.<note xml:id="7" n="1"></note> It has become associated inextricably with the tragically decisive moments of Ordination, and those for me have been threefold. The Invocation governed my admission to diaconate, to priesthood, to episcopate and always. It comes most naturally to mind at every new turn of my fortunes. Who, indeed, could endure the burden &amp; claim of such Ministry without conviction that God is present, accessible, friendly, and active? "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Spirit also helpeth our infirmity: for we know not how to pray as we ought; but the Spirit Himself maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered</hi><hi>".</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brings me another communication from the anonymous "Captain R.N." who has favoured me with so many abusive post cards. He appears to regard railway&#8211;travelling as a form of episcopal self&#8211;indulgence, and residence in a London hotel as a luxurious substitute for the Palace in Hereford!</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"It is to be hoped later on a return will be asked for the number of railway journeys D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Henson has made from Hereford, the time &amp; money expended. This is not a question of theology, but of common honesty". Well, well!</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Nicholas Church, and celebrated the Holy Communion. The Athanasian Creed was not read. I approve the reason, &amp; condemn the illegality of the proceeding. The church is hideous, &amp; acoustically bad, but the service was both reverent &amp; congregational. A layman read the lessons, &amp; read them badly. There were a good many communicants.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to visit the Military Hospital which the Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName> has established in his house. A convoy had arrived from France last week. The men were mostly quite young, &amp; all very cheerful. Their civilian occupations had been most various. In the same bedroom were a clerk, an engineer, a stoker, a farm hand, an ostrich feather cutter, &amp; a paper&#8211;hanger. This mixing up of different social types ought to make for mutual understanding.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in the Cathedral at Evensong. There was a large congregation. After dinner Ella &amp; I went to the Palace, and sate in the garden for a while.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
