<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1357</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Icy rain turning to snow &amp; returning to icy rain prevailed all the morning. I celebrated at 8 a.m. and at Mattins read the lessons &amp; preached the sermon. There was but a petty congregation, though larger than I expected in such weather.</hi> <persName xml:id="4700"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Westmacott</hi></persName><hi>, who served with </hi><persName xml:id="4545"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gough</hi></persName><hi>, denied that there was any running away, only a fighting retreat before overwhelming forces. I decided to make notes of the sermon which I had intended to read at Evensong, and to deliver with their aid what is called an "ex tempore" sermon. Mine host clearly desired me to do this. Accordingly I spent the afternoon in my bedroom, &amp; there made notes &amp; wrote letters to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> &amp;</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName><hi>.<note xml:id="437" n="1"></note> The rain ceased in the course of the afternoon, so that it was possible for people to walk out from Ross. Thus the church was filled at Evensong. My sermon was ill&#8211;delivered, for I had bad headache, caused perhaps by the villainous smell of the lamps by which the church was lighted. However, the <persName xml:id="4450">Archdeacon</persName> professed that he preferred it to my reading! He advised me to make a practice of preaching extemporaneously.</hi> <hi rend="italic">After supper </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Westmacott</hi><hi rend="italic"> read aloud the journal which he had kept during the battle. It was extremely interesting. The courage and endurance of the men are truly amazing. One boy, a young Sub, too badly wounded to walk further, lay down by the roadside to await his fate clutching a brick in his hand, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">It'll do for one more d&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;d German</hi><hi rend="italic">", he said! And this is our Holy War, Crusade &amp; all the rest of it!!!</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
