<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1488</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Birchington by the early (8 a.m.) train, and arrived at Cannon Street about 10 a.m. Having deposited my bags at Paddington, I went to the hair dresser, &amp; had my Absalom's locks abbreviated. Then I went to Rees, and bought some books. I lunched at the Senior United Services Club<orgName xml:id="321"></orgName> (whereto the members of the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> had retired during the temporary closing of the Club for purposes of cleaning), and was joined by</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">W. P. Ker</hi><persName xml:id="22"></persName><hi>, who celebrates today his 63</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> birthday. I showed him</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Anson's</hi><persName xml:id="302"></persName><hi> MS, and we ran through it together. He agreed that it could not be included in my memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. Then I went to </hi><hi>Paddington, &amp; caught the 3 p.m. train to Hereford, where I arrived about 8 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName><hi> arrived from Birmingham soon afterwards.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">This was my first night at the Palace</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A very ominous sign of social disintegration has appeared suddenly – </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">a strike of the London Police.</hi> <hi rend="italic">They demand a considerable increase of wages, the re&#8211;instatement of one of their number who was recently dismissed for insubordination, and the full recognition of their Trade Union! The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">special constables</hi><hi rend="italic"> have been called out, but there seems some reason for doubting their loyalty. Some of them have been heard to say that they sympathized with the strikers, and would not act as "blacklegs". The Government will no doubt yield to the revolters, but their pusillanimous surrender will but encourage the men to fresh essays in rebellion.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
