<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[27]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1382</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; packed my bags before breakfast. After breakfasting at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I walked to Westminster, and called on Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName>. Then I walked into the city in order to lunch at the Mansion House. I called at the Deanery of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's, &amp; had speech with Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> walked with me to the Mansion House whereto he also was invited. I was placed beside Professor McLaughlin, one of the two Americans, in whose honour the lunch was arranged. I proposed a vote of thanks to the Lord Mayor<persName xml:id="315"></persName>, who is rather a superb specimen of municipal functionary. After lunch I went to Paddington, &amp; returned to Hereford by the 4.45 p.m. train, arriving a little before 10 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I beguiled the journey by reading through Ronald Knox's<persName xml:id="2916"></persName> account of his conversion or perversion to Rome. He calls his apologia "A Spiritual Aeneid”, and heads every chapter with a suitable tag from Virgil. Its principal interest is not the explanation of a clever whimsical boy's religious escapades, which cannot have any great importance either for the Church which he decides to desert, or for the Church which he elects to join, but the light it casts on the actual situation within the Church of England, and the revelation it makes of the moral perverseness of what is now called "Anglo&#8211;Romanism". The atmosphere of demoralizing flippancy, in which Ronald Knox and the set to which he attached himself habitually lived, is a novel and most disquieting feature. For behind the band of unbalanced though brilliant boys were many older men who guided and used them.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
