<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1498</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"It is inherent in the office of Bishops that it is their duty to guide rather that to follow those over whom they are placed". &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; Archbishop Tait<persName xml:id="506"></persName>. </hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>For the present Archbishop's view of the duty of "a leader in the church" who "is called to steer in democratic and 'reforming' days", see the Life of A. C. Tait'<ref xml:id="230"></ref> vol. II. p.412.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Hereford by the 9.55 a.m. train, &amp; travelled to Paddington vi&#x00E2; Gloucester, arriving about 3.30 p.m. Having found my room at Garlant's</hi><hi>, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; had tea. There I found the President of Magdalen<persName xml:id="2521"></persName>, &amp; had some talk with him. He is actually at work upon his contribution to the Anson<persName xml:id="228"></persName> life. I walked to Westminster, and attended a meeting of dissentients from the Report of the Majority. Bp of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>, Dean of Canterbury<persName xml:id="212"></persName>, Archdeacon of Ely<persName xml:id="1318"></persName>, Captain Torr<persName xml:id="1735"></persName> &amp; myself.</hi> <hi rend="italic">We are so much divided among ourselves that it is hard to see how we can find a common formula. I dined at the Athenaeum with Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName>, and afterwards sat in the smoking room with him &amp; Sir Walter Raleigh<persName xml:id="1578"></persName>, &amp; talked until 10.30 p.m. It was very pleasant, for both are interesting men, &amp; both have rather special knowledge of affairs. Newbolt told me that he had received from Sir Pertab Singh<persName xml:id="4680"></persName> himself the story of the episode which inspired his poem in the "Times"<ref xml:id="1029"></ref>: that he had been given his (Sir P. S.'s) permission to publish it: + that the gallant Indian was very pleased with it. He said that he took him a day to compose the poem. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[161]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Newbolt told me the following: &#8211; "A Tommie fresh from the front overhears some one in the Tube speaking of two flamboyantly pious speeches of the Kaiser<persName xml:id="4705"></persName> recently reported. "</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We owe a lot to that there Kayser" he observed. "How so?" he was asked. "Because he's kept on praying so loud that at last he's waking Gawd up!"</hi><hi rend="italic">Newbolt says that the news from Germany indicated great depression. There are 20,000 deserters in Berlin, &amp; the Government is powerless to arrest them.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
