<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1364</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliantly fine day, after the morning mists had been dispelled by the sun, but a bitter easterly wind blowing all the while, and withering everything.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I preached in Free S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t </hi><hi rend="bold underline">George's at 11 a.m.</hi><hi> There was a considerable congregation, and very attentive. Mine hostess expressed more than once her appreciation of the sermon.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Old M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Barbour<persName xml:id="4504"></persName> of Bonskeid was in the vestry, &amp; reminded me of my visit in 1890 with Raleigh</hi><persName xml:id="14"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Also, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="1194" display="no"></persName><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Geddes, the Minister at Largs, who had met me at Fairlie<placeName xml:id="39" display="no"></placeName>. In the afternoon mine host took me for walk, and then Sir Richard Lodge<persName xml:id="4615"></persName> came to tea, and talked pleasantly. At 6.30 p.m.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I preached in S. Cuthbert's to a great congregation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Fisher<persName xml:id="1138"></persName> and another minister conducted the service. I was particularly struck by the singing, which was not only very "hearty", but, unless I was mistaken, deliberately intentioned.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">At both services I wore my Convocation robes</hi><hi rend="bold">,</hi><hi> and at both I took the impression that these good Presbyterians are gratified at my doing so! We have travelled far from the days of Jenny Geddes<persName xml:id="4567"></persName>. My sermon in the morning took 33 minutes in delivery, and in the evening I think the sermon was slightly longer. But on both occasions he congregations were very attentive, &amp; showed no sign of being bored. Willie Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName> left a note for me. I telephoned to the New Club<orgName xml:id="323"></orgName> to tell him that I would be leaving Edinburgh tomorrow by the 10 o'clock express. Mine host talked interestingly about his experiences as a Professor in Tokio.</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
