<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1435</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The drought continues with great heat</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> In the close the gardeners were watering the trees which begin to show signs of collapsing. It is becoming apparent that the "roots" will fail as completely as the fruit. Everywhere the turf is becoming a dusty yellow, &amp; the ground is hard as men's hearts. After writing cheques for household accounts, &amp; paying the rent up to the end of June, I presided at a meeting of the Lord Scudamore Trust<orgName xml:id="322"></orgName> at the Town&#8211;hall. Then I lunched, &amp; went off to London for the meeting of the convocation. At Oxford two young ladies got into the carriage, &amp; with one of them I had an interesting conversation. She told me her name, Miss Margaret Wharry, &amp; that she was on her way to start work in the new force of women which is being organized in connexion with the Flying Corps. Her companion, Miss Keble, was of the family of the Tractarian poet. On arriving at Paddington I had much difficulty in obtaining a taxi, but at length I succeeded, and got to Suffolk Street, where Garland's found me a room. In the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> was Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, with whom I walked to Westminster. There I called on Gow<persName xml:id="216"></persName>, &amp; remained to dine with him &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="542"></persName>. On returning to the Athanaeum, I found Hobhouse<persName xml:id="308"></persName> there. He says that Gee<persName xml:id="2920"></persName> is much liked at Gloucester.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">The "Church Times" ignores my visit to Birmingham altogether. The "Guardian" and the "Challenge" limit themselves to the briefest &amp; chilliest record of the fact</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
