<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1452</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> sends me the draft of what he proposes to write in the Hibbert Journal in reply to Lake's<persName xml:id="38"></persName> unfortunate article<ref xml:id="1011"></ref>. It is well&#8211;expressed, and not ineffective, but might perhaps provide occasion for a continuation of controversy, which on many counts would be unfortunate. I returned it with a few suggestions.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another sectarian minister – a Baptist – seeks Ordination. I returned a chilling reference to intellectual equipment, and referred him to <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName>. <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> came to report progress in the matter of the War&#8211;Service on August 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. It seems that the ass, Moore<persName xml:id="4331"></persName>, has done his best to precipitate a crisis by raising the question of the co&#8211;operation of Dissenters. I sent him a note bidding him be helpful! Also, I wrote to Treherne<persName xml:id="4426"></persName>, asking him to come here tomorrow afternoon, &amp; expound to me the situation at S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Barnabas. For the rest, I mooned away the day by reading with care the Prefaces &amp; Rubricks of the Prayer&#8211;book, which have a good deal to disclose about the English Reformation, when closely considered. "The Times", "Punch", and "Rob Roy" filled up the rest of the time, &amp; finally <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> read to me.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">In my present situation, the unapproachable greatness of Sir Walter Scott is brought home to the mind. What the boy read with hasty eagerness as an exciting narrative, the man peruses with deliberate pleasure as a rare treasure&#8211;house of wit &amp; humour. Andrew Fairservice remains the prince of coxcombical cowards, and didactic humbugs; yet half&#8211;owning his own priceless turpitude</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
