<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1371</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was conscious of all the disablements of a heavy cold, when I got up. I was driven to Clifton Parish Church for the service at 11 a.m. It was a celebration of the Holy Communion introduced as "the principal service" on the first Sunday of the month by way of the "thin end of the wedge". If this "experiment" succeeds, the same order will be followed every Sunday. There were no less than 140 communicants, which represented but a small proportion of the congregation. I celebrated and preached. The church was built about 100 years ago, &amp; is a very plain structure, with nothing creditable except the acoustics.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I lunched with the Vicar, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> de Candole</hi><persName xml:id="4544"></persName><hi rend="italic">. He came to Clifton from Holy Trinity in Cambridge, &amp; has been carrying the parish out of the rut of the narrowest conceivable Protestantism. On returning to the Deanery, I rested for an hour, and then went to tea, where the Lord Mayor<persName xml:id="4676"></persName> (Shepherd) [Sheppard], a boot&#8211;maker, &amp; his wife came to meet me. I found him interesting and intelligent. The Bishop came to the service in the Cathedral. I preached to a large congregation.</hi><hi> A West Hartlepool man<persName xml:id="4067"></persName>, whom A. L. Smith<persName xml:id="1170"></persName> introduced to me, came to supper. He is now living in Bristol in charge of important work. After the Bishop had gone home, we sate in our host's study and talked over things. I was assured that there was nothing that could fairly be called "Bolshevism" among the working men of these parts, &amp; that the Welsh miners were moved to loyalty by the German offensive. The rain was falling heavily when we went to bed.</hi>      
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
