<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1482</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline"> Bartholomew's Day</hi><hi> – accursed in the memory of two nations by the undying association with outstanding exhibitions of religious bigotry! The weather dull, and rather chilly. I wrote letters to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Miss Anson<persName xml:id="302"></persName>, <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName>, Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> &amp; several others.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Harold</hi><persName xml:id="1097"></persName><hi rend="italic"> returned to London. I accompanied him to the station, and as we paced the platform before the train's arrival we discussed the moral state of the troops in France, as his experience had disclosed it. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He said that the Medical Officers, who had direct information, held that 90% of officers &amp; men "went with women" after their arrival in France; &amp; that he himself thought that 75% was within the facts</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I inquired whether current opinion among the men held the practice to be reprehensible: &amp; he replied, Certainly not. Indeed if so great a majority are indulging in the sin themselves, a public opinion adverse to it is inconceivable. "I cannot understand", he said, "what the chaplains mean by asserting that there is little actual immorality in the Army. The statement is notoriously untrue, &amp; everybody in the Armies knows that it is. The Chaplains only succeed in making themselves quite ridiculous". Allowing for exceptional men, who wielded considerable influence </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he thought the chaplains as a body were of very small use. Beyond preparing for their Sunday work, they were mostly employed in organising sports &amp; amusement for the troops. If they were withdrawn altogether he doubted whether the Army would be appreciably the worse</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> This is very bad hearing, the worse since Harold is a grave youth, well&#8211;disposed to religion, &amp; not given to exaggeration.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
