<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[24]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1379</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I visited the Minor Canon's Houses, and looked at the vacant house which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Eckett<persName xml:id="4551"></persName> would fain let. Then I went to the Cathedral, and instituted </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> King&#8211;King</hi><persName xml:id="4603"></persName><hi> to the Vicarage of Leintwardine with Adforton. After lunch I presided at the annual meeting of the Diocesan Preventive &amp; Rescue Association. There was a fair attendance. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Higson</hi><hi> spoke very well, &amp; Archdeacon Winnington&#8211;Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName>. Later, at 8 p.m., there was a public meeting in the same interest. The Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName> presided: and Miss Higson and I were again the principal speakers. Again the attendance was quite good. The afternoon post brought me a very kind letter from</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi><persName xml:id="2817"></persName><hi>: and an impulsive, characteristic letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edgar Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName><hi>. The worst of drawing out the confidence &amp; affection of these boys is that they exact more in the way of letter writing than I can easily give. However, I suspect that such letters are more really serviceable, than my ordinary correspondence. Edgar Dobbie, like Olaf Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="2128"></persName>, is exercised on the subject of ambition. Is it wrong to be ambitious? Not altogether an easy question for a spiritual Guide to answer. There is always the Parable of the Talents to appeal to on the one side: if we must reckon with the demand for self&#8211;suppression</hi> <hi rend="underline">(‘He that loveth his life shall lose it’)</hi><hi> on the other. I also received a letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Anson</hi><persName xml:id="302"></persName><hi> who clings with pathetic confidence to the belief that I shall actually carry through the Memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref> of the Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName> which too rashly I undertook. A letter from Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> gives no good account of Carissima's<persName xml:id="76"></persName> health: but an old lady of 77, living in the war zone is not particularly well placed.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
