<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1372</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to Hereford by a fairly rapid train which did the distance (68 miles) in two hours. The last part of the journey was "deceived"<note xml:id="438" n="1"></note> by the conversation of a young officer who had been shot through the liver at Cambrai, &amp; was on his way to attend a medical board. He looked woefully ill. I had a meeting of the Archdeacons<persName xml:id="4450"><persName xml:id="3618"></persName></persName> in the Palace to consider the situation of the clergy with respect to military service. On my return to the Close I had an interview with Archdeacon Ingram about the Confirmation in the Cathedral on Ascension Day: also with Miss Atkinson respecting the Rescue Work of the Diocese: also with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Luard<persName xml:id="4616"></persName> respecting a Public Meeting to raise funds for the Prisoners of the County Regiment: also with Butterworth, the Diocesan Missioner.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Treherne<persName xml:id="4426"></persName>, the Vicar of All Saints, offering him the vacant prebendal stall: also to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Haslewood<persName xml:id="4582"></persName>, the Vicar of Pelton in Durham, offering him the Vicarage of Bredwardine, that hapless living which no one will take, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">where the female churchwarden<persName xml:id="4363"></persName> "lifts up her horn"</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">By chance I bought a copy of the "Daily Telegraph" to wile away the time on the train. To my surprise it contained a long leader on my encounter with Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> in the Upper House of Convocation last Wednesday. The article was more hostile to Gore than to me, but it was friendly to neither of us, &amp; goes to confirm my regret that the "old Adam" was suffered to have his will in making me stand on my own defence, when I had been better&#8211;advised to hold my peace.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
