<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1444</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We finished reading the account of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Arnold<persName xml:id="4499"></persName> in M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Strachey's<persName xml:id="4684"></persName> "Eminent Victorians"<ref xml:id="1007"></ref>. The genius for belittlement which marks this writer's work is more apparent here than in the other biographical sketches. He never even attempts to place Arnold in his temporal "setting", and his suggestions everywhere imply the application of the standards of 1918 to a career which had ended before the first half of the last century had run out. I called successively on <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName>, and James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName>, with respect to divers business matters, mostly unpleasing.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Compston</hi><persName xml:id="2010"></persName><hi> has accepted Bredwardine. I hope this will turn out well. </hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">A long &amp; hysterical letter from the female churchwarden</hi><persName xml:id="4363"></persName><hi> rather suggests trouble in that quarter. I motored to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dew church</hi><hi>, and there confirmed 14 candidates. The Vicar,</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Llewelyn Davies</hi><persName xml:id="4614"></persName><hi>, bears no good reputation. Bickering with his parishioners, &amp; the non&#8211;payment of his debts, are alleged against him. He is an unimpressive little man, speaking indistinctly for lack of front teeth, &amp; seeming to make apology for his own existence. We called on Admiral</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bosanquet</hi><persName xml:id="4515"></persName><hi>, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Cuthbert<persName xml:id="4182"></persName>. I received a telegram from</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName><hi>, saying that he had reached home, but had to go off again on Saturday. So there is little probability of my seeing him.</hi>    
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The news from France continues to be good. Indeed there seems to be reason for thinking that the German offensive has already been brought to a standstill. The Americans have fought admirably. It is reported tonight that</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Quentin Roosevelt</hi><hi>, the ex&#8211;President's<persName xml:id="2340"></persName> youngest son has been killed at the front.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
