<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1376</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another brilliant day. I worked at a Sermon for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Martin's in the Fields on "Reunion". <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went to Ledbury to lunch with the <persName xml:id="3619"><persName xml:id="4119">Bannisters</persName></persName>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Rocke<persName xml:id="4664"></persName> the Rector of Clungunford came to see me. He asked, and received, permission to accept appointment as a motor&#8211;driver. </hi><hi rend="italic">The local paper has a letter abusively expressed on what it is pleased to call my attack on Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>!! Against this must be placed a letter from a chaplain in France. My Lord.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">As one of the Chaplains in France may I say how delighted I am to see that you preached at the Bloomsbury Baptist Chapel, a few days ago. In your sermon you said "I have some doubt as to whether I represent the clergy, but I am absolutely convinced that I represent the laity". My I say that a large number of the Chaplains out here are entirely with you, and are most thankful to you, &amp; pray that you will continue to work for unity (not uniformity). The soldiers are tired of petty jealousies &amp; want reality, &amp; some of my happiest hours out here have been when various denominations have worshipped together, &amp; on several occasions have taken part in the Holy Communion. I only write that you may know that the Chaplains here are working for unity &amp; that your hands may be strengthened as the "Bridge&#8211;maker".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I have the honour to remain, my Lord Bishop.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Faithfully yours</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>E. C. Campbell<persName xml:id="4524"></persName>.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
