<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1451</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On the whole I had a good night, &amp;, though I assent to be bed&#8211;ridden today, I do so with a privy purpose of getting up tomorrow.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Times" reports the beginning of a most formidable strike of skilled workmen.<note xml:id="446" n="1"></note> Though the occasion appears to be practically of the most trivial character, and the Government have issued a solemn &amp; threatening announcement, the rebellious men will pay no heed. They regard their own leaders &amp; their own deliberate agreements as of no account. Some malignant force in the back&#8211;ground, advancing &amp; retiring as it pleases but always present, seems to control these "Labour" troubles. Germany's interest in them is so obvious, &amp; so considerable, that we cannot wonder that the spy&#8211;maniacs point to them as the unquestionable demonstrations of their own demented reasonings.</hi>        
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Meanwhile the German resistance is hardening, &amp; Foch's<persName xml:id="4563"></persName> stroke appears to have reached its limit. D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Pattison’s<persName xml:id="4893" display="no"></persName> boy, Adrian<persName xml:id="4831" display="no"></persName>, is recovering from pneumonia. He shares the nurse with me. She brought from him for my use the circular, india&#8211;rubber cushion wh. is used by the bed&#8211;ridden: &amp; I amused myself by writing him in return a nonsense&#8211;letter. <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> visited me: and Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> came &amp; did what seemed necessary in the way of correspondence.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I sent off the letter to Shakespeare</hi><persName xml:id="393"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Also I wrote a "disciplinary letter, of which a copy is annexed: and I sent my photograph to Miss Ledger, with a letter expressing regret at my inability to carry out my promise of officiating at her wedding next Saturday.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi><hi> [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>July 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Dear M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Southwell<persName xml:id="4683"></persName>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I have learned from the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> with very deep regret the public scandal which once more has gathered about your name. It may, perhaps, be the case that some arrangement may be possible, which, while satisfying your creditors, would leave to me, as your Bishop, no legal power to sequestrate your benefice, &amp; make provision for its religious needs. Nothing can however, deprive me as your ecclesiastical superior, of the melancholy duty of conveying to you a message of censure, and, as one who must needs be deeply interested in your pastoral efficiency, of adding to it an earnest entreaty that you would take into your anxious &amp; penitent thought the greatness of the fault into which you have fallen. Be under no delusion, whatever extenuations neighbours may make, or your own thoughts suggest. No spiritual </hi><hi rend="italic underline">authority</hi><hi rend="italic"> can possibly attach to the teaching of a clergyman who plainly in his own example falls below the moral standard which the conscience of plain men demands, &amp; their behaviour illustrates. "We (teachers)" says S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> James, "shall receive heavier judgement". I entreat you to think over these things, &amp; to seek the help of God to make amends for your offence by more careful living in the future, &amp; more responsible pastorate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, ever to be in genuine goodwill,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Your faithful Bishop</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div></body></text></TEI>
