<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[84]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1437</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> took occasion to make an elaborate &amp; rather vitriolic speech attacking the Liberal Anglicans in general, and Canons Sanday<persName xml:id="359"></persName> &amp; Glazebrook<persName xml:id="4234"></persName> in particular. I was moved to speak scornfully, though I acquiesced in the Archbishop's<persName xml:id="128"></persName> proposal to avoid a general discussion. It was a pity, &amp; opposed to the conciliatory course which I had marked out for myself. I think the general feeling was that</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</hi><persName xml:id="2462"></persName><hi> had abused his advantage. The Bishop of Salisbury<persName xml:id="178"></persName> spoke to me in that strain, &amp; assured me of his desire to establish kindly relations. I lunched with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. Canon<persName xml:id="3746"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Scott from Manchester were there. The Canons of Manchester are seizing the opportunity provided by Welldon's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> departure to try to shake off the yoke which he had imposed. They are "taking counsel's opinion" on a number of questions as to the limits of the decanal authority. In the afternoon the Bishop of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName> brought forward a motion on the subject of the new electorate, how best the gravity of their civic character might be brought home to them.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I suggested that the Abps<persName xml:id="128"><persName xml:id="130"></persName></persName> should draft a letter, to be signed by all the bishops, &amp; published at what sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> <hi rend="italic">appear to be the right time. This secured general approval, and was adopted unanimously. I called on Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, &amp; found her out for the day. Then I walked to Kennington, &amp; dined with Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="2293"></persName> very pleasantly. There was thunder &amp; rain at intervals today.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
