<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[18]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1373</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> accepts the prebendal stall in a very proper letter</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I received from the G.W.R. a "season ticket" to &amp; from London for 6 months, &amp; sent the requisite cheque</hi> <hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;36.14.6</hi><hi>. Also I wrote to Edgar Dobbie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> at Durham School, &amp; had an interview with the Registrar. After an early lunch we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> &amp; I) motored to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Much Wenlock vi&#x00E2;</hi><hi> Leominster &amp; Ludlow, a distance of about 40 miles. Unfortunately rain began to fall soon after we started, &amp; hindered us from enjoying the country. At Much Wenlock I confirmed 26 candidates &amp; gave an address from the words. "</hi><hi rend="underline">He endured as seeing Him who is invisible"</hi><hi>. The service was reverent, &amp; I trust, edifying. After it had finished, we had tea with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Furlong, &amp; were then taken charge of by Miss Gaskell, the daughter of the proprietor of the old Cluniac Priory. She showed as the Prior's House, a fascinating medieval residence. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Gaskell<persName xml:id="4566"></persName> is the patron of Much Wenlock, &amp; one of the two squires. The other is M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> J. H. A. Whitley Bourton. He was in church, &amp; afterwards came into the vestry &amp; introduced himself. The church of the Holy Trinity, Much Wenlock, is a fine medieval building full of interesting features, which, however, I had no time to examine with adequate care. Even through the rain, it was apparent that the little town is of rare beauty &amp; interest. We started on our return journey about 5.30 p.m. and were back in the close about 8 p.m. 40 miles in 2½ hours, an average of 16 miles an hour. There is a good deal of hill work which for a bad climber like our car makes for delay: &amp; the sodden state of the roads did not improve matters.</hi>    
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
