<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1476</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to church at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. It pleased me that the service was read fully as it stands in the Prayer&#8211;book including the Ten Commandments. I doubt whether there is much genuine feeling in the denunciation of that feature of the English liturgy.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">The outcry really comes altogether from the Mass&#8211;mongers.</hi><hi> While the ladies withdrew themselves to church and hospital, I sate at home and wrote a number of letters including one to Olive<persName xml:id="1696"></persName> and one to Ernest. </hi><hi rend="italic">In the afternoon Ella and I called at "Orion", where Sir Edward Carson<persName xml:id="2052"></persName> lives: but we could make nobody hear, so were forced to drop cards in the post&#8211;box and come away</hi><hi>. After tea we walked on the cliffs, and returned on the sands. In the evening lights the scene was impressively beautiful. We noticed an unusual number of soldiers about some with their rifles, and connected them with a story that is current as to some boys having found a bomb of immense destructive capacity placed beside the big gun which guards the coast. Officers from Canterbury are said to have come over to inquire &amp; inspect. The inventive boys are said to have been recompensed with fifteen shillings a piece. So runs the main rumour but there are many ornamental variants, and it is not necessary to believe what one hears. In the present temper of the popular mind rumours rise with prodigal ease, attain vast proportions and are received with greedy eagerness.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
