<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1505</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The wet weather continues. About noon Archdeacon Winnington&#8211;Ingram<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> arrived, &amp; accompanied me on a little tour of inspection. We visited 4 churches: 1. Stretton Grandison, 2. Ashperton, 3. Canon Frome, 4. Munsley, all in the Deanery of Ledbury. The first two are under the charge of the Rev C. C. Randle<persName xml:id="4658"></persName>: the last two under that of the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> L. G. Hunt<persName xml:id="4596"></persName>. The patroness of them all is M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Hopton<persName xml:id="4590"></persName>. We lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Randle: had coffee with <persName xml:id="4589">Col.</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Hopton: &amp; had tea with Col. &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Campbell, (churchwarden of Munsley). In Stretton Grandison there is a notable tablet to Col. Hopton, the Cavalier<persName xml:id="4588"></persName>, underneath which is one of his gauntlets. The inscription is very quaint &amp; interesting. Ashperton Church is woefully dilapidated. It contains nothing more interesting than a tablet with the garter largely carved on it. This has no inscription, but is said to commemorate the Lady Salisbury<persName xml:id="4570"></persName>, in whose honour the Order of the Garter was founded. George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> arrived during our absence: he is bronzed and broadened, but less changed than I had expected. Christian <persName xml:id="1951">Car&#x00F6;e</persName> also arrived. Her uncle, D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Rendal<persName xml:id="2504"></persName>, lately headmaster of Charterhouse, came to dinner. So we made quite a pleasant dinner party.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to Sir Edward Clarke<persName xml:id="4002"></persName> and the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName> on the subject of my projected motion on the report State of our proceedings on the Church &amp; State C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>. Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> most kindly made a copy of my letter to Sir E. Clarke.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
