<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1363</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Still the glorious weather continues. The morning post brought me a letter from <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> enclosing two telegrams. One from Alice<persName xml:id="2763" display="no"></persName> gave the welcome information that our "missing" Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName> is a prisoner in Germany. The other, from Ernest, was sufficiently alarming. It ran thus:&#8211;</hi>    
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Will you marry me Salonica June first Await letter following</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi>"</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>There must be a displacement of the words. "Salonika" should come after "await". But, even so, how can I answer such a question? The telegram was sent from Salonika on the 23</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> : it comes into my hands on the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. He can hardly be waiting there still.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Lady L.<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> motored me to the station, where we parted. I went to Edinburgh without incident, and arrived at 16 Moray Place abot 5 p.m. Sir James<persName xml:id="4555"></persName> &amp; Lady Ewing<persName xml:id="4556"></persName> received me with much kindness</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> He was one of the recipients of degrees in Durham in May 1913, when the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="3129"></persName> was inaugurated as Chancellor. After tea I walked the length of Prince's Street. The sauntering crowd was mostly in petticoats or in uniforms! Miss Nelson came to dinner, a prim spinster rather deaf &amp; a friend of Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName>. Macrae, one of the clergy of the U.F. S. George's Church, came in to ascertain what I wished about tomorrow's service. After he had taken his departure, I talked with mine host for an hour before going to bed.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He appears to be an eminent authority on mechanics, &amp; as such to be actively employed by the Admiralty. I found his conversation informing &amp; full of interest.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
