<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1399</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The sun shone fiercely from a cloudless sky, &amp; the heat was tropical. Radcliffe<persName xml:id="4657"></persName> and I had breakfast together at the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and then I walked to Westminster, in order to preach in the Abbey. There was a large congregation mainly of middle&#8211;aged men, &amp; women, with a large sprinkling of both sexes in uniform. The Archbishop of Canterbury<persName xml:id="128"></persName> sate in the stall behind the dean's pew. Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> was there, but of the Chapter none save the Canon in residence, Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>. My text was Ephesians iv.25. "Wherefore, putting away falsehood, speak ye truth each one with his neighbour: for we are members one of another".</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I preached for 36 minutes, and, I think, held my hearers throughout</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I lunched with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, &amp; then returned to my lodging, &amp; remained </hi><hi rend="underline">perdu</hi><hi>. I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. After having tea in the Club,</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote a note to Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> thanking him for his article in the 'Church Quarterly'<ref xml:id="1002"></ref>.</hi><hi> Lord Muir&#8211;Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName> was in the club. His barber observed to him this morning: "I will not insult you, my Lord, by supposing that your name is not among the 47,000"! The incident is not without a grave significance, for it shows that the public interest is centred on this astonishing law&#8211;suit.</hi><note xml:id="442" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">At 6.15 p.m. I preached in S. Martin's Trafalgar Square, on "Reunion"</hi><ref xml:id="1053"></ref><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Dick Shepperd<persName xml:id="3611"></persName> and the Lambeth Librarian, Jenkinson, were the officiating clergymen. My text was taken from S. John XVII. There was a considerable congregation, which listened very attentively throughout.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Clarence<persName xml:id="1301"></persName> &amp; Dorothy Tait<persName xml:id="2121"></persName> came into the vestry after service. The first in khaki, &amp; looking rather war&#8211;worn. Outside was their father<persName xml:id="1185"></persName>. Clarence Stock<persName xml:id="1178"></persName> was also there. Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> walked with me to D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Beauchamp's<persName xml:id="4481"></persName> house.</hi> <hi rend="italic">He is just back from France, where he had been accompanied by "Canon" Perkins<persName xml:id="170"></persName>, whom he found a tiresome bore, &amp; the French an inexplicable block&#8211;head! He said that it had been pointed out to him that Alsace&#8211;Lorraine was intensely religious, &amp; would not be united with an "infidel" France.</hi><hi> The Americans were associating more closely with the British, rather to their own surprize, &amp; to the regret of the French, who however found them grasping &amp; unclubbable. There was a good deal of sickness among the American troops, notably pneumonia. He found the French hospitals horribly dirty, but the French soldiers very good patients. A young naval officer, Commander Edward&#8211;Collin, was also at supper. After walking with Linetta to Palace Street, we walked together as far as the Admiralty Arch. He had been navigator of the Flag&#8211;ship in the Battle of Jutland Bank. He said that he was so busy at his work, that he could see very little of the fighting. Thus ends an arduous, and possibly also an important Sunday.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The two sermons, taken together, form a kind of programme for my episcopate, viz. a liberal attitude towards doctrinal re&#8211;statement, and practical co&#8211;operation with non&#8211;episcopal churchs</hi><hi> [sic].</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
