<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1358</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I got some private talk with <persName xml:id="4700">W.</persName> after breakfast. He gave a dark view of the moral situation in France. "There seems to be a dense fog of evil which takes you by the throat". French officers had begged him not to judge France by what was now the case in the Northern District, where the British armies were now in occupation. The War had created a flood of sensuality before which everything went down. Practically every French woman was a harlot. The extent of venereal disease was so great that the strength of the Army was seriously affected. An alarming spread of sodomy was becoming apparent. This gloomy picture was not drawn from a morbid imagination, but was a transcript of the facts. He gave a very ill account of the Portuguese, whose cowardice nearly caused an immense disaster, and whose morals were abominable. Yet we read eloquent descriptions of their valour, &amp; formal congratulations are addressed to them by our Leaders!!</hi>           		
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Ross at 10.32 a.m. &amp; had an hour in Hereford before </hi><hi rend="bold underline">going on to London by the 12.42 noon</hi><hi>. <persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName> got in at Malvern, &amp; Professor<persName xml:id="4505"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wright of Oxford. Their conversation whiled away the time. I drove to King's Cross &amp; settled my bags in my room. Then I went to Garland's Hotel in Suffolk Street, &amp; booked a room for next Monday. I dined in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> very pleasantly with Sir Henry Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName> &amp; then went back to King's Cross.</hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
