<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1383</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Another brilliant day, and even hot. My morning was disturbed by visitors. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Haslewood<persName xml:id="4582"></persName>, to whom I have offered the living of Bredwardine came to lunch, and then accompanied me in the motor to the parish, which is 12 miles distant from Hereford. We visited the vicarage and the church, and called on M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Williams<persName xml:id="4895" display="no"></persName>, the squire.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The vicarage is a rather large &amp; rambling house, well set up on the bank of the Wye, with gadens sloping down to the river. There are stables &amp; other outhouses, all looking rather dilapidated. On the whole, however, the place was more attractive than I expected. The church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Andrew is placed a little higher up the slope, and is an interesting edifice. On the north wall of the nave I noticed some herring&#8211;bone work. The font was uncommonly commodious, and might have been Norman. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Williams the squire is a fine looking old man, reputed to be a Protestant. He told me that, when he was an undergraduate at Cambridge, he often breakfasted with F. D. Maurice<persName xml:id="687"></persName>. I understood him to say that he had some family connexion with the Maurices. We were back in Hereford shortly after 5 p.m. and I went to the Palace, &amp; revised a sermon for Sunday. Then Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> came to me with a bundle of letters which kept me busy until dinner time. Alice<persName xml:id="2763" display="no"></persName> writes to tell me that she has received a post card from the imprisoned Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName>, who appears to be confined in Karlsruhe. The country is rushing into the opulent verdure of summer.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
