<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[92]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1445</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I can sympathise with Job, for I am similarly afflicted. My collar is unendurable, &amp; sitting down is a form of torture!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I travelled to Ford, vi&#x00E0; Shrewsbury, where the Vicar (Craft<persName xml:id="4538"></persName>) met me with a motor. Here I confirmed 5 boys and 16 girls in the little parish church, which has a 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> &#8211;century roof, and a Norman window on the southern wall of the Nave. The Vicar &amp; his wife gave tea to several people afterwards, but I wondered at the absence of the clergy from the district. It is true that there was a sudden down&#8211;pour of rain earlier in the afternoon, which might have hindered men, who must travel on bicycles, from venturing out. The hay harvest is in progress, and in this utterly rural district, the clergy make their own hay. Still the total absence of the clergy was surprising, &amp; possibly also suggestive. The Crafts have six children, &amp; have an amiable though poverty&#8211;driven aspect. I managed to catch the express from Shrewsbury. My travelling companion was M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Redmond from Belmont, who obligingly motored me to the Cathedral Close. He told me that his son was a master at Eton, and had met me there when I last preached to the School. I went to</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Pattison</hi><persName xml:id="4893" display="no"></persName><hi>, 34 Castle St., about my ailments, but got little comfort!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The pretty ticket collector is named Eva Luther<persName xml:id="4618"></persName>. She sent her kind regards to Craft, who until recently was Vicar of the parish, in which her family were living. This incident predisposed me to think that Craft must be a good parochus. </hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
