<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1500</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This is poor </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jennie's</hi><persName xml:id="84"></persName><hi rend="italic"> birthday. Was there ever a life more given to others, and more empty of every self&#8211;indulgence? It is 22 years since she died, and I feel still the pang of a grief which was half resentment. That, and the death of my poor little infant, perished ere it lived, have left indelible scars of sorrow and rage on my heart. I cannot get over these tragedies. They seem to focus the misery of the world. How different might my life have been if the child had lived! Now I must needs live "from hand to mouth".</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I breakfasted pleasantly in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName>, and then attended the meeting of the Committee at Westminster. We finished the business by lunch&#8211;time. I lunched at the Athenaeum with Amery<persName xml:id="324"></persName> &amp; Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName>, and then had my hair cut. After this, I walked to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Bull's bookshop, &amp; brought a few books.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">The book&#8211;man was a Conscientious objector. He professed much regard &amp; even admiration for me, &amp; I think the poor fool may have been sincere</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">"When I think of you, Sir: I always picture all things peaceful &amp; beautiful". This to the most cynical &amp; battered old gladiator in the Church!! I dined in the Club with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">W. P. Ker</hi><persName xml:id="22"></persName><hi rend="italic">. He is, indeed, the best of men, &amp; the truest of friends – pure gold. Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> &amp; Newbolt were at the next table, good men both. Ker walked with me as far as the corner of Suffolk Street. The sky was brilliant with search lights.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
