<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1380</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I left Hereford by the early train (7.20 a.m.) and travelled to London arriving about 12.30 p.m.</hi><hi> I proceeded by tube (asphyxiating journey) to Trafalgar Square, &amp; walked to Garland's Hotel. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> &amp; lunched. There the Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="2047"></persName> way&#8211;laid me, &amp; extracted my consent to the absorption of the piece of Worcestershire now included in my diocese into his new "county&#8211;diocese" of Worcester. My predecessor had consented to this, and I could not well see my way to refuse. But I don't like these new dioceses! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">After lunch I walked to Lambeth, &amp; attended a meeting of bishops</hi><hi rend="italic">. We discussed the new situation which will be created by Fisher's<persName xml:id="2107"></persName> Education Bill.<note xml:id="349" n="1"></note> The Bp of Lichfield<persName xml:id="3831"></persName> explained an ‘agreed scheme’ wh. had been drafted by a Committee of Bishops. It seems that the Bishops, even their Lordships of Oxford<persName xml:id="49"></persName> &amp; Southwell<persName xml:id="111"></persName>, have come to understand tht the days of "Church Schools" are numbered. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bp of S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Edmundsbury<persName xml:id="3668"></persName> &amp; Ipswich introduced a report recommending the establishment of a Central Press Information Bureau</hi><hi rend="italic">, to provide trustworthy news on eccles</hi><hi rend="i sup u">l</hi><hi rend="italic"> affairs to the Press.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I strongly opposed the creation of yet another device for strangling such independence</hi><hi rend="italic"> as yet lingers in the Church. It was decided to have a further Report. I walked back to Westminster with the Bp. Of Liverpool<persName xml:id="477"></persName>, &amp; dined at the Athenaeum with the Bp. of Manchester<persName xml:id="242"></persName>. I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> before returning to the Hotel. Here the painters are at work, &amp; the whole place reeks with the smell of fresh paint to my extreme &amp; increasing discomfort.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
