<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[221]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most beautiful morning, mild and bright. The sun shining on the turf, and gleaming on the river, made a jocund spectacle from my study windows. Opulent white&#8211;faced kine on the meadow beyond the river gave an aspect of fat security to the scene. I wasted the morning over the memoir<ref xml:id="996"></ref>. Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> turned up for a few minutes looking well enough, after the luxury of influenza! After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi> <hi rend="italic"> and I called on old M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Bosanquet<persName xml:id="4516"></persName>, whom we found sitting in his study, the very picture of an aged astrologer! He says that the people of Hereford are beyond all others slothful and apathetic, which he attributes to the soft enervating climate and to their consumption of cider in vast quantities. Herein, he but echoes an opinion which I hear frequently expressed. Some add that the people are also excessively sly &amp; untruthful, qualities which arise from the admixture of Welsh blood, &amp; the continuing infection of Welsh example. All this is rather discouraging. On our way home we stopped at the railway station, where I got my season ticket &amp; paid for the same the inordinate sum of &#x00A3;44.1.5. Four years ago this ticket would have cost &#x00A3;26. This means an increase of &#x00A3;36 for a years travelling to London. <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> came to do secretary's work. He tells me that about 2500 munition girls have already left the city, &amp; that the more choice &amp; costly fruits have already fallen in price! The streets are certainly far less noisy &amp; crowded. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="4450"></persName> arrived about 6.30 p.m. in order to be on the spot for his meeting tomorrow. I wrote several letters. </hi>
         </p>
        </body></text></TEI>
