<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[203]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1546</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th </hi><hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Cathedral at 8 a.m. At 11 a.m. I preached in Tupsley Parish Church, a modern building with good acoustics &amp; little architectural merit.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Vicar, Ledger<persName xml:id="4609"></persName>, seemed an intelligent man. He asked my ruling on the case of a woman, confirmed and communicant, who had discovered that she had never been baptised. I told him to ascertain the fact more carefully, &amp; to baptize her privately. If there were any dubiety, the baptism was to be conditional. There was no need for her to be confirmed again.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I preached in the Cathedral at 6.30 p.m. from the words of David. "There is none like that = give it me". This served as a text for a sermon on the Bible.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I wrote letters to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> who, to my regret &amp; disappointment, expresses a disgust of maritime life, and a desire to abandon it<note xml:id="433" display="no" n="1"></note></hi><hi> : and to Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The morning's past had brought letters from both of them. Ernest writes on official Bulgarian note&#8211;paper, which he had "looted" during the recent advance. He is in good spirits, and evidently thinks the end of the war is near, which will release him (as he assumes) from hardships,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">and enable him to marry his Beloved.</hi><hi> I cannot wholly share his hopes. It seems barely credible that the walls of "Militarism" can fall flat so promptly at the ram's horn blast from America. It</hi> <hi rend="underline">may</hi><hi>, of course, be the case that Germany is so exhausted as to be literally unable to continue the War, or too disaffected to be willing to do so. But I doubt both suppositions.</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
