<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1532</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A fine day after the rain, bright but cold. I had breakfast in bed, and then got up &amp; went to service in the Cathedral. The paper reports that the German Government has replied to President Wilson<persName xml:id="2814"></persName> accepting his 14 conditions, &amp; undertaking to withdraw from the invaded territories. This creates an interesting situation. I remained indoors during the afternoon, and even avoided the party of Canadian soldiers whom Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> brought in to tea. At 6.30 p.m. there was a large congregation in the Cathedral.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">As I walked beside the Dean, I reflected on the strange fortune that had brought us together,<note xml:id="427" n="1"></note> &amp; how but a few months ago he was publicly opposing my entrance into the see</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I could wish that I were more adequate to my fortunes, &amp; more able to discern &amp; to utilise my opportunities. I preached on "Change &amp; the Unchanging", using with little alteration the sermon I wrote for Leominster. The congregation was very attentive, but (though I think they could all hear) I found no comfort in my preaching! A general Bridgeford<persName xml:id="4517"></persName> and his daughter were introduced to me as hailing from Hereford. It appears that they live near Pembridge, &amp; that I met the young lady when I preached the Harvest Festival there. He is now stationed at Margate. At supper there came Lieutenant Duff and his wife, &amp; a lady who said she was a niece of the late Archdeacon of Northumberland. Ruth's playing was an agreeable conclusion to a rather futile &amp;</hi> <hi rend="underline">miscellaneous</hi><hi> Sunday, in which I did little, red little, thought little, and wrote nothing. What an account to render!</hi>  
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
