<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1553</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My mind revolved during the night the rather perplexing question, What shall be the subject of my 3 Advent addresses in the Cathedral? To be interesting and to avoid controversy are not easily reconcilable ends, least so when the general subject is hotly debated, and when the individual is immersed (through no fault of his own) in a cloud of suspicions.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The day was dark and damp to start with, &amp; so continued until night. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ludlow</hi><hi>, and there spent the day. I preached in the glorious parish church (S. Lawrence) both at Mattins &amp; at Evensong. Also I celebrated after Mattins. The congregations were smaller than I expected but the weather was wretched, there is an epidemic of influenza, and the War takes many away. The people were attentive, the choir well&#8211;behaved, the service reverent, &amp; the singing good. The Rector, the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> A. E. Lloyd Kenyon<persName xml:id="4602"></persName>, is an unmarried man. As he took his degree in 1883, I assume that he is about 57 years old. The parish is in the gift of</hi> <hi rend="underline">Lord Plymouth</hi><persName xml:id="4708"></persName><hi> . There are, beside the Rector, a Lecturer and a Preacher, separately endowed and approved severally by the Corporation &amp; by the Trustees. This arrangement might easily lead to friction. On our return journey, the car ran into some horses which were straying on the road. The lamp was twisted, &amp; the mud&#8211;guard crumpled up. The horse which did the damage must have had a smart blow, but showed no great resentment. We arrived at the Palace about 11 p.m. The bad weather spoiled what would have been a pleasant experience.</hi>       
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
