<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1542</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the whole day from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. at Lambeth in conference with the other Bishops. We decided to have a special meeting of Bishops in November to discuss further the question of co&#8211;operation with Non&#8211;conformists. This matter having been thus disposed of, we went quickly through many items on the agenda.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> read a letter from Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName> stating that it was illegal for lay men to read Banns</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We had some figures from the Chaplain&#8211;General<persName xml:id="3507"></persName> about the Chaplains. From February to September, 561 names of clergy had been sent in by the Archbishop to the C.G. Of these 314 had been accepted, &amp; 56 rejected. 88 had been withdrawn (i.e.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">the men wouldn't go</hi><hi> ). 35 were medically unfit: 29 had been provisionally accepted: 10 were over&#8211;age: 25 were "pending", and 41 awaited investigation. To keep up the provision 40 fresh chaplains were required every month.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">In the course of the discussion on the Examination Scheme for Service Candidates, I stated that I would not personally be bound by any common scheme, but would retain my liberty of action unimpaired</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Several other bishops were in favour of this course. It was on the whole a tiresome &amp; futile day.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Radcliffe</hi><persName xml:id="4657"></persName><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Oman</hi><persName xml:id="2141"></persName><hi>. Then I wrote to all the nominees to office in the Universities' Lodge<orgName xml:id="267"></orgName>, Durham, asking them to accept the positions assigned to them for the coming year. I also wrote to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName><hi> informing him that I had done so. Then I returned to my Hotel, &amp; concluded a laboriously dull &amp; wasted day.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
