<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1541</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read the '</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi> ' in bed very luxuriously. At breakfast in the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I read the</hi> <hi rend="underline">Daily Telegraph</hi><hi>, and found there, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">to my surprise, a considerable report of my sermon at Hereford on the front page under a conspicuous heading</hi><hi rend="bold">.<note xml:id="432" n="1"></note></hi><hi> I walked to Westminster, &amp; there attended a Committee meeting on the relations of the Church &amp; Nonconformity. All the members of the C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> were present viz: the Bishops of Winchester<persName xml:id="105"></persName>, Ely<persName xml:id="532"></persName>, Norwich<persName xml:id="1816"></persName>, Ripon<persName xml:id="2074"></persName>, Southwell<persName xml:id="111"></persName>, S. Edmundsbury<persName xml:id="3668"></persName>, Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName>, &amp; myself. After protracted discussion we agreed unanimously on the following two resolutions:&#8211;</hi> 
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>That with the sanction of the Bishop Nonconformist ministers and others who are not members of the C. of E. may be invited by Incumbents to speak &amp; to pray in consecrated buildings on occasions other than those of the regular ordinary services of the Church.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>We think that conversely the terms of the previous resolution give the best general guidance for the case of the clergy who desire to take part in services other than those of the C. of E: and that, except in places reasonably regarded as extra&#8211;parochial, clergy sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not accept invitations to do this in other parishes than their own without the Incumbent's consent &amp; the Bishop's sanction.</hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>I lunched with Gow<persName xml:id="216"></persName>, &amp; then went to the Bishops' Conference at Lambeth where our resolutions were discussed at length. There was much timidity, &amp; some hostility.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I called on Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> in 5 Carlton Terrace. I dined with W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> in the Old Universities' Club.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
