<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1533</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Again a fine day, though misty for the early hours. I lay in bed reading until noon, and then got up &amp; wrote letters.</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"One lesson, and only one, history may be said to repeat with distinctness, that the world is built somehow on moral foundations: that, in the long run, it is well with the good; in the long run, it is ill with the wicked. But this is no science; it is no more than the old doctrine taught long ago by the Hebrew prophets" – J. A. Froude<persName xml:id="1409"></persName>.</hi> 
         </p>
</div><div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>"The address of history is less to the understanding than to the higher emotions. We learn in it to sympathise with what is great and good; we learn to hate what is base. In the anomalies of fortune we feel the mystery of our mortal existence, &amp; in the companionship of the illustrious natures who have shaped the fortunes of the world, we escape from the littleness which cling to the round of common life, and our minds are tuned in a higher and nobler key" (Ibid.)<note xml:id="428" n="1"></note></hi>  
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>How far is all this true? How far did Froude believe it to be true? "The illustrious natures who have shaped the fortunes of the world" are by no means edifying company for the most part.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After lunch M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Spooner<persName xml:id="2162"></persName>, Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and I went to the camp, and were shown over it by General Smythe<persName xml:id="4836" display="no"></persName>. We had tea with him very pleasantly. I was pleased to hear that a number of the young officers had been in the cathedral last night, and appear to have been impressed. After dinner Canon<persName xml:id="4133"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Bickersteth<persName xml:id="4510"></persName> came in to see us. He is pretentious, well&#8211;intentioned, &amp; muddle&#8211;headed.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
