<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1555</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Bank, &amp; arranged that &#x00A3;500 of War Loan<note xml:id="283" n="1"></note> should be sold out. This means that I shall have sacrificed &#x00A3;1000 of my savings in order to get into this bishoprick. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Ross, &amp; there I gave away prizes in the Grammar School, and made a speech to the Company. This function being ended, we had tea with Colonel<persName xml:id="4631"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Middleton, and then returned to Hereford, carrying with us Miss Krabbe. I found the Educational Inspector, Edwards, waiting to see me. He had been brought by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bulmer<persName xml:id="4521"></persName>. I had some conversation with him, from which I learned that the County of Hereford is evilly regarded by the educational people, while in Shropshire there is a 4? higher education rate: in Hereford we go no farther than the "whiskey money"! When M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Edwards had departed </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote a letter to a correspondent on the question of marriage with a deceased wife's sister. I suspect that there are not a few cases, like my correspondent's, in which there is a painful conflict between desire and prudence, morality &amp; expediency</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
