<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1537</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a thick fog, which hung over the city all the forenoon. I walked into the City to change a cheque. On the way I was hailed by a khaki&#8211;clad person who introduced himself as </hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Archdeacon Cody</hi><persName xml:id="2907"></persName><hi> from Toronto. He said that</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">everybody in Canada had rejoiced in my appointment to the Bpk.</hi><hi> He had been appointed Minister of Education (whatever that may mean) to the government of Ontario, &amp; was returning to Canada in a week's time to take up his new duties. I promised to preach for him in his fine new church when next I visited Canada. I returned to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parkin</hi><persName xml:id="2846"></persName><hi> joined me at lunch. He gave me a bad account of poor</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Raleigh</hi><persName xml:id="14"></persName><hi> who now seems barely able to communicate with visitors.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Parkin is an ardent advocate of this nonsensical "autonomy", and seems mightily taken with "Life and Liberty".<note xml:id="399" n="1"></note> I indicated my disapproval, which surprised him; but he is getting so deaf that conversation in a public place is not easy.</hi><hi> Having paid my reckoning at the Hotel, we came away to Paddington, where we caught the 3 p.m. express to Hereford. The train was very crowded, but we travelled in comparative comfort. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Best from Burghill was in our carriage.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The rapid advance of the armies under </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">King Albert</hi><persName xml:id="3083"></persName><hi> promises to relieve Belgium of the hateful presence of the German oppressors. With the recovery of the coast, the menace of the submarines diminished, and Londoners allow themselves to assume that there can be no more air&#8211;raids.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
