<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1557</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I motored into Durham with Lady Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName> &amp; Lady Anne Lambton<persName xml:id="3504"></persName>: and went to the Cathedral. I lunched with Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> in the Deanery. The house has rather an empty look, partly because all the feminine adjuncts belonging to a wife are absent, partly because the Dean has very few books. I called on Bishop Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and Hughes<persName xml:id="2953"></persName>. After lunch I went to the meeting of old Dunelmians, &amp; spoke in favour of the Chapel as a War Memorial. Then I had tea with Knowling, &amp; went to the Masonic Hall where I was installed as Worshipful Master of the Universities Lodge<orgName xml:id="267"></orgName> with all the ceremonies of Freemasonry. I was pleased to see there Lieut: Edward O. Cutter, with two wound&#8211;lines on his sleeve. He has been invalided home, &amp; is now in hospital near Leeds. He walked with me to the station, and talked very interestingly. I arrived at Lumley<placeName xml:id="62"></placeName> about 9 p.m. A gentleman, named, I think, Tapper<persName xml:id="4688"></persName>, the architect of York Minster, came here to dine &amp; sleep. I had so heavy a cold on me, and was afflicted with so many rheumatic pains, that I was glad to get to bed.</hi>          
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
