<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1560</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Sunday Paper announces the abdication of the Kaiser<persName xml:id="4705"></persName>, and the renunciation of his rights by the Crown Prince<persName xml:id="3781"></persName>. Was ever in all history a more dramatic example of retributive justice? But there is more anxiety than exultation in our triumph, for Revolution is on the march, &amp; that is a Power which respects frontiers no more than Cholera or Influenza. I remained in my study all the morning, wrote letters, and revised the sermon for the evening. I walked to the Mayor's Hospital, and on the way was accosted by a bicyclist, bent on some errand, who introduced himself as Percy Hull<persName xml:id="4595"></persName>, the organist who has just returned from captivity in Germany. I talked with the wounded soldiers, among whom was a very modest &amp; attractive V.C. In the evening I preached in S. Peter's, to an overflowing congregation. My sermon was that which I preached at Ludlow a week ago, with some interpolations adapted to the new situation.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Norcock<persName xml:id="4345"></persName> sent me his resignation</hi><hi>, but I doubt whether I ought to accept it, though I may not be able much longer to afford a chaplain.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
