<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1547</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a very kind &amp; informing letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Firth</hi><persName xml:id="2143"></persName><hi> in which </hi><hi rend="underline">inter alia</hi><hi> he refers me to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marvel's</hi><persName xml:id="4625"></persName><hi>"</hi><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Smirke</hi><hi> : or, the Divine in Mode: being certain Annotations, upon the Animadversions on the Naked Truth"<ref xml:id="998"></ref>. As I had the book, I looked up the reference, &amp; was richly rewarded. It is a racy &amp; powerful piece.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Hamilton Baynes</hi><persName xml:id="4124"></persName><hi> came to lunch. I had some talk with him about Reunion. His scheme of exchanging Ordination with Berry<persName xml:id="4130"></persName> of Carr's Lane hangs fire. The High Church bishops are afraid of it, and the more it is considered, the less attractive it appears. At 3 p.m. I took the Bishop to the Cathedral Library for a meeting of the British &amp; Foreign Bible Society<orgName xml:id="198"></orgName>. This was a woeful fiasco, for the Dean<persName xml:id="3741"></persName> had arranged an organ recital in the Cathedral at the same hour together with an unveiling of a window to the late organist,</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Sinclair</hi><persName xml:id="4679"></persName><hi>. Thus everybody went to the more attractive fuction, &amp; the Bible Society was deserted! There are disadvantages about octogenarians deans.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After making a short speech to open the meeting, I went off to the station, &amp; caught the 4 p.m. train to London. When I was getting into the Tube at Paddington the gentleman who had been my companion in the train introduced himself as the person who had written to me about <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley's</persName> fitness to be a Canon of Westminster. I said that, while I agree that <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> might fitly be appointed to a Westminster canonry, I did not think he was fitted for parochial charge. He seemed little contented with this answer, &amp; enlarged rather tiresomely on L's merits!</hi>   
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
