<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>While <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> went to church. I remained in my study, and put the finishing touches to the two sermons on the subject of today's celebration. I never remember finding so much difficulty in preparing sermons. One is sick to death of the vain glorious platitudes which fill the newspapers, and yet, when compelled to speak, what else can be said.</hi>   
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was an immense crowd in the Cathedral at the special service in the afternoon. Every variety of organized war&#8211;workers was present. I preached with difficulty, and was not well heard. There was much coughing, and the whole sermon seemed to me a failure. It was too substantial for the occasion, &amp; too elaborate for the congregation.</hi>    
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the evening I preached in All Saints Church. There was a larger congregation.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">After the sermon I was immersed in a cope, &amp; set before the High Altar with a circle of boys in red casscocks</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> <hi rend="italic">Here I remained while the "Te Deum" was sung, &amp; then I read the concluding prayers, &amp; gave the Benediction. Finally we left the Church in procession in which lighted candles were carried!! Now all this is very unpalatable to me, and, if I none the less surrender myself to it, it is assuredly with no purpose of commending such futilities. But can I better indicate the little importance which I attach to these things than by uniting in my public procedure, preaching in dissenting chapels </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">and</hi><hi rend="italic"> wearing a cope? Besides, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">since the cope is unquestionally legal, can I refuse to sanction its use without giving colour to the charge that I am narrowing the liberty of ceremonial within the National Church. Nevertheless</hi><hi rend="i bold">, </hi><hi rend="italic">I felt, as no doubt I looked, an ASS.</hi>
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
