<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1538</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A grey day, chilly but rainless, acutely autumnal.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi> came to see me after breakfast. He is in a quandary, as the Mayor<persName xml:id="4212"></persName> &amp; Corporation, who are due at All Saints for tomorrow morning on account of what is here called "Civic Sunday", object to the Choral Celebration which, since their last visit, has replaced the more familiar Mattins! I told him that he should re&#8211;place Mattins for this occasion.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">He asked me to "wear the vestments" when I come to celebrate at 8 a.m. This, of course, I refused</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Then I was invaded by an Ordination candidate, ardent but illiterate, whom I sent on to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName></hi><hi> : I went round to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">James</hi><persName xml:id="4292"></persName><hi> to seek materials for duly answering the Super&#8211;tax surveyor's letter. The tax&#8211;man was there, &amp; civilly sketched a letter for me. My sermon for the sectaries meanwhile hung fire badly. After lunch</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> and I, taking </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Penelope</hi><persName xml:id="2937"></persName><hi> &amp; another small girl in the car, motored to Bredwardine, &amp; called on the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Compstons</hi><persName xml:id="2010"><persName xml:id="4533"></persName></persName><hi>. The view from the Vicarage garden was magnificent. The autumn tints recalled by their brilliance the Berkshire Hills in U.S.A. when we saw them in the Fall of 1912. It is evident from what</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Compston</hi><hi> said that the feud between the churchwardens has not healed. The female warden is semi&#8211;hysterical; &amp; the male has the exasperating impeccability of a Saint! However I think he means to stick to his job now he has taken it on.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Henson</hi><persName xml:id="4264"></persName><hi>, the Headmaster of the Cathedral School, called to ask me to give away the prizes. We fixed on November 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> at 3 p.m. as the most suitable date. I worked hard at a sermon for the sectaries tomorrow.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
