<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[184]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1525</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A beautiful morning, but the day became gusty with showers of rain in the afternoon. Wonderfully packed up,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I motored with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to Bridgnorth</hi><hi>, 43 miles. Our journey was a "joy&#8211;ride" for the beauty of the country, with the colourings of autumn beginning to glow on the trees. I preached twice in the parish church, celebrated the Holy Communion, and addressed some wounded soldiers in the little hospital. We motored home in a dark night, and arrived in the Palace about midnight.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Prebendary Clark Maxwell</hi><persName xml:id="4167"></persName><hi>, Rector of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Leonard's, Bridgnorth, is an active intelligent man; a High Churchman but of a moderate type: an antiquarian and a man of affairs. His wife<persName xml:id="4531"></persName>, if I understood him correctly, is a grand&#8211;daughter of</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Selwyn</hi><persName xml:id="4673"></persName><hi> of Lichfield. I was particularly pleased with his reading of the lessons, and not less by the attention which the people gave to them. There is an interesting library – the Stackhouse Library – preserved in the vestry. It was left to the Bridgnorth clergy by the</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev Hugh Stackhouse</hi><hi> in 1742, and included "nearly 1240 publications and 163 pamphlets". The greater part of the collection had belonged to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Stackhouse's predecessor in the Headmastership of Bridgnorth Grammar School, the</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev Richard Cornes</hi><hi>, and came into M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> S's possession when he married </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridget Hall</hi><hi>, the relation ad sole executrix of M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Cornes. Some additions have been made by later gifts.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
