<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1535</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>We breakfasted together in the Hotel, &amp; then parted for the day. I went to the club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; spent the morning in preparing a summary of my lecture for (possible) use by the "Times". After lunching in the club, I walked with Newbolt<persName xml:id="3946"></persName> as far as King's College, &amp;</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">then went to the Colonial Office to join a deputation from the Anti&#8211;Slavery Society<orgName xml:id="213"></orgName> on the subject of native rights in Rhodesia</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">W. Long</hi><persName xml:id="2063"></persName><hi> was rather official, and unpromising. Then I returned to the club, &amp; had tea. I saw poor</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="31"></persName><hi>, who looks rather broken by his son's death. Of his 4 sons, only Victor<persName xml:id="4047"></persName> now survives, &amp; he is badly wounded.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I exchanged a few words with Asquith<persName xml:id="215"></persName> who looked very pink &amp; cheerful after his successful speech this afternoon to the National Liberal Club<orgName xml:id="8"></orgName>.<note xml:id="429" n="1"></note> The Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> came in, &amp; I talked with him. He said that he had just received a breezy letter from the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName>, who had been attending a meeting of the Kikuyuist missionaries, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">&amp; reported them to be far more afraid of Henson than of himself</hi><hi rend="i bold">!</hi> <hi rend="italic">I doubt not that his description of me, &amp; their own debased mentality would make those good Evangelicals sufficiently alarmed! Indeed I cannot doubt that the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> agitation against my appointment has rendered me 'suspect'</hi><hi> to the whole pious fraternity : &amp; so far it has for the time being gravely damaged my position in the church. There is a wonderful unanimity of approval of the President's Note to Germany.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
