<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1540</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters, &amp; tried to clear up my table. Then I went off to London to attend the meeting of Bishops. My journey was made interesting by the company and conversation of</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Shaw</hi><hi>, the railway &amp; mining magnate who resides in my diocese. He has recently returned from Paris, &amp; says that Foch<persName xml:id="4563"></persName> declares that, if November be fine, he can end the war before Christmas. He spoke of the demoralizing effects of the war, &amp; gave as an illustration</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">the great increase in pilfering among railway servants &amp; passengers. The G.W.R. had been compelled to cease supplying towels to the lavatories on the trains, as they were generally stolen. A loss of no less than &#x00A3;800 had been incurred form this cause in a brief period</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We spoke of the financial situation after the War, &amp; he was as gloomy as I. On arriving at Paddington I went by the Tube to Trafalgar Square. The train was grossly over&#8211;crowded, &amp; the atmosphere asphyxiating. I dined at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ker</hi><persName xml:id="22"></persName><hi> joined me. The evening papers publish Germany's reply to</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2814"></persName><hi> . It is a careful document, more yielding in appearance than in reality. Meanwhile there are signs that the retreat of the German armies is slowing down, &amp; their resistance growing more determined. The realization of the completeness of disaster which surrender implies may be acting as a tonic on the German nation. Their own frontier is extremely strong, and their armies are still numerous &amp; well&#8211;armed. It is incredible that they should not fight to the last before accepting the terms on which the Entente must needs insist.</hi>     
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
