<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1536</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in the Athenaeum writing letters, and giving the final touchings up to my lecture. Then I walked to Wells Street, and joined <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> at lunch with the Knights<persName xml:id="62"><persName xml:id="450"></persName></persName>.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">K. has had a medical warning, and now meditates retirement from London. It will be a pity for his influence in Printing House Square is valuable</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> We fell in with the Master of the Temple<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> on our way to King's College. Here we had tea in the rooms of Prof. Matthews<persName xml:id="4626"></persName>, the Dean of Theology, and met divers of the professors.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Edward Clarke</hi><persName xml:id="4002"></persName><hi> came also, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Bryce</hi><persName xml:id="389"></persName><hi>, who presided at the lecture. He introduced me as destined to carry on the succession of learned historian bishops, of whom Stubbs<persName xml:id="2924"></persName> &amp; Creighton<persName xml:id="118"></persName> were illustrious examples. But I felt woefully abashed by his words knowing well that I could be no more than one of the Nethinim<note xml:id="430" n="1"></note> in that company! However, I delivered my lecture to a very large audience and was well listened to. On the whole the atmosphere was distinctly sympathetic.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName><hi> dined with us at the Hotel: and then I went round to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Here I had a most interesting conversation with a Club–member, whose name I don't know, and who told me that he had examined much of the evidence for atrocities in Belgium, and the ill treatment of our own prisoners, and that he was convinced not only that many abominable things had been done,</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">but also that there had been very much of a different character which our Government did not suffer to be published, and which would mitigate the horrible aspect of the general position</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Bishop Crofts<persName xml:id="4540"></persName> in </hi><hi rend="i bold">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Naked Truth, or the True State of the Primitive Church</hi><hi rend="i bold">"<ref xml:id="1026"></ref></hi> <hi rend="italic">published in 1675, has much to say on the subject of episcopy.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"When our bishops do ordain presbyters, do they not use the very same form of words which our Saviour used when he ordained the apostles?</hi> <hi rend="italic underline">"Receive ye the Holy Ghost: whose sins ye forgive, they are forgiven" etc.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Do they not then by the same words confer the same powers? (for I hope they use no equivocation, nor mental reservation) if the power be the same, the order is the same by their own rule …………..</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">give me leave to tell you that I shall not easily recede from scripture in fundamentals, either of faith or church discipline; in things indifferent of themselves, or in more weighty matters very doubtfully expressed in scripture, I shall always most readily submit to the interpretation of the primitive &amp; universal church, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I require both primitive &amp; universal; for I shewed before, that in matters of faith there were some errors very primitive, yet not continued by the universal church, but rejected in succeeding ages</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">And at the time of the evangelical reformation by Luther, Melancthon<persName xml:id="4629"></persName>, Calvin<persName xml:id="930"></persName> etc. I can show some errors generally received in most, if not in all the churches in Christendom, but neither approved nor known by the primitive church. Wherefore, I require what you produce sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be both primitive &amp; universal, &amp; this to interpret some place of Scripture doubtful in itself, not plain.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Now as to the business in hand, I cannot yield, that the scripture is very doubtful in it, or scarce doubtful at all: for though in scripture it is not </hi><hi rend="italic underline">in terminis</hi> <hi rend="italic">[in the end] said, presbytery &amp; episcopacy are both one in the same order, yet the same circumstantial expressions are (as I have shewed) so strong and many, that they are equivalent to a clear expression </hi><hi rend="italic underline">in terminis.</hi> <hi rend="italic">Secondly, this is not a matter of any indifferency, but of vast &amp; dangerous consequence, if mistaken. That a church without such bishops as you require cannot be truly called a church, &amp; so we shall exclude many godly reformed churches: For if bishops be of such a superior distinct order as you pretend, if the power of ordination be inherent in them only, then where no bishop no true priests ordained, where no priests no sacraments, where no sacraments no church.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Wherefore I humbly beseech you be not too positive in this point, lest thereby you do not only condemn all the reformed churches, but the Scripture &amp; S. Paul also; who tells us, That the scripture is sufficient to make us wise unto salvation, both in matters of faith &amp; works also, to instruct &amp; thoroughly furnish us to every good work: &amp; will any deny this of ordination to be both a good &amp; necessary work</hi><hi rend="italic">, seeing that the powerful preaching of the word &amp; administration of the sacraments depend upon it? Wherefore I dare not by any means suspect the scripture defective in this weighty affair"</hi>
         </p>
</div>
            </body></text></TEI>
