<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1558</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Today I complete 55 years of life in the world. The elasticity of youth has passed, &amp; I grow familiar after the manner of the ancients with rheumatics, lumbago, and the like. This hateful war has stripped life of everything that made it desirable, and created an outlook so threatening that only the audacity of youth could face it without terror. Yet the review of all these years must needs stir in my mind a deep thankfulness to the God who has led me on my path, and preserved me therein. I wish that I had a clearer vision of duty, and a more resolute purpose. As a bishop I find my way harder to discern, &amp; more difficult to follow than ever before.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi><persName xml:id="2817"></persName><hi> gave me her photograph as a Birthday present, &amp; walked with me to the station at Chester&#8211;Le&#8211;Street. A young officer in charge of a company of troops got into my carriage. We got into conversation, &amp; he told me that he had been one of my congregation in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. He had been preparing for Ordination at Kelham when the War broke out, &amp; was now in some doubt as to his purpose. He came from Norfolk, and his name was </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Everett</hi><hi>. I told him that he might write to me, if he wished to do so. I had half an hour's wait at Durham, &amp; so was able to enjoy the view of the Cathedral</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">without the obstruction of the hoardings, which have now been pulled down.<note xml:id="435" n="1"></note> I was touched by the affectionate greetings of the railway men</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I stopped at York for the night. After dinner an unknown man stopped me to say that he had written to the "Times" on my behalf, when the controversy was proceeding.</hi> 
         </p>
            </body></text></TEI>
