<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[410]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">Monday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1900.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>As the news of my approaching departure from the <orgName xml:id="9">Hospital</orgName> circulates, <hi rend="bold underline">the vultures of ambition scent the carcase of 'preferment'</hi>.  The post brought me a long letter from the <persName xml:id="72">Archdeacon</persName> suggesting that the Hospital would just suit his case.  <persName xml:id="73">Bayne</persName> of Little Ilford came to see me during the morning, and silently indicated an impression that he could fitly succeed me here.  <persName xml:id="79">Trist</persName> came in the afternoon to ask my advice in the character of an avowed expectant.  This eagerness is rather nauseous.  </p>
         <p>I received a letter from <persName xml:id="80">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mattinson</persName>, one of the Benchers of Gray's Inn, sounding me about the Preachership there, vacant thro' <persName xml:id="81">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lupton</persName>'s infirmity.  A few weeks ago I should have clutched at it: now I neither need nor care for it.  <hi rend="bold underline">May God help me to use rightly His new gift of prosperity! I dread this exhilaration &amp; uplifting of heart: what room is there for such sentiment in my present state? I have received an utterly underserved promotion, &amp; am called to a work quite beyond my powers. Have mercy on me, O God, &amp; enable what Thou dost demand</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
