<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[414]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1900.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The morning post brought me a very kindly&#8211;expressed letter from <persName xml:id="87">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Talbot</persName>.  He undertakes to inquire into 'this strange &amp; unexplained delay': &amp; promises every assistance in his power to me as Rector.  For the rest I worried through the day wearily enough.  I am the worst <hi rend="underline">waiter</hi> in the world.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Talbot speaks thus of my new position:&#8211;</p>
         <p><div type="quote">
            <hi rend="italic">'You have indeed a great place to fill, probably (short of the highest) there are none greater in the English Church &#8211; with the double duty of ministering to an important congregation (with a few really poor people) &amp; of taking part in the conduct of the Abbey, for which I see you share my enthusiasm'.</hi></div></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="92" display="no">Lewis</persName> sent me a kind letter.    </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[415]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Nov:, I travelled to Oxford in the same carriage with the <persName xml:id="93">Rector</persName> of Exeter, &amp; <persName xml:id="94">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Jackson</persName>. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold underline">On Saturday, the 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, the official announcement of my appointment appeared</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <persName xml:id="95"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Ramsey</hi></persName> stayed in <orgName xml:id="7" display="no">college</orgName> with me from Saturday to Monday.</p>
         <p>On the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Sun: after Trinity, Nov: 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I dined in Hall at Trinity with the <persName xml:id="96">President</persName>, &amp; afterwards <listEvent><event xml:id="88" display="no">spoke</event></listEvent> to the undergraduates about their <orgName xml:id="15">Mission</orgName> in Stratford.</p>
         <p>On Monday, Nov. 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, came to town, &amp; went at once to Westminster; called on <persName xml:id="44">Armitage Robinson</persName>, and had an interview with <persName xml:id="97">Robins</persName>, the sole surviving curate.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, Nov. 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> went to Evensong at the Abbey, called on <persName xml:id="98">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hunt</persName>, the <term xml:id="8">Rector's Churchwarden</term>, had tea with the <persName xml:id="99">Dean</persName>, &amp; more talk with the curate.<note xml:id="65" n="1"></note>  On these three days I received 115 letters of congratulation &amp; answered them all.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Nov. 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, I received a cutting from the 'Daily News' of yesterday, containing a long &amp; not unfriendly <ref xml:id="271">review</ref> of <ref xml:id="1">"<hi rend="underline">Church Problems</hi>"</ref>.<note xml:id="81" n="1"></note>  I received a dozen more letters of congratulation, wh. brings up the number to 127. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[416]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O God, the Holy Ghost, most blessed Comforter of Christian Souls, look with compassion on me at this time. I am so miserably bound by sin &amp; infirmity that I almost despair of myself. Vain exultation uplifts me at success, however undeserved, I dare to rejoice at the burden of new duties. Have mercy on me, &amp; visit my heart with Thy cleansing, consecrating graces. Give me humility and submission to Thy Will. Purify my motives, chasten &amp; restrain my ambitions, quicken my conscience, direct my understanding, kindle my heart. Come to me for guidance &amp; dedication. I give myself up to Thy government from this hour.</p>
         <p>Come, Holy Ghost, my soul inspire.<note xml:id="7" n="2"></note>   </p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
