<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[412]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1900.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My <persName xml:id="77">sister's</persName> birthday.  I gave her the "Two&#8211;version" Bible as a present.<note xml:id="6" n="1"></note>  A bad head&#8211;ache pressed on me all day: and I was worried (absurdly enough) by the delay in the formal announcement of my promotion.  In the afternoon my sister &amp; I walked to Barking, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="89" display="no">Laws</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="90">Garstang</persName>.  As we passed the Vicarage I noticed a board in the little meadow before the house, "Trespassers will be prosecuted".  <hi rend="bold underline">Laws says the Beckton men comment on it bitterly. "It used to be open house to us all when the little vicar was here: now it is 'Right about turn, &amp; out with you".</hi>  It is certainly an amazing piece of <hi rend="underline">gaucherie</hi> to put up such a notice in such a parish.</p>
         <p>We met <persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName>, &amp; he seemed eager to come to Westminster without delay.  <hi rend="italic">From the "Saturday Review" I received &#x00A3;6.9.6 for matter contributed during Sept</hi><hi rend="i superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to the Editor finally resigning from the Staff.<note xml:id="10" n="2"></note>  Very affectionate congratulations from <persName xml:id="82">Marsden</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="91">Swallow</persName> arrived.  <persName xml:id="92" display="no">Alfred</persName> had made no delay in proclaiming the news.      </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">[413]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>O Eternal &amp; Merciful God, I come to Thee in this time of need. Thou knowest all my weakness and my sin: &amp; yet Thou callest me to do this great thing. Enable what thou dost command. Have compassion on my weakness, &amp; forgive me all my sin. Grant to me the guidance &amp; comfort of Thy Holy Spirit that I may discern rightly Thy purpose, and answer obediently thereto. Show Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee. Look with pity on Thy children in this place, whose teacher, tho' unworthy, I have been. Suffer not my departure to unsettle their minds, but in Thy Providence send here a true shepherd of souls to pasture Thy flock. Especially bless, I pray Thee, the members of the Guild, the Church Officers, &amp; Choirmen, that the spirit of faction find no entrance among them. Overrule all the changes &amp; chances of this world for the benefit of souls, &amp; the setting forward among men of Thy Righteous Kingdom, and grant us all to hold firmly to Thy Truth whatever betide us. Bless us now, O Eternal Father, for Jesus Christ's sake, our most holy Redeemer.</p>
         <p>Amen.  
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
