<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The post brings me a handsomely bound copy of the "Roll of Service" of the University of Durham. It is a long roll of young men's names frequently marked by the asterisk which indicates that not service merely but service unto death was there rendered. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Sir Charles Stawer sends a civil letter, thanking me for my Sunday's sermon to the Darlington sectaries &amp; incidentally telling me that he is bringing out the "Westminster Gazette" as a morning paper on November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. No doubt there is a purpose possibly only half realized of "roping in" to the cause that dubious factor, the B. of D.!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me to Durham where I instituted Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> to an honorary canonry; Pryke to S. Aidan's, S. Shields; Brigstocke to Horden; &amp; the new Incumbent to S. Alban's, Heworth. We returned to Auckland for lunch. Warth, the new Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke's, Darlington, came to lunch.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Later, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Dunn, the School Inspector from Darlington, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Capes, his assistant, waited on me in the matter of the school at West Rainton, where the foolish parson (Rawlins) is prepared to close the school right away, rather than carry out comparatively reasonable alterations.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton and I motored to Darlington, where I dedicated a Mission Hall, which is to ^[illegible]^ be used for Divine Service until a church can be built and consecrated. This district of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Matthew, is cut out of the parish of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke, &amp; is destined to become an independent parish. There was a lay congregation. Canon Cosgrave<persName xml:id="5313"></persName>, the Rural Dean, and Drury, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Cuthbert's, came there Worth read the 2</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> lesson. I preached an old, dull sermon, which was hardly congruous with the occasion. But I had had no time to prepare a sermon, and had tried to adapt a discourse on the consecration of churches, which had been originally preached in Sunderland. After the service, we motored back to the Castle, giving Worth a lift as far as West Auckland. We arrived about 9.45 p.m. A letter from the Archbishop of York permits me to hope that the blind curate of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring will go out of the diocese.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>