<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to London by the early train. I accompanied her to the station in the motor. At 10.30 a.m. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; I motored to Durham, where Fearne was deposited with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi>Quirk. The Confirmation for the School in the Cathedral was a pleasing service. There were 51 boys confirmed, of whom 47 came from the school, &amp; 4 from the cathedral choir. Parents &amp; friends were present in considerable number. I was pleased with the behaviour of the school, with the demeanour of the candidates, &amp; with the hearty singing of the hymns. The brilliant sunshine shewed the marvellous beauty of the great church to full advantage. After the confirmation we walked to the Castle, where in the chapel I licensed two curates. Then we walked to the County Club, &amp; lunched pleasantly with J.G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, Major Vaux, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Dale were the other guests.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We motored to Rainton to see the Vicar about the schools, which, according to the newspapers are summarily to be closed by the education authority, but our labour was lost as the Vicar was absent from his parish. On our way home, we stopped in Durham in order that I might buy some Christmas presents.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We got back to Auckland about 5 p.m., the drive being enriched by the glorious sunsetting.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi rend="italic">December 12</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">My dear Jack,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I return the sermons, which can hardly justify alarm in the most sensitive of episcopal minds! You have expressed yourself very cautiously. I wonder what precise impression was made on your hearers' minds. The longer I live, the more I doubt whether it is worth while attacking </hi><hi rend="italic underline">directly</hi><hi rend="italic"> doctrines and systems which are plainly fading out of men's minds. The danger is that they will fade too fast, so fast that nothing has had time to replace them. Even in the ardour of a cascade against obscurantism we cannot wisely forget in these days the pressing peril of an unbelieving mentality, towards the formation of which many forces cooperate, and among them certainly the destructive efforts of "Liberals". But enough of this.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">You will be ordained to the Priesthood next Sunday. It is a great venture, never so hard to make with courage &amp; hope as in this time. Yet we must get behind depressions &amp; doubts to the ultimate verities which Religion expresses. After all, when one forgets the Church, &amp; reads the New Testament, one is not doubtful as to the direction in which one's allegiance must lie. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Lord I believe: help Thou mine unbelief</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">You have many good gifts, &amp; by God's Blessing will make good use of them in the Ministry.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I shall be ordaining in Durham Cathedral next Sunday, &amp; shall include you in my prayers.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">With all good wishes for the New Year.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I am,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Ever affectionately yrs,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p><p></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Rev. Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName>.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>December 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your letter reminded me that I owe </hi><hi rend="underline">you</hi><hi> a letter, but my private correspondence falls lamentably into neglect, &amp; you must ascribe my neglect to anything except intentional unkindness.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>"Anglicanism" has been published for a fortnight past, &amp; reviews of it have appeared in the "Challenge" and "Church Family Newspaper". I am surprised that the "Spectator" should not have received its copy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your reference to "action taken against Major" startles me, for I had heard nothing on the subject. The Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName> has, in my judgment, been unwisely complaisant to the "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" faction, but his position in a diocese which is crowded with "Anglo&#8211;Catholics" must be a very difficult one, &amp; really it </hi><hi rend="underline">is</hi><hi> extraordinarily difficult to know what course to pursue. The doctrinal question raised by the Cambridge Conference is the most formidable which can be conceived: for it is quite impossible to deny the gravity of the departure from orthodox belief which the Cambridge "Liberals" proclaim: nor is it equitable to refuse to any aggrieved believer his undoubted right to have such "heresy" restrained. All that a just Bishop, however disinclined to legal action, could do would be to decline the prosecutor's role for himself, and to make sure that the accused had all the opportunity for self&#8211;defence which the Law provides.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>You know my opinion about the Cambridge Conference. It was untimely, ill&#8211;judged, &amp; enormously provocative.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>When are you coming to see Auckland?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours a</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ffley</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>