<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I awoke early, and considered what I ought to say, if (as I intend) I address the assembly on the subject of Finance. I mean to postulate som "broad conditions of sound finance", e.g.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">1. Income must be known before expenditure is authorized.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">2. Expenditure must be approved by those who must find the money.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">3. The functions of the Central Board of Finance must be defined and authorized before it proceeds to frame its Budgets.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I mean to show how all these conditions are at present unsatisfied.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Assembly discussed finance with extraordinary ardour until 3.30 p.m. in the afternoon. I made my speech, and it was certainly listened to closely, and even applauded. But I was followed by a succession of orators who "tub&#8211;thumped" with amazing fervour. Among them the Bishop of S. Alban's and Lord</hi><hi rend="italic"> Parmoor<persName xml:id="1736"></persName> were conspicuous. The Bishops of Winchester &amp; Manchester spoke against me, &amp; finally, there was no division, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">a kind of compromise&#8211;formula, proposed by the Archbishop of York, being accepted both by Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> and by Major Birchall</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I was distressed, not so much by the unfairness with which I myself was treated, as by the sinister fact that this blatant rhetorick was evidently pleasing the audience. But the lay members of the Assembly are with few exceptions a canting type of men. I conjecture that many of them are licensed to preach in the churches! After Finance had been disposed of, I walked to S. Paul's Deanery to inquire after Paula<persName xml:id="2067"></persName>. The news was bad: indeed, the end was expected. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Spooner was there: both Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> and Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> were very brave, but evidently much tried.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I returned to the Club, and wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Then I went to the Old Universities' Club in Suffolk Street, and dined with Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> very pleasantly. He is really the best of men.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On the whole I am displeased with this day. It becomes increasingly difficult to see how I can fit in to this new system created by the Enabling Act. Every day my liberty of action seems to grow less, and my alienation from the general life of the church greater.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>