<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I frittered away the morning very uselessly, though, save for my curious absence of purpose, there was no reason why I should not have done some solid work. Why is one so utterly the bondslave of one's own words?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I begin to receive acknowledgements of the presentation copies of "Anglicanism", but everybody is very anxious to get the duty done before they could have had time to read the book! Every copy costs me with the postage the not inconsiderable sim of 7/&#8211;.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I walked for an hour and a half. He said that he believed the effect of their acquaintance with the clergy serving as chaplains during the war had been to lead the men generally to think meanly of the clergy. The hopelessness of the role they were appointed to play in the actual circumstances moved nothing but pity in the case of the best chaplains, and nothing more than contempt in the case of the lesser men. Certainly the situation must have been very difficult.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> W. Livesey sends me his book, "The Mining Crisis, its history and meaning to all workers". In view of my speech to the unemployed at Hartlepool next week, I thought it worth while to read it through: and I found it both interesting and informing, though very ill written. The short letter of acknowledgement to the Author is copied into this Journal. The libel action brought by Thomas, the Secretary of the Railwaymen's Union against the "Communist", has ended in a verdict for the plaintiff with &#x00A3;2000 damages. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Justice Darling, in giving judgment, allowed himself in some severe observations on these woeful agitators who find use for the "Communist". It appears to be established that there is a Bolshevick movement in this country subsidised from Russia, and that it has made considerable progress within the Trade Unions, where the extremely unsatisfactory organization makes it possible for tiny organized minorities to wield an exorbitant influence. This is the conclusion which M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Livesey arrives at. His plea is for a reform of the Trades Unions, and for a reasonable limitation of their functions. The political objective has compromised &amp; ruined the economic service.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>December 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi>, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Livesey,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am greatly obliged to you for your kindness in sending me your book, "The Mining Crisis", which I have read with attention, interest, and appreciation. I think you are serving the interest both of "Labour" and of the Nation by using the special knowledge you possess in order to set the actual facts and tendencies in our industrial life clearly before the public.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The present disintegration of political parties creates a situation eminently favourable to the formation of a new party pledged to advance the true interests of "Labour" in a genuinely national spirit.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Trade Unions having drifted into a false position in which, while ceasing to serve the cause of their members, they are a standing menace to the security of the social order. What you say on p.84 about the true objectives of Trade Union effort seems to me very sound.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I hope you will go forward in the handling of industrial questions.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. faithfully</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>W. Livesey Esq.</hi></p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>