<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Give me, O Lord, the spirit of pastorate, and the assurance of Thy commission, for in truth both have failed in me, and I move doubtfully as in the night. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee</hi><hi rend="italic">. Be with me this day when I speak words of commission to Thy servant in Darlington, and validate my action, for "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">apart from Thee I can do nothing</hi><hi rend="italic">". Come into my own heart, O Saviour, and let Thy Peace reign in my thoughts. Let me prove the truth of Thy word to S. Paul, when in great distress he prayed thrice to Thee against his "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">thorn in the flesh</hi><hi rend="italic">", and prayed in vain. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">My grace is sufficient for thee: for my power is made perfect in weakness</hi><hi rend="italic">." Fulfil to me this day Thy promise to Thy Church never to depart from Thy servants "even unto the end of the world", and grant me the comfort of Thy Presence all the days of my life. Amen</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 9.30 a.m., and motored to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Luke's, Darlington, where I instituted the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">S. F. Warth </hi><hi>to that vicarage. I preached, and celebrated the Holy Communion, at which at least 100 persons communicated. We lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi><hi>, the Vicar of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Cuthbert's, who gave me a good account of the Irish curate. Then we motored by way of Stockton to Hartlepool, where, owing to the badness of the roads, we arrived about 10 minutes after time. I preached to a congregation of Freemasons &amp; their women&#8211;folk, it being the 75</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi>Helen's Lodge. The collection was in aid of the Masonic Restoration for rebuilding the Galilee Chapel of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi>Hilda's Church. My text was </hi><hi rend="underline">Zechariah xiv.20.21</hi><hi>, &amp; my sermon was too elaborate for the congregation, &amp; too religious for the occasion! We motored back to Auckland after the service; Clayton dropped off at Eldon to preach in the mission church, and I reached the Castle at 6.10 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> could not get to the service either in Darlington, or in Hartlepool, a circumstance which troubled me, though it is true to argue that, inasmuch as his absence from Divine service was occasioned by his evident duty, no guilt attached to him on its account.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>