<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received from the Archbishop of Upsala<persName xml:id="2166"></persName>, the following letter:</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Lord Bishop,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>During my visitation in this parish some 30 miles north of Stockholm I have studied its renowned Kalendarium, a manuscript not later than 1198, used in this church during centuries, provided of course with our Saints, Erlth (?) Aatard (?), but at the same time such an eloquent witness of close communion with the Church in England at that epoch and especially with your diocese, that I must write you these lines. Looking through the months I find first Cuthbert then Beda – and other British Saints of old. Where do you think my thoughts went? To Durham Cathedral and to Auckland Castle – envying my daughter the privilege of being there in Auckland Castle during memorable and delightful days and thanking the Biskopinnen and yourself for all kindness bestowed upon her.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>With respectful and thankful sympathies to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Henson I am very sincerely yours,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Nathan S&#x00F6;derblom.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I am quite unable to decipher the name of the place from which the Archbishop writes.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>This dreadful gardener hangs on to the house, which in a few days will be needed for his successor. I went to see him, &amp; was received with extraordinary insolence. But I doubt whether as a citizen I can, or as a Christian I ought to, thrust him forth until he has another lodging. After an early lunch we all went together in the car as far as Durham. Leaving the rest there, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went on to Blaydon, where I dedicated war memorials and preached. It was a wearisome performance for the coughing was incessant and irrepressible. Picking up the party at the College, we returned to the Castle, arriving soon after 6 p.m. Then I wrote to the Moderator welcoming him to the Cathedral &#8211; on December 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>That goose&#8211;prelate, the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName>, will be more incensed than ever when he hears of my action: but he has already excommunicated me twice over!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>November 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Moderator,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I understand from the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> that you have consented to preach in Durham Cathedral on Sunday, the 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> of December; and I take leave to send you the assurance of my genuine satisfaction that you should visit my diocese for that purpose.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It is my intention to be present in the Cathedral on that day, and to celebrate the Holy Communion in the morning as well as attend the afternoon service, when you are to preach. May I say that, if you were yourself disposed to communicate, it would give me real pleasure to welcome you to the Lord's Table.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It needs not that I should assure you of the regard and affection with which I look on the Church of Scotland, how much I desire a frank fellowship </hi><hi rend="underline">in sacris</hi><hi> between that Church and the Church of England, and how rejoiced I shall be to receive the official Chief of the sister National Church in my Cathedral.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Moderator,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>most sincerely yours,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Feeling extremely dilapidated I retired early to bed with the honest intention of working through the rather heavy programme arranged for tomorrow.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName> sent me his Presidential Address to the Royal Historical Society on "</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Some mediæval conceptions of ancient History</hi><hi>". It makes very good reading, &amp; discloses an immense amount of erudition.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>There arrived from the bookseller in 5 large volumes, Lockhart's "Life of Scott", which to my disgrace I have never yet possessed or read. But as President of the Sir Walter Scott Association of Edinburgh, I must remove this shameful defect.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>