<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Frost,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In reply to your letter I must reiterate my decision not to license your brother in my diocese. Since, however, my predecessor – very wrongly as I must needs think – admitted him to Ordination, I will not refuse temporary permission for him to officiate in </hi><hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi><hi>any</hi><hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi><hi> parish – where the Incumbent may desire to give him employment.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I may point out that, since my refusal to license is based on his physical disability, it implies no other disadvantage than is involved in that circumstance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>If a blind man were presented to me for institution to a benefice, I should hold it necessary to make sure that the Churchwardens knew of the fact in good time to object to the appointment if they desired to do so: &amp;, certainly, if they </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> object, I should feel constrained to refuse institution.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I am assured that Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName> consented to ordain your brother with very great hesitation, and with a general understanding that you would look after him</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me, yours v. faithfully,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I left Park Lane in time to catch the 10 a.m. express at King's Cross, and travelled comfortably to Darlington, where William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car, &amp; motored me to the Castle. Among the letters awaiting me was another from the blind curate's brother, which I answered forthwith. I was interested to find that the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi>", not content with their brief notice of my address to the Diocesan Conference, which appeared in last Monday's issue, had two columns of it in the issue of Tuesday.</hi></p>
         <p><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Durham, and dined at the Deanery to meet H. H. Marie Louise<persName xml:id="5406"></persName>, who has been staying with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> for most of this week on an expedition in aid of the Y.M.C.A. I took M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Greenwell in to dinner. The company was not social exalted, but it was friendly, &amp; fluttered agreeably by the presence of a live Princess!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>