<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName><hi> the following letter: &#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>28 Queen Anne's Gate,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Westminster, 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> December 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Lord,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have now read your book on 'Anglicanism' through. If I may say so it is a most brilliant piece of literary work, and not least so the preface.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>You have brought out the difficulties of the existing situation, with its antinomies. What the future holds in store it is impossible to say. The marked phase is the indifference of the public, &amp; the way in which things are drifting. A Catholic movement may have great spiritual advantages, but in this country it is not likely to prove a movement of more than a sect in a nation, which, latently, is profoundly Protestant and pro&#8211;Reformation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wonder whether you have succeeded in making many people </hi><hi rend="underline">think</hi><hi>. I am not sure. The small body of laity who attend to these things is characterised by stupidity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. sincerely</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Haldane:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>Also from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Muir&#8211;Mackenzie</hi><hi> came the following:</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>27 Cumberland Terrace,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Regent's Park, Dec. 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 21</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Bishop,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>It was very good of you to have your …… sent to me, and I have been reading marking &amp; inwardly digesting them with great interest: indeed, as to the preface, I might say glee. I wish I had your glittering powers of expression, wherewith to relieve my mind of some indignation at things as well ecclesiastical as civil.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Ever aff</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ley</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Muir Mackenzie</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Arrowsmith took his departure after breakfast, leaving on my mind a very favourable impression. At 11.25 a.m. I left the Castle, and motored to South Shields arriving at the "Golden Lion Hotel" at 12.45. Here I was entertained at lunch by Colonel Hopkins, a benevolent and wealthy man who has guaranteed the considerable amounts required for the purchase of the new Seaman's Institute. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> was present, &amp; several of the local mayors. After lunch we all proceeded to the Institute, where I dedicated the chapel, &amp; gave an address: then Lord Durham opened the Institute with a key specially made from the metal of a German submarine, or rather, he failed to open it, as the key broke in the lock, &amp; the door had to be opened from inside. A meeting in the large room of the Institute was then held. I got away soon after 4 p.m. and motored back to the Castle, where I found the ordination candidates just arriving. At 7 p.m. there was Evensong in the chapel. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Glynne brought 10 choirboys from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Anne's to lead the singing: &amp; Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> gave a useful address. We conversed at dinner in the normal fashion, Knight holding that this was advisable as tending to make the men take a more human view of the Bishop!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A telegram arrived from <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> telling me that Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> operation was safely over, which relieved me of much anxiety</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I chose a text for the sermon which the Ordination Candidates must write a sermon upon tomorrow morning. It was the following:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>S. Luke VI. 26. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Woe unto you when all men shall speak well of you</hi><hi>!"</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Romans xii. 17. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Take thought for things honourable in the sight of all men</hi><hi>." The combination of these passages provides a subject in the handling of which there is great opportunity of self&#8211;disclosure!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I paid &#x00A3;3.15.0 for the two pigs obtained by Laws. A very plain and painful statement of the case of the Officers &amp; men of the Royal Irish Constabulary arrived. It is being sent to members of the Houses of Parliament, &amp; emanates from "the joint Representative Bodies of Officers &amp; men of the R.I.C." It is humiliating to read.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>