<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[19]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received a shock in the form of a reminder that &#8211; my statement of income for purposes of the Super&#8211;tax had not yet come in. I had thought Lee had sent it in years ago.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Macdonald and Ousey interviewed me about the mission at Bellasis. It appeared that an immediate increase of population was expected at the parochial centre, Bellingham, while the increase at the mission district was postponed. In these circumstances, we all agreed that the place of forming an independent district at Bellasis must stand over, &amp; the Vicar of Bellingham must continue to work the whole area with the assistance of a curate. The site for the mission church at Bellasis should, however, be purchased &amp; the building of the Mission Hall proceeded with.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Major M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi>Gill, the local Baptist minister, came to see me about a conference of Baptist ministers from Durham &amp; Northumberland next May. I said I would have them at the Castle on May 15</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, and would address them at 2.30 p.m. They may have tea, see the castle, and wind up with a short service in the Chapel.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In the course of the afternoon, I had an interview with a young Irish clergyman named Sinnamon, who desires to be admitted to this diocese. Then Lasbrey, from S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Gabriel's, Sunderland, brought a young man, the son of a dissenting minister, to be confirmed prior to his entering Knutsford. I confirmed him in the chapel in the presence of Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, Lasbrey, &amp; Sinnamon. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Lasbrey has accepted appointment as a C.M.S.<orgName xml:id="124"></orgName> missionary to Africa, &amp; will abandon the work he is carrying on with such vigour &amp; apparent success in Sunderland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote, &amp; despatched by the evening post, letters to my brother, the Bishop of Down, Drury, Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>, Duck, and Morton. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The latter, a Freemason in Sunderland, had </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">written to invite me to attend the initiation of the Mayor of Sunderland, who had been so impressed by the Masonic service in Sunderland on October 16</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, that he had decided to become a Freemason.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>