<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">New Year's Eve. 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The last day of the year was fine and calm after a tempestuous night. I spent the morning in letter&#8211;writing and sermon preparation. Cecil Ferens<persName xml:id="4218"></persName> came from Durham to lunch &amp; have some talk. We walked in the Park together, and, as we returned, we observed some large boughs broken from one of the trees. I sent out Laws &amp; Smith to bring in the wood at once, as the aborigines would probably steal it before Monday! The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>C. I. Lockyer came to see me: &amp;, after some conversation, I agreed to let him go as curate to Leadgate, promising to license him after a period of 3 months if all went well. I sent copies of "Anglicanism" to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName>, Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>, Macdonald, Murlow, Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>, &amp; Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>: and I finished reading through "Vocations".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The year has been strenuous, fatiguing, and filled with perplexity.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Its last weeks have been shadowed by private anxiety caused by Marion's<persName xml:id="77"></persName> health. Happily the worst phase seems to have been passed</hi><hi rend="italic">. I do not feel that any problems have been solved. Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> arrival in the diocese has evidently justified itself. Bishop Auckland will shortly be vacant, &amp; will be difficult to fill. Of the sermons preached this year, four were of more than usual interest viz: those preached in the Abbey (Jan</hi><hi rend="i sup u">y</hi> <hi rend="italic">30</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">); in Hull (March 31</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic">) in Durham Cathedral (May 29</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">) and in Birmingham (October 11</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">). The Conference of Liberal Churchmen at Cambridge in August has caused much resentment, and may lead to some attempts to evict unorthodox clergymen. I did my best, though vainly, to prevent the Conference, &amp; then to moderate the public mind by my sermon at the Church Congress. The Good Friday Procession in Sunderland, and my address on the Labour Question in Hartlepool on May 1</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> attracted some notice. On March 10</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> I addressed the House of Lords on the unpleasant subject of Divorce. My address to the Diocesan Conference on October 22</hi><hi rend="i sup u">nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> was largely reported in the Yorkshire Post: In the course of the year I became much attached to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>; and he justified my friendship by very excellent service. The most menacing problem is that presented by the fewness of Ordination candidates.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>