<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I left the castle at 7.45 a.m., and caught the early express to King's Cross. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Meade Falkner</hi><persName xml:id="3553"></persName><hi> was on the train, &amp; insisted </hi><hi rend="italic">on my lunching with him. We had much pleasant conversation. On arriving at King's Cross I drove to 21 Park Lane, &amp; left my bags. As I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I was hailed by one of my old boys, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Duck</hi><hi rend="italic">, who, after going through the Retreat from Mons &amp; the Gallipoli campaign unscathed, is now a messenger of some department, a married man, and the father of two daughters. While I was talking with him, I was laid hold of by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Willie Murray</hi><persName xml:id="227"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who walked with me to the Club. Then I went to the hair dresser, &amp; was shampooed. Returning to the Club, I had tea, &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>. The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi><hi rend="italic"> came in, and had some talk with me. He has received letters from the Bishop of Zanzibar<persName xml:id="3469"></persName> denouncing the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>, and demanding that his name shall be removed from the signatories of the Lambeth Appeal tota. It appears that the Bishop had communicated directly to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> so that 'the fact will be in the fire' immediately. We talked of the extraordinary difficulty of ecclesiastical finance. His Grace said that he was himself embarrassed for the </hi><hi rend="bold underline">unknown private benefactor who had contributed as much as &#x00A3;3000 per annum towards his expenses, was no longer available</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">He says that there will be a difficult discussion of Reservation at the Bishop's Meeting, as the Bishops in the metropolitan areas are indignant at the Bishop of London's toleration of the practice. I asked him whether he had appointed the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Alban's to preside over the official Press Bureau in order to assure us that there would be no tincture of partisanship in its working. He seemed anxious to disclaim responsibility for the appointment. Meade Falkner entertained me in the club at dinner, and afterwards walked with me to Park Lane. We had much pleasant talk, and parted with many declarations of friendship.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>