<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished the sermon, and wrote a short "Message" for the New Year as requested by the Newcastle Chronicle</hi><hi>. The post brought a very cheerful letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName><hi>, who really seems to be making progress to recovery. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi> reported that the car was fit for use, and, after lunch, motored us to Lumley, where we had accepted an invitation to stay for a couple of days. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord<persName xml:id="3465"></persName> &amp; Lady Scarbrough</hi><persName xml:id="3466"></persName><hi> were alone, as "the young people" had gone out to dinner at a comparatively remote house.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lord S. told me that he meditated selling the 4 Tudor busts if he could secure a purchaser. They had been valued at &#x00A3;10,000 apiece. They were thought to be probably the work of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Terrigiano</hi><hi>. I expressed my consternation at the prospect of these precious historical memorials leaving the county. But "needs much when the devil drives". Lord S. shewed me the statement of receipts and payments for his Yorkshire property. The net value of a gross rental of about &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">11,000</hi><hi> was no more than &#x00A3;1600. How can one decently ask for subscriptions from men whose incomes have been almost annihilated by public charges? And how can we get on without the subscriptions?</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>