<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Sir Herbert &amp; Lady Cohen accompanied me to Darlington in the motor, and travelled with me to King's Cross. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> finally decided not to risk the journey. Meade Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName> was in the train, and had some talk with me. I think he is really pleased at being made honorary librarian of the Chapter Library. On arriving at King's Cross I drove to 21 Park Lane, and then went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Here I found a letter from Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> telling me that Paula<persName xml:id="2067"></persName> was seriously ill. I went to the barber, &amp; had my hair trimmed &amp;c, &amp; then walked to Westminster. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The National Assembly was engaged upon the Parochial Councils (Powers) Bill. I made a short speech with the object of provoking a discussion, and was so far successful that the debate went on all the afternoon, &amp; stood over when the House rose</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>I had tea in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where old Sir Courtenay Ilbert was very friendly and conversational. It is difficult to believe that he is more than 80 years old.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I dined in the Prince's Restaurant at the Anglo&#8211;Italian dinner in honour of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Ronald Graham</hi><hi>, the new British ambassador to Rome. Sir Rennell Rodd presided over a numerous company. I sate between Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>, my hostess, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Walter Runciman. </hi><hi rend="underline">The Duke of Sutherland made a surprisingly good speech, and "brought the house down" by exhibiting Garibaldi's slipper which the Liberator gave to his grandfather in 1864</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Ronald Graham</hi><hi> spoke with much candour and good sense. The Italian ambassador spoke in Italian, &amp; consequently his eloquence was lost one me. After the dinner there was the usual delay &amp; confusion in getting away, which is the shadow of all London functions'. I got back to Park Lane about 11 p.m., and proceeded to write up this journal: and to send an account of my proceedings to Ella. The weather continues to be chilly and damp. If Miss Mundella can survive her experience in getting home, she must have larger reserves of strength than she is generally credited with.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>