<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The post brings me a woeful entreaty from S. that I will rescind my refusal to sanction his officiating in the diocese. Is there no place of repentance for him? Perforce I coldly and shortly reject his plea. But it sets me thinking dismally. What ought to be done in such cases as his? Is it quite satisfactory that indebtedness even when aggravated by lying and fraudulency should have the effect of totally ruining the delinquent? Because, a refusal of permission to officiate in one diocese means practically expulsion from the work of the ministry. Is not the sentence excessive? For, it admits of no revision, or mitigation. The offender may be sincerely penitent: he may reform his behaviour: he may entreat permission to resume his ministry. Nothing of all this can avail anything at all. Yet, on the other hand, how impossible it is to permit the continuance in active ministry of a clergyman who has fallen notably &amp; repeatedly below the normal standards of behaviour. The Bishop must give primary place to the needs of the people. It is intolerable that a discredited and dishonest clergyman should be authorized to minister publicly in the churches. The risk of a great scandal arising from the desperate distresses of the ejected clergyman must be run!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName><hi> came to see me about young </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer</hi><hi>. I declined to allow his ordination at Advent on any terms, but gave K. a free hand to make the manner of his taking the examination as easy as possible provided that before being Ordained in Advent 1922, he </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> pass the whole of it.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rudgard</hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Timms</hi><hi>, the churchwardens of Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear, lunched here, and afterwards discussed with me the question of the Vicarage House, which is woefully dilapidated. Ought it to be repaired? Or should it be condemned, &amp; replaced by another? In either case, where is the new person to live while the work proceeds?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">T.H.A. Morris</hi><hi>, Vicar of S. Oswald's, Durham, came to see me, and to ask my counsel on certain matters. Should he continue to shorten Mattins by beginning with the Lord's Prayer? Should he use the Wafer instead of Bread at the Holy Communion? Should he discontinue the Sacring Bell? Should he give up the Cope? A strong section of the people object to all these things. He told me what greatly surprized me, that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jones</hi><hi> is becoming a difficulty on account of his "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" views!!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>December 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Thank you for letting me see your letter to Lord Cave. I think, if there be any fragment of sincerity in the reiterated pledges under which the Enabling Act slipped through Parliament, it is quite essential that the Ecclesiastical Committee should really examine the Bills sent on from the National Assembly, and that Parliament itself should really consider them before it resolves to send them forward for the Royal Assent.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am sorry that you do not share my estimate of the National Assembly, because I have a real respect for your judgment, and a real desire to have you with me in any course I take.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>But I feel very sure that the set of the tide (of which the National Assembly is the most conspicuous indication) is against everything in religious and ecclesiastical life which I think true, wise, and free.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>But I grow old: and am what is now called a "Back Number".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours aff</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tely</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lord Charnwood.</hi></p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>