<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, and took part in the funerals of two incumbents, lately deceased, viz. Thomas<persName xml:id="3958"></persName> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>Giles', and Tolliday<persName xml:id="2928"></persName> of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi><hi>Cuthbert's. Both leave widows and children with little or no provision. I should suppose that the interment of two of the city incumbents of Durham on the same day must be without precedent. We lunched and had tea in my rooms at the Castle.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I prepared an address for the Confirmation candidates in Darlington. It is surprising how difficult I find it is to vary the addresses. There are always certain inevitable things which have to be said to the candidates, and the range of choice in one's exhortations is closely limited.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>We motored to Darlington, and arrived at Holy Trinity Church in good time. I confirmed about 80 candidates. After the service while we were unrobing in the vestry, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Canon Cosgrave<persName xml:id="5313"></persName> introduced to me an oddly&#8211;garbed clergyman as M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Milner, the Vicar of Elton. I held out my hand, but he drew himself up, and made a mighty bow, saying something about the age of confirmation candidates, which sounded insolent. I remembered that he was the preposterous parson who used to address mad letters to me when I was Dean, and who wrote to me recently advocating an earlier age for confirmation. So, accounting him a half&#8211;crazy crank, I kept silence, and ignored his insolence. His parish contains about 130 parishioners, and the patronage is vested in his relations. He was educated at Christ's College, Cambridge, and was ordained in 1883, when he was mathematical master at S. John's College, Hurstpierpoint. I understand that his church is the only one in which incense is burned within the diocese</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>On arriving home, Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> informed me that the Reverend C. S. Hardy, curate of Coundon, whom I ordained to the priesthood last Advent, had died suddenly.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Parliament has been summoned for next Wednesday. I should greatly like to be present at what must be a great historic occasion, but I can spare neither the time, nor the money, for superfluous visits to London.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>