<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Thirty three years ago, on Advent Sunday, I was publicly instituted to the cure of 12000 souls in Barking Parish Church. Today I have to institute M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName> to the Rectory of Stanhope. The way of clerical duty seemed to me obscure &amp; difficult in 1888: it appears almost intolerably so in 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, Shebbeare &amp; his wife, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and I motored to Stanhope, and found on arrival that we had time enough to visit the Rectory. It is a large, but also a convenient and attractive house. The gardens are correspondingly extensive. In the Hall there are paintings of several former Rectors, including Bishops Butler and Phillpotts. (Is it possible to conceive two men more sharply differentiated?) The service of Institution was preceded by shortened Mattins, and followed by the Holy Communion. I preached, instituted, and celebrated:&#8211; There were 118 communicants. We left the new Rector &amp; his wife in their Rectory, and returned to Auckland in time for lunch.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Carruthers</hi><persName xml:id="1261"></persName><hi>, Clayton, and I motored into Durham, and there attended Evensong in the Cathedral. After service &#8211; we had tea with Bishop<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> and M</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Quirk: &amp; then returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Carruthers</hi><hi> spoke about Newstead Abbey, on which lay the </hi><hi rend="italic">curse which has been supposed to attach to the families which enjoyed the possessions of the dissolved monasteries. Sir Arthur Markham's death a few months after he had become tenant of Newstead, had resuscitated belief in the legendary curse. The Webbs, who had owned the building since about 1830, had done some pious works of restoration &amp;c. They had received a letter from the Pope stating that, in recognition of their piety, he would authorize a de&#8211;cursing service in the Abbey. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cardinal Gasquet</hi><hi rend="italic">, a friend of the family, had actually conducted this service, which </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Herbert Chermside</hi><hi rend="italic"> (who married a </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss Webb</hi><hi rend="italic">.) had attended. The whole business had been carefully kept secret: but the said Sir Herbert had told M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> C. all about it. This is a sufficiently startling evidence of the superstition which yet clouds the understanding of our people.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>