<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I walked to the Club immediately after breakfast, &amp; read the papers. Also I wrote to Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; sent him his "reply–paid" telegram. The Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> David's was in the Club, &amp; had some talk with me. I walked to Westminster, made a fruitless call on Lee, called on Charles, &amp; visited both the Abbey &amp; S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Margaret's. Then I went back to the Club, where I fell in with Curgon, who was most friendly. He said that he was strongly opposed to the Prince's visit to India at this time, and that the Viceroy &amp; his Council had pressed for it. I lunched with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, and afterwards we walked together to Lambeth. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">The meeting of bishops</hi><hi> began at 2.30 p.m. I remained until 4 p.m. when I came away </hi><hi rend="bold underline">in order to attend the debate on India in the House of Lords. I sat for 3 hours in the House</hi><hi>, only going out for a cup of tea. Lord Sydenham introduced the subject in a long and rather vehement speech. He was followed by Curzon, who tried, but vainly, to stifle the discussion as inopportune &amp; possibly mischievous in view of the Prince's journey. But he didn't succeed in persuading the House, which was evidently restive under his rather superb direction. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Lords Salisbury and Midleton betrayed a distinctly personal animus</hi><hi>. Lord [sic] made a raucous &amp; hostile speech which brought up Chelmsford<persName xml:id="65"></persName>, whose speech made a distinctly favourable impression. Selbourne<persName xml:id="311"></persName>, Meston<persName xml:id="5458"></persName>, &amp; Sumner<persName xml:id="5393"></persName> all made effective speeches. I came away before the debate closed. I dined at the House of Commons with Murray. Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> was also of the party. At the next table was </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Alfred Mond</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, a repulsive–looking Israelite, and, with him, two young Jews, very obvious &amp; very odious</hi><hi>. After dinner Craik insisted on introducing me to the Attorney General (</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Gordon Hewart</hi><hi>) and the Lord Advocate for Scotland. I went into the House of Commons, &amp; listened to the debate on the Government's Unemployment proposals. A violent &amp; curiously irrelevant speech, extremely ignorant &amp; bitter, was made by Walsh, who is reckoned to be one of the best of the Labour members. Murray walked with me to Park Lane, where I arrived a few minutes before 11 p.m.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>