<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921. S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Hilda's Day.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I walked to the parish church with the Vicar, and there celebrated the Holy Communion, using a special collect for S. Hilda's day, which (I was assured) had been written by Bishop Lightfoot<persName xml:id="1817"></persName>, and sanctioned by his successors. There were more than 40 communicants, mostly of S. Hilda's sex.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>As we walked to the Church through some rather squalid streets, the Vicar told me that two acres thus covered with poor houses still belonged to the benefice, being all that remained of the land originally granted by S. Hilda herself. It is let on a 999 years' lease, and brings in a ground rent of &#x00A3;115 per annum. The memorial cross in the churchyard is modelled on the old Celtic crosses of Ruthwell and Bewcastle, and looks very reverent and stately.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At 11 a.m. the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> W.P. Mayor, Vicar of S. Michael's, South Westoe, came to see me in order to consult me about his great parish, 24000 people. Should it be divided? He was opposed to that course, and, I think, for good reasons: but he has only one illiterate curate to assist him, &amp; cannot succeed in getting another! This shortage of men threatens a complete collapse of the parochial machinery.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>At 12.30 p.m. I dedicated the War Memorial in S. Hilda's churchyard. The function was preceded by a short service in the church, at which I preached. There was a considerable concourse of people. Du&#x00E8;ss (??) of the former clergy of the parish had come together for the occasion. Archdeacon Blackett&#8211;Ord, and Canons Robeson &amp; Boot were among the number.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch Hudson Baker<persName xml:id="3575"></persName> and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I called on old M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Williams, who is in process of resigning the incumbency of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Mary's, Tyne dock</hi><hi>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Then William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Sunderland, where I had an early dinner with Canon Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>, and discussed with him the insoluble problem of the woeful man, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Dowson</hi><hi>. Then we went to S. Paul's, Hendon, where I dedicated a War&#8211;Memorial in the parish church. The Mayor of Sunderland walked beside me in the procession. After service we – for Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had rejoined me – motored back to Bishop Auckland, arriving at the Castle about 10 p.m. This fatiguing and, I must needs think, futile effort forms what men call a Bishop's work!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>