<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, Sunday, October 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Mayor accompanied me to Christ Church, &amp; communicated at the early celebration. I myself celebrated, &amp; there were 52 communicants. At 10.30 a.m. I preached in S. John's Wesleyan Church, of which the Mayor is a member. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> carried the staff, &amp; I wore my red robes. The Prayer&#8211;book service was read. There was a large &amp; attentive congregation and a service which was reverent as well as congregational. At 3 p.m. I preached to an immense congregation in Christ Church, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">mostly composed of Freemasons</hi><hi rend="italic">. Lord Ravensworth<persName xml:id="3719"></persName> read the lessons excellently. The Collection amounted to more than pounsign65. After the service I was photographed in a group of Masons. Then I had tea in a neighbouring house, and met the chaplains of the Seamen's Mission. At 6.30 p.m. I preached again in Christ Church to a very large congregation. The collection was for the Seamen's Mission. We had supper with our hosts, &amp; then motored back to Auckland, stopping in Durham on the way to pick up M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Berry who had been visiting Olive. We arrived back in the Castle about 10.45 p.m. I was more than commonly tired.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>