<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I must keep note of those to whom copies of "Anglicanism" have been presented. Besides those sent through the publishers, I have sent to 1. Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> 2. Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName> 3. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> 4. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Clymont 5. W. P. Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>. 6. Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> 7. Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. 8. Lord Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3465"></persName>. 9. Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName>. 10. Holt. 11. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. 12. Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName>. 13. Arthur Rawle<persName xml:id="813"></persName>. 14. Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>. 15. L</hi><hi rend="superscript">d</hi> <hi>Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName>. 16. Ernest. 17. Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p><hi>I motored into Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Trustees of the Barrington Funds. Then, picking up Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and Clayton, I returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">After lunch Ernest accompanied me to Raby Castle, where I baptized in the chapel, the first&#8211;born child of the Barnards<persName xml:id="5197"></persName>, &#8211; Rosemary Mira</hi><hi>. The chapel was filled with relations and dependents. After tea we returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The newspapers report another religious revival in Scotland</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is said to be similar in character to the Welsh Revival of some years ago but even more astonishing in effect. The form is takes is, of course, severely Puritanic. There is a vehement attack on drink, tobacco, cinemas &amp;c. I wonder whether the movement will spread into England. It would create a difficult situation for "thou who sit in Moses' seat", and have no ardent desire to be unseated. It is stated that certain eminent students of psychology have gone to Scotland to study at first hand the phenomena of a religious movement. This is a sign of the times which must not be ignored or misunderstood. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The assumption is that Religion also can be tamed by Science, analyzed, explained, and explained away. We move far, &amp; move quickly, from the old reverent mystery in which God dealt with the human spirit</hi><hi rend="italic">. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The wind bloweth where it listeth, &amp; then hearest the sound thereof, but caust not tell whence it cometh, &amp; whither it goeth. So is everyone that is born of the Spirit</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Registrar, Lazenby, send me a cheque for &#x00A3;20. to be bestowed on the poor clergy of the diocese. It is generous of him, but I doubt the wisdom of creating expectations by multiplying doles.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>