<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">How far will the Presbyterian Moderator's preaching in Durham cathedral help forward, or throw back, the cause of genuine Christian fellowship? That the general conscience of the community approves such proceedings is, I think, certain. The attendance of the Mayor &amp; Corporation of Durham in the cathedral is an indication of this. But is the general conscience to be trusted in a matter of this kind? Is it really more than a reflection of the irreligious fashion of the age, which finds no reality in spiritual things, and is contemptuous of religious differences because in fact it does not understand or accept the presuppositions of Religious agreement? But I think the deeper religious conscience is also accordant with the attempt to break with the old tradition of ecclesiastical exclusiveness. There is no longer any power of genuine conviction behind the dividing dogmata, and the repugnance against illegality or ill&#8211;discipline only lingers in a few fastidious minds. Such opposition as exists derives exclusively from the small but increasing faction of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks", who have acquired an artificial conscience. The "shop&#8211;boy Ritualist" waxes very indignant over this playing with 'schism": but youth is always intolerant, and ignorance is always suspicious. In the rank and file of the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" movement youth and ignorance prevail. But, it may fairly be asked, what useful result will come from a demonstration of religious fraternity which leaves the situation unaltered, save for the new exasperation stirred in some minds? Are you any nearer a solution of the obstinate problems which underlie the divisions of the churches? I suppose the answer must be that those problems are insoluble, but that, just in proportion as they are ignored, they are found to be irrelevant. Schism and heresy are dreadful evils in theory, but in the practice of real life, what do they matter? What do they mean? Are they more than nettles, which only need to be firmly grasped in order to be made incapable of stinging. Only when they are treated with considerate caution are they able to sting? So I incline to think that the Moderator's visit may have an indirect but not negligible influence in discrediting the divisive tradition by which we are enchained.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">We motored into Durham, and attended service in the Cathedral. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> preached, and I noted with pleasure the strength of his voice and the energy of his demeanour, which gave satisfactory authentication to his own confident assertion that he had recovered completely from his illness. I celebrated the Holy Communion, and among the communicants was the Moderator of the Church of Scotland (</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Clymont</hi><hi rend="italic">). We lunched at the Deanery, where we met two Presbyterian ministers from Durham &amp; Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, who had been invited to meet the distinguished visitor. At 3.30 p.m. we all attended Evensong in the Cathedral. The congregation was much smaller than I expected, but there was no protest, as in the case of D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi> <hi rend="italic">Jowett, and the Moderator's sermon was listened to with attention. He has a pleasant voice, and a good delivery. He prefaced his sermon by a few general observations on Reunion. His text was 2. Timothy 1.7 "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">For God gave us not a spirit of fearfulness: but of power and love and discipline.</hi><hi rend="italic">" It was not a great sermon, but it was well&#8211;phrased, and held the congregation. The Mayor &amp; Corporation appeared to be much interested. I went to the Altar, &amp; pronounced the Benediction. Then I had tea with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cruickshanks</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName><hi rend="italic">. I called on the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed diocesan matters with him. Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I dined with the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Meade Falkners</hi><persName xml:id="3553"></persName><hi rend="italic">. He is the most fascinating and evasive of mortals. He professes an uncriticising belief of all that the Church prescribes, &amp;, though he is nominally an Anglican, his whole feeling and preference are Roman. He is about to go to Rome in order to resume his work in the Vatican Library, where he is evidently welcomed. We rejoined the car at the College Gate at 9.45 p.m. and had arrived at the Castle by 10.15 p.m. I sate with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and had some conversation with him about books and politics. He is, I think, becoming interested in the historical novels I have given him; &amp;, I hope, they are leading him towards a serious interest in history. Why should I not concern myself with shaping one good citizen?</hi></p></body></text></TEI>