<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> went off after breakfast. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi><persName xml:id="344"></persName><hi rend="italic"> writes to remind me that D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Johnson held with me on the subject of the prayers for Divine Mercy in the Litany. I looked out the reference in Boswell. The conversation took place at Oxford on June 11</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1784. It is a question of feeling not of reason. There is, perhaps, no Christian type so far removed from the right Christian temper as the Plymouth Brother, who finds himself unable to use the Lord's Prayer because it includes a petition for forgiveness.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName><hi rend="italic"> and I left the Castle and motored to Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the C.I.B. Committee, &amp; incidentally caught a slight chill, which handicapped me subsequently. After having tea with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Cruickshank</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName> <hi rend="italic">&#8211; we motored to Sunderland, and put up in the very hospitable house of the Mayor (</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Raine</hi><persName xml:id="5371"></persName><hi rend="italic">). There came to dinner half a dozen of the leading citizens, among whom I was glad to see M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dease, who has interested himself considerably in the Blind, &amp; was said to be disposed to misunderstand the case of the blind curate, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Frost</hi><hi rend="italic">. I had some talk with him on the subject, and did, I think, succeed in shewing him that the truth was far other than had been represented to him.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>