<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi>Stevens,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>On Christmas morning I received many messages of goodwill from friends absent and present, but no message was more welcome, or moved me more deeply, than that which you and your friends, now unemployed in West Hartlepool, have sent me.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I shall be greatly obliged if you will convey to all who signed your letter the assurance of my sincere thanks for their good wishes, and especially for their goodness in accepting me as a "friend and brother" in this time of distress.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have watched with sympathy &amp; something very like pride, the brave and self&#8211;respecting behaviour of the great numbers of men in my Diocese who, through no fault of their own, have been deprived of work for many months, and brought into circumstances of much hardship.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Of all British industries perhaps the Ship&#8211;building industry has been the hardest hit by the adverse conditions created by the Great War: for it depends more directly than any others on the general prosperity of the World, and must needs be stricken by the desperate state of the World's exchanges, by the continuance of War in many countries, &amp; by the crushing poverty of the European communities which were the principal buyers of British manufactures.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Because Unemployment is so largely the consequence of untoward political conditions, I believe its relief will follow from an improvement in the political situation.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In all countries thoughtful men and women are coming to see that the World cannot live on Hatred. "Burying the hatchet" is not only right in morals, but also prudent in politics. Every step towards "Peace and Goodwill" between nations &amp; classes will hasten the return of prosperity, for it will bring back confidence, which is the life&#8211;blood of industry.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>If the long quarrel with Ireland can at last be ended, and if the Conference at Washington can succeed in limiting that rivalry in armaments which is the seed of War, </hi><hi rend="bold">[100] </hi><hi>[symbol] I think the foundations of a prosperity, more stable because more accordant with the general conscience, will have been laid.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Statesmen of the World are feeling after a new basis of international relations. Men of goodwill in all nations are feeling after a new basis for economic life. We have had our fill of hatreds, and the world is in ruins. Let us rebuild it in the Name of the Lord by venturing something for Fellowship and Fraternity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Food is getting cheaper. That is something to the good. There is a new hopefulness in the air which will be a tonic to industry. We have some difficult months in front of us, but if we can "stick it" with patience and courage, I believe that the New Year will not have run its course before a great change for the better will have come about.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Well, my dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi>Stevens, I must end my letter by cordially reciprocating the good wishes of yours.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>That the Blessing of Almighty God may be with you all, and make you able to carry yourselves as brave men through whatever trials are yet to be borne; that He will bring again Happiness to your Homes, and give you that steady employment which you desire, and which, I think, you deserve, is the constant prayer of</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your faithful Friend &amp; Bishop</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I sent the above to Macdonald in order that he might make it public in the Press, if he thought well, and might in any case send it on to its destination. It is difficult to know how far to treat seriously effusions from "Labour" men. The secretary, the mendicant, and the agitator severally contribute a distinctive stream of cant into the public deliverances of "Labour", and one may too easily serve some squalid personal interest, when we does but design a public service. The circumstance that I am a Bishop adds substantially to the risk of imposture!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>