<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On arriving at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I found a copy of my new book, "Anglicanism", with a note from Macmillan. It is priced monstrously at 8/6. Before the war it would have been 5/&#8211;, possibly no more than 3/6. The effect will certainly be that it will not sell.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The proceedings at the "National Assembly" were both dull and exciting – an unusual combination. The one belonged to the subject, the other to the members. All the morning we discussed the new Lectionary &amp; all the afternoon we wrangled over Finance. Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> proposed the abandonment of the "test&#8211;school" at Knutsford. That egregious jackass, Major Birchall, moved an amendment. He was supported by Canon Hicks, who has had the impudence to issue an appeal on his own behalf for the continuance of Knutsford. He told us that no less than &#x00A3;8,500 had been already received, and this statement was actually cheered. I gave in my name to speak, but the session ended before my turn had come. Before the House rose, the Archbishop himself addressed the members, urging speakers to address themselves to the "constructive" object of showing a better method than that of the Board of Finance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I dined with Sir John<persName xml:id="2244"></persName> and Lady Struthers. Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> of Worcester was there, Lord<persName xml:id="1394"></persName> &amp; Lady Ernle, the Belgian military attach&#x00E9;, and his wife, Lady S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Helier, and another lady. Prothero<persName xml:id="319"></persName> talked very interestingly about Kitchener, who, he said, was very unhelpful at Cabinet meetings, where he was silent, or refused to make suggestions. Keynes must be read with the grain of salt which attaches to a man who has been turned out: but his book was brilliant and in the main true. Ernest and I walked together as far as Hyde Park Corner. He thinks that the Archbishop of Canterbury looks uncommonly ill, and that he may be seriously thinking of resignation. I cannot believe that his Grace will ever willingly leave the centre.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>