<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The "Life and Liberty Movement" appears to aspire to the government of the Church of England. This morning's post brings a leaflet printed on green paper containing "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">A Litany for use during the Irish Conference</hi><hi rend="italic">". Its authorship is unstated. Hitherto it has been supposed to be the duty of the Bishop to issue instructions for prayers in the Churches, and to authorize forms. Now the episcopal function is being assumed by societies of enthusiasts, who seem to aim at playing in the Church of England the part of the Clubs to the Convention in the French Revolution. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Quo tendimus</hi><hi rend="italic">?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The clergyman's career seems to most people a poor thing: and the clergyman himself a poor creature. It is not a life which anyone with red blood in his veins would touch</hi><hi rend="italic">" – thus did my guest express herself at breakfast before taking her departure. I felt at the moment a sharp movement of repugnance, but on reflection I could not but admit the large element of truth which her words contained. The study of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Examining Chaplains' Report</hi><hi rend="italic"> did not tend to re&#8211;assure me. I have to reject 3 of the candidates, the work being trivial in extent, and worthless in quality. Sunday School teachers might fairly be expected to do better. If we can get no better stuff than has hitherto presented itself, the clergy of England will again be, though for another reason, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">stupor mundi</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Sunderland, stopping on the way at the Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring Rectory inn order to arrange with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> about the Ordination candidates. We dined with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sykes</hi><persName xml:id="3470"></persName><hi>, with whom was the missionary, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mawson</hi><hi> from Shantung who was the "deputation" from S.P.G.<orgName xml:id="23"></orgName> There was a considerable gathering in the Victoria Hall when at 7.30 p.m. I took the chair for the annual meeting of that society. I spoke myself for about 10 or 12 minutes, &amp; then introduced the Bishop of Edinburgh who prosed drearily for 40 minutes. Then came Mawson for 35 minutes, &amp; he interested us all. I gave the Benediction, &amp; the meeting broke up at 9.25 p.m. We motored back to Auckland, where we arrived about 10.45 p.m. There was sufficiently dense mist to make William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> task difficult: but he is an excellent driver, careful and courageous.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>