<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[24]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921. All Souls Day.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A red day&#8211;break followed by a wet day. The excellent Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> made a record by over&#8211;sleeping, &amp; calling me late. However, I got up in sufficient time, though somewhat hustled. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove me to Darlington where I caught the 9 a.m. train in which was a through&#8211;carriage to Oxford. So I travelled without change or companion, and arrived in the Warden's lodgings at All Souls about 3 p.m. There was a numerous party of fellows and quondams for the Gaudy. My mind travelled back no less than 37 years, when first I became a Fellow. Of those who welcomed me then so kindly only Cholmondeley<persName xml:id="3708"></persName>, Holland, Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName>, Reichel<persName xml:id="413"></persName>, Fletcher, Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName>, Johnson &amp; Harding, were present in a company of about 40 persons. All the rest were either dead or unavoidably absent, mostly the first. In Hall I sat between Oman and Ker: and in Common Room I sat between Fletcher &amp; the fire. I noticed with some interest, and, perhaps, with something not far removed from concern, that the simplicity which the War compelled, and which it was thought would survive the War, had practically disappeared. We drank champagne both in Hall &amp; (if we wished) in C.R. also, and the </hi><hi rend="underline">menu</hi><hi> was as long as I remember in the old time.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>November 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bickmore,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>No incumbent has any legal power to give notice of terminating an assistant curacy without the Bishop's consent: and, in view of the great importance of the principle at stake, I cannot permit the law in this respect to be broken. Nor can I give my consent without adequate reason given, unless, indeed, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Spencer Wade himself desires to terminate his connexion with the parish. In this case he can do so by giving you three months notice of his intention, and reporting his actions to me.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I must ask, therefore, for your reasons, and, if in my judgment they are sufficient, I shall be prepared to sanction the giving of the statutory six months notice.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have no doubt there are many individuals who are greatly perplexed about the Creed: and it may be the case that there are some who are kept away from seeking Ordination by their perplexities. But if, as a consequence of the Cambridge Conference, there be started a dogmatic panic, in which unwise decisions are taken by the central authorities of the Church – and this is no improbable contingency – will not the last case be worse than the first?</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Newsome is an excellent fellow, but he has what I call "a hospitable intellect" which welcomes all &amp; every kind of visitor. I think nothing whatever of his practical sagacity: though his geniality &amp; kindness of heart will always make him well&#8211;liked. In this vital matter of Christology, I think Liberal theologians must do a great deal more in the direction of clearing up their own minds before they embark on public discussion. I may be mistaken but I feel curiously sure that the Cambridge Conference was a grave blunder. The times are evil, look at them how you will.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours aff. H.D.</hi></p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>