<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent most of the day in reading through Gore's<persName xml:id="49"></persName> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Belief in God</hi><hi>". It is interesting, well written, and gives the impression of sincerity and a genuine desire to be both fair and thorough. But it is obviously an orthodox "case". The writer is curiously unable to appreciate the effect of his concessions, and sometimes seem to answer his own arguments. He underrates dangerously the result of historical criticism on the documents of the New Testament, &amp; misunderstands the reason why the evidence for the miraculous narratives is found insufficient by many who have no reluctance to admit that miracles may be both possible and credible.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In the afternoon I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName>. We lost our way, and got woefully muddy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName>, lately Archdeacon of Maidstone, but now retired, and living at 84 Woodstock Road, Oxford. That venerable city is becoming the haunt of retired ecclesiasticks.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After dinner I motored to Darlington, and met <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> arriving from London by the 10.23 p.m. express. The night was fair so I sate with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; had much talk with him.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>While I was seeking a place whereat I might obtain a platform ticket, a young man inquired whether I was seeking the "Refreshment Place", &amp; on my replying that I wanted to get a pass to the platform, </hi><hi rend="italic">said that I could get it by putting a penny into a machine which he pointed out. "But I haven't a penny" I replied, whereat he plucked out a penny from his pocket, &amp; gave it me saying that he was glad to be of some use. This small politeness to the Bishop pleased me. I judge that he was probably one of the Methodist youths, who had been among my congregation when I recently preached in the Chapel in Darlington.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Times" had another paragraph about the Religious Revival in north&#8211;eastern Scotland. It appears to be vehemently Sabbatarian, for two journalists who attempted to take photographs on Sunday were set upon by the zealots, and roughly handled. A bad fishing season seems to have occasioned the revival</hi><hi>.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>