<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in working on the "Charge" which I must give to the Ordination candidates. Why do I waste so much time in thinking over, and writing out, an address, which, if delivered extemporaneously "from the surface of the mind" would probably be far more effective? </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I suppose it is an odd kind of self&#8211;respect which makes me shrink from shoddy work: but I doubt my own wisdom in this matter</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, and attended the rendering of Gounod's music in the cathedral. We sate in the Throne, &amp; thought the music sounded better there than in the stalls. After the performance I had tea with the Dawson Walkers<persName xml:id="3161"></persName>. Clayton brought M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Arrowsmith, the clergyman to whom Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> has offered S. Gabriel's, to join the car, &amp; go with me to Auckland. After dinner I had some talk with him, &amp; found him attractive and straight forward. But his health leaves much to be desired. He is to consult his physicians, &amp; let me know their decision.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Sir Walter Scott's last words were worthy of him: they were addressed to his son&#8211;in&#8211;law, and biographer: &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Lockhart, I may have but a minute to speak to you. My dear, be a good man – be virtuous – be religious – be a good man. Nothing else will give you any comfort when you come to lie here</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I read them to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, whose recent study of Scott's novels has made interested in Sir Walter, and I think he was impressed. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hazlitt's</hi><hi> Essay on Sir W. Scott is a curious blend of shrewdness, malignity, and appreciation. He belittles the poetry excessively: he praises the novels judiciously: he abuses the man grossly. But Hazlitt was at every point the very contradiction of Scott. The only trait which the two men seem to have had in common was a passionate love of Shakespeare. "His (Hazlitt's) reading was necessarily fragmentary in youth, &amp; he confessed frankly to the many blanks which he never filled. His love of reading afterwards diminished, and it is </hi><hi rend="bold underline">said that he never read a book through after he was thirty</hi><hi>." "He was driven to isolation by his wayward temper and obstinate adherence to his peculiar political creed. He despised the whigs, loathed the tories, &amp; vehemently attacked the radicals of Beutham's school."</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>