<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The newspaper reports of yesterday's proceedings in the so&#8211;called "National Assembly" are extremely brief. It is apparent that the Press has made up its mind that they are worth little as "copy". We must make our count with the fact that there is no wider effect than that which is made on the Assembly itself to be expected from our speeches. Since I must always be in a minority, that effect in my case must always be practically </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nil</hi><hi rend="italic">. The morning was heavily wasted in discussing a motion for creating a Council on "Social" questions: &amp; the afternoon in dealing with dull &amp; ancient subject of Dilapidations. At 4.15 p.m. the Committee on Church Property met in the 2.A.B. Board Room with Lord Cave in the chair. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> and I walked together to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. I dined in the Club, and afterwards read rapidly through a foolish novel "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Fruit of the Tree</hi><hi rend="italic">". It startled me to see "Bishop Henson and Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>" bracketted in its pages as the final illustrations of the self&#8211;stultifying incoherence of the Church of England!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I lunched in the Club with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Bickersteth</hi><hi rend="italic">, quondam Vicar of Leeds, now Canon of Canterbury. He told me some of his experiences in visiting Japan. English was spoken very generally but sometimes with odd mistakes. Thus a Hospital managed by the missionaries announced that "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">it harboured all kinds of disease, and paid no respect to Religion</hi><hi rend="italic">". He expressed his belief that the poverty of the clergy had been greatly exaggerated. Comparatively few, indeed, have more than a very modest income, but the cases of squalid indigence are not so frequent as the tragical descriptions in the newspapers would appear to imply. I am myself disposed to believe that there is much truth in this view. The clergy have not been unaffected by the general clamour for improved conditions: many of them have been rendered very restive by the contrast between their own small incomes and the exorbitant wages which artisans have been receiving during the War, and brief delusive "boom" of 1919.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>