<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi><hi> writes to report a somewhat unusual service held in his church on Armistice Day:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"The Mayor being a Presbyterian, I asked his Chaplain, the local Presbyterian Minister to conduct the service in church; which he did admirably, &amp; the Congregational Minister, President of the Free Church Council read the Lesson, &amp; I gave the Blessing. All of us wore black gowns, &amp; it was simply a big &amp; most devotional Prayer Meeting."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>As against this must be placed the fact that in S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Saviour's, Hoxton, the Mass is regularly sung or said in Latin. The papers this morning publish a correspondence between </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Joynson&#8211;Hicks</hi><persName xml:id="4295"></persName><hi> and the Bishop of London on the subject. The Bishop explains that he has "completely ostracised" the church, and adds:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"I am glad to say that S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Saviour's, Hoxton, is an isolated case in the diocese, and I know that what is done there is repudiated by the English Catholic clergy in this diocese".</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Joynson&#8211;Hicks</hi><hi>, in his rejoinder, comments on this curious phrase:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"I must add that I am at a loss to understand the meaning of your lordship's expression "the English Catholic &#8211; churches of this diocese". I understand that the Church of England as a whole was catholic in character with all the churches of which it is composed."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>There can be no doubt, I think, that the Church of England is breaking up. Law is in complete abeyance.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spend most of the day in answering the letters which I received on my Birthday. Also I resigned the membership of "Nobody's Friends", on the ground that I found myself unable to attend the meetings; and I wrote to Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> "crying off" my article for the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh</hi><hi>".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Mayor of Sunderland<persName xml:id="5371"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Raine came to lunch, &amp; were shown over the castle. Lucy S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="5443"></persName> went back to the Ladies' College at Durham, rather ruefully.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>