<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The hard frost continues. I decided to "shoot a bow at a venture" in this difficult matter of B.A. Accordingly I wrote to Barry at Knutsford suggesting that he should organize here a school of the prophets. Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored into Durham where &#8211; we attended the meeting of the corporation in the Town Hall, at which the new mayor (Smith) was elected and installed. I made a short speech. Then I accompanied the procession to the Freemasons Hall, where there were refreshments, and many more speeches. I spoke again. After this function I rejoined the car in the College, &amp; returned to the castle. The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Carey Bonner, President of the Sunday School Union, who is visiting Bishop Auckland in the course of a "campaign" designed with the view of reviving Sunday schools throughout the country, came to the Castle for hospitality until tomorrow. I presided in the evening at the Methodist Church at a Lecture which he gave on, "A live Sunday&#8211;School, how to work it". There was not a large audience, but it was very attentive. I made a short speech as chairman in which, perhaps, I appeared more devoted to the cause of Sunday Schools than either my record or my belief really justify! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I was impressed by the almost complete absence of young men from the audience. Old men and middle&#8211;aged men were there in fair numbers, but not young men. Yet, surely, for the effective conducting of Sunday Schools none but young men will suffice</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Before going to bed I had an hour's talk with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Bonner in my study. He described the extreme difficulty which had been experienced in organizing a "Convention" in Rome. It was impossible to obtain the use of any adequate hall, and nobody, diplomatic (except the American ambassador) or political would give official recognition. This was ascribed not unreasonably to the influence of the Vatican.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I received a letter from Gilbert announcing that he had sent a barrel of apples from his orchard as a birthday present. He added some rather discouraging observations on the financial results of his harvest. I received affectionate letters from Philip le Mesurier, Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName>, and Colin Kennedy<persName xml:id="2432"></persName>.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>