<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yesterday was so bright and mild that inevitably one said, the winter is over, the spring has come. Today there is a high temperature, a clouded sky, and a tempestuous wind.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Two great and difficult matters must now be taken in hand viz: &#8211;</hi></p>
         <p><hi>1. Drafting a reassuring pronouncement on Doctrine by the Bishops.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>2. Preparing a memorandum on the Dean &amp; Chapter question.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I doubt if the first is possible: the last is not easy.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> came early, and I had much talk with him on several points of diocesan perplexity. He certainly represents a sound, strong type of Anglicanism, but he is 60 years old, and growing stiff in his mental joints. If only he, and his generation of "High Churchmen" could be rejuvenated! But the tide has receded, and they are in fact &amp; in metaphor "high and dry"! Lomax arrived in due course, and I had an interview with them both on the subject of the proposed "Retreat House". I insisted that as Bishop of Durham I must be both Visitor &amp; Ordinary: and that, not only must the Warden be approved &amp; licensed by me, but that I must approve the appointments &amp; ceremonial of the chapel. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But all safe&#8211;guards are really worthless against "Catholick" ill&#8211;faith. Really instead of 'Punica fides' we should speak of "Catholica fides"</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi><hi>Sykes &amp; Lomax lunched here.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">When I returned from a short "constitutional" in the Park, I received a telegram from Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> announcing the death of his Sister, Anne<persName xml:id="3504"></persName>. This will bear hardly on him, for they were much attached to one another. Then I wrote a letter of condolence.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev: T.J. McKitterick</hi><hi rend="italic">, Vicar of Holy Trinity, Gateshead, writes to thank me for my letter on the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Congress: He says: "I have almost 20 years experience of this diocese, &amp; I feel certain not only that your action was right but necessary. There are many of your clergy who refuse to wear a party label, but who are loyal to the Church of England, &amp; proud of the term Anglican, who will be encouraged by your Lordship's action. I feel sure it will meet with the hearty approval of the overwhelming majority of the laity."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I wish I were equally sure on the point.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>