<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the morning in drafting a pronouncement of the Bishops in answer to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> petition about the Cambridge Conference. There is not the slightest chance of my draft being adopted! After lunch William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Newcastle, and there I had my hair cut. Then I went to the rectory, Gateshead, and had tea with Stephenson. From him I went to Christ Church, Felling, and had an interview with the Vicar (Hoystead) about a man from S</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">t</hi><hi> John's, Highbury, whom he desires to have as a curate. But he is 32, and has no degree. He pleads the privilege granted to ex&#8211;service men, &amp; he proposes to go into residence at Durham University, after his Ordination. I undertook to consider the man's application when he made one. Then I returned to Auckland. In spite of the cold, I sate on the box with William, and had much talk with him.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Montague, the Secretary for India, has had to resign as a consequence of his unparalleled impudence in publishing the representations of the Viceroy of India as to Indian Moslem feelings on the Turkish question, without reference to the Prime Minister or any of his colleagues. The announcement of his resignation was received in the House of Commons with great enthusiasm. If the other Jews, Reading &amp; Samuel, were to follow his example, the Empire would be none the worse! The Fates are clearly hostile to the Government. This episode will give it another blow.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A curate in Sunderland has the impertinence to write to me, &amp; suggest that Auckland Castle should become the "Retreat House" for the clergy of the diocese, &amp; that the Bishop of Durham should betake himself elsewhere! Not only has poverty befallen the successor of the magnificent Palatine&#8211;Bishops, but insult also. It is, indeed, difficult to imagine such a proposition from such a source being made to any previous occupant of the See. "Life and Liberty" has cheapened the episcopate, and lowered its prestige, while pretending a vast regard for episcopacy!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>