<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The petition in the Collect for this Sunday expresses exactly my present necessity. To perceive my duty and to be able to fulfil it – that is my desire. I am perplexed beyond measure, and I am weak beyond belief. In my personal life, in the household, in the diocese, in the Church. I neither see my way nor am able to walk steadily in any way. Perhaps the uncertainty lies at the root of the weakness. If I </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> see clearly, should I indeed walk steadily? Or is my doubtfulness in some directions subtly visited by my deluding spirit into an excuse for unfaithfulness in all? Is not the source of the general mischief to be traced to some particular infidelity? Which of us really knows "</hi><hi rend="underline">the plague of his own heart</hi><hi>"? Did not the Lord warn us that "</hi><hi rend="underline">if the light that is in us be darkness</hi><hi>", the darkness is </hi><hi rend="underline">great</hi><hi>? May not the cleansing of the affections to be an even more pressing need than the illumination of the understanding, and the strengthening of the will? "</hi><hi rend="underline">Make me a clean heart, O God: and renew a right spirit within me</hi><hi>". That petition must come first, and then the prayer for guidance: "</hi><hi rend="underline">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my heart into Thee</hi><hi>". There are no less than six parishes in the diocese now vacant. Bishop Auckland, Burnmoor, S. Gabriel's Sunderland, S. Mary's, Tynedock, S. Giles', Durham, and S. Cuthbert's, Durham. With respect to no one of them is an obviously right appointment apparent: and there is little chance of replacing any assistant curate who may be appointed. The men do not exist. Unless some miracle happens, the ecclesiastical system, as it is now organized, must break down.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> celebrated in the chapel at 8 a.m. I was present but did not communicate, as I was pledged to celebrate later. At 9.45 a.m. we left the castle, and in a quarter of an hour were at Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear, where I instituted the new incumbent, (Wilkinson), and celebrated the Holy Communion. Wafers were used instead of bread, which I don't like, not only because it is always objected against by the people, but also because it destroys the symbolism of the "one loaf". There were a good number of communicants, &amp; so little wine provided that only by watering the chalice abundantly could we manage to give communion to all who presented themselves. The weather was fine, &amp; the little church looked its best. It is one of Hodgson Fowler's works, &amp; incorporates a few old features. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> could find no shelter for the car, &amp; was compelled to play the pagan, by absenting himself from Divine Service. This distressed me. After lunch we (the Pembers<persName xml:id="66"><persName xml:id="937"></persName></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Clayton &amp; I.) motored to Durham, and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. William also attended the service. We returned to the Castle at Auckland after service, and, when tea was over, Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName> &amp; I sate in my study, &amp; discoursed together until dinner&#8211;time.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ought a Bishop to sanction the giving of a tithe in a parish where the parish clergyman is parochially inexperienced, and where the pressure of work is such that the deacon is certain to be overworked</hi><hi rend="i bold">? </hi><hi rend="italic">It is surely a grave wrong to any young man to have his career spoiled at the outset by lack of sound guidance: and it is already the Bishop's proper duty to guard against that contingency. I think it cannot be unfair to postulants that the Bishop has a right to approve or reject the tithes offered by ordination candidates: for his discretion in the matter of Ordination is unlimited: and, therefore, although an incumbent is free to offer a tithe, he cannot require the Bishop to ordain the man to whom he gives it. And, for my own guidance I think these 2 conditions may be formulated:</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">1. The incumbent who gives a tithe must be clearly suitable both by character and by experience for the training of a deacon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">2. The parish must be suitable for securing to the deacon ….. opportunity of preparing for the Priesthood.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>