<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A high wind swept the snow into formidable drifts, and a fresh fall added considerably to the quantity available for drifting. My heart failed me, and, when William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> expressed a certain reluctance to adventure the expedition, and no convenient trains were running, I determined to cancel my engagements at Ebchester and Dipton. Telegrams were sent to that effect.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I stayed indoors, &amp; worked at preparing the Lecture, which I was foolish enough to promise to the Middlesbrough Historical Association. It is humiliating that so petty a matter should cost me so much labour.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> asking him to help me in the matter of B.A. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the English Church Union sent me a copy of a letter he has just issued to that body. It is an interesting document, and merits study. The Union is now organized on a Diocesan basis.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"It has become absolutely necessary to set to work deliberately upon the task of the organisation of the Catholic vote."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In effect, the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> is now a caucus formed to "capture" the new machinery for the "self&#8211;government" of the Church of England.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The Union has laboured to organise the Catholic party in the National Assembly from the very first opportunity. Its members have combined &amp; have invited the co&#8211;operation of others who accept like principles with themselves. A Watching Committee has been formed under the Chairmanship of Lord Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>. A meeting of like&#8211;minded people who represent the Catholic point of view is held before each meeting of the Assembly to consider the agenda for the session &amp; to decide upon a policy &amp;c."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The closest co&#8211;operation between the E.C.U., and the Federation of Catholic Priests is announced. All this is deplorable enough, for not only does it disclose a thoroughly sectarian spirit, but it destroys all possibility of unifying the Church of England. Particular attention is to be given to "packing" the Electoral Rolls, &amp; the meetings of the Parochial Church Councils. In the prevailing apathy, I doubt not that these tactics will be largely successful.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>