<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I breakfasted with Lady Serena<persName xml:id="4311"></persName>, and then walked to the club. Graves told me that, on the Library Committee, he was the only member who objected to "La Vie Parisienne". This is not creditable, for the paper is really nothing but undiluted filth: and the "Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>" (!) has it set out for the boys &amp; maidservants to look at. I went on to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and there spent the day, first, in the Committee on Church Property, and, then, on the Committee on Church Patronage. I called on Downing, and explained to him the situation at Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Wear. He expressed himself most sympathetically, but "Put not your trust in princes"! I dined at the club, and then wrote a number of letters.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I was amused to see that Begbie<persName xml:id="5310"></persName> prefaces his article on "Bishop Hensley Henson" by a quotation from Bagehot, in which mention is made of the description of Pitt that he was cast, and never grew'. It is implied that this is also true of the said H.H. Now I have often quoted the phrase of myself, so that there may be a measure of truth in it. The Article describes me as aggressive, ambitious, conceited, unscrupulous, &amp; merely intellectual. It suggests that I have no principles, &amp; no convictions, only a certain demonic "brilliance" of intellect.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Now, how far is there any truth in this description? It is certainly not true that I have no affection, and no sympathy but the affection is mainly suppressed, &amp; the sympathy is rarely expressed. If I had been so happy as to have children, I should probably have been a better as well as a happier man.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The description of my personal appearance is unprepossessing: it is also curiously inaccurate. He speaks of two projecting teeth in the lower jaw, when he means the upper: and of my "thin lips" whereas my lips are what the novelists call "sensual"!! He "gives himself away" by picturing me as soliloquizing in front of the old mantel&#8211;piece in Durham Castle, and entertaining my guests at Auckland, where I was foolish enough to give </hi><hi rend="italic underline">him</hi><hi rend="italic"> lunch. Talk of "entertaining angels unawares"? It is rather scandalous for one's guest to read one thus.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>