<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I spent the day at Lambeth. The discussions were not without interest. We began with the case of the elementary schools which now tends to desperation. The Archbishop of York was candid: &#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"I don't know any part of England except perhaps Lancashire where the laity, even our own religious laity, are prepared to find the money required to put the buildings in repair, when the present period of educational indifference has passed."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>His Grace of Canterbury gaves us an account of his dealings with the Dissenters, &amp; told us frankly that "there was no chance of the Fisher Bill passing the House of Commons." M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Fisher had undertaken that no privilege should be given to the Roman Catholics which would not be given to the Church of England, but the Archbishop thought we might well accept what the Roman Catholics w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> refuse. I inquired what we are to do in the interval before a general settlement had been effected. There was no money to satisfy even the most urgent demands of the local authorities. The Abp. replied that we must do what we c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> in the circumstances! This means, of course, surrendering the schools. Then the Bishop of Gloucester raised the question of Ripon College, objecting that Major, whether a heretick or not, was certainly a centre of controversy, and, as such, conflicted with the understanding that Principals of Training Colleges should keep out of controversy. The Bishop of Oxford<persName xml:id="602"></persName> spoke at length, &amp; with great discretion &amp; persuasiveness.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Aglionby suggesting that he might go to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Cuthbert's, Gateshead if he could undertake not to outrage the people by "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" extravagances. If he would do so, I would offer him that important parish, not otherwise.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Fisher dined here. There was no other guest. We had much conversation, &amp; I took the opportunity of telling him about my Durham project, &amp; invoking his good offices. He was very frank about the political situation, admitting that the Government was stale, &amp; that a change would probably be good for the country.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>