<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[173]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me in the motor to Durham. The fineness of the morning enabled me to sit with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. We robed in the cathedral, and I "ordained" a deaconess. Also I licensed a Parish Worker. These rather ambiguous "ordinations" of women don't quite please me, but the form used was drawn up by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Lightfoot</hi><persName xml:id="1817"></persName><hi>, &amp; has been continuously used in this diocese. I had some speech with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> about my Scheme, &amp; found him in a rather unpleasant mood. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Watkins</hi><persName xml:id="590"></persName><hi> &amp; he appear to be joining hands in a project of obstruction! We all lunched with the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshanks</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Judge Moore</hi><hi> &amp; his wife were there, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bailey</hi><persName xml:id="2806"></persName><hi>. Then I went to the Castle, and had an interview with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Donald Jones</hi><hi>, who desire to expound the dangers to Bede College involved in the scheme of the University for creating a Department of Education. Then I received a deputation from the parish of Cassop&#8211;cum&#8211;Quarrington, which represented the woeful condition of the said parish, due, as was believed, to the idleness of the Vicar. Clayton &amp; I had tea together in the Common Room, after which we rejoined the car, &amp; returned to Auckland.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> answered my letter promptly and generously</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> He sends the draft of what in his judgment the answer of the bishops to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> petition might fitly be. I wish, indeed, there were any chance of their Lordships adopting it. But there is none, for they are men of a pinched culture and a narrow spirit, swayed by fear more than by principle, dimly conscious that there is really a crisis to be faced, but nervously feeling that they are not the men to face it. He sends me also the newspaper report of the sermon which he preached in S. Mary's to the University on Feb. 12</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">. "I think I made a great impression. The Church was so crowded that many undergraduates could not get in at all, a thing which I believe has never happened before, &amp; the congregation listened intently. I think some of my points bear on the subjects which the Bishops have to consider". This extraordinary popularity of Ralph's is at least one hopeful sign.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>