<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Four years ago today I took my first Confirmation at the small village of Puddleston near Leominster, and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, a lad of 17, drove the hired car. It was the first occasion of our meeting. As well to mark the event, as to enforce a necessary lesson, I gave him a money&#8211;box in which to keep his certificates of money saved.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The publishers send me the review in the "Times Supplement" of my book. It is hostile, but not in expression brutal</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I was prepared for the hostility, and relieved at the absence of the brutality, for I knew that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> <hi rend="italic">was the reviewer! But mainly he misses my point, which is that modern conditions do not admit of the older form of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism", and that no choice any longer remains open to the Church of England but to be loyal to its historic character as a Protestant Church, or to dissolve. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He seems rather to be writing to the gallery than reviewing my book</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There is also a review, hostile and denunciating of course, in this week's issue of the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Church Times</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Lady Catherine Milnes Gaskell sends me a copy of the "Saturday Review" with a review of Elizabeth Asquith's book, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I have only Myself to Blame</hi><hi rend="italic">". Its character is sufficiently indicated by the reviewer's heading "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Dirty Work</hi><hi rend="italic">". Lady Catherine wants me to fulminate against the book, but I tell her that the only result of doing so would be to advertize the poisonous rubbish. Yet it is difficult to leave such outrages on decency unrebuked.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Certainly the variety of denunciation evoked by "Anglicanism" might suffice to demonstrate its freedom from partisanship</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The book literally pleases nobody, and vehemently offends many. It is probable that it will be read by very few, though talked about widely enough. I doubt if reviews have much, if any, effect on the sale of books, but I think they have considerable influence on the reputation of authors. And this is not an unimportant matter in the case of a Bishop, since his authority in his diocese must depend mostly on his reputation. If everybody would read the book before talking about it, I would be content: but, as it is, I fear it is inevitable that I shall be worse thought of than I deserve!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>