<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wasted the whole day in reading through again, &amp; more carefully, the papers read at the Girton Conference. They are less irreverent in tone than I first thought, but beyond doubt they are quite irreconcilable with the doctrine of the Incarnation. With the most ample expressions of homage all the writers insist on the normalness of Christ's manhood, and explain His "Divinity" as nothing more than His moral &amp; spiritual pre&#8211;eminence – He differs in degree, but not in kind, from the rest of us. None appears to attach any importance to His Death, beyond the proof of His Devotion, &amp; the crown of His service. Nor is His Revelation properly final. Indeed it has been already left behind. I cannot think that Christianity can persist on these lines.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Macdonald writes that Freddie is in the Acland Home with appendicitis. I wrote to the lad.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>In an episcopal reply to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName>'s petition, &amp; Burn's gravamen, I think the following points must be included:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>1. We must point out how the petitioners fail to apprehend the actual situation with which the modern church has to reckon.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>2. We must emphasize the need of thinking out theological issues afresh, &amp; re&#8211;stating credenda in terms of modern knowledge.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>3. We must recognize the Girton Conference as an honest attempt to do this, &amp; so far entitled to our approval.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>4. We must note the definite repudiation of Lake<persName xml:id="3172"></persName> &amp; Foakes Jackson<persName xml:id="3566"></persName>, and the evident desire to be true to the historic Christian Faith.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>5. We must indicate our disapproval of the method of public conferences as likely to wound the general conscience, &amp; to stimulate precipitate &amp; presumptuous dogmatising of the half&#8211;educated.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>6. We must affirm our conviction that Christianity stands and falls by the plenary Divineness of Jesus Christ, &amp; that no doctrine of the Incarnation can be adequate which ignores the uniqueness of His relation with God.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>7. We must insist that the proportions of the Faith as presented in the Apostolic writings must always be maintained.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>8. We must end by expressing our belief that there is no valid reason for consternation, but much for prayer &amp; thought.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>