<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Leake,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Your assistant curate, the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> J.S. Jubb, had an interview with me this afternoon at his own request. He informed me that he had definitely accepted the doctrine of the Church of Rome, and formed the resolution of joining its communion. He desired to know whether, in these circumstances, he could rightly continue to perform his duties as a clergyman of the Church of England. I told him that I could not tolerate such gross insincerity, &amp; that I must forbid him to continue to officiate in my diocese. Thinking it possible that he might be acting too precipitately, I offered to give him a week in order that he might think over his position, and, perhaps, take counsel thereon. But he protested that his mind was fully made up, and that any postponement would be useless except to prolong a situation impossible to defend. You will, please, understand therefore that M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jubb is to cease at once from officiating in your Church and parish, and that his license as an assistant curate to your parish is revoked.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am sorry that you should be inconvenienced, but I am well assured that you will agree with my decision.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Believe me, Sincerely yours,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> F.A.E. Leake.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This letter gives a sufficient account of my interview with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Jubb. He telegraphed to me yesterday, asking to see me on urgent business, &amp; I appointed a meeting for this afternoon at the Castle. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He explained that my letter in the "Yorkshire Post" had opened his eyes to the enormity of his position, for he was ministering in the English Church while altogether convinced that he ought to be a Roman Catholick</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> His Vicar had told him that he ought to lay his case before me, and accept my decision. It appears that he has long </hi><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi><hi> [symbol] been doubtful of his position as an English clergyman, that he has for than a year past been in communication with the Roman ecclesiasticks, that he fully intends making his submission to their Church. My letter appears to have given spur to his conscience, and helped him to realize the abominable nature of his conduct. It would be interesting to know whether any more of these Romanisers have been similarly illuminated!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Scarcely had M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Jubb departed when M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Binding appeared, a squat, square figure of a people's churchwarden in revolt against his vicar</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> His long rigmarole left me rather vague as to the nature of his grievance, and the genuineness of his character. However I gathered that there was a case for further inquiry, &amp; this I promised to make.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> and Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> joined us, &amp; William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored us to Bede College, where we were received by the Principal and shown over the building. After tea with the staff, we went into the common room, and there I addressed the students. When this performance was ended, we returned to the Castle.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The 'Times" has not published my letter, though I sent it with a covering note. This may mean nothing save some lack of consideration for the Bishop of Durham, but it may mean another consequence of the successful working of the 'Press Bureau'. The only certain, and certainly the worst, effect of this essay in our official press, will be to create a vast &amp; all&#8211;pervasive suspicion</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> However the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Newcastle</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Durham papers</hi><hi rend="italic"> have reproduced my letter from the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">", and I doubt not that it will soon become generally known. It will set people thinking, &amp; may strengthen some people to stand firm in their own convictions. If only </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burge</hi><persName xml:id="602"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had taken this course at the first, how much might have been effected! </hi><hi rend="italic underline">But he combines the innocence of the dove with the timidity of the hare, not with the wisdom of the scorpion</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Ripon has accepted the Presidency of the Congress, &amp; this is sufficiently regrettable, but he is probably much in sympathy with the Anglo&#8211;Catholic movement</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>