<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The snow returned this morning: during the day there was a considerable fall. I went to Durham by the 10.25 a.m. train, and sate all day in Cosin's Library presiding over a Committee summoned to examine the proposed Dilapidations Bill, and the proposed constitution for the Diocesan Conferences. Little introduced the first, and Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> the last. Bothamly<persName xml:id="3854"></persName> distinguished himself by incessant motions which were invariably rejected, he himself being the only supporter! In the end we passed a resolution welcoming the Dilapidations Bill and approving its provisions but adding a desire that the administrative power of the diocesan Board might be strengthened. We made some important amendments to the Resolutions. On the whole I was pleased with the temper and conduct of the Committee.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I lunched at the Castle with Brown of Monkwearmouth, and we discussed the situation at Rainton, where a pig&#8211;headed parson is creating a difficult situation about the schools.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Archdeacon Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName> writes to me suggesting that the Vicar of Sittingbourne might suit the requirements of B.A. I wrote to the gentleman forthwith sounding him on the subject. This makes my 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> attempt in the matter</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The papers report the speeches of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Asquith</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi><hi rend="italic"> at the Liberal demonstration held in London last night. They were what is called "fighting" speeches, and both disclosed an unusual degree of personal animus against </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi><hi rend="italic">. Asquith suggested that he was treacherous: and Lord Grey that he was ungrateful. Both agreed that he was shifty, untruthful, and unsafe. [All this I believe to be largely true: but]</hi><hi rend="i subscript"> ^</hi><hi rend="italic">Even if all this should be conceded as at least partly true, it yet remains true that</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi> <hi rend="italic">it presents</hi> <hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi><hi rend="italic">only</hi><hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> <hi rend="italic">one, and that the worst, side of a many sided character. A Welsh Dissenting Radical could hardly </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">in the circumstances of modern party politics,</hi><hi rend="i subscript"> ^</hi> <hi rend="italic">be loyal, or truthful, or constant, or trustworthy. But </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">apart from his magnificent natural gifts,</hi><hi rend="i subscript"> ^ </hi><hi rend="italic">Lloyd George is also courageous, versatile, laborious and patriotic. He has 'vision', and he can </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">dare to</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">take risks. These are high qualities, and in a critical changing time such as the present, they are indispensable. During the War they were inestimably valuable: but every step back to normal political conditions makes them less necessary, and renders the absence of </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">some</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">other qualities more lamentable.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>