<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[163]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. The lovely and disconcerting Epistle allures and dismays me. I spent the morning in my study preparing myself for my engagements later in the day. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street where I dedicated a War&#8211;memorial in the Parish Church, and preached at Evensong. On both occasions the church was crowded. We had tea at the Rectory. Sir Arthur Wood and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hale, two of the churchwardens were there also, and I had some conversation with them about the state of the coal industry.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Vicar of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> F.H. Jackson</hi><hi>, is a Cambridge wrangler and apparently keeps up his reading. He is just now absorbed in Einstein's theories, on which he preaches and lecturers to his parishioners, rather (I suspect) to their amazement than to their edification. His experience as a clergyman has been mainly non&#8211;parochial – as a school master and a naval chaplain – and his present situation as Vicar of a parish with 19000 inhabitants, all rough artisans &amp; miners, must be almost overwhelming. But he is certainly addressing himself to the task with remarkable courage. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He has the great advantage of succeeding a thoroughly unsatisfactory clergyman</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Under the late Vicar the Church in Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street "touched bottom". I think Jackson &amp; his wife are liked and respected. The latter is a member of the 'National Assembly', and her election illustrates the absurd character of the electoral system, or rather the practical impossibility in the present circumstances of the church of securing by any electoral system an effective representation of the laity. She was a new&#8211;comer, personally unknown to the parish &amp; diocese: but she circulated a well written "election&#8211;address", and was returned at the head of the poll! She forms one of three female&#8211;representatives from this diocese. M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi> Watkins and Miss Tristram also sit in the Assembly. It is hard to see how the wives and daughter of the clergy can fully represent the laity. They must be described as at least semi&#8211;clerical! I understand that there are in the present assembly some 40 female members, of whom several are the wives of bishops. This surely should not be tolerated.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>