<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>January 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My dear Lady Eden,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I have enquired whether there is any precedent for a Bazaar &amp; Tennis Tournament in the Castle Grounds, &amp; there appears to be none. I do not feel willing to create one without very strong cause, as, in these days, such a precedent is likely to commend itself widely. Besides – this is for your Ladyship's private ear – I have a loathing for Bazaars, &amp; would be loth to have one in my own ground!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Trusting that you will soon get the better of the Influenza, I am</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours v. sincerely</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>This was the answer I returned to a request for the use of the grounds for a Bazaar &amp; Tennis Tournament for the Y.M.C.A. Apart from the reasons alleged in my letter, I should certainly not select </hi><hi rend="underline">that</hi> <hi>object for such special privilege. But mainly I am influenced by a fear that, if permission were once granted, it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be often asked for.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> came to my study after breakfast, &amp; for 1 1/2 hours I dictated to her shorthand this blessed lecture for Middlesbrough. In that time I suppose I provided enough for (at most) 20 minutes delivery. This surely is very slow work.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went into Durham, where I presided at a meeting of the Bede College Committee: and afterwards had an interview with that foolish creature Rawlins of West Rainton. Then I returned to Auckland. Later, J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> &amp; I motored to Witton Park, and there I instituted the Rev. Charles Geeson to the Vicarage of that parish. There was a fair congregation and they listened well to my sermon. The service was not without a certain impressiveness, and, if Geeson be a man of brains &amp; energy, he might make it the beginning of an effective ministry. We returned to the Castle and dined. Wilson returned to Durham and I went to my study and wrote to Dawson on the matter of the West Rainton School. I hope rather than believe that that business is settled.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>