<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, February 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My cold lay so heavy on me that I did not venture into the chapel at 8 a.m. to my great disappointment. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> celebrated in my stead. I shall repeat at Horden with necessary alterations the address which I gave at Chester–le–Street last Sunday.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I wrote to Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> asking whether he could shift the date of my sermon in Westminster Abbey, as I have been asked to preach the Commemoration Sermon at Oxford on June 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, which was the day originally fixed. Also, I wrote to the Dean of Belfast Cathedral declining his invitation to preach. It would take a stronger inducement than that to get me on to shipboard!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>After lunch I motored to Horden, and there addressed a P.S.A. in the Miners' Hall, a low–pitched building with no visible means of ventilation. The atmosphere was asphyxiating: the audience numbered about 200 men, and the managers were cauling sectaries. I had tea with Brigstocke, who is certainly looking much stronger. The air of Horden is doing him good. I preached at Evensong to a large congregation. The service was hearty, and the choir, (composed of men, women, &amp; boys) numbered nearly 60 persons. Immediately after the service we returned to Auckland, where we arrived about 8.45 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>This sort of work would be impossible if I had no motor, and it is not, perhaps, excessive to offer the fact as going far to justify the considerable expenditure, which the motor involves.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The sermon preached at Horden tonight was preached for the 16</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> time. It was originally written for <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's, Westminster</orgName>, in 1910. It was preached 3 times in America, and once in </hi><hi>Scotland. I have preached it 6 times in the diocese of Durham, twice during the War while was Dean, &amp; four times since I have been Bishop. The text is a favourite of mine, as it was of Dean Stanley<persName xml:id="505"></persName> – "</hi><hi rend="underline">I see that all things come to an end, but thy commandment is exceeding broad</hi><hi>." Brigstocke lamented that he had not opened a book since he had been at Horden, and told me that he preached without notes. This means that he predestined to become a windbag. It is a pity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Dismorr,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I agree with you that there is a lamentable absence of sound and careful teaching on the subject of Religion; but I am not very favourably disposed towards short summaries of history and doctrine drawn up with the object of serving some denominational interest. The Truth is not easily set forth in that way even by those who have no other interest than the Truth. And too often the writers of these summaries &amp; text–books care more for their polemical purpose than for the truth. The Roman Catholics have always adopted this method of teaching, but, in spite of their success in making converts, they have earned so ill a reputation as controversialists that no one would accept their statements without reference.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I return your Notes uncorrected, though they contain </hi><hi rend="underline">many</hi><hi> errors, which would have to be corrected before they were printed. The best account of the Church of England in English that I know is the Professor Garatkin's "Church &amp; State in England to the Death of Queen Anne." It is published by Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Longmans &amp; Co.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I sympathize with you in the defection of your daughter from the Church of England; but I have learned in the course of my life that these changes of Church are mainly matters of individual temperament. It may be that only in a sacramental &amp; authoritative presentment can some minds find Christianity intelligible or helpful. Lecky<persName xml:id="3601"></persName></hi> says somewhere that the Roman Catholic Church represents the feminine, &amp; Protestantism the masculine version of Christianity.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours sincerely,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>J. Stewart Dismorr Esq</hi></p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>