<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Four years ago on this day I was consecrated a Bishop in Westminster Abbey, and the occasion hangs heavily in my mind. I went straight to the barber, and had my hair cut. Then I wrote to Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; sent him a communication for the Diocesan Gazette. I found Strong<persName xml:id="120"></persName> in the Club, &amp; talked about my Durham project, with which he professed sympathy. After lunch I walked to Lambeth, and attended </hi><hi rend="bold underline">a meeting of Bishops.</hi><hi> Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> brought forward the memorial to the Archbishop asking him to appoint a Commission on Doctrine with a view ultimately of producing something of the nature of a revised 39 Articles. The Archbishop made a cautious &amp; sensible speech, &amp; then I spoke. I began by a reference to my consecration.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"Four years ago I was consecrated a Bishop in Westminster Abbey. I have ever regarded that day as the unhappiest of a life in which unhappy days have not been few. When I recall the behaviour of a large number of the bishops, &amp; consider how grievous was the injury they inflicted on me, how grave the obstacle to success which they thrust in my path at the start, in what gratuitous &amp; undeserved embarrassment they immersed me, &amp; remember that they are good men who conceived themselves required by their duty to act thus, I could not doubt the depth of the internal divisions of the Church of England."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I argued against the motion, &amp; I think made an impression. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Several bishops thanked me afterwards.</hi><hi> The debate went on all the afternoon; the general sense was, I think, adverse to the proposal. During the discussion the Bishop of Winchester passed me a note – "Your old friend &amp; my very beloved colleague, Macarthur died this morning of heart failure at Luccombe Hill. I had a letter from him in my morning's post." This is sad news. I liked Macarthur, &amp; he liked me. I went to the club &amp; wrote to his sister, who will be desolate. I dined with Lady S.<persName xml:id="3466"></persName>, Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, Sir Russell Rodd &amp; Lady Rodd, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Mildmay were the party, &amp; it was pleasant enough. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Haldane's oleaginous optimism becomes rather wearisome after a while!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>