<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Hard frost, &amp; bright sun. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel, &amp; then, after breakfast, settled down to prepare an address to the men of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street this afternoon. I took my subject from Ferrero's book, &amp; opened my address with a quotation from its pages – "The present position and prospects of Christianity". It gave me material for a discourse which lasted for 3/4 of an hour, and was closely listened to by a congregation of men, which fairly filled the church. The Congregational Minister read the lesson, &amp; the rector conducted the short service: Both going to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, and returning therefrom I sate with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi>, and had much talk with him. We have certainly become very close friends: may Heaven bless the friendship! The fineness of the afternoon, and the absence of wind made motoring very pleasant in spite of the cold. After dinner I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert Simpson</hi><persName xml:id="554"></persName><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName><hi>, and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cecil Fortescue</hi><persName xml:id="4760"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It is, perhaps, a question worth asking, whether it is really worth while to keep in touch with the boys, whose love one wins. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi><hi rend="italic"> is my Godson, and there may be in that circumstance a sufficient reason why I should maintain correspondence with him: but I have no other link with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">George</hi><hi rend="italic"> than that which his own loyal devotion to me constitutes: and as to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cecil Fortescue</hi><hi rend="italic">, he is just a young clergyman of Anglo&#8211;Catholick proclivities who came into contact with me when I was Bishop of Hereford, &amp; elected to form a kind of attachment to my person! Sometimes I incline to think that this kind of correspondence is the abjectest waste of time: and sometimes my thoughts take the opposite direction, &amp; I conclude that the most really valuable work I do, &#8211; is keeping alive a friendship with these young men. It is melancholy to recall the names of many with whom I have not been able to keep touch, &amp; who once saw light in my light. 'Some in the tumult are lost.' It is odd to see myself described as a cold 'logic&#8211;machine', heartless &amp; without feeling for anything but the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">gaudia certaminis</hi><hi rend="italic">", and to know, not only that beyond most men I desire and depend on the affection of others, but also that, in perhaps an unusual degree, I evoke &amp; retain the devotion of young men. We are all mimes and masques in this world.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>