<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A bright but bitter day. This winter seems likely to rival that of 1916: Heaven grant it be not so fatal to the thrushes! Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, where I instituted 4 curates in the Castle Chapel, and then went to my room. Here Harrison came to me to discuss various points of diocesan business. Then I gave lunch to him, Clayton, and old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Watts from Witton Gilbert. Afterwards, I had an interview with the last on the matter of his resignation. He is 84 years old, and desolate since his wife died, and his daughters are married. His main reason for thinking himself bound to resign is his perception of the bad consequences on the female side of his flock of there being no lady in the parish. There is a complication about his responsibility for the vicarage house. The present house has become unsafe by reason of colliery workings, and he has for some years lived in a hired dwelling. A sum of &#x00A3;500 paid as compensation has been lying at interest in the hands of the Ecclesiastical Commissioners. A new vicarage is estimated to cost about &#x00A3;4000. I arranged that he should resign on June 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Graham, the curate from Silksworth, who desires to go to Eldon to serve as curate there, came to see me. I gave him permission on the usual terms. Then Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> looked in to ask whether he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> represent the Diocesan Finance Brd. before the Committee on Church Property and I approved. I called on the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> about 4 p.m. in order to discuss the scheme for revising the constitution of the College, and had tea with him. Welldon is fussy, talkative, and fluctuating. His vanity resists what his good sense recommends. He seems to anticipate difficulty from the side of the University. We motored to Darlington, &amp; there took train to York where we were due at the meeting of Convocation. The Abp's motor met me, &amp; carried me to Bishopthorpe, where all the Bishops of the Province had assembled except Liverpool &amp; Sodor &amp; Man. After dinner I explained the Durham scheme to my brethren, &amp; they received it very kindly. I asked that the Bishop of Ripon should be associated with me in the matter, &amp; this was agreed to in an unofficial manner. We talked awhile before turning in.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>