<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The papers announce the death of Lord Bryce in his 84</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> year. It is but a few weeks since I had speech with him in the House of Lords, &amp; then he promised to visit us here. I first made his acquaintance after my election to All Souls, when he asked me to lunch at Oriel, &amp; intermittently we renewed touch afterwards. He entertained <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and me in Washington in 1909 and in 1912: he stayed some days with us in the Deanery at Durham: he presided at the lecture on "Anglican Christianity" which I gave at King's College in 1919: and occasionally we exchanged letters. I wrote to Lady Bryce.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I dictated to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> the address for the Middlesbrough Historical Association. It will be rare rubbish!</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> seems to indicate that he is coming within the range of religious perplexity. His landlady appears to be smitten with the fashionable madness of spiritualism, &amp; as always is very eager to proselytize:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"Nearly every evening when the others have gone to bed, she and I will have talks about Religion. At times she really makes me wonder lots of things! The After Life is a great topic of hers. There is a part of the Creed which she doesn't believe, 'The Resurrection of the Body'. How </hi><hi rend="italic underline">can</hi><hi rend="italic"> bodies rise again? she says. If you will give me the right meaning of it, my Lord, I should feel very grateful. In a way I think she is rather inclined to believe in Spiritualism – for she is continually telling me of people who have seen certain visions. The subject has often puzzled me, for when such people as Conan Doyle &amp;c are so great on it – it makes one wonder how much Truth there is in the matter."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>George would be a tempting object to a fanatical spiritualist, for his courtesy would lead him to listen with polite attention, &amp; his genuine piety would incline him to treat every religious opinion with respect. It would distress me not a little if his simple faith were really troubled, and his honest conscience sophisticated by the morally disintegrating sophistues of spiritualism.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>