<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[158]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>A Nonconformist from Newcastle writes to thank me for snubbing the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks. His own letter is not uninteresting: &#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>"I write neither as an Anglican, &amp; certainly not as an 'Orangeman' or 'Kensite', but I often ask myself why these gentlemen to whom you have replied stipulate for what is ornate and ritualistic in order to be able 'to convert to our Lord those who do not know him'. Bunyan, Wesley, Farrar, Booth, and others had the happy privilege, I believe, of achieving that grand mission without the extraneous aids sought by the Anglo&#8211;Catholics. If the latter's media &amp; forms are not copied from Rome, why is it that they bear such a striking resemblance to them?"</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The "Yorkshire Post" announces that the Bishop of Ripon will preside over the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Congress", and that among the Vice&#8211;Presidents will be the Bishop of Newcastle</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">I knew that these Bishops had decided to accept an official connexion with the Congress, for they told me that such was the case, but they had clearly not thought out the meaning of their action, &amp; were just "going with the stream", the obviously easiest course. But the general effect of this open difference between Bishops must needs have the worst effect on public opinion, &amp; is an obvious weapon in the hand of the Papist enemy. If Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> had taken a more courageous course, and one more accordant with his own convictions, it is almost certain that no Bishops would have associated themselves with the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholick movement' except those who, like the late Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Albans, are definitely in agreement with it. As it is, the Bishops generally will become connected with it, and make any effective challenging of its propaganda almost impossible. None the less that propaganda is quite fatal to Anglicanism, as many of the Bishops are ready enough privately to affirm. I feel almost asphyxiated by the atmosphere of unreality in which all Anglican life proceeds. Everybody is pretending to be, to mean, to desire, to hope what he verily knows he neither is, nor means, nor desires, nor hopes. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with me to Wolsingham, where we lunched with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joseph Backhouse</hi><hi> &amp; his wife, and then went to the School over which he presides as Headmaster for the annual prize&#8211;giving. </hi><hi rend="underline">This school founded by Bishop James in 1614, is now a secondary school under the Durham County School, and lavishly maintained out of the rates</hi><hi>. It is a mixed school, boys &amp; girls between the ages of 11 and 19 being taught together in the same classes. I inquired whether any disciplinary difficulties emerged, and was categorically assured that such difficulties were unknown. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Headmaster did, however, admit that he disallowed friendships between scholars of different sexes</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Familiarity can do much, but I find it difficult to believe that it can exorcize sex when boys &amp; girls who are well&#8211;advanced in adolescence are thrown together. However, the experiment of co&#8211;education was said to be a complete success in Wolsingham, &amp; certainly the scholars had a wholesome &amp; attractive appearance. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Sam Adams</hi><hi>, as Chairman of the Governors, presided, the Headmaster read his report, I distributed the prizes and made a speech. I had taken no pains to prepare the speech, save to note down on a half sheet that Wolsingham School had 3 distinctive features – it was 1. historical 2. small 3. rural: and that these went far to correct the 3 main faults of modern education viz. 1. Up&#8211;to&#8211;dateness: 2. Mass&#8211;handling. 3. Philistinism. For the rest I picked up material on the spot. Perhaps because the speech was this unprepared, it was rather unusually successful! We carried </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sam Adams</hi><hi> back with us to Bishop Auckland. I sate with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName><hi>, and enjoyed the scenery.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Life and Liberty Movement" sends me notice of a Retreat which it is organizing for members of the 'National Assembly'. The Conductor is, of course, to be a member of the Talbot family – the Rev</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> E. K. Talbot C.R.! A prayer for the Nat: Ass: is enclosed</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>"If in your Diocese there is not already a prayer for the N.A. sanctioned for general use, we hope you may be able to get this one widely known and used among your Clergy &amp; Councillors."!!!!!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>