<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I left the castle at 7.45 a.m., and travelled easily to London arriving shortly after 2 p.m. Leaving my bags in Park Lane, I went to Westminster, and spent the afternoon at the Church Property C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi>. The Archdeacon of Oakham and Prebendary Hay gave evidence on the proposed Dilapidations measure. The Bishop of Bristol walked with me after the Committee had ended, and I tried to learn from him what precisely was intended by the Commission on Doctrine which he and others are asking the Archbishop to appoint. But he could give me no intelligible answer.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Parry Evans<persName xml:id="5414"></persName> came to see me at 6 p.m. at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and we discussed the question of his coming to Bishop Auckland to succeed Lord Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName>. He was ready to accept at once, and didn't think it necessary to postpone his decision until he had visited the parish. He is a tall, spare man, not by any means handsome, but certainly not conspicuously plain! On the whole I was rather relieved by his appearance!! Lord Thurlow's many excellences have not included an impressive physique!</hi><hi> I dined with Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> in the club and afterwards wrote to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName>.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">That creature </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Harold Begbie's</hi><persName xml:id="5310"></persName><hi rend="italic"> book, "Painted Windows" is in the club. I took it, and glanced through it. Certainly the account of </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Bishop of Durham is sufficiently unflattering</hi><hi rend="italic">. It does not seem particularly well&#8211;informed, and the only writing of the Bishop's which is quoted is his speech to the Diocesan Conference last June, which was published in the "Diocesan Gazette". One statement is equally injurious and unfounded. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He says that the Bishop in early days earned the nickname 'Cocksley Cocksure' in controversy with D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Headlam. I asked Headlam whether he was aware of this, and he replied that we never had any controversy, &amp; that the said nickname was unknown. It is the case that when I came to Durham as Dean some local paper called me "Cocksley Cockson", and provided me with a comic coat of arms. That was a poor enough witticism but it was not meant to be unkind.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>