<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I left Bishopwearmouth Rectory at 9 a.m. in a deluge of rain, and caught an excellent train which went through to Bishop Auckland, where I arrived about 10 a.m. The day was frittered away in writing letters &amp;c. Also I paid wages to Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Berry for the household; &amp; had an interview with Frank Berry, who has been staying here on a visit to his mother for a month past. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> gave me a photograph of the Altar in the Chapel taken by himself, very good and clear. I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> answering his questions about "the Resurrection of the body", and warning him against spiritualism. I sent him cuttings from the Yorkshire Post, which give an account of a controversy between Conan Doyle and a man named Tilson Young, who attended some spiritualistic seances, &amp; discovered much fraud. Also I wrote to Gilbert Simpson<persName xml:id="554"></persName> asking him to make George's acquaintance and to befriend him.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"Spiritualism" is a curiously perplexing, and an extremely exasperating factor. It lays hold of the most unlikely individuals, and has a strangely absorbing interest for anyone who has once dabbled in it. The young are attracted by the suggestion of a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">terra incognita</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Science awaiting exploration: and they are only the more attracted by the suspicion of spiritual 'Bohemianism' which attaches to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">mediums</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">seances</hi><hi rend="italic">. Women are completely conquered by the emotional appeal. Their hearts are eagerly engaged from the start, &amp; they are apt to resent any suggestion of imposture as if it professed a Faith rather than cleansed a study. It is quite certain that the effect of dabbling in Spiritualism is mentally &amp; morally unwholesome. Men, and still more women, become completely unhinged, lose their sense of rectitude, and, even when they escape insanity, are quite disqualified for the business of life. This fact might well suffice to justify total abstinence from so unsavoury and perilous an interest: but it does not hold back many people. I cannot personally undertake to investigate the subject, and one is obviously at a great tactical disadvantage in being obliged to preface one's condemnation of Spiritualism by owning that one knows nothing about it?!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>