<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">What shall I preach about on Jan</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">y </hi><hi rend="bold underline">27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> when I go into Durham for the annual Commemoration of Founders &amp; Benefactors in the Cathedral</hi><hi rend="bold">? </hi><hi>There are the fabrick, the foundation, the cathedral system, the Church of England, the Christian Church, Religion – a large choice but all subjects upon which it is impossible to speak freshly and very difficult to speak wisely.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> writes to consult me about the appointment to Burnmoor. I wrote back to him at once, suggesting that he might choose a senior:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"Burnmoor is </hi><hi rend="underline">relatively</hi><hi> a small parish: and, in the present shortage of clergymen might be fairly thought to be too small for a young man. In the general interest of the diocese, &amp; on broad grounds of policy, it might perhaps be right to appoint a senior man, who had "borne the burden &amp; heat of the day" in a great parish, &amp; who would now be best placed in a smaller one."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I recommended the following: &#8211; Seniors – Gadd and Major.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Juniors: &#8211; Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName>, Appleton<persName xml:id="5366"></persName>, and Wreford Brown.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>cf. p. 121. The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> A. S. Silva White, Vicar of S. Peter, Bp. Wearmouth, came to see me with relation to the complaint of one his Churchwardens as to his neglect of parochial duty by his employment as a Teacher in a local school. I sifted the matter thoroughly, </hi><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi> <hi>[symbol] and decided that there was no substance in the complaint. However, I decided that I must have an assurance from the parochial church council to the effect that there was no just objection from the parishioners.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName> &amp; his wife left after lunch. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove them to Darlington, where they would take train to York.</hi></p>
         <p><hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I visited the Infirmary Hospital, and were shown over the place by the matron, Miss Demster, an iron&#8211;faced Scotch woman. On returning to the Castle, I had an interview with the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Bruce George Beale, who desires to leave my diocese on completing two years from his Ordination as deacon. He can't get on with his Rector, and his wife can't hit it off with the Rector's!! The parish, Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, is spiritually a "Dead Sea".</hi></p>
         <p><hi>That excellent man, Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, sends a note as follows: &#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"The engraving of Worcester College, Oxford, which hangs in the doorway of the small dining room of Auckland Castle which was published by J. R. Parker, Oxford, on 21</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> November, 1855, was, as I thought, drawn and engraved by John Henry le Keux, the son of John le Keux, and the nephew of Henry le Keux, the two engravers whose names were found in the Biographical Dictionary."</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>I read the first three Essays of the collection edited by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">R. W. Livingstone </hi><hi>under the title "</hi><hi rend="underline">The Legacy of Greece</hi><hi>". The very brief preface by the Editor is pregnant:</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi>"In spite of many differences, no age has had closer affinities with Ancient Greece than our own: none has based its deeper life so largely on ideals which the Greeks brought into the world. History does not repeat itself. Yet, if the twentieth century searched through the past for its nearest spiritual time, it is in the fifth &amp; following centuries before Christ that they would be found. Again &amp; again, as we study Greek thought and literature, behind the veil woven by time &amp; distance, the face that meets us is our own, younger with fewer lines &amp; wrinkles on its features and with more definite and deliberate purpose in its eyes."</hi></p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>