<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I went to the Club and read the papers. Then to the bookseller and ordered some books including a story for Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>. The young man told me that he had just sent a copy of "Anglicanism" to the Dean of Canterbury. Then I went to the National Galley and saw Gainsborough's "Blue Boy", which is being exhibited before its exportation to America. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Next I went to the Hospital, and visited Marion, who is eagerly looking forward to her return to Birchington</hi><hi>. I fell in with the Bishop of Chester, and, in the course of conversation, happened to mention my need of a good parson to succeed Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName> at Bishop Auckland. He at once mentioned the Rector of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> <hi>George's Southwark, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Pringle, of whom he spoke in the highest terms. I went to the club and wrote to this gentleman forthwith, suggesting that he might see me during my stay in London. After lunch, I walked to Westminster, and attended a meeting of the Committee on Church Property. This went on until 5 p.m., M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>Downing the Secretary of the Ecclesiastical Commission being in the witness's chair all the time. The Bishop of Bristol and I walked together, &amp; then I settled in the club until it was time to get back to Park Lane. Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and I dined together. Then I wrote several letters.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>On reaching Park Lane I found a telegram from Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> in these terms: &#8211; "</hi><hi rend="underline">Reynolds, Burnmoor died this morning. Funeral Friday three o'clock</hi><hi>". This is sudden, and regrettable for Reynolds was certainly one of the best clergymen in the diocese. Where to replace him from is hard to say. Burnmoor is in Lord Durham's<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> patronage. It is said to be worth &#x00A3;420, net, and to have 1690 parishioners. I think, perhaps, I ought to return to Durham to take the funeral. Within a few weeks to lose Lasbrey<persName xml:id="4304"></persName>, Tolliday<persName xml:id="2928"></persName>, and Reynolds is a considerable calamity. Lord Thurlow leaves in a few weeks. Where are the men who can be sent to their parishes? If curates are promoted, their places cannot be filled. The Church is steadily sinking for lack of men.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>