<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>[symbol]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The snow still covers the country, and it is mortally cold. I go to preach and celebrate in a cold church. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Why is it that the churches called Evangelical are so mortally cold</hi><hi rend="i bold">? </hi><hi rend="italic">They almost always smell of varnish, and escaping gas. The windows appear to be never opened, so that the atmosphere is asphyxiating. There is an indescribable suggestion of sanctimonious irreverence and their assistants. The congregations (which are mostly small enough) listen with an air of condescension, unless the preacher be one of their recognised "men of God", when they hang on every word, however foolish, which falls from his lips. You can see that they question the soundness of everyone outside the inner circle of the elect. They are waiting for their shibboleths and, if these don't emerge at the right places, they "have no use for" the preacher!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">We (i.e. Edward Smith, his wife, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> &amp; I) motored into Durham where I preached in S. Nicholas Church, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">It was the formal resumption of public worship after the church had been closed for "renovation": and the Mayor &amp; Corporation attended in State. Among the communicants was William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. It appears to be the practice in this church to administer the Holy Communion with one recitation of the words of administration for every rail&#8211;full of communicants. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But I insisted on the Rubrick being obeyed</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">We returned to Auckland after service. I sate with William both going &amp; returning, but the wind was violent, snow fell continuously, &amp; it was very cold.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ben Spoor, our local M.P., came to tea. He talks with much intelligence &amp; good sense. He has travelled extensively, and has views on most political questions, which he expresses with moderation. I was favourably impressed by him. He seems to think that an election is imminent; that L.G. will gain a majority though one much smaller than that which now exists: that the "Labour" party will carry about 140 seats: &amp; that the Liberals will hardly muster more than 50. He anticipates further trouble in Ireland, so that the Irish policy of the Government is not likely to be much use in a short time. It is an asset which had best be realized at once. </hi></p></body></text></TEI>