<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi>My dear Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>,</hi></p>
         <p><hi>My recollection certainly accords with Pearce's<persName xml:id="636"></persName>. It was the custom for the offer of a gift to be reported to the Chapter, and accepted or declined by the Chapter. I remember the case of the Revised Version of the Bible presented by the 4 Burgesses of Oxford &amp; Cambridge. It was formally accepted by the Chapter, &amp; </hi><hi rend="underline">I think</hi><hi> there was an entry in the Minutes thanking them. This would be in the early months of 1901. Armitage Robinson<persName xml:id="44"></persName> offered a rather embittered opposition, but he was alone. Later, I remember the question being raised as part of the voluminous case against A.R. who had then become Dean: &amp; my recollection is that there was a general understanding that, whatever else was doubtful, the control of the property was clearly in the hands of the Corporation itself i.e. the Dean &amp; Chapter. This was the view on which I myself acted as Dean of Durham. The late Lady Londonderry desired to present a processional cross to the Cathedral. I brought her offer before the Chapter, &amp; only when it had been formally accepted, did she proceed to carry out her intention. Durham, like the Abbey, is a Tudor foundation, in which the Dean has control of the services, &amp; larger powers than in the older foundations.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I do not see how the Chapter c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> reasonably be expected to undertake the responsibility of ownership for properties which it had not itself consented to accept.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>I am worrying my brains over the point, Whether the Bishops sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> make any answer to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> petition about the Cambridge Conference, &amp;, if so, What.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Yours aff</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ley</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Ven: Archdeacon Charles</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi>The ever developing "Ritualism" of Westminster Abbey under an amiable Dean, too susceptible to "social opinion", and too easily led by the minor&#8211;canons, is clearly exercising the minds of the Canons, who, with the possible exception of Carnegie, are opposed to "Ritualism".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p><hi>One of the diocesan lay readers, Thompson, an engineer by trade, &amp; 37 years of age, came to inquire whether I would accept him as a candidate for Ordination, and I refused. I said he was too old, &amp; that he could not reasonably be expected to satisfy my examining chaplains. He received my decision with due submission, &amp; went away.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I walked in the Park, and, as we returned, encountered a stout &amp; well&#8211;dressed female with a colley on a leash, &amp; a puppy running loose. I inquired whether she had never read the notice on the Park gate prohibiting the entrance of dogs: &amp; she said that she had taken her dog in for years. Nevertheless, I made her remove the beast, pointing out that yesterday I had evicted a miner with his whippet, &amp; I could not have one rule for miners &amp; another for ladies! So she went away.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>Clayton and I motored to Stockton, and arrived at the Parish Church more than half an hour before the time appointed for the Confirmation. I confirmed (as I was assured, but the number seemed to me greater) 171 candidates, fairly divided between the sexes. I felt curiously fatigued by the service which took just an hour and a half. We returned to Auckland directly, and arrived just after 9.30 p.m.</hi></p>
         <p><hi>The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Herbert Ratford, whom I met some years ago at the Hague where he was chaplain, writes to express his approval of my project for annexing professorships to the Durham canonries. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> writes to say that he "absolutely agrees with it, &amp; will help me in every possible way". The difficulties will arise mainly from the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> and Watkins<persName xml:id="590"></persName>, and from the clamour to apply the capitular funds to the increase of clerical stipends. I wrote to the Dean suggesting that I should have a conference with the Dean &amp; Chapter on the 18</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> inst. It may do good if I make them understand the situation in which they really stand. That the College can continue on its present lines appears to me wholly improbable. The endowment approaches &#x00A3;40,000 per annum, and may become yet greater. In the present necessity of the Church it is impossible to justify the application of that large sum to the up&#8211;keep of the Dean &amp; five canons in a petty town like Durham. If they were maintaining a Theological Faculty for the Northern Province there might be a sufficient case.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>