<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1178</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A propos of the slight regard in which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="508">Balfour's</persName></hi><hi> Government held </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir William <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName></hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3797">Buller</persName></hi><hi> told me that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Algie <persName xml:id="1710">Whitmore</persName></hi><hi> told him that, before the Parliamentary Secretaryship of the Education offices was offered to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Anson</hi><hi>, it had been offered to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Whitmore</hi><hi>, &amp; declined by him. Now </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Whitmore</hi><hi> had no claim to that office whatever: his entire service being of the conventional party kind.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I called successively on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName></hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2955">Carnegie</persName></hi><hi>, and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName></hi><hi>, and found all at home. Then I kept my appointment with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="277">Lord Portsmouth</persName></hi><hi> at noon. We talked for an hour not to much practical purpose, for he wanted to hear his own voice, and I wanted to avoid committing myself to any partnership of policy with </hi><hi rend="underline">him</hi><hi>! He suggested that a letter sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be drafted setting forth the gravity of upsetting the existing relations of Church &amp; State; that this should be signed by a number of laymen &amp; clergy, &amp; sent to the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>". I promised to "sound" some individuals, &amp; write to his Lordship again. </hi><hi rend="italic">From Lord P. I went to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss <persName xml:id="2712">Mundella</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; there lunched. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss <persName xml:id="1386">Haldane</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; the Bishop of <persName xml:id="602">Southwark</persName> were there. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">When the ladies had retired, Burge spoke to me about the prospect of my becoming a bishop</hi><hi rend="italic">. He said that the <persName xml:id="234">P.M.</persName> had sent for him to seek his counsel, &amp; had expressed his wish to make me a bp. "Well", I observed, "he has his opportunity". Burge said that he had warmly supported the notion, &amp; had subsequently repeated what he had said to the <persName xml:id="128">Abp.</persName>, who had expressed his agreement. He thought it probable that I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be offered Bristol. I said at once that in that case I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have to decline the offer, for it was quite impossible for me to hold a see so poorly endowed. There would not be enough to pay railway fares!</hi> <hi rend="bold">[17] </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burge</hi><hi rend="italic"> was, I think, a little disconcerted at this:</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> but I thought it important to emphasize the point that the only reason why I sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> take a bpk. would be to join him &amp; one or two more in an attempt, even at the eleventh hour, to save the National Church; &amp; that I could be of no possible service if I were embarrassed &amp; humiliated by financial worry</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> "If the opportunity comes to me", he replied, "I shall take care to let the P.M. know that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">you don't mind where you go, provided there's enough to live upon". On the whole I think it is just as well that this inexorable limit on my liberty of action should be known. Poverty is a very real disadvantage, &amp; most of all in the loss of mobility which it compels, &amp; in the inevitable misconceptions which it occasions. If I were to refuse a poor bpk. it w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be ascribed to a selfish love of ease &amp; money: instead of to the true cause, my desire not to get into a false position where I could render no service. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I returned to</hi><hi> Little Cloisters, picked up my bags, and took my departure for King's Cross. My journey to Durham was relieved by the conversation first of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="2423">Stobart</persName></hi><hi>, who was returning from a Conference with the Board of Agriculture, &amp; full of his subject, and then of two young soldiers who professed themselves to be Roman Catholics, &amp; entered on a courageous apologia for the Pope. We were held up outside Durham station for at least half an hour. The station&#8211;master explained that a car had been derailed, &amp; had held up traffic most inconveniently. I arrived at the Deanery about 12.15 midnight, and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">found no "Logic" to welcome me</hi><hi>. The weather which had been rainy &amp; tempestuous now developed into a regular hurricane.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
