<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1237</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of the Chapter, and afterwards wrote to Canon <persName xml:id="3666">Fowler</persName>, accepting his offer of &#x00A3;150 to found a prize for the choir boys, and to the Minister of Munitions, asking that materials might be purchased for patching up the heating apparatus of the Cathedral, which has finally broken down!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I wrote to the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C.</persName> giving him an account of the situation in Hereford.<note xml:id="375" n="1"></note> I stated my own position thus:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“That the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName> is a powerful organisation is unfortunately true: but we have hardly yet reached the point when the King's nominations must be approved by that body before they can count on being effective. For myself, I have to say this. As I was led by long &amp; anxious thought to the conclusion that it was my plain </hi><hi rend="underline">duty</hi><hi> to accept a place on the Episcopal Bench if it were offered me, so I am not likely to be deflected from my course by </hi><hi rend="underline">clamour</hi><hi>. Nor will I yield one inch to a Society with the principles &amp; methods of the E.C.U. It grieves me deeply that you sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have worry on my account, but in this matter, I am absolutely guiltless".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The "Church Times" has another virulent article headed "The Hereford Scandal", &amp; its columns overflow with vituperative letters. The "Guardian" comes down on the same side though with more decency of expression.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[91]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Lord <persName xml:id="586">Halifax's</persName> letter to the "Times" (Dec: 20</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>) is answered in the issue of today by three letters from the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>, <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName>. <persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName> with his <persName xml:id="937">wife</persName> and <persName xml:id="4356">daughter</persName> arrived, and also <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, to stay for Christmas.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
