<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1181</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Bitterly cold. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName> before breakfast. After Mattins I presided at a meeting of Chapter. Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName></hi> <hi rend="bold underline">brought to me the agreement about the advertisement hoarding, which I signed, &amp; paid a year's rent (&#x00A3;12) in advance</hi><hi rend="italic">. I finished reading "The Loom of Youth" by Alec <persName xml:id="4435">Waugh</persName>, who is said to be a lad of 17. The picture of an English Public School is very unpleasing, &amp; must be lop&#8211;sided: for it is almost uniformly dark. That the cult of athletics had proceeded to mischievous extremes was notorious, but that athleticism should be foul&#8211;mouthed, impure, deceitful, &amp; deeply irreligious was not so generally understood. I attended Evensong, and then, as the weather was hostile, abandoned my purpose of a walk, &amp; went into the Cathedral, where I spent an hour in acting as guide to a Belgian soldier &amp; his female companion. </hi><hi>After dinner I read the new volume of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="1125">Acton's</persName></hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Letters</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="973"></ref>, and looked into </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4241">Gwatkin's</persName></hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; State</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="959"></ref>. The latter has a clear note on that foolish tangle of the "Ornaments Rubrick", &amp;, of course, comes to the only conclusion which a candid historian can come to viz: </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that the vestments are totally illegal</hi><hi>. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur <persName xml:id="1916">Morgan</persName></hi><hi>. A letter from the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> crossed mine. His Lordship suggests an amendment of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor's</persName></hi><hi> motion; namely, "to insert the words 'to consider whether that Report is consistent with the terms of reference under which the Committee was appointed, &amp; generally to consider the recommendation thereof, and to prepare a Report". There is something to be said for this, but I suspect my own is better suited to carry the House.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
