<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1196</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters to my two brothers, <persName xml:id="3368">Frank</persName> and <persName xml:id="3128">Arthur</persName>, of whom the first is reported to be ill, and the last has just severed his connection with business. He would like to settle in England, but in the circumstances of the time, who would venture to do that?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Then I wrote a flatterous letter to the Mayor of Tynemouth<persName xml:id="4238"></persName>, applauding his vigorous (not to say also violent) address to his Council on the subject of Housing. As he has been elected to the Mayoralty for the 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> year in succession, I think it fairly safe to conclude that he must be something more than the windbag his rhetoric, standing alone, suggests!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Archdeacon preached at Mattins, but so inaudibly that I even in my stall could scarcely hear what he said. I celebrated the Holy Communion afterwards, where there were but three communicants beside myself.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The new Mayor<persName xml:id="3773"></persName> was followed by the longest "tail" I have yet seen on this occasion. There were no vacant places in the cathedral. I spoke in my <ref xml:id="995">sermon</ref> on the Housing question, which is now everywhere becoming urgent. Lady </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName></hi><hi> (dowager) came to the service with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady <persName xml:id="4208">Zetland</persName></hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wilson</hi><hi>, the artist who is making the processional cross. After tea I showed them the Cuthbert relics, which moved the said artist to great enthusiasm. He brought a picture of the processional Cross, which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Londonderry</hi><hi> is presenting to the Cathedral. I suggested diverse amendments, and particularly insisted on the exact adoption of the model of S. Cuthbert's Cross.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
