<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1167</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Nothing had been heard of "Logic" when we took our departure for Liverpool. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel <persName xml:id="3512">Darwin</persName></hi><hi> travelled with us as far as York, where we changed &amp; went on to Manchester, changing again &amp; then going on to Liverpool, where we were met by the <persName xml:id="477">Bishop</persName> &amp; a motor&#8211;car driven by his daughter. After tea, the Bishop took us to the new Cathedral, of which sufficient has been erected to give a fair impression of the completed structure. The original scheme has been considerably modified, &amp; the scale of the building considerably reduced, but it will be a lofty (116 feet) and noble pile.<note xml:id="329" n="1"></note> Professor </hi><persName xml:id="1619"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattison</hi></persName><hi> &amp; <persName xml:id="4369">his wife</persName> came to dinner. The Bishop was present at the great meeting in Liverpool this week, and says that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName></hi><hi> had a most enthusiastic reception, that he spoke with much deliberation so that every word told, and that his speech was most effective.<note xml:id="348" n="2"></note> A reference to the Bishop's <persName xml:id="4166">son</persName>, the VC who was killed at the Front, aroused great enthusiasm. There can be no question that his Lordship's family are a great assistance. The public credit of his brave sons and the activity of his attractive daughters strengthen the hold which his own exertions have secured on the city. </hi><hi rend="italic">The Bishop told me that the Archbishop's Committee did not go into the question of Franchise: that the members were quite free to take their own line when the question should be raised; and that, in point of fact, he was himself in favour of the Baptismal Franchise. All this is so much grist to my mill!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
