<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[92]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1240</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A mild day, but growing steadily colder as it advanced. I celebrated at 8 a.m. There was a fair muster of communicants, including <persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName> and <persName xml:id="4479" display="no">Ken</persName>. I did not preach at the Choral Eucharist, partly because of my cold, and partly because it seemed to me inexpedient to say anything publicly just yet. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> preached in my stead, prefacing his sermon by a few sentences about the processional cross which he formally accepted in my name &amp; in that of the Chapter. Lady <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName> and <persName xml:id="4220">her sister</persName> were present. I had some speech with them after the service. <persName xml:id="2811">May</persName> carried the Cross at both services, &amp; did so very well. (The young parsons take to ceremonial as ducklings to the water.)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Among my letters was a very kindly expressed letter from <persName xml:id="172">Bishop Browne</persName>, lately Bishop of Bristol, and several from Herefordshire clergy &amp; laity, begging me to attach no importance to the agitation stirred up by the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName></hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1936">Lacey</persName>, lately editor of the Ch. Times, writes to me a long &amp; rather flatterously expressed letter, the gist of which is to beg me to withdraw my acceptance of the bishoprick! But this is surely an impossible course. It would crown the factious activity of the E.C.U. with a resounding triumph, establish it firmly in its insolent pretension to be the mouthpiece of the Church of England, and destroy for ever my personal reputation for courage &amp; consistency. I cannot see how any self&#8211;respecting man in my position could do anything else but go steadily forward, &amp; "face the music". And that precisely is my determined course.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
