<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[50]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1207</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A most beautiful morning. The view of the Minster from my bedroom window was very fine. I walked in to the great church after breakfast to see the arrangement for holding the processional Cross, when it is "off duty". The verger insisted on showing me the Cuthbert Window, a noble work: &amp; then the great East Window, which has no rival. The nakedness of Durham by comparison with York is indeed afflicting. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I carried my motion expressing "regret" – the House would not add "surprise" by 38 to 16. The Prolocutor wished to avoid it, but I was obdurate, &amp; insisted. </hi><hi>But the matter was discussed for nearly 2 hours. I moved, and after debate, withdrew my motion about the Baptismal Franchise, &amp; then I left the House. I walked for an hour with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName></hi> on the bank of the river. <hi rend="italic">He told me that he was informed that there was an idea of moving </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="301">Burrows</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> from Truro to Hereford, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that the Chapter of Truro declared that nothing would induce them to elect me</hi><hi rend="italic">!!! Also, that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="234">Lloyd&#8211;George</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> had been pressed by the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of Canterbury</persName> to translate the <persName xml:id="2980">Bp. of Wakefield</persName> to Hereford, and that he had replied sharply that he would make the appointment himself. Whether there is any truth in these rumours, it is hard to know: but the delay in the appointment gives a great opportunity to the gossip&#8211;mongers, &amp; it is certainly the case that my name is being bandied about, a circumstance which must needs be discreditable to me though I am guiltless. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3571">George</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
