<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[31]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1190</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I returned to Durham by the 10.5 a.m. train from Manchester. It ran well to time, &amp; brought me to Durham shortly after 2 p.m. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Among my letters was one from </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName></hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, which was expressed rather cryptically, but which stated that the <persName xml:id="234">P.M.</persName> had asked him to go to </hi><hi rend="i bold">H</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">___</hi><hi rend="i bold">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">: that he was disinclined to go: that he had not finally refused: that if his going to H. would bring me to S. he would go: that he doubted whether I would accept S. He adds: "The plain straightforward thing is to offer you </hi><hi rend="i bold">H___d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, &amp; I cannot think what hinders it". I replied briefly at once that I would certainly not accept S. if it were offered me. There the tangle stands for the nonce, &amp; I suppose everything will be held up while the P.M. is in Italy. But it is evident that, so far as I am concerned, the issue is closed</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>At 4 p.m. I presided over a meeting of the Heads of City &amp; University who came to confer with the military. Col: Street, Captain Hoyle, &amp; Captain <persName xml:id="4105">Angus</persName> attended, &amp; expounded their demand. Accommodation was required at once for 60 Officers &amp; 1200 men. We discussed available buildings, and made some rough calculations, but everything is curiously inconvenient. My study is temporarily put out of action in order that the fire place may be repaired. In the present state of Durham to inaugurate repairs, however trivial, is to commit yourself to a doubtful fate: just now, of course, I am more than ever tied to my study, by reason of the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Review</hi><hi>" Article which </hi><hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> be completed during this month.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
