<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[28]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1188</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was horrified to read another announcement with a head&#8211;line in large type in the "Newcastle Journal" announcing that the Dean of Durham was about to be raised to the Episcopal Bench. It really is exasperating, &amp; cannot fail to do me harm with the Durham people, who resent my implied readiness to desert them. I left Durham at 10.29 a.m. and arrived in Manchester at 2.12 p.m. Here I managed to obtain a taxi, and get out to Birch Rectory in fair time for the meeting of the </hi><hi rend="italic">Anglican Fellowship which I addressed on the "Church &amp; State" Report. It was a very small company, but the discussion was intelligent and interesting. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4353">Parsons</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, who is one of the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Life &amp; Liberty</hi><hi rend="italic">" Committee, spoke with some liberality, &amp; seemed less conscious of the excessive episcopalianism of his colleagues than might have been expected. I had much talk with mine <persName xml:id="4107">host</persName>, who is interested in psychotherapy, and has himself made some successful essays in faith&#8211;healing. He gave me rather an interesting account of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss Maud <persName xml:id="3591">Royden's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> retirement from the L &amp; L Council. That lady appears to be moving out of the Anglo&#8211;Catholic system in which she was reared, &amp; now tends to regard Bishops as of the "male esse" of the Church! The <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> is thought to have received a heavy snub at the recent meeting of the Diocesan Conference: but his Lordship does not himself share this view, &amp;, in his Diocesan Magazine even expresses a measure of satisfaction at the conclusions reached in the Conference!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
