<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[36]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1194</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My history for this day is soon told. I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong in the Cathedral: finished the Sermon for next Sunday: went to the Town Hall, and witnessed the function of electing the new Mayor. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Alderman <persName xml:id="3773">Pattison</persName></hi><hi>, for the 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> time, becomes Mayor. After this function I walked in the civic procession to the Freemasons' Hall, where refreshments were served, &amp; speeches made. I replied to the toast of "The Bishop &amp; Clergy of all Denominations", and was foolish enough to make a brief speech. I was followed by the Papist, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="4144">Brown</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; a frantick sectary! I walked with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> for an hour. After dinner I read through "</hi><hi rend="underline">Walter Greenaway, Spy &amp; Hero</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="964"></ref>, which had been sent to me by the author, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Holmes</hi><hi>, the ex&#8211;Police court missionary. It claims to be a true narrative, but is as wonderful as any fiction.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The ranting of that sectary haunts me. He appears to be a Wesleyan minister, lately arrived in Durham from Hongkong. I think I had carried the whole company on to a high level, &amp; everything was dragged into the mud by his disgusting buffoonery! Probably I was a fool to have made the effort. The incident brought home to me a hard truth, which it is never wise to forget, that </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the practical hindrance to religious fellowship with Dissenters is but in little measure based on doctrine, but is rather an almost insurmountable repugnance in reverent &amp; cultivated minds to their coarseness, ignorance, and social suspiciousness</hi><hi rend="italic">. These can only be removed by education and the silent corrosives of time. Argument is irrelevant: &amp; spiritual appeals unintelligible.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
