<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[46]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1203</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A gloriously beautiful morning, the eastern sky all glowing with translucent opal, wonderful to look upon.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Judge attended service "in state" at Mattins. In the course of the proceedings, the High Sheriff "felt faint" and retired. This was mischance number one. Then </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="590">Watkins</persName></hi><hi> screamed &amp; ranted intolerably for a full half&#8211;hour about War&#8211;savings! This was mischance number two. I really felt humiliated at such a display in such a place &amp; on such an occasion. The High Sheriff, rather humbled by his earlier experience, brought the Judge &amp; his Marshall (a long man called Harris) to lunch. The Judge, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4395">Salter</persName></hi><hi>, is a conventional lawyer, who sate in the House of Commons, &amp; "takes himself" rather seriously. At Evensong Lady </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2819">Londonderry</persName></hi><hi> appeared with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName></hi><hi> &amp; two other guests (<persName xml:id="4207">Col:</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duncombe</hi><hi>). They came in to tea, whither I brought the Judge &amp; his Marshal after showing them round the cathedral. Divers other folks came in to tea, so that we had quite a party. I omitted to mention that there was a third mischance – </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName></hi><hi rend="bold underline"> slept when he should have "pokered" me to the Lectern</hi><hi>!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After all the company had departed, I felt strangely fatigue, quite as much indeed as if I had been doing good work! After dinner I read poetry to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Liddell</hi><persName xml:id="3721"></persName><hi>, choosing small pieces which are my own favourites, either for their own merit, or for their association with some person that I love. Beyond writing a long letter to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip le Mesurier</hi><hi><persName xml:id="3919"></persName> anent his craving for the Scarlet Woman, &amp; more briefly to the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName>, I have little to put to the credit side of this day's account!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
