<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[59]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1215</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I bade farewell to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="636">Ernest</persName></hi><hi> and <persName xml:id="2109" display="no">his sister</persName>, and went to Victoria, whence I travelled to Canterbury, and arrived in time for lunch. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="2162">Spooner</persName></hi><hi> was on the door&#8211;step, when my cab drove up. After lunch I walked with the <persName xml:id="383">Archdeacon</persName>, and enjoyed much pleasant conversation, and wonderful views of the Cathedral. I was interested in the conversation of a young officer, a <persName xml:id="4132">son</persName> of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="4133">Bickersteth</persName></hi><hi>, who was home from the Front. He expressed opinions which might not unfairly be described as </hi><hi rend="underline">pacificist</hi><hi> [sic].</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="1591">Lansdowne's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> letter in yesterday's issue of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Daily Telegraph</hi><hi rend="italic"> gives immense pleasure &amp; encouragement to the peace&#8211;mongers. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The fact that it had been declined by the </hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> adds to its importance</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is of course well&#8211;written, and lofty in conception, but after reading it carefully twice over, I am reluctantly constrained to conclude that it leads nowhere. For none of the inexorable and indispensable questions which bar the approaches to negociation are fairly faced, still less answered. In Germany's present situation, and in the present temper of the German people, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">there is no visible basis for any peace which would be tolerable or permanent</hi><hi rend="italic">. Thus the only effects of Lord L.'s well&#8211;intentioned effort must be to hearten the shirkers, stimulate the feeling of "war&#8211;weariness", increase the volume of pacificist [sic] sentiment, sow distrust between the Allies, encourage Germany, &amp; weaken Britain. This is truly a lamentable consequence of a high&#8211;minded and, in the circumstances, very courageous action.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
