<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1225</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> sent me a letter which he had received from his nephew, a boy at Sherborne School, whom he had asked to give an opinion on "The loom of youth", the author of which, Alec Waugh<persName xml:id="4435"></persName>, was also a Sherborne boy. The answer is hardly re&#8211;assuring:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“The Book is unfortunately </hi><hi rend="underline">absolutely true</hi><hi>. And the incidents are incidents which I know actually happened. I ought not to say it of my masters but if I did not I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be saying what I don't think, wh. amounts to a lie. </hi><hi rend="underline">The Masters are represented as they really are or rather as they appear to Boys who worry themselves at all about the sort of master who teaches them</hi><hi>. I think that Waugh in his book does not attack this School he does not intend to spite it, as some say he does; but </hi><hi rend="underline">it is an attempt to show to the world the rottenness of this Public School system under which he lived, and I live now</hi><hi> . . . I have been in this House long enough to realize that House Caps &amp; Athletics are set far above all moral feelings. Since the War things have altered, but not much. The school as a whole thinks much more of its caps and cups than of its chapel. It is all wrong, dreadfully wrong, &amp; when one has taken as much interest in one's House as I have, one realizes </hi><hi rend="underline">the awful rottenness of the whole system</hi><hi>. The language in the Book is mild compared with the language used at most Public Schools. It is an awful awakening for most people, &amp; most refuse to </hi><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi><hi> believe it, but it is true, &amp; I hope that the Public Schools system will be utterly changed after the War".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Cruickshank sent this letter to <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName>, &amp; invited his comments. He inclines to think that the picture in the "Loom of Youth" is not representative, &amp; offers evidence for thinking that Sherborne boys are extraordinarily addicted to the use of foul language:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“Language is of course a danger, &amp; the War has made it a great one, but I fancy most boys will not go farther than damn, &amp; certainly I have </hi><hi rend="underline">not yet</hi><hi> heard </hi><hi rend="underline">masters</hi><hi> (or boys for the matter of that) interlard their conversation with boys with "bloody". No – I don't believe that the majority of the Schools have deteriorated as the book sets forth".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>All this is rather surprising, when one contrasts the lavish eulogies commonly passed on the Public School system. <persName xml:id="460">Rutherford</persName> of West</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> could scarcely restrain the scorn with which he regarded the intellectual penury of the English Public School. He considered that the fineness &amp; strength of English character were sacrificed to a tradition of "good form", which in itself was not really very estimable. If neither the intellectual nor the moral influences of a public school are really wholesome, one is left in some inevitable &amp; not wholly unreasonable doubt as to the wholesomeness of the physical. Yet on all hands we are assured that the War has at least vindicated the Public School System. We are told that it succeeds uniquely in equipping boys with the power of leadership.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> went off by an early train to Consett to conduct examinations: he was followed quickly by Harold who went to London. Finally, the <persName xml:id="552">Headlams</persName><persName xml:id="553"></persName> left for Whorlton after breakfast. I kept indoors nursing a cold, and writing letters. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> came in to tell me that he had received the offer of the Deanery of Gloucester. He is evidently very pleased to get preferment. It is curious that quite a Durham "corner" will have been formed in the West of England. The Bishops of <persName xml:id="3831">Lichfield</persName>, <persName xml:id="2533">Bristol</persName> and Hereford, &amp; the Deans of <persName xml:id="1814">Worcester</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="757">Gloucester</persName> will all be old Dunelmians (including in the term men who have held office in the Palatine Bishoprick).</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening paper brought the good news that Jerusalem has surrendered to General <persName xml:id="4103">Allenby</persName>. This event will have considerable effect. With Mecca in successful revolt: &amp; both Baghdad and Jerusalem in British hands the Turks can hardly avoid the sense of defeat.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Against this must be set the disaster at Halifax, of which the full gravity is disclosed by the later telegrams. It is reported that about 2000 have been killed, and 3000 wounded, while the town itself is half&#8211;destroyed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A revolution is announced in Portugal, and a republic in Finland. The Russian Bolsheviks are about to repudiate the Russian national debt, and have coerced the Roumanians into entering with them into an armistice with Germany. Japanese troops have landed in Vladivostock [sic] to maintain order. The vast Russian Empire is quickly breaking up into its constituent factors: and the peace of Asia is threatened by the events compelled by the conflict in Europe.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
