<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1228</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My cold is worse than ever. Beyond going to Evensong, I kept the house. The newspapers contain the formal announcement of my appointment as Bishop of Hereford. Letters, telegrams, and notes came in at intervals during the day. If I may believe my colleagues, they will regret my departure. The Precentor &amp; <persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> sent me letters expressed with affectionate ardour, and the latter assures me that "the boys are all very grieved at my approaching departure". <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> writes pleasantly:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“We all have to thank you, &amp; especially your colleagues have to thank you, for five years of generous rule and friendship".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> writes:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to express my thanks to you for all your help &amp; kindness – you can hardly realize what an assistance it is to a Chapter official to have a Dean who is a real head of community, to whom one can always turn for direction &amp; advice.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> (aetatis suae [the age of] 98) writes thus:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Dean, Pray allow me to express my best wishes on your appointment to the bishoprick of Hereford. Your leaving the Cathedral will be a great loss to myself &amp; many others. It is something however to know that in a larger sphere of influence you will be able to carry on more efficiently the good work with which you have been so long associated.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very faithfully, W. Greenwell</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My physical distress grew upon me as the day wore on. I went to Evensong, &amp; enjoyed the anthem (Spohr) beautifully sung by Kaye. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went out to an entertainment at <orgName xml:id="230">S. Hild's</orgName>, &amp; I languished miserably by my study fire.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
