<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[60]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1216</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins in the cathedral. The service was calming &amp; consolatory, matching my mood of vague &amp; restless expectancy very generously. When I came out, there was a drizzling rain, &amp; a look of menace in the sky. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read through carefully the Bishop of <persName xml:id="1727">Chester's</persName> letter, &amp; wrote an acknowledgment (copy on next page). Also I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gilbert</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hussey</hi><hi> came to lunch, a pleasant lady enough. Later, I walked with the <persName xml:id="383">Archdeacon</persName>, and, the talk inclining that way, </hi><hi rend="italic">spoke of my own rather odd career. He inclined to agree with what </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rutherford<persName xml:id="460"></persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> used to say, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that my not having been to a public school had preserved my individuality</hi><hi rend="italic">. This may, or may not, be an advantage. The certain loss is plain enough. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop <persName xml:id="667">Walsh</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> and his niece came to tea. I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">. To dinner came three officers, rather unusual in aspect and type, but all intelligent &amp; interesting.</hi><hi> One of them, who had served in the Balkans, spoke with contempt of the Serbians, &amp; with loathing of the Armenians. He said that the Fire in Salonika had done no damage to the British, &amp; that the city was no great loss. He did not seem to appreciate the historical &amp; archaeological interest of the great church of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Demetrius.<note xml:id="354" n="1"></note> After dinner we had a lively discussion about the ethics of the Stock Exchange: &amp; when we went into the drawing&#8211;room, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2161">Ruth</persName></hi><hi> played divinely. </hi><hi rend="italic">She is certainly one of the most loveable and interesting women it has ever been my fortune to meet.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">To the Lord Bishop of Chester</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">December 1</hi><hi rend="i sup u">st</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear Lord Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I am very much obliged to you for letting me see the confidential representation wh. you have made to the Bishops of the Northern Province, &amp; which (if you will allow me to say so) is both weighty &amp; effective. More than either, I hold it to be true. Your concluding paragraph presses much into a small space. I think the mischief has gone too far for remedy, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that the Church of England can now only be made morally respectable by disruption</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The root objection to the "autonomy" designed in the Report of the Abps' C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">tee</hi><hi rend="italic"> is, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that it will not merely precipitate Disestablishment (which, indeed, is its proper presupposition), but also leave the "plant" of the disestablished Church securely in the hands of the sacerdotalist party</hi><hi rend="italic">. This must be the result, &amp; I believe was the design, of the policy of "hustle" to wh. the Authors of the Report are committed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I think the discussions &amp; decision of the <orgName xml:id="57">R.C.C.</orgName> were a rebuke to that policy, &amp; called a halt. The large, free C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">tee</hi><hi rend="italic"> appointed by the <persName xml:id="128">Abps.</persName><persName xml:id="130"></persName> to consider the whole subject was far indeed from what Lord <persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor</persName> asked for: &amp;, in point of fact, I voted for it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Again thanking you, I am, my dear Lord Bishop, ever sincerely yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. Hensley Henson </hi>
         </p>
</div><p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>