<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1222</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Among my letters is one from the Editor of the Y. P.<persName xml:id="1460"></persName>, where curiosity appears to not have been satisfied by my telegram of yesterday! He encloses a cutting from the "Westminster Gazette" (which surely ought to be well&#8211;informed!) stating that "the appointment of Dean Hensley Henson, of Durham, as Bishop of Hereford" was causing "some heart&#8211;burning in Wales", where, apparently, "two Welsh ecclesiastics were favourites for the appointment, &amp; there were widespread hopes among ardent Welsh nationalists that another see w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be added to those filled by Welshmen"!! So the plot thickens and I am more mystified and humiliated than ever. Next came a telegram from <persName xml:id="1812">Angel Colenso</persName> addressed to the "Bishop&#8211;designate of Hereford", and conveying "affectionate congratulations": and then the News Editor of the Evening Standard more cautiously asking me to "confirm or deny" the report of my appointment!!! I shall soon be ashamed to show my face in the streets. The afternoon post brought an ecstatically worded letter of congratulations from <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, to whom D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="4481">Beauchamp</persName> (who ought to have known better) had telephoned that precious paragraph in the "Westminster"! I went out to Sherburn hospital, &amp; attended a meeting of the House Committee. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> picked me up there, &amp; we walked back over the fields. Then <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName> arrived, obviously sniffing for information, but I would not speak on the subject, and he soon went off! </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">All this nonsensical confusion seems almost criminal at a time when the fate of civilization is in jeopardy, and the flower of England is withering daily on the battle&#8211;fields of Europe</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
