<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[64]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1218</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A bright but bitterly cold morning. I bade an affectionate farewell to <persName xml:id="2161">Ruth</persName> &amp; the <persName xml:id="383">Archdeacon</persName> (M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi><persName xml:id="2162">Spooner</persName> does not appear at breakfast), and went off to the station. On the platform were the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> &amp; a party. Beyond exchanging greetings, I had no talk with him. On arriving in London, I went directly to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, where I lunched. A telegram from the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> arrived while I was in the dining room talking to Athelstan <persName xml:id="213">Riley</persName>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then I went to Euston, &amp; travelled to Manchester</hi><hi>. On the way I had much talk with two officers on religious matters. One of them guessed my name from the initials on my bag! I drove out to Bishopscourt, and arrived about 7.30 p.m. The Bishop of Manchester &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3173">Knox</persName> had gone to an S.P.G. meeting.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Riley told me that when he rose to make his speech in the R.C.C, he said to <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>, beside whom he was sitting, "I mean to chaff the bishops". When he returned to his seat, he said, "I hope you don't think I was too hard on you". To which the Bishop of Oxford replied with severity, "I detest injustice"!!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Two young ladies in khaki are here on a recruiting mission. One of them is the <persName xml:id="4343">daughter</persName> of <persName xml:id="4253">Canon Harford</persName> of Mossley Hill. I found her a frank and pleasant girl, keen on her work and distinctly humourous. There is also an <persName xml:id="4195">Archdeacon</persName>, from Hampstead, I think, who has been speaking at the S.P.G. meeting. Quite pleasant but wholly conventional. </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
