<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1208</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I paid my reckoning, &amp; took my departure for Leeds after breakfast. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Florence Richardson</hi><hi>, the house&#8211;maid from Tudhoe, bade me a friendly farewell. I arrived in Leeds shortly after 10 a.m., &amp;, after leaving my bags at the Queen's Hotel, walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Club</orgName> in Albion Place, and there read the papers until it was time for me to preach at Holy Trinity. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold Wilkinson</hi><hi>, an old Durham choirboy, played the organ. He hung about with an appropriating affection which was almost touching. Another old choir boy, whose name escapes me, hailed me as I entered the church. There was a considerable congregation, in which I was pleased to observe a number of men. The Dissenting ministers of Leeds turned up in force. After the service I lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4122">Barran</persName></hi><hi> at the Hotel. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady <persName xml:id="2070" display="no">Barran</persName></hi><hi> was there, &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir <persName xml:id="2069">John</persName></hi><hi> appeared at the close of the meal. I spent the afternoon pleasantly enough with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Barran</hi><hi>. First, we visited the ruins of Kirkstall Abbey<placeName xml:id="80"></placeName>: then we went to the Family Factory, where some 2000 girls &amp; women are engaged in making clothing mostly for the army. I inquired how many persons were actually involved in making a soldier's coat, &amp; I was told that not less than 22 had a hand in the work. From the factory we went to the "Outlook Club", and had tea. The secretary seemed an intelligent &amp; pleasant person. From the girls' Club we went to the Club in Albion Square, and there I had half an hour's quiet before dining with the Lord Mayor, the Vicar of Leeds, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4211"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dykes</hi></persName><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir John Barran</hi><hi>, and another. Then I gave my lecture to an audience of about 200 in the Church Institute.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
