<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1212</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>O God, Thou knowest the path wherein I walk, and whereto it leads. Have pity on my blindness, and guide my steps therein. Grant that I may not go astray from the way of Thy Commandments. Into Thy Hands I desire to commit myself. Show Thou me the Way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee. Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName> met in the </hi><hi rend="underline">Hoare Memorial Hall</hi><hi> at 11 a.m. in larger numbers than I had anticipated. The <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> made a half&#8211;apologetic speech at the opening of the proceedings, &amp; then ruled that anybody might speak on anything! The result was an orgy of talk, which had no very clear relevance to anything. Out of the welter of speeches, the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester's</persName> stood out as far &amp; away the best. I <ref xml:id="993">spoke</ref> in the afternoon, &amp; made a very poor speech, saying little of what I meant to say, &amp; much that I had not meant to say, &amp; had better not have said.<note xml:id="355" n="1"></note> </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The <persName xml:id="1123">Bishop of Southampton</persName> asked me whether I was Bishop of H. &amp; said that he had it on the authority of a Cabinet Minister that I was. The Bishop of <persName xml:id="2146">S. David's</persName> said that it was widely believed in Wales that I was coming as Bishop to H. <persName xml:id="636">Ernest</persName> tells me that </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">he</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> is to be the new Bishop in the belief of Bham! So the foolish gossip proceeds, &amp; is most humiliating to everybody. The <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol</persName> arrived just before dinner. He told me that H. had been offered to him, &amp; that he had declined it. It was offered to <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName>, &amp; declined by him. So now it is still open: &amp;, if rumour be true, it lies between Ernest and me</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
