<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[8]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">S. Luke's Day, Thursday, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1172</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A brilliant autumn morning. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> and I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., &amp; I celebrated the Holy Communion. In the bright sunlight the great Church looked very glorious. I attended Mattins, &amp; then set myself to the task of cutting down &amp; casting into suitable form </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicey's</hi><hi> admirable but somewhat discursive &amp; verbose appreciation of the Warden as a law&#8211;teacher &amp; writer. The Mayor&#8211;elect, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><persName xml:id="3773"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Pattison</hi></persName><hi>, called to arrange for the service on "Mayor's Sunday", November 11</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. I promised to preach to the City Fathers. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><persName xml:id="3635"><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Bell</hi></persName><hi> came to lunch. I attended Evensong: and afterwards attended a meeting of the University Lodge, where (with elaborate ceremonial &amp; a plethora of grandiloquent hortation) the officers for the ensuing year were admitted to office. I was appointed Senior Warden. </hi><hi rend="italic">The afternoon post brought a letter from the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C.</persName>, not marked 'private', &amp;, I think, intended for me to publish. After dinner I read aloud to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4243">Ella Hadow's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> brilliant &amp; learned paper on "</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Beethoven</hi><hi rend="italic">", read before the British Academy; and then I wrote &amp; thanked him for it. </hi><hi>I also wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">George <persName xml:id="3571">Nimmins</persName></hi><hi>, addressing the letter to Kobe, Japan: and to an unknown female who had written to me for "spiritual counsel". </hi><hi rend="italic">These appeals are very embarrassing, not because one is reluctant to give any help one may have it in one's power to give, but because one never has any better knowledge of the situation than the appellant himself, (or more commonly, herself) chooses to give. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">That</hi><hi rend="italic"> is hardly ever sufficient to enable a trustworthy diagnosis of the trouble to be made.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
