<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[93]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1241</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received from Archdeacon <persName xml:id="4450">Winnington&#8211;Ingram</persName> a letter expressed in a reasonable &amp; friendly spirit. To this I replied as follows:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>My dear Archdeacon,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am much obliged to you for your letter, of which I appreciate fully both the kindness and the propriety.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You will readily understand that it is impossible for me to make any kind of new statement on questions of Christian doctrine in deference to an agitation conceived in the spirit and carried on by the methods of the <orgName xml:id="20">English Church Union</orgName>; but my record is public property, &amp; I am glad to assist anyone to read it rightly.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The chill from which I have been suffering still hangs about me, &amp; it was thought inadvisable for me to preach yesterday. Being confined to the house, I employed myself in tracing the references which, presumably, were in the mind of the writer of the article in the "Hereford Times" to which you refer. I am confident that you, &amp; every fair&#8211;minded man, will think that the alleged quotation is very unfairly pieced together, &amp; conveys a very misleading impression.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In order that you may judge for yourself, I have just typed out the whole passage without alteration, &amp; enclose it for your perusal. I will only add that the whole plan of the volume "The Liberty of Prophesying"<ref xml:id="86"></ref> is to discuss the "just limits &amp; temper" of that liberty "considered with reference to the circumstances </hi><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi><hi> of the modern church".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have also taken leave to send you a little volume<ref xml:id="87"></ref> of sermons which was published a year after I left Westminster five years ago, &amp; which contains the discourse, "The Notes of my Ministry", in which I endeavoured to sum up the position which I had taken up. I have re&#8211;read it now, &amp; do not feel disposed to alter anything.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>With many thanks for your goodwill, I am, my dear Archdeacon,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>P.S. I should like to add a sentence to emphasize my deep appreciation of the kindness &amp; candour which find expression in your letter, &amp; which are very welcome to me at this rather difficult juncture.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The choirboys came to the Deanery at 6 p.m. and sang carols in the drawing room. <persName xml:id="2817">Lady Londonderry</persName> &amp; her sister were present, <persName xml:id="3553">Meade Falkner</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3554">his wife</persName>, &amp; some others, including <persName xml:id="4479" display="no">Ken</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName>. The presence of those two dear &amp; true men gave me great pleasure. After dinner we sate in my study, and killed time with a foolish card game until we went to bed. Frank &amp; I croaked dolefully over the prospect of a doubled income&#8211;tax, and the general gloom in which all the horizon of life, public &amp; private, is now invested.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
