<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1213</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2533">Bishop Nickson</persName></hi><hi> &amp; I walked in the Park after breakfast. He spoke much of the appointment to Hereford, and said that he believed it would be offered to me. The Palace was not, he thought, excessively large, &amp; the Dilapidation Certificate held good to 1920. There was a pleasant garden. It seemed sufficiently absurd to talk about these things, when the probability is that I shall never be asked to go there at all! The <orgName xml:id="57">R.C.C.</orgName> resumed its discussion. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Proceedings began with a speech by the Bishop of <persName xml:id="105">Winchester</persName>, who attacked both me &amp; the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> with some vigour</hi><hi>. But, of course, I had no opportunity to reply. The <persName xml:id="720">Bishop of Carlisle</persName> made a speech which bored the House exceedingly: &amp; the Bishop of <persName xml:id="2462">Chelmsford</persName> was not much better. Both canted horribly. At the end, after </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh <persName xml:id="314">Cecil's</persName></hi><hi> variation of my amendment had been rejected, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">the motion for a new Committee was adopted, but it was made clear that this Committee was quite distinct from that named in the Report: that its reference was wide: that its members were free: &amp; that it could report when it would</hi><hi>.<note xml:id="424" n="1"></note> I lunched with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName></hi><hi>: walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaenum</orgName>: &amp; then went into the City, &amp; called on </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName></hi><hi>. I could not persuade him to write the Letter on the Church, which </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="277">Lord Portsmouth</persName></hi><hi> suggested. He is evidently very pleased with his experiences in Scotland, where he has been delivering the Gifford Lectures. The unseasonable heat of the weather makes one feel strangely languorous &amp; feeble. I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> from the Club.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
