<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1198</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day has been wasted in fruitless attempts to write the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Article</hi><hi>". I cannot do it: why, I know not, but I have no ideas, and no words! I attended Mattins &amp; Evensong. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The Minister<persName xml:id="4130"></persName> of Carrs Lane Church, Birmingham, writes to accept my suggestion of April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> as the date on which I should preach there. He has "a firm conviction" that my doing so "would further the cause of Christian fellowship". So I am committed to another adventure </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">in partibus schismaticorum [schismatic parts]</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName></hi><hi> sends me a cutting from the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Daily News</hi><hi>" scoffing at some statement which the <persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName> is reported to have made in S. Martin's, Trafalgar Square, where he gave an address on Religion in Public schools. His Lordship, it is alleged, "hoped that in the attempt to extend the Divorce Act their public school boys w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> stand firm in maintaining the Christian law of marriage". It is quite in </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ingram's</hi><hi> manner to perpetrate absurdities of that kind.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Rev. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Reginald W. T. <persName xml:id="4361">Petch</persName></hi><hi> writes to suggest as the title of the address, which I have promised to give in Manchester on December 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, "</hi><hi rend="underline">Limits of Autonomy in the Church of England</hi><hi>", and adds the Bishop's alternative proposal, "</hi><hi rend="underline">A National Church: its Rights &amp; Responsibilities</hi><hi>". Neither the one subject, nor the other pleases me. What would please me best, and probably be most useful, would be a direct attack on the Report of the Archbishops' Committee, but this probably would give offence in some quarters. If only I were free from the "Life" and the "Article"! </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
