<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1197</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName></hi><hi> brought me from the Library a volume containing divers papers by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="4144">Brown</persName></hi><hi>, the local papist, in which he strives to prove that the body of the Blessed Cuthbert was not buried on the site of his shrine, but privily conveyed away by the monks in 1537, that another body was substituted for the saint's, &amp; that this was found in 1827, and mistakenly identified by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="4378">Raine</persName></hi><hi> as S. Cuthbert's. The argument is ingenious &amp; up to a point plausible, but </hi><hi rend="bold underline">it is almost entirely hypothetical</hi><hi>. It breaks down before (&#x3B1;) the positive facts, and (&#x3B2;) the behaviour of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop <persName xml:id="4285">Tunstall</persName></hi><hi>, and (3) the late emergence of the Benedictine tradition. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> and I walked to Kepier, which I had never before visited.<placeName xml:id="79"></placeName> There is a fine ruined gateway and considerable remains of buildings. The farmer's wife showed us a weather&#8211;worn crucifix builded into the wall, and a fine 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century window which had recently been opened out. In the adjacent field a considerable number of men and lads were engaged in the barbarous sport &#8211; rabbit&#8211;coursing. We walked home by the river, and were rewarded by ravishing views of the Cathedral.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName></hi><hi> for her Birthday, and sent in to the Secretary of the Council the amendment to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor's</persName></hi><hi> Resolution which I propose to move on Nov 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> if I get the chance. I named </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName></hi><hi> as the seconder. It will, perhaps, be good for that admirably cautious ecclesiastic to be compelled to declare himself publically for once!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
