<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[44]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1201</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I succeeded in finishing the </hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Article</hi><hi>, but was nowise satisfied with it. However I read most of it to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName></hi><hi>, &amp; he seemed to approve of it, so it will have to serve. I attended Mattins, &amp; attended a meeting of the Economic Committee in the dining room, where we worked at the Report. The Socialist fanatick, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Gobat</hi><hi>, will probably add some note of his own. This will at least indicate that he stands by himself. After the meeting </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi><hi> &amp; I walked for an hour. The sunset was amazingly beautiful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My letters today were of no great interest. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="383">Spooner</persName></hi><hi>, the Archdeacon of that ilk writes from Lambeth Palace, where he was attending a meeting of Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans, to ask me to visit him at Canterbury, when I come south for the R.C.C meeting. He makes no reference to the Hereford appointment, from which I conclude that it has been made, &amp; that he doesn't feel free to mention the fact. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName></hi><hi> writes to say that he has been moved into the Flanders mud and expects shortly to be in action. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="2818">Londonderry</persName></hi><hi> writes pleasantly in response to a letter which I sent to him expressing my satisfaction at his gift of Pelaw Wood to the City</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">" contains a letter from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="4024">Northcliffe</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> addressed to the <persName xml:id="234">Prime Minister</persName>, &amp; declining the offer of the Air Ministry. This letter is written in the worst possible spirit, &amp; might seem deliberately calculated to make mischief with America. The vulgarity and vanity of the writer are, however, now so widely known, that his utterances are always subject to a heavy discount. If the Americans are as shrewd as their reputation suggests, they will see through him</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
