<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[77]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1227</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I had so heavy a cold that work was difficult. However I succeeded in writing to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName> on the subject of the choice of my successor here. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">My confidence in the suitableness of <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName> had been shaken by the evident repugnance of <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> to the notion of his becoming the new Dean</hi><hi>. "You are only echoing <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>" I said: and he rejoined immediately. "No: I have had experience of working with Headlam myself: &amp; I think he's impossible". Yet: the theological faculty of King's College have unanimously asked Headlam to return to his former position as their Dean: &amp;, if I may judge from <persName xml:id="923">Newsom</persName>, <persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName>, <persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, and <persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName>, who all worked under him in London, his colleagues become attached to him. So I </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> put in a word for him in my letter to the Archbishop.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I journeyed to Tynemouth, and, in the Methodist chapel hard by the Town Hall I addressed a meeting on "Housing". The roads were so dark that I could never have found my way to the place of meeting had not a munition&#8211;maiden, whose name she told me was Jessie Green, given me her arm, &amp; steered me. She works from 7.30 a.m to 5 p.m, with 1½ hours off for meals, and earns &#x00A3;1 weekly. The Mayor of <persName xml:id="4238">Tynemouth</persName> had brought together some folk to meet me, among whom was <persName xml:id="4476" display="no">Warshauer</persName>, whom I recall as prominent in the now&#8211;defunct "New Theology" movement. The minister of the Chapel told me that he was an Ilford boy, &amp; had taken from my preaching in Ilford his first serious impressions of religion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[78]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Archbishop of Canterbury</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>December 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Lord Archbishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Last Saturday I received from the <persName xml:id="234">P.M.</persName> the proposal that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> submit my name to the King for the appointment to the bpk. of Hereford: &amp; in consenting thereto I used these words wh. will serve to express to you my motive:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>It has for some while been apparent to me that, if a place on the Episcopal Bench were offered to me, I c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not rightly refuse it in view of the difficult &amp; embarrassing circumstances in wh. the C. of E. now stands: &amp;, therefore, though my five years residence in Durham has been happy &amp; not inactive, &amp; though my retirement from my present position will cause me very real pain &amp; regret, I hold it plain that I ought to consent to the proposal wh. you have been good enough to make to me.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I supposed that this correspondence was severely private, but it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> appear that somebody in Downing St. communicates with the Press. Since the "Times" has an announcement on its front page, &amp; the matter seems to be common property, I make no scruple of writing to your Grace, &amp; telling you where I stand.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This will give me an opportunity of saying a few things about this Deanery, wh. I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to say, &amp; wh. possibly it might be worth saying.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There are aspects of my present position, wh. are not altogether </hi><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi><hi> easy to correlate. On the one hand, the Dean of Durham is the most prominent ecclesiastic next to the Bishop, &amp; his connexion with the University in the past had given him a less professionally clerical character than is usual. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Perhaps the weakness of the present Bishop emphasizes the normal prominence of the Dean</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>It is the fact that a great door of influence on the general life of this part of England is open to any Dean of Durham who can win the confidence, &amp; touch the imagination of the people.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>On the other hand, the Dean ought to be able to guide &amp; develope this great foundation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Grammar School is of primary importance, &amp; it w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be the better for having in the Head of its Governing Body a man who had personal knowledge of the working of a great public school, &amp; was himself a good scholar</hi><hi>. In no respects have I been less really efficient than in these. As it happens, I did the school a great service by insisting on, and carrying through, the building of the new House; but now my inefficiency is growingly apparent to myself. I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to see in my successor a man who w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be zealous for the School, &amp; able to serve it. Durham ought to be the Uppingham of the North. Perhaps even more important is the new Dean's competence to organize here a great centre of clerical training. Now that the theological degrees are open to Nonconformists, there is a good prospect of many candidates for their ministries coming to Durham.<note xml:id="302" n="1"></note> In any re&#8211;arrangement of capitular revenues, the endowments of Durham ought to go towards the establishment of a great theological school. If the Dean &amp; two or more canonries were tied to professorships, we should have in Durham an educational equipment not inferior to Ch. Ch. Oxford. </hi><hi rend="bold">[80] </hi><hi>The patronage of the professorships sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be transferred to the Crown, in order to secure popular confidence. We might compensate the Bishop by bringing </hi><hi rend="underline">both</hi><hi> the Archdeacons into the Chapter. These he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi>, of course, continue to nominate. This is a far cry: but near at hand is the reconstruction of the University in Durham after the War: &amp; in this process a competent Dean might be the dominant factor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is then, I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> desire to press on your Grace, really important that, in the selection of my successor, these considerations sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have weight. It w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be very unfortunate, indeed, if a man came here who c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> neither win the attention of the people, nor guide the development of the institution. If a choice bet: the two sets of qualities must be made, then, in my judgement, the last is more really important than the first.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I do not know whether it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be seemly or serviceable to mention names, &amp; I will not do more than venture a few comments on one man who will certainly come into the minds of many people here as a possible Dean of Durham. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Headlam does seem to me to have many of the requisite qualities</hi><hi>. He w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> probably be eager to make Durham a centre of clerical training: &amp; he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> bring to the attempt a very considerable experience. I incline to think that his brusqueness (not to use a harsher word) w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> probably be mitigated by his tenure of the office: &amp; with D</hi><hi rend="superscript">r</hi><hi> Gee's departure, much of the repugnance to him locally w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi>, perhaps, disappear. Personally I cannot think of any one whom I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> rather see appointed as my successor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Now, having liberated my soul, I must ask forgiveness for </hi><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi><hi> inflicting so much on your Grace. Nor w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> I have done so: but your kindness encourages me to think that you will not resent the liberty I have taken.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>For myself, I am really very unhappy at leaving Durham, and, though I cannot doubt that I ought to go to Hereford, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I shrink from the Episcopate with a kind of terror. Perhaps, at the last moment, His Majesty may object, or something will "turn up" to save me from myself</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, my dear Lord Archbishop, Yours sincerely &amp; dutifully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>My "post" consisted almost entirely of congratulatory letters inspired by the little paragraph in yesterday's "Times". Among these I was glad to receive those from:</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3581">The Master of the Temple</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="1820">Canon Charles</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Knight (<persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName>)</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="1319" display="no">Lord Reay</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>T.A. <persName xml:id="1936">Lacey</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3797">Dunbar&#8211;Buller</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName></hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>The Mayor of <persName xml:id="4238">Tynemouth</persName> expressed his regret at my departure in very kind words, which seemed to have the ring of sincerity. "You must come back again", he said. <persName xml:id="3833">Blackitt</persName> said the same yesterday, intimating his desire to poison our present saintly Bishop in order to hasten the day!!! Well, it is pleasant to be assured that my neighbours have a kindly feeling towards me. Five years ought to give them materials for forming a judgment.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
