<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1209</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the course of my sermon yesterday I referred to the activity of the Leeds industries during the war, &amp; the wealth which must needs be coming to many of the citizens. I said that every man, thus suddenly enriched, should consider in the court of his own conscience whether he ought not apply the ugly term "profiteer" to himself: &amp; I suggested that war&#8211;profits should be made a sacred fund for the Nation's help. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4121">Barran</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> (whom I assume to be the uncle of <persName xml:id="2069">Sir John</persName>) was evidently somewhat discomposed by these words, &amp; afterwards was at great pains to explain to me that the true "profiteers" were the artisans: that most "war&#8211;profits" were only nominally such: &amp; that the nation would gain by the money being in the hands of the so&#8211;called "profiteers". I observed that it must needs give cause for reflection that there should be so much money available for selfish purposes. There has not been so brisk a market for artistic curiosities &amp; landed property for many a long year. This must needs indicate that the War is enabling many people to become purchasers now who hitherto have been unable to come into that category. The sensitiveness of this excellent manufacturer assured me that not only was he making money out of the War, but also that his conscience had been disturbed by my words. I fear that a vast proportion of modern philanthropy is but hush&#8211;money to the private conscience, like the charity which </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Robin Hood</hi><hi rend="italic"> bestowed out of the gains made by his robbing of travellers. The thriftlessness of the artisan provides a soft cushion to break the Fall of the Employer from his clearly perceived standard of obligation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A very boisterous night led in a wet day. I spent the morning in my room writing letters. After lunch I walked with mine host in a wind so violent that one had some difficulty in keeping steadily on. On my return I read a preposterous book <ref xml:id="965">"A secret service Woman"</ref> by Henri de Halsalle, one of the numerous writers who are "exploiting" the present rage with Germans in the interest of their own pockets.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
