<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[42]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1199</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day was devoted to the </hi><hi rend="underline">Edinburgh Article</hi><hi>, with which I made some progress as far as quantity goes, but the quality was lamentable. However such as it is, it must serve, for I can do nothing better. I did not attend service in the Cathedral, but walked for an hour in the afternoon. I dined with the High Sheriff at the <orgName xml:id="89">Club</orgName>. There were present among others a barrister named </hi><persName xml:id="4335"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Mortimer</hi></persName><hi>, who said that he remembered me at Oxford, but I had no recollection of him. He is a sidesman or churchwarden (I forget which) in Holy Trinity, Chelsea. I asked how </hi><persName xml:id="5691"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dudden</hi></persName><hi> was progressing, and he said that the congregations were as large as ever but that there was a great drop in subscriptions. He held D. to be a considerable preacher, but afflicted with a disagreeable voice, which made listening difficult. There seemed a general opinion that the <persName xml:id="234">P.M.</persName> had made an indefensible speech at Paris<note xml:id="352" n="1"></note>: that he may have been "riding for a fall": that it was extremely unfortunate that he should have spoken so rashly at this juncture. I observe that there is still an extremely violent prejudice against </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="215">Asquith</persName></hi><hi>, which seems to me unfounded and unfair. </hi><persName xml:id="3833"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Blackitt</hi></persName><hi> said that he could remember the time when there was no screen in the Cathedral: that he thought the present screen an abomination: that, in his youth, there was a custom of certain laymen sitting in the stalls. The stars were most brilliant, &amp; distributed sufficient light to make me practically independent of the electric torch with which I had armed myself. I was back in the Deanery by 10.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
