<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[87]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1235</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins in the cathedral, and afterwards looked at some of the leading features of the church. It is certainly far richer in historical monuments than Durham, although itself an altogether meaner fabric. Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I went to the Palace which is an inconvenient building, at once pretentious in appearance and very pinched in accommodation. The Deanery at Durham is far more noble and dignified. The garden, however, is pleasant and adequate. Canon <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName> and his wife<persName xml:id="4119"></persName> came to lunch. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He told me that the cong&#x00E9; d'&#x00E9;lire would come before the greater chapter, &amp; obviously feared the result</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><note xml:id="358" n="1"></note> <hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne Wilson</persName> [Willson], the Rural Dean of Hereford, called, and had some speech with me. He said the opposition was really gathered up in a few men, of whom the ringleader was M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4190">Hermitage Day</persName>, said to be the Editor of the "Church Times", who has within the last few years established himself at Hereford. He has a valuable lieutenant in the Editor of the leading local newspaper, the "Hereford Times", who is the Chairman of the local branch of the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName> </hi><hi rend="bold underline">These people are getting up a public meeting of protest in the Town Hall on January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>. Archdeacon <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName> called later, &amp; confirms all this. He says that one of the agitators admitted to him that he himself had no liking for the business, but that the central authority of E.C.U. insisted that it should go on. Lilley also was evidently perturbed, and by no means easy in his mind as to the probable course of events.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4471" display="no">Bateman</persName>, the late bishop's butler, came to see me. He has served at the Palace since the time of Bishop Atlay<persName xml:id="4110"></persName>, &amp; is reported to be "indispensable". I told him that, if I </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> come here as bishop, I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> continue him in his butlership at the same payment (&#x00A3;96 per. ann.). Also I said as much to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4345">Norcock</persName>, a feeble little man to look at, who has acted as chaplain to the late bishop, receiving &#x00A3;120 per. ann. and residing in the Palace. I felt an imposter in making these arrangements for my future seems nowise as obvious as it did. Given a determination on the part of these organized fanaticks to force a crisis, I cannot feel sure that they may not find means of so delaying my consecration, as to create an extremely embarrassing practical situation. My letters included congratulations from the <persName xml:id="130">Abp of York</persName> and the Bp. of <persName xml:id="3933">Peterboro</persName>. The first was embarrassed &amp; lukewarm, evidently scenting trouble ahead. The last was cordial but cautious</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I get the impression that their Lordships are waiting to catch the direction of the wind, &amp; that they w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> find little difficulty in lining up against me</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A clergyman from one of the parishes came round with a company of female choristers carrying Chinese lanterns &amp; singing carols. They were making collections for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Dunstan's Hospital for blind soldiers. I gave them a pound and some civil words. A little parson named Butterfield (!) was introduced to me as a Diocesan Missioner, &amp; said to be a good worker at his job. This has been a strange day filled with varying emotions, most melancholy.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
