<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[49]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1206</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A cheerful&#8211;looking maid, who was careful to tell me that she was a Durham girl, &amp; hailed from Tudhoe, brought me some tea at 7 a.m: and I spent an hour before getting up in preparing my speech on the "Church &amp; State" resolution. <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> met at 11 a.m: and I stuck at the dull business until 4.40 p.m., when I returned to the Hotel. (I lunched at the Deanery, where I had an opportunity of talking over the projected meeting in Manchester on Dec: 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1855">Archdeacon Allen</persName></hi><hi>. From what he said, I gathered that the whole business was being horribly bungled, &amp; might well end in a fiasco. I told him that I would withdraw my promise unless I could be assured that the meeting was fairly representative of the diocese.) </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="130">Lang's</persName></hi><hi> presidential remarks were very brief, &amp; we soon got to business. I gave notice of a motion expressing to the President the "surprise &amp; regret" with which we had received our summons to the <orgName xml:id="57">R.C.C.</orgName> next week, after the members, in reply to the inquiry of the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishops</persName><persName xml:id="130"></persName> themselves, had, by a very large majority, expressed their desire </hi><hi rend="bold underline">not</hi><hi> to discuss the Church &amp; State Report this year.<note xml:id="316" n="1"></note><note xml:id="353" n="2"></note> </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName></hi><hi> agreed to second this, &amp; it stood over for the morrow. Then I introduced </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName></hi><hi>, as Dean of Carlisle, with a brief eulogium. Nearly the whole day was spent in discussing the Reports on the Lectionary &amp; the Psalter. I spoke several times but in the end the Fanaticks triumphed by 35 to 31. The names on my motion were called over.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
