<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[32]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1191</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName></hi><hi> before breakfast: attended Mattins: sent to the Prolocutor the resolution I desire to move in the Lower House. It is identical with that which the <persName xml:id="242">Bp. of Manchester</persName> will move in the Upper. I wrote to Archdeacon </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1855">Allen</persName></hi><hi>, asking him to second it. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Whitehorn</hi><hi>, a secretary attached to the staff of the "Westminster Gazette", who once induced me to address a brotherhood meeting in a Dissenting chapel at Harringay, called here, &amp; I asked him to lunch. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2837">Pemberton</persName></hi><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Angus</hi><hi> also dined. I attended a meeting in the Castle Hall designed to raise funds for the "Bishop <persName xml:id="555">Tucker</persName> Memorial Fund". </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName></hi><hi> presided. The Secretary, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Daniell</hi><hi>, the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName>, and I made speeches to a company of about 25 persons, mostly of the female sex! After walking with the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>, I sent a cheque (&#x00A3;5.) to the Fund, for which I had pleaded. This was less the oblation of evangelising zeal than a reluctant concession to conventional consistency! The evening paper reports further retreating of the Italians, whose new line has already been turned by the advance of the Austro&#8211;Germans. In reading the reports, one has a horrible suspicion that the treasonable doctrines, which have effected this great disaster, are yet working in the minds of the Italian soldiers, so that more dramatic collapses are possible. Reinforcements of French &amp; British troops are pouring in, but will they arrive in time to stay the panic? Have they artillery to replace the guns which have been lost; and stores to replace the vast accumulations which have been burned? </hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
