<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[101]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1246</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">O merciful God, have compassion on me, the worst and weakest of Thy servants, and forgive the sins &amp; blunders of another year. Thou knowest all my intentions, all my difficulties, all my failures. All things and my secret mind lie naked before Thee. Have mercy on me, O Lord, and cleanse me from my sin. Thy Will prevails in the affairs of men, and Thy Wisdom marks out the course of my life. Make known to me, I beseech Thee, the Purpose of Thy Providence, and give me grace to embrace it as mine own. Be with me in the new &amp; perilous road I must tread. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Show Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my heart unto Thee</hi><hi rend="italic">". Grant that my going to Hereford may help Thy people there, and set forward Thy kingdom. Give me wisdom, patience, &amp; courage. Cleanse my personal life, I entreat Thee, and give me a clearer vision of Thy Truth. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">If Thy Presence go not with me, carry me not up hence</hi><hi rend="italic">". Turn the hearts of mine enemies, and bring their evil intentions to nought. Let Thy Peace rule in my mind in the midst of all the tumults &amp; confusions of this time. Open to me an entrance into the hearts of Thy People in Hereford, and enable me to serve them faithfully according to Thy Will. O loving Father, give me Thy Holy Spirit to consecrate me to this Work. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Into Thy Hands I commend my spirit, for Thou hast redeemed me, O Lord, Thou God of Truth</hi><hi rend="italic">". This my prayer I present in the Name of Jesus Christ, Thy Son our Lord.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Amen.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[102]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> David's<persName xml:id="2146"></persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Thank you so much for your very kind letter, wh. was the more welcome to me for its candour. I certainly do not claim infallibility, &amp; it may well be the case that in the course of 30 years many things have been unwisely said. But the attitude which I have tried to take up &amp; maintain is, I am fully persuaded, both right in itself, &amp; indispensable in a Reformed Church. </hi><hi rend="underline">We</hi><hi> cannot take up the ostrich&#8211;like policy of the Vatican in front of the accumulating knowledge &amp; novel situations of our modern world. My personal opinions are far different indeed from many which yet I would not suffer to be roughly disallowed: and, indeed, I am most at home with men like yourself. Hoping, if God permit, for much co&#8211;operation in the future.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, my dear Bishop, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Sincerely &amp; gratefully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[103]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This has been pre&#8211;eminently a year of restlessness, controversy, and finally change. No less than 7 letters have appeared in the "Times" over my signature, &amp; one in the "Spectator". The subjects were the following</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>"The Capitular Foundations" (Jan. 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>)<ref xml:id="881"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Horton's Sabbatarianism" (April 24</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>)<ref xml:id="986"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"The Nation &amp; hasty Measures" (June 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>)<ref xml:id="987"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"Conscientious objectors" (Sept. 15)<ref xml:id="989"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"Mattins on Sunday" (Sept. 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>)<ref xml:id="990"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"The Archbishop's Summons" (October 17)<ref xml:id="975"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>  "  (   ̎</hi><hi>23)<ref xml:id="976"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>"The Clergy &amp; Military Service" (July 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> in "Spectator")<ref xml:id="930"></ref></hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi>On March 25</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> I preached in the City <orgName xml:id="37">Temple</orgName>. I addressed large meetings of Dissenters at Hull (Feb. 22) and Bradford (March 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>). I preached in Leeds, Manchester, Liverpool, York, &amp; Newcastle, as well as many places within the diocese. I preached in Westminster Abbey on Trafalgar day (Oct. 21): addressed a great meeting in the London Opera House on June 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi> in commemoration of the Battle of Jutland: presided at a meeting of the Evangelical Alliance on June 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>: preached at <orgName xml:id="58" display="no">Eton</orgName> to the school, &amp; addressed a meeting in Manchester (Dec. 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>). Both in the Northern <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> and in the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Ch. Council</orgName> I took a prominent, &amp; not unsuccessful part in criticizing &amp; opposing the <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> Scheme. Finally I accepted the bishoprick of Hereford, and was at once immersed in a maze of controversy. On Oct. 12 "Logic" was lost to my great &amp; lasting sorrow.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
