<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[34]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1193</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to S. Gregory's Chapel<placeName xml:id="77"></placeName>, &amp; there received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName></hi><hi> came also. Thus, then, in all Christian semblance, and, I think, intention my Birthday was begun. The passage which fell to be read in the Deanery Chapel at family prayer contained the striking passage, which I would like to be properly entitled to adopt as the formula of my own life: – "</hi><hi rend="underline">We are not of them that shrink back unto perdition: but of them that have faith unto the saving of the soul</hi><hi>". After 54 years of life, there can be no fresh discoveries of power in one's self, and few fresh opportunities for using such power as one possesses. The failures, and still more the faults, of the past weigh heavily on one's conscience, and go far to take all heart out of one's efforts. Still, it is something to realize that the inexorable alternative is "</hi><hi rend="underline">Backwards or Forwards</hi><hi>", and to be steadily set on going forward. My letters were hardly exhilarating, &amp; yet not without a certain suggestiveness:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>1. A very affectionate letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName></hi><hi>, full of distress about the Italian disaster. She says the traitorous troops are reported to be Florentines.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>2. An affectionate letter from </hi><persName xml:id="1812"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Angel</hi></persName><hi>, sending photographs of herself, &amp; of her husband, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Francis Thelwall M.C.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>3. A letter from the Prolocutor accepting my notice of motion for <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>4. A letter from the Rev. </hi><persName xml:id="4130"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sidney M. Berry</hi></persName><hi>, the Minister of Carrs Lane Church, inviting me to preach there early in the next year.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>5. A letter from </hi><persName xml:id="75"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tommie Hall</hi></persName><hi>, sending me Birthday wishes from himself and my god&#8211;daughter, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1416">Audrie</persName></hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>6. A letter from my Godson, </hi><persName xml:id="7"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Spelling</hi></persName><hi>, who still waits for a commission.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>7. A message of good wishes "from one of your old <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> congregation".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I began the sermon for Mayor's Sunday, &amp; wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><hi>. Then we lunched with the <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName>, &amp; found there the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> &amp; Archdeacon </hi><persName xml:id="3688"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Derry</hi></persName><hi>. I asked the Bishop to be the Preacher on January 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, which is appointed to be observed as a Day of Prayer &amp; Thanksgiving.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I presided at a meeting of the Library Committee, where we had but little business. Then I attended Evensong, after which, since it was raining, I walked with </hi><persName xml:id="1898"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi></persName><hi> for an hour in the Cloisters. Then I wrote letters to Linetta, <persName xml:id="4357">Elizabeth</persName>, <persName xml:id="1696">Olive</persName>, </hi><persName xml:id="3542"><hi rend="bold underline">Norman Henderson</hi></persName><hi>, &amp; Harry <persName xml:id="1486">Dibben</persName>. Also to <persName xml:id="277">Lord Portsmouth</persName>. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName>, having reported that two of his children were down with measles, &amp; that the doctor considered it unsafe for him to continue living in the house, I caused him to take up his abode in the Deanery.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The evening paper reports another </hi><hi rend="underline">coup d'&#x00E9;tat</hi><hi> in Petrograd. The Soviet appears to have thrown </hi><persName xml:id="4294"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kerensky</hi></persName><hi> overboard, &amp; announces a programme, of which the first article is a "democratic peace". The Germans claim to be still pressing the Italians, &amp; now reckon their captures to exceed 250,000 men &amp; 2300 guns. Besides such gigantic operations our little advance in Flanders has a petty appearance. There is so far no mention of the arrival of British &amp; French reinforcements at the Italian Front: but there are confident statements that very considerable numbers have already reached Italy. On the whole, however, the dimensions of the disaster which has befallen the Italians tend to grow greater as information trickles in, &amp; its possibilities are reflected upon.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
