<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[9]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1173</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Another brilliant morning. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote a short letter to the</hi><hi rend="italic"> '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">' </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">quoting the relevant portion of the <persName xml:id="128">Abp's</persName> letter to me, and adding that I continued to think the decision to summon the <orgName xml:id="57">R.C.C.</orgName> in November "surprising &amp; regrettable"</hi><hi rend="italic">. The Abp. is perhaps beginning to discover that a dislike for his "secret diplomacy" is very widely felt. After attending Mattins, I wrote privately to the Abp (copy of letter over page). The <persName xml:id="4346">Dean of York</persName> and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> <persName xml:id="4347">Foxley Norris</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> called to be taken to the Carpet Factory. I showed them over the house pending <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> arrival. After lunch I went to Sherburn Hospital, and attended a meeting of the Governors. We appointed a House Committee of six members, of whom I am one. Also we elected some Out&#8211;Brethren, &amp; Out&#8211;Sisters. </hi><hi>In my absence a crowded meeting was held in the Deanery in the interest of Rescue &amp; Refuge Work in the Diocese. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="4438">Bishop of Barrow&#8211;in&#8211;Furness</persName> was the principal speaker</hi><hi>; he stayed the night at the Deanery. Old </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Lindsay <persName xml:id="3189">Wood</persName></hi><hi> gave me a lift in his car as far as the White Gate, but I got home too late to see either the <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName>, or the Dowager Lady <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName>. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>, and made my preparations for departure early tomorrow. After dinner we sate in my study, &amp; &amp; talked. The Bishop of Barrow is amiable and active but conventional</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He believes in the 'National Mission', is disposed to be mildly Socialistic, &amp; rails at the Establishment as the source of our spiritual failures</hi><hi rend="italic">. I did my best to make him look at things from another point of view, but probably only succeeded in shocking him. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>October 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Lord Archbishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is very good of you to find time to write to me, &amp;, of course, I have made no delay in conveying to the public through the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>", the explanation which your Grace holds to be sufficient. That it does not seem so to me will not surprise, for I cannot regard even an unanimous vote of the Canterbury House of Laymen as properly competent to reverse a judgment of the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName>, &amp; I cannot regard </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor's</persName></hi><hi> resolution as anything better than an adroit method of masquing [sic] his real purposes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But I note with genuine distress the ring of reproach in your words, as if you felt in some degree hurt by my preferring a public appeal in the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" to a private reference to yourself. Believe me, nothing has grieved me more than the conviction, which has grown over me during the last three or four years, that your Grace has no use any more for such services as I can render, &amp; no approval for the course of ecclesiastical policy which I represent &amp; pursue. That naturally will not trouble your Grace, for who cares what I think or try for? but it distresses me, because, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">not only do I hold ever passionately to the conception of a National Church</hi><hi> (which is now ridiculed openly &amp; without rebuke) but I have a personal regard for your Grace, which makes your approval very precious, &amp; your censure very </hi><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi><hi> painful. </hi><hi rend="italic">I am persuaded that your Grace does not perceive or realize the utterly unrepresentative character, so far as the people are concerned, of the type of Anglicanism which the "Church and State" Report illustrates, &amp; which prevails in the ecclesiastical coteries which are most noisy &amp; persistent. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">We are, as a National Church, being steered straight on to the rocks, &amp; nothing is left to people like me but the mournful r&#x00F4;le &amp; belated vindication of so many religious Cassandras!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, my dear Lord Archbishop, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>always dutifully &amp; sincerely, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div><p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
