<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1223</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received an affectionate letter of congratulations from my former curate, <persName xml:id="18">Gerald Marshall</persName>, now Rector of Fulham: also an offer from an auctioneer in Hereford to do business for me in the matter of purchasing furniture from the late <persName xml:id="475">Bishop</persName>. Bishop <persName xml:id="4152">Bury</persName>, who might be supposed to know the proprieties in matters ecclesiastical, writes to congratulate. All this is sufficiently absurd. I presided at a meeting of Chapter, where there was nothing important to do: then I prepared notes for a speech on education, and, after lunch, went to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, and gave away prizes at the Secondary School. The dowager Marchioness of <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName> sate on the platform, and, when the actual business of the function had been concluded, whisked me off to <placeName xml:id="62">Lumley</placeName>, where she persuaded me to stay for dinner, &amp; sent me back in the car afterwards. <persName xml:id="4478">General Maxwell</persName>, <persName xml:id="4398">Lord Basing</persName>, <persName xml:id="4486">Lord Cunningham</persName>, a diplomatist named <persName xml:id="4485">Clark</persName>, and Miss Beaumont made up the party, and we had much interesting conversation. General M. spoke in rather an alarming fashion about the military situation in France. He did not apprehend another rebellion in Ireland, but thought it very unlikely that the Convention would produce any workable scheme of government. We had a vivacious discussion of the position of the clergy in this war. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Incidentally he expressed a contemptuous estimate of the present Chaplain General<persName xml:id="3507"></persName></hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>On arriving at the Deanery about 11.15 p.m., I found the fatal letter from the <persName xml:id="234">P.M.</persName> awaiting me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[70]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>December 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Dean of Durham,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishopric of Hereford is vacant and I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be glad if I may submit your name to His Majesty, the King, for appointment as D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Percival's successor.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is not quite the Diocese I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have been inclined to select for you, if there had been any choice, as I should prefer to see you grappling with the needs of some large and industrial population. Such a vacancy, of a more responsible character, may arise in due course; if so, I trust you will have proved your powers of governance &amp; guidance in such a way that I may have the privilege of suggesting your translation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the meantime, if you consent, the Diocese of Hereford will give you an insight into the quiet needs of a rural population, and will enable you to bring your mind to bear on the many problems which confront the Episcopate at this time.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I should be obliged by your replying as soon as possible and am with all good wishes.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very truly,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>D. Lloyd George</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[71]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>December 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Lloyd George,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have to acknowledge your letter of the 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> December conveying the proposal that you sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> submit my name to H.M. the King, for appointment as D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Percival's successor in the See of Hereford.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It has for some while been apparent to me that if a place on the Episcopal Bench were offered to me, I could not rightly refuse it in view of the difficult and embarrassing circumstances in wh. the C. of E. now stands: &amp; therefore, though my five years residence in Durham has been happy &amp; not inactive, and though my retirement from my present position will cause me very real pain and regret, I hold it plain that I ought to consent to the proposal wh. you have been good enough to make to me. I am willing that you sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> submit my name to H.M. the King, for appointment to the bishopric of Hereford, and, if his Majesty shall be graciously pleased to approve your nomination, I shall be ready to accept the appointment, &amp; to do what I can to justify it. I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> like to add that I appreciate the kindness of the terms in wh. your letter is expressed, and thank you sincerely for the confidence and goodwill, wh. it must needs imply.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Lloyd George, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very faithfully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Right Hon</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ble</hi><hi>, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Prime Minister.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
