<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[58]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1214</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>This day was spent mostly in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaenum</orgName> where I wrote many letters </hi><hi rend="bold underline">including one to the</hi><hi> "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" </hi><hi rend="bold underline">on the proceedings at the <orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName></hi><hi>. I wrote also to <persName xml:id="112">my Wife</persName>, to Ernest, to <persName xml:id="2463" display="no">Nimbus</persName>, to <persName xml:id="3571">George</persName>, and to the Baptist Phillips<persName xml:id="4484"></persName>, promising to preach in April in his chapel. Also to the <persName xml:id="4355">Vicar of Barking</persName> promising to preach on Feb. 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. After lunching in the Club, I had my head shampooed. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Then I walked to Lambeth, &amp; saw the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> who was on the point of departure for Canterbury. His Grace was most cordial; thanked me warmly for what he called my public&#8211;spirited &amp; helpful behaviour at the Council: praised my speech: &amp; generally was almost gushing! He referred cryptically to the time, which will not be far distant, when I should have to view these questions from within, and be wearing "other slieves" [sic]. Is this mere hedging to make sure that, if I do go to Hereford, I shall mentally credit his Grace with the character of the author of my preferment? Or, does he know that something is really probable, &amp; was simply speaking in the light of the probability</hi><hi rend="italic">? </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Lewis <persName xml:id="909">Dibdin</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> met me in the Club, &amp; said: "If I held your view, I should regard the proceedings in the Council as a considerable triumph". Lord </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> came to me, &amp; spoke in a friendly way. I thought he did not look very triumphant. I called on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName></hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; talked with him for half an hour. Then I returned to mine host, &amp; made an end of a futile day.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
