<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1226</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I started the day by filling up the new sugar cards for the household. Then I attended the meeting of the economic committee in the Dining room. Colonel <persName xml:id="3833">Blackitt</persName> attended, and made much illuminating comment on our draft report. He brought with him the pay&#8211;sheet from his colliery, and showed us that every conceivable circumstance of the miner's work was taken into consideration in the process of determining the wage which he should receive. I had not supposed that so carefully calculated and equitable a system had been established in this county. There can be no doubt that an irrational &amp; almost irremovable suspicion in the minds of the men is the real source of our economic conflicts. The actual grievances could be removed with patience &amp; goodwill. <persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName> and Blackitt stayed to lunch. Both of them in different ways expressed regret at my impending departure. The <persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> was very emphatic in his personal regret, but thought I could do no otherwise than go. I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and then was motored by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Robson to Blaydon on the Tyne, where I gave away certificates, and made a speech on education, at the secondary School. The building in which the function took place was low&#8211;pitched, and crowded to excess. I think the people were pleased at my coming to them. We returned to Durham by motor, &amp; I was back in the Deanery by 10 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Times" has an announcement that the Bishoprick of Hereford has been offered to the Dean of Durham!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
