<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[85]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1234</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">I walked to Lambeth by way of the Embankment. So bitter was the cold that, though I walked fast, I could not get warm, &amp; arrived at the Palace still half&#8211;frozen. A dense fog grew upon the city as I advanced, so that it was not possible to see across the street. I found the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> at breakfast,</hi><hi> &amp; was shown in to him, where he was taking his meal with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="404">Davidson</persName>, Miss Mills, Sir Lewis <persName xml:id="909">Dibdin</persName>, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4126">Bell</persName>, the chaplain. Afterwards I had an interview with him. He seemed depressed &amp; morose. I think he anticipates considerable trouble over my appointment. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He told me that he was receiving numerous letters calling upon him to see the King, &amp; insist upon this scandalous nomination being cancelled, &amp; that he should refuse to consecrate</hi><hi>!! However, I arranged with him that the consecration sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> take place in Westminster Abbey on </hi><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi><hi> February 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>, and that <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> should be the preacher. He told me that the deanery would be </hi><hi rend="underline">ipso facto </hi><hi>vacated by my consecration: and bade me attend the next meeting of bishops on Jan. 31</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> &amp; Feb. 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I came away from the Palace with an uncomfortable suspicion that the Archbishop w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> like to throw me over if he decently could</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><note xml:id="360" n="1"></note> <hi>He rages against <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd&#8211;George</persName>, whose manner of conducting his Prime Minister's business, he describes as equally unprecedented, dilatory, and scandalous. He has installed in Downing Street an army of inexperienced &amp; arrogant neophytes, who perform their work inefficiently &amp; offensively. These defects are at their worst in the particular case of the ecclesiastical patronage. I suspect that the Abp's </hi><hi rend="underline">amour propre</hi><hi> has been wounded by his own arrangements having been more or less set aside. He mentioned that Hereford had been suggested to two other persons, &amp; I told him that both those persons – the Bps of <persName xml:id="2533">Bristol</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="602">Southwark</persName> – had told me the fact, &amp; sounded me with respect to accepting the vacated see. I could not afford Bristol: &amp; I could not sustain the labour of Southwark. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">This somewhat impressed his Grace, &amp; we parted civilly, but with less than our usual cordiality</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>From Lambeth I walked to Westminster, where I called on <persName xml:id="4306">Lee</persName>, &amp; saw M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Dashwood<persName xml:id="4186"></persName>, his partner. To Lee I gave written authority to act for me in getting the documents etc. from the Crown. Then I returned to S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's Deanery. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I proceeded to Hereford, where we were courteously received by the Dean<persName xml:id="3741"></persName> &amp; Lady Butler<persName xml:id="4154"></persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
