<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[96]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1244</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>O Lord God, in Whose Hands are all the threads of my life, &amp; Who knowest the end as well as the beginning, look upon me with compassion, &amp; strengthen me with Thy Holy Spirit at this time, that I may discern Thy Purpose, and desire with all my heart to serve it. Cleanse me from all pride, resentment, and self&#8211;seeking. Give me grace to perceive my duty and loyalty to fulfil it. Have mercy upon Thy People in the diocese of Hereford, and protect them from danger to faith and morals by reason of these conflicts. Overrule by Thy Sovereign Wisdom even the rage of mine enemies, &amp; bring good out of evil to the Glory of Thy Name and the advancement of Thy Kingdom through Jesus Christ, Thy Son our Lord.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Amen</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Church Times" announces that the public meeting of protest in Hereford will probably have to be abandoned as there is no available substitute for the Town Hall, of which the use has been refused by the Mayor and Corporation. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">It is sufficiently obvious that my opponents are taking a course which ought to lead up to a prosecution for heresy, and it is possible that the logic of their conduct will force them to prosecute: but so far they do not seem fully persuaded that they could substantiate a charge of heresy, and they are deeply pledged not to recognise the authority of the Courts, which, for years past, they have denounced as "Erastian". So they seek to attain their end by raising prejudice and clamour</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="66">Frank</persName> went off with <persName xml:id="937">his wife</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4356">daughter</persName> to the station after breakfast. My chill and the distractions of this squalid conflict have made me but an indifferent host. Katherine pleased me: she bids fair to grow into a good and good&#8211;looking woman. I wrote some letters. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">In the "Times" <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> has a letter, on my side but not very heartily</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The cry of heresy is still very </hi><hi rend="underline">isolating</hi><hi>. After lunch I showed Lady <persName xml:id="4220">Helmsley</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> McClure Robinson over the Cathedral, &amp; then attended Evensong. The afternoon post brought letters from <persName xml:id="1394">Prothero</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="403">Dicey</persName>, both very kind. We motored to <placeName xml:id="62">Lumley Castle</placeName> &amp; there dined with Lady <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName> (dowager). The <persName xml:id="2818">Marquis</persName> was there with is very charming wife<persName xml:id="2819"></persName>: also <persName xml:id="4478">General Maxwell</persName> with his <persName xml:id="4469">wife</persName>. These with Lady Helmsley, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> McClure Robinson<persName xml:id="4480" display="no"></persName> &amp; ourselves made up the party. There was much talk, not of any particular interest, save that I got some conversation with Lord L. about Ireland. He thinks that nothing will come of the Convention, and that the Roman Church does not wish for a settlement. I was certainly well impressed by this nobleman. He is a distinguished&#8211;looking man, with a grave statesman's manner of expressing himself, dignified courtesy of manner, &amp; a pleasing suggestion of candour. His mother told me that he lacked "go", but that may reflect rather the precipitate eagerness of the lady herself than any serious defect in her son. Lady L. is very pleasant to look at &amp; very intelligent. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Everybody expressed great regret at my departure from Durham, and talked indecently &amp; to my great embarrassment of my returning as Bishop</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
