<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[25]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1185</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Last night in the evening paper there was a paragraph extracted from the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Daily Chronicle</hi><hi>",</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">saying that my name was being talked of for the vacant bishoprick</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> <hi>This morning the Newcastle paper prints a longer paragraph from the "London correspondent" of the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Glasgow Herald</hi><hi>" to the same effect. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">This is abominably annoying from every point of view, &amp; my unfriends could not do me more effectual injury than to put about such statements</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>I wrote to </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName></hi><hi> about the <orgName xml:id="57">R.C.C.</orgName> asking whether he w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> second my amendment, &amp; taking occasion to </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">tell him frankly that if, Bristol were offered to me , I must needs decline it, as being too ill&#8211;endowed for me to hold</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3178">Hadow</persName></hi><hi> went off after breakfast. I attended Mattins and Evensong. In the afternoon I travelled to South Shields, &amp; there made a speech to the "Public Health Society" &amp; others in the Council Chambers of the Municipal Blgs. on "</hi><hi rend="underline">Housing as the first step in Social Reconstruction"</hi><hi>. </hi><persName xml:id="4170"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Cochrane</hi></persName><hi>, the local M.P. presided, &amp; was supported by the Mayors of <persName xml:id="4238">Tynemouth</persName> and South Shields. There was, I should judge, a good attendance. I observed with some interest &amp; concern that an artisan who addressed the meeting after I had concluded, made allusion to what he alleged be ill&#8211;conditions in some pits owned by the Dean &amp; Chapter. But we own no pits at all. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4171">Cochrane</persName> &amp; I returned by the same train as far as Gateshead, when she went to Newcastle, &amp; I to Durham. The view of the Cathedral &amp; Castle in the brilliant moonlight was ravishingly beautiful.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[26]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To A. C. <persName xml:id="2099">Benson</persName> Esq</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Nov. 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> 1917</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Benson,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is felt by some of us that, in present circumstances, much good w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be done if a letter were sent to the "</hi><hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" &amp; other papers, signed by some representative laymen &amp; clergy, setting out in calm terms the value &amp; meaning of the National Church as we in England have received it from the past, &amp; pleading for some larger &amp; more sympathetic handling of the "reconstruction", if that is to be undertaken, than is indicated by the Report of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord <persName xml:id="311">Selborne's</persName></hi><hi> C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> &amp; by the programme of the so&#8211;called "Life &amp; Liberty" movement.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName>, <persName xml:id="277">Lord Portsmouth</persName>, Principal Hadow, &amp; some others whom I was able to consult were agreed with me in thinking that no one c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> better draft, or more fitly be asked to draft such a letter, than yourself. I am writing, therefore, to ask whether you can see you way to do this, &amp; generally for your opinion on the matter.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, Sincerely yrs,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>P.S. In case you may not have seen it, I take leave to send you a copy of the Bishop of Manchester's careful &amp; suggestive examination of the recommendations of </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Selborne's</hi><hi> Report.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
