<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[43]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1917.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1200</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I continued to work at the Article, and wrote a certain amount, but the result of my labours is curiously disappointing. Hurried work can never be satisfactory. I attended Evensong, &amp; afterwards left my card on the Judge at the Castle. </hi><hi>While in the Cathedral the notion came to me that the true answer to the challenge, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">why should the Established Church of England not enjoy the same measure of autonomy as that enjoyed by the Established Church of Scotland</hi><hi rend="italic">? lay in the fact that the one being episcopal can only be autonomous as part of a larger system than that of the Nation, whereas the other being presbyterian can possess complete autonomy within the national limits. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Hence to admit the Episcopalian claim is all one with bringing back the internationalism which it was the first object of the Reformers to abolish</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received a long letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip le Mesurier<persName xml:id="3919"></persName> </hi><hi>which rather distressed me. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The youth would seem to be contemplating surrender to the Scarlet Woman</hi><hi>. I so far agree with him that, if he is to accept the "Catholick" version of Christianity, he had better do so as a Papist, &amp; not immerse himself in the moral confusions of Anglo&#8211;Romanism. But it is rather a disappointing conclusion to his protest against the mummeries of S. Chad's. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He is, I suspect, temperamentally disposed towards Papistry</hi><hi>. I don't think it matters very much what his ecclesiastical description shall be, but, if he professes himself a Papist, he cuts his connection with his Protestant friends, &amp; goes outside the main stream of English life. That is the real disadvantage of becoming a Papist: it must needs imply also a banishment from England, in the spirit if not also in the flesh!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
