<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[190]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1315</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Abbey at 8 a.m., &amp; received the Holy Communion. After the service I went into Little Cloisters, meeting <persName xml:id="1951">Christian</persName> on the way, &amp; had some talk with <persName xml:id="636">Ernest</persName>. He doubts if <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName> will accept the Deanery of Durham: but, if </hi><hi rend="underline">he does</hi><hi>, thinks it might be well to run <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName> for Southwark. I agreed, but was doubtful whether M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="553">H's</persName> health would permit his accepting it. Then I went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; on the way slipped ignominiously on the pavement hard by the Wesleyan Hall. After writing to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, &amp; reading over my sermon, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I went to the <orgName xml:id="59" display="no">Chapel Royal</orgName></hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>It is a quaint building, curiously un&#8211;churchlike, with class distinction stamped on every inch of it. There was a good congregation, most of the seats were occupied. The <persName xml:id="3610">Sub&#8211;Dean</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4358">Percival</persName> conducted the service wh. consisted of Litany &amp; Holy Comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi>. I preached from an uncomfortable desk within the rails, &amp; left after the sermon. My text was "All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any", &amp; the sermon was </hi><hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi> new! Lady <persName xml:id="3466">Scarbrough</persName> carried me off to lunch. The <persName xml:id="759">Lyttons</persName><persName xml:id="918"></persName> were there. I had not seen them for years. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Edward <persName xml:id="586">Wood</persName> &amp; his <persName xml:id="4452">wife</persName> were also there</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>He was friendly enough, but we kept clear of doctrinal questions! As I walked to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, I met Lady <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName>, &amp; walked back with her as far as Carlton House Terrace. Then I went to <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, &amp; had tea. At 5.30 p.m., I called on the <persName xml:id="344">Craiks</persName><persName xml:id="793"></persName>. They grow more depressing as time advances, perhaps indeed that is the case with us all. I am certainly duller &amp; more cheerless than formerly!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I preached in S. John's, Westminster. <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName> &amp; his 2 curates were present. There was not a large congregation, but larger than usual. The sermon was again an old one on the text: "Father, forgive them for they know not what they do". After service I changed, and walked to Carlton House Terrace, where I dined pleasantly with Lady Londonderry. The following made up the party:– The Spanish Ambassador &amp; his wife (a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">very</hi><hi rend="italic"> pretty woman, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">very</hi><hi rend="italic"> prettily dressed), Lord <persName xml:id="3220">Stamfordham</persName>, Lord <persName xml:id="1313">Knollys</persName>, <persName xml:id="4491">Saunders</persName>, <persName xml:id="4490">Maguire</persName>, a lady related to the hostess, whose name I forget, &amp; myself. We had much pleasant conversation on politics, architecture, &amp; persons. </hi><persName xml:id="4328"><hi rend="italic underline">Merry del Val</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> is a good&#8211;looking man, not at all Spanish in appearance. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He said that Pius X had condemned the dancing of the Seville choir boys</hi><hi rend="italic">, but when they had danced before him, he so far relented as to permit the dance to continue until the existing garments had been worne out. The resources of sartorial craft had conferred a practical immortality on the vestments! He said that the architectural gem of Spain was neither Seville nor Burgos, but Leon. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">With Lord Stamfordham I had much talk</hi><hi rend="italic"> both about my own appointment to Hereford, &amp; the prospective app</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> to the Deanery of Durham. I gathered that Burge had not yet finally refused, but might do so, in wh. case Headlam w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> probably get it. I backed Headlam against either <persName xml:id="308">Hobhouse</persName> or <persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName>, but not against Burge.</hi> <hi>Maguire was most friendly. He is greyer &amp; has lost much of the vivacious beauty of his earlier life. At first I didn't recognize him. I got back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> about 11.30 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
