<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1336</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Rain was falling rather heavily when I went across to the cathedral at 8 a.m. Mattins was still proceeding, &amp; it was a quarter after the hour when the celebration began. </hi><hi rend="italic">I was myself the celebrant. <persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName>, <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName>, and a minor canon were present. There were about 70 comt</hi><hi rend="i sup u">s</hi><hi rend="italic">, among whom I noticed several of the cathedral school boys, whom I confirmed on the 23</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rd</hi><hi rend="italic">. The service was solemn, and consolatory. I preached in S. Peter's Church to a very large congregation, and afterwards lunched with the Vicar, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> A. C. Moore</hi><persName xml:id="4331"></persName><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">This is a <orgName xml:id="302">Simeon's Trustees</orgName> living, but there was a surpliced choir</hi><hi rend="italic">. I wrote to <persName xml:id="4472" display="no">Elizabeth Smith</persName> and to M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="3813">Darwin</persName>. The weather was very unpleasant as Evensong came on, but, in spite of rain showers &amp; sudden squalls, there was a considerable congregation. I preached from Romans X. 9. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">If thou shalt confess with thy mouth Jesus as Lord, &amp; shalt believe in thy heart that God raised Him from the dead, thou shalt be saved</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bannister</hi><hi rend="italic"> carried the crozier: &amp; I wore my red robes. Before the Benediction the Choir sang the Hallelujah Chorus. As I walked from the Altar in much state, I could not help reflecting on the contrast between the apparent respect with which I was treated, and the obloquy with which I was assailed in this city but a few weeks since. Of course I do not suppose that the enemy has done with me yet: but certainly they have had a heavy fall. When my list of chaplains is made public the "Catholicks" will be restive: and when I am reported to have again preached in Non&#8211;Anglican Churches, they will probably find their voices again. However, as the Blessed Paul said, "none of these things move me".</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
