<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1314</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters, &amp; saw divers people. Then I walked round the cathedral with a verger, &amp; lunched early. </hi><persName xml:id="3619"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bannister</hi></persName><hi> came in to see me about letting his house. The main obstacle is M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4119">B.'s</persName> reluctance to allow her treasures to be handled by new &amp; heartless maids! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I left Hereford at 12.55 p.m., and arrived in Paddington about 6 p.m.</hi> <hi>There I was lucky in getting a taxi, and so got to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> without delay. Here I found </hi><persName xml:id="4346"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Foxley Norris</hi></persName><hi>, the Dean of York, who is due to preach in the Abbey tomorrow morning. I dined with the Barrans<persName xml:id="2069"></persName><persName xml:id="2070" display="no"></persName>. The company was mostly American. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Herbert Samuel</hi><persName xml:id="1480"></persName><hi> was there. He took a gloomy view of the war&#8211;prospects. I asked Prof: <persName xml:id="4149">Bunstead</persName> (?) [sic] of Yale, (an eminent "physicist", who is attached in that capacity to the American Embassy in London,) whether in his judgment, America would have supported President <persName xml:id="2814">Wilson</persName> if he had come in to the War (as he ought </hi><hi rend="underline">on principle</hi><hi> to have done) after the sinking of the "Lusitania". He was not very positive, but inclined to think that President Wilson came in on the first opportunity. I returned to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> about 11 p.m., &amp; then we sate up talking until 12.30 midnight on the chance of there being another air&#8211;raid. In that event, we sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have been required to betake ourselves to the Norman undercroft, until such time as the attack had ended. However there was nothing of the sort, &amp; we did at last go to bed. There are evident signs of nerve&#8211;weakening in these Londoners, though, on the whole, it were but just to allow that they bear their experiences very creditably.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
