<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1306</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to Russell &amp; C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi><hi>, 51 Baker Street, and was photographed for the National Portrait Gallery. </hi><hi rend="underline">I went to Hereford by the 1.40 p.m. train</hi><hi>, which was crowded with soldiers &amp; cadets. On the platform at Hereford I was met by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName></hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4471" display="no">Bateman</persName></hi><hi>. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister's</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> house had a comfortable appearance. Among the letters awaiting me was a brief note from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Edith Morgan</hi><hi rend="italic"> telling me that her brother </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1916">Arthur</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> had been killed in an aeroplane accident.</hi> <hi>"You must forgive me for troubling you by writing but he loved you very dearly". I am sorry the boy is dead. He was neither brilliant nor attractive: but he was genuinely good &amp; religious. He had set his mind with remarkable determination on becoming a clergyman, &amp;, if he had lived, I should probably have helped him to realize his ambition. A telegram from </hi><persName xml:id="4344"><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Nimmins</hi></persName><hi> tells me that </hi><persName xml:id="3571"><hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi></persName><hi> will arrive in Durham tomorrow. I am indeed thankful that his ship escaped the submarines. If disaster had befallen the lad on his first voyage, I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> have felt guiltily responsible for the part I played in sending him to sea. How various are the fates of men!</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">A very violent sermon was sent to me. It had been preached in S. Matthew's, Westminster, on February 2</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">, while my Consecration was proceeding in the Abbey! The sermon was specially addressed to the Members of the Churchwomen's League of Prayer by the Rev</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> T. J. <persName xml:id="4254">Hardy</persName>, Warden of S. Mary's House, Regent's Park</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To Rev Preb. <persName xml:id="4117">Stallard&#8211;Penoyre</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>March 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Canon,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am very much obliged to you for your letter, the motive of which I think I understand, &amp; which I appreciate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is entirely clear to me that, in declining to vote for me as Bishop, you were not only exercising your unquestionable right, but also doing what appeared to be your duty. Your action therefore, left in my mind not the smallest trace of resentment, &amp; I sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be sorry, indeed, if you felt that it rendered your work in the diocese in any measure embarrassed.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The appointment, or re&#8211;appointment, of the rural deans must shortly be undertaken: and until that is done, I must needs ask the existing rural deans to continue in office. I may, since you have raised the question, say now that it is my intention to ask you to be Rural Dean of Bewdley. I hope that you will see your way to accept appointment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>These are difficult days for us all, most of all for men holding ecclesiastical office. We must stand together, &amp; work together as far as we can.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi> 
         </p>
</div>   <p></p>
         </body></text></TEI>
