<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1249</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The temperature fell sharply during the night; and in the morning the ground was covered with snow. <ref xml:id="979">My letter</ref><ref xml:id="980"></ref> in the "Times" of yesterday, acknowledging the letters of congratulation, operated as an incitement to other kindly folks, and a fresh batch arrived during the day. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Among these was one from "Father" <persName xml:id="922">Waggett</persName>, and another, expressed with much kindness, from the Judge, Sir Robert <persName xml:id="4071">Younger</persName></hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Bishop of Exeter (<persName xml:id="31">Cecil</persName>) wrote kindly enough, but added a significant reference to the fears of the Evangelicals. "If you could say a word to still the fears of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Evangelical</hi><hi> party, I think we should all be grateful". </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But I answered that it was "quite impossible" for me to make any statement of explanation or of apology at the present moment, and sent him a copy of "The Notes of my Ministry</hi><hi>"<ref xml:id="87"></ref>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I suspect that there is a good deal of private communication in process among some of the bishops, possibly encouraged by the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>, who desires to get something out of me that might pass for a "recantation" among my opponents, &amp; "save the faces" of Lord <persName xml:id="586">Halifax</persName> &amp; his dervishes. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But on this point I am fully determined to make no concession. Whatever of reassurance can be found in my published opinions I am content that my critics should make the most of: but I will not accept the position of an accused heretick except in a Court of Law, where "before Caesar's judgment" seat I ought to be brought to trial if indeed I have offended, &amp; where I shall at least be free to defend myself</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
