<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1269</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went first to the Deanery at S. Paul's, and then to Bow Church. In the vestry were Lord <persName xml:id="1736">Parmoor</persName>, the lawyers, and the press&#8211;men. The proceedings were punctual and brief. Two objections had been sent in as I already knew would be the case. They were from the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4190">Hermitage Day</persName>, and a layman named Reilly, both from the diocese of Hereford, &amp; they alleged my heresy and general unfitness for episcopal office. These were ruled out as inadmissible, &amp; we then proceeded into the church, where the Litany was read, the usual formalities gone through, I took a series of oaths on my knees, &amp; then pronounced the Benediction. The church was nearly filled with men &amp; a few women. They seemed to be friends of mine. An enterprising photographer took snap&#8211;shots of the <persName xml:id="3741">Dean of Hereford</persName> &amp; myself standing together on the steps of the church. Then I returned to the <orgName xml:id="89">Club</orgName>, having a dreadful head&#8211;ache, induced partly by excitement, &amp; partly by the mugginess of the weather. Indeed, I was in some doubt as to my fitness for travelling. However I made an effort, &amp; got back to Durham by the late train, which ran well to time, &amp; brought me in about 11.30 p.m. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> awaited me, &amp; a pile of letters, among wh. was one from <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>, enclosing a copy of a letter which he had sent to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> withdrawing his protest. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He &amp; his friends will try to make out that I have "recanted" my heresies. But I shall still say nothing</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
