<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1284</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I received the Holy Communion in the Palace Chapel. After breakfast I walked to Westminster, &amp; robed in Bishop <persName xml:id="280">Boyd Carpenter's</persName> house in the cloisters. Then we went together to Buckingham Palace, &amp; I did homage – a quaint ceremony.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Afterwards, the King had some talk with me. He has evidently heard a great deal about my appointment. Probably he has been more disturbed than he acknowledged</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi>From the Palace I went to the <orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName>, and there spent most of the day, not very serviceably. In the course of the proceedings I spoke several times, but ineffectively. After the House had risen, I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; there revised, packed, &amp; sent off to George <persName xml:id="1330">Macmillan</persName> the remaining sermons of the projected <ref xml:id="967">volume</ref>. William <persName xml:id="1173">Temple</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4419">his wife</persName> came to dinner at Lambeth, &amp; at table I sate between them. The <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> devoted himself to Temple most of the evening: &amp; I seemed to discern an ominous connexion between this intimacy &amp; the "Life &amp; Liberty" movement. I see in the "Guardian" that Lord Hugh <persName xml:id="314">Cecil</persName> had given notice of a motion in the House of Laymen, praying the Archbishop &amp; Bishops to make sure that no man is admitted to Holy Orders who does not believe in the Virgin Birth, &amp;c. I do not doubt that such a motion will have an easy course in such an assembly: &amp; that the debate will galvanize into fresh activity the campaign against the luckless Bishop of Hereford.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
