<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[105]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1248</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Beyond writing letters to acknowledge the congratulations of Bishops, I did very little. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The morning post brought a curious letter from <persName xml:id="3946">Newbolt</persName></hi><hi>. He says that he writes "with the greatest possible reluctance" but "<persName xml:id="4414">Stone's</persName> letter in the Times has considerably startled and shocked" him.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“I feel that I must say that I view with the greatest sorrow &amp; apprehension, an episcopate based on the foundation which Stone seems to disclose, and although I am content to leave the matter in God's hands, yet you must not count on my goodwill as anything more than personal to yourself, while I must leave myself free to dissociate myself from the position which you are taking up. I write this with great sorrow and repugnance. But I feel that I must tell you the altered stand&#8211;point from which I view the matter. God bless you and direct you!”</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The afternoon post brought me a letter from the Bishop of <persName xml:id="2462">Chelmsford</persName>, enclosing another, apparently designed for publication, asking me to re&#8211;assure him &amp; his friends as to my orthodoxy!</hi>
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>“Can you see your way to affirm that what you have written does not imply that you have departed from the traditional &amp; almost universal meaning wh. is attached to the words of the Creed "Born of the </hi><hi rend="underline">Virgin</hi><hi> Mary", "The third day He rose from the dead".</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>To this I returned the following answer by the afternoon post:–</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[106]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the Bishop of Chelmsford</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am obliged to you for your letter, the kindly intention of which I cannot doubt. But I think you will understand that it is quite impossible for me to do more than refer inquirers to my published statements on doctrinal issues. I assume that no just or reasonable man would judge of my teaching by sentences, selected with a hostile purpose, divorced from their context and argument, &amp; set before the public in a compromising envelope of innuendo.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Five years ago, when leaving Westminster, I set down "the Notes of my Ministry" in a sermon preached in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, and subsequently published<ref xml:id="87"></ref>. That sermon still seems to me a sufficient statement, and, as you may not have seen it, I take leave to send you a copy with my good wishes for the New Year.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, my dear Bishop, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>These letters of Newbolt and <persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName> suggest that there may be a revival of the famous "Lord <persName xml:id="1336">Shaftesbury</persName>&#8211;D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4373">Pusey</persName>" alliance. The peer would this time be on the "Catholick" side, &amp; the divine on the Protestant: but a "Lord <persName xml:id="586">Halifax</persName>&#8211;Dean <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName>" alliance would serve well enough to sustain the great tradition!<note xml:id="357" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
