<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1255</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" contains a short letter from <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> allying himself with <persName xml:id="4414">Darwell Stone</persName> against my consecration. <persName xml:id="359">Sanday's</persName> letter was too much for him. So the old junction of the Parties repeats itself as I expected</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>Wace will no doubt carry into the opposition camp the bulk of the older Evangelicals. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins in the Abbey, wrote letters, went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> and lunched. Sir Walter <persName xml:id="1578">Raleigh</persName> joined me. He was very emphatic in his support. Henry <persName xml:id="3946">Newbolt</persName> also came to my table in order to assure me of his goodwill. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But there were divers Bishops who looked away, or cast down their eyes, when they saw me coming</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> I received a very cordial letter from Bishop <persName xml:id="1361">D'Arcy</persName> of Down. The value of episcopal letters rises as the opposition developes. I returned to Durham by the evening train, &amp; arrived in the Deanery about midnight. A pile of letters awaited me, among which was one from the Bishop of <persName xml:id="4439">Colchester</persName>, very firmly expressed. Alfred <persName xml:id="7">Spelling</persName> tells me that after the Eucharist in the Hospital Chapel at Ilford last Sunday signatures were invited to a petition against my consecration.</hi>  
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
