<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[202]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1325</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I travelled by train to the Craven Arms, &amp; was there met by the Rev. A. M. <persName xml:id="4451">Winter</persName>, Vicar of Stokesay. I motored to Munslow where I was received by the Rector (Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> G. B. <persName xml:id="4365">Powell</persName>). Here I confirmed 16 persons. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Powell is an oldish man with a harsh manner &amp; an ill&#8211;contented aspect. He is his own Patron, &amp; says that 2/3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rds</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of his people – all told less than 500 – are sectaries. His wife is horribly crippled by arthritis</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>He gave me lunch, &amp; then drove me to Stokesay (8 miles) in his pony&#8211;trap. Here I confirmed 32 persons in an interesting old church with high pews. After tea at the Vicarage, where I met the Churchwardens, I was taken to see </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Stokesay Castle</hi><placeName xml:id="78"></placeName><hi>, a fortified mansion built in the 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> century. This is a building of great beauty, &amp; extraordinary interest. The Vicar walked with me to Craven Arms station. I got home about 8.30 p.m., &amp; found that <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had arrived shortly before.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather was perfect, and the beauty of the country displayed itself to advantage. It would be difficult to imagine more lovely rural scenery. Every element was excellent of its kind – the old churches, the picturesque "black&#8211;&amp;&#8211;white" houses, the well&#8211;tilled fields in which the young corn was springing, the large fat cattle, &amp; flocks of sheep &amp; lambs. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">But the population is dwindling</hi><hi rend="italic">: there is much discontent in the minds of the people: the clergy complain of empty churches &amp; parishioners who prefer sectarian ministrations to their own. Young men are absent in the Army, &amp; even the able&#8211;bodied girls are being requisitioned. The woods are being felled for military uses. There is a dark side to the picture.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
