<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[139]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1267</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I breakfasted with the <persName xml:id="389">Bryces</persName><persName xml:id="2896"></persName> at 3 Buckingham Gate. Our conversation was mostly about topics, theological &amp; ecclesiastical, as my situation suggested. Then I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; got my letters. </hi><hi rend="italic">There was one from the <persName xml:id="929">Bishop of Rochester</persName> to say that he could not join my consecration. So the opposing list is lengthening. It now includes <persName xml:id="49">Oxford</persName>, <persName xml:id="166">London</persName>, <persName xml:id="532">Ely</persName>, Rochester, <persName xml:id="178">Salisbury</persName>, <persName xml:id="2462">Chelmsford</persName>, and (I think) <persName xml:id="2047">Worcester</persName> – 7 bishops.</hi> <hi>There will certainly be some additional names. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Their lordships seek before all things a quiet life, &amp; they dread the vengeance of the <orgName xml:id="20">E.C.U.</orgName> if they lay hands on a heretick</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>On my side I think I can count on the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName>, and the <persName xml:id="602">Bishops of Southwark</persName>, <persName xml:id="2533">Bristol</persName>, <persName xml:id="421">Birmingham</persName>, <persName xml:id="1980">Newcastle</persName>, and, perhaps, S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="2146">David's</persName>, <persName xml:id="3489">Llandaff</persName>, <persName xml:id="31">Exeter</persName>, and <persName xml:id="1643">Lincoln</persName> – a possible 9. I walked into the City, &amp; saw a modest announcement of the Confirmation on the door of Bow Church. It is fixed for 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday. A female hailed me. She said she was Miss Miles, formerly the School&#8211;mistress at Barking. Then I lunched with <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>. Archdeacon <persName xml:id="383">Spooner</persName> was also at the Deanery. Ralph and I walked back to the Athenaeum. <persName xml:id="2216">Pease</persName>, Sir John <persName xml:id="2244">Struthers</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="42">Steel&#8211;Maitland</persName> met, and congratulated me on reaching the episcopate! In the Club I found Sir Lewis <persName xml:id="909">Dibdin</persName>. He was reading my Edinburgh article, and expressed warm agreement with it.</hi> <hi rend="bold">[140]</hi> <hi>He said that he thought that the only danger of a prosecution for heresy would come from <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> &amp; his friends, who had no scruples about the courts; but Wace had no organized party behind him, &amp; probably would do nothing further.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I dined at the House of Commons with Sir Henry <persName xml:id="344">Craik</persName>. There were also dining <persName xml:id="2063">Walter Long</persName>, Sir George <persName xml:id="4464">Younger</persName>, Colonel <persName xml:id="4487">Lucas</persName>, </hi><hi rend="underline">Stanley <persName xml:id="4118">Baldwin</persName></hi><hi>, and two whose names I forget. It was a pleasant party, &amp; the conversation was very interesting. Craik proposed my health, which was drunk with much cordiality. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I replied in a sentence: "Gentlemen, I thank you. I have not so many friends that I can undervalue those who are good enough to place themselves in that category"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> They protested that I had many more friends than I knew or suspected. It may be so, but, if so, they are like the 7000 who supported Elijah, invisible on his scenes of conflict. Walter Long in particular was most friendly. He gave an interesting account of the political situation when Lord <persName xml:id="292">Rosebery</persName> made his famous "predominant partner" speech.<note xml:id="372" n="1"></note> It appears that a considerable section of the Unionist party were not at the moment disinclined to accept Rosebery as leader, &amp; that the speech was made on an understanding with them. But almost immediately he withdrew his speech in another: &amp; when challenged by Long as to his reason replied that while he had received a multitude of protests from the Home Rule ranks, he had rec</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> no expressions of approval from the Unionists! Such a reason disposes of his character as a leader.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
