<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1258</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A letter from </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1082">Fawkes</persName></hi><hi> tells me that there is a prayer leaflet being circulated with the collect for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Matthias' Day! This is a mode of suggesting that I am the modern equivalent of "the traitor Judas"!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Ernest <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName></hi><hi> sends me </hi><hi rend="underline">Geoffrey Dawson's<persName xml:id="2709"></persName></hi><hi> reply to his letter: he writes:</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"My own feeling,</hi> <hi rend="underline">qu&#x00E2;</hi><hi> journalist, is that the public at large are becoming slightly bored by the discussion, but that they will be overwhelmingly on the side of Henson if the higher authorities were in any sense to make a martyr of him."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>It is , however, not the "public at large" which really counts in the affairs of the Church, but that small, fanatical "religious" public, whose tastes &amp; ideals are expressed by the "religious" press.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Canon <persName xml:id="4234">Glazebrook</persName>, as Chairman of the Council of the <orgName xml:id="38">Churchmen's Union</orgName>, sent me the following resolution of the Council:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"The Council of the Churchmen's Union welcome the appointment of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Hensley Henson to the Bishoprick of Hereford, for they believe it will advance the cause of true religion in England."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Bishop <persName xml:id="3694">Mercer</persName> wrote to me in kindly terms. Episcopal letters are now important. I have now received no less than 45 but of these at least 7 must be marked as doubtful, &amp; of the remaining 38, I doubt whether many represent any genuine sentiment of support for me and what I stand for. I wrote to the <persName xml:id="4450">Archdeacon of Hereford</persName> saying that I hoped to carry through the programme of confirmations arranged.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
