<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1329</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The alteration to summer time took effect this morning and made one a little reluctant to get up: but when once the effort had been made, virtue was well&#8211;rewarded. I went to the cathedral, &amp; received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. </hi><hi rend="italic">At 11 a.m.</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">for the first time I preached in the Cathedral</hi><hi rend="italic">. My sermon was one which I wrote for Palm Sunday, and preached in Westminster Abbey </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">before I was a canon</hi><hi rend="italic">, 19 or 20 years ago, from the text S. Mark X.37, 38. I added a few sentences about the fearful conflict now proceeding in France, and read two prayers from the pulpit. There was a large congregation, of which a considerable proportion appeared to be munition girls. They were attentive, &amp; I think they could all hear, though the acoustics of the cathedral are none too good, but I suspect that the sermon was of a type to which they were unaccustomed. We lunched with <persName xml:id="3618">Archdeacon</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="4307">Lilley</persName>, with whom was M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="4182">Cuthbert</persName>. Conversation turned inevitably on the war, and the ladies expressed such Hunnish sentiments that I was led to express myself with more decision than is perhaps prudent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>There was a very large congregation at Evensong, when I preached again. The sermon had been originally written for use in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> on Palm Sunday, 1911, and I inserted some references to the soldiers.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
