<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1312</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I called on Mess</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Beavan &amp; Hodges, who had sent the specifications for the drains at the Palace, and ascertained that, on the most favourable hypothesis, I could not hope to get into the Palace before the end of May. In view of this prospect, I wrote to </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon <persName xml:id="3619">Bannister</persName></hi><hi> inquiring whether he would feel disposed to let his house for the months of April &amp; May.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4345">Norcock</persName></hi><hi> went with me [to] Tenbury. We were met on the platform by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Prebendary <persName xml:id="4377">Ragg</persName></hi><hi>, and walked to the Vicarage. There were 108 candidates, (of whom the majority were males,) at the Confirmation. These came from 9 or 10 parishes. I gave an address from 2. Tim: II.3 "</hi><hi rend="underline">Suffer hardship with me, as a good soldier of Jesus Christ</hi><hi>". There was much tiresome delay in returning. It was nearly 9 p.m. when I got home.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Prebendary Ragg</hi><hi> preceded the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. John <persName xml:id="4264">Henson</persName></hi><hi> as head&#8211;master of the Cathedral School. He has a wife, who looks competent, and three grown up children, two girls &amp; a boy. Also one small boy, who is a pet, &amp; something of an eccentrick! He presented me with an original poem, on the new Bishop of Hereford!! The parish of Tenbury contains about 1200 people. It is on the borders of the three counties – Worcester, Shropshire, &amp; Hereford – and is traversed by a rapid river, the Team. </hi><hi rend="underline">All the boys, with few exceptions, had a loutish, almost brutal look: the girls were more intelligent in appearance</hi><hi>. A lad – </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick Smith</hi><hi> – who brought my bag to the station – was an inn&#8211;keeper's son, &amp; rather superior.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
