<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1308</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the time between breakfast &amp; Mattins in preparing the address </hi><hi rend="underline">for my first Confirmation</hi><hi> which is to take place this afternoon in a little parish, cheerfully named Puddleston. There will be but 10 candidates, too few for such a function. My text is S. James IV.8. "</hi><hi rend="underline">Draw nigh to God, &amp; He will draw nigh to you</hi><hi>". I begin by some general observations on the "covenant method" with its 2 implications of man's freedom, &amp; the conditioning of God's gifts by his exercise of it. After showing that this method governs all human life, I speak particularly of its application to Religion. I ask, Why must there be co&#8211;operation between God &amp; Man before God's Blessing can answer to man's necessity?, and I reply that it is because Man comes from God, &amp; is only then truly human when he is in sympathy with his Maker. I go on to speak particularly of Confirmation. Then after a few words to the Congregation, I address the Candidates on the prerogatives of Youth. "Remember that there is this great difference between youth &amp; age: that when we are young, we live on hopes, &amp; when we are old, we must live on memories. In youth we fashion the memories which will comfort or shame us in later life. Habits are chains: ill memories are stains. While we are young, we have the power of avoiding both. But how? By the help of God given always in response to our appeal. Confirmation opens the way to Holy Communion, the supreme example of the Covenant Method".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[183]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral for Mattins &amp; the Holy Communion (choral). The throne is ill&#8211;placed for the Bishop's edification; indeed I could hear nothing of lessons or sermon but a stray word, now &amp; again. I pronounced the Absolution and the Blessing according to the Rubrick. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">My first Confirmation was not without difficulty for the hired car broke down at once, &amp; had to be replaced with an open car</hi><hi rend="italic">. In this I arrived at Puddleston about 15 minutes after time, &amp; in a frozen condition. </hi><persName xml:id="4345"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Norcock</hi></persName><hi rend="italic"> went with me, &amp; brought the crozier. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">There were but 6 candidates</hi><hi rend="italic"> – 4 boys &amp; 2 girls.</hi><hi> The parson,</hi> <persName xml:id="4322"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Martin</hi></persName><hi>, is a tall, good&#8211;looking man with a strong voice. He told me that he once ranched in California: then was ordained by </hi><persName xml:id="325"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ryle</hi></persName><hi> in the Exeter diocese as a "perpetual deacon": then was made priest by </hi><persName xml:id="358"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robertson</hi></persName><hi>. His squire &amp; organist is </hi><persName xml:id="4456"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi></persName><hi>, a Birmingham financier who is secretary of the diocesan finance. The parish contains about 200 souls, &amp; is entirely rural. The church, dedicated to S. Peter, is mainly modern. The service was reverent, &amp;, I hope, edifying. While we had tea at the Vicarage, the chauffeur went to Leominster, &amp; got a good car. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Wright</hi><hi> lent me a fur&#8211;coat. So I returned home in comfort. </hi><persName xml:id="112"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi></persName><hi> &amp; </hi><persName xml:id="3487"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Cooper</hi></persName><hi> arrived in our own car from Durham. They left on Friday morning: stayed in Newark for Friday night: &amp; at <placeName xml:id="83">Stow House</placeName>, Lichfield, on Saturday. Youd drove well, &amp; the car seems to have done nothing worse than a series of punctures.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[184]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName></hi><hi> called for me at a few minutes after 8 p.m., &amp; took me to the <placeName xml:id="84">Kemble Theatre</placeName>, where a public meeting in connexion with the "War Aims Committee's" movement<orgName xml:id="301"></orgName> was arranged. The building was filled with a representative &amp; enthusiastic multitude. In the chair was M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4212">Mayor</persName>, &amp; I sate on his right hand. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4387">Roberts</persName>, the Minister of Labour, and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4273">Hewins</persName> the local M.P., Under&#8211;Secretary for the Colonies, were the principal speakers. I moved a resolution, which was seconded by M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Evans, a local Labour leader. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">When I rose, the meeting gave me much applause</hi><hi rend="italic">. </hi><hi>The proceedings did not end until nearly 11 p.m.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
