<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[177]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, February 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1305</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote letters in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName> for an hour: called at the Office of Queen Anne's Bounty<orgName xml:id="296"></orgName> in <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; transacted a matter of diocesan business: saw <persName xml:id="249">Gamble</persName> &amp; explained that I was "dining out" on March 9</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> &amp; 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>: attending a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="156" display="no">Ecclesiastical Commission</orgName>: &amp; went for a short walk with <persName xml:id="117">Rashdall</persName>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I met </hi><persName xml:id="3581"><hi rend="underline">Barnes</hi></persName><hi> who told me that the Benchers were well&#8211;pleased with my sermon on Feb: 10</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>, that he himself had read it, &amp; thought it a very sufficient answer to my opponents, the more sufficient since it was indirect.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Also I met <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName>, who told me that the amount of truth in Lord <persName xml:id="586">Halifax's</persName> statement that a bishop had originally proposed my name for bishoprick was the following. Lord <persName xml:id="3220">Stamfordham</persName> had written to him during the vacancy suggesting an interview; that on their meeting he had mentioned the King's desire, and also <persName xml:id="234">Lloyd&#8211;George's</persName> to make me a bishop; &amp; that, as he understood that he (Burge) was a friend of mine, he came to consult him on the matter</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="1820">Charles</persName></hi><hi> told me as a great secret that the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> had asked for a Sunday in June in which to preach in the Abbey on the subject of clerical subscription. On the whole this is probably to be regretted, as his Grace is pretty sure to minimize the significance of his own action in proceeding with my Consecration: &amp; he </hi><hi rend="underline">may</hi><hi> be led to say something which I should have to repudiate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Kenworthy Brown</hi><persName xml:id="4145"></persName><hi> came to see me by appointment. He desires to be licensed as a curate in&#8211;charge of the district of S. Barnabas, which is part of the parish of All Saints, in Hereford, whereof the man </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Treherne</hi><persName xml:id="4426"></persName><hi> is Vicar, a fanatick &amp; the ring&#8211;leader of the opposition against me. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Brown</hi><hi> is a well&#8211;grown man of 28, who took a fair degree at Jesus Coll. Cambridge. He was ordained to the parish of Monmouth, but had left parochial work in order to join the Benedictine Community at Pershore<placeName xml:id="83"></placeName>, where he had continued 3 years. He had now reached the decision that he had no vocation to monkery, &amp; wished to return to parochial work. He was responsible for two orphanages, which it was proposed to establish in the parish of All Saints: Before accepting appointment, he wished to get some kind of guarantee from me, that his work w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be permanent, &amp; since he c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> not continue it if he were not permitted to carry it on as he wished, to know whether I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> permit reservation, incense &amp;c &amp;c. We had some talk together for more than an hour. </hi><hi rend="underline">On the point of private confession he was strangely unreasonable</hi><hi>. I asked what w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be his treatment of Confirmation Candidates in this respect. He gave a discursive reply, of which I conceived the gist that he sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> teach that mortal sins c</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="underline">only</hi><hi> be forgiven after confession to the priest. I did not dislike the young man, but he is clearly hopeless from a disciplinary point of view, &amp; was probably sent to me with a purpose.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
