<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1317</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The weather was unfavourable, being steadily wet. I travelled by train to Ross (9.55 a.m.–10.26 a.m.), &amp; was there met by the Vicar of Ross,</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4330">Money–Kyrle</persName></hi><hi>, who drove me to Bridstow. The <persName xml:id="4450">Archdeacon</persName> was in the church arranging the candidates. I confirmed 47 females and 19 males: and then, after lunching at Bridstow Vicarage, went on to Westow, where I confirmed 80 more, the numerical superiority of the gentler sex being again marked.</hi> <hi rend="italic">In both confirmations I was pleased with the evident care taken in arranging the service, &amp; with the reverent demeanour of the candidates.</hi> <hi>At Bridstow I took as the text of my address Hebrews XII. 1, 2: &amp; the Archdeacon was good enough to express approval of what I said! At Westow I repeated the address on Eph: V.15, 16. The return to Hereford was a tiresome &amp; dilatory performance. Scarcely had I settled at my table before </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4155">Butterworth</persName></hi><hi>, the Diocesan Missioner, came to see me. He is full–filled with all the energetic conventions of his class, &amp; is destined, I fear, to be woefully disappointed with his new bishop. I told him that all organized meetings (conferences, retreats, &amp; quiet days) ought to cease during the War, as all entailed travelling &amp; entertainment, both of which have become very difficult. The station–master this morning told me that more passenger trains are to be cut off in order to make the munitions–traffic easier.<note xml:id="466" n="1"></note> It will soon be practically impossible to get about the diocese at all, except by means of a motor–car. The supply of petrol may be cut off, &amp; then we are completely immobilized.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[194]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p><hi>To Hubert D. <persName xml:id="4109">Astley</persName> Esq.</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>March 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Astley,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You &amp; your friends are most kind to take such thought for my clothing, but I should have no use for cope &amp; mitre, &amp; therefore any money expended on them would be thrown away. May I venture to suggest that in this stern time, there are objects of benevolence which may better gain the assistance of religious citizens than the purchase of archaic vestments, the aspect &amp; significance of which have generally perished from English minds</hi><hi rend="bold underline">?</hi> 
<hi>But your letter was conceived in a lighter vein, &amp; I should apologize for taking it so gravely.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, ever sincerely yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I motored to Abbeydore, and administered Confirmation to 37 candidates, &amp; then, after lunching at the Vicarage, went on to Michaelchurch, &amp; confirmed 32, among whom was an old woman of 96. The church at Abbeydore is magnificent, though but a fragment of the monastic fabric. It has an added historic interest as having been restored by </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4401">Lord Scudamore</persName></hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Laud's</hi><hi> friend &amp; disciple. The wood–work – rails, stalls, screen, and musician's gallery – are all Jacobean or early Caroline work. Nothing could exceed the beauty of the early English ambulatory behind the high altar.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[195]</hi>         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the People's Warden, Bredwardine</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>March 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Madam,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I cannot, of course, enter on any discussion of the untoward incidents wh. have gathered about the question of appointing a new Incumbent for your parish, but I will merely observe that it cannot be to the advantage of the parish that the controversy should be protracted any longer, &amp; certainly it cannot benefit </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4011">Jobling</persName></hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I hope that, as People's Warden, you will exert yourself to create harmony among the parishioners so that the new Incumbent may be able to enter on his duties under favourable conditions.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very faithfully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Beatrice <persName xml:id="4363">Burton–Phillipson</persName></hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I had supper with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4448">Wynne–Willson</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> in order to meet <persName xml:id="4449">his brother</persName>, the Dean of Bristol. We had some interesting conversation on the burning question of "law &amp; order" in the Church. W. W. walked back to the Close with me. He is evidently feeling his way towards "liberal" opinions in theology, &amp; rather surprised me by his expressions about the Virgin–Birth &amp;c.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Vicar of Abbey Dore is the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> G. E. P. <persName xml:id="4162">Cave–Moyle</persName></hi><hi>, a youngish man who has served as a chaplain for the last two years.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Vicar of Michaelchurch is the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. W. <persName xml:id="4259">Head</persName></hi><hi>, also a young man – with babies!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[196]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> Thomas Hobhouse.</hi>
  </p>
         <p>
<hi>March 14</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear Sir, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have to acknowledge your letter of the 13</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> March, &amp; in reply to say that I cannot see my way to accept you as a candidate for Ordination. Your age &amp; blindness form obstacles wh. do not seem to me capable of removal, &amp;, therefore I must go against my own wishes, &amp; return to your request a non possumus.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours very faithfully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The above was my answer to a request for ordination from a Baptist Minister, 48 years old, and "almost blind", who said that "he was in great demand as a Preacher among the Nonconformists", and possessed a private income.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I travelled to Bridgenorth, &amp; was met by </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="4457">Wright</persName></hi><hi>, the Rural Dean, who took me to the Infirmary where I talked to the wounded soldiers. Then I went to a meeting of the <orgName xml:id="198">Bible Society</orgName> in the Town Hall, &amp; made a speech in answer to an Address moved by some sectarian minister &amp; seconded by the Rural Dean. After having tea with </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Preb: <persName xml:id="4167">Clarke Maxwell</persName></hi><hi>, I was driven to Morville, where the 800</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> anniversary of the founding of the <placeName xml:id="86">Priory</placeName> was celebrated by a special service. I preached the sermon. There was a large congregation, &amp; seven neighbouring incumbents were in the procession. The service was very hearty: &amp; I think there was a good spirit in the people.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
