<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1281</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The "Times" contains a pronouncement by the Bishop of <persName xml:id="111">Southwell</persName>, very offensively worded. He speaks of me as "recanting", as "having only myself to blame", and so forth. It made me very angry indeed at first, and then I reflected that the Bishop of Southwell was really not worth powder &amp; shot</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Club</orgName>, and there met the <persName xml:id="225">Archbishop of Dublin</persName>. He said that he thought I had been treated abominably. That is my own opinion of course. I walked to the Post Office in Parliament Street, &amp; sent off telegrams to the <persName xml:id="3741">Dean of Hereford</persName>, &amp; Bishop <persName xml:id="667">Walsh</persName>, fixing the Enthronement for Shrove Tuesday (Feb. 12</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>). As I returned to the Club, I fell in with Rowland <persName xml:id="1394">Prothero</persName>, &amp; exchanged a few words. He also thinks the Bishops have behaved abominably. Sir <persName xml:id="2180">Robert Morant</persName> met me, and said the same.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the morning in writing letters in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName><note xml:id="378" n="1"></note>, and lunched there with <persName xml:id="3706">Bayley</persName> [Bailey] as my table&#8211;companion. Then I fetched <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> from the Deanery (S. Paul's) and took her to Lambeth, where we were to be the guests of the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi><persName xml:id="404">Davidson</persName>. I dined with the <orgName xml:id="66">Brotherhood</orgName> which met at <persName xml:id="216">Gow's</persName> House. After dinner I walked back to Lambeth, arriving just in time for prayers. Before going to bed, I had some talk with the Archbishop.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
