<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">The Epiphany, January 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1252</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m. &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. The church was cold, &amp; there were but few communicants.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">On returning to my room I wrote my reply to the Bishops of <persName xml:id="166">London</persName> and <persName xml:id="105">Winchester</persName></hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">The post brought letters from the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> and the <persName xml:id="301">Bishop of Truro</persName>. These also I answered. It is plain enough that the Farnham section of High Church Bishops will support <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> with ample professions of personal distress in the process! Talbot, Gore, Burrows, Ingram, <persName xml:id="3536">Gibson</persName>, and probably <persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> will go together, and they will draw to their side <persName xml:id="2462">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</persName> certainly, and probably some more Evangelicals.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Service of Prayer &amp; Thanksgiving was attended by a great concourse. Major <persName xml:id="2808">Rowlandson</persName> brought 25 men of the D.L.I. to attend the service. They headed the procession: &amp; after the service I spoke briefly to them in the Chapter House. Four dissenting ministers attended, &amp; two of them – <persName xml:id="4279">Hooper</persName>, a Congregationalist, and <persName xml:id="4004">Fletcher</persName>, a Wesleyan – read the Lessons. The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop</persName> preached well, but far too long. He is too elaborately rhetorical for these people. His voice is wonderful for a man of his years. After service Ladies <persName xml:id="2817">Londonderry</persName> and <persName xml:id="4220">Helmsley</persName>, <persName xml:id="3833">Col.</persName> &amp; Miss Blackitt, the <persName xml:id="3718">High Sherriff</persName>, M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4333"></persName><hi> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4332">Morant</persName>, and some others came in to tea.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi> 
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the Bishop of Winchester</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have received your letter, and thank you sincerely for the kind expressions which it contains. It needs no saying that I appreciate and reciprocate your goodwill.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You will not doubt that I have considered with anxious care the suggestion which you are good enough to make to me, and you will believe that in declining it I am actuated by no petty or merely personal considerations.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It does not appear to me fitting in itself, or serviceable to any good purpose, that I should before my consecration make any statement of the nature which you propose. Nor can I admit that any such statement can fairly be asked of me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, my dear Bishop, most sincerely yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I wrote in practically identical terms to the Bishop of London.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="4450">Archdeacon of Hereford</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Archdeacon,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is good of you to send me the Report of your Christmas Sermon, which I have read with much interest, and a clear sense of the just intention which inspires it.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Someday, if God will, in quieter times we will talk over these grave matters as colleagues and friends. Meanwhile it will suffice if I endorse heartily your assurance of my unity with you and your people in the worship of the Incarnate.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It had been on my mind to send you my thanks for your good offices in my election. I cannot believe that the kind of agitation carried on by the <orgName xml:id="20">English Church Union</orgName> within and without the diocese can commend itself to any fair&#8211;minded Christian man, however conservative his beliefs.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am, my dear Archdeacon,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours most sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div><p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
