<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[119]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1256</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> protest to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> against my consecration appears in the "Times". It will be a new peg on which the enemy can hang protests &amp; declarations. I wrote a number of letters to such of my correspondents as could not wisely be left unanswered. There can be no doubt that the letters of <persName xml:id="4414">Darwell Stone</persName> and <persName xml:id="359">Sanday</persName>, from opposite points, have alarmed older men. <persName xml:id="212">Wace</persName> has declared himself in print. </hi> <hi rend="bold underline">John <persName xml:id="348">Murray</persName>, who had written to the "Times" on my side, withdrew his letter</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Bishop of <persName xml:id="31">Exeter</persName> writes to say that he is reading my books, &amp; finds them disturbing. A clergymen, who had written to me a letter of congratulation, now writes "to ask leave to withdraw his letter of satisfaction at my appointment to Hereford", because he desires to "support D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Wace if I cannot repudiate D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Sanday's exposition of my views"!</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">I do not doubt that Sanday's letter has added to my immediate difficulties, though it compels the full gravity of the movement against my consecration to be seen</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>He is not intelligible to the general public, very alarming to the clergy, and only half acceptable to the educated Churchman. His authority now is far more based on his record than on his declarations. Edgar <persName xml:id="3572">Dobbie</persName> came to see me, and stayed to lunch. I attended a meeting of the Naval Flag day Committee in the Mayor's Parlour &amp; moved a Resolution. Miss <persName xml:id="3427">Lang</persName>, formerly of Broadmeadows, was here today, breaking her journey homewards to the South of Scotland.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[120]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="325">Dean of Westminster</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am told that I ought to ask two Bishops to present me to the Archbishop for Consecration. It had been in my mind to ask you and the Bishop of <persName xml:id="602">Southwark</persName>. I am not sure whether the etiquette or even the rule limits me to Diocesans: but I hope not, because I particularly desire to have you as the Head of the Foundation on which for 12 years I had a place. You will know how these things are done: &amp;, if you can do this for me, I should be grateful.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>It is odd how history repeats itself. The old combination of <persName xml:id="1336">Shaftesbury</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4373">Pusey</persName> against <persName xml:id="171">Temple</persName> is now revived in the new alliance of Wace &amp; <persName xml:id="586">Halifax</persName> against me.<note xml:id="357" n="1"></note> How far these exasperated Octogenarians will be followed by their rank &amp; file remains to be seen. It is a little hard on me that almost all the younger men, who are my natural champions, are military chaplains, and compulsorily silent: while I myself have decided to say nothing before my consecration. However, these things right themselves in the long run.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Always, my dear Bishop, affectionately yours, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>Gore's protest is an echo of his charge: &amp; in view of his teaching &amp; policy was inevitable. That is the real explanation of the alarm of certain bishops. They have "burnt their ships" on the specific issues, &amp; must "save their faces".</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
