<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1330</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The news from France is disquieting, for it is evident that the Germans have broken through our lines, and are still pressing the attack with tremendous vigour. The "</hi> 
<hi rend="underline">Times</hi><hi>" discusses the possibility of their capturing Amiens.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Archbishop <persName xml:id="2166">S&#x00F6;derblom</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Gabriellson</hi><hi rend="italic"> before breakfast. Also, I paid my quarter's episcopal income into the Bank (&#x00A3;787.10.0).</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">After lunch I went to Shrewsbury, &amp; was there met by a lady in a little open two&#8211;seater car, &amp; driven to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pontesbury</hi><hi rend="italic">, a distance of about 9 miles, where there are 3 rectorships of the one church, &amp;, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">of course, a long tradition of quarrelling</hi><hi rend="italic">. M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> <persName xml:id="4403">Seddon</persName> holds two of these rectories, and thus mitigates the scandal. He is an elderly man with a side&#8211;long look &amp; rather an aggressive manner. He told me that the living was worth &#x00A3;1700 per annum, &amp; that the patron was his sister&#8211;in&#8211;law. His wife has recently become a papist to his extreme annoyance. I confirmed 75 persons in Pontesbury Church. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The arrangements were ill&#8211;made</hi><hi rend="italic">; there was a slovenly &amp; heartless manner in the clergy, which displeased me. After tea in the parish hall, I went to Shrewsbury, &amp; thence proceeded to Church Stretton, where I confirmed 70 persons in the parish church. This service was well&#8211;arranged, &amp; I took a favourable impression. The Rector (Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> S. C. <persName xml:id="4453">Woods</persName>) was there: he is acting as a chaplain</hi> <hi rend="bold">[208]</hi> <hi>[symbol] </hi><hi rend="italic">at Southampton. His wife is a sister of M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Sadler, who lives in Durham. The acting&#8211;Rector is a returned <orgName xml:id="124">C.M.S.</orgName> Missionary named Davies, rather a good specimen of an unattractive type. I stayed the night at the Rectory.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
