<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[204]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1327</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Great Offensive is reported at last on a front of 50 miles. At least we are assured that the Germans did not possess the advantage of surprise. Both British &amp; French expected the attack. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me in the car to Stowe, a little parish in the Radnorshire hills; here I confirmed 25 persons, including 8 soldiers from the local hospital. The service was very reverent, &amp;, I trust, edifying. There was a magnificent prospect from the Church porch, &amp; this was seen at its best in the superb weather. After tea at the Vicarage, we motored to Knighton, &amp; visited the military hospital, which has been established in the workhouse. M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi>Rogers, the wife of the Squire of Stow [sic], &amp; a cousin of General <persName xml:id="4103">Allenby</persName>, is the Superintendent. We motored home through fair </hi><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi> <hi rend="italic">scenery, &amp; admired a magnificent sunset. The car did the distance, over 70 miles without accident. The effect of the open air is to make me woefully sleepy at a scandalously early hour.</hi><hi> I suppose one's efficiency does rapidly diminish on the shady side of fifty! Certainly </hi><hi rend="underline">mine</hi><hi> does.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Rev. Canon <persName xml:id="2716">Willink</persName>, Rector of Birmingham</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>March 22</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear Canon Willink,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Some while back I promised to preach in Carr's Lane Church on Sunday, the 14</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> of April next: &amp; I do not propose as Bishop of Hereford to "dishonour the bills" I signed as Dean of Durham. On the contrary I hope that in my new capacity I may be the more able to advance the cause of better relations between the C. of E. &amp; the churches of the English Dispersion. The Bishop of <persName xml:id="421">Birmingham</persName>, who gives me his "full consent to preach at Carr's Lane", tells me what I did not know, that that church is in your parish.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I write to let you know, therefore, of my approaching visit &amp; to suggest, if your wishes in this matter harmonize so far with my own, that I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> preach in the parish church on the same day, April 14th, in the evening. That w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> give me, perhaps, the opportunity of some conference with you on the policy wh. sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be followed in order to establish on a satisfactory basis that interchange of pulpits, for wh. the general conscience is certainly prepared, &amp; wh. ought to be one consequence of the War.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours ever sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
