<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1283</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I read the Latin Litany in a thinly&#8211;attended House, and then sate all day at the debates, lunching with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>. I spoke several times, and, on the question of restoring All Souls Day to the calendar, was in a narrow majority which rejected the proposal.<note xml:id="379" n="1"></note> Also, I assisted to reject the proposal to re&#8211;insert King Charles the Martyr. I was interviewed by an American journalist named Griggs, who came to me in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>. Then I read through the six sermons on Christian Liberty, &amp; sent them to Macmillans as a first instalment of the <ref xml:id="967">volume</ref>. <persName xml:id="225">Archbishop Bernard</persName> arrived at Lambeth. He is not confident of success in the matter of the Irish Convention, but he refuses to despair. He says that Bishop <persName xml:id="1361">D'Arcy</persName> ordains men who are educationally inadequate, &amp; thus defeats his attempts to keep up the standard of education in the Irish clergy. </hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Somebody sent me the letter which the <persName xml:id="1643">Bishop of Lincoln</persName> wrote in his Diocesan Magazine about my election as Bishop of Hereford. It is generously expressed, &amp; reflects real credit on the Bishop. He told me that he had made up his mind to take part in my Consecration before the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> had issued his reply to <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> protest. If the Bishop of Lincoln were not so deeply bitten by all the Radical absurdities, he would be a creditable type of prelate. But one cannot go far with even the best of men who is a feminist, and a total abstainer, and three parts a pacifist</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
