<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[124]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1260</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The bitter cold continues, and makes the process of living more irksome &amp; difficult at every point. It must be dreadful at the Front, yet a letter from <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> was wonderfully cheerful.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a long letter the Rev. W</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi> L. <persName xml:id="4240">Groves</persName>, Rector of Much Birch, Hereford. He has "procured a copy" of "Notes of my Ministry"<ref xml:id="87"></ref>, and finds it extremely alarming. He says that he has "ascertained the opinions of eleven of the clergy of his neighbourhood" and finds that only one approves my appointment!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>An anonymous letter from Folkestone calls upon me to withdraw my acceptance of the bishoprick. On the other hand, an anonymous telegram arrived from London S.W. in these terms:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"Blessed is he that hath the God of Jacob for his help. He will go from strength to strength until he attain unto the City of the Divine Temple."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I don't recognize the passage, but the intention of the author seems to be friendly. The parson, <persName xml:id="4172">Cohu</persName>, writes to exhort me to stand firm, and old M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi>J. R. <persName xml:id="4339">Mozley</persName> writes to tell me that he has sent a letter to the "Church Times", &amp; to send me a copy of it. </hi><hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="4246">Hall</persName>, who was Dean of Oriel when I was a member of that Common Room 33 years ago sends me a friendly postcard</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> A copy of the "Hereford Times" contains an elaborate array of extracts from my works designed to demonstrate my heresy. The rustics of Hereford must be badly puzzled.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[125]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="underline"> W</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi><hi rend="underline"> L. Groves</hi>
</p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Groves,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am obliged to you for your letter, and, though of course I w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> wish that you were not so much alarmed at what you conceive to be my defects, yet I have a natural love of candour, &amp; have ever in my experience found that friendship &amp; confidence can grow from that root. On the questions of doctrine &amp;c. referred to I can say nothing before my consecration for reasons wh. must be obvious to every honourable man.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Let me add that I have received a good many letters from clergy &amp; laity in the diocese of Hereford assuring me of a loyal and kindly welcome. I observe that great efforts have been, and are being, made to create an atmosphere of panic in the diocese, and that circumstance will undoubtedly add to my difficulties. But these situations are not unfamiliar in ecclesiastical history, and, sooner or later, they right themselves.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, sincerely yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[126]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p><hi rend="underline">To the Bishop of <persName xml:id="929">Rochester</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am very much obliged to you for your letter, in which I allow myself to perceive a friendly intention.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>But I remain immovably convinced that no good purpose w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be served by any statement from me, &amp;, indeed, that it would be highly improper for me to make one.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The effect of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="359">Sanday's</persName> letter and Bishop <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> protest has been to de&#8211;personalize and de&#8211;localize the issue. It is objected that such opinions as mine ought to disqualify for </hi><hi rend="underline">any</hi><hi> Bishoprick. Hence we have a large question raised. New Testament criticism with its inevitable bearing on the understanding of the Creed is on trial in my case, as Old Testament criticism was in Bishop <persName xml:id="171">Temple's</persName> half a century ago. History is repeating itself in the junction </hi><hi rend="underline">ad hoc</hi><hi> of the <persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> &amp; Lord <persName xml:id="586">Halifax</persName>.<note xml:id="357" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am distressed that this conflict should have come now, but for that I am not responsible. That it was bound to come sooner or later must have been apparent to any considering observer of events within the Church: &amp; of course I stand for liberty.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ever sincerely yours, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson</hi>
         </p>
</div>
          <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
