<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, February 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1287</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The sermon which I shall preach in the <orgName xml:id="37">Temple</orgName> this morning will necessarily be heard and criticized on the assumption that it was composed with direct &amp; deliberate reference to the controversy which has raged around my name during the last six weeks.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Yet it is the fact that the said sermon was written nearly two years ago, and that my present contributions are limited to a few verbal changes, designed to improve its literary form, and to a few connecting sentences intended to make clearer its argument</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Its text is formed of three passages from the New Testament, viz. S. John VII.48 "Hath any of the rulers believed on Him, or of the Pharisees? But this multitude which knoweth not the Law are accursed. S. Matthew XI.25. "Thou didst reveal them unto babes. 1. Corinthians I.20. "Hath not God made foolish the wisdom of the world?" The essence of the Gospel is thus disclosed in contrast with the spirit of the Pharisees. Perhaps this contrast will be understood to indicate my opinion of my opponents. And if indeed this should be the case, have I any reason to regret it? Such an opinion would only be unfair to the Pharisees, who were at least for the most part sincere in their bigotry, </hi><hi rend="bold underline">whereas I find it impossible to postulate sincerity in the case of many (not all, but certainly of many) of those who have organized this "heresy–hunt"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[164]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I began the day devoutly by receiving the Sacrament in S. Paul's Cathedral. After breakfast, I spent an hour in revising my discourse, and then we walked with <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> to the Temple. The church was densely crowded, and many are said to have failed to gain admission at all. The service was very beautiful, especially the chanting of the Psalms. My sermon was closely listened to, and took a full half–hour in delivery. Many of the choirboys got me to write in their autograph books. Several reporters, including one from the "Herefordshire Times" besieged me after the service. I rashly allowed the latter to have the MS. on his undertaking to send it to the "Guardian" to which it had been promised. We lunched at the Middle Temple very pleasantly with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><persName xml:id="4475"><hi> M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Call</persName>. Justices <persName xml:id="4032">Darling</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4395">Salter</persName> were there, &amp; both friendly.
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="648">Caröe</persName> with <persName xml:id="2127">his wife</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="1951">Christian</persName> came to tea, also <persName xml:id="1178">Clarence Stock</persName> and his Italian friend. I wrote to <persName xml:id="76">Carissima</persName>. To supper came <persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, and after the meal we sate round the drawing room fire, &amp; talked together till bed–time. So ends the last Sunday before I am enmeshed in diocesan chains, &amp; "driven to and fro in Adria" by the pressure of incumbents and societies!<note xml:id="381" n="1"></note> There yet intervenes the truly terrifying prospect of getting out of the Deanery at Durham and into the Palace at Hereford. And the financial problem raised by all these proceedings remains unsolved, and is perhaps insoluble!!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
