<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Septuagesima, January 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1273</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>A deep melancholy came over me as I reflected that this would be the last time of my service as Dean at the Altar of Durham Cathedral. In Frank Campbell's little collection of the Prayer&#8211;Book collects<ref xml:id="966"></ref> arranged for daily use, the collect for this day matched my mood. It was headed "The Sanctification of Trouble", &amp; runs thus:–</hi> 
         </p>
<div type="quote">
         <p>
<hi>We humbly beseech thee, O Father, mercifully to look upon our infirmities; and for the glory of thy Name turn from us all those evils that we most righteously have deserved, and grant, that in all our troubles we may put our whole trust and confidence in thy mercy, and evermore serve thee in holiness and pureness of living, to thy honour and glory; through our only Mediator and Advocate, Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>At 8 a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion. All the canons were there, except <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName>, and both the schoolmasters. The King's Scholars &amp; choir boys came in their surplices, &amp; we sang 3 hymns. A large number of the boys from the School communicated. It was all very solemn and moving. The <persName xml:id="1980">Bishop of Newcastle</persName> &amp; M</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="1981">Wild</persName> communicated, as well as <persName xml:id="648">Car&#x00F6;e</persName>. Beyond these there were not many except from the College. Thus ends my service at the Altar. May God forgive the sin, and accept the desire! The extreme coldness of the Cathedral, where the heating apparatus has now been inoperative for a whole month, may have hindered the devotion of the boys, &amp; didn't help the worship of any.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[150]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName> came to tell me that old D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell</persName> had passed away. I ordered the bell to be tolled, and prepared an obituary paragraph for insertion in my sermon. At 10 a.m. I preached to the troops, who filled the Nave. Lillingston preached at Mattins. The "Dead March" was played after the service. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">At 3 p.m. the Commemoration of Founders &amp; Benefactors was observed</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Three honorary canons appeared, &amp; one of the Durham incumbents (<persName xml:id="3958">Thomas</persName>). The University was fairly represented: the <persName xml:id="3773">Mayor</persName> &amp; Corporation attended in state. A good many of the county people came in, and there was a great congregation. I <ref xml:id="991">preached</ref> from Isaiah xl. 6&#8211;8 &amp; 1 S. John ii. 17, after reading from the pulpit the Form of Commemoration. It was a difficult performance, at which I felt disposed to sit down &amp; cry. However I got through it, and then had to assist in entertaining a drawing&#8211;room full of guests at tea. Among these was Sir Robert <persName xml:id="1552">Williams</persName> and his daughter, who are in these parts on <orgName xml:id="124">C.M.S.</orgName> business. There was much kindness in everybody, and many expressions of goodwill. Then, the general company having departed, I talked with my guests, and went to bed at midnight feeling much exhausted. <persName xml:id="2920">Gee</persName>, now freshly be&#8211;gaitered as Dean of Gloucester, tells me that Greenwell's funeral is to be on Wednesday, and thinks that I ought to be there. This is a fresh derangement of my plans, for that was the day on which I had promised <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName> that I would come up to town.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
