<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1264</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> answer to <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> is printed </hi><hi rend="underline">in extenso</hi><hi> in the morning papers together with his letter to me &amp; my answers. Perhaps I may infer from the publication that the Abp. has satisfied himself that the enemy has abandoned the plan of a prosecution for heresy. On the whole, I am inclined to think that my letter does </hi> <hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi> read like a cowardly surrender, which assuredly in my design it was </hi><hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi>. And any fair&#8211;minded person </hi><hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> see that I could hardly refuse to answer the Archbishop; and that, if I </hi><hi rend="underline">did</hi><hi> answer, I could hardly say less than I said. But I don't like having to say anything.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My budget of letters included a packet of leaflets now being distributed in the Hereford diocese. They are base beyond description, &amp; yet they are being circulated by respectable and representative men of both the parties! It seems incredible, but it is the fact. </hi><hi rend="underline">Oman</hi><persName xml:id="2141"></persName><hi> joined me at lunch in the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>. I had some talk with </hi><hi rend="underline">Sydney Lee</hi><persName xml:id="669"></persName><hi> &amp; </hi><hi rend="underline">Ellison</hi><persName xml:id="1431"></persName><hi>, both friendly. I called on </hi><hi rend="underline">Westlake</hi><persName xml:id="800"></persName><hi> to arrange about tickets for the consecration, &amp; then dined with the </hi><hi rend="underline"><persName xml:id="216">Gows</persName><persName xml:id="542"></persName></hi><hi>. The two boys – <persName xml:id="816">Cuthbert</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="792">Andrew</persName> – were at home, dull youths, &amp; in their manners barbarous, especially the last who is an <orgName xml:id="58" display="no">Eton</orgName> master. Both Gow &amp; his wife were very friendly. I walked back to the Athenaeum, recovered my bag, &amp; returned to my hotel.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[134]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>In the <orgName xml:id="89">Club</orgName> this afternoon, I encountered <persName xml:id="213">Riley</persName> and old <persName xml:id="384">Prebendary Ingram</persName>. The last passed me with deadly glances, but I insisted on shaking hands with the first. Also I ran in to old Bishop <persName xml:id="172">Browne</persName>, &amp; spoke to him. Why must one quarrel with everybody?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Last night John <persName xml:id="984">Buchan</persName> spoke to me in the Club. "You ought to have been a Moderate in our Church" he said: and he may be right. At least there is none of this obstinate nonsense about Apostolic succession in the Scottish Kirk. He spoke of the importance of sending out speakers to the "Chautauquas" in America, &amp; suggested my going.<note xml:id="371" n="1"></note> I did not dismiss the suggestion as impracticable, but said that, if the Archbishop thought it well for me to leave the diocese so promptly, I would not be indisposed to go.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to <persName xml:id="2995" display="no">Adeney</persName>, &amp; spent half an hour in the extreme humiliation of trying on episcopal garments!! The Church papers seem to be "cooling off", though the "Church Times" still speaks darkly of ultimate things! I anticipate that the knowledge that the Archbishop means to go forward with the Consecration will have a sedative effect on the opposition: &amp; there is probably some measure of righteous reaction from the extreme violence of the attack on a man whose main offence is seen to be that he accepted a Bishoprick!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
