<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[117]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1254</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I attended Mattins in Westminster Abbey, sitting in the stall into which I was inducted in December 1900. After service I called on <persName xml:id="4306">Lee</persName>, whom I found rather depressed. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He thought the Consecration w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> probably have to be postponed. He had not yet succeeded in securing the services of an ecclesiastical lawyer to represent me at the Confirmation in Bow Church on the 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> inst.</hi><note xml:id="362" n="1"></note><hi> Leaving him I walked to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, &amp; there the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> came in with <persName xml:id="2534">Kenyon</persName>, evidently preparing the case for the British Museum to lay before the War Cabinet. His Grace spoke to me, &amp; I told him of Lee's fears about the Consecration being postponed. "O, I don't think there is any probability of that" he said. I went to the Barber, &amp; then to <persName xml:id="2995" display="no">Adeney</persName>, where I ordered episcopal garments. Then I returned to the Club &amp; lunched. Several members whom I didn't know came to me, &amp; expressed their delight at my nomination to a bishoprick. After lunch I walked to Acheson <persName xml:id="4477" display="no">Batchelor</persName> (25 Margaret St) who makes rings for bishops, &amp; I inquired whether indeed it w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> be requisite to engrave arms on the ring. He said it was the almost invariable practice. My soul revolts against the grotesque snobbery of my having </hi><hi rend="underline">now</hi><hi> to adopt arms, when I receive a character which might seem particularly incongruous with all that arms symbolize.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[118]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi><persName xml:id="66">Frank Pember</persName> came into the club while I was there, &amp; we had some talk together. I told him of Lee's difficulty about getting a suitable lawyer, &amp; he told me that <persName xml:id="4425">Tomlin</persName> K.C. might do. Then I walked back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
