<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1311</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went with the <persName xml:id="3618">Archdeacon of Ludlow</persName> to <persName xml:id="4125">Beddoe's</persName> office, &amp; there handed to him the above&#8211;letter after telling him what it contained. Then I went to the Bank, &amp; contributed &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="underline">100</hi><hi> to the War Loan.<note xml:id="284" n="1"></note> This is equally absurd and inevitable. The Bank&#8211;Manager was very communicative. He tells me that he is a High Churchman, and a diocesan lay&#8211;reader: that he conducts service, &amp; preaches nearly every Sunday. He says that the farmers are contributing very little to the War Loan.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>March 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4292">James</persName>, </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You are aware, I think, that the office of diocesan registrar has been for some while vacant, and that Bishop <persName xml:id="475">Percival's</persName> retirement creates also a vacancy in the office of Bishop's Secretary.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I write to request your acceptance of those offices, in which, I have full confidence, your action will be of great advantage both to the Diocese and to the Bishop.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have asked M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Beddoe, who during the vacancy has acted as Registrar, to continue to do so until the appointment is made, &amp; then to hand over to the new Registrar the diocesan documents now in his custody.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You will oblige me by giving me your answer to this letter with as little delay as may be convenient.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Very faithfully yrs,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I carried the above&#8211;copied letter to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> James's office, &amp; later in the day I received his affirmative answer. Later still a brief note from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Beddoe announced that he had already heard from M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> James, &amp; was sending him the diocesan documents forthwith. Thus ends, satisfactorily as I hope, an unpleasant business which had to be gone through, but had all the materials for public friction.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
