<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1316</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked across to the House of Lords, &amp; there found </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName></hi><hi>, who had been reading prayers. We walked down the Embankment, &amp; discussed the great question whether he ought to accept the Deanery of Durham. He seemed to incline to an affirmative decision, but he was going to Lambeth, &amp; there the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> may dissuade him. I went to </hi><persName xml:id="4227"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Frowde's</hi></persName><hi> Warehouse, and bought a volume of "Offices" for use in Confirmations: then I called at the S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Paul's Deanery, &amp; saw </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName></hi><hi> and </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName></hi><hi> for a few minutes. Also I received my thick overcoat. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then back to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, to pick up my bags, &amp; so to Paddington</hi><hi> to catch the 1.40 p.m. train. My journey was relieved by the conversation of an <persName xml:id="4421">army chaplain</persName>, who had just accepted from the Bishop of <persName xml:id="2462">Chelmsford</persName> the vicarage of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Luke's, Victoria Docks. He had been in charge of the Malvern School mission in Canning Town. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He spoke with marked contempt of the Chaplain General</hi><persName xml:id="3507"></persName><hi>, &amp; certainly the specimens of that reverent gentleman's manner of carrying on his business which he gave me did justify an infinitude of scorn. When I changed trains at Great Malvern, I found </hi><persName xml:id="207"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Goudy</hi></persName><hi> on the platform, looking very old. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4345">Norcock</persName></hi> <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4471" display="no">Bateman</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> met me at Hereford. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3618">Lilley</persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> called, &amp; wasted an hour. After dinner I corrected some proofs, and wrote a few letters. So runs away another day. It is all very hustled and haphazard, a hand&#8211;to&#8211;mouth method of living, prodigiously futile. Nor do I see any prospect of an escape from this daily round of petty occupations. Of course, the confirmations will not go on always; so far the future holds the promise of relief.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
