<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, February 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1302</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My last day in Durham was spent dolorously in preparations for departure. <persName xml:id="2953">Hughes</persName> came in during the morning, and packed up the <persName xml:id="228">Anson</persName> papers. He also removed the rejected books. I went to the Bank, &amp; arranged with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3901">Moult</persName> for the transference of my accounts. We lunched with the <persName xml:id="3262">Lillingstons</persName><persName xml:id="3263"></persName>, &amp; afterwards walked out to the <persName xml:id="3438">Rogersons</persName><persName xml:id="3439"></persName>, and said Goodbye. The day was perfect: &amp; as we walked home, the beauty of the Banks was seen at its best. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> came to tea. I gave him Blackstone's edition of <ref xml:id="970">Magna Carta</ref>. Then I said Goodbye to the Vergers. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">They said that the last 5 years had been the happiest of their lives</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4473" display="no">Kenneth</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="4468" display="no">Leslie</persName> came &amp; finished tying up my papers. <persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> came in after dinner. I walked round the College with him</hi> <hi rend="bold">[175]</hi><hi> in the moonlight, talking over the past &amp; the future. We were sad at parting. I asked him to be one of my examining chaplains. The scene was ravishingly beautiful, and brought home to me the full measure of the personal loss which my retirement from Durham implies. It certainly is </hi><hi rend="underline">not</hi><hi> conventional cant to say that I go reluctantly, and to my impoverishment &amp; unhappiness.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
