<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[151]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1276</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I spent the day in making preparations for departure. At 3 p.m. I conducted a service in the Cathedral in connexion with D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="3628">Greenwell's</persName> Funeral, which was taking place at Lanchester at the same hour.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[152]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of Canterbury</persName></hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>January 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Lord Archbishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>You are very good, &amp; your kind letter is welcome. <persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> and I will be pleased to accept your invitation to stay at Lambeth from Monday till Friday next week. There can be no question that I shall stand in great need of counsel on many matters, &amp; I am grateful for the assurance that I can draw on your Grace's resources.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The behaviour of the Bishops has certainly made a deep &amp; painful impression on my mind. Obsessed with the ambition of securing a "clean bill of orthodoxy" from the <orgName xml:id="20">English Church Union</orgName>, they seem never to have given a thought to the inevitable, or probable, consequences of their action. My personal relation with the Bishops who have announced to the world, that they cannot assist in my Consecration, must needs be very difficult. To forgive an injury of that kind is a duty which I shall endeavour to fulfil, but to forget is hardly in my power. I shall, however, try to content myself with leaving their Lordships to the comfort of their consciences, &amp; the lasting satisfaction of their memory.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Ordinarily some measure of devotional retirement is permitted to a man on the verge of so</hi> <hi rend="bold">[153]</hi> <hi>momentous a new departure. That has been denied to me, and I have instead to carry to my Consecration a mind harassed &amp; fatigued, and a wounded heart. Were it not that Consecration carries me into a Presence where a Higher Equity &amp; a more generous Charity than that of the Bishops may be counted upon, I could hardly stand it all.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, always,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Lord Archbishop,</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>sincerely &amp; dutifully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi> came to see me. I gave him as a parting gift the old ivory crucifix that I purchased from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="3747">Rushworth</persName></hi><hi> for ten guineas. He is evidently much exercised in mind over the prospect of a new Dean. Of the three names, now alleged to be under the <persName xml:id="234">Prime Minister's</persName> consideration –</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName></hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="308">Hobhouse</persName></hi><hi>, </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="2511">Hutton</persName></hi><hi> – he prefers </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hobhouse</hi><hi>, as being less cantankerous than </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi>, and more liberal than </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton</hi><hi>. But I incline to think that </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton</hi><hi> may be the winner in this race for preferment. He is a High Churchman, and, as such, would commend himself to a Prime Minister who desired to make his peace with the Orthodox after the exasperation provoked by my appointment! </hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hutton</hi><hi> would be popular within a narrow circle, &amp; would make no enemies outside it: but, of course, he is no sense or measure a leader.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
