<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, January 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1253</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I left Durham by the early train. Snow was on the ground, &amp; the weather was bitter. On the platform were the choir&#8211;boys going home for their brief holiday. <persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> was in my compartment, &amp; we sate opposite an interesting and intelligent officer (Captain M. K. Wardle, Brigade Major, 5</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> Infantry Brigade, B.E.F.) who had been in Bourlon Wood, and gave us much interesting information about the Cambrai fighting. As I made my way from Westminster Bridge Station to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, I was hailed by the <persName xml:id="216">Gows</persName><persName xml:id="542"></persName> with whom I had tea, &amp; then went to 3 Little Cloisters, where the ever&#8211;hospitable <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName> was entertaining me. On the doorstep were the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="404">Davidson</persName>, who had come to leave a message that I should come to Lambeth at 6 p.m. This I did, and had a two&#8211;hours interview with the Archbishop.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Archbishop began by explaining that he would probably have to return an answer to <persName xml:id="49">Gore's</persName> protest, and that he wished to be sure that he had not misunderstood my position. He had, therefore, sent for me in order that I might, if I thought fit, explain what I meant, &amp; if he had rightly understood my published statements. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">I began by asking on what footing our conversation was proceeding. If any kind of official investigation into my beliefs were intended, I would decline to make any answer whatever. If the Archbishop were speaking only as one friend to another, I would answer his questions with the utmost candour so far as I could</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>His</hi> <hi rend="bold">[116]</hi> <hi>Grace assented, and we talked freely. It seemed to me that we were, in the matter of personal belief, substantially agreed.<note xml:id="361" n="1"></note> </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop indicated the possibility of his resigning office rather than proceed to consecrate me in the teeth of a really weighty protest from the bishops. I pointed out that his resignation would make it impossible for me to retain office in the English Church</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> How could I go back to my Deanery, discredited and disowned, to teach without authority, &amp; to be the mark of every insult? Besides, <persName xml:id="359">Sanday's</persName> intervention had greatly added to the gravity of the situation. It could not possibly be a personal issue: it had widened into a large question, Whether New Testament Criticism with its inevitable bearing on the historical articles of the Creed was legitimate for English clergymen? His Grace did not dissent from this. I showed him some of the letters I had received from the bishops, &amp; my answers to them. I stayed to dinner. It was rather a melancholy meal, for the Bishops of <persName xml:id="532">Ely</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="3920">Dover</persName> were there, both </hi> <hi rend="underline">very</hi><hi> glum. The former had come up to discuss the situation created by Gore's protest. However we got through the meal, and I took my leave.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">As I walked back to Little Cloisters I reflected on the strange situation into which I had been brought with such dramatic suddenness</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi> <hi rend="italic">My elevation to the episcopate looks like becoming the occasion of my ejection from the Establishment. It will be odd to begin life again in one's 55</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> year!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
