<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1338</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline"><persName xml:id="2763" display="no">Alice Barwick</persName> wrote to tell me that <persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> is reported to be "missing" on the 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi>. The Colonel writes to say that he may be among the wounded prisoners. We must hope the best until we know the worst. He has been a thoroughly good boy, &amp; to me more a son than a godson. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Rev. J. <persName xml:id="4189">Davies</persName></hi><hi>, Rector of Stoke Prior came to see me on the subject of the Bible and Prayer Book examinations. I promised to give the prizes which Bp. <persName xml:id="475">Percival</persName> gave. I worked at a sermon for next Sunday, and then went to the Palace, and began to arrange my books in the shelves of my study. <persName xml:id="4448">Wynne&#8211;Willson</persName> joined me at 2.45 p.m., and we motored to the Munition Works. </hi><hi rend="italic">Here Colonel </hi><hi>[space left blank by Henson] </hi><hi rend="italic">conducted us over the very extensive establishment, in which more than 4000 girls &amp; women are hard at work filling shells. They wore a short tunic, &amp; trousers, very workmanlike. It is an odd employment for Christian matrons. On my return, I went to the Palace, and worked for an hour in the garden. The planting of the crops has hardly made a beginning, &amp; there is little prospect of a suitable gardener.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
