<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1292</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I walked to Westminster, &amp; called on <persName xml:id="4306">Lee</persName>, whom I asked to continue to act as my secretary, and charged to get a seal made, sufficient for purposes of business, but giving me time to determine what I would finally determine to have. There seems to be a considerable liberty in the matter. Then I called on <persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName>, and gave him an account of the Enthronement. I next walked to Acheson <persName xml:id="4477" display="no">Batchelor</persName>, 25 Margaret Street, and told him that I would have the arms of the see engraved on the episcopal ring. Then I called on <persName xml:id="2995" display="no">Adeney</persName>, &amp; finally returned to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, where I lunched with <persName xml:id="984">Buchan</persName> as my table&#8211;companion. Later I picked up <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; the baggage and went to King's Cross. We travelled to Durham in a very crowded train, arriving shortly after midnight. <persName xml:id="3553">Mead&#8211;Falkner</persName>, &amp; Col. <persName xml:id="3652">Herne</persName> were in the carriage. A sharp attack of lumbago seized me as I was entering the Athenaeum about 12.30 p.m., and made all movement painful to me: but as I review the experiences of the last few weeks I can see that I have much to be thankful for both on the score of health, &amp; on that of weather.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>February 17</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I was actually in the course of writing to you when your second letter came in. Bishop <persName xml:id="325">Ryle</persName> will do well enough as Chairman, &amp; his being on the spot is a distinct advantage.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I think we must from the start make quite clear whether we are really aiming at a continuation of the Establishment, or whether we are drafting a constitution for an independent disestablished Church, only suppressing for the time those parts of the scheme which pre&#8211;suppose the actual disestablishment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>If, as is not improbable, the latter is what most of the Committee have in mind, then we must record a protest, and afterwards proceed to insist on making the Church of Ireland rather than that of South Africa, the model of our new constitution. The former is really a far closer parallel to ourselves, &amp; its system, if I understand it correctly, is far more tolerable than that of S. Africa, in which the Tractarian ideal most nearly attained expression.<note xml:id="382" n="1"></note> I think a minority Report is inevitable, &amp; I hope we shall make it as powerful as possible.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The enthronement in Hereford on Shrove Tuesday was marked by emphatic demonstrations of general goodwill.<note xml:id="266" display="no" n="1"></note></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours ever sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi> 
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the Headmaster of Durham School</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>February 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear <persName xml:id="2692">Budworth</persName>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am decanally disembodied, &amp; can only approach you </hi><hi rend="underline">in form&#x00E2; pauperis</hi> <hi>[the character of a pauper supplicant], but it has been pointed out to me that, (though several Deans of Durham held bishopricks, being indeed annexed abusively after the ill fashion of the "good old times", yet) I am the first Dean to be </hi><hi rend="underline">advanced</hi><hi> to a bishoprick since William <persName xml:id="4293">James</persName>, who was made bishop of Durham by James I in 1606, more than 3 centuries since, being at the time Dean of Durham. Whether this circumstance may serve to form a peg on which a disembodied Dean might fitly beg you to grant a half&#8211;holiday to the School, you will determine: but I should take it kindly if you could do so.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours aff</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ect</hi><hi>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I have been giving parting gifts to my colleagues: viz.</hi>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
<hi>The <persName xml:id="590">Archdeacon</persName> – a 1</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi><hi> edition of <persName xml:id="4228">Fuller's</persName> "Worthies"<ref xml:id="968"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="473">Knowling</persName> – Santa Clare's (<persName xml:id="4187">Davenport's</persName>) Treatise on the 39 Articles</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName> – my ivory Crucifix</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2785">Bishop of Jarrow</persName> – Engraving of Durham Cathedral</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3262">Lillingston</persName> – Restoration of the Abbey by <persName xml:id="3518">Hodgson Fowler</persName>.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2800">Precentor</persName> – Life &amp; Works of S. Bernard. translation 4 vols</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2953">Sacrist</persName> – Hutchinson's Durham 3 vols</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3496">Dennett</persName> – <persName xml:id="984">Buchan's</persName> History of the War<ref xml:id="974"></ref> 18 vols.</hi> 
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2811">May</persName> – <ref xml:id="969">Life of Stopford <persName xml:id="3960">Brooke</persName></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2806">Bayley</persName> – <persName xml:id="381">Blackstone's</persName> <ref xml:id="970">"Magna Carta"</ref>.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi>Budworth – <ref xml:id="971">Billings' Durham</ref>.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2810">Poole</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="3553">Meade Falkner</persName> – Enigmes de la Sainte Vierge<ref xml:id="972"></ref></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2809">Freeman</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="4011">Jobling</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="4382">Reeve</persName></hi>
            </item>
            <item>
<hi><persName xml:id="2748">Wilson</persName></hi>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">To the <persName xml:id="117">Dean of Carlisle</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>February 22</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi>1908 [sic]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Dear Rashdall,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I think it is of real importance that you sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> come to the meeting on the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>. It is </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">vital</hi><hi> that we sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>not allow <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> &amp; Co. to "rush" the whole business, &amp; at whatever inconvenience you &amp; I </hi><hi rend="underline">must</hi><hi> keep our hands on this matter. Even if (which I don't think will be the case) there is little but formal business done at the meeting, we shall discover who are our friends, &amp; be able to lay the foundation of some organized effort. The C</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi><hi> is as nearly "packed" as possible, &amp; this adds to the importance of our "playing ourselves" for all that we are worth.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
The Bp. of Manchester wrote to me some days ago. It appears probable that the Dean of West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> will be proposed as chairman, &amp; this seems to be unobjectionable. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Ryle is weak, but not malignant or unscrupulous</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi>The Bishop thinks, &amp; I agree with him, that our first action must be to make clear whether we are really designing to perpetuate the Establishment, or rather are really assuming Disestablishment &amp; drafting a scheme for a disestablished church, only suppressing those features wh. pre&#8211;suppose that Disestablishment is </hi><hi rend="underline">un fait accompli</hi><hi>. If, as is probable, the last be found to be the real intention of the majority, we must record a protest: &amp; proceed to press for the adoption </hi> <hi rend="underline">mutatis mutandis</hi><hi> of the Irish model, rather</hi> <hi rend="bold">[171]</hi> <hi>than the Scottish or the South African. In any case there must be a minority Report, &amp; we must aim at making it as weighty as possible.</hi> <hi rend="underline">Be sure &amp; turn up on the 27</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours aff</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">ect</hi><hi>,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>  
         </p>
</div><p>   
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
