<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1323</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>After breakfast I visited the church with the Rector. It contains the tombs of the parents<persName xml:id="4266"></persName><persName xml:id="4268"></persName> of Lord Herbert of <persName xml:id="4269">Cherbury</persName>, &amp; <persName xml:id="915">George Herbert</persName>. It is a fine monument, with the two recumbent effigies side by side, &amp; a whole row of children above them. There is also a fine carved screen, with rood loft, &amp; miserere stalls. I drove to Montgomery station, about 3 miles, &amp; took train for Shrewsbury. Thence I came directly to Hereford, where I arrived at 1.38 p.m., and found a pile of letters awaiting me. The rest of the day was expended in dealing with an accumulation of correspondence.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi> <hi>[symbol] [symbol]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>To the Bishop of <persName xml:id="421">Birmingham</persName></hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>March 19</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Some months ago I accepted an invitation to preach in Carr's Lane Church, Birmingham: &amp; I do not think it would be either right in itself or expedient for me as Bishop of Hereford to withdraw from an engagement wh. I had made as Dean of Durham. It would, however, be a great satisfaction to me, &amp; a great advantage to the Church, if I c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be assisted by your goodwill &amp; approbation. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Legally</hi><hi rend="italic">, as I maintain, no Bishop has jurisdiction within the walls of a dissenting chapel, wh., so far as he is concerned, is no more than a private building: but, of course, this technical point is trivial beside the large issue of our relations with those non&#8211;episcopal churches wh. have now by God's Blessing grown to be mighty instruments for the world's evangelisation.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I think the time has fully come for establishing exchange of pulpits</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; though the working out of a satisfactory system will take time, it is really important to keep the main question in evidence by occasional acts. I gather from many utterances of yours that you are in agreement with me in thinking that the C. of E. must take a new departure, &amp; that that new departure must carry it into closer relations with the churches of the English Dispersion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Yours ever,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I licensed three curates, and instituted one incumbent &#8211; Rev. R. W. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="4129">Bennett</persName></hi><hi> &#8211; to the parish of Linton. After the oaths had been taken, and I had signed the documents, I went into S. John's Church (the Lady Chapel), and performed the act of institution. First, I read the concluding prayers of the Ordination Service: then I read the deed of institution while Bennett knelt before me, holding the seal: then I pronounced the benediction, laying my hand on his head. After lunch I motored to Canon <persName xml:id="4349">Palmer's</persName> house, &amp; fetched him out to take me to S. Martin's Home for Penitents. The Mother&#8211;Superior from Brighton happened to be there, a quaint&#8211;looking old body. I was shown over the house where a score of "penitents" work at a laundry under the supervision of five sisters. I told them they might wear the vestments in their chapel, as they were not a parochial church! On the whole I was better pleased with the place than I expected to be. I wrote to the <persName xml:id="242">Bishop of Manchester</persName> and the <persName xml:id="117">Dean of Carlisle</persName> about the Church &amp; State Report.<note xml:id="316" n="1"></note> It is clear to me that I can do nothing in the way of amending the <persName xml:id="311">Selborne</persName> scheme. Also I wrote to the <persName xml:id="2533">Bishop of Bristol</persName> inquiring about the position of the diocesan chancellor: and to the <persName xml:id="421">Bishop of Birmingham</persName> about my visit to Carr's Lane Church. I had projected a visit to Kilpeck to inspect the Norman church, but the heavy &amp; persistent rain deterred me from my purpose.</hi> <hi rend="italic">I finished reading "Middlemarch", which I found interesting. The analysis of the religious type expressed by Bulstrode is amazingly accurate &amp; acute.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
