<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1263</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The porter brought me a telephone message from the "Abp of Westminster". Suspecting that this might imply that the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of Canterbury</persName> wished to see me, I walked through sleet &amp; slush to Lambeth after breakfast, and had a short conversation with his Grace. The telephone message was really from the <persName xml:id="636">Archdeacon of Westminster</persName>, but the Archbishop was evidently glad to see me. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He has been alarmed by reports of the impression made among the people by the agitation against my consecration, &amp; is casting about for some means of re&#8211;assuring the panic&#8211;stricken</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><note xml:id="367" n="1"></note><hi> He had drafted a letter to me, &amp; an answer from me to him. The last I amended by adding these words:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"I am indeed astonished that any candid reader of my published books, or any one having knowledge of my public ministry of 30 years could entertain a suggestion so dishonourable to me as a man and a clergyman."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>The "suggestion" of course was that I didn't believe the Creeds. I signed this letter, &amp; left the Abp. free to use it or not as he pleased.<note xml:id="368" n="1"></note> It seemed to me that </hi><hi rend="underline">if</hi><hi> he wrote to me, I could not but answer his letter: and </hi><hi rend="bold underline">that if I answered, the essential thing was explicitly to stand to my ministry, written &amp; spoken</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> The Abp. was evidently pleased at hearing of my decision not to attend the function at the <orgName xml:id="37">"City Temple"</orgName> tonight.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[131]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>From Lambeth I walked to the Abbey, &amp; attended Mattins. The gloom was such that, in order to read my prayerbook, I had to go to the Lectern and use the light of its candles. The 2</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi><hi> lesson was S. Matthew X, threatening &amp; consolatory. I walked with Pearce, &amp; heard about his visit to Sandringham. It seems to have been pleasant &amp; successful. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">H.M. spoke about my appointment to Hereford in terms which disclosed a measure of alarm</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><note xml:id="369" n="1"></note><hi> I went in to the Chaplain General's<persName xml:id="3507"></persName> room, &amp; exchanged some civil words. On my way back to the <orgName xml:id="89">club</orgName> I stopped at Lock's<orgName xml:id="305"></orgName> shop, and there ordered an episcopal hat. Then having received my budget of letters, I wrote answers to such of them as called for answer. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of <persName xml:id="532">Ely</persName> writes to explain why he can neither send me his good wishes, nor take part in my consecration! Bishop <persName xml:id="172">Browne</persName> writes to explain that when he wrote so civilly, he had not grasped the measure of my heresies</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi><hi> On the other hand, Prebendary <persName xml:id="4436">Webster</persName> writes sympathetically and the <persName xml:id="4282">Mayor of Croydon</persName> writes so candid and manly a letter that I answered it. In the afternoon, Mead Falkner came into the club, and walked with me as far as Westminster, where I called at <persName xml:id="4306">Lee's</persName> office, and was told that the confirmation had been fixed up for Wednesday next. It is not expected that the enemy will prosecute me for heresy, and, short of doing so, there seems little that they can do. But malignity such as theirs is both persistent and resourceful, &amp; there may yet be developments.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p><hi>To the Mayor of Croydon</hi></p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Mayor,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am greatly obliged to you for your kind letter. You will readily understand that I do not feel free to make any doctrinal statement before my Consecration: but I will take leave to observe that the method adopted by my opponents is equally effective &amp; unfair. Sentences &amp; paragraphs are torn from my books apart from context, argument, purpose, and evident drift: &amp; these are paraded before the general public wh. does not &amp; cannot know enough of the high &amp; difficult questions at stake to pass any reasonable judgment. Thus an atmosphere of religious panic is created in which justice expires, &amp; every malevolent suggestion acquires plausibility.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I do not doubt that the good sense &amp; equity of my countrymen will not permanently allow an organized clamour to drive from their memories the manner &amp; purpose of a public ministry of 30 years.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>Believe me, my dear M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Mayor,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>faithfully &amp; gratefully,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. Hensley Henson.</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>I called on the <persName xml:id="216">Gows</persName><persName xml:id="542"></persName>, and had tea with them. They had heard that the Bishop of <persName xml:id="3933">Peterborough</persName> was on my side: also that Bishop <persName xml:id="280">Boyd&#8211;Carpenter</persName> was indignant at the attacks on me. Neither <persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName> nor <persName xml:id="325">Ryle</persName> has answered my letter.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
