<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[138]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1266</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I went to S. Martin's, &amp; received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. <persName xml:id="3611">Dick Shepperd</persName> recognized me, &amp; came across the church to ask me to breakfast: but I declined, &amp; went to the <orgName xml:id="89">Athenaeum</orgName>, where I breakfasted. There I found <persName xml:id="3455">Jevons</persName>, &amp; had some talk with him. After writing to <persName xml:id="77">Marion</persName>, I walked to S. John's, Westminster, &amp; heard an excellent sermon from <persName xml:id="427">Ralph</persName>. In the pew behind me were <persName xml:id="389">Lord</persName> &amp; <persName xml:id="2896">Lady Bryce</persName>: &amp; two pews in front were the <persName xml:id="543">Murray Smiths</persName>. The congregation was smaller than I expected, for the galleries were almost empty, &amp; the body of the Church was not more than two thirds full. Geoffrey <persName xml:id="2709">Dawson</persName> was there, &amp; <persName xml:id="1209">Kitty</persName>. I went for a short stroll with Ralph after service. </hi><hi rend="italic">He told me that he had sent his Consecration Sermon to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop</persName> with a letter in which he urged him not to stultify his whole life by throwing me over. The Abp. had replied in a friendly spirit, saying that he thought the opposition had exhausted itself. </hi><hi>I lunched with <persName xml:id="636">Pearce</persName>, &amp; afterwards attended service in the Abbey, &amp; heard him preach. He made a kindly allusion to my consecration. Then I went to the Athenaeum, &amp; had a long talk with <persName xml:id="3581">Barnes</persName>, the Master of the Temple. As I sate at dinner in the Club, I was joined by Sir Henry <persName xml:id="344">Craik</persName>, with whom I had much interesting talk. He seems to have made up his mind to resign the Churchwardenship of <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>. After reading for nearly an hour, I walked back to Morley's Hotel, &amp; went to bed. Thus ended a very idle Sunday, but in my present circumstances it is hardly judicious for me to preach, or make any public appearances.</hi> 
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
