<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1270</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The "Times" contains the announcement that <persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> has withdrawn his protest in response to the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop's</persName> letter. He professes to be entitled to assume that I don't disbelieve what he thought that I did disbelieve, &amp; that I give an </hi> <hi rend="underline">ex animo</hi><hi> belief to what he thought I doubted. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Is he really entitled to make this assumption? I certainly did not intend him to be so</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Stuckey <persName xml:id="3733">Coles</persName> writes again, not quite so hopefully as Gore.</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"We now have your reassuring statement </hi><hi rend="bold underline">which as a matter of fact reads to us like a retractation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi> Probably to your mind there is some reconciling statement which would shew that a retractation is not needed."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Well, they won't get anything further from me to re&#8211;assure them</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The <persName xml:id="276">Bishop of Durham</persName> writes a long, embarrassed, &amp; affectionate letter to explain that he proposes to take part in my consecration, but could not, if he were asked, present me! I wrote &amp; told him that I was glad he did not feel compelled to absent himself</hi><hi>.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The Archbishop of <persName xml:id="2166">Upsala</persName> sends me a telegram. "Hearty congratulations". He doesn't know what a bed of thorns I am being pitched on to.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> W. M. Pigott writes to congratulate me. He says that he was "one of the small boys whom in about the year 1880 you taught at the Grammar School, Brigg", and that he "had never forgotten that, in those far&#8211;off days, before you had taken orders </hi><hi rend="bold underline">you used to say that your highest ambition was to become Archbishop of Canterbury".<note xml:id="377" n="1"></note> I certainly cannot remember any such ambition for myself,</hi> <hi rend="bold">[147]</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">though I do remember about that time sketching out a wonderful scheme for the re&#8211;union of Protestantism in which the Archbishop of Canterbury played the leading part</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
