<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1331</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> <persName xml:id="4453">Woods</persName> had some talk with me about his parish. He desires to sign on for another year as chaplain. I returned to Hereford, and after lunch motored to Hampton Bishop, &amp; confirmed 23 persons in the parish church. After service we went to the Rectory, &amp; had tea with the <persName xml:id="4410">Rector</persName> and M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi> Scarlett Smith. On returning to Hereford, we went to the Palace where our furniture is rapidly arriving. It looks a long mass of mingled stuff as it stands piled in the Hall.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There awaited me among yesterday's letters two from Birmingham, the one from </hi><persName xml:id="2716"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Canon Willink</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; the other from </hi><persName xml:id="4124"><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Hamilton Baynes</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">Both expressed great anxiety that I sh</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> postpone my visit to Carr's Lane Church, &amp; both professed to be actuated by a desire to advance the cause of reunion</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic"> I only half&#8211;believe this profession, but I thought it judicious so far to defer to the professors as to request from M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Berry<persName xml:id="4130"></persName> the postponement of my visit. He is said to be in France, so I marked my letter 'immediate'. Hamilton Baynes is engaged in negociation with Berry with the object of amalgamating his congregation with that of the Birmingham Cathedral. He says the <persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of C.</persName> has cognizance of this project, &amp; favours it. He fears that any controversy caused by my preaching on April 14</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> might militate against his scheme!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi> <hi>[symbol]</hi>
         </p><div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">To Bishop Hamilton Baynes</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>March 26</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> 1918</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>My dear Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I am much interested in your project, &amp; shall follow its fortunes with attention &amp; sympathy. I have written to M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi> Berry &amp; begged to be allowed to postpone the fulfilment of my promise to preach in Carr's Lane Church, adding the suggestion that June 30</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi> w</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi>be a possible date. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">If he refuses to release me from my bond, I shall be obliged to carry out my promise on the 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">April</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> <hi>You cannot hope to take any effective step </hi><hi rend="underline">without</hi><hi> provoking controversy: &amp; my deliberate conclusion is that one sh</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi> determine a course deliberately, &amp; go forward resolutely </hi><hi rend="underline">letting</hi><hi> the fanaticks howl.</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">I am interested also in what you tell me of the action of the Archdeacons in the matter of my consecration</hi><hi rend="italic">. It was of course in equal measure both extraordinary &amp; indecent. But when so many Bishops allowed themselves to act with such extreme impropriety and, so far as I am concerned, with such evident injustice, I cannot think too hardly of archidiaconal follies.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>I do not believe there is any sincerity in the renewed talk about reunion by so&#8211;called "Catholicks".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>However, I am Yours sincerely,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>H. H. Hereford</hi>
         </p>
</div>         <p>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
