<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1918. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">1259</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> day</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi>The post brought me a very kindly worded letter from </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> <persName xml:id="2063">Walter Long</persName></hi><hi>, which was the more welcome since he may fairly be regarded as an excellent example of the country gentleman, a class of some importance in the diocese of Hereford. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Mackarness<persName xml:id="4315"></persName></hi><hi> writes civilly from Oxford:–</hi>
         </p>
<div type="letter">
         <p>
<hi>"I have just received a circular inviting my signature to a protest to the <persName xml:id="128">Abp. of Canterbury</persName> against your forthcoming consecration to the See of Hereford. I have no intention of signing it."</hi>
         </p>
</div>
         <p>
<hi>It is evident that the enemy is busily at work, but, perhaps, the fact that a petition to the Archbishop is being signed argues a consciousness that nothing effective can be done at my Confirmation. The "Spectator" has some justly severe observations on the circulation of a leaflet in the diocese of Hereford inviting prayer against my consecration, &amp; suggesting the collect for S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi> Matthias' Day as a suitable prayer!</hi><note xml:id="365" n="1"></note> <hi rend="bold underline">I suppose there will be many petitions signed in the churches today after appropriate discourses</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline"><persName xml:id="1898">Cruickshank</persName></hi><hi> re&#8211;appeared after a month's absence. He came to see me, and read most of the letters from bishops which have come to me. He had not realized the possible developments of the agitation against my Consecration. We discussed the chances of the appointment to this Deanery. <persName xml:id="552">Headlam</persName> and <persName xml:id="308">Hobhouse</persName> appear to be the two likeliest candidates, &amp; of these the last is said to lead. But I incline to think that Headlam would make the better Dean. He would stand up for the Foundation against these Church Reformers, &amp; make a good fight.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
