<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[21]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Advent Sunday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A wet disconcerting day. Only 14 c<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.  On this day 21 years ago, I was instituted to the Vicarage of Barking. May God for Christ's sake forgive the sins which have hindered, and the blunders which have defeated my Ministry! I am far more perplexed today than then, and I was a troubled man then. On the following Monday (Dec: 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> 1888) I preached for the first time in the Abbey, a special sermon for Advent.</p>
         <p>At Mattins the congregation was rather meagre, and the coughing really disabling. I preached from the Gospel, "Who is this?" <hi rend="bold underline">taking up my parable against the new Theologian's alternative, "Jesus or Christ?</hi>
<hi rend="bold">"</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the afternoon I went to Bethnal Green, &amp; addressed about 500 men in the 
<placeName xml:id="8">Excelsior Hall</placeName>.  My remarks were disconnected enough, for I read them bits of my American Journal, and moralized on the way.  However, they seemed to like it. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>The church was well–filled at Evensong. I preached from Isaiah II.3 "Out of Zion shall go forth the law, &amp; the Word of the Lord from Jerusalem".  We sang the "Dies Irae" after service.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[22]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday, Nov: 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1909, I went to Chigwell, and <hi rend="bold underline">lectured for an hour to the boys on "The Yellowstone Park"</hi>, illustrating my lecture with the 21 slides I purchased some weeks ago. 
<persName xml:id="82">Marsden</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2057">Russell</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2058" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jones</persName> were present.</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, Nov: 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1909, I dined with 
<persName xml:id="284">Sir John Wolfe Barry</persName> at the Anniversary dinner of the 
<orgName xml:id="166">Royal Society</orgName>.  
<persName xml:id="665">Butcher</persName> proposed the toast of the evening.  The toast of the medallists was responded to by 
<persName xml:id="2060">Sir James Dewar</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="261" display="no">Major Ronald Rosen</persName>. As Sir John &amp; I drove back to 
<placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> we noticed a great force of police in Trafalgar Square keeping back a very demure crowd gathered to hear the result of the voting on the Budget.  
<persName xml:id="1591"><hi rend="bold underline">Lord Lansdowne's</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> motion was carried by 350 to 75</hi>.<note xml:id="106" n="1"></note> </p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Dec: 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1909, I dined with the 
<orgName xml:id="64">Past Overseers Society</orgName>, where I proposed the Toast of the City of Westminster.  
<persName xml:id="2063">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Walter Long</persName> was a guest, also 
<persName xml:id="14">Sir Thomas Raleigh.</persName></p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2062">Oxley</persName>, the old sidesman, died suddenly in the Almshouses.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
