<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I travelled to Edinboro from King's Cross in bright sunshine as far as York, &amp; then rain.  In the carriage was a Scottish minister returning from Italy. We entered into conversation on Church questions.  He seemed fairly hopeful of re&#8211;union with the 
<orgName xml:id="118">U.F. Church</orgName>, though himself plainly a very stiff advocate of the Establishment.  <hi rend="bold underline">I received a warm welcome from </hi>
<persName xml:id="2014"><hi rend="bold underline">Principal Whyte</hi></persName>.  There dined here 
<persName xml:id="1491">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Taylor&#8211;Innes</persName>, the author of the <ref xml:id="283">Law of Creeds in Scotland</ref>, with whom I had much talk.  Apparently the results of the schism of the Wee Frees is in the Highlands very bad.  There is a deficiency of ministers to serve the churches which have been handed over to the little church by the Parliamentary Commission: the quality of such ministers as are procurable is very unsatisfactory.  Meanwhile the people have given up church&#8211;going, and are in danger of drifting out of religion.  <hi rend="italic">Astonishing fanaticism is reported from the Highlands e.g. the people are incited to swear with uplifted hand that in no circumstances will they enter an U.F. church!</hi>  It appears to be very doubtful whether these fanaticks can use the property they have attained.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
