<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After breakfast I walked round to 39 Palmerston Place and called on 
<persName xml:id="1135">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mitford Mitchell</persName>.  We talked together for half an hour.  He says that 
<persName xml:id="2015">Carnegie Simpson's</persName> <ref xml:id="316">"Life of Rainy</ref> <hi rend="bold">["]</hi> will tend to 'put up the backs' of the established clergy, &amp; so make Reunion the more difficult.  If the union shall be effected he anticipates a secession of upper&#8211;class folk to the 
<orgName xml:id="161">Episcopal Church</orgName>, and a secession of incorrigible Voluntaries to some form of dissent.  But neither secession would be considerable, and the united church, including 70 or even 75 of the religious people in Scotland, would enjoy a new prestige, &amp; might well attract a certain number of indifferent Christians.</p>
         <p>Leaving Mitford Mitchell I went to the Cathedral, &amp; joined in the daily service, which was proceeding in a side chapel.  Then I walked the length of Princes' Street enjoying the sunshine &amp; the noble prospect.  I lunched with the students in the 
<orgName xml:id="162">College</orgName> Hall; &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">met the Professors. </hi>
<persName xml:id="2016"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Martin</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, (
<persName xml:id="1019">Addis's</persName> brother&#8211;in&#8211;law</hi>) presided, 
<persName xml:id="2017">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McEwan</persName> sate opposite; &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2018">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kennedy</persName>, successor to 
<persName xml:id="2019">Marcus Dods</persName> beside me.  After lunch I had to make a short speech to the students.  Then the 
<persName xml:id="2014">Principal</persName> took me for a drive round the Salisbury Crags &amp; Arthur's Seat returning by way of the <hi rend="bold">[5]</hi> [symbol] Grass Market.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">At tea&#8211;time I took part in a lively discussion with mine 
<persName xml:id="2020">hostess</persName> on the value of fraternal association which yet did not imply fraternal recognition at the Holy Communion</hi><hi rend="italic">.  In my view the last ought to precede the first.  The large 
<orgName xml:id="189">missionary convention</orgName> next year will provide a conspicuous illustration of the other procedure.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I observe that the Anglican representatives are mainly sacerdotalist</hi><hi rend="italic"> e.g. the Bishops of 
<persName xml:id="105">Southwark</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="49">Birmingham</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2021">Frere</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2022" display="no">"Father" Kelly</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2023">Neville Talbot</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2024">Lionel Ford</persName>, &amp;c. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Not one of these would feel himself free to receive the Communion in a non&#8211;episcopal Church, &amp; probably would not willingly give the communion to an unconfirmed person</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>At dinner came 
<persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2026">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kelman</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1140">Prof. Patterson</persName>, and 
<persName xml:id="2027" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Barbour</persName>.  Also 
<persName xml:id="14">Raleigh's</persName>  Brother in Law 
<persName xml:id="2523">Simpson</persName>.  We went to the College, and there I gave my address (in a borrowed hood) to a great assembly of students, clergymen, &amp; a few ladies.  The Principal in his introductory speech exhibited a copy of my book, <ref xml:id="78">"The National Church"</ref>, and urged the students to read it!  They all seemed to like what I said: &amp; the students were very attentive, &amp; loud in their applause.  After coming home we had some conversation, &amp; so to bed.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Mine host talked much, and with evident fondness for the subject of religious revivals, and other extraordinary spiritual phenomena.  He admitted that 
<persName xml:id="2028">Torrey</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2029">Alexander</persName> were much inferior to 
<persName xml:id="2030">Moody</persName>.  He told me that there were districts in Scotland famous for the religious revivals which seemed to inhere in the soil: that these revivals emerged suddenly in connection with the regular ministry of the church: that they transformed for good whole towns &amp; localities: &amp; were lasting in their effects.  He had recently attended a conference in Aberdeen where the survivors of the great revival of 1859 &amp; the following years had come together, &amp; borne remarkable testimony to the permanence of the holy impressions which they had received therein.  Aberdeen appears to be eminent in these respects.  The level of preaching is higher there than in Edinburgh, and the inhabitants more than commonly open to religious impressions.  Of Moody's work in Edinburgh he spoke in terms of high approval, admiring especially the close cooperation of 
<persName xml:id="2031">Henry Drummond</persName> with the American evangelist.  The two men were naturally antithetical in temperament &amp; habit, but they worked together with unvarying harmony.</p>
         <p>
            
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
