<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">"Why art thou so full of heaviness, O my soul: and why art thou so disquieted within me?  Put thy trust in God: for I will yet give him thanks for the help of his countenance"</hi>.  </p>
         </div>
         <p>The depression of the Saints at least carries this comfort that one has <hi rend="underline">that</hi> link with them, if no other.  In these states of mental &amp; moral collapse every trifle becomes transmuted into a sinister token or omen of disaster.  Thus the circumstance that we numbered but 13 at Holy Communion thrust across my unhappy mind the uncomfortable thought of betrayal. 'Which then is the traitor?' was the question which intruded itself as I looked over the kneeling line of communicants!  Truly one's severest censor is within one's self.</p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation at Mattins, including the 
<persName xml:id="125">Duke</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="820">Duchess of Buccleugh</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="195">Sir George</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1130" display="no">Lady Bartley</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="747" display="no">Capt. Butler</persName>, &amp; one or two lingering M.Ps [sic].  I preached on the episode recorded in the first lesson – Jehoiakim cutting the roll. 
<persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName> sang the service quite sufficiently well.  We had 
<persName xml:id="2011">Purcell's</persName> 'Bells' anthem.  Mainly this was a comforting service.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1864">Balfour Wilson</persName> came to lunch.  He seems very well now.  Also 
<persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName>, whom I have not seen for months.  Both went to 
<orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's</orgName> first.  
<persName xml:id="554">Gilbert</persName> came with me in the afternoon to the 
<orgName xml:id="65">Leysian Mission</orgName>, where I addressed a large assembly of men.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At Evensong there was another large congregation.  <hi rend="italic">I was unable to finish my sermon, for my voice suddenly cracked, &amp; I could not recover it! This was a ludicrous &amp; humiliating performance, but the congregation behaved beautifully</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="121">Custard</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="1203">his wife</persName> came in to supper.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
