<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[15]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1909.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2046">Brand</persName> lunched here, and afterwards had some conversation with me on religious topics.  </p>
         <p>

<persName xml:id="433"><hi rend="bold underline">Canon Wilson</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> wrote to me asking for information as to the origin &amp; meaning of the Rubric at</hi> the end of the Confirmation Service.  He has an actual case of intolerance in view:&#8211;</p>
         <p>'Here in Worcester &#8211; this is private &#8211; a case has arisen of a lady &amp; her son, communicants in the Scottish National Church, being refused permission to communicate in her parish Church, with the deliberate consent of the 
<persName xml:id="2047">Bishop</persName>, who excludes her from every Church in his diocese.  This seems to me monstrous.  But they entrench themselves behind the letter.'</p>
         <p>I wrote to him giving some reasons for the wider interpretation of the Rubric: and adding some references.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="413">Harry Reichel</persName> arrived on one of his business visits to town.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[16]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Nov. 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I attended the anniversary meeting of Trinity Presbyterian Church in the Clapham road. Old 
<persName xml:id="394">Lord Strathcona</persName> presided, &amp; there was a large attendance.  The minister, 
<persName xml:id="2048" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Smyth Wood</persName>, has the reputation of a popular preacher.  He hails from Ireland.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, Nov. 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, a presentation of a silver salver with a purse containing &#x00A3;170 was made to the out&#8211;going Precentor, 
<persName xml:id="297">Daniell&#8211;Bambridge</persName>.  The 
<persName xml:id="44">Dean</persName> presided, &amp; the 
<persName xml:id="296">
<persName xml:id="208">
<persName xml:id="122">Canons</persName></persName></persName> (save 
<persName xml:id="109">Wilberforce</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="752">Barnett</persName>) were with him.  Bambridge has been 26 years in Westminster, mostly at the Abbey.  There is a feeling of change in the air.  Who will go next?</p>
         
         </body></text></TEI>   

