<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[115]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910. Pitnacree.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Pouring rain to begin the day!  I wrote letters to Gilbert, 
<persName xml:id="630">Bob</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>.</p>
         <p>The rain ceased about 1 p.m. and the afternoon &amp; evening were fine.  The 
<orgName xml:id="193">scouts</orgName> arrived at lunch time, 22 in number with 
<persName xml:id="2262" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Poycy</persName> in charge, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2263" display="no">his father</persName> in attendance.  Lunch was given them in one of the pantries.  Afterwards I took some photographs of the party.  They had tea about 4.30 p.m., &amp; then went off; two of their number having failed to reach the station in time for the train, were left at the hotel to follow by the first vehicle that would take them.</p>
         <p>There is some danger of these scouts being spoiled by the well&#8211;meant folly of their friends.  Everywhere they are made welcome, &amp; too often they are feasted &amp; fussed over absurdly.  By consequence they are not getting from their discipline the graces of discipline, but are rather being disinclined for the normal severities of life.  These boys are the choir boys of All Hallows, Barking E.C., and in their case one must assume all the softening &amp; demoralysing [sic] conditions apparently incidental to the Anglican choir boy's situation.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
