<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[102]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The post brought me some letters, including one from 
<persName xml:id="113">Harold</persName> conceived in a penitent mood: and one from 
<persName xml:id="1043">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bovey</persName> announcing the sudden death of 
<persName xml:id="1242">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fleet</persName>.  I wrote to Harold, &amp; also to 
<persName xml:id="2739" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fleet</persName>.</p>
         <p>Then we walked over the plain: on the road we met some khaki&#8211;clad troops, &amp; took three photographs of them.</p>
         <p>After tea our host went a&#8211;fishing, &amp; our hostess drove us to Old Sarum, which lies about 3 miles from Salisbury, &amp; makes an impressive spectacle against the sky.  It consists of an outer rampart running round the whole extent of the fortress; then a dry moat; then another rampart environing the city proper; &amp; within a Norman castle, which is now being excavated.  A good deal of the masonry has been uncovered, &amp; the ground plan is being made out.  Two dungeons give an ugly impression of feudal possibilities.  I took some photographs.  The whole place is richly vested in grass, bushes, &amp; some trees.  We saw it to great advantage bathed in the sunlight of a beautiful summer evening.  The country was lovely as we drove back to Milston, which we reached about 8 p.m.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
