<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[72]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright morning but a cold wind.  I celebrated at 8 a.m. in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's; there were 18 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>There was a very crowded church at 11 a.m.: but the most part of my regular hearers, mistakenly assuming my absence, were not present.  The collection was less than last Sunday.  I preached from two texts, I. Chron. 29.15 and I. Cor. 15.58.  After the Benediction the 'Dead March' was played.  The Anthem was 'Crossing the bar'.  
<persName xml:id="1028">Lord Wolmer's</persName> Banns were read for the first time.</p>
         <p>At Evensong the crowd was immense.  I allowed six men to occupy the sedilia; and allowed the step of the Comm<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> rail to be used as a seat: benches &amp; chairs were placed in the Chancel: indeed, I think, no more people <hi rend="underline">could</hi> have been brought into the Church.  
<persName xml:id="1019">Addis</persName> preached.  We played the 'Dead March' after service.  The Offertory just exceeded &#x00A3;10.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[73]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The 
<orgName xml:id="48" display="no">Prayer&#8211;book Revision Committee</orgName> met at the 
<placeName xml:id="13">Church House</placeName> on Wednesday, Thursday, &amp; Friday (May 11&#8211;13).  
<persName xml:id="2383">Canon Dalton</persName> of Windsor produced an immense list of amendments, which mostly failed to commend themselves.  
<persName xml:id="2382">Canon Keymer</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="1020">Archdeacon Taylor</persName> of Southwark &#8211; two other new members &#8211; indicated that they would be serviceable members.  The new secretary, 
<persName xml:id="2381">Archdeacon Robinson</persName>, is immensely more competent than 
<persName xml:id="166">Ingram</persName>.  But, when all is said, progress is horribly slow.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2380">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Llwyd</persName>, whom we met at Seattle last year, came to visit us on Thursday, the 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> May.  He is now Vice&#8211;Provost of Trinity College, Toronto, and is over here on the quest of an endowment for the college.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The annual vestry was held on Thursday, the 12</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> of May.  I nominated 
<persName xml:id="344">Sir Henry Craik</persName>, and the parishioners re&#8211;elected 
<persName xml:id="156">Fedarb</persName> as wardens.  The sidesmen were re&#8211;elected with the addition of 
<persName xml:id="1668">Cyril Mills</persName>.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">On Fedarb's motion the two old chairs in the inner vestry, which I assume to be disjecta membra of the Speaker's seat in the gallery, were presented to me</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
