<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Day, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The morning was very raw &amp; cold.  Later there developed tendencies to a smoky fog, but these came to nothing, and the latter part of the day was pleasantly fine.</p>
         <p>The Communicants were less than last year, but more than most years.  At 7 a.m. 37: at 8 a.m. 107: at 11 a.m. 229 making a total of 373.  I preached at the Choral Eucharist from S. John. XX.9, my subject being <ref xml:id="621">'The Argument from Prophecy'</ref>.  At Evensong, 
<persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName> preached an excellent sermon from the famous words of Job, 'I know that my Redeemer liveth &amp;c'.  The congregations were large, &amp; the offertories reached nearly &#x00A3;30.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> was much fluttered in the Abbey by the 
<persName xml:id="44">Dean's</persName> order to the choir to turn to the East for the 'Gloria in excelsis'.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1261">Miss Markham</persName> came to breakfast, &amp; to supper.  She says that her maid came away from the 'Three Hour Service' in the Abbey impressed with the extreme antiquity of the Dean. 'The Dean is really too old a man to be allowed to attempt that service', she said.  He is 5 years older than I.  Miss Markham herself assumed that he verged on 90!!  This sham antiquity is as matters go in England an asset of considerable value.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Easter Monday (March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1910) I went to Aldeburgh on a visit to </hi>
<persName xml:id="1494"><hi rend="bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Sinclair</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, who has established himself there in a commodious house hard by the churchyard</hi>.  In the house were staying 
<persName xml:id="1494">Archdeacon Sinclair</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2457">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> G. Rentoul</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2458">his mother</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2456" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wade</persName>.  On Tuesday we motored to Blythborough &amp; Southwold &#8211; two remarkably fine churches.  On Wednesday we visited Framlingham Castle &amp; Church.  In the latter are the tombs of the Norfolk, who commanded at Flodden, of his son, the unfortunate Surrey, &amp; of Henry Fitzroy, Henry VIII<hi rend="superscript underline">th's</hi> natural son.  On Thursday we went to Dunwich, where the last of many churches is visibly slipping into the sea.  On Friday I returned to Westminster: my travelling companion was young Rentoul, whom I found sufficiently interesting.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
