<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[111]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910. Kirkmichael House.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dubious morning passed into a fine day.  
<persName xml:id="227">Murray</persName> went off early to attend a political meeting.  I went in to the station with him, and on returning to the house talked with mine 
<persName xml:id="666">hostess</persName> in the garden.  Then I bestowed my last film on a photograph of a family group.  By this time the motor was at the door.  In the process of taking farewells my top hat was forgotten.  We motored as far as Lochmaben, &amp; there <hi rend="bold underline">were met by the carriage which carried us to Kirkmichael House, where we had arranged to spend the weekend with </hi>
<persName xml:id="2309"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="bold underline">All</hi></persName>, who is living there with her daughter 
<persName xml:id="2186">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pollok&#8211;M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Call.</persName>  We arrived about 1 p.m.  After lunch M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pollok&#8211;M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Call motored us through Dumfries to Caerlaverock Castle, &amp; then homewards by way of the Solway.  The Castle is a triangular ruin surrounded by a moat.  We returned about 5.45 p.m. &amp; had tea: then the elder lady, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Call, took me &amp; the dogs for a walk.</p>
         <p>I must have contracted a chill in the course of the afternoon for I felt miserably ill in the night, &amp; half suspected I was down with influenza.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
