<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[88]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The 
<orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName> met today, with the 
<persName xml:id="128">Abp. of C.</persName> in the chair. The first motion of importance was one by 
<persName xml:id="1736">Sir Alfred Cripps</persName> in these terms:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">"That the R.C.C. earnestly desires to promote Educational peace founded on the principle of religious equality &amp; the recognition of the claim of Church parents to equality of treatment in the vital question of the religious instruction of their children in the public elementary schools".</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">He made a violent &amp; uncompromising speech, &amp; was seconded in the same vein by 
<persName xml:id="2252">Sir Samuel Hoare</persName>.  Then I moved </hi><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="italic">an amendment, "To omit all words after 'equality' and to substitute the following 'and therefore recognizes that the privileged position of the Church schools in the 'single school' areas can no longer be rightly maintained, &amp; that the vital question of the rel: instruction of children in the public elementary schools can only be equitably answered by confining the teaching in such schools to those elements of Christian Faith &amp; Morals on which English Christians generally are agreed'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">In the course of my speech I referred to the 
<orgName xml:id="189">Edinburgh Missionary Conference</orgName> in proof of the position that in spite of our denominational divisions there was a fundamental agreement in faith &amp; morals.  </hi>
<persName xml:id="49"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Gore</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> interrupted me with a vehement protest. I pointed out that the Conference had prayed &amp; praised together, &amp; even rehearsed the Apostles' Creed: &amp; these circumstances might fairly be supposed to indicate a consciousness of fundamental agreement among the members</hi><hi rend="italic">. Subsequently I withdrew the amendment mainly because I knew that the Abp. of C. desired that there should be no division. His Grace sent me a very friendly little note. Later the Conference carried a fanatical motion of 
<persName xml:id="1748">Lord Halifax</persName> on the Marriage Question.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[90]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday afternoon (July 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910) the Abp. of C. presented to the 
<persName xml:id="212">Dean of Canterbury</persName> the portrait which had been subscribed for by some 400 of his friends.  I attended the function as one of the subscribers.  That evening I dined in the 
<orgName xml:id="42">National Club</orgName> as the guest of 
<persName xml:id="764">Sir John Kennaway</persName>.  After dinner there were some speeches.  I replied to the toast of my health.  Two Indian gentlemen spoke rather alarmingly about the seditious propaganda among Indian students in this country.  Old 
<persName xml:id="2077">Sir Charles Elliot</persName> spoke depressingly on the same theme.</p>
         <p>On Saturday afternoon I baptized 
<persName xml:id="2076" display="no">Alexander Frederick Ramsay</persName> the son of 
<persName xml:id="1033">Fred Ramsay</persName>, the Churchwardens' clerk.</p>
         <p>I lunched with 
<persName xml:id="566">Fleming</persName> &amp; had some talk with 
<persName xml:id="2253">Bishop Brent</persName>.  He promised to preach in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> on July 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
