<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after the Epiphany, January 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A warm, wet, windy morning.  The congregation in the Abbey at 10 a.m. was very small.  Probably the excitement of the first polls affected church–going.  I preached an old sermon, in which some lines of 
<persName xml:id="2441">Churchill</persName> were quoted, which much delighted 
<persName xml:id="737">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Erskine</persName>.  After service I called on 
<persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> in order to learn the result of the polling.  The Conservatives have gained 18 and lost 3 seats.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="3420">Holmes</persName>, of the Collegiate Hospital of S. Catherine in Regent's Park, preached in the Abbey at 3 p.m.  He took for his text a sentence from 2. Peter, 'making your election sure': &amp; played on the word 'election' grotesquely.  I understand that this empty &amp; voluble preacher, who waked the echoes of the Abbey, is considered very highly by the diocesan authorities.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1282" display="no">Wilfrid Hill</persName> came to see me.  <lb/>At Evensong there was a large congregation in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.  I preached another old sermon.</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="bold">40</hi>]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">On Monday Jan</hi><hi rend="i sup u">y</hi><hi rend="italic"> 17</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, 1910, 
<persName xml:id="122">Hine Haycock</persName> came with me to </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">
<orgName xml:id="47">Zion College</orgName>, where I read a paper to the</hi><hi rend="italic"> "Christian Conference" on <ref xml:id="447">'Must the expression of Christian Brotherhood in Interchange of Pulpits &amp; Intercommunion be hindered by the possession of an historic episcopate?'</ref> 
<persName xml:id="1936">T. A. Lacey</persName> made a rambling speech in opposition.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Afterwards we went to Trafalgar Square to observe the crowds awaiting the results of the polling.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Jan., I travelled to Edinburgh from King's Cross, &amp; arrived nearly 40 minutes after time.  I drove at once to 39 Palmerston Place, where I was to be the guest of 
<persName xml:id="1135">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mitford Mitchell</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="491"><hi rend="bold underline">Lady Frances Balfour</hi></persName> was there: &amp; to dinner came 
<persName xml:id="2026">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kelman</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1511" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pagan</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1524">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Norman M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1140">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Patterson</persName> all very pleasant, &amp; <hi rend="underline">conversible</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The next morning, Sunday 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Jan. 1910, I preached in Free S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> George's.  Before service an unknown lunatick insisted on sharing the pulpit with me, &amp; had to be evicted by force.  This was rather disturbing to the congregation, but I had no knowledge of the incident until afterwards</hi>.  I preached from the Sermon on the Mount: my sermon took 35 minutes to deliver.  [<hi rend="bold">41</hi>] When we came out of St. George's, the snow was falling fast.</p>
         <p>Lady Frances went back to Whittinghame at 6 p.m. dropping me on the way to the station at S. Cuthbert's.  There the congregation was fairly large considering that 
<persName xml:id="1139">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wallace Williamson</persName> was being inducted at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles' today, &amp; was preaching his first sermon tonight.  The Church, which seats 2000, was nearly three parts full.  <hi rend="bold underline">I had been asked to <ref xml:id="448">preach</ref> to 'Young men'</hi>, and I had prepared my sermon on the supposition that young men would form the bulk of my congregation.  In point of fact, it was an ordinary congregation.  Young men were present, &amp; so were young women: nor were ancients of both sexes absent.</p>
         <p>On Monday, the 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi>, the weather was odious, uniting every type of badness.  I wrote 
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="76">Mother</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>.  Then I lunched with 
<persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford Bell</persName>, and <hi rend="bold underline">met the </hi>
<persName xml:id="2154"><hi rend="bold underline">Bishop of Edinburgh</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, an amiable &amp; all but toothless old man.  He told me with much gusto the story of the King's insistence on </hi>
<persName xml:id="130"><hi rend="bold underline">Lang's</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> attending the parish church at Balmoral.  A </hi>
<persName xml:id="2159" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Colonel Stuart</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> was there: both he and </hi>
<persName xml:id="1077"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Bell</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> had been in S. Cuthbert's last night</hi>.  Afterwards mine host took me to the University Club, where I read the papers.  Then I went to 7, Charlotte Sq: at 6.45, in order to have some conversation with 
<persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName> on the question of the 
<orgName xml:id="176" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Divorce Commission</hi></orgName>.<note xml:id="112" n="1"></note>  He is plainly suspicious of Lang: &amp; wants me to be a witness.  [<hi rend="bold">42</hi>] I pressed on him the importance of investigating the <hi rend="underline">whole</hi> subject of marriage–conditions, &amp; reporting in a very large &amp; thorough way, so that the means of effective discussion &amp; finally of legislation might be given to the public.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I was much impressed by the partisan violence displayed in conversation by 
<persName xml:id="2015">Carnegie Simpson</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="2016">Martin</persName>. They seemed incapable of allowing any justification for the Unionist position, which none the less I defended, much to their astonishment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> January, I wrote letters, &amp; then walked into the city, as far as S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles', where I was recognized by the 
<persName xml:id="2322" display="no">old Beadle</persName>.  After lunch, mine host &amp; I went to the Club, &amp; afterwards visited the old Parliament House, &amp; looked into a Court, where a foolish case against a schoolmaster for thrashing a cheeky boy was in progress.  After tea we visited old 
<persName xml:id="124">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacGregor</persName>, &amp; found a crowded room–full of women.</p>
         <p>Wednesday, the 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi>, was another bright and very cold day.  After writing letters &amp;c. till lunch time, mine host took me to see Heriot's Hospital, a very interesting 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century foundation.  One of the boys had slipped &amp; broken his leg just as we arrived.  We walked back through the Grassmarket, where I observed with surprise that the scene of the martyrdoms was unmarked [<hi rend="bold">43</hi>] by any memorial.<note xml:id="113" n="2"></note> 
<persName xml:id="275">Maimie Parker–Smith</persName> called.  </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1137"><hi rend="italic bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Cameron Lees</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline">, late minister of S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Giles', and his successor 
<persName xml:id="1139"><hi rend="italic bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Wallace Williamson</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> dined here.  They were very interesting</hi><hi rend="italic">.  Our conversation turned on the Irvingites, &amp; the alleged gift of tongues.<note xml:id="151" n="3"></note>  Williamson said that he had heard it at an ordination in the 
<orgName xml:id="3" display="no">Catholic Apostolic Church</orgName> in Edinburgh.  He found himself compelled to go forth from the assembly, so repulsive to him was the noise, 'like some animal', but he admitted that the performance seemed genuine.  </hi>
<persName xml:id="1137"><hi rend="italic bold underline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Lees</hi></persName><hi rend="italic bold underline"> asked me my opinion of the Papist Boanerges, </hi>
<persName xml:id="2241"><hi rend="italic bold underline">Bernard Vaughan</hi></persName>.<note xml:id="250" n="1"></note>  He related one good mot of that unpleasing person.  Speaking of 
<persName xml:id="292">Lord Rosebery</persName>, he said 'He's a fine man for a fine day"</hi><hi rend="italic">. Rather to my surprise D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> L. said that he had ever been, &amp; was still, politically a Liberal.  He added that before 1885 most of the Kirk leaders were Liberal.</hi></p>
         <p>On Thursday, the 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi>, I lunched with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kelman.  There were present 
<persName xml:id="614">Prof. Lodge</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2327">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacGregor</persName> (an U.F. Minister), 
<persName xml:id="2015">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Simpson</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="244">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> G. A. Smith</persName>, &amp; another. Afterwards 
<persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName> fetched me in his motor–car for a tour in the poorer districts in order to show some objects of interest.  We saw the chapel of the Magdalen Hospital, which contained the only prae–Reformation stained glass in Scotland.  This consisted of some armorial bearings, including those of Mary of Guise.  The chapel had considerable historical interest, for [<hi rend="bold">44</hi>] there 
<persName xml:id="2239">Knox</persName> held the first Assembly of the Kirk.  Afterwards the Chapel was bestowed on the Hammermen of Edinburgh, &amp; they placed their notices on the walls from the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> to the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> centuries.  We went on to the Cannongate [sic], &amp; looked at a very interesting 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house of the 
<persName xml:id="2443" display="no">Earl of Huntley</persName>, &amp; a more magnificent 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century mansion of the 
<persName xml:id="2442" display="no">Earl of Murray</persName>.  This was the house from which Argyll looked at the prisoner Montrose.  In the grave–yard opposite are buried 
<persName xml:id="2242">Adam Smith</persName>, &amp; many other notable Scotchmen.  Finally we visited Knox's House, where 
<persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName> showed me with legitimate pride the very interesting &amp; well–assorted collection of Knox–memorials.<note xml:id="114" n="4"></note></p>
         <p>On Friday, Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I lunched with the students at the New College; &amp; afterwards addressed the members of the 
<orgName xml:id="6" display="no">Missionary Union</orgName>. Then I was carried off to the 
<orgName xml:id="5" display="no">University Settlement</orgName>, where I gave a short address to the workers.<note xml:id="115" n="5"></note>  Old 
<persName xml:id="2014">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Whyte</persName> came to both functions, and made <hi rend="underline">very </hi>flatterous speeches respecting me!  I suspect that Christian Socialism of the conventional type goes far among these good people; but I was careful to avoid hurting their feelings.  That queer creature, 
<persName xml:id="2444" display="no">Munro Fergusson</persName>, is at the head of the Settlement.  
<persName xml:id="2026"><hi rend="bold underline">Kelman</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> evidently plays the part of a Scottish Scott–Holland</hi>.</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="bold">45</hi>]</p>
         <p>Returning to the house I resumed reading a new book on <ref xml:id="331">'The Wars of Religion in France'</ref> by a Chicago Professor of European History; 
<persName xml:id="183">James Westfall Thompson</persName>. It is very well–done.</p>
         <p>There came to dinner two divines of the established Church, 
<persName xml:id="1141" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Weir</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="2394">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacLean</persName>.  The last is said to write the 'Scotsman' leaders on ecclesiastical subjects.  We had much conversation on matters urgent in Church &amp; State.</p>
         <p>On Saturday, Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 
<persName xml:id="275">Maimie Parker Smith</persName> carried me off to lunch with 
<persName xml:id="2395">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Davidson</persName>, the 
<persName xml:id="128">Archbishop of C's</persName> brother.  
<persName xml:id="2396">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi></persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2397" display="no">Miss Davidson</persName> were also at lunch.  They live at a large house delightfully situated, with a noble view of the Forth with the Fife–shire hills beyond.  We had much pleasant conversation mainly political.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> D. has been a great traveller.  He said his 
<persName xml:id="2398">grandfather</persName> had been born as long ago as 1745: his 
<persName xml:id="2399">father</persName> not being born until 1811.  This is a long period to cover in two generations.  Also he told me a story of Lord Young.  <hi rend="bold underline">Addressing 
<persName xml:id="2400">Alfred Austin</persName>, he inquired whether he still wrote poetry.  Yes, replied the Laureate, 'I must do something to keep the wolf from the door".  "Do you read your poetry to the wolf?" asked the old Judge</hi>.  Afterwards I walked to Holyrood, &amp; again looked at the old houses in the Canongate.</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="bold">46</hi>]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Sunday, the 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Jan</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">y</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1910, I preached in S. Cuthbert's</hi>.  D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacGregor took the first prayer, &amp; his assistant read the lessons, &amp; did the rest.  I preached &amp; gave the Benediction.  My sermon was on "Associations in Judgment".  The church is said to seat 2500 people, &amp;, save for a few seats in the corner of the gallery, seemed to be quite full.  Afterwards I lunched with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MacGregor.  
<persName xml:id="412">James</persName> &amp; Maimie Parker–Smith were also there, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2401" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cunningham (?) [sic]</persName>.</p>
         <p>In the evening I preached in the U.F. Church at <hi rend="bold underline">Morningside</hi>. 
<persName xml:id="936">Forrest</persName> conducted the service very reverently.  I read the lessons, preached, &amp; gave the Benediction.  There was a large &amp; attentive congregation.  I preached on "The criticism of scruples".  Forrest came back with me to supper with mine host.  On the way he told me that 
<persName xml:id="1525">Cooper</persName> was raising the question of doctrinal subscription in the Re–union Conferences.</p>
         <p>I returned to Westminster on Monday, Jan. 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Friday I attended the memorial service for old </hi>
<persName xml:id="232"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Talbot</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> in the Abbey, and read the Lesson</hi>.</p>
         <p>Afterwards I gave a Lecture on the "Yellowstone" to the Westminster Boys.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>