<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[106]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910. Rose Castle.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Glorious weather.  We spent the time before lunch in viewing 
<placeName xml:id="48">Rose Castle</placeName>, and its grounds: &amp; in going [for] a stroll through the meadows to the village Church.  We took several photographs in the course of these proceedings.</p>
         <p>Rose Castle is a fine building of pink sandstone; it is of various dates.  The Strickland Tower &amp; the Kitchen being the oldest parts.  It is surrounded by a broad moat now forming a fine kitchen garden.  The flower gardens laid out in the formal Dutch fashion are good.  An early 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Bishop, 
<persName xml:id="2297">Percy</persName>, worked great improvements in the castle.  He restored the chapel, using in the work much excellent oak panelling (linen&#8211;pattern) from Lambeth, to which he had access thro' 
<persName xml:id="2299">his wife</persName>, the 
<persName xml:id="2300">Abp's</persName> daughter.  Little appears to be known of the history of the building.  The name is ancient for Edward I dated a charter from 'la Rose.'</p>
         <p>After lunch, the Bishop &amp; I had a long conversation together sitting in the garden.  He is an odd mixture of shrewdness &amp; vanity, perhaps also of coarseness &amp; sentiment.  Mainly he impressed me as genuinely anxious to make a fight against the dominant Tractarianism, but woefully embarrassed by the poor quality of his associates.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>He told me that 
<persName xml:id="1132">Straton</persName>, the Bp. of Newcastle, is greatly successful within his diocese.  All the diocesan funds are flourishing, &amp; he himself is the idol of the people.  Yet so successfully do the Tractarians obscure these facts, that in general belief he is a bull&#8211;necked tyrant of the narrowest sympathies, &amp; nothing more.  I agree that the 'log&#8211;rolling' &amp; 'belittling' of that party are very potent &amp; mischievous factors.</p>
         <p>I urged him to use his powers as Ordinary under the Rubrick to put forward a schedule of Lessons &amp; Psalms to be used in stead of the undesirable ones provided in the Prayer&#8211;book.  It seemed a new idea to him that he could to this, &amp; promised to consider the matter.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">He said that he regarded my present position as the greatest in some ways in the C. of E:; that he would not exchange it for any bpk.; that my influence was wider than that of any bp.  But this seemed to me but little convincing: though I admit that from some points of view it w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be difficult to find a better strategic position</hi>.</p>
         <p>After tea we bade farewell, &amp; came away.  Our 'tourist ticket' did not serve us from Carlisle to Ruthwell.  We arrived at the last at 7.5 p.m., were met there by the motor, &amp; driven to 
<placeName xml:id="19">Murraythwaite.</placeName></p>
</body></text></TEI>
