<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[74]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, May 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This is my 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Whitsunday in Westminister.  The Church is partially draped with violet cloth for the Royal Mourning.  
<persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated at 7 a.m. when there were 14 com<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>; I celebrated at 8 a.m. when there were 61.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation at the choral Eucharist, but no abnormal crowd.  The 
<persName xml:id="784">Speaker</persName> was present with 
<persName xml:id="1731">his wife</persName> &amp; daughters, and all communicated.  I preached an old sermon, adding an appendix relevant to the occasion.  There were 195 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>At Evensong the Church was quite full, but there was no repetition of the excessive crowd of the last Sunday. I <ref xml:id="622">preached</ref> on I. Cor. XII.26.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday (May 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910) I went across to the Palace, &amp; had some conversation with the Speaker with respect to the service on Friday.  He has just returned from visiting 
<persName xml:id="1730">his brother</persName> at Constantinople.  He evidently has no great confidence in the present r&#x00E9;gime in Turkey.</p>
         <p>On Thursday (May 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910) the body of the late King was carried with great pomp from Buckingham Palace to Westminster Hall for the Lying&#8211;in&#8211;state.  I watched the procession from the roof of 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, where a party of about one hundred persons had assembled.  The 
<persName xml:id="296">Subdean</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2460" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lloyd</persName> dined here: the last also staying with us.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Friday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1910, the late King was buried at Windsor with extraordinary pomp</hi>.  The weather was brilliant, a Thunderstorm in the night having dispersed the clouds &amp; cooled the air.  As the day advanced, the temperature rose, &amp; in the afternoon was sultry.  The roof of S. Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi> was occupied by, perhaps, 150 people, members of the congregation, church officers, choirmen, &amp; private friends.  No finer view of the procession could have been gained anywhere.  The blaze of colour presented by the cohort of monarchs &amp; princes was almost dazzling.</p>
         <p>At 1 p.m. a memorial service was held in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Church was reserved for members of Parl<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>, &amp; their friends.  These were seated by the assistance of the House of Commons attendants, who wore their badges.  But the Members did not fill much more than half the Church; so the general public were admitted until the whole had been filled.  </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName> sang the service; 
<persName xml:id="109">Wilberforce</persName> read the lesson: I read at the Altar the concluding prayers &amp; pronounced the Benediction.  The Anthems were "Behold all flesh is as the Grass" (Brahms), and "Blest are the departed" (Spohr).  The Hymns were 401, 'Now the Labourer's task is o'er', and 165 'O God our help in ages past'.  The 'Dead March' was played while the congregation stood; &amp; Chopin's 'Marche Fun&#x00E8;bre' as they left the Church.  The whole service took an hour &amp; ten minutes.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1687" display="no">Albert Stewart</persName> had tea with me: I gave him a copy of my sermons.  Afterwards I took 'Logic' for a constitutional.</p>
         <p>The crowds continued to hang about the Abbey for hours.</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
