<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[34]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Christmas, January 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I celebrated in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's</orgName> at 8 a.m.  There were 23 cts, including 
<persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName>.</p>
         <p>At 10 a.m. I preached in the Abbey, repeating the sermon I preached last year in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's, but mitigating the allusions to the Messina earthquake.  It was the smallest congregation I have ever preached to in the Abbey.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Welldon preached an excellent sermon in the afternoon from the words: 'Behold, I make all things new'.  It was, perhaps, the best sermon I have heard him preach, the only one that seemed to justify the exalted descriptions of his preaching which I have listened to from his friends.  There seemed to be a very large congregation.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I preached in the Abbey at the Evening Service.  There was a large congregation.  My <ref xml:id="619">sermon</ref> was, I fear, rather wearisome to listen to.  
<persName xml:id="14">Raleigh</persName> was in the congregation.  He came in afterwards to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[35]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Tuesday, Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910, a service was held in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi> synchronously with the Funeral of 
<persName xml:id="607">Earl Percy</persName> at Alnwick.  The 
<persName xml:id="609">Duke of Argyle</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="637">Princess Louise</persName> attended in person, and 
<persName xml:id="611">Lord Colebrooke</persName> represented the King.  The 
<persName xml:id="176">Bishop of Peterboro</persName> &amp; I officiated.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1135"><hi rend="underline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Mitford Mitchell</hi></persName> called on me.  He declares himself an 'agnostic' on Tariff Reform: &amp; prophesies a few Unionist gains in Scotland.  As to the Union of the Scottish churches <hi rend="italic">he says that the religious women on both sides are hostile to the project</hi>: that many of the rural clergy of the Established Church are so: but that the wisest laity are favourable.  Unhappily Scottish opinion generally is not interested in Church questions.</p>
         <p>On Friday, Jan<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> the choirboys from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi> came here for their party.  With the aid of 
<persName xml:id="55">Knox's</persName> lantern, I exhibited the coloured slides of the Yellowstone &amp; Niagara.  
<persName xml:id="18">Gerald</persName> brought a wonderful selection of toys.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
