<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I was called late, &amp; had barely time to hustle on my clothes, &amp; get around to 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi></orgName> unbathed &amp; unshaved.  
<persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> celebrated, there were but a dozen com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>Rain set in shortly after breakfast: &amp; spoiled the congregation at Mattins.  However, there was a fair congregation in the circumstances.  I preached on the Church, a carefully prepared sermon, but dull &amp; wearisome.  The congregation was visibly bored!  Afterwards I celebrated the Holy Comm<hi rend="superscript">n</hi>; there were 90 communicants.</p>
         <p>There was a fair congregation at Evensong considering the unfavourable weather.  I preached an old sermon on 'The Saints', which like the chariots of the Egyptian King 'went heavily.'</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> met on Nov: 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1910 for a special session dedicated to Prayer Book Revision.  On that day, which was my Birthday, I attended the session, feeling miserable by reason of a chill contracted overnight.  I spoke at the end of the afternoon discussion.  Then I went to Paddington &amp; took the chair at a public debate, arranged by the local C.O.S. &amp; Church Socialist Leage on Socialism.  There were 6 champions on either side.  I was distressed to notice that 4 of the Socialist speakers were young Anglican clergymen, &amp; that their language was wild &amp; crude.  In truth it was a conflict of dervishes verses attorneys!  The room was crowded largely with young men, whose sympathies were obviously Socialistic.  I was reduced to physical misery by this performance, &amp; reached home shortly before midnight in a state of collapse.</p>
         <p>The next two days &#8211; Wednesday &amp; Thursday &#8211; were spent in bed.  I missed an unusually important discussion in Convocation, and paired with 
<persName xml:id="376">Knox&#8211;Little</persName> for the division, which took place on Thursday.  The Fanaticks were beaten by 71 to 44.</p>
         <p>The 
<persName xml:id="1219">Archdeacon of Leicester</persName>, the 
<persName xml:id="1123">Bishop of Southampton</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="250">Watson</persName> were our guests for the Convocation.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
