<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After the heavy rain last night the atmosphere is humid, warm &amp; languorous.  There were but 16 communicants at the early celebration.  
<persName xml:id="55">Knox</persName> was celebrant &amp; I assisted.</p>
         <p>At Mattins the Church was well filled.  I preached on the Healing of the Paralytic, which came into the Gospel for the day.  I celebrated afterwards, when there were 92 communicants.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon Gilbert &amp; Reggie went with me into Hyde Park for the benefit of Logic's health.  The sultriness of the atmosphere made walking very fatiguing; &amp; portended a tempest.</p>
         <p>Rain fell shortly before service–time, but in spite of it there was a fairly large congregation at Evensong.  I preached from the Psalm: XIV. I. "<hi rend="underline">The fool hath said in his heart: There is no God</hi>".</p>
         <p>The Offertories during the day exceeded £25.  Reggie, Gilbert, &amp; Albert came to supper.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday afternoon we left town in order to spend a few days with <hi rend="bold underline">the </hi>
<persName xml:id="648">
<persName xml:id="1951">
<persName xml:id="2127">
<persName xml:id="2128">
<persName xml:id="2501"><hi rend="bold underline">Caröes</hi></persName></persName></persName></persName></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> in Surrey</hi>.  They have created a most fascinating 
<placeName xml:id="14" display="no">house</placeName> out of an Elizabethan farm house.  The barn has been transmuted into a delightful drawing room.  The furniture is all antique, &amp; in keeping with the house.  </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Caröe motored us to Winchester, where we went over the Cathedral, &amp; lunched with </hi>
<persName xml:id="2500"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Rendall</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> at the School</hi>.  In the Cathedral we fell in with 
<persName xml:id="207">Goudy</persName>, who had come over from Southampton, where he is staying with the 
<persName xml:id="1123">Bishop</persName>.  Then we went on to Romsey, which we inspected: &amp; then returned to Winchester where we visited S. Cross, &amp; had tea.  Here we dropped Olaf, the eldest son – a delightful lad – that he might return to the School: &amp; we ourselves went back to Vann, arriving just in time for dinner.  
<persName xml:id="2502">Sir William</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2503">Lady Chance</persName> came to dinner.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Christian took us for a walk through the woods to the top of the hill, whence noble prospects on all sides open to view.  The country is ravishingly beautiful.  Our hostess drove us to Charterhouse School at Godalming <hi rend="bold underline">where we lunched with 
<persName xml:id="2504">Rendal</persName>, her brother in law</hi>.  He took us to see Loseley, a noble Elizabethan mansion near Godalming, which is the scene of a well–authenticated Ghost–story.  We also visited the Watts Gallery, &amp; then made our way back to Vann.  On <hi rend="bold underline">Thursday</hi> we returned to town.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[134]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday I travelled to Hull, in order to fulfil a promise that I would take part in the opening of a new Wesleyan Methodist Mission Hall.  <hi rend="bold underline">One of the local M.P.s, </hi>
<persName xml:id="2505"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Thomas Ferens</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> (Holderness House, Hull) was mine host</hi>: &amp; he entertained two wealthy Wesleyans, 
<persName xml:id="2506">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rank</persName>, a millionaire–miller, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2507">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Holloway</persName>, a large contractor &amp; builder.  All these rich men appeared to be very hearty Wesleyans.  The meeting was very enthusiastic.  About 2000 people were crowded into the Hall; &amp; there was an overflow meeting to which, however, I did not go.  Rather to my surprise there was a <ref xml:id="345">short report</ref> of my speech in the Times (Friday, Oct. 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) under the heading "Canon Henson on the Function of Religion."  I travelled back to town of Friday morning.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName> went with me for a walk in the Park on Saturday afternoon, &amp; afterwards had tea with me.</p>
        
</body></text></TEI>
