<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[135]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1910.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very close warm day.  I celebrated at 8 a.m. when there were 22 com<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>At Mattins there was a very large congregation, a circumstance not wholly unconnected with the fact that S. John's is closed (quite illegally) for repairs.  I preached on the Cleansing of the Temple, repeating a sermon first preached in the Abbey a year ago.</p>
         <p>
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> was crowded at Evensong.  I preached from <hi rend="underline">Psalm 49.20</hi> 'Man being in honour hath no understanding: but is compared to the beasts that perish.'  In the course of the sermon I made allusion to the revolution in Portugal, quoting some lines from 'Richard II.'  The offertory was &#x00A3;<hi rend="underline">8.13.0</hi>.</p>
         <p>There came to supper 
<persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName>, Gilbert, Reggie, and 
<persName xml:id="727">Roxburgh</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday (Oct: 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) I interviewed 
<persName xml:id="2115">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Arthur Mackarness</persName> with respect to the marriage of 
<persName xml:id="2116" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cobbold</persName>, an innocent party.  He gave, &amp; set down in writing, the most positive assurance that her conduct had been irreproachable throughout the cruellest experiences.  Then I saw separately M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cobbold (who impressed me well) and 
<persName xml:id="2117" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Babington</persName>, whom she proposes to marry.</p>
         <p>I presided over a meeting of the Westminster Incumbents who elected 
<persName xml:id="2177">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ellis</persName>, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's to be a Governor of 
<orgName xml:id="60">Grey Coat Hospital</orgName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday (Oct: 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">) I wrote &amp; sent in to the 'Spectator' a long letter headed <ref xml:id="371" display="no">"Sectarian Anglicanism"</ref>, sharply challenging the pronouncement of 
<persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> at the Church Congress.  I shall not be surprised if the Editor fails to publish it</hi>.</p>
         <p>In the evening I attended the public meeting of the 
<orgName xml:id="179">Congregational Union</orgName> in Horton's Chapel at Hampstead.  It is an octagon seating some 1400 persons.  Every seat was occupied mainly with ministers, for the most part senior men, strong looking, but rather dour.  The Master of the Rolls (
<persName xml:id="2187">Cozens&#8211;Hardy</persName>) was in the chair, &amp; made an excellent little opening speech.  I spoke for rather more than half an hour, &amp; was very well received.  
<persName xml:id="393">Shakespeare</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="323">Sylvester Horne</persName> also spoke.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
