<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[256]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most glorious morning.  Before breakfast there was Brigade drill in which three Battalions &#8211; 
<orgName xml:id="200">Civil Service</orgName>, 
<orgName xml:id="209">London Scottish</orgName>, &amp; 
<orgName xml:id="70">Queen's Westminsters</orgName> &#8211; took part.  I went with the troops, &amp; enjoyed the spectacle greatly.  The London Scottish make a fine show.  Their uniform is very effective as it shows the face, &amp; has a pretty waving short petticoat above the bare knees.  The Queen's Westminsters <hi rend="bold">[257] </hi>are certainly disadvantaged by trailing their rifles.  This seems to be an old arrangement coming down from a time when a distinction was really drawn between muskets &amp; rifles: but <hi rend="underline">now</hi> everybody has rifles.  There may be a practical reason in the fact that when the weapon is carried at the shoulder, the sun glinting on the barrel might reveal the troops to an observant enemy.</p>
         <p>The London Scottish immediately after arriving in camp began to make preparations for their departure to Scotland, where they are to march from Oban to Glasgow.  </p>
         <p>I accompanied the signalling party, and admired the simple yet subtle machinery by which the heliograph compels the sun to transmit messages across immense tracts.  In India, I am assured, that many miles have been thus covered.</p>
         <p>The "Times" contains the substance of <ref xml:id="531">my little letter</ref> correcting the alarmist statements about the men's sufferings from heat.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon the captains issued pay to the men of their companies.</p>
         <p>After dinner I attended the Concert given by our own men in Y.M.C.A. tent.  At the close we vindicated our Christian character by singing a hymn, reading a Psalm, &amp; receiving a Benediction!  It was odd, perhaps incongruous, but well&#8211;intentioned.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
