<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[226]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~Surely God w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have the Church, his Spouse, as not an Harlot, so not a Slut; &amp; indeed outward decency in the Church is an harbinger to provide a lodging for inward devotion to follow after.  But we w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not have Religion so bedaubed with lace, that one cannot see the cloth: &amp; ceremonies which sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> adorn, obscure the substance of the Sacraments, &amp; God's worship.~~</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2095" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Tho</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">s</hi><hi rend="underline"> Fuller</hi></persName>. "Joseph's Parti&#8211;coloured Coat" [v. <ref xml:id="355">Selected Sermons</ref> vol: I. p. 217]</p>
         </div>
         <p>A brilliant warm morning.  I celebrated in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's at 8 a.m.  There were 73 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>At 11 a.m. the congregation was unusually small, and the comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> only numbered 168.  I <ref xml:id="637">preached</ref> for 33 minutes, but with difficulty on account of the heat.</p>
         <p>At 4 p.m. I baptized 
<persName xml:id="2289">Ethel Grace White</persName>, another of the 
<orgName xml:id="116">Stockwell College</orgName> Students.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="706">Sir Dyce Duckworth</persName> came to show me a letter he had written to 
<persName xml:id="2290" display="no">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Cobb</persName>.  I advised him to keep a copy.</p>
         <p>Ernest &amp; I walked Logic round S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's Park.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="293"><hi rend="bold underline">Edwin Saxton</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> came to see me</hi>.  He has rushed across to get Whitsunday with his family, &amp; sails again tomorrow.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[227]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>At Evensong the Church was by no means crowded.  This may, perhaps, be explained by the great heat.  I preached an abbreviated Sermon on I. Thess: V. 19, 20.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="800">Westlake</persName>, Gilbert, Ernest, George, &amp; Reggie came in to supper.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~The Holy Ghost is not an idle spectator, but a party that leads us by the hand, &amp; holds up our hands to conquer these Amalekites, as Aaron &amp; Hut held up the hands of Moses.  The Apostles were like things shut up, that durst not come abroad till they were filled with the Spirit, that had no heart to offer themselves to the trial of any affliction, but kept out of the way: but in God's help, as David says, they leapt over the wall, &amp; ventured forth out of that narrow imprisonment.~~</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="639"><hi rend="underline">Bishop Hacket</hi></persName> (ob: 1670)</p>
         <p><ref xml:id="356">'A Century of Sermons'</ref> p221</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>
