<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[253]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The camp was astir by 5 a.m.  Pipers &amp; bugles &amp; drums making sleep impossible to the laziest.  I did not myself get up, but read in bed until 6.30 a.m., when the servant brought me tea, &amp; the scantiest supply of shaving water.  I was rather startled at the publicity in which one was expected to take one's tub.  The entire battalion seemed to be gathered for the spectacle.  Indeed I flinched to the extent of drawing the bath inside the tent.  Breakfast at 7.30.  At 9 a.m. the Brigadier was to make his inspection.  The Colonel &amp; his staff met him, &amp; went round the camp.  I went also, and, on the way, took several photographs.  Then I visited the Y.M.C.A. tent.  Lunch at 1 p.m. for those who stayed at home; for the others when they returned from their drill.  I went round to see them dine at 3 p.m.  Within a few minutes of returning the rear of the Encampment was alive with naked men performing miracles of ablution with the smallest amount of water.  At 4.45 there was a 'Fire&#8211;Alarm', when everybody in the camp rushed into prominence howsoever apparelled.  Then tea was served outside the tent.</p>
         <p>After dinner I visited the Y.M.C.A. tent where the London Scottish were giving a Concert [sic].  They made me address them, &amp; received what I said very well.  Then I went to <hi rend="bold">[254] </hi>the London Scottish mess &amp; talked to their Col. (Malcolm) &amp; the Brigadier.  Finally I walked with two of our officers to the cliffs &amp; looked with delight at the ravishing spectacle of the moon&#8211;lit tranquil sea.  The view of the great harbour seen from above was very fine.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
