<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[288]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. Copenhagen.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>We got up about 6 a.m., &amp; had tea &amp; coffee on board.  The steamer arrived at Kors&#x00F6;r at 7.30 a.m.: where the train for Copenhagen was waiting.  We arrived in that city about 10 a.m., passed with ease the least suspicious 'customs' in the world, &amp; proceeded to the Hotel Angleterre, where we had engaged a room.  As soon as we had washed &amp;c, we went to Cooks, recovered our letters, &amp; got some money.  Then we lunched in the Hotel.  Next we visited the Thorwaldseu Gallery, which is admirable.  The greatness of that Sculptor is made clear by so amazing a collection of his works, all master&#8211;pieces.  Then we went on to the Glyptothek, where we did but scant justice to a notable collection of sculpture, both ancient &amp; modern.  But we were fatigued by our travels, &amp; our legs refused their office.  So we had tea, &amp; then hired a taxi to drive us about the city.  We enjoyed this drive much, though the air was <hi rend="italic">keen, &amp; we were not adequately clothed.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">I bought yesterday's 'Standard', &amp; learned that 
<persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName> is to be the new Bishop of Oxford.</hi>  <hi rend="italic bold underline">So the wind still blows steadily from the old quarter; &amp; only the S.S. blend goes forward!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[289]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">This vacates a third bishoprick &#8211; Birmingham &#8211; Probably we shall see a Socialist sent there. 
<persName xml:id="421">Russell Wakefield</persName> or 
<persName xml:id="890">Masterman</persName> would suit well enough</hi>.  The last has had connections already with Birmingham.</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
