<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[217]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Statement of Income sent in:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>cf. p. 84</cell>
               <cell>Ecclesiastical Commission</cell>
               <cell>&#x00A3;</cell>
               <cell>1453.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Queen Anne's Bounty</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>14.</cell>
               <cell>6.</cell>
               <cell>8</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>v.p. 255</cell>
               <cell>Easter Offerings</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>30.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Surplice Fees</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>50.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Ch. Ch. Graveyard</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>95.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Value of Rectory</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>233.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Rent of Anker House</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>7.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Payment from S. John's</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>17.</cell>
               <cell>0.</cell>
               <cell>0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell>Wife's Income</cell>
               <cell/>
               <cell>
<hi rend="underline">160.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi rend="underline">0.</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell>
<hi rend="underline">0</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell/>
               <cell/>
               <cell>&#x00A3;</cell>
               <cell>2059.</cell>
               <cell>6.</cell>
               <cell>8</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I married </hi>
<persName xml:id="2199"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Hamar Greenwood</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> M.P. and </hi>
<persName xml:id="2200" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Miss Margerie Spence</hi></persName>. 
<persName xml:id="215">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Asquith</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2198">Sir Wilfrid Laurier</persName> signed the Register.</p>
         <p>Then I attended a meeting of the 
<orgName xml:id="13" display="no">Psycho&#8211;therapeutic Committee</orgName>. We had 
<persName xml:id="2201">Miss Eleanor Reed</persName> before us for examination.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2110">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burke</persName> dined with me, &amp; we discussed the question of publishing the Churchwardens Accounts &amp; Registers of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. It will cost about &#x00A3;600.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[218]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Thursday, May 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1911 (Ascension Day) I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's at 8 a.m. &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 29 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. My wife &amp; I left for Scotland by the express leaving Euston at 10 a.m. It arrived at the Princes Street Station Edinboro precisely to time, 6.15 p.m. We dressed &amp; dined with the High Commissioner at the North British Hotel. A young man politely volunteered to get me my ticket for hat &amp; coat: &amp;, when he gave it me, told me that he had been a student at Harvard when I went there 2 years ago. I took 
<persName xml:id="2246" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fleming</persName> in to dinner. Afterwards I had some talk with 
<persName xml:id="1391">Lord Glenconner</persName>, &amp; also with 
<persName xml:id="1388">his wife</persName>.</p>
         <p>The Moderator, 
<persName xml:id="2491">Principal Stewart</persName> of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's, is prostrated with illness. His place is being taken by 
<persName xml:id="712">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Adam Muir</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName>.</p>
         <p>On Friday, May 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> mine host &amp; I attended the Breakfast of the U.F. Moderator. Afterwards I attended the U.F. General Assembly, where I continued from noon until past 3 p.m. About 2.30 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">I addressed the Assembly which received me with great honour, rising</hi> <hi rend="bold">[219]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="bold underline">when I came forward. I spoke on Unity, &amp; was listened to with almost ravenous attention.</hi>  The Moderator (
<persName xml:id="2492">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wells</persName>) thanked me very nicely. Then 
<persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> &amp; I had tea with 
<persName xml:id="2025">Lord Guthrie</persName>, &amp; after that he lent us his car, &amp; we went for a drive. This was spoiled by a mist which came up from the sea &amp; obscured everything.</p>
         <p>There was a company at dinner including 
<persName xml:id="235">Sir Mark Stewart</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="833">Prof. Cowan</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2390">Ramsay Sibbald(?)</persName> the minister of Braemar. A Berwickshire laird who sate next me said that he &#8211; being an elder in the Church of Scotland &#8211; had communicated in England until four years ago, when his attention was directed to the Rubrick at the end of the Confirmation Service. I assured him that that Rubric did not apply to his case: &amp; bade him resume with a good conscience his practice of Holy Communion in the Ch. of England.</p>
         <p>Then I went to a densely crowded reception in the Art Gallery, where I rejoined my wife.</p>
         <p>On Saturday morning both Ella &amp; I attended the General Assembly of the Established Church. Mine host, 
<persName xml:id="1135">Mitford Mitchell</persName>, introduced a report on the English Presbyterian congregations. He eulogised 
<persName xml:id="566">Fleming</persName>, &amp; sent by him a message to the 
<persName xml:id="166">Bp. of London</persName> in response to one <hi rend="bold">[220]</hi> [symbol] which Fleming had conveyed from the Bishop on the preceding day. He (Mitford Mitchell) hoped the Bishop w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> translate his friendly words into friendly action by requiring his clergy not to repel from Communion those Scottish Presbyterians who desired to receive the Sacrament. 
<persName xml:id="1139">Wallace Williamson</persName> seconded the report, &amp; said that he had been invited by English clergy to communicate on the Continent, &amp; asked how this could be reasonably refused in England which was given abroad. The Moderator called on me to speak, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">I made a short speech. I said that though unofficially present in the Assembly, I was undoubtedly, in a deep &amp; important sense of the words, clothed with a representative character: that the Bps (i.e. the majority of them, for there were exceptions) did not in this matter represent the Church of England</hi>. I endorsed the compl<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> to Fleming, &amp; said that there was another Scottish Church in London &#8211; 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> &#8211; in which Scottish influence had reached in England its high water mark when the Solemn League &amp; Covenant was subscribed in 1645. I spoke of the sympathy between the Churches of England &amp; Scotland growing from the circumstances that they were both established, national, &amp; reformed. While I was speaking I was interrupted by the discharge of cannon for the Royal Birthday, &amp; I commented on the fact. The Moderator humourously [sic] described it as a <hi rend="underline">Cannon&#8211;aid</hi> organised specifically for my behalf. The High <hi rend="bold">[221]</hi> [symbol] Commissioner was present in the Assembly during my speech, but left immediately afterwards.</p>
         <p>I lunched at the 
<orgName xml:id="190">New Club</orgName> with 
<persName xml:id="42">Steel&#8211;Maitland</persName>. Old 
<persName xml:id="235">Sir Mark Stewart</persName> was there, &amp; expressed himself very warmly in appreciation of my speech.</p>
         <p>Then I bought the Times &amp; the Spectator, and read them in the beautiful gardens which intervene between Princes Street &amp; the Castle Hill. There is quite a respectable report of my speech to the U.F. Assembly in the "Times"; &amp; my <ref xml:id="380">letter</ref> in answer to 
<persName xml:id="213">Athelstan Riley</persName> appears in the "Spectator."</p>
         <p>Later in the afternoon I attended the reception of the Moderator's daughter, where also appeared the 
<persName xml:id="2498">Bishop of Bombay</persName>, who is advocating the cause of Eurasian education.<note xml:id="233" n="1"></note>  He stutters very badly.</p>
         <p>In the evening mine host had a dinner party. 
<persName xml:id="1629">Lord</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1680">Lady Haddo</persName>: 
<persName xml:id="2493">Sir Andrew</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2494">Lady Frazer</persName>: 
<persName xml:id="2495" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Frazer</persName>, the widow of the 
<persName xml:id="2496" display="no">late editor</persName> of the "Scotsman": Fleming &amp; his wife: 
<persName xml:id="1759">Prof. Kay</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2497">Prof Rankin</persName>: besides my wife &amp; I.</p>
         <p>I had some very interesting conversation with Sir Andrew Frazer. He spoke of 
<persName xml:id="1018">Curzon</persName> with much appreciation, having been much associated with him in India.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
