<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[309]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, Sunday after Trinity, September 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. Stockholm.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>O for the mighty wakening that aroused</p>
         <p>The old&#8211;time Prophets to their missions high;</p>
         <p>And to blind Homer's inward sunlike eye</p>
         <p>Show'd the heart's universe where he caroused</p>
         <p>Radiantly: the Fishers poor unhoused, </p>
         <p>And sent them forth to preach divinity:</p>
         <p>And made our Milton his great dark defy,</p>
         <p>To the light of one immortal theme espoused!</p>
         <p>But half asleep are those now most awake;</p>
         <p>And save calm&#8211;thoughted Wordsworth, we have none</p>
         <p>Who for eternity put time at stake.</p>
         <p>And hold a constant course as doth the sun:</p>
         <p>We yield but drops that no deep thirstings slake;</p>
         <p>And feebly cease ere we have well begun.</p>
         <p>676. 
<persName xml:id="2454">Thomas Wade</persName>. 1805&#8211;1875.<note xml:id="245" n="1"></note></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The weather has improved.  We start the day with sunshine.  
<persName xml:id="2272" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Owen</persName> &amp; his friend took their leave of us, &amp; went their way by the morning train.  We betook ourselves to the English Church.  There was a numerous congregation mostly of women, perhaps members of the Women's Conference which has been in session here under 
<persName xml:id="2455">Lady Aberdeen</persName>.  The service was spoiled by the clergyman.  His voice was curiously harsh &amp; unpleasant; &amp; he made the worst of it.  His sermon was a painful exhibition of conceited histrionics.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[310]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch we made an expedition to Drottningholm, an island in Lake M&#x00E4;lar, wheron is a palace and a curious lodge, the <hi rend="underline">China Slott</hi>, furnished with all manner of Chinese articles.  The gardens, laid out in the old French style, are charming.  We (i.e. 
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I, 
<persName xml:id="2413">Sir Godfrey</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2414">Lady Thomas</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2415">their son</persName>) had a very comfortable tea, &amp; then returned by the steamer to Stockholm, enjoying on the way an exquisite sunset.</p>
         <p>The 'Times' of Friday announces that 
<persName xml:id="178">Ridgway</persName>, the suffragan&#8211;bishop of Kensington, is to be Bishop of Salisbury.  It is a very astonishing appointment.  The Brothers Ridgway are hardly the kind of men to make Episcopacy considerable.  The new Bishop is described as 'a strong High Churchman'; he will certainly bring to the Bench neither learning, nor distinction: &amp;, of course, he will support in all essential matters the reigning Triumvirate of Sacerdotalists (
<persName xml:id="105">Talbot</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="49">Gore</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName>).  The 
<persName xml:id="215">Prime Minister</persName> has now to appoint to the Deanery of Norwich, &amp; the rich benefice of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Botolph's Bishopgate.  The latter <hi rend="underline">perhaps</hi> carries with it the Suffragan&#8211;bishopric.  Thus a way is opened for an arrangement between the Prime Minister &amp; the 
<persName xml:id="166">Bishop of London</persName>, for the first has the nomination to the benefice which finances the Suffragan&#8211;Bishoprick, &amp; the last has to nominate the Suffragan Bishop.  It would be curious if 
<persName xml:id="166">Ingram</persName> found himself landed with a liberal Suffragan.  Probably there is an opening here for 
<persName xml:id="890">Masterman</persName>, or 
<persName xml:id="898">Peile</persName>.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
