<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[262]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. Bruges.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather continues warm &amp; sunny.  I had a short walk before breakfast.  This meal we took in the hotel at 8 a.m., and then went out to see the city.  Our first object was <hi rend="underline">Notre Dame</hi>, a stately church with a tower &amp; spire 400 feet high, making a conspicuous feature in every prospect of Bruges.  Here we saw the magnificent tombs of Charles the Bold and his daughter Mary, Maximilian's wife.  Also Michael Angelo's tender &amp; beautiful 'Virgin &amp; Child' in the Southern aisle.  The Church is full of pictures, none of pre–eminent worth.  Next, we went to the <hi rend="underline">Hospital of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> John</hi>, which has a rare treasure of Pictures by Memling.  Nothing could exceed the delicacy &amp; charm of his compositions.  Then we visited the <hi rend="underline">Musée Communal</hi>, where several pictures by Jan van Eyck, Memling, &amp; Gerard David drew the homage of our interest &amp; admiration.  Then we went on to the <hi rend="underline">Beguinage</hi> <hi rend="bold">[263] </hi>picturesque &amp; restful, but the church not worth looking at.  We wound up our morning's inspection by visiting the cathedral, <hi rend="underline">Sint Salvator</hi> (S. Sauveur), an imposing church with five aisles, some 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century windows in one of the eastern chapels, excellent 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century choir stalls &amp; above them the arms of the Knights of the Golden Fleece including Edward IV of England, many notable pictures of the earliest period of Flemish art, and a Churchwardens' Vestry full of curious antiques.  We returned to the Hotel &amp; lunched.  Then we rested awhile.  Our next move was a drive for an hour in &amp; about the city.  It is full of surprising vistas, but the canals, though certainly adding much to its beauty, are unsavoury, &amp;, I should suppose, also unhealthy.  On our way we took several photographs, &amp; stopped to see divers objects of interest, e.g. the <hi rend="underline">Église de Jerusalem</hi>, very curious &amp; shown by a quaint old dame, the <hi rend="underline">Chapelle du Sant Sang</hi>, a two–storied church, filled with modern glass &amp; curiosities, &amp; the <hi rend="underline">Hotel de Ville</hi>, fine but gaudily restored.  Then we had tea in the Grand Place, to the accompaniment of chimes from the great <hi rend="underline">Belfry</hi>.  This is a dominating factor in every view of the City, and makes the day musical from morning till nightfall.  This completed our afternoon expedition, &amp; we returned to the Hotel.</p>
</body></text></TEI>