<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi> <hi rend="bold">Sunday in Lent, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I travelled to Brighton by a slow train which left Victoria at 8.50 a.m. &amp; arrived at 10.52 a.m.  The Churchwarden of Holy Trinity met me on the platform, &amp; motored me to the Church.  I preached to a very attentive congregation, repeating the sermon preached in the Abbey on Laodicean 'Lukewarmness.'  I returned to town by a rapid train crowded with week&#8211;enders.</p>
         <p>The rain fell heavily at church&#8211;time; nevertheless 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> was fairly well filled at Evensong.  I preached on "Jacob's Dream".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Friday, March 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1911, I dined with the 
<orgName xml:id="203">Institution of Civil Engineers;</orgName> &amp; through not feeling well I did not enjoy the dinner, I found pleasure in the conversation of 
<persName xml:id="1862">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bonney</persName>, who sate next me.  On my return home about 10 p.m. I read for two hours, &amp; then went to bed: but about 2 a.m. felt very ill, and when I had risen fell suddenly in a faint.  Then I was violently sick &amp; showed all the signs of a chill on the liver; after the fashion which but too often has laid me low.  On Saturday I was miserable: &amp; on Sunday had to remain in bed.  
<persName xml:id="216">Gow</persName> very kindly preached &amp; celebrated for me at Mattins: &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName> preached at Evensong.</p>
         <p>The next day the 'Times' had a <ref xml:id="413" display="no">notice</ref> of my 'sudden illness'; which I regretted, but could not resent.  I solaced myself by reading the new volumes of 
<persName xml:id="1126">Frazer's</persName> <ref xml:id="414">3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>. Edition of the Golden Bough.</ref></p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[176]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The 
<orgName xml:id="13" display="no">Psycho&#8211;therapic C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi></orgName> was attended by the 
<persName xml:id="2525">Rev: Francis Boyd</persName>, Warden of the 
<orgName xml:id="204">Guild of Health:</orgName> and we spent two hours in trying to make out his position.  He was an agreeable man to deal with, good tempered &amp; well&#8211;mannered, but an utter fanatick.  He did not seem able to grasp either the force of his own language, or the logical sequence of reasoning.  He disclaimed 
<persName xml:id="2248" display="no">Hickson</persName> with energy.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
