<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[255]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went with the 
<persName xml:id="2571" display="no">Quartermaster</persName> to see the breakfast distributed to the men.  The food is set out in portions for the companies, from whom detachments are told off to fetch it to the tent of feeding.</p>
         <p>Next, I interviewed the 
<persName xml:id="2572" display="no">Band&#8211;master</persName>, who is responsible for the hymns on Sunday.  He made a long face when he saw the number of the hymns.</p>
         <p>Then I went to the artillery, &amp; saw the provender issued for the 700 horses we have in camp.  The guns make a fine show, as they are taken out for manoeuvres.</p>
         <p>I walked down to Dover, &amp; bought a warm vest, and a towel: also a bottle of ink.  There I lunched, &amp; read the 'Times', returning to camp about 2.30 p.m.  The carriage cost no less than 5/. for bringing me up the hill.  It is a steep pull, but that price is excessive.</p>
         <p>The division in the H. of L. last night resulted in a government majority of 17 &#8211; 131 to 114.<note xml:id="109" n="1"></note>  
<persName xml:id="128">The two Abps.</persName>
<persName xml:id="130"></persName> and 11 bps. voted in the majority: 2 bps. &#8211; 
<persName xml:id="2047">Worcester</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2573">Bangor</persName> &#8211; voted with 
<persName xml:id="703">L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Halsbury</persName>.<note xml:id="243" n="2"></note> Meanwhile the strike continues &amp; extends, menacing London with actual hunger. This blending of the political crisis with the economical is full of ill omen.<note xml:id="110" n="3"></note></p>
         <p>I wrote to 
<persName xml:id="1204">Mary Scott</persName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[256]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">
<persName xml:id="2574">Colonel Malcolm</persName> of the 
<orgName xml:id="209">London Scottish</orgName> told me that he had recently visited Rangoon.  There he had seen an old &amp; skilful elephant who walked on three legs, pushing a great teak log with the fourth.  He noticed that the huge creature's head was bandaged, &amp; kept cool with water.  On his inquiring what the reason of this might be, he was assured that these elephants are very sensitive to the heat, &amp; do not work when the sun is fierce.</hi>  On the occasion of the King's visit (as Prince of Wales) to Rangoon, he was shown these working elephants about 1 p.m.: &amp; no less than 4 were believed to have died on account of the exposure.</p>
         <p>After dinner I went out to see a signalling competition.  The two points by which merit is determined are accuracy &amp; promptitude.  A message is flashed, received, transcribed, &amp; forwarded.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
