<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[237]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~"It is indeed one of the miracles of Christianity, that by reconciling man to God, it restores him to his own good opinion: that it makes him able to bear the sight of himself: &amp; in some cases renders solitude &amp; silence more agreeable than all the intercourse and action of mankind."~~</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2148"><hi rend="doubleunderline">Pascal</hi></persName> l.c. p. 205</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. and preached at 11 a.m. and at 7 p.m.</p>
         <p>The 
<persName xml:id="325">Dean</persName> celebrated at 12.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="630">Bob Bineham</persName> and 
<persName xml:id="554">Gilbert Simpson</persName> came in to supper.  I wrote letters to 
<persName xml:id="2149" display="no">Walter White</persName> and others.</p>
         <p>My text at Evensong was the Logion &#x3B3;&#x3B9;&#x3BD;&#x3B5;&#x3C3;&#x3B8;&#x3B5; &#x3C4;var&#x3C3;&#x3B1;&#x3C0;&#x3B5;var&#x3C3;&#x3B9;&#x3C0;aplhagreek&#x3B9; &#x3B4;&#x3BF;&#x3BA;&#x3B9;&#x3BC;&#x3BF;&#x3B9; which I rendered "Become trusted money&#8211;changers".</p>
         <p>The congregations were fairly large, but they seemed in great part made up of tourists. The Parliamentary seats were distressingly empty.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[238]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>On Monday, July 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1911, I travelled to Mundesly on Sea, and preached to the members of 
<persName xml:id="1543">Campbell Morgan's</persName> 
<orgName xml:id="206">'Bible Conference'</orgName>.  They were gathered in a large tent, in which no less than 900 chairs had been placed.  All these were occupied, &amp; besides there were not a few standing.  There were a considerable number of ministers present, including several Church of England clergymen.  Of these, 
<persName xml:id="2548">Canon Girdlestone</persName>, an aged but vigorous man, had some speech with me.  I preached on the words: "I see that all things come to an end: but Thy Commandment is exceeding broad".</p>
         <p>On Tuesday, July 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I returned to town by the early train, breakfasted on the train, &amp; got into 
<placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> before noon.  <hi rend="bold underline">Thus I was in good time for 
<persName xml:id="1536">Lord Anson's</persName> marriage, at which I assisted.  
<persName xml:id="114">Welldon</persName> performed the principal part, &amp; gave the address</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  
<persName xml:id="2110">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burke</persName> had an interview with me respecting the <ref xml:id="416">projected publication</ref> of the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's registers &amp; Churchwardens' Accounts.  The latter are more voluminous that we supposed.  It seems too costly to publish them beyond the end of Elizabeth's reign.  That is from 1460 to 1603.  The registers we shall carry from 1538 to 1660.  If these are tolerably edited, they will form an important contribution to historical science.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[239]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday July 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, I attended the wedding of 
<persName xml:id="2379">Major Guest</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="3418">Miss Lyttelton</persName>.  Then 
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I walked to Lambeth where a crowded Garden Party was in progress.  I had some conversation with the old 
<persName xml:id="3414">Abp. of the West Indies</persName>, who is a wiser man than most of his brethren.  On returning to Dean's Yard I found 
<persName xml:id="771">Sir R. Mowbray</persName>, &amp; a young American, named 
<persName xml:id="3417" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> James Charles Craft</persName>, desiring to be taken into the Abbey.  After satisfying them, I found 
<persName xml:id="1259">Reggie Still</persName>, who turned up to attend the 
<orgName xml:id="103">Guild</orgName>.  This I had totally forgotten.  However I made shift to talk from the notes I had prepared for my Etonian sermon.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Friday </hi>
<persName xml:id="2161"><hi rend="bold underline">Ruth Spooner</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> dined here, &amp; talked about music with 
<persName xml:id="600">Ernest</persName></hi>: also 
<persName xml:id="695" display="no">Herbert Gritten</persName>, who is making a short stay in England.  He had much talk with me about his experiences since he left the 
<orgName xml:id="32">Choir School</orgName>.</p>
         <p>On Saturday afternoon (July 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>) we went to Eton to spend the week&#8211;end with the 
<persName xml:id="3415">Provost</persName>.  The Provost of King's (
<persName xml:id="3416">Montague James</persName>) dined, &amp; was very civil &amp; interesting.  The portraits of Etonians which adorn the Provost's house are wonderful, &amp; must be priceless.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
