<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[298]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. Stockholm.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">An immense grunting female marshalled me through miles of corridor to a rather dilapidated bath&#8211;room, where &#8211; at a cost of 1 kr. 50 or. &#8211; I restored myself to a measure of self&#8211;respect</hi>.  Before breakfast I expended 40 or. in getting shaved.  The operation was performed swiftly, effectively, &amp; (a welcome novelty) <hi rend="underline">quietly</hi>.  Even the professional loquacity of a Swedish barber stood dumb before the natural fortress of Language.  After breakfast we walked out into the City, which looked ravishingly beautiful in the sunshine, &amp; reflecting in its water the bluest of blue skies.  We visited the Riddarhus, the Royal Palace, the Storkyrka, &amp; the Riddarsholm Kyrka where lie the remains of Gustavus Adolphus, Charles XII, &amp; Bernadotte.  The historic interest of the Royal tombs gives an artificial importance to a small &amp; much mutilated Gothick church.  The Storkyrka is a brick church built or rather re&#8211;built in the Gothick style during the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century.  It has a fine 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century altar piece in silver, ivory, &amp; ebony: &amp; a seven&#8211;branched brass candelabrum of the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century.  The public statues of Stockholm are good, &amp; well&#8211;shown.  From the palace windows one gains the noblest views of the city.  We returned to the hotel for lunch, &amp; were pleased to find our luggage from Copenhagen in our room.  It had been fetched by the porter &amp; carried through the custom&#8211;house <hi rend="bold">[299] </hi>without difficulty.</p>
         <p>After lunch I wrote several letters, which required to be sent in answer to several forwarded from England viz:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>To 
<persName xml:id="429"><hi rend="underline">Manning</hi></persName>, consenting to add my signature to a manifesto to be put forward by the <ref xml:id="408" display="no">'Churchmen's Union'</ref>.</item>
            <item>To 
<persName xml:id="2367" display="no"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Thomas</hi></persName>, refusing permission to a Nonconformist minister to 'assist' at a wedding in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's.</item>
            <item>To 
<persName xml:id="2368"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Algernon Villiers</hi></persName> permitting his marriage in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, with 
<persName xml:id="2369">Miss Paul</persName>.</item>
            <item>To 
<persName xml:id="2370" display="no"><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Walker</hi></persName>, Sec: of the London &amp; Middlesex Archaeological Society granting permission for the said society to view S. Marg<hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi> on Sept. 28<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> at 4 p.m.</item>
         </list>
         <p>Then we left cards on 
<persName xml:id="1579">Sir Cecil Spring Rice</persName> at the British Legation, &amp; on 
<persName xml:id="718">Lady Kilmarnock</persName> at her residence.  We next went on to the Skansen, &amp; viewed the collection of Swedish birds &amp; beasts.  The owls, eagles, &amp; brown bears are excellent: the rest disappointing.  There was but one polar bear.  The elk looked mean &amp; dilapidated, &amp; they no longer possessed a pool in which to drink their fill.  An American bear with two cubs obligingly gave them suck &#8211; a curiously humane function.  Our return to the Hotel was delayed by a protracted but fruitless effort to purchase some methylated spirit for the nourishment of the small lamp which boils the water for our early tea!  Finally we had to appeal to the h&#x00F4;tel porter!</p>
         <p>
</body></text></TEI>
