<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[294]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. On the Steamboat from Gothenberg to Stockholm.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I did not succeed in sleeping: &amp; I <hi rend="underline">was</hi> conscious of the ship's motion; but the night went through without disaster and the day broke beautifully.  This bright promise was not adequately maintained.  As we had another series of 8 locks to traverse, the captain suggested a morning walk.  The young man and I issued forth accordingly, &amp; were soon overtaken by the Dutchman.  About 8 a.m. we had some tea.  Then we walked again through more locks, &amp; then had breakfast, a substantial meal.  I had some conversation with the Dutchman.  He says his brother has become a Roman Catholic after boxing the compass of sectarianism.  He is an individualist himself &amp; perceives the natural affinity which draws Sacerdotalists into alliance with Socialists.  I inquired of the present state of the Dutch church.  He replied that it had suffered in credit &amp; influence through political activity.  Allying itself with the Roman Catholics against the Liberals, it was becoming corruptly organized.  He was very convinced that our "Die&#8211;Hard" Peers were the true patriots: but I told him 'twas a sound rule in judging English politics to take account of the individuals concerned.  In this case of the "Die&#8211;Hards" there was a striking poverty of ability, character, &amp; experience.  Then I conversed on deck with the Oxford Don on critical &amp; ecclesiastical questions.  The wind rose, &amp; our enjoyment waned proportionately.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[295]</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Enough, if something from our hands have power</p>
         <p>To live, and act, and serve the future hour;</p>
         <p>And if, as toward the silent tomb we go,</p>
         <p>Through love, through hope, &amp; faith's transcendent dower,</p>
         <p>We feel that we are greater than we know.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2271" display="no">Wordsworth</persName>. 538.</p>
         </div>
         <p>My mind begins to turn more constantly towards Westminster, &amp; the ordering of my life there.  For it is becoming plain to me that there I must probably remain.  The problem of duty is curiously hard to solve.  At this moment I am pledged to two pieces of extra work.  (1) The volume, <ref xml:id="83">"<hi rend="underline">The Creed in the Pulpit</hi>"</ref> for Hodder &amp; Stoughton: &amp; (2) The Essay on the <ref xml:id="385"><hi rend="underline">H. of C. &amp; S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> Margaret's</hi></ref> wh. I have undertaken as my share of the editing of the Registers &amp;c.  Then there are several matters, which could be more effectively handled, if I could but concentre my mind on them.  (1) Something could be done with my 
<orgName xml:id="92">Territorials</orgName>.  (2) The 
<orgName xml:id="169" display="no">Shakespearians</orgName> might be more thoroughly ordered.  (3) The 
<orgName xml:id="103">Communicants' Guild</orgName> might be more adequately worked.  <hi rend="bold underline">Preaching must be the principal business of my life: and I must arrange for a list of Abbey preachers during January.  It is a programme more familiar than attractive</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  However there is nothing else for me to do at present.</p>
         <p>Lake Vetten was amiable, though just disturbed enough to show us that had he been really vicious we should have had an ill time.  The journey then lay for a long way through pretty canals.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[296]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After supper I had a great discussion with the Dutchman mainly, the Oxford Don (his name is 
<persName xml:id="2272" display="no">Owen</persName> of Keble) &amp; the other passenger intervening.  The 'bear' was a silent but attentive listener.  We started with so small a matter as the adoption by Great Britain of the decimal system: &amp; then moved by rapid strides into the great issues of Religion.  Nearly 30 years ago I remember when I attended 
<persName xml:id="395">Liddon's</persName> Greek Testament lecture[s] in Ch. Ch. Hall on Sunday evenings that he said 'twas a notable proof of the truth &amp; gravity of Religion that in any discussion between men it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> surely happen that sooner or later the matter w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> run into religion.  So it happened with us.  The Dutchman is well&#8211;read, but too much governed by those large &amp; raking generalisations which have so great a fascination for the continental mind.  I gather that his father was a Calvinist pastor; &amp; that he has reacted with some vehemence from the Calvinistic teaching.  Some things I said seemed to impress him.  His main difficulty seems to be the apparent impossibility of reconciling the notion of a final revelation of truth in the Past with the notion of truth as a progressively realized apprehension, into which the slowly accumulating experience &amp; knowledge of mankind are gathered.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
