<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[334]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911. Brussels.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>I strove with none, for none was worth my strife.</p>
         <p>Nature I loved and, next to Nature, Art,</p>
         <p>I warm'd both hands before the fire of life;</p>
         <p>It sinks, and I am ready to depart.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2202">Walter Savage Landor</persName>. 576.<note xml:id="227" n="1"></note></p>
         </div>
         <p>We were duly called by the porter at 6 a.m.: but I had been already a long time awake, pondering the past &amp; vainly essaying to forecast the future.  The morning was dull, with rain falling intermittently from a heavy sky.  Gusts of winded [sic] added fretfulness to gloom, and moved fears in us as to the condition of the English Channel.  Our packing was now a facile &amp; familiar thing, so that we were ready for the omnibus at 10 minutes before 8 o'clock.  Our last francs were dispersed in the costly &amp; thankless process of farewell, and we vanished from Brussels.</p>
         <p>We found the sea disturbed, &amp; the steamer crowded.  The 
<persName xml:id="2206">Lord Mayor</persName> &amp; his party were on board, returning from their visit to Vienna.  His Lordship was in high spirits, &amp; talked much, assisting perhaps by his conversation to avert the 'mal de mer', which rather to my own surprise I escaped.  
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was not so fortunate.  She retired below, &amp; suffered in obscurity.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[335]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On arriving in my house I found a pencilled note from 
<persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> conveying two pieces of intelligence &#8211; that the 
<persName xml:id="296">Sub&#8211;dean</persName> died suddenly this morning, and that he himself had just accepted the Deanery of Norwich. Thus both my friends are removed at a stroke; &amp; I am left in more complete loneliness than ever</hi>.</p>
         <p>On Saturday the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Sept: 1911, 
<persName xml:id="296">Duckworth</persName> was buried (i.e. the ashes brought from Golder's Green) in the Abbey near his stall.  There was a numerous assembly of mourners, and, I think, very sincere regret at his loss.  Yet who would not covet a departure so swift &amp; easy?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Swedish Professor </hi>
<persName xml:id="2166"><hi rend="bold underline">S&#x00F6;derbl&#x00F6;m</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> from Upsala and </hi>
<persName xml:id="2203"><hi rend="bold underline">his wife</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, dined here.  So did </hi>
<persName xml:id="208"><hi rend="bold underline">Beeching</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> &amp; </hi>
<persName xml:id="241"><hi rend="bold underline">Sir F. Bridge</hi></persName>.  I was much interested in the Professor's account of the Reunion negociations between the English &amp; Swedish Churches.  He appears to have been the leading spirit on the Swedish side.  I was at once surprised &amp; interested to find that he welcomed my Scottish Lecture as likely to advance the cause in Sweden, by calming the fears of those who suspected in these flirtations with England the thin edge of the Sacerdotalist peril.  I half promised to give some Lectures at Upsala.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
