<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[348]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A fine cold morning with some disposition to be foggy.  I celebrated at 8 a.m.  There were 18 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2054" display="no">Wilson</persName> preached at 11 a.m. in the interest of the 
<orgName xml:id="17" display="no">Seamen's Mission</orgName>, &amp; afterwards lunched with us.</p>
         <p>Gilbert &amp; Reggie accompanied me to Anerley, where I addressed an assembly of men on "Church Unity" in the Congregational Church.  There were a good many questions, which seemed to indicate rather a bitter spirit.  <hi rend="italic">The minister, 
<persName xml:id="2588">Wallace</persName>, spoke afterwards with some freedom on the subject of the recent public reconciliation between 
<persName xml:id="1520">Forsyth</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="392">Campbell</persName>. He described as a carefully engineered piece of acting. Indeed the impression he left on my mind was a painful one. Congregationalism must be in a bad way.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's</orgName> at Evensong in spite of the rain.  I <ref xml:id="641">preached</ref> from S. Luke xx.2.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[349]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On All Souls Day, Nov: 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1911, I did fully intend to go up for the College Gaudy.<note xml:id="35" n="1"></note>  But there was a strike of taxi&#8211;cab drivers, &amp; vehicles were difficult to obtain.  This was the more inconvenient since it came on to rain heavily.  
<persName xml:id="112">My wife</persName> drove me some way on the road to Paddington, &amp; then dropped me to take another cab &amp; therein to proceed to the station.  But I could not get a cab: &amp; the omnibuses were all thronged.  Time passed, &amp; I despaired of getting to the station in time for the train.  So I sent a telegram to the 
<persName xml:id="228">Warden</persName> excusing my absence, &amp; returned home.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
