<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[356]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1911.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended the celebration of Holy Communion in Henry VII<hi rend="superscript underline">th's</hi> Chapel.  
<persName xml:id="130">Lang</persName> was the celebrant, &amp; from his hands I received the Sacrament.  There was a very small attendance of the members of the 
<orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I travelled to Manchester by the 10.30 a.m. express from Euston. A young minister met me on the platform, &amp; conducted me to the 
<placeName xml:id="50" display="no">Free Trade Hall</placeName>, where the 
<orgName xml:id="210">Manchester &amp; Salford Wesleyan Mission</orgName> were holding their annual demonstration.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A young lady, 
<persName xml:id="2112" display="no">Miss Hilda Rank</persName>, was in the chair.  I spoke for 25 minutes, &amp; was very well received by an audience of some 3000 people.  
<persName xml:id="2113">D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Saleeby</persName>, whom I listened to yesterday in the 
<placeName xml:id="10">Jerusalem Chamber</placeName>, was another speaker.  We travelled back to town together, &amp; I found him a very interesting companion: though I should judge him somewhat disposed to be a Fanatick on the questions which he makes his own.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[357]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Wednesday, Nov: 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1911, I attended the Meeting of the Representative Church Council, and I was bored to death by a prosy 'debate' ('twas a succession of disconnected &amp; insufferable monologues by our too well&#8211;known self&#8211;puffers) on Church Finance.</p>
         <p>At 12.30 I 'dedicated' the window in the Tower&#8211;porch, which the widow &amp; family of 
<persName xml:id="195">Sir George Bartley</persName> have set up to his memory.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I returned to the Council, &amp; made a foolish speech about giving the suffrage to Women who were communicants of full age.</p>
         <p>On Thursday, the 23<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, I attended the 
<orgName xml:id="85">Letters of Business C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi></orgName> at 10 a.m.: &amp; the Council at 11 a.m.  We spent the morning in talking over another of these vague, useless resolutions about better relations with Nonconformists. 
<persName xml:id="1748">Halifax</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="213">Riley</persName> cooed softly like turtle&#8211;doves: &amp; I walked out <hi rend="underline">clatteringly</hi> before the vote was taken.</p>
         <p>In the evening I wrote another letter to the 'Times' on Welsh Disestablishment, answering a letter of 
<persName xml:id="321">Carlyle</persName>.<note xml:id="238" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, my <ref xml:id="387">letter</ref> appeared, together with <ref xml:id="388">another</ref> from 
<persName xml:id="2099">Arthur Benson</persName>.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
