<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[426]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Twenty five years ago I was ordained on this Festival in the parish church of Cuddesdon.  Almost everybody has died, &amp; almost everything has changed.  In that long time &#8211; half a </hi><hi rend="italic underline">long</hi><hi rend="italic"> working life &#8211; what have I done?  The mountains of M.S. sermons represent almost all: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">they</hi><hi rend="italic"> disgust me so much that I can hardly hold myself back from burning the lot.  Yet what remains to me but to increase the rubbish heap till the end comes?  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Not one bishop who was on the Bench in 1887 is now included in the Diocesan Episcopate</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  All are dead.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I myself am least changed of all the men I know</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  Puzzled &amp; unhappy I was a quarter of a century ago: today I am only more puzzled &amp; more unhappy. And there mingles with the perplexity &amp; unhappiness elements of remorse &amp; self&#8211;distrust, which were hardly present then. For I have failed greatly, personally &amp; publicly: and I can no longer alleviate my humiliation by the hope of recovering myself, &amp; retrieving my position. At 49 one has no illusions left: &amp; not even the vanity of a Fool can pretend not to see the whole extent of one's possibilities. The air is heavy &amp; depressing: and it rains continuously.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[427]</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Ashamed I come, yet worshipping that love</p>
         <p>Which first enkindled hope within my heart,</p>
         <p>Which lifted my unhallowed thoughts above,</p>
         <p>And taught me from my low desires to part.</p>
         <p>Thou, Suffering One, didst breathe forgiveness still,</p>
         <p>And bid me cry to heaven, &amp; never cease,</p>
         <p>Till boundless mercy should my wish fulfil,</p>
         <p>And dull despair make way for radiant peace.</p>
         <p>Beloved of my soul, for nought I ask</p>
         <p>But grace to love my Saviour and my Friend,</p>
         <p>To bow, rejoicing, to the humblest task,</p>
         <p>And to my Father's Will my spirit bend.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1869" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">James Drummond</hi></persName>. <ref xml:id="361">'<hi rend="bold underline">Johannine Thoughts</hi>'</ref> p.74</p>
         </div>
         <p>At 8 a.m. 
<persName xml:id="800"><hi rend="bold underline">Westlake</hi></persName> celebrated.  There were but 16 communicants.  After service I walked round to Downing Street, and left a note on 
<persName xml:id="246"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Asquith</hi></persName> as to 
<persName xml:id="231">Elizabeth's</persName> Confirmation.</p>
         <p>The rain diminished the congregation at Mattins.  I preached on <ref xml:id="613">'Isaiah's Vision'</ref>, and afterwards celebrated the Holy Communion.  There were 62 communicants.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1077">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Glassford Bell</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1580" display="no">Miss Bovey</persName>, another young lady, &amp; Gilbert were guests at lunch.  Afterwards Gilbert read <ref xml:id="362" display="no">'Romany Rye'</ref> to me for 3/4 an hour.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[428]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Church Parade of 
<orgName xml:id="92">Territorials</orgName> at 4 p.m. was favoured by bright weather, for the rain ceased about noon, &amp; the afternoon was fine.  I preached from S. James ii.12 '<hi rend="underline">So speak ye, &amp; so do: as men who are to be judged by a law of liberty</hi>'. The National Anthem at the close was sung with notable fervour.</p>
         <p>About a dozen of the choirboys came to tea pleading that there was no time for them to get home before Evensong.</p>
         <p>There was a large congregation at Evensong, when I preached for the third time, taking for my text the words, "<hi rend="underline">I could not see for the glory of that light</hi>", which formed the text of the first sermon I preached after my Ordination.  It was preached in S. Paul's, Oxford, on June 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1887.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1204">Mary</persName> &amp; 
<persName xml:id="1256">her sister</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName>, the 
<persName xml:id="122">Precentor</persName>, Gilbert, &amp; Reggie came in to supper, &amp; were all very chattersome &amp; gay: &amp; with their talk &amp; laughter I brought to a close an anniversary, which never fails to sadden &amp; in some sense terrify me.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[429]</hi>
         </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Monday, June 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1912, I dined for the first time with the </hi>
<orgName xml:id="107"><hi rend="bold underline">Literary Society</hi></orgName>.  The company numbered no less than 18.  
<persName xml:id="2085">Sir Sidney Colvin</persName>, the President, was there, &amp; I sat beside him as a new member.  On my other side was 
<persName xml:id="2096">Sir Matthew Nathan</persName>, also a new member.  Among those whom I identified were 
<persName xml:id="1458">Arthur Elliot</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2102">Briton Rivi&#x00E8;re</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="348">John Murray</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2103">Prof: Darwin</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2100">Norman Moore</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="984">John Buchan</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="653">Valentine Chirol</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2107">Fisher</persName>, &amp; 
<persName xml:id="2106">Admiral Custance</persName>.  It was a very agreeable evening.  On Tuesday afternoon, the 
<orgName xml:id="85">Letters of Business Committee</orgName> met, &amp; sate until midday on Thursday.  
<persName xml:id="301"><hi rend="bold underline">Burrows</hi></persName> <hi rend="bold underline">appeared, and we gave him an Ordinal, in which we all wrote our names. The Bishop&#8211;designate of Truro is plainly much pleased with his escape from Birmingham</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>To my surprise I received a cheque for &#x00A3;<hi rend="underline">26.5.0</hi> as a present from the executors of 
<persName xml:id="2104">Sir Julius Wernher</persName>, in recognition of my services in the Memorial Service in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Saturday, the 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> June, I married 
<persName xml:id="2105" display="no">Colonel Browne</persName> in S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Margaret's.  His first marriage had been annulled ten years ago.  It was an odd case, not easy to decide, but the course I took seemed to me most equitable in the circumstances</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
