<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[407]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I travelled to Manchester by the train leaving S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Pancras at 10.5 a.m.  It arrived at 3.40 p.m. having made several stoppages to meet other trains.  The Strike has compelled many re&#8211;arrangements perplexing to the traveller.  I preached in the Congregational Church House to a considerable congregation, mainly men of the city&#8211;type.  The train left at 5.50 p.m. &amp; was grossly overcrowded as far as Derby.  <hi rend="bold underline">Everybody talking excitedly about the Coal Strike</hi>. However we reached S. Pancras in good time, about 10.5 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[408]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I finished my last Puritan lecture with much difficulty, and with no satisfaction to myself, for I seemed to miss saying just what I designed mainly to say!  I delivered the poor thing on Friday afternoon to a congregation which was certainly the largest I have had at these lectures. The attention of the public was just beginning to be aroused.</p>
         <p>The inspector from Scotland Yard called to tell me that the Bow Street magistrate had sentenced 
<persName xml:id="2616" display="no">Ward</persName> to three months imprisonment.  The sentence is severe, but perhaps not too severe: for truly, I think the man has been stealing for a long while past.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2128"><hi rend="bold underline">Olaf Car&#x00F6;e</hi></persName> came to see me, &amp; we had quite a long talk together over 
<persName xml:id="2238">Thompson's</persName> position. <hi rend="bold underline">He confesses to a secret inclination to take Orders</hi>.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
