<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[412]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Easter Monday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received four five&#8211;pound notes from 
<persName xml:id="2618">Miss L. B. Cochrane</persName> with a note emphasizing the anonymity of the gift, &amp; stating that it was 'for the poor &amp; needy at your own discretion'.  I wrote cheques to distribute it: &#x00A3;10 to 
<persName xml:id="1792">J. W. Eisdell</persName> for distribution in Barking: &#x00A3;5 to 
<persName xml:id="2056">Miss Graham</persName>: &amp; &#x00A3;5 to 
<persName xml:id="156">M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fedarb</persName> to be added to yesterday's collections for the 
<orgName xml:id="172" display="no">Strike Victims' Relief Fund</orgName>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[413]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">On Saturday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> 1912 we travelled to Norwich where we stayed with 
<persName xml:id="208">Beeching</persName> at the Deanery</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  I preached in the Cathedral on Sunday evening.  The nave was crowded.  On Monday, the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April, we visited the Castle &amp; some of the churches of the City.  The next day, Tuesday, the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April, <hi rend="bold underline">we journeyed to Aldeborough to visit the 
<persName xml:id="1494">Sinclairs</persName></hi>.  We made a stay of 4 hours at Ipswich, visiting several churches &amp; driving about the town.  <hi rend="bold underline">On Wednesday we saw the eclipse of the sun very conveniently</hi>
<hi rend="bold">.</hi>  It was astonishing to observe that, as the sun's light failed, the tulips closed, &amp; the birds sang their evensong.  In the afternoon we motored to Framlingham, where we viewed the ruins of the castle, &amp; the remarkable tombs in the parish church.  Then we proceeded to Dennington, where we had tea with 
<persName xml:id="2059"><hi rend="bold underline">Eric Farrar</hi></persName>.  The parish church is extraordinarily interesting.  There is some early painted glass, some wonderfully carved 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century benches, a carved pyx cover of the same date, wonderful chantry screens, some medieval chests, &amp; a priest's chamber.  Also a tomb&#8211;stone with the inscription</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Too bad for heaven: too good for hell.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Where he is gone, I cannot tell.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We returned to Westminster on Friday the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> April.</p>
         
            
</body></text></TEI>
