<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[403]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A chilly depressing day settling down to a quiet soaking rain.  At 8 a.m. I celebrated in 
<orgName xml:id="16">S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's</orgName>.  There were 28 communicants.</p>
         <p>The Church was well&#8211;filled at Mattins.  We used the special Psalms &amp; Lessons put forth by the 
<persName xml:id="128">Archbishops</persName>
<persName xml:id="130"></persName>.  I preached from "He is our Peace", making no direct allusions to the Strike.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">
<persName xml:id="2010">Compston</persName></hi> celebrated afterwards.  There were 39 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.  At 4 p.m. was the Church Parade of my 
<orgName xml:id="70">Territorials</orgName>.  In spite of the execrable weather there was a fair muster.  I preached from the words of Mordecai to Esther: "<hi rend="bold underline">Who knowest whether thou hast come to the kingdom for such a time as this?</hi>"  My theme was the crisis &amp; the duties it suggested.  The National Anthem was sung with extraordinary fervour.</p>
         <p>I preached (for the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> time) at Evensong.  Though the evening was wet, the Church was full.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[404]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Monday 
<persName xml:id="344">Craik</persName> came to see me with one of the Scotland Yard Inspectors: &amp;, after some discussion, I consented that a watch should be set on 
<persName xml:id="2616" display="no">Ward</persName>, &amp;, if he were caught in the act of stealing from the Offertory, he should be given in charge.  Accordingly, the Inspector &amp; 
<persName xml:id="800">Westlake</persName> arranged a trap by marking coins, &amp; placing them in the plate after the Wednesday Lecture.  The result was decisive.  <hi rend="bold underline">Ward was caught infalgrante delicto</hi>: &amp; was forthwith given in charge.  This is a lamentable business.</p>
         <p>There was a large attendance at my lecture on Friday afternoon, perhaps due to the slightly improved weather, but possibly also in some small degree to a growing interest in the subject.  Some evidence of the latter was given in the evening when I dined in Lincoln's Inn Hall with the 
<orgName xml:id="203">Civil Engineers</orgName>.  
<persName xml:id="2617"><hi rend="bold underline">Sir W</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">m</hi>
<hi rend="bold underline"> White</hi></persName> spoke to me about the lectures, the brief reports of which in the "Times" he had plainly read with attention.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
