<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[458]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~"As we desire to be accepted of God, to receive comfort to our souls by the things we do, and thereby to do good to others, let us be well&#8211;informed in the duties that by virtue of own proper function belong unto us, &amp; therein be faithful &amp; diligent.  Much pains may be taken, &amp; diligence used in other men's matters, &amp; little thanks gotten for all that pains &amp; diligence.  Yea, we may bring by such pains &amp; diligence much trouble to ourselves, &amp; yet no comfort in all that trouble.  Wherefore S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter exhorteth Christians from suffering '<hi rend="underline">as busy&#8211;bodies in other men's matters</hi>'.  And it is remarkable, that he reckoneth their sufferings among the sufferings of malefactors. '<hi rend="underline">Study therefore to do your own business</hi>'.  Let magistrates, let minsters, let husbands, let wives, let all sorts so do."~~</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1577">Gouge</persName>. <ref xml:id="338">'God's Three Arrows'</ref> p. 40.</p>
         <p>[A.D. 1631.]</p>
         </div>
         <p>This sober counsel of the excellent Puritan may seem to rebuke the venture on which I proceed today &#8211; <hi rend="bold underline">preaching 'with the gloves off' about the Putumayo atrocities</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>  <note xml:id="150" n="1"></note> But I suppose, there may be exceptions even to the rule of <hi rend="bold">[459]</hi> [symbol] pastoral duty.  And is it not fairly maintained that this is one?</p>
         <p>There was a very large congregation at Mattins.  <hi rend="bold underline">My sermon on the Putumayo Blue&#8211;book took over 45 minutes to deliver, and was listened to with close attention</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  I celebrated the Holy Communion.  There 118 communicants including the Swedish Professor, 
<persName xml:id="2166"><hi rend="bold underline">S&#x00F6;derblom</hi></persName>.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I preached again to a very large congregation.  My text was, "Who is my neighbour?["]  The Offertory for the 
<orgName xml:id="157">Children's Country Holiday Fund</orgName> exceeded &#x00A3;32.</p>
         <p>I attended the evening service, when once more the Abbey Church had a great congregation.  Northcote preached a characteristic sermon of the conventional parochial type: &amp; &#x00A3;15 more was collected for the C.C.H. Fund, making a total for the day of &#x00A3;89.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I gave a verbal promise to Prof. S&#x00F6;derblom that I would proceed to Upsala in September 1914</hi>, and give a course of 8 lectures on some subject connected with the history &amp; literature of the English church.</p>
         <p>We had a large party at luncheon including a Canadian professor of philosophy, 
<persName xml:id="2182"><hi rend="underline">William Caldwell</hi></persName>, and an American clergyman, named 
<persName xml:id="2183" display="no"><hi rend="underline">Mercer Johnston</hi></persName>.  Also 
<persName xml:id="62">Kirshbaum</persName>, who had preached in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>
