<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[446]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We bade a pleasant farewell to our hosts, and returned to town, where we arrived a few minutes after 11 p.m. [sic].  I went immediately to the Chapter Meeting, which sat till nearly 1 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="802"><hi rend="underline">Launcelot Troutbeck</hi></persName> came to see me.  We had some talk about the possibility of him becoming a clergyman.</p>
         <p>I dined with the 
<orgName xml:id="107">Literary Society</orgName>.  There were but seven of us dining &#8211; 
<persName xml:id="2085">Sir Sidney Colvin</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2097">Sir Henry Cunningham</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="653">Sir Valentine Chirol</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2099">Arthur Benson</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2098">Champneys</persName>, 
<persName xml:id="2096">Nathan</persName>, and myself.  <hi rend="bold underline">After dinner I walked back to Westminster with Chirol, holding much interesting converse with him about India</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[447]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<orgName xml:id="68">Convocation</orgName> met on <hi rend="underline">Tuesday</hi>, the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> July, and <hi rend="underline">Wednesday</hi> the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> the 
<persName xml:id="1123">Bp. of Southampton</persName> &amp; the 
<persName xml:id="1219">Archdeacon of Leicester</persName> stayed here.  The first day was occupied with Prayer&#8211;book Revision: the last mainly with the Relations of Church &amp; State.  </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There is a reckless temper in the Anglican clergy which facilitates the way of the 'high&#8211;fliers': and, unfortunately, the Abps. have given them a lead.  In the Church as in the State leaders strive to divine the set of the wind that they may run before it, &amp; so long as they can be first in the race of folly they account themselves to be 'leading' their followers</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, <hi rend="underline">Thursday</hi>, the 
<orgName xml:id="57">Representative Church Council</orgName> met.  There were, of course, the inevitable Welsh Church resolutions recommended by the inevitable speeches.  These ended, we had 
<persName xml:id="1748">Lord Halifax</persName> on the feet demanding urgency for his resolution about Deceased Wife Sister.  I made some fight, &amp; did succeed in getting a modification of the original wording.</p>
         <p>On <hi rend="underline">Friday</hi>, the 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, the whole morning was spent in discussing a platitudinous resolution on Industrial Unrest.  After lunch I carried a Rider to this effect:&#8211; 'that improvement in economic conditions is most gravely compromised by breaches of agreement, &amp; by the exercise of intimidation, whether on the part of employers or employed'.  I spoke for 25 minutes, &amp; was well received.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
