<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
<hi rend="bold">[419]</hi>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended service in chapel. 
<persName xml:id="1565"><hi rend="bold underline">Stokes</hi></persName> breakfasted with me in the Coffee Room. Then I returned to town by the 11 a.m. express. <hi rend="bold underline">
<persName xml:id="2258">Selbie</persName></hi>, the Principal of Mansfield, was in the carriage: we had some conversation on the Disestablishment question. Arrived in 
<placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, I found Ernest awaiting me. He went to work on the cuttings&#8211;register.</p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the Abbey, when the service was arranged to commemorate the centenary of 
<persName xml:id="1348" display="no"><hi rend="bold underline">Browning's</hi></persName> birth. A special anthem composed by 
<persName xml:id="2559">Parry</persName> was sung.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Then I instructed </hi>
<persName xml:id="246"><hi rend="bold underline">Elizabeth Asquith</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> for an hour. The impudent child asked me whether I would like to be a bishop! This, when a bishoprick is actually vacant, though truly a most uninviting one. Poor 
<persName xml:id="647">Stubbs</persName> died at last yesterday, &amp; Truro has lost its 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Bishop</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[420]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Saturday, the 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> May 1912, the 
<orgName xml:id="208" display="no">Welsh Conciliation Committee</orgName> met in the dining room, and agreed to publish in the papers the resolutions to which they had reached an accord.<note xml:id="239" display="no" n="1"></note> There was some indignation felt at the action of 
<persName xml:id="2325">Baumgarten</persName> in breaking away, &amp; letting out secrets.</p>
         <p>Then 
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I went to Cambridge, &amp; put up at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's Lodge with the 
<persName xml:id="4">Vice&#8211;Chancellor</persName>. The next day, <hi rend="bold underline">Sunday, the 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> May, I <ref xml:id="449">preached</ref> in the Chapel of Jesus College, &amp; afterwards to the University in Great S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Mary's</hi>. There was a fair congregation of dons, but of under&#8211;graduates perhaps 50 or 60. Yet I was assured that this was far above the average attendance, so grievously has church&#8211;going declined in the University. After the sermon, we called on the 
<persName xml:id="757">Master of Trinity</persName>, and on 
<persName xml:id="573">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burkitt</persName>. Then we had tea with 
<persName xml:id="1862">Prof. Bonney</persName>, who had collected a party to meet us, including 
<persName xml:id="1178" display="no">Clarence Stock</persName>. We attended Evensong in S. John's Chapel, and afterwards I dined in Hall. There I met 
<persName xml:id="2560"><hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Holland Rose</hi></persName>, the historian.</p>
         <p>On Monday we came away by the 9.45 express, having spent a very agreeable 'week&#8211;end'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[421]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">
<persName xml:id="570">Edith Bruce</persName> died of heart failure, having had to endure a supplementary operation</hi>. The poor woman has been more or less languishing these many months since the former operation. My wife &amp; I travelled to 
<placeName xml:id="39" display="no">Fairlie</placeName> on the afternoon of Ascension Day (May 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1912), &amp; on the next day, I conducted the Funeral Service. The local Presbyterian minister offered a prayer before the coffin was carried out of the House. The cemetery at Langs is beautifully placed, on the slope of the cliff, commanding the loveliest views of the Great &amp; Little Cumbrae, with the distant Arran hills, &amp; the avenue of islands &amp; promontories which leads to the Kyles of Bute. We returned to London the same evening motoring with 
<persName xml:id="1549" display="no">Monty Parker</persName> to Kilmarnock, &amp; joining the Scotch Mail at Carlisle. We arrived at Euston at 3.50 p.m., &amp; at once drove home, &amp; went to bed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Ascension Day, the 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> May, 1912, the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> reading of the Welsh Disestablishment Bill was carried by a majority of 81</hi>, the final phase of the debate was marked by a characteristic outburst of the 
<persName xml:id="234">Chancellor</persName>, in which he fell upon the 
<persName xml:id="368">Duke of Devonshire</persName> with much ferocity. There is no real desire that the Bill should pass outside the ranks of the baser&#8211;sort of Nonconformist. But the log&#8211;rolling necessities of the Government carry it forward as it were automatically.</p>
         
</body></text></TEI>
