<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[451]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~The number of men sinning neither extenuateth the sin, nor exempteth from judgment: but rather aggravateth the sin, &amp; pulleth down more severe &amp; speedy vengeance.  Multitudes of sinners are as multitudes of faggots, or other combustible fuel, which are so much the sooner set on fire: &amp; being once set on fire do burn so much the more fiercely.~~</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="1577">William Gouge</persName>. <ref xml:id="338">'God's Three Arrows'</ref> p.25.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated at 8 a.m. in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's.  There were 17cts.</p>
         <p>The heat was very great, &amp; the church was full, when at Mattins I preached on "The Problem of Politics".  The sermon was a long one, but I went through with it inexorably.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2348">President M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Vey</persName> of the State University in North Dakota lunched here.  He seemed to think that the general attitude of English people towards Americans is unfriendly.</p>
         <p>I preached in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's &#8211; a very exhausting performance.  Afterwards 
<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I had supper at the Deanery.  
<persName xml:id="1255">Linetta</persName> was there, &amp; two Canadian women.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[452]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>On Monday the 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, I found myself paying yesterday's Bill for heat &amp; effort.  I had to 'cry off' a lunch with 
<persName xml:id="1731">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowther</persName>, &amp; a dinner with 
<persName xml:id="2244">Sir John Struthers</persName>.  <hi rend="bold underline">But I read through the truly terrible report of 
<persName xml:id="252">Sir Roger Casement</persName> on the Putumayo abominations</hi>.  Also I wrote to 
<persName xml:id="695" display="no">Herbert Gritten</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Tuesday, the 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, I sent &#x00A3;5.5.0 to Sir R. Casement in response to the Appeal for an R.C. Mission in the Putumayo district. Also a letter to the <ref xml:id="410">Times</ref> supporting the same</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Then I attended the 
<orgName xml:id="166">Royal Society's</orgName> Anniversary service in the Abbey.<note xml:id="148" n="1"></note> In the afternoon we travelled to Southampton to visit the 
<persName xml:id="1123">Bishop</persName>.  The car met us at Southampton West.  After tea we motored to call on a neighbour &#8211; a large but by no means wealthy landowner named 
<persName xml:id="2245" display="no">Fleming</persName>.  He shewed us his charming garden &amp; horses, of which he had a considerable number.  He appears to make both a business &amp; a hobby of breeding &amp; exhibiting horses.</p>
         <p>On Wednesday, the 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> we motored to Winchester, &amp; were present at the 'Diocesan' service in the Cathedral.  The Bishop of the Diocese (
<persName xml:id="105">Talbot</persName>) preached.  The service was well&#8211;organized, hearty, &amp; dignified.  
<persName xml:id="2349" display="no">M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Valpy</persName> &#8211; a Suffragette, though not as yet violent &#8211; joined us at Winchester, &amp; returned with us to Bassett.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[453]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>On Thursday, the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, we motored to Portsmouth, &amp; were shewn over the dockyard.  The Admiral's barge carried us pleasantly from one point to another, &amp; his coxswain was a most intelligent guide.  The oldest buildings date from 1670.  We were specially interested in the submarines.  We had tea very pleasantly with Miss Moore, from whom I bought some Indian trifles brought home from India by Q. Mary.  There were derelicts from a recent bazaar.  I was much interested in the portraits of admirals which adorn Admiralty House.</p>
         <p>On Friday, the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> July, we motored again to Winchester, where we lunched at the Deanery, &amp; afterwards attended the 'Schools service' in the cathedral.  
<persName xml:id="602">Burge</persName> preached very effectively.  In the congregation I noticed the Warden of Winchester School (
<persName xml:id="601">Sir Kenneth</persName>), 
<persName xml:id="2350" display="no">Vidal</persName>, &amp; sundry old Wykehamists of my acquaintance.  We motored back to Bassett for tea, &amp; afterwards walked for two hours thro' the woods.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On Saturday, the 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, we left Bassett, &amp; travelled to Shrewsbury, in order to spend the week&#8211;end with the 
<persName xml:id="541">
<persName xml:id="777">Alingtons</persName></persName>.  The boat&#8211;races were happening, &amp; a 'flare&#8211;up' afterwards, all which we observed with due interest &amp; sympathy</hi>.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
