<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[376]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, January 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1912.</hi>
         </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>~~'The more any one doth only <hi rend="underline">notionally</hi> know in the matters of Religion, so as that the temper of his spirit remains altogether unsuitable &amp; opposite to the design and tendency of the things known; the more he hath lying ready to come in judgment against him; &amp; if therefore he count the things excellent which he knows, &amp; only please himself with his own knowledge of them, <hi rend="underline">'tis but a like case as if a man should be much delighted to behold his own condemnation written in a fair &amp; beautiful hand</hi>: or as if one should be pleased with the glittering of that sword which is directed against his own heart, &amp; must be the present instrument of death to him: &amp; so little pleasant is the case of such a person in itself, who thus satisfies his own curiosity with the concernments of eternal life &amp; death, that any serious person would tremble on his behalf, at that wherein he takes pleasure, &amp; apprehend just horror in that state of the case whence he draws matter of delight'~~</p>
         <p>[v. 
<persName xml:id="2274">John Howe</persName> <ref xml:id="359">'A Treatise of delighting in God'</ref> p. 181, London. 1674.]</p>
         </div>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[377]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="427"><hi rend="bold underline">Ralph</hi></persName> preached at Mattins, a most admirable sermon on S. Paul.  He said that Saul of Tarsus was evidently a town bred man: &amp; shewed the fact by blundering when he used rustic metaphors e.g. in supposing that <hi rend="underline">seed</hi> sown in the earth died, &amp; that wild olives were grafted into good ones.  His handling of the Conversion was strong &amp; masterly.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2461"><hi rend="bold underline">Nash</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, the </hi>
<persName xml:id="215"><hi rend="bold underline">Prime Minister's</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> Secretary, telegraphed to </hi>
<persName xml:id="752"><hi rend="bold underline">Barnett</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, suggesting that we sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> send an announcement to the press stating that the absence of ceremony in unveiling the monument of </hi>
<persName xml:id="509"><hi rend="bold underline">Campbell&#8211;Bannerman</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> was according to precedent.  I wrote a brief note to that effect, &amp; sent it to the </hi><ref xml:id="392"><hi rend="bold underline">'Times'</hi></ref><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="636"><hi rend="bold underline">Pearce</hi></persName> preached in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's at Mattins, &amp; afterwards lunched here.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I <ref xml:id="616">preached</ref> in the Abbey at 3 p.m.  My subject was the Miracles of the Gospel: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I spoke very openly as to the incredibleness of the "nature&#8211;miracles", and the religious unimportance of all miracles</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2285"><hi rend="bold underline">Herbert Nicholson</hi></persName><hi rend="bold underline">, my God&#8211;son, came from Barking to see me</hi>.  He lunched here, &amp; then returned home.  He is 16 this week, small for his age, &amp; with no definite scheme of work before him.</p>
         <p>
<persName xml:id="2462"><hi rend="bold underline">Watts&#8211;Ditchfield</hi></persName> preached in the Abbey at 7 p.m. &amp; afterwards joined us at supper.  He is not a great preacher.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
