<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[258]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The "Times" prints a short letter from Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> in reply to my letter of yesterday. <hi rend="bold underline">He denies the truth of Abbé Portal's assertions to which I had directed attention</hi>.</p>
         <p>"If the Abbé spoke about the reconciliation of the Roman &amp; Anglican communions upon the basis of Tridentine decisions, he must have been speaking about it as something which seemed to him desirable or possible, not as of something agreed upon in our conversations. <hi rend="bold underline">As a matter of fact it has not only not only been agreed upon, but not even discussed at Malines hitherto, at least in my hearing"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> This seems to be categorical enough.</p>
         <p>The Labour Congress at Liverpool made short work with the Communists, whose much–vaunted attack fizzled out very feebly. But what real importance attaches to "card–votes"? The constituencies of the two sets of delegates, that which met at <hi rend="underline">Scarborough</hi>, &amp; that which is now meeting at <hi rend="underline">Liverpool</hi>, must have been mainly composed of the same individuals. Yet the one is as ardent for the "Class–War" as the other for constitutional action"</p>
         <p>Miss Christopher &amp; her nephew, Faith Beaumont, Capt. Page–Gourlay, &amp; D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MCullagh came to dine. With ourselves and our guests we made up a party of twelve persons.</p></body></text></TEI>