<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I corrected, and despatched the second batch of proofs. This, and the correspondence occupied the whole morning. After lunch I walked round the Park with Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>. He is very indignant with the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> for their unmannerly attack on Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>. The more I reflect on the Archbishop's letter to Lord Shaftesbury, the more deplorable I think it. He tacitly concedes their impudent claim to be the guardians of the faith. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to play tennis, and afterwards had some talk with me. He seems to have settled his mind to preparing for Ordination.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pember <hi rend="underline">wrote to ask me to officiate at Katherine's<persName xml:id="4356"></persName> wedding in Oxford at the end of September, reminding me that I had done as much 30 years ago when she &amp; Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName> were married.</hi> How well I recall the scene! We were all younger then, &amp; the world had a brighter aspect.</p>
         <p>I sent £<hi rend="doubleunderline">5</hi> to the miner who wrote to me a few days ago, &amp; sent me his pay–sheets to demonstrate his poverty. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi><persName xml:id="5286"></persName>, the Rector of Chester–le–Street, answering my inquiry, wrote to say that he was an honest man, &amp; desperately poor. So I allowed myself the indiscretion of sending him a present. What can be the future of this great multitude of miners, gathered about pits which can never be worked profitably in the actual conditions which now obtain? It is a terrible question.</p></body></text></TEI>