<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The papers announce </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the death of the Bishop of Oxford</hi><persName xml:id="602"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It is but a few weeks since he preached at Durham, and said – so Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> told me – that he had never felt so physically fit in his life. I first made Burge's acquaintance in 1885, when I was a Fellow of All Souls, and he was a Scholar of University, and both of us were laymen. I had just put forward my project of the Laymen's League to resist Disestablishment and Disendowment, the policy which had appeared in Chamberlain's Radical programme. We soon went our different ways. I left Oxford for Bethnal Green, &amp; he, after staying in Oxford as a don, went to Repton as Headmaster, &amp; very quickly transferred himself to Winchester. I was ordained in 1887, and he not until 1897, though he was my senior by 15 months. In 1911 he succeeded Talbot as Bishop of Southwark, from whence he was translated to Oxford to succeed Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> in </hi><hi rend="italic underline">1919</hi><hi rend="italic">. Thus, himself by temperament, breeding, and conviction a Latitudinarian of somewhat old&#8211;fashioned type, he had to follow in his episcopate the two leaders of neo&#8211;Tractarianism. His natural amiability disinclined him for controversy, and he did certainly exhibit a complaisance which delighted his opponents &amp; disconcerted his friends, while surprising both. He was a man of</hi><hi rend="bold">[83]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="italic">distinguished appearance and courtly manners, endowed with a notable gift of dignified and elegant speech, and of a winning &amp; loveable disposition. But he had the faults of his qualities. He shrank from conflict, and was more yielding than his duty really allowed. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Latterly, his growing deafness provided a physical excuse for what was really an ethical defect. In private life he was charming – simple, considerate, interested, &amp; affectionate.</hi><hi rend="italic">He was true to his friends, and genuinely devoted to religious liberty. He could not understand either the pettiness or the strength of ecclesiastic partisanship, &amp; was easily hoodwinked by professions of devotion and pleas of conscience. Hence his episcopate at Oxford was more welcome to the Romanisers even than his predecessor's; and it is probably not excessive to say, that he did more for the success of the recent Anglo&#8211;Catholic Movement, which he disliked and distrusted, than any other Bishop.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I can never forget that he stood by me throughout the storm which heralded &amp; accompanied my entrance on episcopal office. He and Bishop Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName> "presented" me at my Consecration. Last autumn he and his wife stayed here: &amp; he commonly sate beside me at the Meetings of the Bishops at Lambeth. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Burge's</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> death is probably a misfortune for me personally. I have many detractors, and few friends. He was one of the few, and his influence was most potent where I am weakest. This circumstance was, of course, more important formerly than it can be now, when my career, such as it is, lies behind me. </hi><hi rend="italic">Indeed, his death should remind me of my own, which cannot be long deferred, and may be close at hand. My own generation is passing away, and its place is being taken by another generation with which I have little in common, less, perhaps, than most of my contemporaries. The loneliness of a Bishop, which, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi><hi rend="italic"> was lamenting, &amp; which is a cold shadow on episcopal life, is for me deepened by childlessness, by the increasing deafness of my Wife, and, most of all, by the estrangement f almost all, who w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> naturally stand closer if I could – but I cannot&#8211; share their policies and hopes. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">When my father and mother forsake me, the Lord taketh me up</hi><hi rend="italic">" says the Psalmist: and as another says, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">There is a Friend that sticketh closer than a brother</hi><hi rend="italic">". Yet, my heart fails me sometimes, when I look forward, and I could find it in me to envy </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Burge</hi><hi rend="italic"> the peace &amp; freedom which have come to him so quickly. For him "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">rest in the Lord</hi><hi rend="italic">": for me the dust &amp; danger of the Fight, &amp; then?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I received from the Archbishop the revised "List", and, according to his direction, destroyed the old. Then I wrote to his Grace, &amp; told him that I had done so, taking occasion to add some observations about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge.</hi> Then I wrote to poor <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Burge</hi>, who will be terribly distressed.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="5385"></persName> brought his father, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Westcott</hi>, the Bishop's<persName xml:id="1047"></persName> eldest son to lunch. <hi rend="bold">(</hi><hi rend="bold underline">He is rather a squalid person to look at, but he improved in conversation.) He told me that when the Prince of Wales, brought a Roman cardinal to Wynyard, &amp; proposed to give him precedence over the Bishop of Durham, Bishop Westcott refused to accept the invitation to meet H.R.H. This gave rise to the often&#8211;repeated legend that the Prince said there were only two persons who would correct him, his mother &amp; the Bishop of Durham. The palms in the Chapel were presented to the Bishop by the Marquis of Bute, and had been blessed by the Pope.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and attended the meeting of the Board of Education. It was announced that several more schools must be given up – West Auckland, Bishop Auckland, Pittington, &amp; Monkwearmouth. On returning to the castle, I received the Bishop – coadjutor of Albany U.S.A. &amp; his wife.</p>
         <p>Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> &amp; I talked again over his Ordination, &amp; he declared his intention of being Ordained. <hi rend="underline">Laus Deo</hi>!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I asked Bishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Oldham</hi><hi rend="italic"> whether he had met </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><hi rend="italic"> during his healing mission in the States, &amp; he replied that he had been very favourably disposed towards him, that his missions had attracted enormous crowds, &amp; seemed to be eminently successful.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">With time &amp; reflection, hwever, his opinion had largely changed. He had followed up the cures, &amp; found they "came to very little". Moreover, he was not well impressed by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> himself. His first view</hi><hi rend="italic"> of the manwas, indeed, not likely to create a good impression, for he came upon him in his shirt&#8211;slieves [sic] counting his gains! He said that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><hi rend="italic"> must have made much money for in 3 daysmhe netted 1400 dollars, &amp; more than twice that amount at another place. I inquired how the Bishop was able to know the precise amount, &amp;</hi><hi rend="italic underline">replied that his secretary had to send Hickson a cheque for more than 4000 dollars for a few days missioning.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hickson</hi><hi rend="italic"> stipulated that no deductions were to be made for expenses etc. All this accords but too well with what one hears of his proceedings in other places.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Both Bishop </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Oldham</hi><hi rend="italic"> and his wife are strong opponents of Prohibition, &amp; both partook of wine at dinner. They are evidently Republicans, &amp; have the meanest opinion of President Wilson. </hi></p></body></text></TEI>