<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I leave Oxford with a strange sense of loneliness, almost as if I had been expelled. Everybody is kind enough, &amp; I love every stone of the place, yet I do not belong to it, nor can I enter without an effort into its interests and ideals. <hi rend="bold underline">There is no unhappier condition under which any man's life can be passed than that of remoteness from the common experiences: and that is precisely my unfortunate lot. At every turn I must be silent lest I should be either offensive or absurd. Exiled by no fault of my own from the normal life, social &amp; intellectual, I might have gained a foothold in Oxford, &amp; become in some sense intelligible to it, if I could have thrown myself into its ecclesiastical activities. But this became altogether impossible. The solitude grows ever more complete. The same fortune pursues me in the world outside Oxford. I do not share the general enthusiasms, nor am I intelligible to my contemporaries. Set in a chair of great authority I can command neither the confidence of colleagues, nor the loyalty of subordinates. It is probably the case that the experiences of youth are most keenly felt &amp; most vividly appreciated in later life.</hi> Therefore the absence of happy &amp; honourable experiences in youth is so grave a calamity. Old age must live on memories, as youth on hopes. And the quality of the memories goes far to determine the quality of old age. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[118]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After breakfast I walked round to the Sheldonian with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Chelmsford</hi><persName xml:id="65"></persName><hi rend="italic"> (&amp; Hardinge<persName xml:id="548"></persName>),and voted for Lord Oxford &amp; A. The opinion seems to be general that he will be defeated. I ran into </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Amery</hi><hi rend="italic">, who had travelled up by a very early train in order to support </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">L. Cave</hi><hi rend="italic">: &amp; there were many other inveterate Tories doing the same, making it quite evident that the party motive was in full vigour. The science men are joining with the parson's against </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Asquith</hi><hi rend="italic"> who, as they maintain, "let them down" in the recent Commission. Thus his loyalty to the tradition of Oxford has tended to destroy the chance of election. It is very odd world indeed. I travelled by way of Leicester, Nottingham, Sheffield, York to Darlington where I was met by the car, &amp; driven to Auckland. There I changed, and returned to Darlington in order to attend the Banquet arranged in connexion with the Railway Centenary. I sate between </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Churchill</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">L. Gainford</hi><persName xml:id="2216"></persName><hi rend="italic">, &amp; was fairly interested.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">L. Gray of Fallodon</hi><hi rend="italic"> presided, &amp; </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic"> proposed his health. They exchanged pleasant compliments based on reminiscences of undergraduate life in Balliol, and again '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">the iron entered my soul'</hi><hi rend="italic">. So I came away in some haste&amp; depression, as irrational as it was, perhaps, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">impolite</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>