<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The great spiritual blunder of the Infallibilist view of Revelation lies in the assumption that there <hi rend="underline">can</hi> be infallible teaching at all except by a Being as incapable of living a false life as of pronouncing a false proposition.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">R. E. Hutton</hi>. Pref to 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Ed. of Theol. Essays.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The weather was mild, bright, and spring&#8211;like today. I received a very interesting letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi><persName xml:id="4430"></persName>. He must have some good stuff in him to write so interestingly. Also, I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>.<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> Life in Johannesburg is clearly not going to be a "walk&#8211;over".</p>
         <p>I worked at the Book, and then lunched with the Rotary Club, and addressed them on "<hi rend="underline">Publicity and Justice</hi>".</p>
         <p>Later, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winston</hi>, where I confirmed about 70 candidates. The beautiful church was crowded with a very attentive &amp; well&#8211;behaved congregation. The candidates pleased me by their devout &amp; determined demeanour. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         <p>Two persons have written to me making reference to my article, "The Parson in Parliament", which is the second of the six which I promised to send to the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>. Thus I have assurance that the poor thing has appeared &amp; that Escombe has gained another twenty guineas!</p></body></text></TEI>