<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>We all motored to Durham for the Missionary Festival. The Conference in the Cosin Library was not a very lively affair. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi> was windy &amp; dull: and the discussion was unfruitful to say the least. After lunching with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, we went to the Cathedral for the special service. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi><hi rend="underline"> preached an excellent sermon, which was excellently delivered</hi>. His voice seemed to suit the building. Then we had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, and were joined by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie Dobbie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName>. We motored to Newcastle, and dined at the Railway Hotel with Lady Ravensworth, before going to Wallsend, where I presided at a large meeting of the Mothers' Union, which was addressed by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hubert Barclay. She spoke well &amp; sensibly. We returned to Auckland immediately after the meeting, and arrived there shortly after 10 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">R. J. Campbell</hi> writes to ask me to promise to preach in Holy Trinity Church, Brighton, on April 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> next year! These distant promises are apt to fail of fulfilment. Yet it is difficult to refuse the request, which is expressed with much courtesy. And, of course, I did preach the Robertson Jubilee Sermon in 1916.</p></body></text></TEI>