<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[252]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and discussed the discipline case with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. He undertook to see the Registrar, and show him the incriminating letters, &amp; I promised (if not warned off by a telegram,) to go to the Registry on Monday at 4 p.m. I then returned to Auckland, and wrote to the accused man telling him that he would have to face legal proceedings, and that until he had cleared his character, he must not officiate in the parish church. I said that the formal inhibition would follow, &amp; that I would make provision for the services on, and after the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of October. That's a pleasant letter to receive from one's Bishop!</p>
         <p>The papers report the appointment of the Dean of Bristol, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burroughs</hi><persName xml:id="3777"></persName>, to be Bishop of Ripon. He is only 43, and will replace <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName> as our youngest Bishop. If distinction at school and college were a trustworthy indication of understanding and ability, the Episcopate of the Northern Province will have received a notable addition, for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burroughs</hi> has an exceptionally brilliant record. But the letters to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, by which he first became known to the general public, gave me but a mean impression of his ability.</p></body></text></TEI>