<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went off to visit M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Percival in Wales. I proceeded to London, and put up at the Master's House in the Temple. Before dinner we walked and talked in the Temple Garden for more than an hour. There came to dinner Sir Alfred Hopkinson, lately principal of the University in Manchester, and one whom I judged to be the County Court Judge of Birmingham. The local Worcester papers contain accounts of the Diocesan Conference. <hi rend="bold underline">I was amused by the following in Berrow's Worcester Journal</hi>:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"On the question of patronage reform the conference listened to one of the most fascinating addresses ever delivered since Bishop Perowne revived the Conferences. To match the vivid interest shown in the Bishop of Durham's arguments and the whole&#8211;hearted enjoyment of his wit, <hi rend="bold underline">one would have to go back to the days of Bishop Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, when thrust and counter&#8211;thrust were oftener witnessed than they are today</hi><hi rend="bold">".</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>Well, well! The enjoyment was severely limited to the place of assembly! I suppose Gore's episcopate – the last of the old regime, before the breaking&#8211;up of the historic see &#8211; has in retrospect an aspect of greatness.</p></body></text></TEI>