<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Reunion of the clergy whom I have ordained was held</hi>. At 11.30a.m. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. The communicants numbered 23. Altogether 37 attended. After lunch we spent the afternoon in the garden, talking &amp; playing games. Then came tea, and Evensong in the Chapel, at which I gave a short address. After this, the men took their departure. I took occasion to talk to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick</hi> about the vacancy at S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's, Annfield Plain. He undertook to consider his own preferment, &amp; to let me know his decision.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">J. A. Little</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to dine, &amp; stay the night. I offered him the Vicarage of S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> John with S</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Marg. Monkheseldon. He promised to consider the matter, &amp; let me know.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dobson</hi><hi rend="italic"> stayed to dine &amp; sleep. He has certainly shown capacity during the vacancy at Whickham.</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">If only he could correct his pronunciation, which would offend the ears of an educated congregation, he would go far</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is strange but true, that small personal defects outweigh the most substantial merits. This circumstance should never be lost from mind in our estimate of men. There is no more insecure foundation for the judgement of any man than the measure of success which he may achieve in his profession. That may be no more than a proof of the crazy partiality of the world.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>