<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[234]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The two greatest uprisings of the private religious spirit &amp; temper against what was common and customary were, I suppose, Monasticism and Puritanism: but Monasticism &amp; Puritanism outwardly so different, yet with so many deep affinities both in their good and their evil, if they could have had their way unchecked, would have broken up the Church in the attempt to cleanse it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Church</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Pascal &amp; Other Sermons</hi> p. 109 </p>
         </div>
         <p>The "Church Times" takes up its parable again on the subject of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Barnes's</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> delinquencies. Not now his heresies, but his practical deficiencies form the theme! It appears that he is neglectful, discourteous &amp; unbusinesslike! The statements have an ill book, &amp; only the well&#8211;grounded suspicion of <hi rend="underline">all</hi> statements which spring from the "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" camp can hold one back from taking an ill&#8211;impression. On the other hand, Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> has a brilliant effective answer to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> attack on Barnes. It appears on the first page of the C. of E. Gazette, Bainbridge who holds an important position in the diocese of Birmingham, &amp; is a moderate High Churchman, spoke with surprising decision about his Bishop's failure to handle his business properly. This is very regrettable. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[235]</hi></p>
         <p>I wasted my whole morning in writing letters. I wrote to Tom Hay, and Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName>. In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Ravensworth, where I presided over a meeting organized for the Gateshead Deanery in the cause of foreign missions. Representative of S.P.G.<orgName xml:id="23"></orgName> and C.M.S.<orgName xml:id="124"></orgName> gave addresses of a mortal dullness, which added to the coldness of the Hall reduced me a woeful state of chilled boredom! However there was a considerable gathering, and there was tea and some kind of entertainment following on the meeting. Miss Andersen entertained us ("the platform") in her own sanctum. We returned to Auckland after tea, &amp; I had time to complete, copy, &amp; despatch my letters to Robin before dinner. Why do I waste my time and strength in writing to young men, who cannot possibly have any real regard for me? </p>
         <p>Thus ends a week which has been more completely wasted than any which I can recall. The loss of working time is irreparable, &amp; endangers my whole scheme of activity. I fear that I am trying to do the impossible eg: be an active bishop, keep up correspondence with young friends, entertain guests, and write for the newspapers, all at the same time. I shall soon be 62 years old, &amp; my mind grows as stiff as my limbs! </p></body></text></TEI>