<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[243]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday, September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The Socialist candidate has been returned to Eastham, through the intervention of a liberal candidate. The actual vote for Socialism was smaller than at the General Election. I spent the whole day indoors, for rain began to fall shortly after breakfast, and continued to fall in varying degrees of violence until the evening. I wrote something more of the Article for <hi rend="underline">the Bishoprick</hi>, and pledged mine host to take in that journal. Lady S. begged me to preach in the Chapel on Sunday, <hi rend="bold underline">and I promised to do so though I have no robes with me. The Vicar, who acts as Chaplain came to see me</hi>. He is an ex&#8211;naval Chaplain. I spent the afternoon in reading a painfully interesting &amp; powerfully written Russian War&#8211;novel.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Hadow arrived before dinner bringing with him a breeze of optimism &amp; confidence</hi>. He spoke to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi>, of whose essential disinterestedness &amp; patriotism he is fully persuaded. His great fault is an excessive belief in his own powers of reconciliation, &amp; thus, in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow's</hi> view, explained his worst failures. As one of his best friends phased it, Lloyd George was "too fond of harnessing the devil". <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi> refuses to take the proceedings at Scarborough seriously. But herein I must judge him to be mistaken.</p></body></text></TEI>