<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[42]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Do you know that in the R.C. Church Confirmation is only reserved to Bishops by custom? in missionary districts where dioceses have not been established, Rome gives faculties to its Vicar Apostolic, who is only a priest, to confirm. This is, of course, exceptional: but it shows what the theology of the matter is.</p>
         <p>Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Alfred Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName>. May 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The police knocked up Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> at 1.30 a.m. to inquire whether I was alive, <hi rend="bold underline">as reports of the Bishop of Durham's sudden death were current in London and Manchester</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote letters, and worked at the Book. Then, after lunch I spent an hour with the dentist, &amp; then I tried to clear up my room. It was a Herculean task, for the accumulation of books &amp; papers had been undisciplined for an unusually long interval, on account of the book.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote to that old humbug, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Charles Harris, who flatters himself that he is going to transform the E.C.H. into a society of sacred study &amp; the home of sound learning! He assures me that the united Convocations will provide the authority to which all good Anglo&#8211;Catholics will defer!</p></body></text></TEI>