<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[144] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>If a great change is to be made in human affairs, the minds of men will be fitted to it, the general opinions and feelings will draw that way. Every fear, every hope will forward it; and then they who persist in opposing this mighty current in human affairs will appear rather to resist the decrees of Providence itself than the mere designs of men. They will not be resolute and firm, but perverse and obstinate.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burke.</hi><hi rend="underline">Thoughts on French Affairs</hi>. 1791. (iv.377)</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished and despatched an article on 'Tennessee' for the </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Evening Standard</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. The conclusion of the laughable farce of the trial at Dayton is announced today.</hi> The school teacher, Scopes, is of course condemned, &amp; fined 100 dollars!</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Durham, &amp; had a consultation with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> about the vacant benefices. Then I had an interview with Wallis, &amp; arranged that Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> should go there next term. After tea with Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> I returned to Auckland. Almost immediately the crank, Lomax, from Ferryhill appeared, and <hi rend="underline">blathered</hi> for nearly an hour! I wrote to George Adam Smith<persName xml:id="244"></persName> asking him to come, &amp; address the clergy. </p></body></text></TEI>