<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8a.m. There were 9 communicants, including the Archbishop and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Page&#8211;Gourlay. Both the Archbishop and I remained at home during the morning. I wrote to the Bishop of Peterborough about the age of Confirmation candidates: to my godson, Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName>: and to my brother Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>.</p>
         <p>Lang tells me that when he was Bishop of Stepney, he saw a good deal of Hickson, but "dropped" him because of his fondness for mixing himself up with spiritualism etc. Yet he considered him an honest &amp; devout, though exceedingly unbalanced &amp; emotional man. He thought his financial procedures, though extremely unwise &amp; unsatisfactory, not necessarily dishonest.</p>
         <p>After lunch the Archbishop went off to Hartlepool to preach in S. Hilda's: and I walked for more than an hour in the Park with my other guest. </p>
         <p>I motored to Penshaw, and preached in the Parish Church. The congregation consisted mainly of young men &amp; women. I could not complain of inattention. After service the members of the parochial church Council met me in the vestry, &amp; seemed very pleased with themselves. The vicar, Holme, has been incumbent for more than 25 years. Penshaw is in the gift of the Bishop of Manchester, &amp; is worth nearly &#x00A3;600 per annum.</p></body></text></TEI>