<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Wherever we look in the animal kingdom we find that habit is response to environment and that inherited structure is nothing but the crystallization of the habits of past generations.</p>
         <p>Macbride "Zoology" in 'Evolution in the light of modern knowledge' p.261</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The lumbago was severe enough to make me send for D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Macullagh, &amp; to confine me to my room</hi>. So I read a lot more of this book which old Wilson led me to buy, &amp; which is presently a fair account of 'Science up to Date'. Save when the jargon makes it almost unintelligible, I find it very interesting.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="5385"></persName> came to see me, &amp; brought back the copy of the 'Modern Churchman', which I had lent him in order that he might read Fawkes's<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> vivacious article on 'The Council of Nicoea'. I was surprised to find that it made no impression on him. But he reads no poetry, &amp; has little taste for literature. These Cambridge men are queer embodiments of culture!</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hawke</hi> of Bearpark writes to accept nomination to Monkwearmouth in succession to Canon Brown, whose institution to Northallerton will not take place until October 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, so that everything is rather 'previous'!</p></body></text></TEI>