<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[226]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I put the finishing touches to my centenary sermon before breakfast, and after breakfast went immediately to Gateshead Fell church for the service at 10.30 a.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> went with me to carry my staff, &amp; did his duty "as to the manor born". The Mayor &amp; Corporation of Gateshead attended in state, &amp; there was a considerable congregation. The Rector's son, a stout cleric with an "Anglo&#8211;Catholic" intonation read Mattins, &amp; I celebrated the Holy Communion. There were 61 communicants, though the parish contains more than 5000 people, &amp; it was the 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> Sunday in the month, let alone the centenary commemoration. Old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Mitchell is far gone in the eighties, and he has held the Rectory for 27 years. After the service we returned to Auckland. We walked round the park with the dogs during the afternoon: and then I wrote letters, read the Spectator, &amp; talked with Jimmie.</p>
         <p>In the course of the day I had much talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi> about the Christian ministry, and his own Ordination thereto. He seems to have settled his mind very firmly on his purpose, and is very determined to master the requisite knowledge. How far his natural powers will make this easy, I am not sure: but he certainly is not below the average, &amp; that is not saying much now.</p></body></text></TEI>