<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[135]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left Canterbury after breakfast. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was to go her own way to visit her friends. On arriving at Victoria, I first drove to S. Paul's Deanery &amp; deposited my baggage, &amp; then went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> for lunch. At 2.30 p.m., I attended the meeting of the Ecclesiastical Courts Commission, and then had <hi rend="bold underline">an interview with the Archbishop of Canterbury at the Athenaeum, on the subject of applying the Barrier Act to the constitution of the Church Assembly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> His Grace was friendly but elusive, and suggested that I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> write to him as Chairman of the Standing Committee of the Assembly proposing a resolution. We then discussed the impending vacancy at the Deanery of Westminster. He expressed himself very strongly against <hi rend="doubleunderline">Carnegie's</hi> appointment, but evidently thought that, in the absence of any other person, &amp; that one of quite evident fitness, it was nowise improbable. His Grace "sniffed" at the notion of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop D'Arcy's</hi><persName xml:id="1361"></persName> appointment, &amp; seemed nowise attracted by anyone whom I could mention. He suggested as a possible candidate, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicky Sheppard</hi><persName xml:id="3611"></persName>!! I observed that I thought some academic or intellectual distinction ought to be an indispensable qualification in the case of the Dean of Westminster.</p></body></text></TEI>