<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[253]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Wilt thou forgive sin, through which I run,</p>
         <p>And do run still, though still I do deplore?</p>
         <p>When Thou hast done, Thou has not done;</p>
         <p>For I have more.</p>
         <p>Wilt Thou forgive that sin which I have won</p>
         <p>Others to sin, and made my sin their door?</p>
         <p>Wilt Thou forgive that sin which I did shun</p>
         <p>A year or two, but wallowed in a score?</p>
         <p>When Thou hast done, Thou hast not done;</p>
         <p>For I have more.</p>
         <p>I have a sin of fear, that when I've spun</p>
         <p>My last thread, I shall perish on he shore;</p>
         <p>But swear by Thyself, that at my death Thy Son</p>
         <p>Shall shine, as He shines now and heretofore;</p>
         <p>And having done that Thou hast done;</p>
         <p>I fear no more.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">John Dunne</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Lines written in his later years on his sick&#8211;bed, &amp; sung to the organ by the choristers of S. Paul's</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[254]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A brilliant morning. The sun shone on trees which were beginning to glow with the dying splendours of autumn. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Penelope</hi><hi rend="italic"> communicated. I carried a heavy heart to the Altar. It is terrible that at this time in this place, where so grievous perplexities enfold us, it is we, the Lord's ordained ministers who '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">make the Lord's People transgress</hi><hi rend="italic">'. The Collect was relevant to our present needs in this diocese. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Let thy continual pity cleanse and defend thy Church</hi><hi rend="italic">". The general laxity which is disclosing itself in society generally, is having its effect on the clergy. They too are no longer sure of their ground: no longer acquiescent in their lot: no longer comforted by their creed. There are no unhappier and more discontented faces anywhere now than those of the clergy. And sometimes there are cynical &amp; debased faces also, but these, I think, more commonly among the Roman priests, with whom the rule of compulsory celibacy has to be reckoned with. In a secularized society, casting to enjoy itself, the clergy find themselves tied to professions &amp; employments which pre&#8211;suppose religion, and which are unintelligible &amp; superfluous where religion is not. They are, &amp; know themselves to be, "fish out of water"; and they resent the fact, resent it all the more vehemently as Religion fails to keep its hold of themselves.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[255]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing a discourse for use later. After lunch I walked around the Park, where I lighted upon a company of young miners, about a dozen, sitting on the grass apparently engaged in discussion, but probably employed less guilelessly, when my back was turned! However, I sate down with them, &amp; we talked in the friendliest fashion for half an hour. They are both intelligent and polite. <hi rend="bold underline">One of them, who rather aggressively disclosed himself as a Roman Catholic, said that one shilling a week was deducted from the earnings of every D.C. miner for the Priest</hi>. He c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> get free of this charge by going to the office &amp; asking to be relieved of it: but I gathered that this was rarely done, as the Priest would get wind of it, &amp; would want to know the reason why. <hi rend="underline">All</hi> the "off&#8211;takes" are deducted, however small the miner's earnings during the week might be. In one case the amount left, after this deduction, was no more than threepence! This seems hard, but probably the actuarial basis of the various insurance funds, to which the men contribute, requires that the contributions sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not vary. I motored to Sunderland, &amp; preached at Evensong in S. Paul's Hendon. The church was not more than four fifths full. There was a celebration of the Holy Communion to follow Evensong, but for this I did not wait, but returned to the Castle where I arrived about 9.30 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>