<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We left the Vicarage of Halifax at 9.35 a.m., and motored to Auckland Castle by way of Keighley, Skipton, Settle, Kirby Lonsdale, Sedbergh, Brough to Barnard Castle, arriving about 10 minutes before 2 p.m. The distance was about 115 miles. I never saw the hedge&#8211;rows, radiant &amp; odorous with wild roses, look so lovely. The brightness of the weather showed the country to great advantage.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The annual meeting of Archdeacons and Rural Deans</hi> met at 4 p.m. After tea in the State room, we had a conference in the Library. The Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> introduced the idea of training Ordination candidates, &amp; described his scheme for training young men of the humbler class. It was approved, everybody undertaking to bring this matter before his Ruri&#8211;decanal Chapter in October. Then we went in the Garden, &amp; played bowls &amp; croquet for an hour before dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">These Rural Deans are, I think, good, loyal, and religious men, very anxious to do their duty to the diocese, but they are becoming, or have already become old men: they are weighted with parochial cares: they are pinched in the matter of finances; &amp; they are as baffled as their Bishop by the situation to be faced.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>
