<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Yesterday's '<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>' gave prominence to the statement that Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> was to be made Dean of Westminster. As this communication was dated from Birmingham, it had an air of verisimilitude, which made it disquieting. I cannot bring myself to believe that the Prime Minister<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> <hi rend="underline">could</hi> consent to give so heavy a blow to the Episcopate, or invent the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> with the prestige of so great a triumph. But the times are out of joint, and anything is possible. This morning's post brings me a letter from Barnes himself, written from an address in Oxfordshire where he appears to be taking his holiday. He makes no allusion either to Ryle's<persName xml:id="325"></persName> death, or to any rumours of his own appointment to succeed him. He thinks that the Archbishop was '<hi rend="underline">tired &amp; in need of a holiday when he sent his reply</hi>' and adds: "It is unlike him to have affirmed without enquiry that the pretentious &amp; ignorant "scholarship" of the E.C.U. was worthy of serious consideration, and I am surprised that he did not rebuke the E.C.U. for the studied insolence of their letter. I do not propose to reply to it. But I am reading a paper next week at the Modern Churchmen's Conference at Oxford where I will re&#8211;state my opinions &amp; combine them with that positive religious teaching which you are right in asking me not to forget".</p>
         <p> It is much to be desired that he will be as good as his word.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>' re&#8211;prints the 'Observer's 'announcement' about Barnes, and garnishes it with a picture of the Dean – presumptive! But it also publishes a paragraph pointing out that he is rather specially unsuitable for the position of Dean of Westminster, &amp; proposing as one more obviously fitted for it, the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName>!! It seems to be taken for granted that the bad precedent of appointing a diocesan Bishop to that Deanery shall not only be followed, but followed without the extenuating circumstances which was held to justify it viz. the bishop's failure of health. Both Barnes and Temple are comparatively junior bishops, &amp; both have hardly entered on middle age. I showed Darling<persName xml:id="4032"></persName> my correspondence with the Archbishop. He is strongly opposed to Anglo&#8211;Catholicism.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Justice Stareleigh </hi>was modelled on an actual judge named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gazelen</hi>. This man was described by L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi> as a little &amp; rather consequential personage, who was quite unconscious of the impression which his characteristic method of fulfilling his functions made on others When he was fold that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dickens</hi> had modelled his ridiculous judge on himself, he was so mortified, that he took to his bed, &amp; gave up the ghost! <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Darling </hi>derived his knowledge of these circumstances from a number of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Gazelen's family.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[202]</hi></p>
         <p>Our guests spent the morning in visiting the Bowes Museum at Barnard Castle, and seeing the church at Staindrop. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went with them, and brought them back to lunch. In the afternoon Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and Di went to play lawn tennis at Darlington, and I walked in the park with Darling and Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>. After tea L'Danesfort<persName xml:id="2092"></persName> and Lady Pothers arrived to dine and sleep. The vicar<persName xml:id="5414"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Parry Evans came in to dinner. Di made the evening pass pleasantly enough with her songs. The normal absence of music is a grave condition under which to live. </p>
         <p>Darling is certainly a very brilliant &amp; versatile person. He is within 4 years of being 80 years old, &amp; yet he throws off articles for the evening papers (for which he receives a fee of fifty guineas for each one) with the utmost ease; &amp; these article have the ease and gaiety &amp; movement of a man in the fresh flow of his genius. He has an unfailing supply of musing &amp; racy anecdotes, and his reading, which has been uncommonly wide, is at the disposal of his conversation. It is difficult to discern any evidence of age. Craik is older by nearly 3 years, but he is in mind and manner a much older man. Danesfort is only 72, but physically and mentally he is the oldest of my three guests. </p></body></text></TEI>