<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I cannot give up to all the Deists in Great Britain the existence of witchcraft, till I give up the credit of all history, sacred and profane. And at the present time, I have not only as strong, but stronger proofs of this, from eye and ear witnesses, than I have of murder; so that I cannot rationally doubt of one any more than the other.</p>
         <p>J. Wesley. Journal. May 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1776.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I expended the morning, very rashly, on the Book, for I have nothing ready for next Sunday, when I am pledged to preach two sermons. Stephenson brought to lunch the Vicar designate of Whickham, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Huthwaite</hi>, a lugubrious man who has been a prison chaplain through most of his life! Also, Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, &amp; his registrar, Burrill, came to lunch. In the afternoon I motored to Tow Law, for a Confirmation, and after tea with the Astronomical Vicar, Espin<persName xml:id="5315"></persName>, went to Stanley for a second Confirmation. Both services pleased me. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Earl Grey</hi> arrived during my absence. We had some conversation after dinner. He gives me the impression of having been hustled into ecclesiastical interests by the ardour of his wife's relations!</p></body></text></TEI>