<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[249]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came with me as far as Darlington where I took train for Oxford, travelling as far as Banbury without change. A beautiful rainbow heralded my approach to Oxford. I had scarcely settled myself in All Souls College before Frank<persName xml:id="66"></persName> appeared, &amp; carried me to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's, where the young people were engaging in making sure that all things were in readiness for the morrow. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Richards, the Vicar of S. Mary's, an "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" was filling in the registers as far as might be, in order to economize time. The bridegroom, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline">Charles Galton Darwin</hi> is 37 years old, and of a bulky figure. <hi rend="underline">Katherine</hi><persName xml:id="4356"></persName> is 25. He is a Professor in Edinburgh, holding a mathematical chair if I err not. Leaving S. Mary's I went to a hair&#8211;dresser, &amp; got myself brushed up for the function!</p>
         <p>I dined with the Pembers, and went to bed about 11 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My article in the Evening Standard entitled "The Lure of Moscow" appeared in yesterday's issue</hi>. This I learned from the <hi rend="underline">Newcastle Daily Journal</hi>, which a fellow&#8211;traveller had left in the train, &amp; which called attention to what I had said. I found the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> in the Common Room, &amp; read the Article. To my annoyance the population of Petrograd was stated to be 80,000, whereas I had written correctly 800,000.</p></body></text></TEI>
