<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[241]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The real analogue to the Fundamentalists of today is not the early Church, but the State–religion of the Roman Empire. The religion of heathen Rome had reached the "Fundamentalist" stage by the first century. No educated Romans believed it, but few said so. The Pious lower classes were heathen Fundamentalists, &amp; the pious upper classes were Institutionalists. Between them they kept heathenism in existence for three centuries: though the Christians, the Experimentalists of those days, won in the end.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lake</hi><persName xml:id="3172"></persName>. <hi rend="underline">The Religion of Yesterday &amp; Tomorrow</hi>. p. 160.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I worked at the Article for '<hi rend="underline">The Bishoprick</hi>', but made little progress. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petrie</hi><persName xml:id="5351"></persName> &amp; his wife, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi> &amp; his curate <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mudford</hi> came to lunch. Afterwards <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I walked round the Park. On returning to my study I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kirsopp Lake's</hi> new book "<hi rend="underline">The Religion of Yesterday &amp; Tomorrow</hi>". It is painfully interesting, perhaps because it is painfully perverse. The new Religion, of which he essays to describe the character, would be no religion at all. There is a very bitter tone running through the Book. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Thurlow</hi> came to see me. They are growing fine boys.</p></body></text></TEI>