<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I read M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Crantz's "Account of the Mission into Greenland". Although I make much allowance for the liberty which I know the Brethren take, in their accounts of one another, yet I do not see any reason to doubt that some of the Heathens have been converted. But what pity that so affecting an account should be disgraced with those vile doggerel verses: just calculated to make the whole performance stink in the nostrils of all sensible men! In the evening the multitude that flocked together obliged me to preach abroad. I saw but three or four that seemed unaffected: and those, I suppose, were footmen; a race of men who are commonly lost to all sense of shame, as well as of good and evil.</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Journal. Aug. 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1767.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The quondam Fellow of Lincoln College, Oxford, cannot be altogether and always submerged by the unwearying mission&#8211;preacher. He must have suffered much from his exstatick and unlettered disciples, whose taste for "doggerel verses" was insatiable &amp; indiscriminating.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I slept intermittently in the sleeper, and about 7.30 a.m. went to the Railway Hotel, had a bath and breakfast, &amp; then was carried by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Spicer &amp; his wife to the business&#8211;house in the City, hard by Blackfriars Bridge. There was a gathering of the Spicer clan, headed by the old Privy Councillor, now 80 years old. The service was held in a large room at the top of the building. A large company (perhaps about 300) of the employees of the firm formed the congregation. I preached for nearly 20 minutes, and then (<hi rend="bold underline">with a cheque for &#x00A3;26.5.0. in my pocket, the preacher's fee which I destine for the Escombe Fund)</hi>, I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Later, I went to King's Cross, where I was joined by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi>, and we travelled together to Darlington. A parson from the Winchester diocese, who was in the carriage travelling with his wife to Middlesborough in order to attend the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Conference, introduced himself to me as having met me some years ago. His name was Richards, &amp; he seemed a fairly intelligent man. On arriving at Auckland we walked in the Park before dinner. Donaldson was very appreciative of its beauty. After dinner I had much conversation with him on many subjects.</p>
         <p>If any one had told Donaldson &amp; me, when we were both young men living in Bethnal Green 38 years ago, that we should come together as bishops respectively of Durham &amp; Salisbury, we should have been highly amused.</p></body></text></TEI>