<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>The common problem, yours, mine, everyone's,</p>
         <p>Is – not to fancy what were fair in life</p>
         <p>Provided it could be – but, finding first</p>
         <p>What may be, then find how to make it fair</p>
         <p>Up to our own means: a very different thing!</p>
         <p>No abstract intellectual plan of life</p>
         <p>Quite irrespective of life's plainest laws,</p>
         <p>But one, a man, who is man &amp; nothing more,</p>
         <p>May lead within a world which (by your leave)</p>
         <p>Is Rome or London, not Fool's paradise.</p>
         <p>Embellish Rome, idealize away,</p>
         <p>Make paradise of London if you can,</p>
         <p>You're welcome, nay, you're wise.</p>
         <p>'Bishop Blougram's Apology.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The newspapers report the death of the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName> at the age of 69 years. He has been more or less an invalid for many years</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">He with Burge<persName xml:id="602"></persName> presented me for consecration on Feb. 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd </hi><hi rend="bold underline">1918. Now they are both gone</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ryle</hi> was a loveable man of considerable ability &amp; tenacity of purpose, but not in any sense great. He preferred the society of his intellectual inferiors, &amp; enjoyed their adulation. Hence he was a weak Dean, dominated by his minor–canons. He had <hi rend="bold">[194] </hi>[symbol] a fine appearance, a courtly manner, &amp; an excellent voice. These physical advantages counted for much in a position so constantly associated with public functions. I suspect that an element of personal vanity cooperated with the flatterous insistence of the minor cannons &amp; servants to make him unduly tolerant of ceremonial innovations. He was certainly sentimental and emotional to an uncommon degree. I judge him to have had a relatively feeble sense of discipline, though no inadequate sense of his own official prerogatives<hi rend="underline">. Under his influence the Abbey became as centre of Anglo–Catholick experimentation, &amp; definitely ceased to maintain the tradition of rather old–fashioned Liberalism with which the Deans Stanley and Bradley had identified it</hi>. Ryle was bound to the Archbishop of Canterbury by a close personal friendship, as well as by the mutual understanding born of frequent official cooperation. <hi rend="underline">I doubt whether this intimacy was wholesome to either of them</hi>. If I may believe the statements of Canons Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, &amp; Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>, he showed little regard for the rights &amp; preferences of his capitular colleagues: <hi rend="underline">but they all allowed that he was very loveable</hi>. The weakness of his health added a reason of great cogency why they should acquiesce in decisions, which they disliked and resented.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[195] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>August 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925.</p>
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ryle,</p>
         <p>Today I read in the papers the news which I have been fearing &amp; expecting for many weeks past. The long weakness &amp; suffering have reached an end; and he is at peace. I must send you a few lines of deep &amp; affectionate sympathy. I am recalling my own connexion with him, &amp; there is nothing in it throughout but what is good to remember. He with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge</hi> stayed with me on Feb. 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>. 1918 when I was consecrated in the Abbey: &amp; I always felt assured on his friendship. He will be widely &amp; deeply regretted. In these dark &amp; difficult times his gentle wisdom was invaluable. I suspect that his personal influence was effective over a far larger area than he himself suspected. He <hi rend="underline">is taken away from the evil to come.</hi> In Church &amp; State the new prevailing forces were not such as he liked or trusted. <hi rend="underline">Your</hi> loss I may not speak of. "<hi rend="underline">The heart knoweth its own bitterness</hi>", and One other knows it: &amp; he can comfort also. May God Himself bless &amp; strengthen you in this time of sorrows!</p>
         <p>Believe me, most sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pease from Darlington came to tea: she was very vehement against the Government for yielding to the Trade Unions. Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> arrived during the afternoon, &amp; (in spite of the lumbago) I took him for a walk in the Park. It is an astonishing evidence of the strength of party attachments that he is quite keenly on the side of the Government in spite of the fact that its surrender to the Trade Unions violates his principles as well political as economic. I think, however, that he greatly underrates the unpopularity which the Government has brought upon itself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to place tennis. He gives an excellent account of the new Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's, Spennymoor. He appears to be winning the hearts of the people. The fact that he is unmarried makes it possible for him to bring the people to the Vicarage more freely than his married predecessor could do. An anonymous communication, inspired by my article in the "<hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>" of last Wednesday, ends by describing the Church of England as 'the Ishmael among the churches'. Save for the exceptional isolation in which she stands, it is, perhaps, difficult to see any fitness in the description, save perhaps where the Sectaries come in!</p></body></text></TEI>