<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[244]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Why should it be so strangely difficult to speak about Religion? There is not, indeed, much difficulty about using the current coin of religious phrase, and satisfying the ear of the church–going public by a rehearsal of welcome &amp; familiar platitudes. But, then this is no more than a hallow convention, which implies no conviction in the preacher, and quickens no conscience in the congregation. To speak sincerely, intelligibly, and helpfully about Religion becomes, I think, increasingly difficult. There is an initial problem to be solved viz. to discover in what language to address the people. For there is small likelihood of edification, if preacher &amp; congregation move on different planes of thought &amp; feeling, using dialects of the spirit which are mutually intelligible. Yet, this is precisely what I feel to be the case when I preach. The meanings which I place on familiar words are not those which (I suspect) my bearers are placing on them. They do not understand, because they do not share. The emotions which are dominating me. There are no common terms between us. This alienation is at its worst when I preach to a congregation of which I know nothing.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[245]</hi></p>
         <p>I put together a few notes on the two texts:–</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">I see that all things come to an end, but thy commandment is exceeding broad</hi>", and "<hi rend="underline">The world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever</hi>": and I preached in the Chapel of Sandbeck House to a congregation of servants and tenants. Lord S. thanked me for my sermon: &amp;, of, course, Lady S. was foolishly effusive. I was more pleased by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow's</hi> approval. <hi rend="bold underline">Having no episcopal robes with me, I preached in my walking dress</hi>.</p>
         <p>The chaplain and his bunch came to lunch: and afterwards Lord S. motored Hadow and me to the ruins of Roche Abbey. These have now been handed over to the card of the Board of Works, and considerable excavations have been made. <hi rend="bold underline">Hadow and I had much conversation on ecclesiastical affairs. We are mainly in agreement, but, or course, he cannot realize, as I must needs do, the extent to which the influence of the Church of England has declined</hi>. His characteristic optimism blinds him to facts which I cannot ignore, and he is not forced, as I am, to see at close range the personnel of the clergy.</p></body></text></TEI>