<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[236]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant fine morning, with the bite of incipient winter in the air. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> assisted. We numbered 8 communicants. I preached at Mattins in South Church to a congregation which may have numbered 150 persons, of whom certainly not more than 40 were grown males even when clergy &amp; choirmen are reckoned in the number! And yet this parish is said to contain 16,000 people! There is, indeed, another (small) church, &amp; 3 mission rooms, but all of them are said to be very badly attended. It is a disconcerting spectacle. </p>
         <p>Ernest and I walked round the Park with the dogs. Then I wrote to Malcom Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName> telling him that I had appointed Duncan to the parish of Dawndon. This seemed to me a judicious proceeding, as Dillon is said to have pressed another man very strongly! </p>
         <p>I wrote to Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> approving his article in the C.E.N., and telling him the disconcerting account of Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> which I received from Bainbridge. It occurred to me that possibly <hi rend="underline">he</hi> might give Barnes a friendly hint on the subject. But I suspect that Barnes is a man who does not take good advice easily. There is a strain of obstinacy in him which may on occasion develops quickly into what the Americans call "pure cussedness"! </p></body></text></TEI>