<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[247]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from the Archbishop of Canterbury asking <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and me to be his guests at Lambeth during the next meeting of the House of Bishops. "It would be a great help to us if you can". Now what does this mean? Is it a characteristic attempt to clip my wings by bringing me into a situation in which my freedom would be small? Certainly I should be ill&#8211;placed for independent action if I were actually living under the Archbishop's roof when I desired to take it. Of course, Ella is eager to go to London, and, in other circumstances, her wishes would rightly weigh with me: but here are issues of public duty at stake, &amp; I must not let any merely personal consideration affect my course. I cannot doubt that the Archbishop has already determined the course which he will pursue; and that that course will be of the same type as heretofore. It will seek to minimize the risk of a serious crisis, by avoiding the central issue, and fastening attention on details: and his method of getting his way will be the old familiar method of manipulating individuals, persuading this man to silence, &amp; that one to acquiescence! But, if it be the case, (and I must needs think that it is the case,) that every postponement of the central issue prejudices the ultimate solution of our problem, then I must not lend myself to all this.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[248]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I declined his Grace's invitation, availing myself of the conventional plea of "a previous engagement</hi><hi rend="bold">"</hi> but phrasing it oleaginously.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Surtees</hi>, the Rector of Brancepeth, came to see me about the appointment to Willington, of which he is patron. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rainbow</hi> brought <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald</hi> to see me in spite of the rain.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cliffe Cock</hi> went off after breakfast, and I worked, not very effectively, on the Article.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came to report himself after his holiday in France. He is eager, affectionate, and devout. If he has the mental power requisite for his examinations, and the staying power indispensable for pastoral work, he ought to do well. But I dare not be too sanguine, for my experience of Ordination candidates does not authorize optimism.</p>
         <p>I borrowed from Sandbeck a horrible book about Russia – "<hi rend="underline">From the Two&#8211;headed Eagle to the Red Flag 1894&#8211;1921 by General P. N. Krassnoff in 4 volumes, Brentano's Ltd. London</hi>. It gives a luridly realistic account of the Russian Revolution. The translation is execrably made, but it may be literal enough. It is repulsive, but has the ring of truth. The Russian people was a blend of decadence and savagery.</p></body></text></TEI>