<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in sermon&#8211;preparation, and the writing of letters. I wrote to Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName>. After lunch, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Satley, and there I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dermid to the Vicarage. The little church was two&#8211;thirds filled with a congregation, largely composed of children, which coughed relentlessly throughout. A hurricane of wind escorted us going &amp; returning, &amp;, on our return journey, was accompanied by a fierce rain&#8211;storm.</p>
         <p>Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> arrived about 7 p.m. to stay the week&#8211;end. He has been travelling in the Levant, &amp; is full of enthusiasm for what he has seen.</p>
         <p>Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> sends to ask for my emendation of the Article about Confirmation. I think the following might suffice:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is the custom of the Church of England to defer Confirmation until those who have been baptised in infancy have been instructed in the faith, and are able intelligently &amp; responsibly to take (publicly) upon themselves their obligations as members of Christ Church.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I think the two elements of instruction in the faith and responsible profession of membership should be stated.</p></body></text></TEI>