<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[209]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><persName xml:id="4032"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Henry Craik</hi><persName xml:id="344"></persName> went off by the midday train. The former was born on Dec. 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1849, &amp; will shortly complete 76 years of age: the latter was born on Oct. 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1846, &amp; will soon complete 79 years. Both are astonishingly alert and vigourous. But why do I find myself more in harmony with the generation older than myself, than with my contemporaries &amp; juniors? </p>
         <p>The Archdeacon of Lindisfarne and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mangin came to lunch. Also Hugh Lyon and his wife.</p>
         <p>A certain M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hugh F. Spender, wrote to me from Switzerland criticising my article on "Prohibition &amp; Personal Liberty", which appeared in the 'Westminster Gazette', and enclosing a long "reply" from an American named, rather suggestively, Tipple! I wrote a brief answer, and copied it into my 'Register'.</p>
         <p>Then I set to work on the task of reducing my table to order. The books on 'Spiritual Healing' etc. (which had been bought together for my book) were transferred to my dressing room: <hi rend="underline">&amp; I proceeded to destroy a number of letters. It is, of course, wholly improbable that anyone will be concerned in producing a Biography, for which letters might serve as material, &amp; I have no son or other relation who would value anything of mine out of a personal affection for me. Why, then, should I be at the pains either to preserve letters, or to continue this account of my daily proceedings? Why, indeed?</hi></p></body></text></TEI>
