<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I heard "Judith" an oratorio, performed at the Lock. Some parts of it were exceedingly fine: but there are two things in all modern pieces of music, which I could never reconcile to common sense. One is, singing the same words ten times over; the other, singing different words by different persons at one and the same time. And this, in the most solemn addresses to God, whether by way of prayer or of thanksgiving. This can never be defended by all the musicians in Europe, till reason is quite out of date.</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Journal March 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1764</p>
         </div>
         <p>Here John Wesley utters the mind of the great majority of English folk: and the fact explained the unpopularity of anthems except among choirmen &amp; organists.</p>
         <p>I completed revising the MS. of the book, and re&#8211;wrote the concluding passage. It is a poor performance. The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. Holliday, Vicar of Hamsterley, came to see me, about the redemption of his "fell&#8211;rents", which amount to about &#x00A3;13 per annum, &amp; paid by custom. He stayed to lunch.</p>
         <p>The Ordination Candidates – 3 deacons &amp; 2 priests – arrived in time for Evensong at 7 p.m. Davison of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, Auckland, gave an excellent address. After dinner we all walked in the garden, the weather being very warm and still.</p></body></text></TEI>