<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[250]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in my room working at the Article. Then I lunched in the Buttery, where I found Grant Robertson, whose loquacity (which was always considerable, and has now become torrential) made reasonable conversation difficult. Then I put together a few notes for a marriage&#8211;address, &amp; went to S. Mary's. The ceremony took place in the Chancel, which was filled by the relatives of the bride &amp; bridegroom. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Richards read the abbreviated preface, I tied the knot, &amp; Johnson took the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd </hi>part of the service. Then I gave the address, and added a Benediction, &amp; the function ended. There were no hymns, &amp; no bridesmaids, but the chancel was prettily decorated with flowers, &amp; there was an atmosphere of much goodwill. The reception was held in the Codrington Library, &amp; there was a great concourse, from which I escaped as soon as I could. The Poet Laureate was introduced to me, &amp; started talking about the necessity of a new morality, since the morality of Christianity was plainly exhausted!! I walked to Christ Church, &amp; called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi><persName xml:id="250"></persName>, whom I found in his study. He promised to put together a list of books for this volume of the Home and University Library which I was fool enough to promise, &amp; which will, I fear, <hi rend="underline">never</hi> be completed. I dined in College.</p></body></text></TEI>