<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[103]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The sixteenth century, as a century of ideas, real, grand, and numerous, is not to be compared with the thirteenth: the ideas are not so pure, not so living, nor so refined: the men are not so earnest, so single&#8211;hearted, so loveable by far. Much doubtless had been gained in strength of purpose, and much in material progress: but compare the one set of men with the other as men, and the ideas are ideas, &amp; the advantage is wonderfully in favour of the semi&#8211;barbarous age, above that of the Renaissance and the Reformation.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bp. Stubbs</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Lectures on Eur. Hist</hi>. p. 2. </p>
         </div>
         <p>Is this a just or an intelligent judgment? Does it not rather reflect the strong preference for the earlier age which Bishop Stubbs did undoubtedly possess? The 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century was marked by everything he cared for most in the Church &amp; State: the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> disclosed all that he most feared and disliked. The one was the crown of medievalism: the other was the fontal spring of modernism. Bishop Stubbs by temperament, conviction, habit, and interest was a thorough&#8211;going medievalist.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[104]</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the castle at 1.35 p.m., &amp; motored to Halifax by way of Catterick, Ripon, Harrogate, &amp; Bradford, arriving at 4.45 p.m. Bishop Frodsham &amp; his family received us at the Vicarage, a large house of which part dates from Queen Anne. At 7.45 p.m. there was a great "<hi rend="underline">Service of Thanksgiving for the ancient parish of Halifax</hi>". The old parish church is a large building in the perpendicular style, accommodating, as I was assured, 2000 people on the floor. The clergy, churchwardens, and choirs of all the dependent parishes attended The acoustics of the church are good, so I did not find it difficult to deliver the sermon, and, as I was fold, succeeded in making myself heard throughout the building I was not well&#8211;impressed by the behaviour of the choir&#8211;boys in the Vestry. Bishop Frodsham does not appear to be a good disciplinarian: he exhorts where he ought to command: and he thanks the officers of the Church for performing their functions. I turned in his offertory book to the record of Easter. The number of communicants hardly exceeded 400 out of a population of 8000. Yet Bishop Frodsham did not seem to be either concerned or disconcerted by the fact: he spoke confidently of "making Halifax what Leeds was under Hook"!</p></body></text></TEI>