<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to the Temple Church at 8.30 a.m. and received the Holy Communion. There were, perhaps, as many as a dozen communicants. At 11 a.m. I went again to the Church for Mattins, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; preached to a large congregation from "Heal the Sick", repeating substantially what I said at Manchester about Hickson's doctrine, that the original Commission of the Church included physical healing. The attention was close, and I think the people were interested.</hi> After service Lord Desart, the Treasurer, of the Inner Temple took me to lunch. Lord Darling<persName xml:id="4032"></persName> was there, &amp;, as usual, very friendly. I sate between Lady Jersey and Lady Desart. The first was keen about Socialist Sunday Schools, and the last was full of the ill deeds of the Irish Papists, who burned down L<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> Desart's ancestral home, &amp; behaved abominably. After lunch we went into the Library; I was interested to see the greatly enlarged reproduction of Parnell's signature, and Piggott's forged version of it. After lunch I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Then I called at S. Paul's Deanery, but found both Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> absent.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Returning to the Temple, I found the Master entertaining one How, a relative of the Dean's, who had just returned from Greece. He insisted on the difference of the Athenians and the rural Greeks, greatly to the disadvantage of the former.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I dined at the Travellers' Club with M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Rawlinson M.P. for Cambridge University</hi><hi rend="italic">. He admitted so frankly that he had been mistaken in supporting the Enabling Act that I could not but relinquish the resentment which his behaviour had provoked. We had a most interesting talk. He had been in charge of the inquiry into the American psychologist, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Homer Lane's</hi><hi rend="italic">, conduct of the 'Little Republic'. He said that the man's guilt was beyond reasonable question: that the whole arrangements of the institution were shameless, &amp; that, he believed, the man to be a mesmerist.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">The Bishop of Liverpool</hi><hi rend="italic"> made an ill impression in the witness&#8211;box, &amp; was evidently a foolish person. He thought that the whole episode could not but react unfortunately on the bishop's influence in his diocese. We drove back to the Temple about 11 p.m. and parted in high good&#8211;humour!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>