<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[229]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Preaching is a principal part of governing, and Christ himself ruleth his church by his word. Hereby bishops shall govern hearts, and make men yield unto them a true and willing obedience, reverencing God in them. Many in consumptions have recovered their healths by returning to their native air, wherein they were born. If episcopacy be in any declination or diminution of honour, the going back to the painfulness of the primitive Fathers in preaching, is the only way to repair it.</p>
         <p>Fuller. "The Good Bishop' A.D. 1640 v. 'Holy &amp; Profane State' p. 263.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Fuller offers as illustrations of "the good bishop" two men – S. Augustine and Bishop Ridley. But neither of these excellent men is easily imitated by a modern bishop.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon, Gerald and I motored to Staindrop, and looked at the parish church: then, we went on to Barnard Castle, and visited the Bowes Museum. Among the Turner drawings, which are now being exhibited there, is a very interesting sketch of Durham. We got back to the Castle in good time for tea.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We shall understand little of Bolshevism unless we clearly realise that Communism is much more than an economic doctrine or a political system; that in strict and literal truth the Communist sect is an organised religious community, provided with all the organs &amp; the characteristics which distinguish other institutional religions. Communism has its Holy Scriptures – namely, the writings of Karl Marx – which are revealed, inspired &amp; infallible. It has its commentators &amp; scholastics, its prophets &amp; its martyrs. It has its body of dogmas, its orthodoxies, &amp; its heresies. It has its Ecumenical Councils &amp; International Congresses, its rituals &amp; its symbols, its processes of initiation &amp; excommunication. It has its promises of salvation, its millennial hopes, its schemes of rewards and punishments, its paradise &amp; its hell. Like Christianity, it claims a universal character, it inspires its followers with a fanatical devotion, and like Mohammedanism, its [sic] promulgates its doctrines with the sword.</p>
         <p>Sarolea. Impressions of Soviet Russia. p. 64.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[230]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Shadwell</hi><persName xml:id="30"></persName>, inviting his opinion on my project of an introductory article in "the Bishoprick". <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi><persName xml:id="5358"></persName> called in the course of the morning with reference to Sir C. Harrington's visit to Shildon. I wrote to invite the General to put up at the Castle. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Dobson</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">James Duncan</hi> lunched here, &amp; talked with me about their several plans of work. After they had gone, I took <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald</hi> for a walk round the Park. Then I motored to Sunderland, picking up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> on the way. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="2841"></persName> went with me to act as my staff&#8211;bearer. We had a meal at Bishopwearmouth Rectory, &amp; then went to S. Stephen's, Ayres Quay, where I admitted the Rev. <hi rend="doubleunderline">E. Yates Moore</hi> to the perpetual curacy, which had been vacated by the resignation of the drunken reprobate <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry</hi>. There was a large congregation, &amp; a considerable gathering of the Sunderland clergy. The service was solemn &amp; significant. Before starting homewards, I went in to the Institute where some kind of a parochial reception had been arranged, &amp; there I spoke a few words. We were back in Auckland by 9.45 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Carmichael</hi>, (erstwhile <hi rend="doubleunderline">Winnifred Webster</hi>) had arrived on a short visit.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Viviani, formerly Prime Minister of France, is reported to have died</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> He is said to have been a really good orator. He was also an aggressive atheist.</p></body></text></TEI>