<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[90]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The Archbishop of York and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Page&#8211;Gourlay went off after breakfast. I wrote to that strange clergyman, Hodgson<persName xml:id="5274"></persName> of Escombe, telling him politely not to make a fool of himself. Then I gave a final revision to so much of the Book as had been copied.</p>
         <p>Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> wrote to me an ardent, affectionate letter about his decision to be ordained. We must now face the matter of his preparation. </p>
         <p>The Vicar designate of Castle Eden came to inform me of the reasons why he had withdrawn his acceptance of the living. It appears that the income is no more than &#x00A3;349: that of this &#x00A3;50 is an annual contribution from Colonel Busdon which may be withdrawn at the donor's pleasure: that the Rectory is extremely dilapidated, &amp; costs much to keep up. He appears to have heard disconcerting accounts of the patron, and the patron's wife. The one forgets his promises, &amp; the other oppresses the parson!</p>
         <p>I ordered M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> George Waine to set up the new Boiler of 75 gallons capacity at a cost of &#x00A3;57.10.0. This with the boiler which has been already placed for &#x00A3;23: makes a large &amp; quite unforeseen expenditure. The sixpence off the income tax will be exhausted by "extraordinary" items, which had not come into my calculations. Jimmie's preparation for Holy Orders will certainly cost money.</p></body></text></TEI>