<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[220]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A fresh set of proofs arrived, which I corrected and returned to the publishers. Among the letters was one from Tom Hay, pleasantly written, and signed "Yours affectionately". Why should I interest myself in youngsters of his age, who are coming on to the scene, which I must soon be leaving? If that infant had lived, I should have had a lad in whom interest would have been a duty as well as an interest: but now? Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> and I mounted the hill to the hut, from which the range of hills were to be seen in rare beauty. After lunch, Miss Haldane<persName xml:id="1386"></persName> took us to a large house near to Stirling, where Sir K. Muir lives. His wife is a Bulgarian, the daughter of the Bulgarian ambassador, a tall, slim, dark&#8211;eyed, mystery&#8211;laden woman, such as the Slav race produces. Her sister was there, a handsome but rather sinister lady, whom one could with little difficulty imagine in the r&#x00F4;le of a Charlotte Corday! Both ladies talked with freedom and intelligence about their own country. They expressed great fear of Russia: much hatred of Roumania &amp; Greece: much confidence in the Bulgarian peasantry, and much contempt for the Orthodox Church. <hi rend="bold underline">Lady Muir is a great friend of Miss Buchanan, the daughter of the late Sir George Buchanan<persName xml:id="4148"></persName>. She asked me about Harold Knowling<persName xml:id="113"></persName>, who was, she said, now married to Miss Buchanan! Her sister pursued the subject, speaking with evidently strong</hi><hi rend="bold">[221]</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> dislike of Harold who was, in her belief, a bad &amp; vulgar but clever man. She said that he placed the blame of his divorce on Elsie. I could not but observe that he had himself written to me stating that he was himself solely blameworthy in the matter, and that his desertion of his 3 charming children was unpardonable. The news of Harold's "marriage" shuts the door on every possibility of reconciliation with Elsie<persName xml:id="2056"></persName>. What a miserable tangle has been created! No marriage ever started with such fair promise – mutual love, youth, some congruous tastes (e.g. music), sufficient means, good health, and then, in due course, strong &amp; attractive children: and yet, all has worked out to this woeful disaster</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The view of Donne Castle was very striking: &amp; the vast dimensions of the Hotel at Glen&#8211;eagles compelled our wonder.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Edmund &amp; Lady Gosse arrived</hi>, and his ceaseless prattle amused and, perhaps, fatigued the company. He tells me that he is 77 years old, seven years older than our host. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName> is certainly in appearance and, I suspect, in mind older than his years: but he has taken much out of himself in the course of his life. He talked with vivacity of his political &amp; legal experiences, and told some capital stories. Before going to bed he asked <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph</hi> and me to witness his will. An ominous sign!</p></body></text></TEI>