<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[121]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went off after breakfast. I spent the morning in writing letters, revising sermons, &amp; interviewing an Ordination candidate named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Savage</hi>, who aspires to be ordained at Advent. Then, after an early lunch, I motored to Darlington, and took train for King's Cross. <hi rend="underline">My compagnon de voyage was a young man named Thomas Hay, who was journeying to London to be examined in Chemisry by the University. We had much conversation, &amp; I invited him to propose himself for a visit to Auckland. Probably I shall never see him again.</hi></p>
         <p>N.B. T.H. wrote to me, &amp; we exchanged several letters before the year ended. My letter in support of Lord Durham's<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> appeal appeared in the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi>. I read through an account of <hi rend="underline">Henrietta Countess of Oxford</hi> (1694&#8211;1755) by the Librarian of Welbeck, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. W. Goulding.</p>
         <p>Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> carried us off to the Savoy Hotel, London, where 'Independence Day' was celebrated by a Banquet over which the American Ambassador presided. It was a terribly dull business until it merged into absurdities which would have seemed in a Bethnal Green "smoker". The speech of the evening was delivered by the Hon. Nicholas <hi rend="doubleunderline">Longworth</hi>, Speaker of the House of Representatives, who is son&#8211;in&#8211;law to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Roosevelt</hi>. I was terribly bored, &amp; glad to get away.</p></body></text></TEI>