<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Charles had stood at the head of Christendom for forty years, at such a height above other princes, both in power and fortune and character, that nothing but national vanity can account for the comparison between him and Henry viii, or between him and Francis I.</p>
         <p>Stubbs. Lectures. p. 142</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the morning in clearing up my room, &amp; writing some acceptance letters, &amp; then, after an early lunch, I motored to Darlington, &amp; caught the train leaving at 1.5 p.m. which brought me to King's Cross at 6.15 p.m. I went at once to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, where I was received by Archdeacon<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Charles.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There came to dinner mine host's brother, a surgeon of distinction, who had been entrusted with the care of their Majesties when they visited India, and spoke in terms of great admiration of the Queen</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Charles told us a strange yarn about the appointment of Studdart Kennedy<persName xml:id="5432"></persName> to a Westminster Canonry, &amp; its frustration by his efforts. Her Majesty seems to have set her heart on the appointment, and have been reconciled with difficulty to its cancellation. One must make deductions on ethnical grounds!</p></body></text></TEI>