<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I believe that the future of religion is intimately bound up with the fate of Animism; and especially I believe that, if science should continue to maintain the mechanistic dogma, and consequently to repudiate Animism, the belief in any form of life after the death of the body will continue rapidly to decline among all civilized peoples ntity.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">W. M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Dougall</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Body &amp;Mind</hi>. Preface.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I worked at the Book. If but I could take a year over it, I might say what I want to say, but as it is, I cannot. After lunch Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I walked to the Binchester Crags. </p>
         <p>The papers announce the death of two sisters, aged respectively 85 and 84 – M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> G. Talbot &amp; Lady Frederick Cavendish. We have travelled far since the Phoenix Park Murders in 1882 startled the country.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Trade Unions appear determined to "join up" with the Russian Communists.</hi> All the generous speaking, which commands the enthusiastic approval of the Churches, seems to have no effect whatever on the policy of "Labour".</p>
         <p>I wrote to Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>, once more suggesting that he should be ordained. <hi rend="bold underline">Elsie<persName xml:id="2056"></persName> sent me Rex's<persName xml:id="2799"></persName> photograph.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>