<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Today I enter upon "the sixth year of translation" from Hereford to Durham. My faults &amp; blunders have been many, but even my severest critick must allow that the times have been unpropitious, &amp; circumstances hostile. The economic crisis has steadily deepened all the time until now we seem on the brink of a definite collapse of the main local industries. Diocesan finance has been rendered greatly more difficult: and the obsession of the public mind has rendered the fulfilment of spiritual duty more than commonly difficult. These five years have witnessed the introduction of the new system of ecclesiastical organisation created by the Enabling Act. This has added gratuitously to the many difficulties of the time. The almost complete failure of Ordination Candidates has created a situation which is almost deadlock, &amp; which must speedily become so. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> has been with me all the time, and has drawn so many threads of diocesan administration into his hands that his approaching departure fills me with dismay. If I could solve the problem of finding candidates for Ordination, I would fear nothing. But <hi rend="underline">that</hi> failure threatens collapse of everything.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The papers report that Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> was the subject of a hostile demonstration when he showed himself at the Miners' Demonstration in Durham on Saturday. He was hustled, his hat lost, &amp; finally was got away by the police in a launch. This is a very unfortunate occurrence. As far as Welldon himself is concerned, he only gets his deserts. He has given abundant provocation by his incessant &amp; untimely talking: &amp; his folly in appearing at the demonstration was in all circumstances gross. To me, probably, the consequences are more serious for it means, not only a great enhancement of personal risk for (unlike the Dean) the Bishop has to be continually moving about the diocese, &amp; hostile demonstrations in mining villages are not unlikely, but also, &amp; this is more serious, a destruction of potential influence. My article in the 'Evening Standard' was necessarily difficult for the miners to accept, but (in spite of Cook's denunciation) I think it would have been accepted, &amp; is certainly capable of defence: but when read, as it needs must be read, in the light of the Dean's speeches &amp; interviews, it becomes simply, from the miners' point of view, offensive. Moreover, all the blame of his provocations will be carried to my account. The whole business is most regrettable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>If the Church of England becomes in general what it already is in some of its churches, it is not likely that English public opinion will permanently acquiesce in its privileged position in the State. If it ceases to be a Protestant Church, it will not long remain an established one, &amp; its disestablishment would probably be followed by a disruption in which opinions would be more sharply defined, and the latitude of belief and the spirit of compromise that now characterise our English religious life might be seriously impaired.</p>
         <p>Lecky. "The Map of Life". p. 234</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Bryan's sudden death is announced. It has followed closely on his amazing display of obscurantist fanaticism</hi>. How will it be interpreted? As the orthodox interpreted the sudden death of Arius? Or, as the Kensitites interpret the death of the fanatical buffoon whose name they carry? It is at any rate a sufficiently dramatic epilogue to the country theatre of Dainton! Fanaticism sucks nutriment from every variety of fortune, &amp; I doubt not this champion's death will simulate his followers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[154]</hi></p>
         <p>The publishers (Hodder &amp; Stoughton) send me an advance copy of another presumably didactic novel by Hutchinson, the author of "If winter comes". This also purports to exhibit th puzzlement of the post&#8211;bellum mind. Its hero, Simon Paris is a slightly less muddle&#8211;pated &amp; unfortunate edition of Mark Sabre.</p>
         <p>The weather changed, and there was rain at intervals throughout the day. There was a fall in the temperature, though the atmosphere continued to be thunderous &amp; heavy.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> arrived shortly after 6 p.m.</p>
         <p>Enormous pressure is evidently being brought to bear on the mine&#8211;owners in order to compel them to "withdraw" the proposals which they have advanced. This they will not do unless it shall have been made quite clear that 'withdrawal' does not imply 'abandonment', still less 'repudiation': for they are still convinced that, if the mining interest is to be made remunerative, these proposals are indispensable. Can they be blamed? I do not think so. The situation is too serious to allow of any more make&#8211;belief. It is an easy &amp; obvious attitude to assume that mine&#8211;owners and miners are <hi rend="underline">equally</hi> unreasonable and obstinate: but is it also just or helpful or prudent? After all, there is such a thing as economic law.</p></body></text></TEI>