<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[80]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Feb. 26. [1769] The 36 Psalm was sung this afternoon in Cary Church by the Singers. Done out of Pique to old Willm. Burge. Old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Burge concerns himself too much with the singers.</p>
         <p>Dec. 17. [1769] The Singers of Cary did not please me this afternoon by singing the 12 Psalm, New Version, reflecting upon some people.</p>
         <p>v.Diary of a Country Parson, the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. Woodforde 1758&#8211;1781. pp. 84, 95. </p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a curious exhibition of independence by a village choir in the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. It argues a considerable knowledge of the Psalms, as well as an impudent readiness to apply them to unpalatable persons. Undoubtedly a piquant would attach to the choice of psalms in public worship when once it was realized that it had a personal reference. The incumbent seems to have had no control of the choice, which was apparently made by general agreement of the choirmen. Even the most thorough&#8211;going champions of parochial democracy now hardly go to the length of claiming control of the service for the choirmen: but, as M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Asquith would say, 'we are getting on'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I began the day by "hoisting the white flag" in the matter of going to Cambridge in order to dine at Corpus Christi College in memory of the death of Matthew Parker, 350 years ago. But I did not feel equal to the journey, to say nothing of the festal dinner.</hi> So I telegraphed to the Master, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Will Spens</hi> who was to have been mine host, following up the telegram by apologetic letters. Then I spent the whole morning in reading the report of <hi rend="underline">Birth&#8211;Control Commission</hi>. It doesn't amount to much, but its general effect is decisively adverse to the practice.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went off for a short holiday. I hope he may succeed in coming to some arrangement with the Bishop of Salisbury, whom he is to visit before he returns.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I had tea under the copper beach [sic], very pleasantly. The day was warm and windless. I amused myself by reading "<hi rend="underline">The Diary of a Country Parson, the Reverend James Woodforde, 1758&#8211;1781</hi>" edited by <hi rend="doubleunderline">John Beresford</hi>, &amp; published by the Oxford Press. It covers the same period as that which Wesley's <hi rend="underline">Journal</hi> covers, &amp; casts an interesting side&#8211;light on the state of the Established Church at the time when the Methodist movement was at flood&#8211;tide. On the whole the picture is far more favourable than the common estimate of the XVIII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century would suggest.</p></body></text></TEI>