<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Neither the 'Church Times' nor the 'Guardian' makes the smallest allusion to the meeting of the Worcester Diocesan Conference! This silence can hardly be accidental, or unintentional. The method of ignoring me altogether alternates with that of violent insult. What matter? If one could only placate one's own conscience, one w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> snap one's fingers at the world. I wrote letters including one to Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>, whose birthday is tomorrow.</p>
         <p>At 10.30 a.m. we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Miss Pearce, &amp; I) left the Castle &amp; motored by way of Tenbury &amp; Leominster to Hereford (45 miles). We arrived at 12.30 noon, &amp; lunched at the Palace. After lunch we went to the Cathedral, &amp; were shown the memorial chapel, &amp; the new painted windows. Then I went to Lilley &amp; talked with him until tea&#8211;time<hi rend="bold">.</hi><hi rend="bold underline">After tea we returned to Hartlebury</hi>, via Malvern &amp; Worcester, (43 miles). The weather was perfect, and the country, in the fresh beauty of spring was superb. I took the 'Guardian', &amp; read through the report of Archbishop Lang's address to his Diocesan Conference. It is eloquent enough, but, of course, entirely in the interest of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, with whom his Grace is essentially agreed.</p></body></text></TEI>