<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I made a vain attempt to get speech with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, who was about to go to Mattins in the Abbey when I called. He says that the "<hi rend="underline">Call to Action</hi>" has made a solitary flutter. I called on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Downing</hi> at the Ecclesiastical Commission's Office. He asked me what manner of man the Vicar of Escombe might be, since he had written in very insolent terms to Sir A. Wood! I could but tell him to ignore <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi><persName xml:id="5274"></persName> altogether. I have certainly some strange clergymen in this diocese. I went to Hugh Rees, and bought a few books. Then I went to King's Cross, and caught the 1.15 p.m. express to Darlington. The train was inconveniently full. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and Leng met me at Darlington. On arriving at the Palace, we got to work on the letters, of which there was a considerable accumulation.</p>
         <p>The difficulties of episcopal office are intensifying, and they all run back to two facts – the cleavage in the Church disclosed by the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, and the failure of the supply of Ordination Candidates. The first paralyzes discipline: the last arrests work. What the situation will be in five years' time I hardly dare contemplate. The only consolation I can discern is the certainty that there must be some decisive change in the present intolerable position.</p></body></text></TEI>