<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>As for Pronunciation, <hi rend="bold underline">you know Protestants make their Celebration in a tongue known unto all the people communicating, and in a loud voice, according to the universal practice of the Church of Christ in primitive times</hi>, as hath been confessed. So that the People's ears may be their own witnesses, whether the words of Consecration, either by Prayer, or together with the form of Repetition of the words of Institution, be truly delivered: which freeth them from your Romish perplexity of not knowing whether the Priest hath truly Consecrated, by his muttering the words in an inaudible voice.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Morton</hi><persName xml:id="4636"></persName><hi rend="underline">. On the Eucharist</hi>. A.D. 1610</p>
         </div>
         <p>Bishop Morton would not have satisfied our Anglo&#8211;Catholics. His view of the Mass left no place for misunderstanding, and he was nowise ashamed of being a Protestant.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; attended a meeting of the Chapter. The reason for my attending was the terrible state of the capitular finances which – it was suggested – would make my scheme for re&#8211;constituting the Foundation, all but impractical. But the Statement of the Treasurer <hi rend="bold">[98] </hi>showed that the income was improving, &amp; that in 20 years' time, the Fabric Fund, which has been exhausted by the expenditure on the Tower, would have been restored. There was, then, nothing more to be said. I refrained from pointing out that I had been brought to the Chapter on a fool's errand. But that was indeed the case!</p>
         <p>Picking up Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> I motored to Whickham, &amp; there lunched with Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> Thompson. The churchwarden, M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Glass was there. He is a mining manager, &amp; spoke very intelligently about the mining situation. At 3 p.m. I instituted the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M. H. Huthwaite</hi> to the Rectory. There was a considerable and attentive congregation. After the service I went to the Parish Hall, where the new Rector was formally welcomed. Then I had tea, and came away. I don't know what to think of this parson, that he means well is certain, but he has an almost grotesque appearance, &amp; has had no parochial experience. We got back to Auckland a few minutes after 6 p.m. Thus practically the whole day was frittered away. <hi rend="italic">I found a letter from Sir I. Marchant inviting me to write a volume on "the Future of the Church of England"! I declined for I am too busy, and I am not confident that the Church of England has a future!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>