<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[179]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather being wet and tempestuous the expedition to the wall which I ha planned fpr my guests was abandoned. I spent the morning on writing letters, for Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> having gone off for his holidays I had to do everything myself, and in preparing notes on the <hi rend="underline">Thirty&#8211;nine Articles</hi>, which had been suggested as the subject of an <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> Article. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><persName xml:id="1082"></persName> and I walked round the Park during the afternoon.</p>
         <p>L<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> General Sir Aylmer Hunter&#8211;Weston &amp; his wife called about tea time, &amp; were shown the Castle. </p>
         <p>Some more proofs arrived from Williams &amp; Norgate.</p>
         <p>The Wine&#8211;growers' Association telegraphed to me requesting that I would allow them to republish my article on 'Prohibition' which had appeared in the '<hi rend="underline">Westminster Gazette'</hi>. It will add to the odium with which I am regarded in the world of Temperance Advocates. And, of course, an article of that kind dealing with a subject which has so many facets, and making in every paragraph assumptions which, if not reasonably disputable, are none the less likely to be hotly disputed, must needs be enormously provocative. <hi rend="bold underline">Total abstinence is really a religion to its advocates: it is also a highly organized 'movement': and a considerable vested interest.</hi> Women are its staunchest advocates, &amp; they carry into their advocacy the ardour, unreason, &amp; persistence of their sex.</p></body></text></TEI>