<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[87]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">How far is it legitimate to bring personal influence to bear on a young manin order to induce him to be Ordained</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p>Assuming that you know him well, and that your knowledge of him has led you to the opinion that he is well suited for the career of a clergyman, how far may you avail yourself of his personal affection for yourself in order to carry him to the conclusion at which you have arrived? What place in your mind can rightly be given to your own wishes in the matter? <hi rend="bold underline">All these questions press on me as I reflect on my conversation with Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>, and his consent at my instance to be ordained.</hi> His scruples were certainly such as rather confirmed my belief in his fitness for Ordination, than weakened it. His age – 23 – gave a measure of urgency to the decision in his case, for education does not grow easier as the years pass, &amp; the most urgent need of the Church at the present time is a provision of <hi rend="underline">young</hi> clergymen. <hi rend="bold underline">Then, I did not originate the idea of Ordination in his mind, for that was his ambition when at Durham School, and laid aside through his repugnance to the "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" which was pressed on him by certain clergymen. I separated the idea of Ordination from its associations, renewed it, &amp; added the influence of personal affection. After all, is not personal influence the distinctively Christian method of working conviction in men's minds? Am I not in line with Gospel precedents in using it</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p>Pemberton<persName xml:id="2837"></persName> wrote to ask for another letter for circulation to the Press in support of Lord Durham's<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> Appeal. I wrote, and sent a letter, though truly I grow weary of the subject. Then we all went to Raby, &amp; lunched with Lord Barnard<persName xml:id="5197"></persName> &amp; his wife. After lunch I opened the F&#x00EA;te in the Castle grounds which had been organised in aid of the Fund for re&#8211;casting etc the Bells of Staindrop Church. The weather was fine, and there was a large attendance.</p>
         <p>The Archbishop of York arrived about 7p.m. and I took him for a walk in the Park. We had a dinner party to meet him viz. Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight, Captain Page&#8211;Gourlay, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Braley, Professor<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cruickshank.</p>
         <p>I took occasion to speak to the Bishop of Jarrow about the possibility of Jimmie's Ordination, and asked him to be sympathetic and encouraging if J. came to him for advice about his reading.</p>
         <p>I have nearly finished Woodforde's Diary of a Country Parson, and so far I have noticed no reference whatever to Confirmation. He mentions his performance of service in his parish church, occasional services, visitations etc. but never makes an allusion to this duty, which now takes a prominent place in the scheme of parochial duty. Similarly, I have noticed no reference to Confirmation in Wesley's Journal, where it would naturally be found. </p></body></text></TEI>