<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[187]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The week&#8211;end oratory is not re&#8211;assuring. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cook</hi> calls loudly for Revolution, &amp; suggests that Joshua <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sankey</hi> has been persecuted by the classes for his sympathy with the miners. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas</hi> condemns the subsidy, but proclaims his belief in 'nationalisation' as the only way. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dobbie</hi> predicts a fierce struggle on the Railways! It is sufficiently evident that the surrender of the government was as surprising to its enemies as it was dismaying to its friends.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> sending him a copy of my letter to the Abp. The final batch of proofs arrived, were corrected, &amp; dispatched. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke Westcott</hi><persName xml:id="5385"></persName> played bowls with me, but <hi rend="bold">I was half&#8211;crippled with lumbago, which my efforts at playing made worse.</hi> Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to see me about various matters of business, of which the most important was the providing of a successor to himself. He told me that he had passed his 77<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> birthday, so that, although he is wonderful for his years, the repulsive contingency of his retirement <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be faced. He readily agreed with my suggestion that <hi rend="underline">Cecil Ferens</hi><persName xml:id="4218"></persName> should be sounded as to his willingness to undertake the work, &amp; promised himself to broach the matter to him. I authorized him to fill in the date of Talbot's resignation, &amp; to inform both Talbot &amp; the Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> secretary. This will probably come as an unwelcome surprise to Talbot himself, but I cannot keep Annfield Plain permanently vacant.</p></body></text></TEI>