<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[129]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The extent to which the supply of Ordination candidates may be affected by the decline of the Birth&#8211;rate among the clergy, whose sons have in the past provided many &amp; the best candidates, is, perhaps, illustrated by the circumstance that the Bishops, who are probably representative in this respect of the clergy as a whole are largely celibate and childless:&#8211;</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Celibates</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Childless</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">York</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Canterbury</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">London</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Durham</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Oxford</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Carlisle</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Worcester</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Winchester</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Salisbury</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Manchester</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Southwark</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Lichfield</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Truro</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">S. Alban's</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Norwich</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Bath &amp; Wells</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Gloucester</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>Here are no less than 17 bishops out of 37 who are childless. Take such a proportion throughout the clergy, &amp; it will be apparent that the hereditary character of the clerical profession is not being maintained. It is probably true that the proportion of unmarried &amp; childless men in the upper&#8211;middle class is not less among the lay than among the clerical element.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[130]</hi></p>
         <p>I walked to Westminster, &amp; spent the day in the Assembly, where a futile discussion of the everlasting question of religious education occupied us. I lunched at the Westminster Deanery: &amp; afterwards attended a Garden Party at Lambeth.</p>
         <p>The newspapers report the debate on the Mining Crisis last night in the House of Commons. <hi rend="bold underline">Ritson, one of our Labour members referred contumeliously to the Bishop of Durham, &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook announces his intention of "answering" that gentleman, whose income – as the</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Daily Herald</hi>" <hi rend="bold underline">is good enough to inform its readers is &#x00A3;7000 annually! The</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" <hi rend="bold underline">re&#8211;produced some of my article in the</hi> "<hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>", <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; no doubt other newspapers have done as much. So there are materials for a "week&#8211;end" flutter.</hi><hi rend="underline">Per contra</hi><hi rend="bold underline">our Trade&#8211;Union member, Bartle, met me at Lambeth, and volunteerd the statement that he approved what I had written</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>The Pope of Alexandria was taken ill at the dinner at which he was being entertained by his English Brethren. I inquired of Athelstan Riley<persName xml:id="213"></persName> what was the nature &amp; extent of his illness: and was informed that <hi rend="bold underline">he had lunched not wisely but too well with Lord Beauchamp earlier in the day</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>The venerable Dean of Chichester, D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hannal, was taken suddenly with a paralytic seizure yesterday in the Assembly, &amp; was with some difficulty transported from the Hall by the Archdeacon of Middlesex.</p></body></text></TEI>