<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>That man, I think, has had a liberal education who has been so trained in youth that his body is the ready servant of his will, &amp; does with ease &amp; pleasure all the work that, as a mechanism, it is capable of; whose intellect is a clear, cold, logic machine, with all its parts of equal strength and in smooth working order; ready, like a steam engine, to be turned to any kind of work, and spin the gossamers as well forge the anchors of the mind: whose mind is stored with a knowledge of the great and fundamental truths of Nature and of the laws of her operations: one who, no stunted ascetic, is full of life and fire, but whose passions are trained to come to heel by a vigorous will, the servant of a tender conscience: who has learned to love all beauty, whether of Nature or of art, to hate all vileness, and to respect others as himself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">T. H. Huxley</hi> quoted by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Julian Huxley</hi>, his grandson in a centenary notice published in the 'Observer' on May 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>, 1925.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at the book, and wrote as much as a chapter, but all woefully confused and incoherent. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> came to lunch, and talk business. He seems to get about the diocese to some effect. I walked in the Park for an hour. The weather became almost sultry.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Natural science, from being a toy for speculative minds, has become, &amp; been recognized as, one of the foundations of any civilization which we can for the present envisage. The sciences of dead matter vindicated their immense practical importance during Huxley's life&#8211;time: the sciences of living matter are now in train to achieve the same triumph. Nationalism, like a plague of boils, came to a head in country after country, but is itself producing (besides appalling wars) an internationalist anti&#8211;toxin which will moderate its violence. <hi rend="underline">The medieval scheme of thought, persisting, however totteringly and with however many modifications, in spite of shock after shock since the time of the Renaissance, has finally crashed to earth</hi>. In its place is apparent chaos. But the chaos is in reality due to the rapidity with which mankind is assembling materials for a new edifice.</p>
         <p>Julian Huxley.</p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>