<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I attended the Church of England service in the morning, and that of the Kirk in the afternoon. Truly "no man having drunk old wine, straightway desireth new". How dull and dry did the latter appear to me, who had been accustomed to the former!</p>
         <p>Wesley, Journal, may 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1772 at Edinburgh.</p>
         </div>
         <p>It is the retaining of liturgical tradition, perhaps, more than anything else that has given distinctiveness to the type of Christianity presented by the Church of England.</p>
         <p>The post brought me two interesting brochures viz:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. The State of England at the Peace of Ryswick. 1697; by Marjorie Bowen</p>
         <p>2. Sir Richard Kaye. Bart. D.C.S. Dean of Lincoln, by R. W. Golding, F.S.A. the Librarian at Wellbeck.</p>
         <p>Also a long and pleasantly written letter from Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName>.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; presided over a meeting of the Lightfoot Trustees. Then I had some talk with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> about Jimmie's<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> preparation for Ordination. Then I lunched with Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, &amp; had a talk about the capitular finance. Then I attended Evensong in the Cathedral: &amp;, afterwards, confirmed 189 candidates there. Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName> acted as my chaplain, and came back with me as far as Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"My Lord of Durham" (i.e. Richard Trevor, who became Bishop of Durham in 1752), writes Kaye, under date 30 January 1766, "told Archbishop (of York) <hi rend="underline">that he grew rich in spite of himself, for he cou'd not find means sufficient to dispose of the immense income of this See"</hi>. In the following year he again states that the Bishop avers "that he cannot prevent himself from growing rich," and he adds that he could point out to his Lordship many ecclesiastical ways and means within his own diocese of relieving himself from so much wealth".</p>
         <p>v. Goulding's "Sir Richard Kaye", p.15 </p>
         </div>
         <p>But, now, 'the wheel has gone full circle', and <hi rend="bold underline">the Bishop of Durham has to write articles for evening papers in order to find money for his private benefactions</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> It is odd to read the account of Bishop Trevor's wealth alongside that of Wesley's journeys. While the miners of Durham were totally destitute of spiritual oversight, the Bishop Palatine at Auckland Castle was worrying himself how he could spend his vast income! He added rooms to the great house, and adorned it with pictures, but he never gave a thought to the toilers who created his embarrassing wealth!</p></body></text></TEI>