<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[257]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I felt very sore and bruized in consequence of my fall. During the morning I wrote letters including one to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gamble</hi><persName xml:id="249"></persName>, who had written to ask for my <hi rend="underline">"Notes on Spiritual Healing"</hi>. I sent him the proof. From "<hi rend="underline">John O'London's Weekly</hi>", I received the proof of my fifty&#8211;guinea article on 'Religion and Science'. It is certainly not worth the money!</p>
         <p>There was a great gathering of the Mother's Union in Bishop Auckland, at which <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> played her part. A number of Israel's Matrons came in to lunch; among them the principal speaker, a dominating female named <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Boas</hi>, who claimed to have met me in Oxford 40 years ago! I hate reminiscences which occasion familiarity without creating sympathy or confidence!</p>
         <p>I took my constitutional in the Park with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> MCullagh. <hi rend="underline">He says that he saw two kingfishers in the Wear last week</hi>. What would they find to eat in that polluted stream?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter on the Abb&#x00E9; Portal's statements about the Malines Conversations appeared in the Times. It reads like the echo of a distant past, so completely have all ecclesiastical interests been submerged by the rising tide of secular anxiety</hi>. Yet since we have to tread the tiresome road of ecclesiastical activity, the issue it raises is as present &amp; pressing as ever.</p></body></text></TEI>