<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[182]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Now, who shall arbitrate?</p>
         <p>Ten men love what I hate,</p>
         <p>Shun what I follow, slight what I receive;</p>
         <p>Ten, who in ears and eyes</p>
         <p>Match me: we all surmise, </p>
         <p>They this thing, &amp; I that; whom shall</p>
         <p>my soul believe?</p>
         <p>Not on the vulgar mass</p>
         <p>Called "work", must sentence pass.</p>
         <p>Things done, that took the eye &amp; had the price:</p>
         <p>O'er which, from level stand</p>
         <p>The low world laid its hand,</p>
         <p>Found straightway to its mind, could</p>
         <p>Value in a trice;</p>
         <p>But all, the world's coarse Thumb</p>
         <p>And fingers failed to plumb,</p>
         <p>So passed in making up the main account;</p>
         <p>All instincts immature,</p>
         <p>All purposes unsure,</p>
         <p>That weighed not as his work, yet swelled</p>
         <p>the man's account.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p>Thoughts hardly to be packed</p>
         <p>Into a narrow act,</p>
         <p>Fancies that broke through language &amp; escaped,</p>
         <p>All I could never be,</p>
         <p>All, men ignored in me,</p>
         <p>This, I was work to God, whose wheel</p>
         <p>the pitcher shaped. </p>
         <p>Browning. Rabbi ben Ezra.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Acting Editor of "<hi rend="underline">John O'London's Weekly</hi>" writes to suggest that I should write an article of about 3000 words on the lines of my '<hi rend="underline">Tennessee</hi>' Article, and offers an honorarium of fifty guineas. <hi rend="bold underline">The money is tempting, &amp; would pay half the year's college expenses of J.D. I yielded to the sordid temptation, &amp; wrote to accept the proposal, promising to send the article by September 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> at the latest</hi>.</p>
         <p>Having done one rash thing, I proceeded to keep on Ossa by doing another – <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to the Archbishop about his letter to the President of the E.C.U.</hi><orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> read my letter, &amp; approved it hugely, but his judgement is as dubious as his sympathies are apparent!</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Fawkes</hi> went off by the noon&#8211;tide train. By my advice he offered Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> his controversial assistance.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p>I picked up two miners from Ferryhill, &amp; walked them round the bowling green. Then I called two young airmen – their names were Bate &amp; Stephenson, &amp; both belonged to Bishop Auckland &#8211; &amp; showed them the garden, as we were going into the Castle, General &amp; M<hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> Dudgeon arrived, and joined us. When they had gone off an Ordination candidate named arrived. He did not altogether please me, but I could see no ground for rejecting him.</p>
         <p>Duncan &amp; his wife came to lunch. I offered him the living of Dawdon in succession to Graham White, &amp; bade him talk it over with his wife, &amp; let me know his decision. If he accepts, this batch of vacancies will have been filled viz;</p>
         <p>Annfield Plain Dick replaces Talbot</p>
         <p>Monkwearmouth Hawke " Canon Brown</p>
         <p>Monkheseldon Little " Bell</p>
         <p>Hutton Henry Dobson</p>
         <p>Blackhalls Heap</p>
         <p>Colonel Burdon writes to say that he has at last found a clergyman who will accept Castle Eden. Bearpark vacated by Hawke is in the gift of the Dean &amp; Chapter: and Willington vacated by Duncan is in the gift of the Rector of Brancpeth.</p></body></text></TEI>