<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Broad in inclusion<hi rend="bold">, </hi>only because it demands but <hi rend="underline">few</hi> articles of belief, not because it is wide in theory, the Church of Common–Sense, which always tends towards the Hard Church, is the resort of the strong–minded theologians, and forms a court standing midway between the narrow crypts of Low Evangelical doctrine beneath, and the venerable decay of the High Church towers above. Its heroes are men of somewhat menacing understanding, –– not Broad Church men, if M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maurice, Dean Stanley<persName xml:id="505"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lynch, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin Brown are of the Broad Church, –– latitudinarians, but not Catholic in the tone of their theology, –– sharp and confident in their logic, –– given to browbeat their adversaries on the spot rather that to go <hi rend="underline">with</hi> them their mile, or at least up to the utmost point of common conviction, –– dry and un genial towards intellectual doubt, –– shrewd partisans, eager assailants of "extremes", and champions of that neutral precipitate of Christian theology, orthodoxy in its cooling stage.</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">R. H. Hutton</hi> "<hi rend="underline">The Hard Church</hi>" in Theological Essays: p.338 </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Lincoln Diocesan Conference seems to have been "dealing faithfully" with the Bishop of Durham!</hi> Evidently, the criticisms of the Enabling Act in "Quo tendimus?" have gone home. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName><hi rend="bold underline"> made a point when he said that I was more likely to lead a Fascisti movement, than to champion democracy. But I am quite incapable of doing either. </hi></p>
         <p>The Bishop of Winchester has given us another example of what is (in ecclesiastical circles) called "leadership" by issuing a pronouncement on <hi rend="bold underline">the Age of Confirmation</hi>. He will not confirm under 10 years of age! If an age so tender be conceded, the principle of intelligent responsibility is surrendered, &amp; there is no intrinsic reason why we should not conform to the convenient Eastern rule, &amp; make confirmation one of the ceremonies belonging to infant baptism. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> came in to tell me that his father died last night. He has been sitting up for several nights, and looks rather exhausted. </p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> brought to me a note from the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> informing me that, at his Archidiaconal Visitation in Sunderland today, the Churchwardens of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Stephen's formally presented their Vicar (Parry) for drunkenness and dishonesty! So I am in for a "discipline" case <hi rend="bold underline">within a few months of the man's arrival in the diocese 'by Exchange</hi><hi rend="bold">'.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>