<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[136]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left the Deanery of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's after breakfast, and went to King's Cross. Having deposited my bags there, I went to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; spent the morning at the Commission on Ecclesiastical Courts. It was soon apparent that an "Anglo–Catholic" Caucus had been at work overnight, &amp; had agreed upon a course in the crucial matter of the Final Court. Greatly to my surprise, Sir Lewis Dibden<persName xml:id="909"></persName> &amp; Chancellor Errington<persName xml:id="5423"></persName> fell in with the proposal. I suspect that Cantuar: has been pressing them. It was impossible to discuss the matter adequately so I refused my assent, &amp; indicated the necessity of a minority report. Both the Bishop of Worcester<persName xml:id="636"></persName> &amp; Canon Wilson were absent, so that I was alone, with sympathy rather than support from Prebendary Sharp. I lunched at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> &amp; killed the time there until I went off to King's Cross in order to catch the 5.30p.m. express. Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> was my compagnon de voyage, and we had some talk together, &amp; also dined together. At Darlington Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> met me with the car. Before going to bed I went through the letters that have accrued during my absence &amp; wrote some cheques in payment of a series of bills! The consignment of scriveners' quills has arrived from Halifax: and an interesting letter from Robin<persName xml:id="4430"></persName> was among the letters.</p></body></text></TEI>