<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The facts of comparative anatomy and embryology, and the definite proofs of kinship afforded by the reactions of the blood, make it certain that the human family was derived from one of the anthropoid apes…….In fact it can confidently be assumed that the ancestors of the human family were sprung from a stem common to the ancestry of the gorilla&#8211;chimpanzee stock, after the ancestors of the orang &amp; the gibbon had begun to differentiate from the still more primitive anthropoids….Man's ancestors certainly advanced to the stage of the giant anthropoids (in the Miocene or possibly even in the Oligocene Period) before distinctive specialisation of structure &amp; function produced the orang, the chimpanzee, the gorilla, and man respectively from a common stock.</p>
         <p>v. G. Elliot Smith 'Anthropology' in 'Evolution in the Light of Modern Knowledge'. P.293,4</p>
         </div>
         <p>Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> sends e a letter which he has received from the Bishop of Birmingham<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>, in which he (the Bishop) writes: "I think it best that I personally should pay no attention to the E. C. U. manifesto. Naturally my paper at Oxford on 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> will reiterate my position, which as you know is <hi rend="bold">[190] </hi>that of all unbiased men".</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Most of the bitterness which has attended the promulgation and criticism of evolutionary theories might probably have been avoided if both parties to the dispute had been careful to remember that you neither explain what a thing is by saying how it came to be there, nor explain how it has come to be there by saying what it is.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Taylor</hi> 'Philosophy' in 'Evolution in the light of modern knowledge'. P.476</p>
         </div>
         <p>Perhaps the last assertion is somewhat overbold. In any case "unbiased" is a difficult word to allocate satisfactorily! But the less merely personal controversy the better. After writing the necessary letters, I spent the morning in reading <hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray's</hi><hi rend="underline">Erasmus and Luther</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="4448"></persName> came to lunch, and stayed on to dine and sleep. He had divers matters of business to discuss. The Westcotts<persName xml:id="5385"></persName> came to dinner.</p>
         <p>I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anson Phelps Stokes</hi><persName xml:id="1565"></persName>, who has now become a Canon of Washington Cathedral, &amp; wants to learn how best to make a cathedral foundation generally useful to the community.</p></body></text></TEI>