<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>We left Carlton–on–Trent at 11.30 a.m., and motored to Bishop Auckland, arriving at the Castle about 5p.m. We lunched by the roadside shortly after leaving Selby, and we stayed nearly an hour in York, in order to see the Five Sisters, which have been cleaned, &amp; now look very splendid. We visited two of the parish churches. A woman was kneeling in one of the pews: when she perceived that a clergyman was in the church, she came &amp; asked me to say a prayer for her son, who was dying in a nursing home. The poor creature seemed in such distress that I could not but yield to her wish, though, indeed I have no facility in such extemporaneous prayer.</p>
         <p>On reaching the Castle Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> brought a considerable accumulation of letters, some of which were unpleasing, &amp; none of which was interesting. The first batch of proofs of my '<hi rend="underline">Notes on Spiritual Healing</hi>' arrived. I like the type, but the stuff reads worse than I expected!</p>
         <p>A copy of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Van Mildert's</hi><hi rend="underline"> Bampton Lectures </hi>(2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> edition 1815), which I have long wanted to get, was sent to me by Blackwell.</p>
         <p>The Tennessee Article in the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> seems to have occasioned a small spat of fanaticism, which expresses itself in Bibliolatious tracts and letters! By a blunder, which I had no opportunity of correcting, for I see no proofs of these articles, some words of mine are attributed to Bishop Westcott<persName xml:id="1047"></persName>!</p></body></text></TEI>