<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit Monday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'By repeated observations I find I can command thrice the number in the open&#8211;air, that I can under a roof'</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Sept. 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1759.</p>
         </div>
         <p>But whereas the number which can hear the individual voice effectively in the open air has a definite limit, it is difficult to limit the number which can hear under cover, for the issue turns mainly, not on the size of the building, but on its acoustic qualities. Similarly, with the preacher's voice, far more turns on its "carrying power" than on its strength or compass. But the new scientific expedients (broad casting, loud speakers etc) make all such calculations superfluous. <hi rend="bold underline">The age of orators is past</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>We (Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and I) motored to Borcovicus on the wall, returning by way of Blanchland &amp; Stanhope. The weather, which was disposed to be showery at the start, steadily improved as the afternoon wore to evening, &amp; our drive over the moorland was in the brilliance of a cloudless sky. But the wind was keen, &amp; our motor "sprung a leak" as we approached Blanchland, which delayed us for about half an hour. We left the Castle at 2 p.m., and did not return until 9 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>