<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Men are qualified for civil liberty in exact proportion to their disposition to put moral chains upon their own appetites – in proportion as their love to justice is above their rapacity, &#8211; in proportion as their soundness and sobriety of understanding is above their vanity and presumption – in proportion as they are more disposed to listen to the counsels of the wise and good, in preference to the flattery of knaves. Society cannot exist, unless a controlling power upon will and appetite be placed somewhere: &amp; the less of it there is within, the more there must be without. <hi rend="underline">It is ordained in the eternal constitution of things that men of intemperate minds cannot be free. Their passions forge theirs fetters.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burke</hi><hi rend="underline">Letters to a Member of Assembly</hi> (iv. 51) </p>
         </div>
         <p>I received &#x00A3;20, from the Evening Standard, &amp; paid it into the Bank forthwith. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I wrote an Article on 'Prohibition' and sent it to the Editor of the Westminster Gazette.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> wrote to say that Geordie<persName xml:id="571"></persName> had undergone an operation for appendicitis, &amp; that by consequence her own plans were deranged. I sent the inf. of my sermon in memory of Roland Bradford to his brother. </p></body></text></TEI>


