<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[237]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Charles II, "hearing that Waller the poet intended to give his daughter in marriage to a clergyman sent to remonstrate with him for marrying her to a failing church. 'Sir', replied Waller, 'the king does me very great honour to take any notice of my domestic affairs; <hi rend="underline">but I have lived long enough to observe that this falling church has got a trick of rising again</hi>'.</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lightfoot</hi> '<hi rend="underline">Leaders of the N.C.</hi>' p. 152</p>
         </div>
         <p>A curiously warm day, but sunless &amp; threatening rain. I wrote with difficulty another article for the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>, taking as my title "<hi rend="underline">The lure of Moscow</hi>", and as my subject the recent session of the Trade Union Congress at Scarborough. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth Kay</hi> came to lunch to discuss the question of his <hi rend="underline">baptism</hi>. His father states that he was baptized privately by a Disserting Minister, and formally received into the Church by a curate of the parish church. This last went <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> himself remembers, &amp; also produces a formal statement from the said curate. In these circumstances, ought he be baptized <hi rend="underline">sub condicione</hi>? The Vicar took me to see a parishioner who is carving a communion table for the Memorial Chapel in South Church. He is a railwayman, but nowise enamoured of his Union!</p></body></text></TEI>