<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>An urgent letter from <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> bidding me come back for the Railway Function as we were summoned to travel by the Royal Train!! The sweet lady has lost her fair head at the mention of Royalty. I wrote to Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> saying that I should be absent, &amp; giving him the reason. Chelmsford<persName xml:id="65"></persName> is in the College, so I asked him what he thought was my duty, and he was quite clear that I ought to stay up, and vote. Then I sent a telegram to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Chelmsford</hi> and I walked round Magdalen Walk, &amp; had much talk. He spoke highly of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hickson</hi>, who impressed him as sincere &amp; spiritual; &amp; said that the young men of his entourage were greatly taken with him. What is to be made of this?</p>
         <p>I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank</hi><persName xml:id="66"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Katherine</hi><persName xml:id="4356"></persName>. The latter has got her hair "shingled", and professes to be vastly pleased with it. But I still hoed with S. Paul that "if a woman have long hair it is a glory to her"! We talked of affairs in the Church, but I take the impression that nobody cares two pins about ecclesiastical affairs, nobody outside the organized functions which, though irresistible in the [ Church, are but a petty force in the State. I called at Blackwell's, &amp; asked them to try &amp; get <hi rend="doubleunderline">Van Mildert's</hi> publications for me. Then I returned to College, and had tea by myself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p>To my amazement (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Hardinge</hi><persName xml:id="548"></persName>) A. H. appeared at dinner with a guest. Two days ago his son, a Cambridge undergraduate of 21, was found dead beside his motor–cycle! Was it a proud Stoical fortitude, or an unfeeling indifference that led him thus to present himself in public at such a time? (I wrote to him when I read of the calamity in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, but I do not think he could have received my letter). It is a strangely unfeeling world, &amp; he (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hardinge</hi>) has not seen the best side of it. But I could not avoid a certain sense of repugnance at seeing him able to come abroad with such a grief on him. Perhaps, indeed, we childless men idealize fatherhood, &amp; credit fathers with a depth of affection for their sons, which they do not feel, &amp; which <hi rend="underline">we</hi>, if we <hi rend="underline">had</hi> sons, could not feel. I had some talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sumner</hi>, who is the great–grandson of the Bishop of Winchester. He is a distinguished–looking man, &amp; of an agreeable address. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Peers</hi>, one of the junior fellows, is engaged on a thesis "<hi rend="underline">On Roman agrarian policy</hi>", a slim youth with a mane of light–brown hair falling over his face. After dinner we played bowls in the quadrangle. Everything was most restful, and delusive!</p></body></text></TEI>
