<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>He confessed to viewing with a certain misgiving the tendency of some of their men to develop an elaborate ritual at the expense of the sermon. If it was done to cover a certain loss of faith in preaching, the minister might just as well write "Ichabod" over his church doors, for vestments &amp; liturgies &amp; a tiny ten&#8211;minutes' sermon were never going to make a church a power. If it was done in the hope of attracting the outsider, it was a pretty desperate expedient. Preaching must be their strength and glory still.</p>
         <p>(Inaugural Address of Rev. J. D. Jones D.D. as Chairman of the Congregational Union of England &amp; Wales &#8211; Times. May 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925.).</p>
         </div>
         <p>Lord Milner's<persName xml:id="839"></persName> death is reported in the newspapers. He had just been elected to be 'our honoured Lord &amp; Chancellor' at Oxford. Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName> came to see me about the discipline case &amp; stayed to Lunch. Canon Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> lunched here, &amp; then accompanied me to Gainford where I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bidwell to the Vicarage. Then I returned to Auckland, only to set out again almost immediately for West Hartlepool, where I confirmed about 120 persons in Christ Church. After the service we returned to Auckland. A fine warm day.</p></body></text></TEI>