<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[216]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I showed my proof of "Lourdes" to D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gillies, and he read it through. He expressed great approval, &amp; some surprise at my scientific temper. "You would have made a first&#8211;rate man of science". He added that he had never suspected that the Papist doctrine about S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Mary was so recent. Probably his opinion must be discounted by his civility. N.B. Mine host told me that Gillies is a New Zealander, who came up to Cambridge as a rather feeble youth. There he developed great athletic capacity: he rowed in the University Eight, played Cricket for the University &amp; did other enviable things of that kind. In due course he became a distinguished surgeon, being particularly skilful in the remaking of countenances wrecked by the War.</p>
         <p>Steel&#8211;Maitland<persName xml:id="42"> motored us to Cloan. On the way we stopped to see Dunblane Cathedral, which has been well&#8211;restored. Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, half&#8211;crippled with sciatica, received us with kindness: &amp; after tea Miss Haldane walked us to a view&#8211;point on the adjacent hill, from which a noble prospect of mountains was gained.</p>
         <p>Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> arrived at dinner&#8211;time fresh from the Conference of Modern Churchmen at Oxford. He thought Fawkes's<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> paper was too provocative, and had been assured by those who heard it that Barnes's<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> pronouncement was dignified, persuasive, and powerful. The extracts printed in the newspapers had <hi rend="bold">[217]</hi> not given me this impression. Ralph himself entered the lists in defence of Barnes, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">his</hi> pronouncement will shortly appear in print. So the impudent address of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> will have been answered: but of course, it will have done its work none the less, for those who read &amp; enjoyed it will give no attention to the rejoinders. The ill consequences of religious controversies – viz: the embittering of resentments, deepening of prejudices, &amp; hardening of partisan positions – are mainly connected with the fact that for the great majority of controversialists the process is not really controversial, but only a concentration of mind on a single point of view, &amp; the confirmation of opinions by ceaseless iteration! </p>
         <p>Lord Haldane is as incorrigibly optimistic as ever: he approves the subsidy: acquiesces in the apparent importance of the State in front of the Trade Unions: thinks that there is no real danger in the Communist movement: &amp; assumes that we are passing comfortably into a new phase of social organization in which 'sovereignty will be divided'. But he doesn't really face the formidable practical issues which must be faced, &amp; faced quickly, if the nation is to escape the most terrible disasters. If, as seems certain, the mining industry can only proceed on a much reduced scale, something like half a million men &amp; lads will be permanently unemployed: how are they to be disposed of? That is the real problem first to be solved.</p></body></text></TEI>