<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A wet morning following a wet night. The crops are ready to be gathered in. Fine weather now would be great blessing to the country. We are in such a pass that the comfort of the people, now wholly given up to their holiday&#8211;making, is a matter of grave political importance: and rain in holidays breeds discomfort, &amp; so far predisposes to sedition. If this wet weather should continue, and ruin the harvest, a great national disaster will have taken place.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8a.m. Frank, the butler's boy, assisted in preparing the altar etc. in Alexander's<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> absence. We numbered 6 communicants.</p>
         <p>I motored to Eastgate in Weardale, and preached at Evensong in the little parish church. The congregation may have numbered as many as 60 or 70 persons, which perhaps, as the population is no more than 346, is quite up to the average. But the absence of boys and young men was very marked. There was but a single choirboy on duty, the main part of the choir being girls. Old Canon Croudace<persName xml:id="5311"></persName> is clearly failing: he spoke of resigning the Rural Deanery, but there is nobody who could be set in his place. I asked him to hold on yet for a while. After service I motored back to the Castle.</p></body></text></TEI>