<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A dull morning followed by a fine afternoon &amp; brilliant evening. The day like a genuine Christian matured into beauty, &amp; was then most fit for earth when ripe for repose. In the morning I worked on the preface of my book. Miss Hill and her niece, an amiable plump damsel, came to lunch. <hi rend="bold underline">Our host &amp; hostess went off to the funeral of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Baldwin, the Prime Minister's<persName xml:id="4118"></persName> mother</hi>, and <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored for an hour through Droitwich. After tea, Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and I played bowls. The afternoon post brought me <hi rend="italic">a proposal from the Editor of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Morning Post</hi><hi rend="italic"> to write three controversial articles for his journal. They might be subsequently published, &amp; he would pay a fee of fifty guineas. He writes: "I hope to obtain from the pen of one of the most prominent of the Anglo&#8211;Catholics a statement of their aims &amp; objects. This w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be followed the next day by your answer, &amp; so on, each replying to the other until the end. In this way you </hi>w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> have the last word". I am not altogether indisposed to do this and Ernest thinks that I should: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but I think I must stipulate that my opponent be one who, in my judgment, is a man of suitable standing &amp; character to be dealt with on a basis of controversial equality by the Bishop of Durham</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>