<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, Sunday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, who hast given thine only Son to be unto us both a sacrifice for sin, and also an ensample of godly life; Give us grace that we may always most thankfully receive that his inestimable benefit, and also daily endeavour ourselves to follow the blessed steps of his most holy life, through the same Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is one of the Reformation collects (1549) and is constructed from the Epistle for the Day (I S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Pet. ii. 19f.), where the sinlessness &amp; meek behaviour under oppression which marked the Life of Jesus are specially emphasized. It is the metier of Christians to suffer. "<hi rend="underline">Even hereunto were ye called: because Christ also suffered for us, leaving us an example, that ye should follow his steps</hi>". There is a thoroughly Pauline touch in the phrase, '<hi rend="underline">that we, being dead to sins, should live unto righteousness</hi>'.</p>
         <p>The connexion between creed and conduct is never so clearly affirmed as at Eastertide, and, perhaps, in these difficult modern days, never so hard to vindicate. For our triumphant affirmations of belief have to march along with our most anxious examinations of evidence.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[13]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We numbered 10 communicants, including our guest Bourke. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Winston where I preached in the parish church. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hughes, the late Vicar's son, read the service. I ordained him to the diaconate four years ago, at the request of the Bishop of Rangoon in whose diocese he has been working. After service we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bourke &amp; I essayed to walk in the Park, but were driven back by rain &amp; hail. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. A brisk brief thunderstorm with vehement rain enlivened the afternoon. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Bourke went back to Evenwood after dinner. He left us a pleasant impression.</p>
         <p>I amused myself by reading Coulton's<persName xml:id="4746"></persName> 'Medieval Garner'. It casts a strange light on the religious &amp; moral condition of the 'Ages of faith'. A lay&#8211;brother 'somewhat grievously tempted' prayed to Christ in these terms, "<hi rend="underline">In truth, Lord, if Thou deliver me not from this temptation, I will complain of Thee to Thy Mother</hi>". This impudent petition was effectual, &amp; the moral of the story is disclosed by the question, '<hi rend="underline">Who would not be edified by Christ's so great humility</hi>?' The morality of the age was on a par with its theology. <hi rend="bold underline">It is a sinister sign of our time that Coulton's care &amp; learning cannot secure attention from our 'Anglo&#8211;Catholics'</hi>.</p></body></text></TEI>