<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the day in the National Assembly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Most of the morning was wasted in the discussion of Clergy Pensions, which had stood over from the preceding debate, &amp; Lord Forester's speech against the Shrewsbury Bishoprick Measure was made in a very thin House. <hi rend="bold underline">After luncheon I made a speech in his support. It was well listened to, but, of course, quite ineffective. The Measure was approved by a large majority</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The fight will be renewed in Parliament, but I cannot doubt that the result will be the same. The small, organised faction that calls itself "the Church" has determined its course, &amp; <hi rend="underline">no</hi> argument can divert it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My article on the Coal Crisis appears in the "Evening Standard", and reads rather sombrely. Gee expressed his approval: &amp; so did Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. I am not sure whether it can do any good: I am disposed to think it</hi><hi rend="underline">may</hi><hi rend="bold underline">do harm. Why, then, did I write it</hi><hi rend="bold">?</hi></p>
         <p>We all (i.e. Ralph, Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I) dined at the Mansion House. The papist Lord Mayor entertained us well, &amp; expressed himself quite politely. Both the Archbishops were commendably brief, &amp; relevant. On the whole it was quite a pleasant evening.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury told me that he would have voted with the minority this afternoon, if he had voted at all. If his opposition to the Shrewsbury Bishoprick had been made public, would the Measure have carried? I cannot believe it: but </hi><hi rend="underline">leadership</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> which does not</hi><hi rend="underline"> lead</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> makes much possible</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>