<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Clayton's<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> reunion of Knutsford students was held here. About 25 appeared</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> I saw something of them, &amp; shewed the Chapel to them all. Tooley is leaving his parish in Sunderland, and going to the diocese of Newcastle. I told him that he must continue to regard himself as one of S. Cuthbert's sons, &amp; return as soon as possible. Snell, the curate of South Westoe, came with a tale of woe. He has accepted the curacy of Winlaton, and, being quite immobilized by his penury, is at his wit's end to get there! What can be done for these penniless parsons? He has only been 15 months in the diocese, &amp; is therefore not eligible for assistance from the Crewe Trust.</p>
         <p>I addressed the men at Evensong in the Chapel, &amp; then rashly said that I should be pleased to have them here again next year. Shore, of Roker, is secretary of the Knutsford Brotherhood.</p>
         <p>Sykes from Middlesbrough stayed the night. He is a fat humourous man, with his Anglo&#8211;Catholicism chastened by his native good sense. He spoke of the <hi rend="bold underline">Anglo&#8211;Catholic Mission at Middlesboro, which in his view was a great success</hi>. But he admitted that only his own intervention had prevented untoward incidents such as have occurred at Southampton.</p></body></text></TEI>