<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was a considerable thunder&#8211;storm during the night, but at some distance, and the air was rather sultry all day. I spent the morning in preparing notes for this afternoon, &amp; then went in to Worcester with mine hostess &amp; <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. I lunched with the Chairman of the County Council, who entertained the Bishop &amp; other members of the Conference. After lunch I spoke to the Conference for an hour on the Report of the Pensions Committee. Then various questions were asked, which I answered: &amp; then we came away. I was pleased at the reception which was given to my speech. We returned to Hartlebury where Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> &amp; I played bowls.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The afternoon post brought an exceedingly rude letter from Haslewood, &amp; another from his wife!</hi> Also, a cheque for &#x00A3;20 came for the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> Article in the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi>. At first, I was disposed to ignore Hazlewood's [sic] letter, but afterwards I wrote him as mild a reply as seemed possible, but I doubt if it will do any good. He has behaved badly, &amp; he knows it. His wife is an excessively foolish woman, &amp; adds fresh elements to the confusion. He hungers for a change, &amp; has himself made a change almost impossible.</p></body></text></TEI>