<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Tell us not that ye will sacrifice to the Lord our God, if we will sacrifice to Ashtaroth or Melcom: that ye will read our Scriptures, if we will listen to your traditions: <hi rend="underline">that if ye may have a mass by permission, we shall have a communion with good leave and liking</hi>: that ye will admit the things that are spoken of by the Apostles of our Lord Jesus, if your Lord &amp; Master may have his ordinances observed, and his statutes kept. Solomon took it (as well he might) for an evident proof, that she did not bear a motherly affection to her child, which yielded to have it cut in divers parts. He cannot love the Lord Jesus with his heart, which lendeth one ear to his Apostles, &amp; another to false apostles; <hi rend="underline">which can brooke to see a mingle&#8211;mangle of religion and superstition, ministers &amp; massing priests, light and darkness, truth and error, traditions and scriptures.</hi> No, we have no lord but Jesus: no doctrine but the Gospel: no teachers but his Apostles. Were it reason to require at the hand of an English subject, obedience to the laws and edicts of the Spaniard?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Richard Hooker</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Sermon V</hi>. Sect: 7.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[120]</hi></p>
         <p>As I feared, the spirit of political partisanship has prevailed against that of public duty. The result of the polling for the Chancellorship of Oxford University was:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Lord Cave.</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">987</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Lord Oxford &amp; Asquith.</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">441</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Majority.</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="doubleunderline">546</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;"/>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;"/>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters, &amp; paying bills. Chute came to consult me about the offer which he has received to have himself considered by Magdalen College for the position of Dean of Divinity. I could not but counsel him to go if the call came: but his departure will be a heavy loss to the diocese. Yesterday's post brought a letter from Graham White informing me that he felt constrained to go to the Mission field, &amp; must therefore resign Dawdon. He also will be a loss to the diocese. The fates are hard on Durham now.</p>
         <p>I motored to S. Andrew's, Tudhoe Grange, &amp; collated the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> D. W. Marsh to the Vicarage. There was a fair congregation, &amp;, I think, everybody meant well.</p>
         <p>After dinner I wrote to Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName>, bidding him not to be discouraged, &amp; suggesting that he should start reading with the object of being ordained at Trinity next year. That will serve for the first stage.</p></body></text></TEI>