<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[147] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I chased up as much business as possible, and then (after an early lunch) motored to Barnard Castle, where <hi rend="bold underline">I presided over a meeting of the Governors</hi>. The members in the School are still falling, and there is no chance of any recovery until this still deepening cloud of economic distress lifts from our community. I noticed, perhaps absurdly, that when I entered the Council Room, none of the Governors rose save two or three out of a dozen. It is a 'sign of the times'. Time was, when the knaves had no more thought of showing that rudeness to the Bishop of Durham than of stealing Durham Cathedral! And I don't think they <hi rend="underline">meant</hi> to be rude. It is only that the Bishop no longer carries authority, or commands deference. He is just one of themselves, enigmatically entitled &amp; endowed!!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I motored to Knowlden<persName xml:id="5439"></persName> in Darlington, &amp; then continued my course to Riccall Hall, 10 miles south of York, where I stayed the night with Lord<persName xml:id="2092"></persName> &amp; Lady Danesfort</hi>, very pleasant kind people, but getting old and ailing. I had much talk with Lord D. He is still as fond an impenitent Irish Tory, and _ this is the dreadful thing about Irish Toryism _ very probably quite right in the diagnosis of and remedy for the disease of the uncivilized Papists who constitute 'the Irish problem'!</p></body></text></TEI>