<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[159]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A letter from Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> reaches me this morning. It contains the following reference to the mining crisis:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The coal situation, I fear, is bad, &amp; must be faced: &amp; for this reason I hope the Gov<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> will not try and postpone the evil day".</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">That is the mine&#8211;owner's view, &amp; regards solely the economic aspect of the crisis.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The 'Daily Mail' announces that a settlement has been reached</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">The terms appear to be a frank surrender to the threat of the Trade Unions. The industry is to continue on the existing uneconomical conditions, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Government will re&#8211;imburse the mine&#8211;owners for their losses up till next spring</hi><hi rend="italic">. Meanwhile, there is to be a Royal Commission to investigate thoroughly the whole state of the Industry, in order to discover whether economies are possible. The mine&#8211;owners are willing to withdraw their proposals, and the men are to continue in work.</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup i doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Baldwin</hi><persName xml:id="4118"></persName><hi rend="italic"> must </hi><hi rend="italic underline">either</hi><hi rend="italic"> be a weaker man than a Prime Minster ought to be, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">or</hi><hi rend="italic">, he has information about the state of the country which makes surrender to the Trade Unions unavoidable.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">160]</hi></p>
         <p>Denis Webster with his Spanish wife &amp; her cousin came to lunch. It was odd to hear from the lips of a pretty young Spanish female an energetic defence of bull&#8211;fighting. She admitted that football was coming into popularity in Spain, and was tending to oust the bull&#8211;fight. We all motored to Gawdy Hall, at Harleston, and had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sancroft&#8211;Holmes, a widow lady, whose husband was the direct descendant of the nonjuring Archbishop's elder brother. After tea she showed us the Treasures of the house. The Sancroft relics – a fine portrait of the Archbishop when he was Dean of York, his chair, clock, and common&#8211;place book – were perhaps the most interesting. But there was much else – furniture, vestments, and china. A curious object was Oliver Cromwell's shaving bason – a fine Chinese bowl improvised for the purpose of shaving the Protector! After seeing the garden we returned to Bramfield. The House, largely refaced, is a fine Elizabethan mansion, standing on the site of a yet older house. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sancroft&#8211;Holmes is childless. What will be the destination of her treasures?</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>', which has throughout taken up a position of marked hostility to the mine&#8211;owners, professes to hail the settlement as the most satisfactory mode of averting a formidable crisis. But its leading article is curiously feeble, and can only be explained on the supposition that it has ben, directly or indirectly, inspired. </p></body></text></TEI>