<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName> told me with much vivacity &amp; enthusiasm the story of the process by which he passed from the life of a curate in a poor London parish to resume at Oxford his earlier studies, &amp; to become a scholar of European distinction. His Bible class on 1. Corinthians led him to go behind the Commentaries. He found himself unable to accept <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dilmann's</hi> renderings of the Ethiopic text, &amp; accordingly made himself master of that crabbed tongue. His corrections of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dilmann</hi> gained acceptance in the learned world, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dilmann</hi> himself acknowledged their soundness. He became at a stroke a recognized member of the confraternity of European savants.</p>
         <p>I came away from Little Cloisters after breakfast and transferred myself to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. The papers contain fairly long accounts of yesterday's service in the Abbey, but my name is omitted, though I must have been rather prominent as I took the precedence of my See. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> assumed that the omission was intentional and waxed angry. I did not think it mattered.</p>
         <p>I called at 10 Downing Street, &amp; had a brief interview in a dark room with one of the Prime minister's secretaries. He was civil, but reserved &amp;, as it were, embarrassed, very unlike the free and friendly manners of my previous interviews. I suspect that the influences now dominant at the centre are nowise friendly to the Bishop of Durham &amp; <hi rend="underline">his</hi> views.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p>After lunching at the Athenaeum, I went to Paddington and caught the 4.45p.m. express to Oxford. Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName> travelled by the same train, &amp; we shared a taxi to our colleges. <hi rend="bold underline">At 7 p.m. I attended evensong in Oriel Chapel, &amp; afterwards dined at the Gandy. I proposed the toast 'Floreal Oriel", &amp; my speech was quite nicely received. The company, about eighty in number, consisted mainly of middle&#8211;aged and old men, of whom many were parsons. I sate beside Professor Baldwin Brown, who proposed the toast of the Provost &amp; Fellows, &amp; I was interested in his speech. He said that he was the first undergraduate who, as a Nonconformist, availed himself of the abolition of tests, &amp; that, for this reason, the Provost D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Hawkins, took a special interest in him, &amp; showed him much kindness</hi>. He described the old Provost as a man good to look at, with silver hair &amp; a fine intellectual countenance. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Phelps</hi> made an excellent speech, amusing &amp; extremely well phrased. In the course of it, he announced that "Royalty" – by which he was understood to mean their Majesties – would attend the sexcentenary celebration of Oriel next ear. These college celebrations bring home to me my academic solitude very poignantly. I got back to All Souls shortly after 10 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>