<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in the Assembly, where we talked about the need for some restraint in the publication of nauseous trials. Then I lunched at his Club with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Boden</hi><persName xml:id="2936"></persName>, who is in some danger of developing into a sybaritic&#8211;Socinian, a type of "liberal churchman" which is not pleasant to contemplate. In the afternoon I joined the Bishops of Chichester, Gloucester, &amp; Truro, in revising our draft of the 39 Articles. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; had tea. I wrote to George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, &amp; then walked to S. Paul's Deanery, &amp; dressed for dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I dined at 81 Albert Hall Mansions with Lord Darling</hi><persName xml:id="4032"></persName><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The company consisted of mine host &amp; Di, another young lady, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Muir MacKenzie</hi> &amp; his daughter <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Clive</hi> with her son, a young fellow of rather heavy but not unpleasing appearance. It was a pleasant evening, though the conversation left in my memory no deposit of thought or phrase worth recording. I walked the whole way back to S. Paul's Deanery, &amp; took rather more than an hour in doing so. There were many people in the streets, for it was a fine night: <hi rend="bold underline">I watched them, &amp; did not observe a single person the worse for drink, nor anything which</hi> could be reasonably described as ill&#8211;conduct. Surely this is very a notable &amp; encouraging fact, &amp; knocks the bottom out of Prohibitionist argument.</p></body></text></TEI>