<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>How completely the speaking must rest with <hi rend="underline">you</hi> on May 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>! Is Viscount Cecil of Chelston one of the new titles? Is he one of the Salisbury Cecils? and does he know anything about Durham Castle? I wish, indeed, that I could be there to hear you; your naso&#8211;suspendere&#8211;adunco touch charms me; there is no one to whom I listen so readily. The last time was when you were 'opening' the new scientific buildings, &amp; urging the establishment of a chair in Architecture.</p>
         <p>J. Meade Falkner<persName xml:id="3553"></persName>. Letter. April 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">'Your naso&#8211;suspendere&#8211;adunco touch' is rather disconcerting, and recalls to my mind "Henson's contemptuous ire" of Raleigh's<persName xml:id="14"></persName> college poem. Both remind me of a quality which it is unfortunate to possess, and impolitic to indulge. I think it has nearer kinship with the "soeva&#8211;indignatio" of Dean Swift, than with the 'satiric vein' of critics. It may go far to explain the curious aversion, half fear, half dislike, which I seem to provoke! For at bottom the Bishop of Durham is neither ungenerous nor unkind. "Your eyes give you away" was a saying of Beeching's<persName xml:id="208"></persName> about me: &amp; I think there is probably truth in his words. On the whole, I like to be on good terms with my fellows</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, &amp; took train for London, where I put up at Garland's Hotel. After a visit to the hairdresser, I walked to Westminster &amp; went to the H. of L. The much&#8211;expected Budget was being introduced by Winston Churchill<persName xml:id="2441"></persName>, while <hi rend="bold underline">L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Moran introduced his Bill for providing improved public&#8211;houses in Scotland, &amp; incidentally giving the quietus to the Temperance Act of 1913. I made a very poor speech, which probably undid all the orational reputation which I gained by</hi> my former effort! Lord Oxford spoke against the Bill very effectively, &amp; then the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> reading was by 38 to 23, everybody understanding that the Bill w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> go no farther. <hi rend="bold underline">L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Moran asked me to dine</hi>, as he had just received a note from his wife saying that a guest had fallen through. So I went to 105 Eaton Place, &amp; I had a most interesting evening. <hi rend="bold underline">Haig, Jelicoe, &amp; Neville Chamberlain<persName xml:id="4164"></persName> were there with their wives. Lady Carmichael &amp; I made up the party. I had a long talk with Haig, &amp; was amazed at the freedom with which he gave expression to what was evidently a very strong feeling against the French, </hi><hi rend="bold">(</hi><hi rend="bold underline">&amp; against Lloyd George</hi><hi rend="bold">).</hi> He said that he had deposited in the British Museum a frank account of the way in which we were 'let down' by the French, an account which would not see the light for some years.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[18]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>How did the redoubtable general impress me? With the best will in the world it is impossible to say that he looks worthy of the role which he has played. He would never arrest attention in any company. He is a well&#8211;built handsome man with a frank soldierly manner and a curiously inadequate brain&#8211;case. His virtues are clearly rather those of character than of intellect. He applied the term "humbug" to Foch, who, he said, had excused himself for acquiescing in a belittlement of the English achievement on the ground that he was a member of the French government. I inquired about the conduct of the German armies, and he was frankly contemptuous of the famous outrages. He said that the French behaved very badly, &amp; 'ran away' disconcertingly on many occasions. His admiration for the German soldiers was evident &amp; expressed freely. Nothing would, in his opinion induce the English to fight alongside the French again. Walking away with the Jellicoes, I asked him about Hickson in New Zealand, &amp; he spoke well of him, especially of the good effect of the services held in preparation for his healing mission. I liked all the ladies, especially M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Neville Chamberlain, &amp; Lady Haig.</p></body></text></TEI>