<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I talked with a young man, who seemed to be under strong convictions: but I fear only seemed. I am surprised that, in so many years, this is the first hypocrite of the kind I have met with: the first who appeared to have deliberately put on the mask of religion, purely to serve a secular end.</p>
         <p>John Wesley's Journal. Dec. 25<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1745</p>
         </div>
         <p>Wesley's Journal begins in 1732, and the first hypocrite is noted in the entry for Christmas Day, 1745. Perhaps, the date may suggest that the hypocrisy was not very serious. At Christmas the mendicant is apt to "put on the mask of religion, purely to serve a secular end". The "secular end" is commonly not more distant than the nearest public house! Or, should a more serious view be taken, and the first hypocrite be interpreted as a sign that Methodism had already acquired so much of an ecclesiastical character as to exhibit the most constant feature of a Christian church? There is a ruthlessness about Wesley's judgments of men that disinclines the student of his Journal to place the worst construction on the severe language in which he describes the subjects of his censure.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I received the Holy Communion together in the little chapel of the Castle. Then came a mingled post. From Lazenby<persName xml:id="3135"></persName> the document on Parry's resignation signed by him &amp; only requiring my signature to make it legally binding. I signed and despatched it without delay. Then, from Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName>, a woeful account of the boiler at Auckland, which supplies hot water to the baths, &amp; which must be renewed at a cost of &#x00A3;23. I finished the Preface to the Book, which now, in its rough draft, is completed. Indeed I have exceeded my allotted limit by about 2000 words, which many, perhaps, be cut out on revision. After lunch we all motored to Ludlow, and, after visiting the Church and the ruins of the Castle, had tea in "The Feathers". We went by way of Cleobury Mortimer, &amp; enjoyed the noble prospect on either hand from the Clee ridge. We returned by way of Tenbury. The narrow tortuous roads bordered by tall hedge&#8211;rows are extremely perilous for motorists. The afternoon post brought me an affectionate letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Haldane's death is reported. She was in her 101st year, &amp; in full possession of her faculties. It seems but yesterday that her centenary was the subject of general congratulations.</p></body></text></TEI>