<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[246]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I left Sandbeck after breakfast &amp; returned to Auckland. From Rotherham to York I shared the carriage with a voluble &amp; rather dogmatic gentleman, whose name, if it may be assumed w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be that which was attached to his bag, was Irwin. He spoke much &amp; optimistically about the state of trade, said that he was a friend of Raine<persName xml:id="5371"></persName>, &amp; was well acquainted with the present condition of the mining industry. <hi rend="bold underline">He referred contemptuously to Bishop Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, expressed admiration for Bishop Westcott<persName xml:id="1047"></persName>, &amp; described the Duke of Northumberland<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> as 'the M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Cook of the mine owners'</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> He said also that he was "behind the scenes" of the Coal Commission, &amp; 'had reason to know' that their report w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> recommend he purchase of minerals by the State, and the offer of &#x00A3;50,000,000 to the present owners.</p>
         <p>Leng met me at Darlington, &amp; motored me to Auckland. I spent the time until dinner, save for a short walk in the Park in writing letters. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> had brought for the week&#8211;end a lad named Cliffe Cock, the son of clergyman whose parish abutted on Windermere, &amp; who had been one of the students at the Castle under Bishop Westcott. He was a gentle well&#8211;mannered youth who aspired to be a land&#8211;agent. He had been at a Sedbeigh school for five years, and left a year ago.</p></body></text></TEI>