<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[71]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I thought it would be worth while to make an odd experiment. Remembering how surprisingly fond of music the lion at Edinburgh was, I determined to try whether this was the case with all animals of the same kind. I accordingly went to the Tower with one who plays on the German flute. He began playing near four or five lions; only one of these (the rest not seeming to regard it at all) rose up, came to the front of his den, &amp; seemed to be all attention. Mean&#8211;time, a tiger in the same den started up, leaped over the lion's back, turned and ran under his belly, leaped over him again, &amp; so to fro incessantly. Can we account for this on any principle of mechanism? Can we account for it at all?</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Journal. Jan 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1765</p>
         </div>
         <p>Wesley experimenting with music on lions is a more attractive and intelligible figure than Wesley experimenting with hell&#8211;fire on small children. The most unattractive entries in his famous 'Journal' are those which narrate his handling of childhood: and, perhaps, it is largely owing to his influence, that Dissenters (for, in spite of his efforts, his followers fell into that description) have no aptitude for understanding children.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m. Then I prepared a "charge" for the candidates.</p>
         <p>The men whom I have myself ordained are already, though I have not yet completed 5 years of episcopate in this diocese, coming into the line of preferment. Gomes&#8211;Williams is to go to Holy Trinity, Gateshead: and Cecil Booth is to undertake the new district of Cleadon. I think I shall offer Annfield Plain to Dick. It is interesting to note that these three men have all got degrees from Oxford and Cambridge.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote a brief answer to a letter I received from the preposterous curate, Jobb, who went to Rome two years ago, and after a brief sojourn under the Scarlet Woman's petticoat, came back to the Church of England, &amp; is now an assistant curate in Middlesbrough.</p>
         <p>I spent an hour in the Park chatting with whom I found there. Picking up two pit&#8211;lads – Matthew Fairless &amp; John Hilton – I showed them the garden, &amp; (as they were obviously interested) the Castle also.</p>
         <p>I motored in to Durham, &amp; witnessed the oaths etc in the Chapter&#8211;House. Then I dined in the Common Room. Then I delivered my charge to the Candidates in the Deanery Chapel after which I returned to Auckland.</p></body></text></TEI>