<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>That there are many demoniaques in the Primitive Church, and few Madmen, &amp; other such singular diseases, whereas in these times we hear of and see many Mad men and few Demoniaques, proceeds not from the change of nature, but of names. But how it comes to pass, that whereas heretofore the Apostles, &amp; after them for a time, the Pastors of the Church, did cure those singular diseases, which now they are not seen to do ……. is another question.</p>
         <p>Hobbes. 'Leviathan. Part iv. ch. 45 (p.356.)</p>
         </div>
         <p>I finished the sermon, &amp; then suffered a reporter to make extracts from it for the Yorkshire Post. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I motored to West Hartlepool to attend the marriage of the Vicar of Willington (Duncan). The function was numerously attended. Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> 'tied the knot': a former Vicar assisted: &amp; I gave an address. We attended the reception at the Grand Hotel, &amp; then called on the Pooles. We got back to Auckland in good time for Evensong in S. Peter's Church. There was a disappointingly small congregation, &amp; my sermon was delivered to a listless congregation. We came away as soon as the service was over. The weather all day was bright &amp; spring&#8211;like.</p></body></text></TEI>