<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The church which these men (the converts to Catholicism) joined was pledged to change the moral &amp; intellectual atmosphere in which Englishmen moved &amp; breathed. Neither freedom of thought nor political liberty had as yet reached their perfect development in England, but it was beyond doubt that the victory of the Papacy would extinguish both.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">S. R. Gardiner</hi>. Hist. of England. i. 231.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Robson</hi> making a suggestion for the proposed memorial window in S. Hilda's, Hartlepool. Then I motored into Durham, &amp; had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Heap</hi>, to whom I offered the charge of Blackhalls, which he accepted. Then I went to the Castle, &amp; instituted a bunch of curates among whom was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Neville Hudson</hi>. Then I lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, and afterwards had an interview with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> about this unhappy business at Sunderland. Then I motored to Monkheselden, &amp; confirmed about 60 persons in the little old parish church. After tea with the Vicar (Bell) I went on to Horden, &amp; confirmed 34 persons. (This from a parish of 11,000 people in which more 20 boys &amp; girls reach the age of 14 every year). After service I returned to Auckland. My letter appeared in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>.</p></body></text></TEI>