<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I packed my bags, &amp; had them carried across to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. After breakfast, I walked to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, and called on de Candole, with whom I found Carnegie. It appears that <hi rend="bold underline">the Socialist Canon, Donaldson<persName xml:id="2419"></persName>, finds it hard to make both ends meet, &amp; is pressing for some juggling with the Abbey funds which would bring relief! I said that</hi> it seemed to me in the highest degree improbable that there was any legal power in the Chapter to take over the payment of rates &amp; dilapidations which is now made by the Canons personally. I lunched at the Athenaeum, &amp; then walked again to Dean's Yard to attend a meeting of the Q.A.B.<orgName xml:id="296"></orgName> governors. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frere</hi><persName xml:id="2021"></persName> was there. I passed him a note in these words:&#8211; "I understand you propose to invade the patrimonium S. Cuthbert &amp; proclaim the banner of Anglo&#8211;Catholic revolt against S. Cuthbert's servant &amp; successor". He replied by the inquiry 'Is Stockton yours?', &amp; when I nodded an affirmative he wrote "Then I am in mercy! <hi rend="bold underline">I got Ebor's sanction for going to Middlesbro' &amp; thought that Stockton was in the same boat: but I do not recognize your description of my task!" Finally</hi>, he said that he would cancel his engagement. I walked back to the Athenaeum &amp; had tea. Then I went to King's Cross, &amp; caught the 5.30 express to Darlington.</p></body></text></TEI>