<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I began the day by writing to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and inevitably my letter took a more than commonly religious tone. The Ordination, and the memory of my own Ordination 38 years ago, determined the direction of my thought. In his present situation, cut off from contact with any Church, even an epistolary sermon may not be wholly unwelcome, and George is, I think, himself genuinely religious.</p>
         <p>The morning is brilliantly fine, just such another summer's day as that on which I was ordained in Cuddesdon Parish Church, on June 5<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1887. How differently the world looked then! Had any one told me that I should come to sit in the Chair of Bishop Butler, whose "Analogy" I had hastily crammed for the Bishop of Oxford's examination, I should have held him to be jesting. As I look back over the years, I can see that I was happiest when I was closest to the people, that is, during the 7 years 1888&#8211;1895, when I was Vicar of Barking. Every step forward in the hierarchy has meant a step away from the spiritual work with individuals which is the true work of the Christian minister: and now, as a Bishop, I am almost completely secularized. For business is not the less business because it is ecclesiastical business, and a Bishop is submerged by ecclesiastical business.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[74]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I had a conversation with an ingenious man, who proved to a demonstration, that it was the duty of every man that could, to be 'clothed in purple and fine linen', and to 'fare sumptuously every day': and that he would do abundantly more good hereby than he could do by 'feeding the hungry &amp; clothing the naked'. O the depth of human understanding! What may not a man believe if he will?"</p>
         <p>John Wesley. Journal. Feb. 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> 1767</p>
         </div>
         <p>Wesley states the "ingenious man's" argument with obvious prejudice, and "answers" it with a brace of exclamations. Nevertheless, it was probably sound enough. To develope industry &amp; provide work for the poor, is better than to debase them with "indiscriminate almsgiving": and, in any case, a world of excellent Methodists would be mortally dull. But the issue between the "ingenious man" and the famous preacher presents itself at every turn. What is the concern of Christ's Religion with civilization? What right has the Christian man to interest himself in culture? How can he fitly enjoy the world, when his citizenship is in heaven? An ancient and insoluble problem.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I motored to Durham for the Ordination. There was, perhaps, a larger congregation than in recent years, though small enough. Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName> preached a good sermon, which, however, he spoiled by too vehement a delivery. He spoke too loud, &amp; waked the echoes of the cathedral. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, though present in the Deanery, absented himself in spite of the canon of 1604. I ordained the following:</p>
         <p>Priests:</p>
         <p>Harold Prescott Griffiths.</p>
         <p>Reginald Royle.</p>
         <p>Deacons:</p>
         <p>Albert Frederick (de) Burton.</p>
         <p>Samuel Moore.</p>
         <p>Rothwell Richardson. </p>
         <p>After service, I called on Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, &amp; talked to him about the Cathedral scheme. Then I lunched together with the newly&#8211;ordained men at the Bishop of Jarrow's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> house, and afterwards talked with him until it was time to go to the Cathedral for Evensong. I occupied the Throne, and, after service, returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>With some difficulty (for I felt strangely fatigued) I put together some notes for the sermon to Spicer's work&#8211;people. After dinner, I walked in the Park with my chaplain. The stillness of the evening &amp; the beauty of the scene were very restful. Later I went to Darlington <hi rend="underline">en route</hi> for King's Cross.</p></body></text></TEI>