<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. but with much physical discomfort through giddiness. Perhaps, the sudden heat has been too much for me. The five candidates communicated.</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post'</hi> announces that the Bishop of Peterborough has 'promulged a diocesan rule' <hi rend="bold underline">that the age for Confirmation is to be twelve, and that, for special reasons, he will accept candidates at ten! And he is an Evangelical bishop!</hi> I wrote to ask for an explanation.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park in the afternoon. It looks most beautiful. I picked up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robert Bothwell</hi>, aged 20, a chauffeur, earning &#x00A3;2 weekly, &amp; not contented with his job: a pleasant lad, &amp; aspiring to emigrate to Canada.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Davison</hi> gave another excellent address to the Ordinandi. He is, perhaps, a little too much disposed to quote his own experience, but that is a venial fault. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson Walker</hi><persName xml:id="3161"></persName> came to Evensong, &amp; stayed to dinner.</p>
         <p>The Editor of the <hi rend="underline">Morning Post</hi> wrote to inquire whether I would accept Kidd, the Warden of Keble, as an opponent in the columns of his paper. I replied that I would not accept anyone who was not of equal rank in the hierarchy with myself.</p>
         <p>The weather was bright, warm, and still.</p></body></text></TEI>