<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The new Vicar (of Scarborough) showed plainly, why he refused those who desired the liberty for me to preach in his church. A keener sermon I never heard. So all I have done to persuade the people to attend the church is overturned at once! And all who preach thus, will drive the Methodists from the church in spite of all I can do.</p>
         <p>John Wesley, Journal. June 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. 1784.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters, and preparing notes for a speech on the League of Nations<hi rend="bold underline">. The </hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Times</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> has a long, platitudinous &amp; very canting letter from the Bishop of Winchester on "The Call to Action". I was so much moved by it as to write a short letter to the same journal.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and had a conference with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> with respect to Parry's case. Then I went on to Jarrow, and addressed a meeting in support of the League of Nations Union. The meeting was held in a large &amp; hideous chapel which was about half full. There was little enthusiasm, &amp; much cant! I went back to Auckland after the meeting. I received a pleasant letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and also from my brother, who sent a contribution of &#x00A3;25 towards the Escombe Repair Fund.</p></body></text></TEI>