<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[140]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> went off to Darlington before breakfast. I finished the Bradford Memorial Sermon, &amp; put together some notes for an address to the lay&#8211; readers, taking the Tennessee trial for a subject. Then I motored to Durham, and lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. I attended the annual service of Lay&#8211;readers in the Cathedral, and formally admitted 33 to office. Then I delivered my address, which pleased Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> and Knight, &amp; was attentively listened to by the lay&#8211;readers, and a congregation which (the vergers said) was largely composed of American tourists. If so, they had the salutary experience of hearing that their great Republic was some 60 years behind Great Britain in theological learning! Colonel Burdon came to see me at the Cosin Library about the vacancy at Castle Eden. Cruickshank spoke to me about Jimmie<persName xml:id="3572"></persName> with whom his friendship is closer than I had supposed. Then I returned to Auckland, where I found a letter from the Editor of the "Evening Standard" stating "how exceedingly gratified" he has been with my articles, especially the "illuminating article" on the Mining Crisis, and hoping that "the Bishop will find time &amp; inclination to continue the series indefinitely". He would like to announce the fact. Bother him!</p></body></text></TEI>