<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>My late friends, Professor Haughton, had with Professor Huxley a friendship the warmth of which was not affected by their wide differences in religious opinion. Huxley one day said to him: "There are those who profess to believe what I consider to be false: but I do not regard their opinions, because I doubt the sincerity of some &amp; the intellectual capacity of others; but I respect you &amp; I know how sincerely you believe what you hold so strongly, &amp; I should like very much to know how it is that you believe what I can't believe". May I speak frankly? Said Haughton, "Certainly", said he. "Then", he said, "I don't know how it is, except that you are colour blind". Huxley was much struck. He said: "Well, it might be so. Of course, if I were colour blind, I should not know it myself".</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">D. Salmon</hi> quoted by D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> E. Lyttelton. Times. May 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925. </p>
         </div>
         <p>After breakfast I motored with Lord Grey into Durham, where I presided over a meeting of the clergy in the Chapter House gathered to consider the Pensions Measure. Lord G. spoke well &amp; usefully: &amp; we avoided any direct censure of the scheme. After lunching with me in the Castle, he returned to London. I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, &amp; then went back to Auckland. It rained hard all day long. </p></body></text></TEI>