<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Thursday, 30 (Aug 1759) I preached at the Tabernacle in Norwich, to a large, rude, noisy congregation. I took knowledge what manner of Teachers they had been accustomed to, and <hi rend="underline">determined to mend them or end them</hi>. Accordingly, the next evening, after sermon, I reminded them of two things: the one, that it was not decent to begin talking as soon as service was ended; &amp; hurrying to and fro, as in a bear&#8211;garden. The other, that it was a bad custom to gather into knots just after sermon, &amp; turn a place of worship into a coffee&#8211;house. I therefore desired, that none w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> talk under that roof, but go quietly and silently away.</p>
         <p>John Wesley, Journal Aug. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1759.</p>
         </div>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">To mend them or end them</hi>" – this phrase, applied to the House of Lords, was often on the lips of Radical orators in the eighties of the last century. The references to a 'bear&#8211;garden', and a 'coffee&#8211;house' are interesting as giving the social setting of Wesley's great work. Eighteenth century England could hardly be better indicated than by those long obsolete institutions.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p>I wasted most of the day in writing an article (No. 3) for the Evening Standard. Its subject – <hi rend="underline">Disestablishment and the present Discontent in the Church</hi> – was suggested to me by the Editor. It is a subject on which I can say much, but nothing prudently.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter headed 'Durham Castle' appeared in the 'Times'</hi>. Now Pemberton<persName xml:id="2837"></persName> writes to say that what the Committee wanted from me was, <hi rend="underline">not</hi> a letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, but a letter for private circulation.</p>
         <p>I motored to Winston, and 'collated' Canon Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName> to the Rectory. The weather was brilliant, so that the exceeding beauty of that lovely parish was seen to full advantage. The little church was quite full, largely with people from Tudhoe Grange, who came in two motor&#8211;omnibuses full of them – to see their old parson collated. More than a dozen clergy attended, a circumstance which indicates the high regard in which Canon Wykes is held. The Vicar of Barnard Castle was conspicuous by his absence. He is an ill&#8211;bred man, and I much fear, he is also what is far worse, an ill&#8211;natured man. After service I returned to Auckland.</p></body></text></TEI>