<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[225]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>We left Cloan shortly before 11 a.m., and motored to Gleneagles Station where we took the train for Perth. There we had to wait about 45 minutes. We got a through–carriage to Newcastle which we reached at 4.16 p.m. having had about 15 minutes in Edinburgh. Leng was ready with the car, and carried us to the Castle in little more than an hour. There were letters awaiting me, including an interesting one from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi><persName xml:id="4430"></persName>, and the remainder of the proofs. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi><persName xml:id="3805"></persName> had arrived shortly before, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> arrived shortly after our arrival.</p>
         <p>Our visit to Cloan was extremely pleasant. The house is most comfortable and beautifully situated. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="956"></persName> and his sister are admirable hosts, and their hospitality is enriched by conversation of a higher type than most country houses can provide. We were fortunate in the weather. I showed the proofs to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Haldane</hi><persName xml:id="1386"></persName>, <hi rend="underline">and she returned them after perusal with expressions of approval</hi>. Before leaving the house we, i.e. Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, Gosse<persName xml:id="2083"></persName> &amp; his wife, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I were photographed by Miss Haldane's secretary. The household included two dogs – an aged Aberdeen terrier, &amp; a very noble retriever called 'Bruce'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge</hi> writes to acknowledge my letter of condolence on her husband's<persName xml:id="602"></persName> death. Her handwriting is very difficult to read, but I gather that she has taken a house in London – 90 Inverness Terrace W.2. – and will live there.</p></body></text></TEI>