<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[308]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Rain fell almost without intermission throughout the day. Nevertheless we left the Castle about 10.15, &amp; motored to Alnwick Vicarage, where we arrived about 1 p.m. Here we were kindly received by Archdeacon and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mangin. The Duke<persName xml:id="4828"></persName> and Duchess of Northumberland came to lunch to meet us. He paid Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> a high compliment for his articles in the "Morning Post", a newspaper of which his Grace is understood to be the proprietor. After lunch we were shown over the Castle. Both the Duke and the Duchess are obviously proud of their great house, well acquainted with its treasures, &amp; able to explain them intelligently. The Castle is full of precious things, rich of various interest. I never saw a more sumptuous example of medieval art than the Sherborne Missal. The "History of the World" by Sir Walter Raleigh, being he very copy presented by the Author to the Earl of Northumberland who was his fellow&#8211;prisoner in the Tower, interested me particularly. There are many relics of Queen Elizabeth &amp; Mary Queen of Scots. Nothing could have been more urbane than the Duke's behaviours, which, perhaps, was more than I had reason to expect. We parted in much amiability. After looking at the fine parish church, &amp; having tea at the Vicarage, we returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[309]</hi></p>
         <p>I received the following letter from Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Henson,</p>
         <p>I am afraid that, having read only one page, I wrote a rather misleading postcard about your Spiritual Healing. I am in considerable agreement with your fear of the tendencies of 'spiritual healing', &amp; the excitement it causes. But when I read the book through I found myself much less in agreement with it than I had hoped – as I dare say you would expect But I cannot but say no. I feel disposed to argue – finding so much of your argument unfair &amp; indeed uncritical. But I refrain.</p>
         <p>I hope you are well. Yours ever.</p>
         <p>Charles Gore.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I must place that in the scales against Archbishop D'Arcy's<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> frank approval of the book, The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" today has half a column about the book, very coldly written and evidently out of accord with my whole attitude. But it does not actually criticize or censure! The Archbishop of Dublin writes rather a perturbed letter. He evidently is in bondage to the text of Scripture, &amp; probably represents the general body of Evangelicals, as well in England as in Ireland. </p></body></text></TEI>
