<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[276]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I left Birmingham at 8.45a.m. and arrived in York at 12.45p.m. After lunching in the hotel and getting my hair cut, I walked to S. William's college, and addressed a meeting of the Preventive and Rescue association. The other speaker was a rather nice&#8211;looking lady from Lawbridge, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Rackham</hi>, who spoke well, but with a dangerously "feminist" bias. There were several reporters present, rather to my surprise, for I had supposed that this was a private meeting for workers, &amp; my address was designed accordingly. After the meeting, I had tea at the Deanery, where the Archbishop picked me up, &amp; carried me to Bishopthorpe, where we had a "small early dinner", &amp; then returned for the "public meeting" at 8p.m. This was a failure. There was a small audience, &amp; no reporters. This was the more annoying as my speech had been prepared with a direct view to making public my attitude of "Birth control" and "sex&#8211;education". However, it matters little, &amp; it may well have been a good thing that my opinions on these grave questions should remain unknown. After the meeting we returned to Bishopthorpe, &amp; talked on many things until after 11p.m. when we retired. The weather was foggy and then wet. </p></body></text></TEI>