<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[298]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Two rival philosophies or theologies, which I believe ultimately involve conflicting conceptions of God and His mode of operation, are contending for the soul of the Church of England. In our judgment, one of these philosophies is incompatible with the historical character of that Church. If it prevails, the Church of England, as history knows it, will vanish. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Storr</hi><persName xml:id="1899"></persName>. Oct: 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1925. at Lambeth.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the whole day in writing letters, clearing off the accumulation of the week. In acknowledging to the publishers the receipt of 6 copies of my book on <hi rend="underline">Spiritual Healing</hi>, I took occasion to tell Sir Hume Gordon that I couldn't possibly send the MS. of the book on the <hi rend="underline">Reformation</hi> by December 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, as I had foolishly (but conditionally) promised. I sent copies of the Notes to Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName>, and to Sir Frank Brown.</p>
         <p>I bought for the relatively large sum of &#x00A3;3.14.3. the reprint of Scot's <hi rend="underline">Discovery of Witchcraft</hi> (1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> edition. 1584) edited by Brinsley Nicholson, &amp; published by Elliot Stock in 1886. It is difficult to justify this extravagance, but this book is one I have long wanted.</p></body></text></TEI>