<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[301]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>A people which is without a Bible in its mother tongue, or is restrained from using it, or wilfully neglects it, is also imperfect, or degenerate, or lifeless in its apprehension of Christian Truth, and proportionately bereft of the strength which flows from a living Creed.</p>
         <p>v. Westcott<persName xml:id="1047"></persName>. History of the English Bible. p. 3.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I paid my half&#8211;year's rates: and wrote a few letters. Then I read Westcott's History of the English Bible with a view to the lecture on Tyndale. </p>
         <p>Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> sent me a cutting from the "Daily Express" of Oct. 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> headed "Faith&#8211;Healers Attacked" containing nearly a column of notice of my book, garnished with a rather truculent picture of the author!</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park during the afternoon with Beck. Canon Tuckey &amp; his wife, and Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName> &amp; his wife, came to lunch.</p>
         <p>Lilley &amp; his wife with a certain Miss Fox, who chauffeured them, came here from Edinburgh, bringing with them a dog. I had a good deal of talk with Lilley, who has now to all appearance reconciled himself to living out his life in Hereford, from whence, on any reasonable principle of preferment, he ought long since to have moved to a larger sphere.</p></body></text></TEI>