<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[297]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Stephen, the young footman who has been looking after me, packed my bag – a dropsical phenomenon. He hails from Bucks, and has served in the Army. He is 25 years old, so was too young for the war. He loves birds &amp; horses, being of a country breed himself, yet he prefers life in the towns, because <hi rend="underline">there</hi> he has friends &amp; amusements. I gave him Buchan's novel "John M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Nab", with which I had solaced sleepless nights.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I spent the morning in the House of Bishops</hi>, where, perhaps, the pace and dignity of our proceedings were advanced by the absence of the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's on the count of illness. We engaged in the work of mangling Mattins &amp; Evensong. <hi rend="bold underline">I urged that the question of the Athanasian Creed should be debated in public, and the requisite 6 bishops supported me. These, to my surprise, included neither Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, Nixon, nor Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName>.</hi> I lunched at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; then went back to Church House, where I continued until it was time to get away for my return to Auckland. I travelled by the 5.30 p.m. express, having for my travelling companions two members of the wealthy West Hartlepool merchants, of which one now sits as Member for the Sedgefield division. Leng met me with the car at Darlington.</p></body></text></TEI>