<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[310]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The Editor of John O'London's Weekly sends me some letters that he has received from readers of my Article on "Religion and Science". The do not, perhaps, come to much, but they are serious &amp; apparently sincere.</p>
         <p>I went to Durham, and spent the day in the Chapter House where the Sub&#8211;Commission entrusted with reporting to Durham Cathedral held its session. The members of the Sub&#8211;Commission were, I think, all present, and so were the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> &amp; Canons. The Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Edmundsbury &amp; Ipswich (Chairman) presided, &amp; called on me to expound my scheme, which I did, &amp; then answered questions. The Dean followed, and excelled himself in tactless but hostile irrelevance! Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> and Dawson&#8211;Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> spoke well. I did not get the impression that the Sub&#8211;Commission were really favourable. After lunching with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, I returned to the Chapter house, where the inquiry was resumed. I insisted that the Bishop <hi rend="underline">was </hi>Ordinary of the Cathedral, which was agreed to. I came away in time to catch the train back to Durham. Stocks sent me from the Cosin Library a bulky volume of Sir Thomas More's English Works in black&#8211;letter. It is horribly hard on one's eyes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[311]</hi></p>
         <p>Sir Arthur<persName xml:id="5262"></persName> and Lady Pease came to dinner. I had hoped that he would have got into talk with Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, &amp; given him some first&#8211;hand information about the mining industry: <hi rend="bold underline">but that calamitous deafness defeated my intention</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi> I did, however, myself get much from him. He was less despondent over the ultimate destiny of the industry than I had expected, but he was very pessimistic over the immediate future. The subsidy would, he thought, reach a total expenditure of at least &#x00A3;25,000,000. He was disconcerting on the subject of the railway&#8211;men, who would probably join the miners if trouble ensured when the subsidy was ended next May. He was strongly opposed to the purchase of minerals (Royalties) by the State, and he did not think anything could be done in the matter of "by&#8211;products". I asked him whether he thought the coal&#8211;commission was a strong one. He replied that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Herbert Samuel</hi> was clever, but yielding that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Beveridge</hi> was tiresome &amp; inefficient: that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lawrence</hi> was an honest but nor very intelligent soldier: &amp; that the other man was well&#8211;enough. He said that attendance at these Commissions, &amp; preparation of the statistics required inflicted on the Coal Companies much inconvenience &amp; expenditure.</p></body></text></TEI>
