<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[332]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I had an accumulation of letters to write, and the writing of them occupied most of the morning. I wrote a number of cheques, and then received a parson named Chalmers, who is Secretary for C. M. S. in this part of England. I was favourably impressed by him, &amp; kept him to lunch. Lilburne came by appointment to talk over my offer of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's, West Hartlepool. He decided to "place himself in my hands" i.e. accept it. After these parsons had departed I walked round the Park with Beck.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>" has a notice of my 'Notes' which is respectful and even complimentary. What can this portend?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> arrived to spend the week&#8211;end. I took occasion of his presence to consult him on the draft of the Ecclesiastical Courts Commission's Report. He shared my strong objection to the proposed Final Court.</p>
         <p>General Harrington telegraphed to say that he had a swollen face, &amp; could not come to lunch tomorrow as had been arranged. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> also made some plea for absenting himself. So our luncheon party shrank quickly to very modest proportions. We are all growing old, and disinclined to exert ourselves. Why should we ever leave our own fire&#8211;sides?</p></body></text></TEI>
