<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[304]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>I have put twenty of these witchmongers to silence with this one question; to wit. Whether a witch that can turn a woman into a cat &amp; can also turn a cat into a woman?</p>
         <p>Scot's Discovery. p.74.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I wrote a "Birthday letter" to Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, &amp; sent him the "Notes". Also, I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> telling him to take the advice of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wallis on the matter of matriculation. Also, to the Principal of Bede College counselling him to walk as Agag "delicately" in the matter of the sectarian students, who, for conscience sake, absent themselves from the Chapel services, &amp; make no good use of the freedom they thus obtain. Then an absurd little man called Parsons had an interview with me about an absurd little society called "the Crusaders", which has presented an Altar to Stranton Church in memory of one of their number, &amp; wants me to bless it. I told him that I was not quite such a jackass as was apparently thought i.e. I conveyed as much in suitable language. He lunched and departed. I motored to Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Religious Education Board. Colonel Thomlinson was elected Treasurer in place of Canon Brown. Then I went to the Castle &amp; interviewed 4 applicants for Diocesan grants. After this I went back to Auckland.</p></body></text></TEI>