<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[259]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The flames which closed over Savonarole had early convinced Niccolo Machiavelli that no reform was to be looked for from Rome.</p>
         <p>Prof. F. X. Kraus of Munich in C. H. ii.5</p>
         </div>
         <p>Lord Halifax has a tasty letter in the Times in which he writes rudely about "remembering the time when he used to beg the Bishop to be less extreme in his opinions". I wrote a rejoinder, which, however, I was in two minds about sending, for he is nearly 90 years old, &amp; of course, on that account privileged. However, I did send it. It is plain enough that the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Abb&#x00E9; Portal's</hi> statements have caused something like consternation in the Anglo&#8211;Catholic Camp.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Car&#x00F6;e</hi><persName xml:id="648"></persName> telegraphed from Hartlepool to announce his coming for the night; &amp; appeared in due course in time for dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Shadwell</hi><persName xml:id="30"></persName> continues his Articles on "Communism" in the "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Times"</hi>. They are certainly very disconcerting, and the proceedings at Liverpool cannot dissipate the unpleasant impression which they make. Two facts emerge clearly from the exchange of civilities between Scarborough and Liverpool – <hi rend="bold underline">that "Labour" is now confessedly &amp; unreservedly "Socialist", and that "Communism" is making rapid way with the rank &amp; file of the Trade Unions</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>