<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[289]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I got to Lambeth in good time for the Celebration in the Chapel at 8.30 a.m. So far as I could see, all the Archbishops &amp; Bishops were present, save only the Bishop of Southwell who is mortally ill. At 10.30 <hi rend="bold underline">the session in the Hoare Memorial Hall</hi> began with an excellent address by the Archbishop, clear, dignified, &amp; short. Then the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Norwich</hi> moved his resolution dividing the Revision into 2 parts. He disclaimed any intention of postponing the treatment of Holy Communion to the Greek Kalends, <hi rend="bold underline">but I insisted that that was the inevitable effect of the motion, and all his supporters confessed that their reason for supporting it was nothing else</hi>. My speech was delivered from carefully prepared notes, &amp; did, though very brief, state that I conceive to be the true issue. The main object of Revision, I said, was to restore the reign of law in the Church of England. I spoke of the worsening of the situation since 1906, when the Royal Commission issued its Report: described the effect of the War, &amp; the Anglo&#8211;Catholick Movement which had exploited it. I pointed out what was the distinctive character of that movement. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[290]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Then I described the alternative before the Church viz: </hi><hi rend="italic underline">either</hi><hi rend="italic"> to move along the line of least resistance by dealing only with the non&#8211;controversial matters, &amp; leaving the Holy Communion alone, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">with the result that the Church w</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> be completely Romanized within a generation, or to carry through a careful, considerate, &amp; complete Revision which would satisfy men of goodwill, guard he type of English Religion, &amp; make possible the restoration of Law &amp; Order</hi><hi rend="italic">. My conclusion was as follows:&#8211; 'We come to our task as English bishops, pledged to guard the truth which we have received, &amp; not free in conscience to assent to changes which w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> introduce error, but also as Statesmen, who must take account of actual forces. For myself I sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> judge no sacrifices of preference or sentiment too great if it would bring peace &amp; harmony to the Church, but as a loyal son of the Church of England, charged with great responsibility in its administration, I will not purchase the fallacious promise of peace by concessions which cannot but draw with them consequences of ultimate disaster to the supreme</hi><hi rend="bold">[291]</hi> <hi rend="italic">interest which the Church itself exists to serve – the interest of Christ's Religion". The discussion was continued until lunch&#8211;time, when the division was taken – The Bishop of Norwich lost his motion. Only 9 bishops voted for it, and 24 against. The minority consisted of the following:&#8211; Norwich, Worcester, Birmingham, Gloucester, Exeter, Sodor &amp; Man, Bradford, Bristol, and Bath &amp; Wells</hi>.</p>
         <p>I dined in Par Lane. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hardinge</hi><persName xml:id="1588"></persName> was the only other guest. We had much interesting conversation. I raised the question of Kenya, &amp; found him most interesting. He spoke freely of his Indian experiences, which had opened his eyes to the ill&#8211;treatment which Indians and Africans have to endure at the hands of the Colonists. I asked him whether he thought the policy of Indianisation could succeed, &amp; <hi rend="underline">he replied decisively in the negative</hi>. After dinner we discussed the O.M.S. of which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hardinge</hi> is the President. I gave him some information about the County of Durham, &amp; pointed out some difficulties.</p></body></text></TEI>