<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[331]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I left 21 Park Lane after breakfast, and went to the Club. After making a brief visit to the Assembly, where I found a futile discussion of Housing in progress, I went to Hugh Rees. Then I collected my bags, and went to King's Cross, where I caught the 1.15 p.m. express, which arrived an hour after scheduled time at Darlington, being delayed by a fog between Doncaster &amp; York. Leng met me with the car, &amp; brought me to the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Queen Alexandra</hi> died at Sandringham this afternoon in her 81<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> year. The Prince of Wales cancelled his engagement to lunch in the City. There can be no doubt that this Royal Lady had endeared herself to the nation, so that her departure will evoke much regret. No breath of scandal ever suggested any unworthy behaviour on her part. The public sympathized with her as a wife whose lot had not been the easiest. A beautiful face and genuine kindness of heart go a long way in this world, &amp; her Majesty had them both.</p>
         <p>My godson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Spelling</hi><persName xml:id="7"></persName>, sent me &#x00A3;4.3.4 being 1000 pennies, to the Escombe Repair Fund. He accompanies his gift by a letter in which he gives high praise to the '<hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi>'.</p></body></text></TEI>
