<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[312]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925. Guy Fawkes' Day. </hi></p>
         <p>I went in to Durham, and again attended the meeting of the Sub–Committee. The accounts of the Cathedral were considered, and I was amused by the Receiver's candid confession that "for himself he could not distinguish between a plough and a turnip". <hi rend="bold underline">I was impressed by the intelligence with which the Bishop of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> E. and J. conducted the business. He was plainly at home in the sphere of finance.</hi> The cost of the Choir, including the incomes of the 4 minor canons, is about £6000 per annum. I lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight, &amp; then returned to Auckland, and paid the month's house accounts. The first number of the <hi rend="doubleunderline">'Bishoprick'</hi> made its '<hi rend="underline">débût</hi>. It has a mud–coloured cover, and is monstrously dull. I motored to Annfield Plain, and there "admitted" Dick to the perpetual curacy of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's, in succession to the unctuous and intolerable Talbot. The mean little iron church was barely filled with a congregation, in which the devout sex predominated. There was a good attendance of the local clergy, headed by the Rural Dean. At intervals sounds from without reminded us that Guy Fawkes had still some observants! After service I returned to Auckland. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[313]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">"Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the well is deep"</hi> – <hi rend="doubleunderline">this was Ralph's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> sufficient criticism of Carnegie's new book on "Anglicanism"</hi>. My sapient friend, who is more deaf than ever, went off about noon. He has gained a surprisingly prominence among his contemporaries. </p>
         <p> "The newspapers have discovered that I am good 'copy', and they are working up a 'stunt'", he observed with reference to the rather hectic headlines, which announced a review of his essay in the newly published volume, '<hi rend="underline">Science, Religion and Reality</hi>". I asked him whether he would have gone to the <hi rend="underline">Westminster Deanery</hi> if he had been offered the opportunity, &amp; he replied that the transfer had been discussed. He would remain at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's until the public wearied of him. We groaned together over the gloomy future which lay before civilization. He thought the western world was marching to a great catastrophe; but, perhaps two centuries ahead, the world might recover. I pointed out that the worse feature in the present situation was the evident deterioration of humanity itself, and <hi rend="underline">this</hi> factor promised nothing but continuous decline. He did not dissent. We parted in a mood of profound depression which not even his wit could lighten. </p></body></text></TEI>