<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[273]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Nations would do well </p>
         <p>To exhort their truncheons from the puny hands</p>
         <p>Of heroes, whose infirm and baby minds</p>
         <p>Are gratified with mischief, and who spoil,</p>
         <p>Because men suffer it, their toy, the World.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cowper</hi>. "<hi rend="underline">The Winter Morning Walk</hi>".</p>
         </div>
         <p>I occupied the morning in making notes for my addresses at York to the Diocesan Preventive &amp; Rescue Association. The subject is utterly disgusting, and the people whom it interests hardly less so. Here are some of the headings, appalling enough in themselves:&#8211;</p>
         <p>Disappearance of the old Reticence on Sex&#8211;questions – how far wholesome, &amp; within what limits.</p>
         <p>Psycho&#8211;Analysis, &amp; Sex&#8211;instruction in Schools based on it, how far likely to be good for children or teacher.</p>
         <p>"Birth&#8211;Control". how far morally legitimate in itself: &amp; how far to be publically advocated.</p>
         <p>Publication of Obscene Matter in Divorce reports etc., how far to be restricted by law.</p>
         <p>Venereal Disease – prophylactics against.</p>
         <p>Feeble&#8211;minded – their prodigal fertility, how far to be restrained, or even sterilized.</p>
         <p>Marriage &amp; Divorce – </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[274] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, &amp; took train to York, where I changed trains, &amp; had an hour's wait. I arrived at 7.30 p.m. &amp; drove to the Principal's house (67 Wellington Road, Edgbaston). There was a dinner&#8211;party which included Sir Gilbert Bailing, an eminent surgeon, &amp; Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>. Also the Bishop of Birmingham<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Barnes.</p>
         <p>Sir E. Bailing said that one reason for the sudden decline &amp; all&#8211;but&#8211;collapse of the French after Nivelle's defeat was the fact that <hi rend="underline">no provision had been made for the wounded, about 100,000, who were scattered about France in a woeful state. The medical organisation of the French Army was deplorable</hi>.</p>
         <p>It is clear to me that the Bishop's difficulties in Birmingham are not solely attributable to his conflict with the Anglo&#8211;Catholics. He is a member of the labour party, &amp; tends to emphasize the fact. Birmingham is the home of a rather aggressive Imperialism, and this temper is most strongly found among the Church&#8211;people. He is not only a pacifist, but so quixotically honest that he feels bound to press that character on the public notice. He told the British Legionaries that he held "conscientious objectors" to be deserving of as much respect as ex&#8211;service men; an opinion which was more exasperating than welcome or convincing! </p></body></text></TEI>