<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[318]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>After the tempest of yesterday the weather was fine. My post included "Birthday letters" from Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>, Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName>. Also, a friendly note from Hadow, thanking me for a copy of the 'Notes'. The Bishop of Limerick wrote approvingly of them, and sent me hiss Address on Bishop Jebb, which I found very interesting.</p>
         <p>I went in to Durham, and attended the installation of the mayor, Alderman Waite, who entered on the office for the second time in response to the unanimous request for the Corporation. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> was present, &amp; we both made short speeches then everybody went from the Town Hall to the Freemasons' Hall, where were refreshments &amp; more speeches. I walked with the ex&#8211;mayor, Holliday, a Papist, &amp; was very friendly with him. After this function I went to the Deanery and picked up <hi rend="doubleunderline">R. J. Campbell</hi>, who had promised to stay the night at Auckland. He had been summoned home to minister the Sacrament to a sick parishioner. However he came out to the Castle &amp; had tea. I sent him in the car to Darlington to catch the 5.18p.m. express.</p>
         <p>George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> telegraphed his congratulations on my Birthday, my god&#8211;children, Alfred Spelling<persName xml:id="7"></persName> and Audry Hall<persName xml:id="1416"></persName> wrote me affectionately.</p></body></text></TEI>