<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[299]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 8 communicants, including <hi rend="doubleunderline">James Wilson</hi>, the new butler's boy, who entered my service last week. His predecessor was a good lad, who very sensibly decided to accept a position at an adjacent colliery, where there was some prospect. I am sorry to lose him, but think he has chosen wisely, for he was not naturally well suited for 'service'.</p>
         <p>I prepared notes for the evening's sermon, wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Robin</hi><persName xml:id="4430"></persName>, read the 'Observer', and walked in the Park for an hour with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. The autumnal colouring seen in the sunlight were ravishingly beautiful.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">S. Paul's, Spennymoor</hi>, is celebrating its "Jubilee". I attended Evensong, &amp; dedicated a new Altar. Also I preached to a congregation which filled the Church to its utmost capacity. My text was "<hi rend="underline">Man doth not live by bread alone</hi>", &amp; my sermon, delivered from notes, was closely listened to. The Vicar of Tudhoe, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bell</hi>, carried the pastoral staff. There is quite a flourishing troop of the Church Lads Brigade in the parish. They lined the path, &amp; gave me Khaki: for, indeed, the discipline of military service "bites on" to something in the adolescent which nothing else appeals to with equal success.</p></body></text></TEI>