<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[319]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Macdonald writes to "congratulate" me on "<hi rend="bold underline">The Bishoprick</hi>". "It is exactly what Fred Glyn of Brancepeth and his friends sighed for and aimed at when we ran the effort under the same name years ago. We wanted to combine the Diocesan Gazette with something worth reading: but were <hi rend="underline">blocked</hi>. I have turned the pages with delight and admiration".</p>
         <p>After writing some letters, &amp; revising two old sermons which I mean to make serve at Leeds, I set to work on an article for the '<hi rend="underline">Evening Standard'</hi>, taking as my subject (on the editor's suggestion) the attempt to work up a crisis on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph's</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName> Article, in '<hi rend="underline">Science, Religion &amp; Reality'</hi>. I worked at it until it was finished &amp; despatched, but it was poor hasty stuff equally unworthy of theme and author!</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and spent an hour and a half in examining the Ordination candidates in their "Anglican classic". Three took Butler's Analogy and three Jewel's Apology. None of them really knew much about their book, but I "passed" them. I returned to Auckland in time for dinner, a violent storm of sleet proceeded all the way. Olive<persName xml:id="1686"></persName> wrote me a Birthday letter.</p></body></text></TEI>
