<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[303]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Bishop of Glasgow &amp; Galloway</hi>, in thanking me for a copy of 'Notes, takes occasion to send me a newspaper cutting of a letter by <hi rend="doubleunderline">McClelland</hi>, the Minister of Trinity Congregational Church (where I am pledged to preach &amp; lecture in April 1926) in which he sets for his (extremely heretical) notions of the Trinity. I replied that my preaching in the Church did not, &amp; could not, imply my agreement with the minister's views. Nevertheless, I anticipate that trouble will grow out of my visit.</p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, &amp; opened a <hi rend="underline">Palestine Exhibition</hi>. The secretary in charge told me that he had been in Kenya, &amp; that the treatment of the natives was cruelly oppressive. I returned to Durham, &amp; had tea with <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. G. Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName>. Then, accompanied by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; Wilson, I motored to <hi rend="underline">Monkheseldon</hi>, &amp; collated the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. J. A. Little</hi> to the vicarage of the united parish. The Church was crowded. I thought it well to allude to the long delay in filling up the incumbency. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hicks</hi>, the self&#8211;sufficient &amp; tiresome churchwarden, was much in evidence to Clayton's exceeding annoyance, but everything went well enough. On my return to Auckland I found a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Abp. D'Arcy</hi><persName xml:id="1361"></persName><hi rend="bold underline">acknowledging in terms of emphatic approval my gift of the 'Notes'. But he, like Lilley is a flatterous Irishman. Still he is an eminent man, &amp; there was no reason why he should have written so approvingly if he didn't approve</hi>. </p></body></text></TEI>