<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[277]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left Bishopthorpe after breakfast and travelled to Darlington, where Leng met me with the car, &amp; motored me to Auckland, in time for me to go through my letters before lunch. <hi rend="bold underline">Among them was one from Old Lord Halifax, thanking me for my sermon at Birmingham, of which he had read a report in the Yorkshire Post, and, I suppose, holding out the olive&#8211;branch!</hi> After lunch I motored to Barnard Castle, &amp; presided over a special meeting of the Governors? to consider how to effect economies in the working of the school. Bircham<persName xml:id="5380"></persName>, was of course, offensive, but there was no explosion. On returning to the castle I wrote a number of letters, &amp; then, after an early dinner, went to the town hall to witness an entertainment arranged by the Waifs &amp; Strays society. In the "interval" I made a short speech in advocacy of the cause, &amp; then went back to the castle. </p>
         <p>A long letter reached me from Bishop Knox in answer to my request that he would give me frankly his views about disruption A. its rightfulness B. its likelihood &amp; C. its procedure. He has evidently been thinking over the subject. But I doubt whether there are half a dozen bishops on the Bench who would have the courage to break away however gross the provocation might be. The age of churches is past. </p></body></text></TEI>