<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[324]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>The bitter cold continues, and there is a waxing frost. I accompanied mine hostess to Meanwood Church, where the annual service of ex&#8211;Service Men was held. Colonel Kitson Clark led about 120 men to the function, which was impressive and well&#8211;arranged. When the proceeding in the Church were concluded, we all marched to the Memorial in the Churchyard. Here we stood freezing and bare&#8211;headed while the brass&#8211;band played Chopin's March to the bitter end! Then we sang a hymn, and at the Vicar's request I pronounced the Benediction. <hi rend="bold underline">At 2.30p.m. there was a great gathering of Freemasons in Leeds Parish Church, all the 14 Lodges of the City being represented</hi>. Lord Lascelles read the first lesson, and read it remarkably well. There was much, and excellent musick, and then I preached on Truthfulness. The congregation, which practically filled the church, was attentive, &amp; I think heard me easily. I had tea in the Freemasons' Hall, &amp; then lay perdee [sic] in the Church Institute until Evensong when I preached on "The Love of Money" to a considerable congregation. By this time the fog had become inconveniently thick. However we got back to Meanwoodside without accident.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[325]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitson Clark</hi> is an interesting man. He was educated at Shrewsbury School and Trinity College, Cambridge where his father was, and his son is a Fellow. He himself took a first in Classics, and keeps up his classical reading. His present interest is Roman Britain. He is the head of a long established and well&#8211;reputed engineering firm, which manufactures locomotives. But it has fallen on evil days. The great railway companies prefer to manufacture their own locomotives, and the exorbitant demands of the Trade Unions have destroyed any chance of making good in the international market. He spoke very openly of the financial embarrassment into which the firm had been brought. The bank will no longer advance money, &amp; its last advance was made on the security of his private fortune. I inquired whether many manufacturers were in a similar plight, and he replied that they were. 'We are at the end of our resources' he said. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kitson Clark</hi> is an able, versatile, public&#8211;spirited man, very proud of his family and of his civic record. I suspected that he has "too many irons in the fire". But it is sad hearing that men of his type cannot hold their place in our commercial life.</p></body></text></TEI>