<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[261]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>While dressing it occurred to me that I would write an article for the <hi rend="underline">Evening Standard</hi> on <hi rend="underline">"The fatal Imposture &amp; Force of Words"</hi>, to borrow the heading of a famous sermon by <hi rend="doubleunderline">South</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler's</hi> Sermon "<hi rend="underline">Upon the Government of the Tongue</hi>" may be useful. I will illustrate from "Copec", C.E.T.S.<orgName xml:id="188"></orgName>, C.E.I N.S. and the recent congresses at Scarborough, Liverpool, &amp; Stockholm. It is the political analogue of commercial advertising – a calculated bluff, or a game of imposition.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><persName xml:id="552"></persName> writes to me a rather interesting letter, in which he discusses the reasons for the distressing state of things in Durham. He mentions three: (1) the diocese has suffered from having two extraordinarily bad Bishops – Baring and Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>. (2) the wide spread extension of Council Schools. (3) the failure of the University of Durham. I think he ought in justice to add <hi rend="underline">the course of political &amp; economic development, which has stimulated all the tendencies of the age which are anti&#8211;Church, and even anti&#8211;Christian</hi>. "You have tremendously uphill work now. I should think you wanted really twice as many clergy as you have got". Throughout England the situation of the Church is very difficult but, perhaps nowhere (except possibly in the dioceses of Sheffield, Southwell, &amp; Lichfield) so difficult as in the diocese of Durham. Here we are moving quickly to a complete collapse of the system.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[262]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Confusion and complexity in writing is indeed without excuse, because any one may, if he pleases, know whether he understands &amp; sees through what he is about; and it is unpardonable for a man to lay his thoughts before others, when he is conscious that he himself does not know whereabouts he is, or how the matter before him stands. It is coming abroad in disorder, which he ought to be dissatisfied to find himself in at home.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler</hi>. <hi rend="underline">Preface to Sermons at the Rolls</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I read this passage from "our own Butler" to the Ordination candidates, when they came to me for their private interviews.</p>
         <p>The 'Times' prints my letter. I am more than ever doubtful as to the wisdom of writing it: but I didn't want the legend to grow up that I had been originally one of Lord Halifax's lambs, &amp; his letter did unquestionably suggest nothing less.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshank</hi><persName xml:id="1898"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName> came over during the afternoon, &amp; had some talk with the candidates. After dinner I gave a sort of charge in the Chapel, poor stuff and ill&#8211;prepared.</p></body></text></TEI>