<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[287]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>The Christian pastor, bowed to earth</p>
         <p>With thankless toil, and vile esteemed</p>
         <p>Still travailing in second birth</p>
         <p>Of souls that will not be redeemed.</p>
         <p>Yet steadfast set to do his part,</p>
         <p>And fearing most his own vain heart:</p>
         <p>Keble</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is not a picture that allures the eyes of modern youth!</p>
         <p>I left Nottingham by 8.43 a.m. (Great Central) which reached London shortly after 11 am. Leaving my bag in Park Lane, I drove to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Then I visited the barber, and the bookseller. After lunch, I walked to Westminster, <hi rend="bold underline">and attended the meeting of the House of Bishops</hi>. The proceedings, which were of a preliminary nature, were conducted in private. More was a long discussion over the question whether our debates sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be open to the public. Their Graces produced a series of resolutions <hi rend="bold underline">the effect of which was to keep the discussions private save when one third of the bishops desired publicity. I opposed this, and ultimately the proportion of bishops needed was reduced to six i.e. 1/6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of the number. The Archbishop of C. was evidently anxious to conciliate me, but, I fear, my course will be very offensive to him!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[288]</hi></p>
         <p>I dined at the Ship Restaurant in Whitehall with 10 other Bishops, members of the Missionary Committee, of which (by a foolish deference to an old friendship with Donaldson) I am a member. We were the following viz. Salisbury, Manchester, Winchester, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Albans, Peterborough, Bradford, Coventry, Chelmsford, Durham, &amp; Chester. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Garfield Williams, who is some kind of a missionary secretary, was also of the party. After a rather gross &amp; unwholesome meal, we began the serious business. It appears that a serious of reports has been prepared, describing the problems which confront the Church over the whole area of foreign missionary enterprise: that these reports are to be presented by "experts" at a great gathering in London on January 26&#8211;8 next year: that 30 or 40 representatives from every diocese are to attend this gathering with the object of acquiring knowledge &amp; enthusiasm which w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> qualify them for "enthusing" their several dioceses. It is a grandiose scheme enough, but it will cost much money. I doubt whether my poor broken diocese can take any effective part in it.</p></body></text></TEI>