<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[333]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">The Sunday next before Advent, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I motored to Gateshead, and preached at Christ Church, prefacing my sermon by a few words about Queen Alexandra. After the service the 'Dead March' was played on the organ. I returned at once to Auckland Castle, where our reduced party came to lunch viz. the High Sheriff &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Stobart, General Thwaites, Captain &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bradford. After the guests had departed Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> and I walked round the Park. On returning to the Castle I wrote to the Archbishop of York explaining that I should not attend the meeting of the Commission, and making some criticisms of the draft&#8211;report. I indicated my disagreement with the proposed constitution of the Final Court. On this point I feel strongly enough to sign a separate Report, if the majority of the Commission adhere to the draft.</p>
         <p>My pusillanimous decision to absent myself from the Commission will give me four days, which had otherwise been spent in London, and will save me perhaps as much as &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">8</hi>. If, as seems not improbable, there develops a considerable fog, I shall be spared much discomfort and some risk. Nevertheless, to "cut engagements is ever a base performance!</p></body></text></TEI>
