<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[320]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Rather to my surprise the Bishop of Manchester<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> writes to say that, having read my book, he is "in almost complete agreement with me". Considering his close union with Gove this is rather astonishing. The <hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi> has a notice of the book, polite but rather frigid. The writer (as was clearly the case with the author of the notice in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>) is in sympathy with the faith&#8211;healers, <hi rend="doubleunderline">R. J. Campbell</hi> writes approvingly of the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> which he thinks is "something entirely new in Diocesan literature".</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; attended the High Sheriff's lunch in the Shire Hall. It was mainly composed of military men. I congratulated <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Stobart</hi>, the High Sheriff, on being appointed to the command of the D.L.J. Brigade. My little speech in proposing his health seemed to be much appreciated. After lunch I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Fawkes<persName xml:id="1082"></persName> writes: "The Bishop of Winchester said not long ago that he looked at – I forget whether it was Prohibition or Spiritual Healing – "with guarded approval". <hi rend="underline">Nothing</hi> can keep a man who expresses himself in that way from Canterbury!" An oracular, friendly, yet non&#8211;committed mode of speech is certainly very common among their Lordships of the English Bench. </p></body></text></TEI>