<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[315]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The evidence seems to me to point to a purposiveness running through all nature, sleeping in the stone, dreaming in the flower, and partially awake &amp; conscious in man, a single purpose which points to a God who is both immanent and transdescent.</p>
         <p>v. Inge<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. I.c. 367.</p>
         </div>
         <p>A stormy day throughout with torrents of rain. I motored to Durham, and, after attending the Board of Finance which elected M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wylie to be Diocesan Surveyors in the room of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Moscroft resigned, and lunching with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, I presided over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference in the Chapter House. Nicholson, the Organist of Westminster Abbey, addressed us on the subject of "Music in Church". I think the audience were interested, and some questioned were asked, which he answered. Then I summed up &amp; the meeting dispersed. I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; Angel<persName xml:id="1812"></persName> went to the play to see the 'Three Musketeers'. I dined alone, &amp; concerned myself with preparing notes for tomorrow's sermons, and clearing up my study.</p></body></text></TEI>
