<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[307]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Pompanatius writeth that the kings of France do cure the disease called now the king's evil, or queen's evil; which hath been always thought, &amp; to this day is supposed to be a miraculous and peculiar gift, and a special grace given to the kings &amp; queens of England. Which some refer to the propriety of their persons, some of the peculiar gift of God, &amp; some to the efficacy of words. But if the French king use it no worse than our Princess doth, God will not be offended thereat: for her majesty only useth godly and divine prayer, with some alms, &amp; referreth the cure to God and to the physician.</p>
         <p>Reginald Scot's Discovery. A.D. 1584</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ralph Inge</hi><persName xml:id="427"></persName> arrived in the course of the morning, and I talked with him until lunch. Afterwards I motored into Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Committee of Bede College. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Braley</hi><persName xml:id="5464"></persName>, our new Principal is a man of courage and determination. After tea with his wife, I returned to Auckland. I sent, as I had promised, copies of the 'Notes' to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; Ernest. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went out to a concert at Willington. Ralph and I had much talk together. Frank came to see me. </p></body></text></TEI>
