<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[328]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A territorial Colonel came to breakfast. I walked across the Park to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and read the papers. Then I went to the Church House, and spent the day in the Assembly, where the discussion of the Clergy Pensions Measure was proceeding under the pilotage of that astonishing octogenarian, Lord Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">I dined at Grillions</hi>. The following members were there:–</p>
         <p>Lord Balfour</p>
         <p> " Fitz Alan</p>
         <p> " Crawford<persName xml:id="5377"></persName></p>
         <p> " Selbourne<persName xml:id="311"></persName></p>
         <p> " Darling</p>
         <p> " Sumner<persName xml:id="5393"></persName></p>
         <p> " Donoughmore</p>
         <p>Sir Owen Seaman</p>
         <p>Sir Ernest Pollock<persName xml:id="5517"></persName></p>
         <p>Sir Gilbert Murray</p>
         <p>Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName></p>
         <p>The Bishop of Durham.</p>
         <p>The conversation was animated, and ranged over a wide area. I sate between Lords Fitz Alan and Sumner – a Papist and an Erastian.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[329]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Reference being made to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Almeric Fitzroy's</hi> recently published '<hi rend="underline">Memoirs</hi>', I raised the question how far it was morally legitimate to record in a private diary the conversations in which one took part. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Crawford</hi> spoke strongly of the arrogance of Fitzroy's conduct. He said that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Queen Victoria</hi> had exacted a promise that he would keep no private diary, when she appointed him (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Fitzroy</hi>) to his office as Secretary to the Privy Council: and that when he sent a presentation copy of his book to her present Majesty, it was returned uncut! It is difficult to imagine a more severe snubbing. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Hugh Cecil</hi> thought it was fair enough to keep a private journal so long as you did not publish it during the life–time of anybody whose reputation could be affected, or whose feelings might be wounded. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Balfour</hi> was in great form, amusing, witty, and amazingly vivacious. As we were putting on hats and coats, he took occasion to thank me for my letter about the attitude of the Reformers towards <hi rend="doubleunderline">Copernicus</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Galileo</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi> and I shared a cab as far as Park Lane. It was quite a pleasant evening.</p></body></text></TEI>