<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[260]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> went by an early train. Colonel Craster and Christian went off after breakfast. The Headmaster of Barnard Castle School, the treasurer, &amp; two of the Governors, Burkitt and Lingford met me here for an informal Committee meeting. This is a drop of no less than 21 boarders this term, a fact which gravely affects the solvency of the school, so gravely as to make the reduction of the staff unavoidable. But as the dismissal of masters is within the control of the Governors, I insisted on a special meeting being convened.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName> &amp; I walked round the Park after lunch. The Ordination Candidates – five in number – arrived in time for Evensong at 7 p.m. The address was given by Baily, the Vicar of Heaterycleugh. It was very simple, the utterance of a good, humble&#8211;minded pastor, whose scheme of duty was as intelligible as it was arduous, but certainly did not include any intellectual effort!</p>
         <p>Shadwell's<persName xml:id="30"></persName> Article in today's Times was disconcerting. It describes Durham as seething with revolutionary feeling, &amp; says that Sunderland is the "Red" centre. Indeed, an open outbreak might occur at any moment, &amp; will almost certainly not be postponed beyond next spring! This is uncomfortable.</p></body></text></TEI>