<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[283]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Remember ye not how in our own time, of all that taught grammar in England, not one understood the Latin tongue? How came we then by the Latin tongue again? Not by them, though we learned certain rules and principles of them, by which we were moved and had an occasion to seek further; but out of the old authors. Even so we seek up old antiquities, out of which we learn, and not of our church: though we received many principles of our church at the beginning, but more falsehood than truth.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyndale</hi>. '<hi rend="underline">Answer to More</hi>'. p.55</p>
         </div>
         <p>The rain fell heavily during the night, and was still falling when the day began. It had amended into "spitting" by the time that <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> left in the motor to visit M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Luirk at the Lakes, &amp; Ernest on the way.</p>
         <p>I travelled to Nottingham by a train which left Bp. Auckland at 12.50 p.m. &amp; changed at Darlington, arriving at 5.8 p.m. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Field met me at the station, &amp; carried me to S. Mary's Vicarage. Three local magnates came to dinner, but I have forgotten their names. &amp; of their conversation have remembered nothing worthy of recording. </p></body></text></TEI>