<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[275]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Robertson</hi> and his mother accompanied me to the cathedral where I preached to a great congregation, in which (so far as I could judge) men greatly predominated. The attention was close and sustained. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Guy Rogers</hi>, Rector of Birmingham, and his wife came to lunch. <hi rend="bold underline">He is filled with all the windy platitudes of Socialism, but is said to be succeeding in his present post</hi>. The University Service was held in the Great Hall of the University, and was attended by a great crowd of students. The acoustics are not good, but I think I made myself heard, though the exertion was considerable. I preached for the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> time in S. John's Sparkhill. This is a large church, not very good in its acoustics, and it was densely crowded. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arrowsmith,</hi> the parson, motored me to Bishopcroft, where I had supper with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><persName xml:id="3581"></persName> and his wife. It seemed to be a fairly commodious house, and is surrounded by some 16 acres of ground. I talked with the Bishop about the ecclesiastical situation in Birmingham. He is rather obstinate and embittered but seems to have been rather badly treated by these? Catholic Fanatics. </p></body></text></TEI>