<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[284]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S. Luke' Day, 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The cross of Christ is composed of many other crosses – is the centre, the type, the essence of all crosses. We must <hi rend="underline">suffer</hi> with Christ whether we <hi rend="underline">believe</hi> in Him or not. We must suffer for the sin of others as for our own: and in this suffering we find a healing and purifying power and element. That is what gives to Christianity, in its simples &amp; most unlettered forms, its force and life. Sin and suffering for sin: a sacrifice, itself mysterious, offered mysteriously to the Divine Nemesis or Law of Sin, &#8211; dread, undefined, unknown, yet sure and irresistible, with the iron necessity of law. This the intellectual Christ, the Platonic – Socrates did not offer: hence his failure, and the success of the Nazarene. Vicisti Galilae".</p>
         <p>"John Inglesant" ii.82.</p>
         <p>"We preach Christ Crucified: to the Jews a stumbling&#8211;block, and to the Greeks foolishness: but to them that are called, both Jews &amp; Greeks, Christ, the power of God and the wisdom of God".</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[285]</hi></p>
         <p>Professor Kirkcaldy, who dined here last night, holds the Chair of Economics, and is said to be a man of some distinction. He was plainly restive when I spoke of the book on 'Kenya', which has so greatly distressed me, and I can easily imagine him the champion of a handling of the African natives which might more easily be commended to the Director of a Chartered Company than to the Disciples of Christ. Indeed, he mentioned the cruel assumption born of a 'corrupt following' of Charles Darwin, that these lower races were doomed to extinction in the struggle for existence. That is the formula which excuses the worst excesses of commercial greed.</p>
         <p>I preached at Mattins to a great congregation of surgeons, doctors &amp; nurses. The Mayor &amp; Corporation also attended in state. My subject was "<hi rend="underline">Christianity &amp; Medicine</hi>", and <hi rend="underline">my sermon was mainly taken from my book on Spiritual Healing, which is due to appear this week</hi>. I gave the MS. to the President of the <hi rend="underline">Doctors' Association</hi>. The attention of my hearers was close, &amp; I think they were impressed. During the afternoon I walked for an hour with mine host. Nottingham is certainly a finely&#8211;placed city, &amp; its historical associations are many &amp; interesting. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[286]</hi></p>
         <p>In the Museum, which was thronged with young men and women of the working class, whose vivacity &amp; talkativeness contrasted notably with sombre taciturnity of our miners, there is a good collection of modern pictures, &amp; some interesting objects. Among the latter I noted particularly the standard which the ill&#8211;fated Charles set up at the beginning of the Civil War, or a facsimile thereof, &amp; the original MS. of Colonel Hutchinson's Memoirs.</p>
         <p>At Evensong I read the lessons, &amp; preached a second sermon. There was a considerable congregation, though the church was not crowded, and it was certainly attentive. Before going to bed, I had a good deal of conversation with mine host. He expresses himself with some vehemence against the Anglo&#8211;Catholics, though he himself passes for a "High Churchman". He thinks that this diocese ought to be divided, but admits that there is no enthusiasm among the people for the division. I was interested to observe that the law was freely broken in the service tonight. The psalms were <hi rend="underline">not</hi> those appointed in the Prayer Book, and after the anthem the prayers were unauthorised, a minge&#8211;mangle of petitions expressed in what seemed to be very stilted forms. The Bishop of Southwell was prayed for by name.</p></body></text></TEI>