<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[306]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">All Saints Day, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>A foggy morning, depressing &amp; disinclining for effort that intolerable bicycle having again broken down. I had to start early in order to make a d&#x00E9;tour, &amp; pick up Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>. This 'laced' the fog's depression with an element of personal irritation, &amp; made me more than ever incompetent for work. One of the worst features of "spiritual" work is the necessity of going through with it, however incongruous your mood may be! The programme must be carried our though you be cast in the part of the Saint &amp; have the mind of a Devil!</p>
         <p>I left the Castle about 9 a.m., picked up Clayton on the road &amp; motored to West Hartlepool. He officiated and preached at S. Oswald's. I preached &amp; celebrated in Stranton Church. On the whole I was pleased with the service. One of the Churchwardens, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Carter</hi>, a brick&#8211;maker, gave me lunch. His eldest son &amp; two charming little girls were also at lunch. Clayton returned with me to Durham, where we attended the service in the Cathedral, and afterwards had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>. As I sate in my throne, I cast back my mind across the five years since I was placed there at my Enthronement on October 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920. The cloud of economic depression was then heavy on the diocese, and it has never really lifted. Today it is heavier than ever. I returned to Auckland, &amp; was in my room around 6 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>