<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[302]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"They(i.e. witches) attain such credit as I have heard to (my great grief) some of the ministry affirm, that they have had in their parish at one instant, XVII or XVIII witches: meaning such as could work miracles supernaturally. Whereby they manifested as well their infidelity and ignorance, in conceiving God's word; as their negligence and error in instructing their flocks".</p>
         <p>Scot's Discovery. p.3.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent my whole morning in writing letters, and preparing notes from a sermon. After lunch I walked round the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lilley</hi>, and the dogs. He expressed great approval of my '<hi rend="underline">Notes</hi>', and added the flatterous remark <hi rend="bold underline">that I was almost the only writer left who troubled himself to write good English</hi>! Of course, he is Irish! I motored to South Shields, and had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hudson Barker</hi><persName xml:id="3575"></persName> about that foolish creature <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jubb</hi>, who, his Roman escapade being summarily ended, now clamours for permission to return to this diocese. Then I went to S. Jude's, &amp; preached a sermon from the words "<hi rend="underline">Other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, even Jesus Christ</hi>".</p></body></text></TEI>