<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[292]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1925.</hi></p>
         <p>We discussed last night the probable consequences of our democratic experiment in India, &amp; Lord S. quoted the opinion of an eminent Anglo–Indian engineer to the effect that "we should lose India in five years". Lord Hardinge<persName xml:id="1588"></persName> thought the process would be more gradual, but he agreed that we should lose India. I asked him whether he knew Ghandi, and he said that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ghandi</hi> was particularly deferential to him, as having championed the cause of the Indians in S. Africa. He was a sincere fanatick.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I was interested in Lord H.s account of the </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Kaiser Wilhelm</hi><hi rend="underline">, whom he claimed to know well.</hi> He believed that he was really opposed to War, but not strong enough to stand up to the warlike tendencies. He was a weak man, physically, mentally, &amp; exorbitantly vain. The Crown Prince had stayed with him in India, &amp; given him much trouble &amp; anxiety by his pranks. Our talk turned on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick Sheppard's</hi><persName xml:id="3611"></persName> criticisms of the Prince of Wales, which we agreed in condemning, while admitting that H.R.H. was a cause of anxiety. So we gossiped pleasantly enough.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[293]</hi></p>
         <p>Another wet warm day made the session of the Bishops' House more than ever fatiguing. We were mostly concerned with trivialities: we were not well directed, for the elder Archbishop was plainly tired, and the younger was plainly confused. The Hall is acoustically bad, &amp; there is much disturbing noise from the street outside. We sate in private, &amp; became irrelevant &amp; conversational, with the result that we made very slow progress. At our present pace I calculate that we shall not complete our task under ten years! The general impression was that we had wasted the day.</p>
         <p>I lunched with Jack Boden<persName xml:id="2936"></persName> in the Oxford &amp; Cambridge Club. He had got a friend of Hutton's, a S. John's Oxford man, named Hoare, to me – an ill–looking but pleasant–speaking man, who was prodigiously friendly at short notice!</p>
         <p>The papers report our proceedings yesterday at some length. It was a practical mistake on the part of 'liberals' to vote in the minority, as it gave the impression of divided counsels.</p>
         <p>I received a characteristically devoted letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jimmie</hi><persName xml:id="3572"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[294]</hi></p>
         <p>I dined in Park Lane with mine host &amp; hostess. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Rennell &amp; Lady Rodd</hi> came to dinner, &amp; we had some interesting conversation. He spoke very favourably of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi>, and said that his position in Italy was more firmly established than before. The fatuity of his opponents had played into his hands. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Rudd</hi> began to talk about religion, which she held to be petering out. None of her servants went to Church, therein following her example. I made such defence of Christianity as was possible, but, indeed, my heart almost fails when I recall the facts, of which I know so much more than the critics of Christianity. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Rennell</hi> expressed great apprehension of the developments in China, where the vast population was in contact with Bolshevism by the land routes. <hi rend="bold underline">Rather to my surprise Lord S. said that he had a pew in Gough's<persName xml:id="5448"></persName> church at Brompton, &amp; worshipped there. He liked the service, but the preaching was a succession of topical 'stunts'</hi>. After dinner I retired to my room to write letters etc. &amp; left mine host &amp; hostess at Bridge with their guests. Thus ends a dull, and, I suspect, wasted day.</p></body></text></TEI>