<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[186]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.         </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>I began an article for the Bishoprick, on the name "Protestant" which passed into the vocabulary of Christendom just 400 years ago.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I accompanied Chelmsford to Mainsforth Colliery, where he formally opened the Pit&#8211;head Baths, which had been erected by the Miners' Welfare Fund. We began by going through the building, &amp; being shown the numerous arrangements for the man's convenience and comfort. Then we lunched in a tent very pleasantly. I sate between the Chairman, Mr. Dorman, of the firm Dorman Long &amp; C</hi><hi rend="i sup u">o</hi><hi rend="italic"> which owns the mine, and M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ben Turner, the new Minister for Mines – a tubby little fat man with the expansive geniality &amp; unctuous fervour of his professional mission&#8211;preacher.  After lunch there was a meeting of the workmen, who attended in large numbers.  I think there could hardly have been fewer than 2000 present.  Chelmsford spoke, &amp; then in succession Turner, Richardson, Robson, &amp; Straker.  The speakers seemed very </hi><hi rend="bold">[187] </hi>[symbol] <hi rend="italic">anxious to pose as disinterested reformers of society &amp; champions of the miners.  They were evidently </hi><hi rend="italic underline">intrigued</hi><hi rend="italic"> at seeing me there &amp; worked in some references to my presence.  After this function we returned to Auckland &amp; had tea.  Then we walked round the Park, deceiving the way with converse.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We had a dinner party. There dined</p>
         <p>Lord Chelmsford &amp; Sybil Lady Eden.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Peel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Peel.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McCullagh &amp; Miss Headlam.</p>
         <p>Pemberton &amp; his wife.</p>
         <p>Lionel &amp; Fearne.</p>
         <p>The Bishop &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Hensley Henson.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[187]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi><hi rend="italic">, in an interview which is reported in the local paper, attempts to justify his insults to his Bishop.  His real motive, we are to understand, was </hi><hi rend="italic underline">an honest indignation at my attack on Socialism in the sermon preached 3 years ago at the re&#8211;opening of the Church, &amp; a zeal for the Establishment!</hi><hi rend="italic">  The notes from which the Sermon was preached were published in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="italic"> Socialism is not so much as named in them, but a parallel is suggested between Mohammedanism in the VIII</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">Century and Bolsherism in the XX</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
