<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
	 <hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">. 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">WILSON'S FUNERAL</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful morning, and the air cool and fresh. The beauty of the outlook over garden, park, &amp; country as I looked at it from my dressing room moved me to shame for my ingratitude to the Giver of all Good for so great a blessing. Those Christians of an older time who thanked God for the boons of daily experience, for the measure of their temporal prosperity, for the unearned felicities of health &amp; situation, for their preservation from the deserved penalties of their blunders &amp; sins were more right in their spiritual attitude than we who moan &amp; grumble unceasingly in the midst of God's gifts.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I went into Durham, and attended the Funeral service in the Cathedral. There was a considerable congregation, but smaller than I had expected. Memories are very short, and even the best are soon forgotten. I returned to Auckland in time to sit for an hour to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Speed, whom I then motored for 2 hours in the beautiful country beyond Tow Law.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[171]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Lionel went out to play lawn&#8211;tennis, so I had M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Speed to myself at dinner.  We had a considerable discussion on the subject of Christianity, and therein, of course, on the answer which ought to be returned to the crucial question, '<hi rend="underline">What think ye of Christ? Whose son is He</hi>'? He is an eclectic, and would have all religions to be true, &amp; none to be rejected. But I insisted on the uniqueness of the conception of God, which Jesus taught, and in Himself disclosed. He has evidently dabbled in Spiritualism, &amp; inclines to a vague pantheism. But he has read Gore's little book on "Jesus of Nazareth" in the Home University Library, and has not been impressed. I thought it my evident duty not to let him think that I agreed with him, &amp; so no doubt I succeeded in giving him the impression that I am rather an obsolete type of fanatical Christian!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">The poor man is plainly puzzled by the Protean character of my countenance. He cannot determine which of my many and diverse aspects is the true expression of my very self. I wish I could make up my own mind on that question</hi>!</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
