<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[319]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful autumnal day, with a coolness of temperature which suggests the oncoming of the winter.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi> came to see me about S. Paul's, Stockton, and undertook as Rural Dean to be responsible for maintaining services and such pastoral charge as are indispensable during the six months of the Vicar's absence from duty.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Rainbow</hi> with her two children, Gerald and Mary, came to lunch.  They sate down to eat, and rose up to play, like the Israelites.</p>
         <p>Ella's party seemed to be largely attended. The fineness of the weather made lawn–tennis possible. Among the company were Sir Alfred &amp; Lady Palmer, &amp; Colonel and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dillon; but there were no clergy, except <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bartlett</hi>, who told me that he would accept Stella.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Maimie Parker–Smith</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Gaisford</hi> arrived for a visit.</p>
         <p>I made an attempt to compose a sermon for the Opening of the Session of the University College at Nottingham on October 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, but I made little progress. The truth is that I have nothing to say.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
