<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A dull chilly day, with essays at raining, very dull &amp; depressing. I spent the morning in trying to put together a speech for Convocation.</p>
         <p>Duncan came to lunch, &amp; to tell me what had been happening at Dawdon. He said that the strike had certainly been engineered in the interest of the "Labour" party with a view to damaging Londonderry's position, and defeating Robin's candidature at Darlington. But the rates of pay were so low that the men were seriously discontented. He had striven to maintain an independent attitude, &amp; would continue to do so, though, of course, it was a difficult attitude to maintain. I walked and talked with him for two hours.</p>
         <p>Lionel accompanied me to Darlington where I took train to York to <hi rend="bold underline">attend the Convocation tomorrow</hi>. I was met at the Station by the Archbishop's motor, &amp; so arrived at Bishopthorpe, where the Most Reverend received me kindly. It is odd to reflect that only a few months ago the general opinion had decided that I should be host, not guest, in this house.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[192]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There were 8 bishops beside the Archbishop at dinner, viz:&#8211; Durham, Chester, Sheffield, Bradford, Liverpool, Manchester, Carlisle, &amp; Sodor &amp; Man. Wakefield, Newcastle, &amp; Ripon were absent. After dinner we went through the draft of the Address to the King, &amp; agreed upon its form.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Bishop John Sarum would appear to have introduced the modern practice of doing homage to the Sovereign in robes: "With his sense of the fitness of things &amp; dignity of office</hi> he sent in a request to her Majesty that he might come &amp; pay homage in his robes.  The usual custom, I believe, was that after dinner the Bishops went in in evening dress, which he thought unseemly. The Queen quite liked and approved the idea." (v. Life. p. 159). The statement that the two new Archbishops arrayed themselves in copes and mitres in order to do their homage is, Temple assures me, wholly without foundation. I was greatly surprised when I read it in the newspaper, &amp; am glad to know that it was baseless.<hi rend="bold">]</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
