<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[184]</hi>
                                                              
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">DARLINGTON ROTARIANS</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington and lunched with the Rotarians in the King's Head Hotel. After lunch I spoke to them for1/2 an hour on 'my holiday in Southern France'. They listened demurely, and applauded decently. A local Wesleyan – a canting, cadaverous man expressed the thanks of the company for my address, &amp; did so with much superfluous unction.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hyde told me that the model of Stephenson's engine which had been made for M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ford had cost £2400: and that the cost of the express engines on the L.N.E.R. was from £8000 to £10,000.</p>
         <p>After luncheon I returned to Auckland, &amp; my arrival at the Castle synchronized with a thunderstorm.</p>
         <p>Divers people came to Ella's party, including Lag, Archbishop Söderblom's son, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Sharp from Bishopton. In spite of the weather, some lawn–tennis was played.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Two letters, occasioned by my speech on artisan candidates for the Ministry, came this afternoon.  The one was from a grocer of 37; the other from a Baptist minister of 29.  The first I said that I could not advise a man of his age to leave his employment &amp; seek admission to Holy Orders.  To the last, I said that no Nonconformist minister could rightly seek <hi rend="bold">[185]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ordination in the Church of England unless (α) he was convinced of the inadequacy of his present ministerial commission: and (β) he could conscientiously accept the doctrine &amp; discipline of the Church of England as these are set forward in the legal standards, and expounded by the representative Anglican divines. These conditions being satisfied, he should consult the Bishop of his diocese on the subject of qualifications for Holy Orders.</p>
         <p>Lord Chelmsford arrived to spend the week–end, and "open" some pit–head baths. Also, Miss Headlam arrived for the week–end. Before turning in I had much talk with C. on matters political &amp; ecclesiastical.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
