<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[336]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>I spent much of the morning in writing to Sir Henry Lunn, who is evidently perturbed by my [<hi rend="italic">added in red</hi>] challenge 'Has a lasting union of churches ever been gained by diplomacy?' He enumerates a series of sectarian 'unions' winding up with the union of the Presbyterian Churches of Scotland. I point out that these unions were all within the Protestant sphere, &amp; in cases where there was no barrier of fundamental principle between the uniting churches. I had in mind the case of churches where that barrier does exist. Sir Henry Lunn is an excellent Christian, whose hobby is the uniting of Churches. He spends much time, &amp;, I should suppose, much money in organizing Conferences of one sort or another, &amp; is never so happy as in the company of Anglican ecclesiastics, preferably High Church bishops, with whom he can exchange compliments and be photographed. How far any lasting good results from these holy picnics in Switzerland &amp; Scotland may be doubted: but he enjoys them vastly.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[337]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">'Manus ad clavum: oculus ad coelum</hi>'</p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">first version crossed out</hi>]</p>
         <p>If firm the steersman's hand the helm doth hold,</p>
         <p>If the bright stars above his eye doth track,</p>
         <p>He through calm days &amp; winter's stormy cold, </p>
         <p>A forward course shall urge, nor guidance lack.</p>
         <p>Welch from Gateshead, who is going out to Nigeria to work under Bishop Lasbrey, came to say Goodbye, &amp; stayed to lunch.</p>
         <p>Warth came to see me, &amp; told me a dreadful story of his domestic worries.</p>
         <p>One of the cherry trees in the drive was blown down by the gale.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
