<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[140]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
            
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" has nearly a column on "Disestablishment", not unfriendly, but entirely non&#8211;committal.</p>
         <p>I took my guest and motored to Staindrop, where I showed him the fine parish church. Then we went on to High Force, moving through the most beautiful country. There was, of course, very little water in the Fall, but the gorge which forms its setting looked magnificent. We returned to the Castle in good time for lunch.</p>
         <p>N.B. The word 'Force' used in the North of England for a cascade or waterfall is said by the Oxford Dictionary to be of Scandinavian derivation.</p>
         <p>The Archbishop took his departure after tea leaving the impression of an amiable and cultivated man, whose considerable experience of the world had induced neither secularity of mind nor sourness of temper. His conversation indicated a chastened optimism, which, while resolved to face disturbing facts, refused to surrender the large certitudes of his faith.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[141]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>'<hi rend="underline">There is no God</hi>', the wicked saith,<lb/> 'And truly it's a blessing,<lb/>For what He might have done with us<lb/>It's better only guessing.'</p>
         <p>But country folks who live beneath<lb/>The shadow of the steeple;<lb/>The parson and the parson's wife,<lb/>And mostly married people;</p>
         <p>And almost everyone when age,</p>
         <p>Disease, or sorrows strike him,<lb/>Inclines to think there is a God,</p>
         <p>Or something very like Him.'</p>
         <p>(Quoted by the Bishop of Massachusetts (D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Charles Lewis Slattery) in his 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Annual Address to the Convention of his diocese April 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1929.)</p>
         <p>An apostate bishop in France <hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>(Talleyrand)<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> was once asked by a young atheist how he could found a religion.  "There is only one way", answered the old bishop, "you must get yourself crucified: you must rise again on the third day: then you may succeed".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
