<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[277]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harold Speed went away after breakfast, leaving a mixed but mainly favourable impression.  He is vain, self&#8211;conscious, and talkative, but he is also frank, humourous [sic], and cheerful.  On the whole, he gave little trouble, and evidently tried to fit in to the (to him) unfamiliar, &amp;, perhaps, unpalatable arrangements of an episcopal household. Then the Bishop of Jarrow took his departure.  I lent him the proofs of two Nineteenth Century Articles, that of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Boys Smith, &amp; my own.</p>
         <p>I wrote some necessary letters, and then prepared a letter to the 'Church Times'. That journal contained a criticism, or rather a correction, of "<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>". I had assumed that the Test Act extended to Members of Parliament, whereas it only dealt with civil, military, &amp; naval officers. The difference is more apparent than real so far as my argument is concerned: but it is never a small thing that one holding my position should be convicted of inaccuracy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[278]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times Literary Supplement</hi>" has two columns headed "<hi rend="underline">The Bishop of Durham's Apologia</hi>", politely expressed, but hostile. I should judge that it represents the general attitude of Churchmen.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Chelmsford</hi> sent us 2 brace of grouse, for which I wrote him a letter of thanks.</p>
         <p>I discovered written in pencil on the fly&#8211;leaf of the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> volume of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lecky</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">History of England in the xviii</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> century</hi>, the name of '<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Ainger</hi>'.  I met him on several occasions when first I lived in Westminster.  He was a quaint little spare white&#8211;haired man with shining eyes, a thin high voice, &amp; a quick manner.  I remember how severely he was accustomed to speak of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi> 
<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>who<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> was then his colleague at the Temple, &amp; whom he judged to be 'disloyal'.  Since then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Alexander</hi> has carried the same disloyalty, or reputation for disloyalty, into his new position as Canon of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's.  How far do their reputations deal justly with men?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
