<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[94]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant morning, but the air still sultry, and a hot comfortless wind in gusts. I could not keep in bed in spite of the doctor's admonition overnight, &amp; so had my bath, dressed, &amp; went to my study. The wall&#8211;flowers in the bed below my window make a brave show, which is the more noteworthy since most wall&#8211;flowers in the district perished in the great Frost. A pair of thrushes are building in the ivy, but mainly there is a dearth of these beautiful birds; probably they, like the wall&#8211;flowers, perished in the Frost. It is reported that black&#8211;birds are uncommonly numerous; they are tougher birds than the Thrushes.</p>
         <p>I made little headway with my work, and finally decided to refurbish an old "Charge" to Ordination candidates, which I wrote in 1919 at Hereford. This occupied me most of the afternoon, &amp; was not finished when the Candidates arrived for Evensong at 7 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[95]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>D<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Mess came to lunch.  He is certainly not beautiful to look at, but much may be pardoned in a man who will produce so good a piece of work as "Industrial Tyneside".  He wants an income of &#x00A3;1200 per annum to finance his Bureau effectively. At present he has only &#x00A3;600.  I promised to write to various trusts to which he is applying for assistance in order to support his application.</p>
         <p>Principal Wallis gave the Address to the Candidates.  It was simple, practical, and effective, refreshingly free from unction and cant, a circumstance both surprising and welcome.  After dinner he had some talk with me in my study.  He said that he had information from Liverpool that Gibson, <hi rend="italic">(Red X in the left margin here)</hi> the disreputable fellow whom I rejected &amp; whom the Bishop of Liverpool ordained without reference to me, is turning out very badly as might have been foreseen.  The new Bishop of Manchester is finding <hi rend="bold underline">a queer lot of men bequeathed to him by his distinguished but too&#8211;yielding predecessor.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
