<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[270]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> accompanied me to <hi rend="underline">Seaton Carew</hi>, where I visited the camp for unemployed mining lads, which is being managed by members of Toc H. The Mayor of West Hartlepool and divers members of the Corporation were also visiting the Camp, and we headed rival teams in a tug of war. I was victorious, only however to be woefully beaten at quoits. I made a speech to the boys – about 200 of them – at tea: and also to the Toc H. helpers &amp; the guests. Then we returned to the Castle. Warth had some private speech with me about his own position, which appears to be extraordinarily difficult.</p>
         <p>I had a "heart to heart" talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> about his position &amp; prospects.  On the whole I was reassured, &amp; allow myself to regain a measure of confidence.  He is fearfully sensitive &amp; self&#8211;conscious. I do <hi rend="strikethrough">d</hi> not doubt that he imagines many slights where none exist, &amp; inflicts on himself much mental distress.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[271]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the good days of ghostly ignorance,<lb/>How did cathedrals rise and zeal advance!<lb/>The merry monks said visions at ease,<lb/>Large were their meals, and light their penances.<lb/>Pardons for sins were purchased with estates,<lb/> And none but rogues in rags died reprobates.<lb/> But now that pious pageantry's no more,<lb/> And stages thrive as churches did before.</p>
         <p>See the Harleian Miscellany. ii. 21<lb/>(Lecky. Hist: of England. ii. 179 note)</p>
         <p>Poor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knowlden</hi> is clearly "done for".  His curate, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moore</hi>, reported that he had a fall last night: that he tends to mental wandering: that he is not competent to act for himself: that his sister has been sent for.  When I inquired what was the nature of his illness, I was told that he suffered from that hateful &amp; hopeless malady known commonly as "creeping paralysis".  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Poole</hi> asked me about young <hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot</hi>, who, until lately, has been <hi rend="doubleunderline">Warth</hi>'s curate. I advised him to take him as his colleague. As the evening drew on, the rain which had been threatening, began to fall.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
