<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[302]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A very hot night followed by a very hot close day.  I worked at the Letter for the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick </hi>all the morning, and after lunch went out to Windlestone, where a Fête of the G.F.S. was in progress. I made a short speech to the girls, &amp; then returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Gateshead where I instituted the new Vicar (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Greenwood</hi>) to the parish of Venerable Bede, in succession to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Waterbury</hi>.  He is not prepossessing to look at, being rather dingy &amp; with a craven manner, but one cannot safely infer character from first impressions.  There was a considerable congregation, a reverent service, and a creditable choir.  After the service the new Vicar brought his wife &amp; two children into the vestry, &amp; introduced them to me.  I gave each of the children a florin, which would make them good episcopalians for the nonce![?]  We returned to Auckland, stopping on the way Windlestone, to pick up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[303]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"It is true that England was without an ally in the world, and that America had two of the greatest Powers in Europe assisting her in the struggle, yet still in the fourth year of the war Washington gravely doubted whether there was sufficient power, sufficient patriotism, sufficient earnestness in the States to carry it to a successful issue."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Lecky, History V. 27</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I had not realized until I read Lecky's account of the American revolution how much of what is distinctive of American Society finds its explanation in the specific characteristicks of that crisis. The low moral level on which the whole movement of independence developed, the dominating influence of money, the arrogance and ill&#8211;faith of the American diplomatists, &amp; the vindictiveness &amp; corruption of American politics all have been perpetuated. If only the politicians and generals of Britain had not exhibited a sustained &amp; extreme incompetence, it is evident that American Independence would have been easily extinguished.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
