<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[321]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful autumn morning. I dressed to the cawing of rooks, and the spectacle of a pair of thrushes feeding on the lawn. The glory of this beautiful world grows on me as the time draws on when I too must bid it farewell for ever.</p>
         <p>I went over to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's, &amp; there celebrated the Holy Communion.  The queer Irish curate, Hamilton, assisted.</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="doubleunderline">Observer</hi>' has an account of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Jeans</hi> and a review of his newly&#8211;published book&#8211; "<hi rend="underline">The Universe around us</hi>". The astronomer is represented as speaking to this effect:</p>
         <p>"There was no longer the conflict between science &amp; religion.  Think of the antagonism of the Darwin&#8211;Huxley days – not so long ago.  All that had become a merest echo.  Today the scientist &amp; churchman were eager to listen each to each, conscious of working towards a mutual end, if by different methods."  'The theologian wants to know what the scientist has to say: the scientist realizes that, while his is entitled to speak of what he knows, e is not entitled to impose on that <hi rend="bold">[322] </hi>knowledge a personal dogma on religious philosophy'. This, too, was a definite gain for the good."</p>
         <p>I am not sure whether the new civility isn't more dangerous to faith than the old fisticuffs.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Gateshead where I dedicated a chancel&#8211;screen in S. Mary's, and preached to a congregation which did not fill so much as the nave.  The good churchwardens expressed delight at the size of the congregation, a circumstance which cast a disconcerting light on the normal state of affairs.  However, the people were attentive, the service reverent and the Rector in the seventh heaven!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Thomas Reed</hi>, the donor &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Wood the designer of the screen supped at the Rectory.  Pattinson and I did so also.  Welch, the assistant curate, leaves for Nigeria in a few days.  The lure of the foreign mission field is too strong for the abler of our younger clergy.  We returned to Auckland, and on our arrival walked round the bowling green to enjoy the spectacle of the Castle under moonlight.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
