<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>An uncertain blustering morning, very comfortless and irritating. Before going to bed I finished reading an historical novel, or rather a study of Leonardo da Vinci cast in narrative form called '<hi rend="underline">The Forerunner</hi>' by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dmitri Merey Kowski</hi>.  I found it interesting &amp; suggestive, but neither adequate nor satisfying.  </p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  There were 9 communicants, including <hi rend="doubleunderline">John</hi> and the 4 <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brydens</hi>. [symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur</hi>, to whom I sent a copy of "<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>".</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>' states that the late <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Spooner</hi> left more than £<hi rend="doubleunderline">34,000</hi>: which, on his widow's death, is to be equally divided between his two daughters.  So <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Inge</hi> will soon be able to make a substantial contribution to the Dean's tenuous resources!</p>
         <p>Indoors I felt so chilly that I had my fire lighted: but outdoors I found the weather so warm that I perforce took off my mackintosh. There is a stuffy uncertain wind, and a suggestion of thunder in the air.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[150]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. W. Smith with his son Alec called on me.  The latter is lodging in Sunderland, where he is learning the business of milling.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wilde had asked my wife to be kind to the youth, and she had written to invite him to play lawn–tennis.  He gave his address as 36 Azalea Terrace S.. Sunderland.  I gave them tea, &amp; shewed them the Chapel, &amp; wrote to Jimmie Dobbs telling him to call.</p>
         <p>I read a book which Inge recommends – <hi rend="underline">Progress &amp; Religion</hi> by <hi rend="underline">Christopher Dawson</hi><persName xml:id="5588"></persName>  It is extremely interesting, &amp; leads to the conclusion that only in a return to Christianity can modern civilization be saved from ruin. He says many acute things e.g.</p>
         <p>"Real scepticism is usually tolerant, and the intolerance and iconoclasm of the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century philosophers, like that of the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Reformers was the fanaticism of the sectaries of a new gospel.  <hi rend="underline">The French Enlightenment was, in fact, the last of the great European heresies</hi>, and its appeal to Reason was itself an act of faith which admitted of no criticism."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[151]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Again, this is illuminating:–</p>
         <p>"Social and political revolution has become so common a feature of modern European life that we are apt to forget how rare such movements are in history.  They occur only when a culture is undergoing a process of internal transformation. <hi rend="underline">Social revolution is an index of spiritual change</hi>."</p>
         <p>Or again this:–</p>
         <p>" It is not only the Socialists and the revolutionaries who threaten the modern European order. As in the case of the militarist capitalism of the later Roman Republic, <hi rend="underline">the greatest danger to the industrial capitalism of modern Europe comes from its own inherent instability</hi>.  The exploitation of the world by the new industrialized societies of Western Europe, like that of the Mediterranean lands by Rome in the first <hi rend="sub">̭</hi>and<hi rend="sub">̭</hi> second centuries B.C. has been too rapid to continue indefinitely."</p>
         <p>This sets one thinking.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
