<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[292]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold"> , 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi> went away before lunch.  He is astonishingly alert &amp; cheerful, though he is nearing eighty. </p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Northern Echo</hi>" reports a strange explosion from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simpkinson</hi>, the outgoing Rector of Blaydon or Stella, who is to be instituted to Merrington on Sept. 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. He says incidentally:</p>
         <p>"When I was ordained there were 17 curacies vacant in the Diocese; today there are more than 170. When I first knew Durham many of the incumbents were of the highest order: today one sees few worthy to fill their shoes."</p>
         <p>He was ordained in 1892 by the Bishop of Durham (Westcott), and has held his present position for 16 years. It is apparent that his relations with his parishioners are strained, &amp; that he himself regards them with little charity. With what feelings will the people at Merrington award his advent, when they read these unworthy words addressed to the people of Blaydon?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[293]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went to Shildon, and presided at the opening of the Church School after extensive alterations.  The function was performed by <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Hornsley</hi>, the Manager of the Northern Railways (or some such official). I took occasion to speak about the Council Schools, with obvious reference (though, of course, I did not name him) to the mischievous bletherings of the ass, Merryweather.  It had begun to rain when we returned to the Castle. </p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> addressing my letter to Bombay.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Korsteiner</hi> arrived on a short visit.  She is an agreeable person, but, Lord!, how these aging females accumulate!</p>
         <p>The latest statistics show that children grow rapidly fewer, &amp; people over 55 form an ever larger proportion of the population. And <hi rend="underline">of these last there are more than 500,000 more females than males</hi>. This dominance of the middle&#8211;aged &amp; senile cannot be wholesome. The tone of society becomes querulous, self&#8211;centred, &amp; cynical. Nothing brave or generous can get a hearing.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
