<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[128]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi>, the Vicar of Stockton, in acknowledging receipt of the Charge, writes interestingly as follows:</p>
         <p>"I had been of the opinion that disestablishment was bound to come, but I have heard Socialists argue that an established Church completely controlled by government might be a very valuable weapon for their cause, and was consistent with their principles.</p>
         <p>I am interested too in what you say about mining parishes. I have just been reading the life of one of my predecessors, Gray, afterwards as Bishop of Capetown the opponent of Colenso. He gives as one of his reasons for accepting Stockton that he despaired of making any impression whatever on the miners of Byers Green. Things have certainly improved, if but little since then."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop Temple</hi> is reported to have declared definitely and decisively against Disestablishment.  Well, well!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[129]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Godfrey</hi> sends me a friendly message:&#8211;</p>
         <p>"This morning I have read the Introduction, &amp; venture at once to say a word. No doubt you do right to put on record a defence against the charge of inconsistency. But no one who knows you will have treated that charge seriously. Resolute independence of parties inevitably results in one party after another being disappointed &amp; angry with you, as you have very clearly shown. I need not elaborate this but I think you may be interested by the strong feeling of one of your many friends that you have pursued throughout a more consistent career than most men of power can achieve."</p>
         <p>It is pleasant to have such a confirmation of what is certainly the verdict of my own self&#8211;judgment. No doubt in due course I shall hear a very different estimate from the "reviews", as the denunciations will be grotesquely called.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[130]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Lateran Treaty was duly ratified in Rome yesterday, and now the Temporal Power has been restored to the Papacy.  How long will it continue?  The speeches of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mussolini</hi> in the Italian Parliament and the rejoinders which they have called forth from the Pope indicate the existence of formidable opposition in both camps.</p>
         <p>The weather became exceedingly close &amp; sultry. There was a considerable thunder&#8211;storm during the afternoon, but though there was plenty of thunder and lightning, there was very little rain. I walked round the Park, and, on returning to the Castle, wrote to William.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Brooke</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fosca Wescott</hi> went away in their car this morning.</p>
         <p>The new Government has been now formed. All the Ministers were announced, &amp; had their pictures in the morning's papers. They kissed hands on their appointment this morning. The King is reported to have been re&#8211;assuringly well &amp; cheerful.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
