<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[288]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"I do not wish to introduce this system of daily and practically private celebrations for all clergy in priests' orders, which would be alien to the character of our teaching and dangerous to our own spiritual life."</p>
         <p>Bp. J Wordsworth H.C. p. 120.</p>
         <p>John Wrightson, Kenneth, Fawkes, Pattinson and I lunched here, and afterwards motored to Jarrow, where we inspected the "Saxon" church. Then we went on to Monkwearmouth and visited that church also. The old clerk (or sexton) recognized me, &amp; was, of course, most assiduous. I do not remember having seen before the remarkably interesting "Saxon" remains in the Vestry. Then we had tea at Bishopwearmouth Rectory, where we found the family assembled (except Jack). After this, we returned to Auckland Castle well pleased with the expedition. Wynne–Willson is cheerful, but looks desperately ill.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[289]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pepys </hi>in his <hi rend="underline">Journal</hi> has several references to the religious complexion of the H. of C. which passed the Act of Uniformity.</p>
         <p>i. 362. 'The great talk of the town is the strange election that the City of London made yesterday for 'Parliament men …..<hi rend="underline">men that are so far from being episcopal that they are thought to be Anabaptists</hi>: and chosen with a great deal of zeal, in spite of the other party that thought themselves very strong, calling out in the Hall, "No Bishops! No Lord Bishops! It do make people to fear it may come to worse, by being an example to the country to do the same. And indeed the Bishops ae so high that very few do love them'.</p>
         <p>ii. 42. '<hi rend="underline">This day the Parl</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline"> met the comm</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi><hi rend="underline"> of D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Gunning of S</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="underline">. Marg</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">t's</hi><hi rend="underline">, West</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> …. </hi>Sir W. Batten told me how M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Price (among the two or three that did refuse today to receive the Sacrament upon their knees) was offered by mistake the drink afterwards, wh. he did receive, being denied the drink by D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gunning, unless he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> take it on his knees: &amp; after that by another the bread was brought him, &amp; he did take it sitting, which is thought very preposterous."</p>
         <p>iii. 48. <hi rend="underline">Members ordered to renounce the Covenant</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[290]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gwatkin's </hi><hi rend="underline">Church &amp; State in England to the Death of Queen Anne</hi> (Longmans, Green &amp; C<hi rend="superscript">o </hi>1917) states that the Parliament (1661) began by imposing the sacrament on its own members after Queen Mary's evil example. Its next step was the Corporation Act". (p.353)</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Cambridge Modern History</hi>. Vol. V ch. XI. 'Religious Toleration in England' by Gwatkin. "Presbyterianism as a political power was destroyed at once by its exclusion from the Commons &amp; the Corporation: but could it still obtain some concessions in mattes of religion? The answer was the Act of Uniformity (May 19, 1662). … Even the Cavalier Parliament only passed the Act by a majority of six (156 to 180).</p>
         <p>For muddle–headedness and the nakedest <hi rend="bold underline">Erastianism</hi>" it would be difficult to find any Anglican composition more distinguished than Dean Stanley's "Address delivered in Sion College Feb 15. 1865" on 'The Connexion between Church and State'. It is printed in the volume entitled 'Essays chiefly on questions of Church &amp; State from 1850 to 1870' (John Murray. New Edition. 1884)</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
