<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[264]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I went to South Church, and preached at Mattins, but I was distressed by so heavy a cold that I was glad to hand over the Celebration to Pattinson.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Gloucester</hi> with his secretary, Sister Lavinia, and an <hi rend="doubleunderline">American Professor Adams Brown</hi> &amp; his wife, came to lunch, and to see over the Castle.  I found the incessant talking very fatiguing.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Observer</hi>" contains a short, and rather "sniffy" notice of '<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>', by the man, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Iremonger</hi>. He, perhaps, is hardly the critic who would do justice to anything of mine.</p>
         <p>I motored to Shildon, &amp; preached at Evensong to a congregation which was larger than I expected, since the annual Festival in connexion with the Flower–Show was in progress.  I was pleased with the service which was read by a lay–worker, and with the lessons which were excellently read by two young laymen: &amp; the singing was very good &amp; congregational. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[265]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"The resources of casuistry have never been a monopoly of the disciples of Loyola; and <hi rend="underline">State Churches, though they have many merits, are not the schools of heroism</hi>."</p>
         <p>Lecky.<persName xml:id="3601"></persName> Hist: of England i. 79</p>
         <p>The truth of the historian's <hi rend="underline">obiter dictum</hi> is being remarkably illustrated in the Church of England at the present time.  On all hands, I hear suggestions of delay, of postponing the crisis &amp;c &amp;c, in plain terms, of 'eating out of Jix's hand'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> expressed himself very determined on the matter of the South Indian Reunion Scheme.  We must insist on carrying it at the Lambeth Conference.  But 1) I am not sure that we can: and 2) I doubt whether most of the bishops are prepared for the consequences.  Many will make their support contingent on the maintenance of the unity of the Anglican Communion.  The threat of disruption will certainly be made, and whether it will remain no more than a threat Time only can show.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
