<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, May 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hector Bamlett</hi> came to see me by my appointment.  I offered him charge of the mission which Booth is about to vacate in order to take up his work in South Shields.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi> walked round the Park with me. We discussed the results of the voting which have been announced this morning.  Labour is going ahead, &amp; Liberalism is nowhere.  Robin has failed at Darlington through the intervention of the Liberal candidate.  Harold Macmillan has been turned out of Stockton.  It is some compensation to know that both Sir Thomas Inskip and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Saklatvala have been turned out.</p>
         <p>Lionel and I motored to Sunderland, where I instituted the new Vicar (Johnson) to S. Andrew's, Roker. He is a rather coarse&#8211;looking man of a florid complexion &amp; rather carnal aspect! There was a fair congregation considering that the polls were being declared. After the service we had supper with Sir John &amp; Lady Priestman. After taking Wynne&#8211;Willson back to his house, we returned to Auckland. There was no sign of popular excitement anywhere.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
