<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.        </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">THANKSGIVING FOR THE KING'S RECOVERY</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A calm, over–clouded morning and warm, of doubtful omen. Before getting up I finished the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> volume of Mackinnon's book.  The conference at Marburg in October 1529 – just 4 centuries ago – showed Luther at his worst.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 15 communicants including Lord Chelmsford, Miss Headlam, William &amp; his newly–confirmed wife, Rufus, Elland &amp; his wife &amp; son. The Gospel, with its message. "<hi rend="underline">If thy brother hath ought against thee</hi>" connected itself inevitably with Hodgson. I don't think it would be true to say that he has ought against me, for his attack was causeless, &amp; such injury as it may do me in the public mind in quarters where there is no knowledge of the facts may be considerable, but so far as I am concerned, must remain unredressed.  It would be intolerable for me, the Bishop, to embark on a public discussion with <hi rend="underline">him</hi>.         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We all motored to Durham for the Thanksgiving service, which was numerously attended</hi>.  I made all possible effort to make myself audible, but I fear without complete success.  The Mayor and Corporation were present, and the boys of the School, but, term being over, the students of the University were absent.  On the whole I thought the service was well–arranged, impressive, and (so far as could be felt and seen) edifying.  Afterwards we all went to Ramside, and lunched with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pembertons</hi>. Both the girls, Penelope and Betty, were there, and Penelope's child, Charles, a pretty little cheerful boy of 3½.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi> came to tea, &amp; afterwards went with Lionel and me to S. Ignatius, Sunderland, where <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">I preached at Evensong in place of the Bishop of Oxford, who had been required to preach in his own Cathedral at the Thanksgiving Service</hi>. There was a large congregation, and a hearty service. My sermon was listened to attentively. After service I had a few words with an Ordination candidate of whom Baily spoke in terms of warm commendation. We returned to Auckland Castle on the conclusion of the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
