<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Lionel came with me to Darlington, where I took the 8.55 a.m. express to King's Cross. I travelled very comfortably, having the compartment to myself after York. The Archbishop of York and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Forster, the late High Sheriff, came and talked to me.  I was surprised to find that the latter was not greatly perturbed by the result of the General Election.  He thought that Macdonald had formed as moderate a ministry as he could, &amp; that he would not be able to do much harm.  He was optimistic about the immediate future of the Durham mines.  On arriving in London I drove to 21 Park Lane, &amp; deposited my bags.  Then I went to the Club, &amp; washed.  After a <hi rend="italic">visit to the Hair&#8211;dresser, I drove to Lambeth and attended the meeting of the Bishops.  Bell made his first appearance as Bishop of Chichester.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic"> presided, and seemed to be in rude health and high spirits.  He explained that the elaborate transformation of the Garden which is proceeding was being carried out by some anonymous </hi><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi> [symbol] <hi rend="italic">friend who had undertaken to find the money.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Barnes</hi><hi rend="italic"> was present in a very </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">militant </hi><hi rend="i bold">(</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">brazen</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="i bold">)</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic"> mood.  I think </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="i bold">(</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic"> his head is turned </hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="i bold">)</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">he is not unsatisfied</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^ </hi><hi rend="italic">by the great publicity which his utterances secure, &amp; the considerable popularity which he has gained with the non&#8211;religious public.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I remonstrated with him for his Westminster Sermon, but I found him quite (</hi><hi rend="i subscript underline">^</hi><hi rend="italic underline">impenetrable</hi><hi rend="i subscript underline">^</hi><hi rend="italic underline">) inaccessible to argument on that topic</hi><hi rend="italic">!</hi><hi rend="i subscript">^</hi><hi rend="italic">  Let him heed the warning against those who '</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">love the praise of men, more than the praise of God</hi><hi rend="italic">'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Several of the Bishops (e.g. London, Chester, Wakefield, Bath &amp; Wells) thanked me for the charge: &amp; Truro, who might have been offended at the references to himself, was quite appreciative. On the whole, I incline to think that it has served its purpose. The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">" has a notice of it, more frigid than actually hostile.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined in the Athenaeum with the two brothers </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Pearce</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; then, after writing to Ella</hi> and looking at the illustrated papers, walked back to Park Lane.</p>
         <p>The weather has become very hot &amp; sultry, and I shall be surprised if we traverse the night without a storm.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
