<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[168]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Dull morning, &amp; much colder. Ella and Fearne went off to London by the midday train. I surrendered myself to this tyrannous painter, &amp; thus waster the entire morning. After lunch, I sate for yet another hour, &amp; then took M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Speed for an airing in the open car.  We ran up Weardale as far as Stanhope, and returned to tea.</p>
         <p>I write to Ruth condoling with her on the loss of her Mother. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Spooner did not long survive her husband.  To be bereaved of both parents almost at one stroke even though as in this case they are fourscore, is no common bereavement.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Speed is much intrigued by the picture in the small dining&#8211;room which we have been taught to regard as Paul Veronese's sketch for his vast picture "The marriage of Cana in Gahlee' which is in the Louvre.  He has satisfied himself 1. that it was painted before the large picture.  2. That it was drawn by Veronese; but 3. executed by one of his pupils.  The alterations indicate the working of the Master's mind, &amp; are all notable improvements. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[169]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Luxmoore replies to my letter of condolence as follows.</p>
         <p>My dear Lord Bishop,</p>
         <p>My best thanks for your very kind letter, and sympathy, and I am happy to think that in the sixteen years you mention <hi rend="bold underline">a very large amount of the pleasure that my father had in his life was in your own friendship, courtesy &amp; companionship and in such work as he was able to give to you.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My mother's death made a great blank in the happiness of his life, and it was such friendship that went far towards filling this.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>A.A. Luxmore.</p>
         <p>Wilson will be sincerely regretted by many to whom his kindness was shown.  William was, I think, rather a part of his, and he often inquired about him.  When he meditated a visit to South Africa he intended to look up William.  Clayton and Trotman were devoted to him, and he liked them both especially Clayton. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
