<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[348]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I attended a Physical Drill demonstration in the Auckland Football Field.  About 3000 children performed in presence of a great throng of parents, relations, and neighbours.  The spectacle, as I saw it from the Pavilion, was pleasing and impressive.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson</hi>, the Director of Education, was there, and I suggested to him that I should write a letter of appreciation, &amp; address it to him. He rather jumped at the notion. Accordingly, on returning to the house, I wrote a flatterous epistle, &amp; addressed it to the Shire Hall. If, as is not unlikely, the letter gets into the papers, the ass Merryweather will be indirectly but severely rebuked.</p>
         <p>[symbol] Some amiable person sends me a type&#8211;written letter, signed " A Private Patron", addressed to the Bishop of Winchester, in answer to some circular that he has addressed privately to "The Patrons of the Diocese". It is grossly abusive to the Bishop, &amp; to me!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[349]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Here is the final paragraph:&#8211;</p>
         <p>"Several friends of mine who are members of the National Assembly tell me that you are freely spoken of in the Assembly as 'the cad of the Church'.  If any man has ever earned that title it is you, <hi rend="underline">and that evil, soulless, &amp; Christless black&#8211;guard, who sits in the seat of Handly Moule, namely Hensley Henson, one of the most evil men of this generation. Truly he is a 'viper' in a surplice' if ever there was one</hi>."</p>
         <p>Well, well.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi> came about 7 p.m., and administered the oath &amp;c. to my solitary Ordination candidate, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harry Legg Clothier</hi>. I wonder what are the mental reserves with which this youth – he is fresh from Mirfield – has taken his solemn pledges. The practical value of these official subscriptions is now reduced by the plausible casuistry of partisanship to nothing at all. But the farce goes on.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
