<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">PAU</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I was much awake last night, and my thoughts went back over the series of events which have had the effect of cutting short my public career, and reducing me to the nowise impressive situation (so far as ecclesiastical politics are concerned) of an "<hi rend="doubleunderline">extinct volcano</hi>".  If, at the close of 1927, I had taken the course, which general opinion expected me to take, and which both <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi> (who must be supposed to represent the King) and the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi> desired me to take, to what should I have committed myself?  After what I had written &amp; said about the effect of rejecting the Revised prayer Book, <hi rend="underline">I could not decently or honestly have defended the existing Establishment. I could only have declared for a drastic revision of the Establishment designed to secure the Church of England against Parliamentary control. But could I honestly pretend to think that such a Revision was a practical policy</hi>?  And, if I did not think so, then could I <hi rend="bold">[4] </hi>[symbol] honourably advocate it?  I am now half inclined to wish now that I had carried out the plan which did first present itself to my mind when the action of the H. of C. was announced viz: <hi rend="underline">move a resolution in the H. of L. in favour of Disestablishment</hi>. But I thought<hi rend="underline"> then</hi> that the episcopate itself would have taken some decisive step: &amp;, nothing more was done than the transparently futile declaration of the Church Assembly, the moment for such a Resolution had passed<hi rend="underline">. And my sermon in Cambridge at the end of January, 1928, followed by the publication of 'The Book &amp; the Vote', had 'burnt my boats' on the main issue</hi>.  The retirement of the Archbishop, and the appointmnt of Lang as his successor, &amp; Temple as Lang's successor – both of whom were known to be more earnest champions of eccclesiastical authonomy than I – seemed to promise more adequate action, and I wrote the Article – <hi rend="underline">'Disestablishment by Consent' – </hi><hi rend="bold underline">[5] </hi><hi rend="underline">[symbol] in the Nineteeth Century (Jan</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">ry</hi><hi rend="underline">, 1929) in order to focus opinion</hi>.  But I soon learned from speeches &amp; attitude of the new Primates that they had no mind for any other course than the maintenance of the <hi rend="underline">status quo</hi>: and <hi rend="underline">I was left in the highly invidious position of isolation</hi>.  Meanwhile, a kind of panic set in among the clergy &amp; religious laity, to whom the mere mention of Disestablishment &amp; Disendowment was terrifying: <hi rend="underline">and I became the magnet of a thousand fears and suspicions</hi>. However, I garnered now the harvest of resentments which had been sown in many controversial fields during the course of a career, which had mainly born the character of conflict. Instead of the champion of the Church, as I had been regarded in December 1927, I acquired the odious character of a 'troubles of Israel'. Support came to me from no quarter of the ecclesiastical horizon. The politicians were hostile: and the Sectaries, ever more political than religious, made no movement of sympathy!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[6]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We visited the office of the <hi rend="underline">Societe Generale </hi>where I changed cheques for £25.00 into 3090f. which represents an exchange of nearly 124f. to the pound.  The we walked to the Castle, and went through it with the official guide.  It contains much beautiful tapestry and furniture.  Henry IV and Louis XIV divide the visitor's attention.  We retuned to the Hotel for lunch, and afterwards went on the adveertized tour to <hi rend="bold underline">Eaux Chaudes</hi> and <hi rend="bold underline">Eaux Bonnes</hi>. The road lay through a magnificent gorge, and the views of the snow–clad Pyrenees were extremely fine. We had tea at Eaux Bonnes, &amp; Ella and Fearne bought cards. The fee for this excursion was 40f. for every person.</p>
         <p>Thus the total expenditure was;–</p>
         <table>
<row><cell>
<hi>Carriage</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>120f.</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Tip to Chauffeur</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
                  
<hi>10f.</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Tea</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
                  
<hi>18f.</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Tip to Guide</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
                      
<hi>5</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<cell>
<hi>153f.</hi>
</cell>
</row>
         </table>
         <p>We got back to the Hotel about 6 p.m. The weather was fine but threatening rain.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[7]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The ox appears to be the common draught animal</hi><hi rend="italic"> of this district.  it is a large buff–coloured beast with fine horns, &amp; a pleasing appearance.  The dignified slowness of its movements, and the antiquated aspect of its furniture contrast sharply with the motors which fly past it on the roads.  What a jumble of old &amp; new the world has become!  The state of our minds is probably as queer a blending of the two as that of our streets.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After dinner I wrote to Godfrey Charnwood and then I went to bed.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The French papers give much prominence to the outrage at Delhi</hi>, when a bomb was thrown in the Assembly. It is impossible to deny that the episode casts a lurid light on the indian situation. That the origin of the outrage must be sought in Moscow appears to be universally agreed. The return of a Labour Government to power just at the momnet when the Soviet is actually organizing revolt in India would be particularly unfortunate. The Figaro emphasizes this point. Unhappily the British electorate knows little, and cares less, about conditions in India.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
