<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[268]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received letters from <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi>: both write in good spirits, &amp; seem to be happy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi> declines nomination to Coniscliffe on the ground that the house is "impossible" – large, damp, cold, and inconvenient.  If this be so, I shall find it difficult to fill the living.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning with my painter, who was engaged in what he called "coordinating" my precious countenance! Certainly, of all the tiresome experiences of life, "sitting" may advance a strong claim to the primacy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord &amp; Lady Scarbrough</hi> came to lunch.  They viewed the picture, &amp;, though not without some criticisms, approved it.  They were the more interested in it, as Lord S. is himself about to be painted by Lazslo.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon &amp; M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Robinson</hi> from Winchester called, &amp; were shown over the Castle.  Afterwards I motored them into Durham with my painter to whom I showed the Cathedral.  Then we picked up Ella &amp; Fearne, &amp; returned to Auckland Castle.  Rain began to fall as we approached Auckland.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[269]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"It is difficult to over–estimate the amount of evil in the world which has sprung from vices in literature <hi rend="bold underline">that may be distinctly traced to the circumstances of the author</hi>. Had Rousseau been a happy and a prosperous man, the whole history of modern Europe might have been changed."</p>
         <p>(Lecky.<persName xml:id="3601"></persName> Hist: of England. ii. 76)</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This connexion between a man's circumstances and his opinions is as certain as it is very humiliating.  It should lead us to be on the watch against everything which depresses the condition of men, especially of such as are sensitive and talented: and </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">it should make us very suspicious of those opinions of our own which might naturally grow from our situation</hi><hi rend="italic">.  Especially in the case of the young ought we to try to make circumstances as favourable to sane &amp; cheerful opinions as possible, for </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">if the iron has entered into the soul of a boy, there is small hope that the man will outgrow the wound</hi><hi rend="italic">. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The thoughts of a boy are long, long thoughts</hi><hi rend="italic">', writes a poet very truly.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
