<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[345]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> September, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Vicar of Pallion gave me a horrifying account of the overcrowding which proceeds in demure little streets of neat new five&#8211;roomed houses, which the Sunderland Corporation has erected for the use of the 'slummites' evicted from the inner part of their city. He said that the rent – 17/6 per week (it had been reduced to that figure from 27/6) being altogether beyond the means of the tenants, they were driven to sub&#8211;letting, &amp; that as many as 4 families were existing in a single house. This is very abominable, but the remedy is not so apparent as one could wish. The rent, though exorbitant, is probably not 'economic': and it is hard to see why the rate payers of Sunderland should be taxed in order to house a section (and that the least desirable) of the inhabitants. Yet the situation in Pallion is so revolting as to be properly intolerable. Unless we are to enslave the people, &amp; house them on terms of slavery, it is not easy to justify the expense of housing them decently, and the coercive discipline necessary to make them keep the houses decent.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[346]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="doubleunderline">Tubby" Clayton</hi>, the organizer &amp; prophet of "<hi rend="underline">Toc H</hi>." was brought to see me by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Slater</hi>, the local "<hi rend="underline">padre</hi>". They both lunched here. What do I think of "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Tubby</hi>"? Frankly, much what I thought before seeing him; &amp; that is not much. In shape, type, &amp; aspect he is not ulike "<hi rend="doubleunderline">Gypsy" Smith</hi>. I cross&#8211;examined him rather closely about "<hi rend="underline">Toc H</hi>.", and was not well impressed.  He goes off in large &amp; picturesquely phrased generalities whenever he is in a 'tight place'.  And I did not succeed in gaining a clear notion of the methods &amp; objectives of the movement.  He claims that it has revolutionized the conditions under which young Englishmen go out to India to work: that it <hi rend="strikethrough">was</hi> 
<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>is<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> the main source from which Ordination candidates are obtained: that it provide<hi rend="strikethrough">d</hi>s Scout&#8211;masters &amp; C. L. B. Officers all over the country: and, in fact, that it <hi rend="strikethrough">was</hi> 
<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>is<hi rend="subscript">^ </hi>the hope of the future.  Both he and his 'bear – leader' spoke of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pestle</hi>, whom they were evidently anxious to disavow. But I perceived that he had been more closely connected with '<hi rend="underline">Toc H</hi>' than they cared to admit.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[347]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and 'opened' an Exhibition organised by the <hi rend="underline">Colonial &amp; Continental Church Society</hi>.  I made a speech, and gave my notes to the reporters.  Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi> showed me divers "sites" which had been suggested for the new school, which is to be built in the town.  I said that the matter was so important that a Conference with the <hi rend="underline">Board for Religious Instruction</hi> ought to take place.  Then I returned to Auckland, &amp; found Ella's party in full swing.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joan Surtees</hi>, the High Sheriff's daughter, who divorced one husband, now designs to take another.  She evidently asked to get speech with me: and I had much talk with her.  Her father divorced his wife, so that the tradition of domestic felicity is not exalted.  How woeful it is!  And here is <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inge</hi> telling the world that the church has no message <hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>for<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> it,, and another of his prating crew deriding the very notion of the 'spiritual' and the 'religious'.  We live in strange times, &amp; our worst foes are they of our own household.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
