<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[350]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Michael &amp; All Angels, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p rend="Normal" style="text&#8211;align: left; text&#8211;align: right;">
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">ORDINATION</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A steady rain fell during the night, and continued when we gathered in the Hall for the Litany, which was read here for our convenience as well as in S. Mary's according to the Rubrick. This is the second occasion on which I have adminstered Holy Orders in a parish church. I ordained a deacon (Surtees) in S. Andrew's, Bishop Auckland, some years ago. From the parochial point of view the arrangement is generally thought to be advantageous, but the candidates commonly prefer to be ordained in the cathedral. Having but a single candidate, and the Chapel being still in the hands of the workmen, I had this year no choice. In "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" parishes there is the risk that unwittingly the Bishop may find himself associated with a lawless ceremonial which he dislikes, but cannot avoid.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[351]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Pattinson, Clothier &amp; I motored to South Shields, &amp; there, in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's Tynedock I ordained Clothier to the diaconate.  There was a fair congregation, and the service was very devout.  Garland's sermon was a very poor performance, but he is a good parson, and, in Charles II's luminous phrase, "his nonsense suited their nonsense".</p>
         <p>We motored to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishopwearmouth Rectory</hi>, &amp; there lunched. Then we went to All Saints, &amp; I dedicated a memorial window set up in honour of Mary Boddy, the late Vicar's Wife. There was a large congregation, &amp; I preached on the Effect of Christianity in exalting the position of Women. After tea with the Vicar &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Saxton, we returned to Bishopwearmouth Rectory, where I rested until it was time to go to the parish church for Evensong.  I preached the sermon, &amp; dedicated a litany desk presented in memory of some member of the congregation.  After the service we returned to Auckland Castle.  The number of cars on the road was very large.  This may be explained by the fact that their licences will in many cases run out tonight.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
