<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The very Rev<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Walter Harper</hi>, sometime Dean of Christchurch, N.Z. would appear to be a man of strong opinions &amp; choleric temperament. I received from him a brief letter as follows:&#8211;</p>
         <p>'Saying attributed to A. P. Stanley late Dean of Westminster. "<hi rend="underline">When a man puts on the lawn slieves, he deteriorates mentally and spiritually</hi>". There are some brilliant exceptions among Bishops, notably so among those who have worked in New Zealand &amp; the islands of Melanesia. It might be well for you to consider how far the reported statement of Dean Stanley applies to you. Your unconsidered remarks re: Disestablishment may produce disastrous consequences . (see Article in English Review.) A keen sense of duty &amp; regard for the welfare of the church ought to lead to resignation of the Office of a Diocesan Bishop. Perhaps it is not too late to publicly and wholeheartedly confess that your views are foolish, uncalled for &amp; indicate clearly the "<hi rend="underline">sin of stupidity</hi>".'</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The stars in their courses</hi><hi rend="italic">" are fighting against the Bishops. What malignant influence led the lawyers of the Church Assembly to adopt the cause of the Vicar of Hauxton against one Stevens, a local landowner, who repudiated his obligation to repair the chancel of Hauxton Church, and has been imprisoned for disregarding the verdict of the diocesan chancellor. Somebody sends me a copy of "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Christian World</hi><hi rend="italic">" (July 18</hi><hi rend="i superscript">th</hi><hi rend="italic">, 1929) which gives much prominence to an article, '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Laws &amp; Lawlessness, the Stevens Case &amp; the Prayer Book by Wickham Steed</hi><hi rend="italic">'. It draws an effective contrast between the decision of the Bishops to ignore the law in the matter of the Prayer Book: and the Church Assembly's relentless insistence on the law in the case of Hauxton Chancel. I shall be surprized if this trumpery business in the Ely diocese does not develope into a considerable agitation. It just provides a concrete illustration of the preposterous paradox which the Establishment has now become. The popular imagination may easily find in it a fixed point about which to concentrate itself.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Ella and I motored to Harrogate, in order to attend the Speech Day of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Queen Ethelburga School</hi><hi rend="italic">, which is one of the Woodward Schools.  We lunched at 12.45 p.m. with Miss </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Young</hi><hi rend="italic">, the Headmistress.  At 2 p.m. there was service in the Chapel, when I preached the sermon.  Then followed the Prize Distribution at which the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Dean of Westminster</hi><hi rend="italic">, as Provost, presided.  The prizes were distributed by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Baillie</hi><hi rend="italic">, the Vice&#8211;Chancellor of Leeds University. He made a rather long oration, which was perhaps too heavily homiletic for the occasion. I supported the Vote of thanks in a brief foolish speech: &amp; then we all had tea. One of the girls introduced herself to me as the daughter of M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Gray Turner</hi><hi rend="italic">, who had operated on me for appendicitis! On the whole I was favourable impressed by the School, and by the bright &amp; healthy appearance of the girls. I learned with much satisfaction that the Woodward Schools are to be extended to the colonies, where they are much needed. After tea we returned to the Castle arriving back at 6.45 p.m. having travelled 112 miles in going and returning. There were clouds, but no rain.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
