<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[282]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"It is a great calamity for a people when its criminal classes have learned to take an active part in politics."</p>
         <p>Lecky<persName xml:id="3601"></persName> iii. 157</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Leng</hi> took the Austin car into Newcastle to have some repairs effected = &amp; left me without resource for my journey to South Shields where I had arranged to institute <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Booth</hi> to the Vicarage of Holy Trinity.  However <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> succeeded in raising a car in the town, which carried us to South Shields in time for the service.  A large number of the local clergy attended – an evidence of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi>'s popularity. There was a considerable congregation including a rather unusual proportion of men. I spoke from I. Cor: I.10 "<hi rend="underline">Now, I beseech you, brethren, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, that ye all speak the same thing, &amp; that there be no divisions among you: but that ye be perfected together in the same mind &amp; in the same judgement</hi>". It seemed to be a sincere &amp; edifying service: but then who can tell?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[283]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"It cannot be too emphatically stated that there is no historical evidence for the theory which connects the new birth of Europe with the passing away of the fateful millennial year &amp; with it of the awful dread of a coming end of all things."</p>
         <p>Rashdall 'Universites' I. 31</p>
         <p>Among the clergy at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi>'s institution was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Holmes</hi>, who had been Vicar of the church when I came there as a Missioner more than 30 years ago. Also, there was a decent–looking man in a black gown, who took his place with the clergy, &amp; was afterwards introduced to me as the local Baptist minister.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Alfred Fawkes</hi> arrived from Scotland for a short visit.  He seems very well, but looks more papistical than ever!</p>
         <p>The newspapers give prominence to the statement that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Father Vernon</hi>, the most prominent of the Anglo–Catholick preachers, has been received into the Roman Church. I should think it neither unlikely nor undesirable that his example should be followed by others.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
