<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, May 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The day started well but became blustering &amp; unpleasant as it advanced.  </p>
         <p>A Congregationalist minister named George Foster, who was recommended to me by Spurries, came to see me at his own request in order to offer himself as a candidate for Holy Orders. He is 33, married, &amp; has one child: has never been to any college: and was "ordained" by the Congregationalists. He seemed to be well meaning but to have a curiously inadequate view the gravity of the step he desired to take. I was not very encouraging, but said that I would ask the Bishop of Jarrow to report on his educational qualifications.</p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Cullagh and Lionel. He (the old doctor) is an indefatigable reader, &amp; has just finished the five volumes of Creighton's Papacy, &amp; was properly chagrined at its abrupt termination just when the most interesting period had been reached. I lent him the book, "Where Socialism failed."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Dick Shepperd's appointment as Dean of Canterbury is announced in the papers.  He has been 22 years in Orders, and has made himself famous (or notorious) by the extravagance of this writing &amp; speaking.  He was the Secretary of the Life and Liberty Group of which Temple was the leader, &amp; Bell the <hi rend="underline">amicus curiae</hi>. The overthrow of the old methods, standards, &amp; ideals could hardly be more complete. Baldwin's zeal for Youth &amp; feminism carries all before it. Yet something more respectable than mere conservative prejudice may feel misgivings at the sharp &amp; sudden departure from the old paths. The Deanery of Canterbury has in the past been associated with seniority &amp; scholarship. It has become a post for juniors &amp; pass&#8211;men: for I think Dick S. may be so described. The C.H. for General Booth, &amp; the premier Deanery for Dick Shepperd make one rub one's eyes, &amp; wonder where we go.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
