<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[306]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie Lillingston</hi> writes to me from Castle Forbes, C. Longford, where he has been tutoring a son of Lord <hi rend="doubleunderline">Granard</hi>:&#8211;</p>
         <p>"I have been struck by the great poverty of the people – no one will risk capital here, and it does not seem to me that the present régime, as it stands now, will last a long time.  The local Protestant Church has been restored &amp; endowed by Lady Granard, &amp; is fairly well attended &amp; conducted considering the sparseness of the population, but the minister has such a brogue that I can hardly understand a word he says.  The Church of Rome, of course, embraces the vast majority of the people, and all the priests I have met have been very pleasant men, &amp; seem to have a tremendous hold on the people.  But it is extraordinary how they all hunt and fish and shoot, a thing which few Church of England clergy do".  </p>
         <p>In fact the Protestant has the crude severity of the English Sectary, &amp; the Popish priest the amiable secularity of the old&#8211;time English parson.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[307]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The vi<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> volume of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lecky</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">History of England</hi> has an account of the Test &amp; Corporation Acts.  It states clearly that Dissenters could sit in Parliament and exercise the franchise (p. 3).</p>
         <p>"It is indeed a singular &amp; characteristic fact that the laws of Elizabeth making it a criminal offence not </p>
         <p>to attend public worship in England were not repealed until 1844 and 1846. (p.11)</p>
         <p>After lunch Ella, Mrs. K, and I motored to Spennymoor to see the scene of the great Fire of yesterday, in which a large furniture manufactory was destroyed, &amp; a number of families burnt out of house &amp; home. The Vicar gave us such information as he could, &amp;, on his advice, I sent my contribution to the Northern Star Relief Fund. I gave &#x00A3;10, which is more than I can afford.</p>
         <p>Adamson of Grangetown came to see me, &amp; I discussed with him the complaint which I had received from a parishioner. Then I walked to 3 Waddington Road, &amp; inquired after Kenneth. I saw his father &amp; then called on Dr. McCullagh.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
