<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, July 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>When passions are calm, shams flourish.  Mere verbal Theories which could not stand the strain of a real agitation, pass muster in the calmer intervals. </p>
         <p>Leslie Stephens. History of English Thought in the xviii<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Century. vol. ii p. 166.</p>
         <p>This is being demonstrated in the case of the Establishment of the Church of England.</p>
         <p>I motored to Barnard Castle, and presided at a meeting of the Governor. The decline in numbers continues, &amp; the school is no longer paying its way. We decided to hold a special meeting to consider the situation.</p>
         <p>Hodgson &amp; Bircham were both present, but quite well–behaved.</p>
         <p>Numerous company appeared to play tennis, including Sir Edmund &amp; lady Chaytor.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lag Söderblom</hi> came also.  He gave an ill account of his father's health.</p>
         <p>The drought continues, but the heat is less oppressive. The country generally is getting to look 'burnt up'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Carnegie Simpson</hi> reviews the Charge in the '<hi rend="underline">British Weekly</hi>' rather belittlingly, the book will "not precipitate a crisis'.</p>
         <p>'But it will help to prepare the Anglican mind for what will happen some day – and in politics "some day" may easily mean "any day" – and meanwhile he (the Bishop of Durham) is to be credited with an intellectual candour and a moral courage which, along with an exceptionally clear and forceful style will find for his book appreciative, even if not always, convinced, readers.'</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Times of India</hi>' has an article which purports to give an account of the Bishop of Durham but so evidently knows nothing about him that its estimate of his character &amp; opinions is worthless.</p>
         <p>"At length Dr Henson reached Hereford: but his visits to London were so innumerable that Anglo–Catholic curates w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> ask pertly whether he thought his Diocese was situated somewhere in the metropolis".</p>
         <p>Now did you ever? I am notoriously an absentee from nearly all meetings in London.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
