<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[107]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edmund Bishop's</hi> pamphlet – "<hi rend="underline">The Genius of the Roman Rite</hi>' – which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dearmer</hi><persName xml:id="2633"></persName> had sent me.  He distinguishes in the Mass between the older elements which are originally Roman, and the later which came from other than Roman sources, and he maintains that the former are recognizably marked by the '<hi rend="underline">sobeness and sense</hi>' which are characteristic of the Roman genius. At the Counter–Reformation the Roman Books received definitive form, &amp; the Congregation of Rites was created '<hi rend="underline">to keep observances on the lines laid down in those books</hi>'. But the non–Roman spirit has continued to be active, though being no longer able to express itself in the fixed official services, it utters itself in what are called "<hi rend="underline">devotions</hi>". '<hi rend="underline">This is the explanation, too, of that contrast which so many writers have drawn between the tone of our official prayer books, the missal, the breviary, &amp; the rest, and the books of devotion in general use amongst us</hi>". It is an evil choice between the crude, crisp literalism of the Dark Ages", and the luscious sentimentalism of latter day 'Democracy'!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[108]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I had asked Dearmer whether he could tell me when gongs as 'sacring bells' were introduced into the Church of Rome. He replies:</p>
         <p>'So far as I know gongs are a nineteenth–century invention, but I could not swear to it'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop Söderblom</hi><persName xml:id="2166"></persName> and his daughter left the Castle at 12.30 noon.  He vainly pressed me to attend another of his endless congresses in August.  The dear man's belief in these gatherings is unlimited.</p>
         <p>After lunch we motored to Pittington where I consecrated a burial ground.  The weather was curiously cold, &amp; I thought it judicious not to give an address.  We had tea at the Vicarage.  I had a short interview with old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Buddy</hi>, who evidently shrinks from the thought of resignation, though he has been confined to the house for the last 8 months! I rather weakly consented to let the matter stand over until the end of the summer. He will not complete the necessary tenure of the benefice for seven years until the end of the year.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
