<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[272]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After much hesitation, I declined the invitation of the Editor of '<hi rend="underline">History</hi>' to write an article on the Castle: and I suggested the <hi rend="doubleunderline">K. C. Bayley</hi> should be asked to undertake it.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charlie Sillingston</hi> in answer to his letter from Ireland, where he is wrestling with the problem presented by the two spoiled boys of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Granard</hi>, whose American wife treats her children with the criminal indulgence which has produced that awful product, 'the American Boy'!</p>
         <p>[symbol] Also I wrote at some length to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vernon Storr</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">made copy of my letter, as likely to be serviceable as a record of my opinions at this difficult time</hi>.</p>
         <p>I must have renewed my chill yesterday, when I foolishly sate for awhile in the open watching cricket, for today I am physically in an ill case.  </p>
         <p>We (i.e. the Painter, Ella, Fearne &amp; myself) motored to Sherburn Hospital, &amp; had tea.  Leaving the ladies to play tennis, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Speed</hi> &amp; I went on to Durham, &amp; saw the Castle.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[273]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The '<hi rend="underline">Evening World</hi>' has a column by '<hi rend="underline">A Lady of Title</hi>' which contains rather copious references to Auckland Castle which makes it quite evident that the writer is none other than <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Chaytor</hi> who dined here on August 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.  She mentions <hi rend="doubleunderline">Darling</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Di</hi>'s singing and <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Speed</hi>, and my portrait, and Bek's sword.  <hi rend="bold underline">There are few things which seem to me more objectionable, &amp; potentially mischievous than the practice, which is said to be increasing, of abusing hospitality in the service of journalism. Who will accept invitations to dinner if they have reason to suspect that their conversation will be reported by somebody at the table? [symbol] Even if invitations are accepted, the freedom of social intercourse is destroyed, &amp; everybody talks warily. Yet neither Ella nor the Painter seemed to see the enormity of this penny&#8211;a&#8211;liner's eavesdropping. No doubt the latter is pleased to be talked about on any terms, but the former might be expected to be sensitive on the subject. Perhaps, only men are resentful of spying &amp; gossip, which are too near the feminine interests to provoke indignation</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
