<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[157]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The great heat continues.  I spent most of the day in the Assembly.  The debate on my motion provoked replies of amazing irrelevance, and the motion itself was of course lost, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I think that an impression was made which may be useful</hi><hi rend="italic">. In the afternoon I made a speech about artisan candidates for Ordination which was much applauded, though it was really a very poor ragged performance.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined at the Mansion House where the Lord Mayor entertained the Archbishops and Bishops, and proposed the health of the Lord Mayor.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lang</hi><hi rend="italic"> made his first appearance there as Archbishop of Canterbury.  He made rather a pompous speech, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">in which he took occasion to express himself a believer in the Establishment</hi><hi rend="italic">, a statement which seemed to me to be rather coldly received.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Temple</hi><hi rend="italic"> proposed the toast of the overseas Bishops, &amp; the Bishop of Bombay responded.   He is a heavy speaker, &amp; rather preached than made an after&#8211;dinner speech.  I wrote my name in the Lord Mayor's book.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Dibdin</hi> was almost oleaginously civil to me in the Assembly today.  Perhaps he also, like others, has felt, after reading "Disestablishment", that I may be perverse, but am not either necessarily insincere or apparently inconsistent.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pelham</hi>, the Bishop of Barrow&#8211;in&#8211;Furness, sent me a note of approval of my speech, "<hi rend="underline">and even more for the way in which you said it. It was simply magnificent</hi>".  Nevertheless, the speech was not satisfactory, &amp;, when I sate down, I had the consciousness that I had failed to say what I really wanted to say, &amp; had not succeeded in conveying the intention with which I spoke.  <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Haigh</hi><hi rend="italic"> reminded me that in 1921 I had taken another line on the subject of poor clergymen: &amp; I could not but confess frankly that the years had compelled a change of attitude.  We may like artisan&#8211;candidates or not: but we cannot escape from the fact that there are few others!</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
