<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[314]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Loxley</hi>, Rector of Byers Green, offering him Coniscliffe, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sharpe</hi>, the Vicar of S. Barnabas, Worcester, offering him S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Cuthbert's, Gateshead.</p>
         <p>My post this morning included no less than 4 episcopal letters. The Bishops of Oxford, Gloucester, Southwark, &amp; Blackburn wrote to me on divers matters.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Blackburn </hi>writes:–</p>
         <p>"I do agree with you about the Pastoral letter – it was dull and wordy, and could mean little or nothing to our simpler folk, with the result that I think it has fallen quite flat, &amp; has not stirred the clergy at all".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Oxford</hi> writes more kindly:–</p>
         <p>"I think the Archbishops meant more than Bible classes. I find some resentment in the Rural Deaneries that they should be supposed to be in need of study".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi>'s 'Notes' on the anti–Modernist agitation are excellent, &amp; ought to do good.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[315]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">The Bishop of Southwark</hi> gave an account of the recent episode in the Canterbury Convocation:</p>
         <p>'The Furse–Barnes business in the Canterbury Convocation was more unfortunate.<hi rend="bold underline">  Furse read a carefully prepared &amp; laboured attack on Barnes; the Archbishop called him to order more than once, but with increasing vehemence he went on his way.  Barnes was absurdly sensitive and frequently interrupted.  It was the more unfortunate and unfair as Barnes had been unprovocative  in the speech he had made earlier</hi>.           </p>
         <p>This is interesting and not insignificant.</p>
         <p>Ella, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> K, Pattison and I motored to Hetton–le–Hole, where I dedicated the reredos &amp; panelling placed in the parish church as a memorial of the Women who were killed in the Darlington Railway Accident on June 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1928.  There was a large congregation of women including many members of the Mothers' Union.  My sermon, delivered from the Chancel Step, was well listened to.  After the service we all drove to Chester–le–Street, and had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Barrett.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
