<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[230]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I worked all the morning at the Article, but have not yet "struck oil".</p>
         <p>In the afternoon I went to Darlington, where a F&amp;ecircte in aid of the British Legion was formally opened by the Countess Haig. Before the function there was tea in a tent. I sate beside Lady Haig, and had some conversation with her. She is a frail, thin, rather sad looking woman with a pleasant expression and manner. She told me that she had much difficulty in protecting her son, the present Earl, who is just eleven from the newspaper men, &amp; even more difficulty in avoiding them herself. I made a brief &amp; foolish speech in response to an unexpected call from the Mayor. There can be no doubt that I am very helpless without preparation.</p>
         <p>Lord Thurlow, with his wife, &amp; two sons, Harry &amp; Francis, arrived to stay the night. The boys have grown tall. Harry is now at Sandhurst, &amp; Francis is about to enter at Cambridge.</p>
         <p>The weather today is cooler, &amp; there are threatenings of rain.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[231]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Old Mr. Proud the Coroner came in after dinner to meet the Thurlows, and I had some conversation with him. He is an enthusiast for birds, and evidently knows a good deal about them. Lord Grey and he had commerce together in this interest. When he was a young man living at Binchester, he often passed through the Park, &amp; encountered Bishop Baring. He described the Bishop as a mild amiable person, 'not the least like a bishop', who kept six cows, &amp; liked to talk about farming. I asked him whether he had noticed changes in the levels of the Park, &amp; he replied with an emphatic affirmative. He said that there were far fewer birds in the Park than heretofore, and agreed with me that the numerous magpies were probably to a large extent responsible for the fact. He breeds several kinds of birds, &amp; has a number of ducks on his pond. I promised that I would visit him, &amp; see his aviary. These old men – McCullagh the doctor, and Proud the Coroner – are admirable examples of types which were once commoner than they are now.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
