<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929, Biarritz.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Before going to bed I wrote to Lillington and Gerald Rainbow.</p>
         <p>The night was very warm, and the mosquitoes very active. We changed our watches to summer&#8211;time – a perturbing process.</p>
         <p>Letters from Lionel &amp; Jack Clayton arrived, &amp;, after breakfast, I wrote to the latter.  Then we attended morning service in the English Church.  There was a fair congregation mainly of women with a sprinkling of old men.  The choir was mainly composed of females in surplices, an arrangement which I detest.  When R. J. Campbell introduced a female choir in the City Temple, there was considerable disturbance over what was thought a violent breach of decorum.  Now such choirs are frequently seen in Anglican churches.  I do not doubt that the 'monstrous regiment' of women, having succeeded in occupying the choir&#8211;stalls, will soon proceed to lay hands on the pulpit and even the altar. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[41]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The officiating clergyman was elderly. He wore a black hood, which may have been the hood of the Oxford B. D., but looked equally like the too&#8211;familiar vestment of the literate. He had a loud and rather uncultivated voice, a considerable command of language, and the carriage of a popular orator who affects the character.</p>
         <p>Then I wrote to Lionel &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arthur Rawle</hi>.  We walked round the cliff to the golf&#8211;course (which seemed too restricted in area), and then had tea very comfortably in the <hi rend="underline">Hotel Regina et de Golf</hi>. Then, the air being sultry and exertion by consequence distasteful, we returned to the Hotel.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Arthur.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> of yesterday reports the presentation of a motor car to the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Norwich</hi>. The presentation was made by the Home Secretary who warmly thanked the Bishop for "the marvellous lead he gave them in the House of Lords".</p>
         <p>'He (the Bishop) was their champion throughout the country, &amp; spared neither time nor labour to set forth what they <hi rend="bold">[42] </hi>believed to be the true Evangelical doctrine on which the Church of England was founded, or re&#8211;founded at the Reformation.' The Bishop's reply was not uninteresting. Of course he had a fling at me.</p>
         <p>"The fact that there had been no Prayer&#8211;book revision was no reason why people should, in an impetuous &amp; unwise way, call out for disestablishment. The two things had nothing to do with each other."</p>
         <p>It is odd that the Prayer Book Controversy should have transfigured Bertram Pollock into a demagogue: and me into an advocate for Disestablishment.</p>
         <p>After dinner, I wrote yet one more letter – to my brother Gilbert.  <hi rend="underline">I have now written to no less than 36 persons since I came abroad, and to two of them, more than once. This may be allowed to be a creditable performance; which argues some kindness, &amp; much industry</hi>!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
