<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[228]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, July 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There was a welcome rain last night which penetrated as much as three inches.  I made a start on the article for the <hi rend="underline">Nineteenth Century &amp; After</hi>, but made small progress.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Rufus</hi> joined the Army and went off without so much as a word of farewell!  Yet I have been kind to him.  I confirmed him.  But there is little sentiment in these people, &amp;, of course, no consideration!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson,</hi> my new chaplain, came to stay a few days here before Lionel departs to learn something of his duties.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">The notices of the Archbishops' Letter are not very complimentary. Indeed it is a very poor production, &amp; leaves one in some astonishment that their Graces should have thought it worth putting out</hi>. The solitary suggestion is so trivial as to seem almost petty. "<hi rend="underline">Bible study circles</hi>" are hardly the prime requisite in such a situation of confusion as that into which the Church has come. Yet I can find nothing else in the Pastoral Letter.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[229]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>An American Bishop, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Atkinson</hi>, the co&#8211;adjutor of (I think) Arizona, who has been staying at the Deanery, Durham, came to see me. He is a hale old man of 72, like all Americans loquacious &amp; dogmatic, but unlike many Americans, not offensive.</p>
         <p>Jimmie Dobbie brought his fianc&amp;#x00E9; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Joyce Jobling</hi>, to tea. She is a young pretty girl with an intelligent manner. The spectacle of a clergyman "in love" is always a little ridiculous, but one must make allowances.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received a formal invitation to the functions in Edinburgh in October</hi> which are to "consummate" the Reunion of the two Presbyterian Churches in Scotland.  I accepted, but without enthusiasm, <hi rend="bold underline">for these orgies of mutual compliment are very trying, &amp; make me melancholy! Moreover, I think the unreality of this particular fusion is in some respects unusually great. There was never any adequate cause for the schism: &amp; the principal motive in bringing it to an end has been religious than economical.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
