<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[61]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">AUCKLAND CASTLE</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I filled the day with writing cheques, letters, &amp;c, and looking round on the ravages of dilapidation. The very cold weather has held back the vegetation so that the country has still a bleak almost wintry appearance. Daffodils are in flower, but the wall&#8211;flowers are only beginning to blossom. A football game was proceeding in the Park when I walked there during the afternoon.</p>
         <p>That odd youth, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Noel Lamidey</hi>, who was a clerk in the Chapter Office, when I was Dean, writes to me from Melbourne, sending me some excellent photographs of the Australian blacks, &amp; a very intelligent discussion of Australian affairs. ["At present I am not too widely possessed of this world's goods, but then I have youth, (for I am only 34 on the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>), ambitions, and ideals, which I hope, may one day carry me over the top." The youth, as I remember him, was a very anaemic, feeble&#8211;looking person, who seemed predestined to an early death.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[62]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>He tells me that at a trials of a local Labour leader – Holloway, Secretary of the Trades Hall Council – for inciting the Lumber Workers Union to defy the decision of the Arbitration Court, the knave had the impudence to refer to me as providing a precedent for his advocacy of law&#8211;breaking.  "In a statement to the Unionists and the Press, he said: "the best way to defeat bad laws is to ignore them, &amp; I strongly advise members to ignore all orders or requests which encroach upon the rights and principles of collective bargaining." …  In his defence he, the accused man, claimed to speak as he did under moral laws, &amp; that [British history teemed with incidents of men &amp; women who had ignored laws in defence of liberty and freedom of speech.  Sir Edward Carson had defied the Government in what he believed to be the rights of Ulster, &amp;] <hi rend="underline">quite recently the Bishop of Durham had urged the people to disobey the law with regard to the new Prayer Book, and had gone unpunished</hi>." He was fined &#x00A3;50.</p>
         
            </body></text></TEI>
