<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[172]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">. 1929.                 </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                                                 </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi> appeared to have seized the opportunity of my absence from Escombe to make a rather gross attack on me, which is reported very prominently in the <hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>.  The facts are these.  A service had been arranged for 3 p.m. on Wednesday, &amp; I had promised to preach: but on Sunday, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi> died, &amp;, I conceived to be my obvious duty to attend his funeral at 2.15 p.m. in Durham Cathedral.  On Monday, therefore, the Rural Dean went to Escombe, &amp; suggested to Hodgson that the hour of service should be altered to 6 p.m. in order that I might be able both to attend the funeral, &amp; to fulfil my promise.  He refused to alter the hour, wrote to me an insolent letter, and struck an attitude of aggrieved protest.  In these circumstances, I informed him through my Chaplain that I could not attend the service.  The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" has a report on its front page headed 'Vicar criticizes Bishop' which suggests that I had kept a congregation waiting for 3 hours, &amp; includes a general denunciation of the Bishop , &amp; a particular censure of me!  </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[173]</hi>
                                                                     
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                    </p>
         <p>Now, I apprehend, that Hodgson had no cause at all for his (simulated) indignation.  Every engagement is made with the implied understanding that no unforeseen hindrance will emerge.  I could not have foreseen Wilson's death.  In view of his position, long service as an Officer in the diocese, &amp; personal friendship, I was bound to attend his funeral.  The postponement of the hour of service would have caused no inconvenience to anybody: &amp; ample time was given to enable such notice to be given.  How gratuitous the whole outburst was is apparent from the fact that <hi rend="bold underline">he took occasion to enlarge on the iniquity of the Bishops in the matter of the Revised Prayer Book, and the "obsession" of the Bishop of Durham with the subject of Bolshevism, subject which, however interesting and important, were hardly relevant to the occasion.  I suspect that the triumph of "Labour" at the General Election has stirred vast hopes in the minds of their clerical supporters.  The key to Hedgson's gratuitous insolence is probably his desire to command himself to the powers that be, &amp; thus to gain some advancement! </hi>    
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
                                              
         </p>
         <p>Kenneth came to lunch.  He is taller and thinner than before.  He is curiously wayward and irrational, but I think it is probable that the root of his folly is the wound to his <hi rend="underline">amour propre</hi> caused by his being required to read for a pass degree.  I am in much doubt as to my duty towards him.   </p>
         <p>Two Bede College students — <hi rend="bold underline">Tate</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">and Hughes – came to see me with the object of being accepted as candidates for Holy Orders. The latter was a particularly attractive young fellow.</hi>  
<hi rend="bold underline">I accepted them both</hi>.   </p>
         <p>I have spent most of the morning &amp; part of the afternoon in "sitting" to Mr. Speed.  After tea I took him for a run in the motor.  We visited the fine Churches of Sedgefield and Hartlepool, which he admired greatly especially the latter.  The weather became colder as the day drew to a close, and a fire again became welcome in my study.  </p>
         <p>Mr. Baldwin visited Durham, and received a degree: but I did not attend the ceremonial.  My presence might well have been unwelcome.                                 </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
