<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[242]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A close and cloudy day. I wasted the morning in doing the correspondence. Then I read Ogg's book, which is most interesting. In the afternoon I walked in the Park, &amp; had much talk with the young men there. This being the early–closing day, the Park is invaded by the shop–assistants.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Archdeacon &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Rawlinson came to dine.  I had much talk with him, and was perhaps, rather perturbed by his vague and visionary opinions.  He is evidently a very convinced "Anglo–Catholic" of the new type, which is much more patient of criticism, &amp; far less tenacious of dogma than the old, but also much more devoted to emotional sacramentalism.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The papers print the test of the draft agreement between England &amp; Egypt. It has an unpleasing appearance, &amp; suggests a policy of "scuttle". The effect of such an agreement on public opinion in India can hardly but be considerable and mainly mischievous. Quo tendimus?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[243]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>From <hi rend="underline">Durham Old</hi> The Bishop ivy sends,</p>
         <p>A friendly envoy to <hi rend="underline">New Durham's</hi> Friends.</p>
         <p>What grew on <hi rend="bold underline">Auckland Castle</hi> grows again,</p>
         <p>And shall grow faster in the soil of <hi rend="bold underline">Maine</hi>.</p>
         <p>"About 100 years ago a Friends' Meeting was opened at a place called Durham, Maine, U.S.A. and Friends in that meeting will celebrate the event at Quarterly Meeting there on August 31<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>?  <hi rend="bold underline">It has been suggested that they secure some Ivy Roots from Durham, England, so as to grow ivy over the porch of the Meeting House, &amp; the Field Sec.</hi> who is an Englishman has requested me to get someone from Durham to ship about half a dozen Ivy roots from Durham City, I suppose, at any rate from Durham C<hi rend="superscript underline">ty</hi>."</p>
         <p>From a letter addressed by James Wild, North Ferrisburg, R. D. 2 to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Matt. Robson of Bp  Auckland.</p>
         <p>July 26, 1929.</p>
         
            
         
         </body></text></TEI>
