<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[338]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">17th Sunday after Trinity, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The wind has fallen. I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's, and celebrated the Holy Communion.  There were 40 communicants, and among them John and Alexander.  The cherry tree, broken by last night's gale, has a woeful appearance, and defaces the drive.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi> and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George</hi>.  Also, I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lomax</hi> in answer to his voluminous account of a 'crisis' in his parish.  Some of his Choirmen have joined the <hi rend="underline">Wesleyan Male Choir</hi>, and he has required them either to retire from it, or to end their connexion with his choir! There must be no playing with schism in Ferryhill. He sends me a 'pastoral' which he has circulated in his parish, giving the parishioners 'sound doctrine' about the Catholick Church, &amp; he invites my opinion of it. I sent him together with my reply a copy of "<hi rend="underline">Ecclesiastica: a Triplet of 'Old Sermons'</hi>" which I issued in 1910 as a 'Christmas Card' for my people in Westminster.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[339]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"Always, in history, when men thought they were returning to the past, they were also creating a future that had never yet been."</p>
         <p>G. G. Coulton</p>
         <p>This might serve as the text for a Dissertation on the Reformation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Egglestone, where I preached at Evensong.  The "diamond jubilee" of the consecration of the parish church was being celebrated.  The deaf Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ladell</hi>, read the Prayers, and Pattinson the lessons.  After service we all went to the adjacent 'big house', and dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir William Gray</hi>, the ship&#8211;builder from West Hartlepool, and his newly&#8211;married wife. She is simple, unaffected, and rather attractive than pretty. After dinner we returned to Auckland. There was a moon, which shone intermittently through heavy banks of cloud. The wind, which had been high, fell at nightfall.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
