<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Some rain had fallen in the night, not enough to affect the water&#8211;supply (which is becoming a cause of anxiety) but enough to refresh the crops, &amp; beautify the country. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m., and administered the Sacrament to the 6 candidates.</p>
         <p>Rawlinson &amp; Wynne Willson came over for the Conference, &amp; stayed to lunch. After the youth had departed, I had some talk with W. W. about Jimmie. His preparation for his Degree has necessarily interfered with his work, and he has himself disclosed (along with much that is attractive &amp; precious) an impulsiveness and an instability, which arouse misgivings. What should be done for the best in his own interest? The situation has been complicated by his becoming engaged to be married to a very suitable girl, but only 18! I said that, if he failed to pass his exams, I thought that the attempt to get a degree must be abandoned: &amp; he must accept the position of a 'literate'. He cannot indefinitely divide his energies. It is time that he gave himself up to his ministry.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A party of 4 Canadian ladies arrived. One of them was Mildred Dennistoun, the wife of Ella's cousin. I left them in Ella's keeping when I went to Durham at 6 p.m. I called at S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> John's College, &amp; saw the Principal, who was in bed.  Then I presided at a meeting of the Lightfoot Trustees.  It is evident that the public demand for his books has almost petered out.  I dined with the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; then witnessed the taking of Oaths etc. by the Candidates in the Chapter Office.  When this was done, we all went to the Deanery Chapel, &amp; there I delivered my Charge, after which I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The General Election is extraordinarily decorous and even dull.  <hi rend="bold underline">It would seem that the introduction of women has emptied politics of interest, &amp; extended over the whole area of conflict </hi>a <hi rend="underline">Treuya ferniarum</hi>.  <hi rend="bold underline">The use of the new method of 'broadcasting' the speeches of the leaders has taken value from public meetings: &amp; the enormous multitude of electors has destroyed any real chance of educating them. Mad apathy prevails, &amp; while all three parties profess the most complete confidence, none has any trustworthy knowledge.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
