<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[256]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>An alarming report appears in the papers that Hugh MacNaughten, the Vice&#8211;Provost of Eton, is 'missing'. Loss of memory is feared, and some fatal accident. He was a particular friend of Ralph Inge, who will certainly feel acutely any disaster that may have befallen him. Later in the day, the news came that his body had been found in a backwater of the Thames.</p>
         <p>I wasted the day in sitting for my picture, in writing letters, and in preparing notes for a sermon on 'Intolerance'.</p>
         <p>Ella, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin, Speed and I motored to Walworth Castle, and had tea with Sir Alfred and Lady Palmer.  We saw the famous chestnut tree which has rooted itself over a large area in the manner of the well&#8211;known banyan tree.</p>
         <p>Lord Darling arrived a little before 6 p.m. I met him at the station; &amp; talked much with him before dinner. He was in excellent form, &amp; told stories from his judicial experience. Harold Speed "played up to" him admirably, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi>Darwin was flattered by his reminiscences of her father.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[257]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Darling</hi><hi rend="italic"> vouched for the following:&#8211;</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">An art&#8211;dealer sold a picture for &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="italic underline">700</hi><hi rend="italic">. The purchaser, happening to meet the painter, learned that the sum paid for painting the picture was only &#x00A3;</hi><hi rend="italic underline">100</hi><hi rend="italic">.  Very indignantly he protested to the art&#8211;dealer, and was met by the offer to re&#8211;fund the money, &amp; buy back the picture.  This was accepted, &amp; the picture was again offered for sale.  Another purchaser appeared &amp; inquired the price of the picture.  He was assured that the rule in fixing prices was to add 10 per cent to the actual amount paid for the picture.  A reference to the books showed that this was &#x00A3;700.  Accordingly the picture again changed hands, this time for &#x00A3;770.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">What was the moral aspect of this whole transaction?</hi><hi rend="italic">  That there was a serious </hi><hi rend="italic underline">suppressio veri</hi><hi rend="italic"> is apparent, though it is the case that no lie was actually spoken.  There can be no doubt that the traffic in pictures, as well the new as the old, rivals the traffic in horses in chicanery, swindling, and impudent fraudulency.  The ignorance and vanity of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">nouveaux riches</hi><hi rend="italic"> provide a fat soil for the thievery of the dealers.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
