<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The drought continues, but it is not quite so hot. I wrote to Graham White proposing that he should succeed Turner as Vicar of S. Paul's West Hartlepool.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">[symbol] M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Holford&#8211;Knight's question to the Prime Minister about the proceedings of the Bishops is stated to have been withdrawn for technical reasons.  I have no doubt that the Prime Minister is in some dubiety as to the answer which it would be judicious to return.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella and I motored to Stockton where we attended the wedding of Miss Ropner in Holy Trinity Church. The bridegroom was the son of M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Purvis, the late Vicar, who "tied the knot".  I gave the address.  After the service, we attended the reception at M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Leonard Ropner's house.  There was a mighty gathering of the Ropner clan.  The day had now grown to be sultry, and I started a headache.  As we returned through Bishopton, while Leng went to see his mother, Ella &amp; I walked on, and were recognized by the Bank&#8211;Manager, Sharp, <hi rend="bold">[207] </hi>[symbol] who lives in the village.  He hospitably insisted on our coming in to tea.  On <hi rend="italic">his table was a copy of "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Disestablishment</hi><hi rend="italic">", to which he directed my attention. He had bought, and (what is more remarkable) read it. He expressed agreement with my conclusions.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lionel</hi> and I motored to Hunwick, where I instituted that queer creature, whom I ordained four years ago, the Rev. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Albert Frederick de Burton</hi>.  In spite of the heat there was a considerable congregation.  The late Vicar, Briggs, was only five years in the parish, grumbling all the time against the house.  What do the people really think about the clergy?  The certainly hardly ever see them as an example of contentment: <hi rend="bold underline">I doubt where there is anywhere a more discontented set of people than the parish clergy. Yet they are, by comparison with the majority of their parishioners, better paid and better housed than their people: and no one, who has any adequate knowledge of the facts, could think that they are overworked. Yet they are devoured by a hungry discontent. Why</hi>?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
