<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
                                                                 
         </p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">Friday June 28th. 1929.       </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]                                </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The weather has been colder today, but there is still no sign of rain.  Apprehensions of drought come from all parts of the country.  I spent the day in sitting for my portrait, interviewing an Ordination Candidate (clothier)], and motoring Mr. Speed to Jarrow, where the Rector (Booth) showed us his most interesting Church.  </hi><hi rend="bold underline">He was rather crest&#8211;fallen when my painter pronounced his "Vandyck" to be the work of an inferior pupil, &amp; works about &#x00A3;5.! I had not myself seen before the very interesting fragments of Anglo&#8211;Saxon work presented in the porch.</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi><hi rend="italic"> returns to the charge.  The morning paper contains more denunciations of the Bishop of Durham.  Of course this matters little here where the foolish fellow is known, but his venomous nonsense gets repeated in the newspapers throughout the country, and tends to create an impression (impression) of me which is equally injurious and untrue.  But any attempt to correct that impression (impression) would play into Hodgson's hands, &amp; make him seem to be important.  So I must just "grin &amp; bear it"! </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
