<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[412]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday</hi>, <hi rend="bold">October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The morning post brought me disconcerting letters from the delator, <hi rend="underline">Tippetts</hi>, &amp; the archdeadon of Macclesfield. I decided to postpone the institution, which had been arranged for next Friday. Accordingly, telegrams were at once sent to the Churchwarden of Winlaton, announcing the postponement of the service, &amp; to the Vicar–designate, doing the same, &amp; adding the summons to come &amp; see me without delay. I received a telegram from the latter saying that he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> arrive today.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Wynne–Willson</hi> writes to say that, in spite of his advice, &amp; in the teeth of my letter, Jimmie Dobbie has decided to accept the offer of the school–mastership. I am sorry to hear this.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">There is a fair report of my observations on the Times leader in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Newcastle Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">. The statement which </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Temple</hi><hi rend="italic"> read &amp; approved appears in full. This will, I think, go some way towards removing the impressions which the Times leader cannot but have made, &amp; will tend to concentrate attention on the Commission.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[413]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="underline">Burkitt</hi> came to lunch, and to talk over the Barnard Castle School business.</p>
         <p>An Australian clergyman, the <hi rend="underline">Rev. Canon Cakebread</hi>, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Jude's, Randarick, Australia, called with a letter of introduction from the Abp. Of Sydney. I inquired about <hi rend="underline">Hickson</hi>'s<persName xml:id="5413"></persName> Healing Mission, and he expressed much doubt as to its permanent results, and some disgust of <hi rend="underline">Hickson</hi>'s financial methods.</p>
         <p>The Rev. Walter Brain arrived about 6 p.m. He is a heavy, florid man, not attractive in general aspect. He was evidently perturbed in no common degree, as was indeed only to be expected. I cross–examined him on the 3 matters concerning which I was not satisfied, viz. his physical adequacy to so heavy a charge as Winlaton: the allegation that he 'drank': and the allegation that he was in debt. He made out a fairly good case for himself, and gave me the names of two gentlemen in Bollington who, he said, were respectable and respected. I wrote to both of them before dinner. It is horribly inconvenient as the furniture is arriving tomorrow!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
