<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[368]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Wind and rain continued through the night with a violence which made me feel anxious for the Chapel. It was still raining in the morning when I left the Castle in order to go to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Anne's.  I celebrated at 8 o'clock.  There were about 90 communicants, and it was necessary to re&#8211;consecrate.  I suppose the larger number was occasioned by the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harvest Thanksgiving</hi>, which was being observed.  Alexander, Elland, and John were among the communicants.  Again I was painfully impressed by the absence of young males.  Considering that I have myself <hi rend="italic">confirmed in this parish about 400 boys during the last 9 years, it does seem strange that not more than 5 were present at the Holy Communion on a special occasion. Assuming that at least as many were at South Church, and doubling the number to allow for the later celebrations in both churches, and there is a total of 20, just five per cent! Yet I am sure that the present Vicar prepares his</hi> confirmation candidates with much care.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[369]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing a sermon for the "Diamond Jubilee" of the church at Jarrow Grange tonight. I wrote to Wykes, and to my godson, Gilbert.</p>
         <p>I read through Professor Williams's criticism of 'Disestablishment'. It is, as one would expect, brilliant, original, &amp; effective, but it does not appear to be adequate. It ignores altogether the almost complete paralysis of discipline which the Establishment now necessitates, &amp; which is in my view the weightiest count against it.</p>
         <p>Pattinson and I motored to Jarrow, where I preached in Jarrow Grange Church to a very large congregation. I felt woefully ill, and, when I got back to the Castle, was violently sick. M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullough was sent for, and prescribed. I soon felt better, and assume that it was but a passing indisposition: but such untoward occurrences are unusual with me, and as one draws towards the three score years &amp; ten, one's 'margin of safety' becomes ever narrower. It is a comfort to know that at least the Appendix is no more in the region of possibilities!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
