<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[448]                                                           </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbols]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Midleto</hi>n spoke to me last night about the disadvantage which came from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Baldwin's lack of experience in political life.  He said that he (Baldwin) was very forgetful, and that he took no advice in his ecclesiastical appointments.  Thus in the appointments to the Primacies, he had not even consulted the Chairman of the House of Laity (Selbourne).  Herein I must confess (though I did not tell L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Midleton as much) I think the Prime Minister showed his good sense.  <hi rend="bold underline">We talked about Q. Victoria, &amp; he said that he found her very difficult when he was War&#8211;Minister. He thought that her letter to L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">d</hi> 
<hi rend="bold underline">Lansdowne on the subject of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Gladstone was indefensible, but she became extremely autocratic and if she once formed a hostile opinion of anyone, nothing would induce her to abandon it.</hi>  He spoke very strongly about the abominable behaviour of L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Rothermere to Baldwin.</p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="bold">[449]                                                           </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbols]  </p>
         <p>Before descending to breakfast, I wrote to Ella: telling her of my purpose to return by the late train. After breakfast, I walked to the Athenaeum, &amp; from thence to the Assemby, where I listened for awhile to the debate on the Cathedrals Measure. <hi rend="underline">Hutton</hi> made his 'maiden' speech. That quaint creature, <hi rend="underline">Turner</hi>, also spoke. I left the Assembly at noon, &amp; went to the bookseller, where I obtained a copy of the report on Religious Education. I went to the Club, lunched, &amp; read the Report. Then I drove to Harold Speed's Studio, and looked at my picture. Lord Darling &amp; Di arrived for the same purpose, and afterwards drove me back to the Club. There I prepared 'notes' for my speech, &amp; then walked back to Lambeth.</p>
         <p>The archbishop having gone to a dinner of Balliol men, I presided in his place at dinner. 'Fish' Cecil and his wife came to dine. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Creighton sate beside me, &amp; made herself very agreeable. I went off to bed directly prayers were over.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
