<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[458]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Green</hi> acknowledging his letter addressed to me nearly a fortnight ago.  In view of his great age, the letter is a remarkable production, so remarkable that I have inserted it in my Journal.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Green</hi> was ordained in 1860, when he must have been 30 years old.</p>
         <p>In that year Convocation condemned "<hi rend="underline">Essays and Review</hi>", and the English Church Union entered on its mischievous career.  We have travelled far since then, but not far enough to escape from the woeful circle of competing fanaticisms in which the Church life of England was then bound.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Green</hi> went as a deacon to Seaham Harbour where he worked for 3 years (1860&#8211;63): then for 5 years (1864&#8211;68) he was at Bishop Auckland, when he became Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript">t </hi>Mark's Millfield, Sunderland (1868&#8211;75). Then he left the diocese of Durham, and went to S<hi rend="superscript">t </hi>Paul's, Beckenham for 17 years (1875&#8211;1902)</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[459]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">November 6</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1929</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">My Lord Bishop,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The impulse under which I feel compelled to write this letter, though more than half blind through age, is quite irresistible, and such as perhaps not a single other clergyman would share.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was born in Durham as long ago as 99 years, the son of highly intelligent parents, who were both by strong conviction Congregationalists, holding that such a connection as Church and State was one of Spiritual adultery.  Under this influence I was brought up, and became for a short time a Congregational Minister.  When my views underwent such a decided change as brought me to Bishop Auckland seeking Ordination, it was with the open avowal that I still adhered theoretically to the position of what was called a "Free Churchman". On that understanding I was </hi><hi rend="bold">[459] </hi><hi rend="italic">accepted by Bishop Longley by whom I was commended to Wilkinson for a title.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Further particulars are needless. Enough has been said to explain the very remarkable effect your Lordship's words last week have had upon me.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">What a change I have lived to see! And how keenly the memories I have of Church Work under such varied circumstances as I have known, together with my personal associations with Bishop Auckland as my home for years should keep me in constant sympathy and prayer for you.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">With deepest respect,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Yours,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Charles Green</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Pray pardon all defect.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[461]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to Jack Clayton, Angel Thelwall, Leslie Wilson, Cross, and Duncan.</p>
         <p>That quaint creature – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Milner</hi> – sends me a lengthy remonstrance against my omission of the word 'priest' in my address at the Institution last night.  It is something that he should have brought himself to the point of being able to express himself without actual rudeness.  I don't dislike him, though his eccentricity is sometimes almost too extravagant.  I sent him a brief and civil letter.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Sunderland for the first of the Ruri&#8211;deaconal meetings of Parochial Church Councillors.  I should suppose that something between 300 and 400 attended.  We met in the Bishopwearmouth Parish Hall, under the chairmanship of the Rural Dean.  I spoke for nearly an hour, &amp; then questions were invited.  There was some hesitation to begin with, but soon the questions came in fair number.  We separated in good humour with one another.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi> thought the meeting was a great success.  At least it was not an obvious failure.</p>
         <p>
            </body></text></TEI>
