<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[475]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I received from the Eccl. Com. A copy of the letter which they have addressed to Car&amp;#x00F6;e. It states that the Commissioners will defray the cost of the "extraordinary repairs" to the castle (pounsign<hi rend="doubleunderline">2290: 7: 10</hi>), and also an additional expenditure of 1. &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">1081: 3: 9.</hi> on repairs and 2. &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">78:7 ;6 </hi>in making good dilapidations at the Lodge and three Cottages. Total &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">3349: 19: 1</hi>  This great expenditure leaves for further consideration the whole question of re&#8211;building the stables etc. which, if it ever mature, will be very costly.</p>
         <p>I had a meeting with the Archdeacon in Durham Castle, when we discussed much diocesan business, including the appointment to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's, West Hartlepool, and Bellasis.  We lunched in my rooms. After lunch Pattinson and I motored to Darlington, where I consecrated an addition to the Cemetery.  The rain mercifully held off until the little service was over.  I took occasion to exhort the mayor to prohibit the introduction into the cemetery of glass&#8211;globes &amp; earthenware headstones.   His Worship seemed somewhat disconcerted by my zeal!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[476] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Stella, and there I instituted the new Rector (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Bartlett</hi>) in succession to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simpkinson</hi>, who has been transferred to Kirk Merrington.  There was a large attendance of the parishioners, and a good muster of the clergy.  I noticed the size &amp; competence of the choir.  In spite of his querulous observations when he left the parish, I think that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Simpkinson</hi> was both liked and respected.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi> came back to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street with us.  He tells me that his foolish neighbour, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Merrywether</hi>, has re&#8211;kindled the Protestant bonfire <hi rend="italic">by announcing a "Requiem Mass"!  I fear that M. is an incurable donkey.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jackson</hi><hi rend="italic"> says that his wife differs with him both on the question of Disestablishment and on that of Church Schools.  She is a 'last ditcher' on both questions.  I could not avoid a fellow&#8211;feeling: for </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi rend="italic"> might certainly be described as an intractable 'last ditcher' on the one question – Disestablishment.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We got back about 9.30. p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
