<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[432]    </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday </hi><hi rend="b strikethrough">Saturday</hi><hi rend="bold"> November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>I have lived sixty–six years in this strange world, and, in the fresh consciousness of the fact, I feel baffled and incipiently senile!  My "Birthday Letters" indicates sufficiently the incurable childishness of my character. </p>
         <p>They are from the following: –</p>
         <table>
<row><cell>
<hi>Angel Thelwall</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Kenneth Hodgson</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Kitty Wilson</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Leslie Wilson</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Betty Wilson</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Brooke Westcott</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Mary Radford</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Fosca Westcott</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Olive Pollok–McCall</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
<hi>Nancy Wynne–Willson</hi>
</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Andrew Hall</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Alfred Spelling</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>William Badham</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Noel Lamidey</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>George Nimmins</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Linetta Richardson</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
<row><cell>
<hi>Jack Clayton</hi>
</cell>
<cell>
</row>
         </table>
         <p>I went in to Durham, &amp; "ordained" a deaconess in the Cathedral, returning home to lunch.  Pattison brought his fianc&amp;#x00E9;e to that meal – a little pleasant girl who plays the piano.  </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[433] </hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked round the Park with "Beck", who grows more matronlike daily.  They over–feed her both at the Lodge &amp; in the Kitchen.  The afternoon sun illumined the leaves which yet linger on the trees, and creates a scene of sombre brilliance.  On returning to the Castle, I addressed and despatched copies of the <hi rend="underline">'Bishoprick'</hi> to such lay – members of the Assembly as I could identify.  Then I acknowledged as many as possible of my Birthday Letters.  </p>
         <p>Mary Radford says that Kenneth had called on her, but that unfortunately she was out at the time. This information so far as it goes is reassuring, but the strange youth remain a very dark horse, and what is to become of him is hard to see. He, at least, came into the burden of my responsibilities through no partiality of my own. His mother's appeal led me to be interested in him before I had so much as seen him: and before deciding to help in sending him to Oxford. I consulted Ella, who will be the poorer for my expenditure.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
