<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[409]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The Archbishop expressed surprise and regret at the article in the Times.</hi><hi rend="italic">  He thought that the issue of the Agenda for the November Assembly could not be long delayed, and that the statement from Cantuar: which it w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> contain, w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> correct the statements of the Article.  He said that he had seen the said statement, &amp; that it was satisfactory.  I suggested that the Article could hardly have been written without the assistance of some bishop of influence: &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he said that, while the late Abp. of C. would not have directly inspired it, it did represent his mind, &amp; may well have reflected his conversation.</hi><hi rend="italic">  I remember that, when I saw his Grace in the Athenaeum on Thursday, I was disagreeably impressed by his evident desire to get the Commission hustled out of the way.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He may well have talked in the same strain to somebody (e.g. Pearce or Buckle) connected with the Times, and thus, without intending or knowing it, have been the source of an article which is both a grossly inaccurate statement of fact, and a very unfair representation of issues.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[410]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I celebrated the Holy Communion in S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Anne's Church at 8 a.m.  Both my guests, the Archbishop and Peter, attended and received the Sacrament.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Before leaving the Castle </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I drafted a short response to the Times Article with the object of introducing it into my address this afternoon on the off&#8211;chance of getting it into the Monday newspapers. I showed what I had written to the Archbishop. He warmly approved of it, and thought it desirable that it should be said.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The Bishop of Jarrow thinks that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the origin of the Times Article is probably to be traced to an interview of Lang &amp; Dawson. If this be so, Lang is playing a very unworthy part. Unhappily I cannot think it incredible.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The service in the Cathedral was most impressive. A great congregation of students, &amp; dons together with the Mayor &amp; Corporation, &amp; a numerous representation of the general public listened to a very fine sermon &amp; finely delivered. The Abp. has an admirable voice, a good presence, a deliberate manner, &amp; a clear enunciation. And, above all, he has excellent matter.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[411]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Leaving his Grace to lunch with the Dean, &amp; to make his way home from Durham, we returned to Auckland for lunch.</hi><hi rend="italic">  Peter accompanied me to Silksworth, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">where I addressed a gathering of about 100 men.</hi><hi rend="italic">  The Vicar, (Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> W. Atkinson) is rather a feeble type, who is passing through the familiar transition out of Evangelicalism into Anglo&#8211;Catholicism.  He was evidently proud of his Men's meeting, but as his parish contains more than 7500 people, of whom probably 2000 are males above the age of 16, it did not seem to me to justify much boasting.   But I cannot imagine men, especially young men, being either attracted or impressed by that kind of parson.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I returned Peter to his lodgings in Ferryhill, &amp; then went on to Auckland, stopping on my way through Durham to give my MS. to Rushworth, the Reporter, in order that some report might, if possible, get into the Monday newspapers.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">Before parting from Temple, I said to him, "I think we have reached a complete mutual understanding, &amp; can depend on one another", and he cordially agreed. There are difficult days ahead, &amp; misunderstandings in our own camp are disastrous.</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
