<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[396]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This is the anniversary of my marriage in Westminster Abbey 27 years ago.  I sent <hi rend="strikethrough">card</hi> Ella a message of affection in some doggerel lines, "A crab to a crab after 27 years".  In these days that is a respectable duration for life&#8211;long vows!</p>
         <p>Last night I wrote to William, whose marriage, if nothing untoward happen, is to take place early in November.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's at 8 a.m.  Among the small company of communicants were Alexander, John, and Harry Leng.  The epistle from Ephesians vi was indeed relevant to my case.   In senses other than those which the phrase could have carried to the Apostle, &amp; yet not wholly remote, I may say of myself that I am "an ambassador in bonds".  And 'that I may speak boldly as I ought to speak' is, perhaps, the prayer that most insistently is required by my present state.  The weather was dull and depressing, not helpful to the spirit of a puzzled bishop!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[397]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>From one Crab to Another after 27 years.</p>
         <p>Oct: 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1902 – Oct 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1929</p>
         <p>Before the Altar in Saint Peter's fane<lb/>We stood together, and our vows exchanged.<lb/>Far from that holy scene our way we've ta'en,<lb/>North, West, &amp; North again our steps have ranged.<lb/>Twenty and seven the number of the years.<lb/>And numbers numberless our court of cares,<lb/>In cloud of sorry and in light of joy<lb/>Still held the Bond, nor could the years destroy.<lb/>God's Blessing sealed it in Saint Peter's shrine, <lb/>When He gave Thee to me, &amp; made me Thine</p>
         <p>					H. D.</p>
         <p>I revised my sermon, and then drafted a letter to the Parochial Church Councillors, which the Rural Deans can issue with their own invitations to the meeting, which I propose to address before Christmas.  </p>
         <p>Ella accompanied Pattinson and me to Sunderland, where I preached in S. Thomas' Church to a large congregation on the centenary of the consecration.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
