<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[429]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I paid the contractor a further sum of &#x00A3;250 on account of the Dilapidations on the Castle. This makes &#x00A3;500 on his contract, and &#x00A3;144 for the extra work, =&#x00A3;544. The Dean of Westminster acknowledges on a postcard the copy of the 'Bishoprick', which I sent him. He "appreciates it very highly".</p>
         <p>The two Archdeacons arrived at 11 a.m. and sate in conference with me until 1 p.m. when we all lunched. After this, they took their departure. This is an experiment in administering the diocese viz. a monthly conference of the Bishop &amp; Archdeacons.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Southwark sends me his charge. He adds the following:</p>
         <p>'I admire the perseverance with which you are bearing your witness. I doubt if you will convert the Church to the necessity of Disestablishment, but I believe you will arouse many to a sense of the intolerable nature of the situation we have been placed in by Parliament.'</p>
         <p>This perhaps is worth something.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[430]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Pattison and I motored to Winlaton, where I instituted the Rev<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. Walter Brain to the Rectory. As Cecil could not attend I myself administered the Declaration of Assent, and the Oaths. In my address I made illusion to the unsatisfactory state of the parish, which had come about through the inability of the late Vicar, an octogenarian, to carry so heavy a burden. The Rector had forgotten the key, so we had to stand in the open, while a maid was found who had the key to the back&#8211;entrance! I gave Jackson, who, as Rural Dean, had carried out the induction of the Rector, a lift back to Chester&#8211;Le&#8211;Street. We got back to the Castle at 9.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>I quoted in my address a description of the people of Winlaton in the early XIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century: &#8211;</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"They are hospitable &amp; kind to strangers: &amp; while the morality of the bulk is not below that of their neighbours, the villagers generally have a singularly unhappy reputation for being great adepts at boxing, gaming, &amp; general mischief&#8211;making; while as poachers, the neighbouring squirrely (?) declare them to be unequalled in the kingdom".</hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
