<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[384]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A beautiful morning. I breakfasted with mine host &amp; hostess, &amp; then revised my notes for the "lecture". I had not contemplated anything more than an informal talk to a theological society with no reporters present, but notice of the performance was given in S. Mary's yesterday and the 'Church Papers' have suggested that I contemplated a "pronouncement"! Of course the time of day will be unfavourable to aggregation, and the subject does not seem to interest the general body of Churchmen. So it may be the whole business will be a fiasco, but when reporters are present anything is possible, &amp; one dares not be wholly unprepared. The report of my sermon in 'the Nottingham Guardian' is very brief, but I was impressed by the large amount of space given in that paper to reports of sermons. How ought this fact to be interpreted? How many purchasers of the paper read these reports of sermons? Yet the editiors &amp; proprietors must suppose that publishing them pleases the public.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[385]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"The British in India have always been inclined to over&#8211;estimate Hindu susceptibility in the matter of caste. They have not realized that most of the great Hindu reformers, and they have been many in number since the Buddha's time, have openly &amp; with impunity disclaimed against the dangers &amp; perversions of that institution ……</p>
         <p>What the Hindu failed to understand and watched with ever&#8211;growing suspicion was a Government which oscillated between covert acceptance, or even carefully veiled approval of evangelists, who were spreading what was presumably their own religion, &amp; nervous disapproval of them &amp; all their work. And when in later years this same intriguing Government opened &amp; supported schools which, without open profession of religion, undermined the very foundations of caste, it is small wonder that they attributed such mysterious rulers the most sinister designs on their institutions."</p>
         <p>Mayhew. Christianity and Government of India. P.86, 87.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[386]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The "lecture" was delivered to an audience consisting of both sexes, which nearly filled a kind of theatre in the building recently vacated by University College. There were a good many clergymen present. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Field, lately Vicar of S. Mary's, presided. I spoke for about 45 minutes; there was a vote of thanks, &amp; then the company dispersed. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Darwin spoke to me afterwards.  I gave my notes to a Reporter, who promised to return them.  I returned to the Vicarage &amp; lunched, after which I went to the station &amp; took a train for Darlington where Long &amp; Alexander met me with the car.</p>
         <p>In the train I finished reading through Mayhew's book. It is extremely interesting and re&#8211;assuring to those who, like myself, cannot help feeling rather sceptical as to the future of Christianity in India. He accepts 'Mother India' without reserve as a faithful portrait of Indian society. His observations on Gandhi are important and illuminating. There is evidently nothing effective in the way of social regeneration to be looked for from him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
