<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[469]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to the Abp. of Dublin asking for information about the Irish Church Missions. The literature of the Society gives me the impression that it is one of those hateful blendings of philanthropy and proselytizing, which have done so much harm to Ireland in the past.</p>
         <p>In spite of my disapproval of that position for it, the pictury of Amy Schaeffer, 'Christ the Consoler', was (as the Newcastle paper informs me) dedicated yesterday as an Altar&#8211;piece in the School Chapel of Barnard Castle School.  The service was performed by an "old boy", the Vicar of Huddersfield, with no reference to me.  Headmasters are, I know, 'a law unto themselves', and, therefore, I think it judicious to ignore what is, none the less, &amp; insolent proceeding.  <hi rend="bold underline">An English Bishop has plenty of training in the elegant gymnastic feat known colloquially as "taking it lying down</hi><hi rend="bold">"</hi>.</p>
         <p>Rufus made his appearance, looking smart enough in his gunner's uniform, but, I thought, rather pallid. He has been moved to Aldershot, &amp; has hardly settled in there.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[470]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In wind and rain I walked for an hour in the Park with old D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullagh, to whom on returning to the Castle, I lent "Henry VIII". He is an omnivorous reader.</p>
         <p>Pattinson and I motored to Sunderland, where I attend a reception of S.P.G. supporters in the "Edward Hall", preliminary to a meeting in the larger 'Victoria Hall'. For an hour I did my best to be pleasant, but with indifferent success! Then I presided at the meeting which was well&#8211;attended. The two speakers were Bishop Frodsham and a layman called Barker, who was deaf &amp; brandished a terrorizing ear&#8211;trumpet. Both speeches were disappointing, for quite obviously neither had been prepared. My own observations from the chair were very brief, but at least they were connected, &amp; had been thought over.</p>
         <p>The local clergy were present in good number. Evidently Dawson and Jackson who were primarily responsible for organizing the meeting had exerted themselves. But the chosen speakers were quite lamentable, &amp; 'the hungry sheep looked up, and were not fed'!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
