<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[473]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The post brought me a very brief letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi>, from which I learned that <hi rend="underline">Graves's Autobiography</hi> was his birthday present to me.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">This perhaps, indicates the literature which now affects him. It is really bad stuff.</hi><hi rend="italic">  I wrote to him at once, &amp; at great length, speaking very frankly about his conduct and prospects.  If he takes this also on bad part, I shall have to conclude that he is a waster.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After lunch <hi rend="underline">Ella</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi>, and I motored to Durham, and attended Evensong in the Cathedral.  The service was "special" for the <hi rend="underline">Preventive and Rescue Association</hi>. After a sermon from the Dean, (which, perhaps, was rather too sentimental.) I received the "<hi rend="underline">Women's Offering</hi>", which reached the respectable total of &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">557</hi>.  Then we returned to Auckland.   </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkett</hi>, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Barnard</hi> came from Barnard Castle to discuss the report of the Commission on the Finances of the School.  After agreeing on this, we had tea.</p>
         <p>A telegram from the "<hi rend="underline">Daily Mail</hi>" asked me for an Article on '<hi rend="underline">Modernism</hi>', which I immediately refused.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[474]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Noel Lamidey</hi>, and sent him a copy of the "Bishoprick".</p>
         <p>The parish is engaged in its annual orgy, and everything is deranged in consequence.  The cook distributes "sittings" of tea: &amp; the butler sells all manner of worthless things at usurious rates.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> attend a meeting.  All the time I languish for my dinner!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rufus</hi><hi rend="italic">", the under&#8211;gardener, who went off to join the Army without any word either intention or farewell, has reappeared, looking quite smart in his artillery&#8211;man's uniform.  He says that there is a good chaplain, and that he gets the Holy Communion.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ella</hi><hi rend="italic">, who has a fondness for the military, came upon him in the Butler's pantry, and was pleased with his appearance.  The good feeding and regular exercise do work wonders with these adolescents, who, as things stand now in the County of Durham, do commonly lack both adequate food and adequate exercise.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Birney</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Wilton Park confirms my impression that </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the unemployed adolescents are suffering from insufficient food.  He says that 95 per cent of his parishioners are out of work.  </hi>
         </p>
         </body></text></TEI>
