<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[442]                                                              </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]   </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929. </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">LAMBETH</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Lang disclaimed with emphasis the suggestion that he designed the dropping of the Commission, and expressed his assured conviction that there was no likelihood of Temple's motion being "turned down" by the Assembly in the February session. But he has taken no steps towards ensuring that the right men sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> consent to join the Commission, though he said that he thought the members ought to be impartial men, who c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> "act as a jury": and that persons who had views "like yourself" could submit their opinions.  The whole business is rather farcical, for there is no dubiety whatever about the essential issues, &amp; hardly any as to the only possible solution of the practical problem.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> admitted that the appointment of the bishops, the re&#8211;casting of the ecclesiastical courts, and other matters could not be excluded for the Commission's view: but these are the essentials of the Establishment.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[443]                                                         </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>I received the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. The Archbishop celebrated without assistance for both his chaplains had overslept and failed to appear! After breakfast I walked to the Club and wrote letters. Then I walked in to the City, and ordered stationery etc. from Partridge &amp; Cooper Ltd., 1 &amp; 2 Chancery Lane, E.C.4. I paid the amount (&#x00A3;2:18:6) and ordered the stuff to be sent on. Also, I ordered a dozen shirts from Whippell &amp; Co., &amp; bought myself a pair of warm gloves. On my way back to the Athenaeum, I went in to the National Gallery to see the Titian, of which a copy is at the Castle. There I came upon L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Crawford&#8211;Balcanes with a lady, whom he introduced to me as the Princess Patricia.  I lunched in the Club, &amp; then betook myself to the Assembly, where I spent a dreary afternoon, the business being of the most boring character conceivable.  I spent some time at the Club, &amp; then walked to Lambeth for dinner.     </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[444]                                                           </hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>Athelstan Riley was in the Club, &amp; eager to talk. He had read the 'Bishoprick', and, of course, did not find it wholly to his taste. He grows so deaf that conversation with him becomes very difficult<hi rend="italic">.  </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Lord Ernle</hi><hi rend="italic"> was also there, &amp; we exchanged words.  "Last time we met, you were tub&#8211;thumping in the House of Lords", he said.  "Yes, I rejoined, and now I am in the gutter".  "You are, indeed", he said, "but never fear: you will come out of it all right".  The Bishop of Oxford was rather anxious to persuade me that the complete statement of his speech w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">show that he was not so sharply parted from me on the question of 'Disestablishment' as the brief report in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> suggested.  He said that he w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">send the entire speech.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There came to dinner Viscountess Bridgeman, Sir Lewis Dibdin, &amp; some others. I had some talk with Lady B. &amp; found her very pleasant, also with old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Creighton who was astonishingly amiable.  Lang is certainly a very good host, &amp; the Palace is more comfortably ordered than heretofore.  He "enjoys the papacy".</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
