<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[360]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Vincent Baddeley went away after lunch. He is evidently rather perturbed at the prospect of a Socialist's governments treatment of the Services.</p>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and called on Canon Cosgrave, who was reported to have fainted at the League of Nations meeting yesterday. Then I went on to West Hartlepool &amp; made a vain attempt to see Canon Knowlden. His sister reported him to be growing weaker. I suppose there is nothing to be done save to wait developments. I called on Canon Poole, who is acting as Rural Dean in Knowlden's stead. My approach to the Castle as I returned was glorified by a rainbow.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Gore, Turner, Brightman &amp; Spears with other like&#8211;minded Anglo&#8211;Catholicks have put out a manifesto against the South Indian Reunion scheme. "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">They c</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic underline">not remain in communion with any Church that formally sanctioned" some of its provisions</hi><hi rend="italic">. Thus violence again replaces discussion.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[361]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"There are combinations in the picture of Jesus which, as a picture, at any rate, seem to me unique, and which I am inclined to think are not merely picture, but portrait. I mean such combinations as his humility and his sense of authority: his sternness &amp; his gentleness: his great pity and his great purity: his tinge of asceticism &amp; his lack of asceticism: his constant living with God and his compassionate forthcomingness towards many sinners: his hatred of sin &amp; his active friendliness &amp; sympathy for the outcast and the "lost" …….. I do deduce from them that Jesus was original – original in his character as also in his way of life: a new phenomenon among the Jews, which has scarcely been repeated."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">(C.G. Montefiore</hi>. '<hi rend="underline">The Originality of Jesus'</hi> in Hibbert Journal, October 1929.  This is a notable article far more Christian than the utterances at Girton)</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
