<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[437</hi>]                                                            </p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I attended Morning Prayer in the Chapel, and then was shown the Pepysian Library by Clerk. I had no idea of its wealth of interest. Pepys's books – about 3000 in number – are preserved in his own book&#8211;cases and in the order which obtained at the time of his death. They are placed according to size, &amp; carefully numbered &amp; catalogued. The variety of his interests is amazing. After lunch I accompanied the Vice&#8211;Chancellor to Great S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Mary's, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi> preached from the words "<hi rend="underline">Get thee behind Me, Satan</hi>". He allowed himself to say many extravagant things e.g. that Churches are 'necessary evils'; that Christ was not the founder of the Church &amp; so forth. There were sufficient undergraduates on the floor of the Church to fill the back of the centre, but the attendance of Heads &amp; Dons was very small, and the galleries were completely empty.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[438]                                                      </hi> 
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>After the sermon I walked back to college with the Vice Chancellor, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">then went to S. John's, where I had tea with Xan, &amp; two of his friends. Before the latter arrived I had some talk with Xan about his difficulties. He said that he was seriously thinking about Ordination, &amp;, indeed, expressed himself far more religiously than I had allowed myself to expect.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The Chapel was filled with surpliced men at Evensong, when I preached on the War. My congregation was very attentive, and the Master assured me that I had "got hold" of it. He thanked me warmly for my sermon, so I suppose that it went off all right. We had much pleasant conversation in the Combination Room, and afterwards in the Master's Study. So ended what has been on the whole an agreeable Sunday.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Magdalene College</hi> is certainly a very fascinating place, curiously complete in itself.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
