<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[387]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="doubleunderline">Father" Vernon</hi>'s Apologia came from the publishers "<hi rend="underline">One Lord One Faith an Explanation by Vernon Johnson</hi>" It is well written, gives an impression of intellectual weakness &amp; limited knowledge, and suggests that his 'conversion' had little enough to do with any reasons for it which he offers, or, indeed, with any reasons at all.  It was an affair of temperament.  That the position which, as an 'Anglo–Catholic' missioner he took up, &amp; the necessity of dealing with the doubts &amp; difficulties of his multiplying problems, which that position involved, did have profoundly disturbing effect on his mind, <hi rend="strikethrough">&amp;</hi> by bringing home to him the irrational &amp; unsatisfactory character of Anglo–Catholicism, appear to be evident enough.  But the sudden &amp; decisive effect of his visit to Lisieux, and the influence of the Life of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Theresa – a brand new Popish saint of the modern neurotic–erotic variety – argue that his understanding is not strong, and that his emotions and facile &amp; vehement. He will disturb a multitude of 'Anglo–Catholics'.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[388]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>All the papers seem to have extracts from my speech on 'Disestablishment' but none has the same. There has been in every case a selection. On the whole I think the gist of what was said is fairly conveyed.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi> arrived at lunch time.  His unfortunate attack of bronchitis, which sent him abroad for a month, has been a principal course of the delay in the work on the Chapel.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullough</hi>. The autumnal colouring, seen in a mild sunshine with a faint haze in the air, was most beautiful.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Caröe</hi> exhibited rusted rods and decayed stone from the Chapel, and announced a truly formidable programme of repairs.  All the pinnacles must be rebuilt, all the mullions of the clerestory windows renewed, &amp; much done to Cosin's roof – the total expenditure will run into thousands of pounds.  The Ecclesiastical Commissions may begin to regret their decision to 'take over' the Chapel!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[389]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"The survival of ancient literature did not depend on its worth and beauty. Posidonius, whose influence great writers like Cicero, Virgil, Seneca, Plato, and on the leading religious systems was so permeating, is representing only in quotation."</p>
         <p>v. Angus "the Religious Quests of the Graeco–Roman World, a study in the Historical background of early Christianity" p. 11</p>
         <p>This is a very disconcerting fact, &amp; breeds in the mind a thousand perplexities. We commonly assume that the dominating factor in survival is quality. And this assumption acquires a solemn importance in the use of the documents which constitute the New Testament, &amp; which contain all we know of the Life, &amp; Teaching of Christ. May we authenticate /it by a reasonable Act of Faith in the action of the Spirit of Truth? 'Criticism, acute, ever–changing, never really harmonious, is a poor foundation for any positive statement.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
