<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[414]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday</hi>, <hi rend="bold">October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Arthur Raine and two brothers named Graham from Ferryhill came to see me about the unhappy dispute with that ridiculous old fanatick, Lomax.    They made the best impression on me, &amp; were evidently in real religious distress.  I could not blame them for joining the 'Wesleyan Male Voice Choir', nor for refusing to leave it: but I condemned their secession to Merrington, and told them that they ought to return to their own church.  We said prayers together, and so parted.  I gave them each a copy of the sermon "Continuity".  The elder of the Graham brothers asked if he ought to throw up his work because it involved Sunday labour.  Lomax insists on his doing so.  I replied, with Elisha, that he might bow himself in the House of Rimmon!  Really, Lomax's rigorism is too absurd.  It is extremely distressing that he should throw into opposition against himself the consciences of these sincere &amp; simple Christians.  The pity of it is that he is himself something of a saint.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[415]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">Xan Wynne–Willson wrote to me at length from Cambridge explaining why he could not offer himself for Ordination. He cannot see his way to accept the credenda. I suspect the influence of his Modernist tutor, M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Boys Smith.  I replied to his letter also at length.</hi>  There is an ominous suggestiveness about the religious development of the young men who pass from Christian homes to the Universities.  Kenneth at Oxford, &amp; Xan at Cambridge – both run the same course.  They cease to profess &amp; call themselves Christians!  It is, I suspect, rather the contemptuous atmosphere &amp; the habitual disregard of Christian obligation than any reasoned rejection that determines this result.  The transition is too sudden from Christian homes to a novel, brilliant moving world in which Christianity has no place, &amp; is only referred to with a smile or a sneer.  The discussion of moral &amp; religious questions is marked by the ruthlessness of youth, the arrogance of ignorance, and the hostility of scepticism.  Against comrades and superiors what chance has the lad?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
