<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[355]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>No ticket for the Edinburgh Function having arrived, I definitely laid aside my intention of attending it. Probably the omission is explicable as the result of some confusion in the arrangements, yet it is difficult to understand how it could have happened if any real desire for my presence had been felt by these Presbyterians, or any importance attached to it. Yet it is odd that I, of all Anglicans, should be absent, for I am probably the only English Bishop who feels himself free in conscience to receive the Holy Communion in a Presbyterian Church, &amp; who has received it in the Church of Scotland. But there is an evident desire in Scotland, not unconnected with politics, to emphasize the Reunion of the Scottish Churches as a triumph of "Establishment", and my recent declaration in favour of 'Disestablishment' as, in England, morally requisite, is apt to be highly resented by the Scots. Nevertheless, I think, if only for historical reasons, they ought to have shown more consideration for the Bishop of Durham.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[356]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> writes to me from Ireland enclosing a letter which he has received from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop</hi> asking him to arrange a Retreat for the Deacons who are to be ordained at Advent to the Priesthood, &amp; stating that such a retreat was usual in the days of Bishop Westcott and Canon Body.  He also said that he would arrange a retreat at Mirfield if this retreat in Durham could not be managed!!!  "<hi rend="underline">The hungry sheep look up and are not fed</hi>."  I am, although I shall ordain them, &amp; they will swear canonical obedience to me, completely outside the religious orbit of these young Anglo&#8211;Catholicks.  They belong to an <hi rend="underline">ecclesiola in ecclesia</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick, &amp; they will own him as entitled to their regard, but their own Bishop, no!  I told <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rawlinson</hi> that if there must be a retreat, I had rather it should be held in the diocese than at Mirfield: &amp; that, if he himself would conduct it, I should be grateful.  Thus I make a virtue of necessity.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[357]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Macmillans</hi> sent me the statement showing the sales of '<hi rend="underline">Disestablishment</hi>'. I was surprised to see how very small they are. Even allowing for the fact that first, the General Election, and then the Holidays were unfavourable conditions for the sale of books, the number sold is suggestively meagre. Here is the statement:&#8211;</p>
         <p>73 presented<lb/>273 sold to the Public<lb/>489 sold to the Author<lb/>18 sold to America<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">1166</hi> on hand on 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> June, 1929<lb/>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">2019</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I don't quite understand why the account should <hi rend="bold underline">not be brought later than June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi>. I sent a cheque to Macmillan's for my debt – &#x00A3;64:6:0 – which represents the cost of sending the Charge to the Clergy of the Diocese.</p>
         <p>I think it is time that I accepted the decision of the British Public not to read any book from my pen. If reviews could secure a sale, or indicate quality, it were far otherwise: but balance sheets heed neither compliments nor author's vanity!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[358]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I took Baddeley &amp; Pattinson to Finchale Priory, where we inspected the ruins of the Priory.  These were seen to great advantage, for the fineness of the afternoon showed up the exceeding beauty of the curving river and steep wooded banks.  Then we went to Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, and visited the parish church.  A cadaverous looking verger recognized me, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">showed us the anchorite's cell, a building divided between a coal&#8211;hole and a rather dingy room. In the latter were his wife &amp; children</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi>  After this we returned to Auckland for tea.</p>
         <p>It occurred <hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>to me<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi> that I might get something out of Arthur H. Stockwell Ltd. by asking him to send me, instead of the money, as many copies of the volume "The Kingdom of God" as it will purchase.</p>
         <p>I received a brief telegram from Linetta – "Much love. Linetta Richardson" – so I conclude that she is 'happily married'. It is a strange union, &amp; can have little of the normal provision for connubial bliss: but then she is altogether abnormal.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[359]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"The visitation of the cathedral churches belongs unto the metropolitan of the province: and to the King, when the archbishoprick is vacant.:</p>
         <p>Phillimore. 165.</p>
         <p>That all deans and chapters are subject to the visitation of the bishop "jure ordinario", and of the archbishop of the province "jure metropolitico", is a well&#8211;established maxim of ecclesiastical law."</p>
         <p>Phillimore. 204.</p>
         <p>How are these statements to be reconciled? I wrote to Chancellor A. J. Lawrence to ask for the answer to that question.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi> came in to dine, thus forming a 'male quartett' [sic].  We had much pleasant talk during dinner, &amp; afterwards went to my study where our conversation took a literary turn, &amp; my books were in requisition.  The old man went home after dinner.  He is a very loveable old man, sweet&#8211;tempered &amp; with an old&#8211;world courtesy of manner which in these hustling days is becoming rare. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Baddeley</hi> shared my liking for him on the basis of a single evening's acquaintance.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
