<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[479]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A Canadian clergyman who will be in England about Christmas time writes to ask for permission to celebrate the Holy Communion privately.  <hi rend="bold underline">I refused his request pointing out to him the schismaiick suggestion, and referring him to the 71</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Canon</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> produced at lunch two queer products of the Feminist Movement, of whom one pernoctated here.  She was tall, cadaverous, bespectacled, and dramatick, drank hot water at breakfast, pot&#8211;wine at lunch, favoured plays in churches, and expounded histrionicks to school girls!  How greatly favoured were our ancestors, who shared the human&#8211;race into spear–side and spindle&#8211;side, and observed the boundary!</p>
         <p>The afternoon post brought me a bulky volume – '<hi rend="underline">Some Memories of a Soldier</hi>' by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hugh Lenox Scott  </hi><hi rend="underline">Major&#8211;General U.S. Army retired</hi>.  General <hi rend="doubleunderline">Scott</hi> was the Commandant at West Point, where we stayed with him in 1909.  I remember being greatly interested in his descriptions of Indian and Buffalo, on both of which he was a recognised authority.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[480]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and attended a meeting of the Preservation Committee.  We have collected something over &#x00A3; 40,000 and are spending it.  The report of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Faber</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jones</hi> on the progress of the work, was favourable.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Speed</hi> and his wife arrived.  The portrait was unpacked, &amp;, I think, has a good appearance.  I like it better than I did.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sam Storey</hi><hi rend="italic"> and his wife came to dinner.  I asked him whether his wife was getting to like Durham, &amp; his answer confirmed the rumour that had already reached my ears to the effect that she was already pining to go elsewhere.  It is the usual complaint, that there is no society and nothing to do.  But the result is that everybody of social position deserts the county, &amp; Durham is becoming a kind of provincial 'East End'.  Then men pretend to be astonished at the dominance of "Labour" in the county!  There is no longer any sense of duty to the district, no local loyalty or patriotism.  The employers and landowners are becoming unknown by face to their workmen &amp; tenants.  What can be the outcome of all this!</hi>
         </p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>

