<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[466]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">BARNARD CASTLE </hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wretchedly wet, depressing day with suspicions of thunder. I left the castle after breakfast, and motored to Barnard Castle School for the meeting of the special Committee appointed to investigate the financial position, &amp; to make proposals to the Governors. We met at 10 a.m. and sate until 3.20 p.m., with an interval for lunch. We were, I think, all present viz:&#8211; D<hi rend="superscript">r </hi>Eustace Hill, Barkett, Sir Walter Raine, Hodgson, and two others with myself.  In attendance were the Headmaster, Bursar, &amp; Clerk.  We began by going over the school buildings.  The Matron was fetched in, &amp; examined on the possibilities of economy in her department.  We rejected <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bircham's</hi> violent proposition to cut down on the Headmaster's salary by &#x00A3;200: but we recommended acceptance of the Bursar's offer to retire on his pension at Easter, and then to be re&#8211;appointed on the lower stipend of &#x00A3;200 per annum.  We made some other recommendations affecting a total economy of between &#x00A3;800 and &#x00A3;900 per annum.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[467]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi> writes to assure me of the "excellent impression" made by the meeting of Parochial Church Councillors last Tuesday.  "The lucidity of your explanation &amp; the fact that you did not desire to convert them to a Disestablishment policy on the spot has exploded a great deal of misunderstanding.  But above all the patience with which you dealt with the questions &amp; resolved difficulties charmed them.  All sorts of people have spoken to me about it, &amp; I think you ought to know that you have, so far as Wearmouth is concerned, accomplished your object, &amp; have won many friends."  This is satisfactory so far as it goes.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Peter Richardson</hi> came to dinner.  He is full of plans for his approaching marriage.</p>
         <p>Another very disconcerting letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Radford</hi> about <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kenneth</hi>. I begin to suspect that there must be a kink in the boy's brain. His behaviour on ordinary assumptions is inexplicable. It is certainly a melancholy outcome for an enterprize which in its origin was entirely benevolent. But now I am totally at a loss how to perceive my duty with respect to him.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
