<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[464]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Raven</hi> writes for 50 copies of the Letter in the Bishoprick.  He wants to put them into hands of the younger clergy in the Liverpool diocese, who come to him for instruction every week.  He adds:</p>
         <p>"May I add my gratitude for your speech on the Education report? It was full of compensation for the boredom of these previous days. It is well that we should occasionally be asked to face facts and helped to realize their meaning."</p>
         <p>This is pleasant enough, &amp; may be set against a rather ill&#8211;natured reference to my speech in the <hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>.</p>
         <p>Canon Osborne acknowledges my flatterous letter about his book. It evidently pleased him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Froggatt</hi> accepts the hon: canonry vacated by Knowlden's death.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Leslie Wilson</hi> came to see me.  He has left his situation, &amp; seeks employment at the Synthetic Works.  He desires to get out of "service" because he thinks, 'there is nothing in it.'  On the whole, I am disposed to agree with him.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[465]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to South Shields, where, in S. Michael's Hall, I addressed the Parochial Church Councillors of the Jarrow Rural Deanery, on the Relations of Church and State.  About 200 were present, &amp; the meeting was presided over by that fantastic goose, the Rural Dean, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hudson Barker</hi>. He posed &amp; grimaced like a prima donna! The Councillors listened with admirable attention, &amp; a gravity which, like the night of Egypt, '<hi rend="underline">might be felt</hi>'. They were, I conjecture, more puzzled than edified by my oration. A rousing Protestant denunciation of the Bishops would have been more to their taste! Such questions as were asked disclosed rather suspicion of the new Prayer Book than resentment at the action of the House of Commons in throwing it out! The churchmanship of these North&#8211;country folk is purely local: they, like most English people, are at heart congregationalists. This habit of mind has been strengthened in them by the dominance of various types of Nonconformity. They were, however, commendably polite, &amp; applauded decorously when I had ended my address! The night was damp &amp; boisterous.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
