<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[426]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The newspapers have fairly full reports of my Conference address; the Newcastle Journal again produces my photograph! The public must surely be growing weary of the sight of a not particularly attractive countenance!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">. R. C. Langdon–Davies</hi> came to lunch.  He aspires to be ordained next year, and is now at Mirfield.  I gave him five names of the clergy needing curates, to whom he might with reason apply for a title – Baily of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Ignatius, Sunderland; Stephenson of Gateshead, Garland of S. Mary's. Tynedock; Sleddick of South Westoe, &amp; Bell of S. Hilda's. Darlington. He impressed me favourably. He is more developed than most candidates from the older universities, being 26 years old, &amp; having taught in schools both in South Africa and in Sweden.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Noel Lamidey</hi> sent ne a booklet on '<hi rend="underline">Australian Aboriginal Art</hi>' issued by the National Museum of Victoria.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi> sends me a cargo of birthday good wishes by the Dutch air–post from Java.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[427]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Pattinson</hi> and I motored to Sunderland, where I dedicated an altar to the memory of <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Burdon Frazer</hi>, whom I ordained to the deaconate at Advent 1927, and who died in the summer of 1928.  He was a loveable and promising young man, whose early loss was widely lamented.  His parents were in the congregation, &amp; were introduced to me afterwards.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edgar Jackson</hi>, the Vicar of S. John's Sunderland, has held that position for 10 years. He is a good and devoted man, with a rough exterior and a raucous voice. He is a strong "Anglo–Catholick", but loyal to the Church and Bishop. He has certainly gained a remarkable influence over the squalid population to which he has the pastoral communion. The church was built in the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. century, &amp; has a fairly comfortable appearance.  His curate, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop</hi>, is one of the most promising of the younger men.  He is an Oxford man, &amp; makes a good second to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jackson</hi>. The poverty of the congregation was as apparent as their piety was noteworthy. We returned to Auckland after the service.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
