<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[471]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received from Bishop Hine a very interesting letter giving me an account of Robert Keeble, the author of 'Simon called Peter'. His final judgement is the following:</p>
         <p>"Dear Keeble was, I think, a mixture of sensuality and holiness – the two ever contending within him – the former held in check for years by his priestly calling, then getting the mastery, &amp; driving him into the opposite pole of disbelief."</p>
         <p>The story he tells is a very sad one. This strange interlacement of sexual passion &amp; religious devotion is both common &amp; baffling. It explains, perhaps, both the immense scandals and the almost incredible self sacrifice of Christian History: and it compels a certain suspicion of all conspicuous devotion while it prohibits any sweeping censure of the moral collapse of "saints". That disgusting book 'Elmer Gantry', illustrates this enigmatic blending of the sexual and the spiritual in the case of an evangelist of the popular protestant type. It is the key to the dramatic failures of prominent "Anglo Catholick" clergy, whose fame as 'confessors' and 'directors' has been considerable.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[472]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Katherine Vane</hi> and her daughter came to lunch.  I motored to Stockton, and "opened" the Missionary Exhibition.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Guy Wrightson</hi> presided.  There was a considerable gathering including most of the local clergy.   After the function, I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I motored to Houghton–le–Spring, and addressed the Parochial Church Councillors of that Rural Deanery in the Kepier Hall. The Rural Dean (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Watson</hi>) presided, &amp; there was a large attendance. On the whole I was pleased with this meeting. The attention was close &amp; sustained, though I spoke for fifty minutes. Then came a good many questions which I answered. The proceedings ended at 10.15 p.m., when I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>Somebody send me "<hi rend="underline">Goodbye to all That An Autobiography by Robert Graves.</hi>'  This appears to be a <hi rend="underline">very</hi> frank disclosure of the post–war mentality.  I conjecture that it has been sent in consequence of my reference to "Simon called Peter".  The author is also the author of an "intimate biography of his friend Aircraftsman Shaw (late Col. T.E. Lawrence)."</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
