<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[362]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1929.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A most beautiful morning but with an autumnal keenness in the air. Yesterday's gale has withered &amp; scattered the leaves from the trees.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>, as I expected, is replenishing her supply of "Protestant" fervour for the Establishment by the company she keeps at the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's Deanery.  She writes to me in the approved style of censure, ignoring as they all do, the salient &amp; determining factor in the situation, and assuming that nothing but an almost insanely eccentrick individualism can have induced me to say that I can no longer defend the Establishment.  <hi rend="underline">Did a man's wife ever help him at a pinch when his duty and his interest pulled in opposite directions</hi>? I doubt it. Women are more tenacious of their causes than men, &amp; less influenced by principle. In this case I really do not think that the dear lady has any real grasp of the issues involved, &amp; simply can't get away from the assumptions &amp; phrases of respectable "Society"!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[363]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"To reconcile the rigour and activity of this [Presbyterian] censorship of morals with its small apparent result is perhaps the most perplexing problem of the Scottish Reformation.  With all its great qualities, <hi rend="underline">Scotland has never stood high either in chastity or in sobriety among the nations of Europe</hi>: &amp; the ecclesiastical records bewail at all times the astounding iniquity of the people …….  Nor should we fail to note that a certain unnatural vice made its appearance in Scotland soon after the Reformation, <hi rend="underline">which is said to have been quite unknown there before</hi>.  In 1570 two men were burnt at Edinburgh for this offence: &amp; <hi rend="underline">the vice grew to alarming proportions in the noontide of Protestantism about the middle of the next century</hi>."</p>
         <p>v. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mathieson</hi>.  <hi rend="underline">Politics &amp; Religion in Scotland. 1550&#8211;1595</hi>
         </p>
         <p>vol. I. 188f</p>
         <p>Here is food for reflection.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
