<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I read <hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Wicksteed's</hi><persName xml:id="4444"></persName> <hi rend="italic">Hibbert Lectures. "The relation's between Dogma &amp; Philosophy illustrated from the Works of S. Thomas Aquinas',</hi> which I found very interesting &amp; suggestive. They are also extremely well&#8211;written. Then, after breakfast, Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> came and we went through correspondance: after which I began the sermon for the Railway Men. Brown of Monkwearmouth came to lunch, and afterwards talked of many dull things for more than an hour in my study. He says that Lomax<persName xml:id="5279"></persName> of Ferryhill, (whom he describes as a saint, though eccentric &amp; "wealthy") has a scheme for establishing a "Retreat" House for the clergy, to be under the control of the resident chaplain, who sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be licenced by the bishop. He suggested Bishop Hornby, erstwhile of the Universities Mission in Central Africa: <hi rend="italic">but I indicated some suspicion of having one of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">soi disant</hi> <hi rend="italic">"Catholicks" planted down in my diocese. </hi>Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I motored to Sedgefield, but failed to find the Arch&#8211;deacon at home. Loxley and Ellershaw accept the honorary canonries, though the first explains that his health is so decayed that he must probably soon retire from active work. I think, however, that the old man is pleased at the compliment which probably as coming from the bishop has a certain value in his eyes. For these "Catholicks", though accustomed to set at nought all episcopal directions do yet cherish a mighty&#8211;respect for the episcopal office!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>