<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The work of patronage is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">the</hi><hi rend="italic"> shadow on my life and work. Never does an opening occur without my having to feel the complicated problem of the needs of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">parish</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; the claims of the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">clergy</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; without a feeling, often very bitter, that every appointment means several disappointments to the men I respect as brethren."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Bishop Moule</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>I extract this from a letter written by my predecessor to some parson who had begged for preferment, and who sends the letter on for me to read by way of assisting his appeal. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop's patronage is his principal disciplinary instrument, as well as his chief means of influencing the religious life in his diocese. </hi>There is hardly any possibility of harmonizing the parson's claims with the needs of the parish, or the wishes of the people. All the items of the clergyman's case for promotion are more often than not counts in the parochial case against his appointment. Ill&#8211;health, seniority, the waxing claims of a growing family, an ailing wife &#8211; <hi rend="bold underline">all are synonymous for inefficiency. </hi>How can a bishop rightly appoint to a parish on other grounds than that of the spiritual interest of the parishioners? And when will this ground be found identical with the personal claims of individual clergymen? <hi rend="bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">Why has </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName><hi rend="italic"> been pursued with preferment since his Ordination? On no professional considerations could the cult of juniority, which his case illustrates, be justified.</hi><hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[89]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a number of letters conveying seasonable wishes to divers of my friends. The Rev<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> T.F.P. Rawlins, Vicar of Rainton, came to lunch. He has got into a foolish conflict with County Educational Authority because it allowed a dance in Lent to be held in the school buildings which it has taken over from the Anglican trustees. <hi rend="bold underline">I conceived an ill impression of him, as an obstinate &amp; tactless man, who has set his parish by the ears within a few months of his arrival as vicar</hi>. An ordination candidate from Darlington came to see me: aged 21 years, working at King's College, London, and hoping to get into S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's, Stockton, where the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> A.J. Bott is Vicar. After lunch I motored into Durham, but to little purpose as Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> was absent, &amp; the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> had gone out. On returning to the Castle, I found the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName> at tea, and soon we were joined by Lady Gainford and her daughter. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName> sent me an invitation to preach in the Abbey on May 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, but at that time I am knee&#8211;deep in Confirmations, &amp; I had to decline. The "Times" announced that that crack&#8211;brained female, the Countess Markievitch, has been sentenced to two years hard imprisonment with hard&#8211;labour. How long will it be before she is again turned loose on the country? Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Joseph Verdin</hi> of Weobley has died at a great age. It is a matter of some moment to the diocese of Hereford whether his nephew, the new owner of the property, will continue to contribute to the church.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>