<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">This is William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> Birthday, &amp; he attains the dignity of 20 years</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I gave him Wells' History of the World. The pictures will interest him if nothing else!</p>
         <p>I dictated letters to Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> before motoring to Durham in order to catch the train to Newcastle, where I presided over a meeting of the Governors of the N.E. County School. I got back to Auckland about 3.30 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Archdeacon Watkins<persName xml:id="590"></persName> sent me a copy of his letter to Bishop Moule protesting against D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Jowett's preaching in Durham Cathedral. It was a very oily document, virulently designed though lovingly expressed. I sent it back with civil acknowledgements!</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne went out to some Masonic entertainment to which Lady Thurlow had invited them. I seized the opportunity to clear off some private letters. I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, who has been rather neglected of late. The hustle in which I live seems to leave no time for writing anything but diocesan and public letters. <hi rend="italic">Also I wrote to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Cecil Fortescue</hi><persName xml:id="4760"></persName><hi rend="italic">, who had told me of the completion of the work of restoring the parish church of Leysters. That young man would, I think, be glad to come into this diocese, &amp; (though he is rather feather&#8211;headed, &amp; would probably develope into a "Catholick") he might be very useful if charged with a new district. It is absurd on the face of it that a man of his years &amp; temperament should be set down in a village of 130 people.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>