<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gray, the Vicar of Eldon, called to see me with respect to a man from his district who is desirous of being accepted for Ordination. He has been a working miner until a year ago when he entered S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's, Highbury <hi rend="bold underline">having been encouraged to do so by Bishop Moule. </hi>But he is more than 32 years old, married, the father of one child, and (save for his savings which will certainly not carry him through his 3 years course at the theological college) without private means. He has nothing better than an elementary school training to build on. This man presents a difficult problem.</p>
         <p>After lunch, I walked with Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> to Escombe, and there visited the most precious little Saxon church, built out of Roman stones from Birchester about the middle of the 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Century as is supposed. The parson, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi><persName xml:id="5274"></persName>, is an odd man, who was a working miner before his Ordination. I was pleased with his intelligent knowledge of his church, and with his conversation.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Proud, a local solicitor, came to see me on behalf of Ellis &amp; Co., the sitting tenants of the Castle Garden. I made a provisional suggestion that they should rent the whole garden for &#x00A3;65: supply the Castle with fruit &amp; vegetables at market rates: occupy the Lodge &amp; have charge of the Gate.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[24]</hi></p>
         <p>Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> writes to inquire what my intentions as to the motion on Divorce in the National Assembly may be. Lord Parmoor has a motion "earnestly protesting against the proposal to introduce additional grounds as a justification for divorce." Rashdall is a very courageous but a very tactless orator. He writes:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I am not sure what your views are on the subject. I know you do not disapprove of the remarriage of the innocent divorcee in case of adultery, but I am not sure what you think about additional grounds. I have slowly and reluctantly arrived at the conclusion that the majority report of the Commission is right. If you agree with me, will you speak? They will listen to a Bishop."</p>
         </div>
         <p>I told him in reply that I did not hold marriage to be indissoluble, and that I did not interpret our Lord's words in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Matthew as if they were words of a statute, but I had an unhappy feeling that behind the present clamour for a change of the Marriage Laws there was a great volume of hypocritical self&#8211;indulgence. However, I did not intend to give a silent vote, and I would do my best to secure him a hearing. It will be wholly unfortunate to be compelled to "antagonize" all the orthodox, both Catholick &amp; Protestant, over this miserable matter of divorce, but I could not honourably let the issue go by default, nor could I refuse support to Rashdall.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>