<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[69]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast, George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> took his departure. Then, when I had written some indispensable letters, I set to prepare a speech in advocacy of the appeal for the Durham Colleges, which the College&#8211;folk appear resolved to work into my proposal of the toast of the college tomorrow. I am not wholly pleased with this arrangement, <hi rend="bold underline">nor do I think it sound tactics that I should "spread myself" over two appeals for funds&#8211;that for the better payment of the clergy, &amp; that for the Durham colleges</hi>. Nor is it easy to see how I can escape coming into collision with the Newcastle branch of the University. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moscroft</hi>, the diocesan architect, came to lunch, &amp; to examine the matter of insurance. Also <hi rend="doubleunderline">Petrie</hi>, the vicar of S. Barnabas, Hendon. After lunch I went to the County School for girls, &amp; distributed the certificates. The inevitable speech having been made, I returned to the castle. That ever generous lady, <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Dillon</hi>, sends me two books as a Christmas present, viz: <hi rend="underline">Admiral Sims' "The Victory at Sea"</hi>; and <hi rend="underline">Wicksteed's<persName xml:id="4444"></persName> Hibbert Lectures on "The Relations between Dogma &amp; Philosophy, illustrated from the works of S. Thomas Aquinas</hi>". I read a good part of the first: it gives an interesting account of the submarine war, &amp; shows how very nearly the Germans succeeded <hi rend="italic">in forcing us to give in. Our people were richly fed on official lies all through the War. We are reaping the harvest now in an orgy of mutual distrust. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>