<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[65]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Time rushes forward with such remorseless rapidity that I shall be too late for this New Year's Letter which I have promised to issue..There are some specific topics which must be dealt with e.g.</p>
         <p>1. Clerical Poverty, and herein the High Sheriff's Appeal.</p>
         <p>2. The electoral rolls, &amp; their significance in the future.</p>
         <p>3. Ordination candidates. The place of education.</p>
         <p>4. The limits of a Bishop's power. (&#x3B1;)  his material i.e. the quality of his clergy. (&#x3B2;) law &amp; equity. (&#x3B3;) his income.</p>
         <p>5. The roots of clerical failure.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On the urgent subject of clerical poverty </hi><hi rend="italic">there are some things that must be said e.g. its bearing on the efficiency of the clergy, on their mobility, on their public influence. I must refer to the Appeal issued by the High Sheriff last year, &amp; press for contributions. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">But the subject is tiresome: the clergy are unpopular: the public mind is filled with other matters. I see no prospect of relief</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">It is indeed a woeful thing that I should have to set aside all the great matters of religion and morality, and fasten on this hateful business of clerical finance. The subject of "Reunion" might seem to demand notice, but I doubt whether there is anything to be said that could either assist the cause, or interest the public. That what I should say would almost certainly offend the clergy may go without saying.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>