<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent some time in the melancholy task of preparing materials for Lee to state my case to the Income Tax authorities. Then I put together some notes for my function this afternoon.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> to Stockton&#8211;on&#8211;Tees, and there received addresses from the Mayor and Corporation, the Clergy of the Rural Deanery, &amp; the Nonconformist minister. I made a speech in reply which seemed to be appreciated. After an early dinner with the Rural Dean (Douglas) I presided at a meeting convened to support the Missions to Seamen. <hi rend="italic bold underline">Two Chaplains spoke, &amp; bored me dreadfully with a variety of legends designed to illustrate their work. These narrations induce in my mind an almost total unbelief. They have been so often repeated, and never quite without alteration, until they have acquired platform&#8211;perfection. Iteration has created conviction in the minds of the orators themselves, &amp; they come to repeat them with a taking fervour! </hi>The weather was foggy, so that motoring was not easy. However, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> brought us home in safety by 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Birmingham writes to ask me to be one of the preachers at the Church Congress which is to meet in that city in October next year. Can I bring myself to do this?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>