<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The Ordination was very solemn and moving. Watson preached an excellent suitable sermon, and the music was very helpful. I was rather surprised, however, at the smallness of the congregation. We lunched at the Deanery and then motored to Seaham, where I dedicated a tablet to the memory of the late Marchioness of Londonderry<persName xml:id="2817"></persName>. After tea in Seaham Hall, we went to Wynyard in order to stay a night with the Londonderrys<persName xml:id="2818"><persName xml:id="2819"></persName></persName>. We attended Evensong in the Chapel, and then dressed for dinner. There was nobody but M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sanderson from Ireland, and the Londonderrys themselves with Lord Castlereagh<persName xml:id="4430"></persName>, who has grown a tall lad curiously like his grandfather. We had much interesting conversation on many subjects, and separated to go to our bedrooms in high good humour with one another.</p>
         <p>Before leaving Durham I had some talk with Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> about Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. He is, I think, attracted by the prospect of coming north to a great charge, but he rather shrinks from the obligations of large parochial work.</p>
         <p>Also, I consulted the Bp. of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> as to the disposition of the vacant honorary canonries. He approved my intention of bestowing one on old Loxley of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's, &amp; the other on Ellershaw.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>