<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[70]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp;, at 11 a.m. administered confirmation to 55 boys, of whom 4 were cathedral choirboys &amp; 51 were from Durham School. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, &amp; 3 canons were present. Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName> carried the staff, and forgot to give it into my hand for the benediction. I confirmed every boy separately, &amp; the boys were rather slow in coming up, so that the service took an hour &amp; a quarter, rather longer than I should have expected. After the confirmation, I licensed 3 clergymen of whom one (Guillanne) was the Professor of Hebrew, &amp; one the lecturer in Hellenistic Greek. Then I lunched in the Common Room at the Castle with 3 dons: &amp; after that I visited the Head Deaconess. These excellent women are full of goodness but they asphyxiate me! She expressed an ardent desire to have the Sacrament reserved in the chapel! Then I went back to the Castle, and wrote a number of letters. At 7 p.m. I dined in college. It was an odd gathering, rather like a gaudy at a Sunday School, for while the general plan was that of a gaudy, the spirit was that of a Sunday School. Nothing could well have been graver, more decorous, more demurely Pharasaic! My speech was rather hollow &amp; even grotesque as addressed to so petty an audience, &amp; in so incongruous a setting. But it had been sent in advance to the newspapers, and was really rather an unusual <hi rend="underline">affair</hi> altogether. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; the car were waiting for me: I changed, packed my bag, &amp; returned home, where I found that Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> had returned, &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had arrived. I went to bed at 11.15 p.m. very tired. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>