<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The year that ends tonight must take rank in my life as one of exceptional importance. It would be difficult to find a parallel to the personal triumph implied by my translation to Durham within 2 1/2 years of my appointment to Hereford. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi><persName xml:id="1173"></persName>, whose experience has been often compared with mine had been 16 years at Exeter before he was moved to London. But in reality there is no resemblance between the two cases. Except <hi rend="bold underline">that both were marked by explosions of fanaticism</hi>. For while in 1869 there was a genuine alarm among sincerely religious men to whom <hi rend="doubleunderline">"Essays &amp; Reviews"</hi> appeared as a treason to Christianity, in 1918 there was nothing more respectable than an artificial agitation worked up by a handful of fanatics, who thought they had an opportunity of securing a domestic victory. The hollowness of the attack on me was immediately apparent when I had entered into possession of my bishoprick, and when after 2 1/2 years I left it, there was a remarkable outburst of public regret. My welcome in the diocese of Durham was even more remarkable, &amp; far more difficult to understand. My enthronement on October 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> was the "high water mark" of my "career". When I stood in the great throne in Durham Cathedral, and blessed a vast congregation, which had assembled to do me honour, I could not but recall the obloquy and humiliation which had been heaped upon me less than threeyears before. The ardour <hi rend="bold">[92]</hi> [symbol], of the people was not limited to the City of Durham. Wherever I have been in the diocese, there have been similar demonstrations. It is, I think, true to say that my appointment has been remarkably popular. But the difficulties of my position are such that I cannot doubt that I shall disappoint the public expectations, &amp; become acutely unpopular before long.</p>
         <p>On January 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1920, I baptized <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Nicholas Church, and on March 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. I confirmed him in the church at Onibury. For these solemn &amp; decisive acts I prepared him myself. From this intimacy in very sacred matters there grew a relation between us far closer than that of master &amp; servant. When I left Hereford I gave him his choice, either to remain as chauffeur to my successor, or to accompany me to Aukland castle. He chose the latter, &amp; has so far carried himself excellently. Inasmuch as personal relations form so great a part of one's life &amp; probably wield a greater influence over one's character than anything else, I do not think it superfluous to note as one of the memorable things of this year the circumstance that he and I were thus closely brought together.</p>
         <p>On February 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> I officiated at the funeral of my dear friend <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas Raleigh</hi><persName xml:id="14"></persName>. In March the <hi rend="underline">memoir of Sir William Anson</hi><persName xml:id="228"></persName> which I edited &amp; mainly wrote made its appearance. Of sermons the most important were those preached to the Methodists at the Eastbrook Mission in Bradford on March 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi>, to the King at <hi rend="bold">[93] </hi>[symbol] Windsor on April 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, to the University of Cambridge on June 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, to a great congregation in the nave of Westminster Abbey on July 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, to the Benchers at the Temple on July 25th, to a congregation of Swedes in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Clara's Church, Stockholm on Sept: 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, to the University of Glasgow in the Bute Hall on October 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, at my enthronement in Durham Cathedral on October 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and the sermons in the diocese.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The visit to Sweden, and my presence in the Cathedral at Upsala on September 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline">, were notable events. </hi>Time alone will show what precise significance is to be attached to the participation of English Bishops in Swedish consecrations.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Lambeth Conference brought me into personal contact with the Anglican episcopate, &amp; made me known to them. I think they were surprized to discover that I was not exactly the outcast they had supposed. Several of the Bishops expressed their appreciation of the r&#x00F4;le I played in the debates, &amp; certainly whether for good or for ill that r&#x00F4;le was a considerable one.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I am now a member of the House of Lords, but it appears doubtful whether I can make anything of the position. For ecclesiastical legislation has now been transferred from Parliament to this so&#8211;called "National Assembly". </hi><hi rend="italic underline">There</hi><hi rend="italic"> the extreme repugnance with which the Assembly inspires me makes effective action almost impossible. I suspect that my influence must in the future decline very rapidly.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>