<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to the Cathedral at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> celebrated, and all the Canons and Minor Canons were present. The collect, and epistle accorded strangely with my mood, and with my situation. The lessons for the day, which I read through before the service began, might have been specially selected for the occasion. Wisdom VI 1&#8211;22 "<hi rend="underline">Hear therefore, ye kings, and understand; Learn, ye judges of the ends of the earth… For the Sovereign Lord of all will not refrain himself for any man's person, neither will he reverence greatness</hi>". 2 Timothy I is nothing else than a solemn &amp; moving charge to one who holds an office essentially the same as mine. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Linetta</hi><persName xml:id="1255"></persName> was waiting for me outside the cathedral, having journeyed from London for the purpose, &amp; she brought an affectionate letter from Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. The post brought also kind messages from Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> and Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">At 11 a.m. the ceremonial of the Enthronement took place</hi>. The weather, which had been dull, became brilliant as service proceeded. Everything went through without hitch of any kind. An immense congregation representing every phase of social life in the County, &amp; all the grouped institutions which have grown up around the College, filled the Church. Photographers were very active both before &amp; after the service. I preached with difficulty owing to an untimely cold, which rendered me as hoarse as a raven. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[6]</hi></p>
         <p>The spectacle of the incomparable church filled throughout with an eagerly interested multitude was very impressive. The mass of robed clergy was a pleasing variation on the generally sombre appearance of the congregation. <hi rend="bold underline">After the Enthronement followed the Mayor's luncheon in the Hall of the Castle</hi>. This was a really notable assembly. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> proposed my health, and I replied in a speech, which I had taken some pains over. It was, perhaps, rather too serious for the occasion, but I thought it well to give an air of gravity to my words. And certainly it was admirably listened to. After the lunch, I had tea with the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watkins<persName xml:id="2762"></persName>, &amp; then I went back to the Castle to obtain some rest. I dined with Bishop &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quick. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, Linetta, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; the young lady from Manchester made up the party. The question of a memorial of Bishop Moule was raised. I said that, if the diocese desired to commemorate him, the proper place for a memorial would be the cathedral, but in view of the general poverty, and of the pressing necessities which we cannot see our way to meeting, any considerable contribution to such a memorial would be extremely improbable. A memorial erected by his friends might take the form of a presentation to the Chapel at Auckland e.g. a stained glass window, or plate for the chapel etc. But I doubt whether he was considerable enough to justify a memorial.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>