<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We motored from Sunderland to Hartlepool arriving at the Town Hall about 10.30 a.m. Here the Mayor &amp; Council presented an Address, &amp; I made a speech. Then we were taken [to] the great ship&#8211;building works of Mes<hi rend="superscript underline">srs</hi> W<hi rend="superscript underline">m</hi> Gray &amp; Co. Ltd; where M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maurice Gibb received us, and showed us over the works. After this we went to the Municipal Buildings of West Hartlepool, &amp; here the Mayor &amp; Corporation of that Borough presented an address, &amp; I made another speech. Then the Incorporated Chambers of Commerce entertained me at Luncheon in the Grand Hotel. The President, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sydney Hogg, presided over a company of important business men numbering about 100. Col. Thomlinson<persName xml:id="5284"></persName> proposed my health: &amp; the toast was "supported" by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gibb &amp; Councillor Carter. The last, a working man, spoke very simply &amp; movingly about unemployment giving his own experience in illustration. I made a speech in reply. It was very closely listened to, and will (possibly) do good. <hi rend="bold underline">At least I spoke very plainly &amp; earnestly about the industrial situation, &amp; the inefficiency of the clergy which resulted from their poverty</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>From the Grand Hotel I was hurried off to a bazaar in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James's parish, &amp; here I made a fourth speech. Then I went to Christ Church Vicarage, &amp; rested for an hour, after which I was taken to a reception of "Church&#8211;workers", and talked to them severally. After that, a "square meal" as Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName> called it (one of those hideous hybrids known as "high tea"). We all went to the Town Hall for the final function of the day. Macdonald presided over a considerable audience, which included about 150 lads of the Hartlepool Boys Brigade, who had formed my "Guard <hi rend="bold">[63] </hi>[symbol] of honour" through the streets. Here a series of addresses were presented viz: </p>
         <p>1. From the Chapter &amp; Conference of Hartlepool Deanery</p>
         <p>2. The Ministers of the Sister Churches.</p>
         <p>3. The Hartlepool Employment Committee.</p>
         <p>4. Trade Unions, Shop Stewards, &amp; members of the Works' Committees.</p>
         <p>5. Hartlepool Boys Brigade.</p>
         <p>6. The League of Nations Union.</p>
         <p>7. Welcome to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Henson<persName xml:id="112"></persName></p>
         <p>These I took as the 'heads' of my speech which occupied about an hour in delivery, but was listened to without signs of fatigue. I took occasion to urge the careful preparation of the electoral rolls, if the "National Assembly" was to be worthy of its name. <hi rend="bold underline">I dwelt at some length on the phenomenon of unemployment</hi> &#8211; "A mass of unemployed men is so much loose powder lying about ready for the revolutionary spark to kindle"; '"ca canny" only enlarges the mischief' &#8211; I took up, &amp; developed a phrase from the Trade Union member's address, which spoke of "true partnership between Capital &amp; Labour", &amp; elaborated the old parallel between the "pontifex = bridgemaker", &amp; the Bishop. I spoke with some energy in defence of the League of Nations to the great delight of its supporters, a small but ardent group, but rather to the disgust of old Colonel Robson! We returned to the Castle after the meeting, and arrived a few minutes before 11 p.m. I hope my five speeches will have done no harm!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>