<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Christmas Day, December 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. All my household, except one maid, communicated. Afterwards I gave my Christmas gifts. To William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> I gave "Woodstock", &amp; to James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName>, "The Gladiators". While we sate at breakfast the Town Band came &amp; played outside the Castle, I gave them &#x00A3;1. The sordid motive of these performances is, of course, obvious enough, and yet they add something to the Festival that I would not willingly lose. Nor will I allow myself to think that no more adequate intention is in the Bandsmen's minds than the collection which rounds off the carols! I went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName> for Mattins, and there preached from the words in Titus III. 4. <hi rend="underline">"The kindness of God &amp; his love for man"</hi>. There was a considerable congregation. The post brought the account for legal fees on my translation from Hereford to Durham, &#x00A3;260: 6: 2. Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> sent me <hi rend="underline">"Italian gardens of the Renaissance &amp; other studies" by Julia Cartwright</hi>, which looks attractive. Also, she sent a fascinating set of picture&#8211;postcards "<hi rend="underline">Miniatures of the Life of St Cuthbert from the late XII</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="underline"> century Manuscript executed at Durham Cathedral Priory</hi>", now in the British Museum. After lunch we motored to Durham, &amp; attended Evensong in the Cathedral. Carols were sung very sweetly. I gave Christmas Boxes to Freeman, Hardy, &amp; Reeves, each &#x00A3;1.: &amp; to Jobling's daughter 10/&#8211;, and the assistant porter 10/&#8211;. We had tea with the Rogersons, &amp; then returned to the Castle, where we arrived a few minutes before 7 p.m. The weather had become quite mild.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>