<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>A snow mantled country. I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> communicated, but he had so bad a cold that I did not think it advisable to take him with me to Ryhope, as I had intended. My usual Sunday programme was followed: the morning was occupied in preparing a sermon which was delivered later in the day. After lunch we all motored to Durham, save the aforesaid George. There <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> were left to go to the Cathedral for the advent music, and visit their cronies. I went on to Grangetown, dropping Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, and arriving in a blizzard at least 10 minutes after time. Here I unveiled a war memorial, and preached a sermon. In spite of the weather, there was a considerable congregation. Adamson<persName xml:id="5268"></persName>, the Vicar of Grangetown, is son of the old Vicar of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring<persName xml:id="4101"></persName>, whose impending resignation has been announced. A youngish parson, Bentley&#8211;Goddard, now curate to Aglionby<persName xml:id="5267"></persName> at the Ven: Bede's Church, Sunderland, was also there. He struck me as promising. After tea at Grangetown, I went to Ryhope, &amp; preached to a considerable <hi rend="italic">congregation. The Vicar; Rev. P. Y. Knight, is an unmarried man, &amp; has been 35 years in Orders. He is a mighty talker, but appears to be an earnest &amp; hard&#8211;working clergyman. Here the archdeacon (Watkins<persName xml:id="590"></persName>) joined us at supper, &amp; motored with me as far as Durham, where I left him in the College, resumed my ladies, &amp; returned to the Castle</hi> arriving a little before 11p.m. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>