<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>My cold was so heavy on me, that I abandoned my intention of celebrating in the cathedral. This was a sharp, perhaps a salutary, reminder that there are limits imposed by the body on the will, that the plans we make must always have a note of interrogation against them, a note which becomes more prominent &amp; menacing as the years pass. This is Arthur's<persName xml:id="3128"></persName> Birthday, and I wrote to him. He and I are getting into the greyness &amp; dereliction of old age &#8211; he is 58 today, and I shall be 57 in a few days. Also, <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> pointing out that, since she was originally responsible for my going to Oxford, she must share with the Prime Minister the guilt or the credit of having made me Bishop of Durham! </hi>Having thus done my duty to my family I set to make notes for a sermon at Ryton tonight. It is the celebration of the 700<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> year since the consecration of the Church of the Holy Cross; and normally I should have found pleasure in preparing a sermon, filled with historical references, and leading up to some modern applications; but my head is as thick as a drain pipe, and as empty as a churchwarden's! Neither thoughts nor words come to me. It will be a woefully bad start, but I see nothing for it but to do what I have always despised the clergy for doing, viz: trust to the inspirations of the moment! After yesterday's exaltation, this is a fall indeed!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[8]</hi></p>
         <p>I lunched at the Deanery with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, &amp; then Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> arrived with the car from Auckland, and we all (together with Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName>) motored to Ryton, and there I preached in the parish church of S. Cross. The 700<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> anniversary of the consecration of the church was being observed. A great congregation came together, many being unable to obtain admission. I preached from Galatians VI.14. "<hi rend="underline">But far be it from me to glory save in the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, though which the world hath been crucified unto me, &amp; I unto the world.</hi>" The district being full of miners, and many of them being in the congregation, I addressed some earnest words to them as to their duty in the ballot this week. After the service, I spoke to the choir, and showed them the beautiful pastoral staff presented to Bishop Lightfoot. After supping with the Hunters at the Vicarage, we motored home, dropping Linetta at the Railway Station that she might return to London by the night train, and leaving me at the Castle. We got back about 11 p.m. being somewhat 'let &amp; hindered' by the violent wind, which blew out our lights. Thus I made a beginning of my work in the diocese, &amp; began it with the particular part of the work, which my previous career might seem to suggest that I can perform tolerably, viz: preaching. I had not been able to complete the writing of my sermon, which was largely extemporaneous, &amp; therefore verbose &amp; incoherent!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>