<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[21]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>My birthday has been marked by a number of very unpleasing experiences. We motored in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Harrison's car to Hartlepool, and lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi><persName xml:id="3698"></persName>. In his house I interviewed the two quarrelling parsons &#8211; Turner and Duff. Then we lunched, and returned to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName>. Here I found among my letters a doleful communication from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harold</hi><persName xml:id="113"></persName> informing me of what I had long secretly expected &#8211; his financial collapse. He pleaded hard for financial assistance which of course I had to refuse. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came to report further disaster to the car. It raises a doubt whether I may not be compelled to face the purchase of a new car. This, at present prices, is a ruinous matter.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">My letters contain some unpleasant reminders of the new &amp; almost menacing insistence on some increase of their emoluments which marks the clergy. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">They are sinking into debt, and into the inefficiency of which debt is the surest condition</hi><hi rend="italic">. Meanwhile, the prospect of raising funds for their assistance grows ever less promising. We are locked into a calamitous circle. Inefficiency breeds a dislike&amp; contempt of the clergy, these in turn, hinder the laity from removing </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the tap&#8211;root of inefficiency &#8211; the squalid poverty of the clergy. </hi><hi rend="italic">Unfortunately, an appeal has already been issued, and has so far succeeded as to spoil the pitch for anything more effective.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">'Why art thou cast down, O my soul? Any why art thou disquieted within me? Hope thou in God: for I shall yet praise him, who is the help of my countenance, and my God.'</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>Too rarely do we remember the mercies which have crowned our lives. The immediate anxieties cloud the horizon, and we can see nothing else. When I look back over the 57 years of my life, the causes for thanksgiving leap into prominence, and I am ashamed of the fears which darken and depress my mind. <hi rend="bold underline">The astonishing outburst of affection which has marked my return to Durham has amazed &amp; moved me in equal degrees. I cannot understand what there was in my record as Dean to create such personal attachment. Yet as to its sincerity and wide extension I can have no doubt. My central and prevailing desire is to justify the confidence of the people by being faithful to my trust. I come to this great See as one who is far advanced in middle life. In the nature of things I can have but a short time in which to work. Butler was Bishop of Durham for less than two years: Lightfoot's tenure did not exceed ten years. I can hardly hope for much more. There is no comparison between the difficulties of my position, &amp; those with which my predecessors had to reckon. </hi><hi rend="underline">"Show Thou me the way that I should walk in for I lift up my soul unto Thee."</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>