<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning contemplating my charge for the candidates, who made their way to Durham in the course of the afternoon. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored in, and arrived about tea&#8211;time. The Dawson Walkers<persName xml:id="3161"><persName xml:id="3461"></persName></persName> came to dinner at the Deanery. After dinner, I delivered my charge to the candidates, and then had some talk with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>. I sounded him on the subject of my scheme for linking the canonries with professorships in order to create in Durham a really strong theological school able to attract students, both Anglican and Nonconformist. He expressed himself as generally favourable, and I told him that I should now consult the two archbishops. <hi rend="bold underline">If he were a more trustworthy person</hi>, I should feel that a substantial advance has been made in getting his agreement. But in view of his too well founded character for "letting down" a colleague, I fear that I must not give much importance to his fair words. Also, I thought it well to sound him as to the disposition of the two vacant honorary canonries. He was not opposed to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Budworth</hi><persName xml:id="2692"></persName> being given a stall: and thought it probably advantageous that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ellershaw</hi> should be given the other. But he doubted, and in this respect I incline to agree with him, whether the diocese would approve both canonries being given to non parochial clergy. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>