<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[64]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I felt rather decadent &amp; played out after the exertions of yesterday. In the morning I dictated letters &amp;c. After lunch <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored into Durham, where she distributed prizes at the Girls' High School, and I presided at a meeting of the Board for Religious Education. Here we appointed two inspectors of schools in the diocese for one year at a stipend of &#x00A3;100. Batten of Greatham, &amp; Surtees of Brancpeth, were selected. I saw Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> in the Chapter clerk's office, and left with him the "letters dimissory" which I had received from the Bishop of Rangoon. Then I joined Ella at tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>: &amp; then, picking up George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, returned to the Castle. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">George</hi> seems to have grown since I last saw him: he has a more virile aspect, &amp; carries himself in a manly way. I had a great talk with him, &amp; was pleased by his frankness, his good sense, &amp; his good feeling. He certainly is one of "Nature's gentlemen", &amp; the experiences of his life are strengthening without hardening a character, naturally refined &amp; gentle. He has now been "round the world", &amp; seen many lands. His account of the Eastern ports gives a painful impression of vice, organised &amp; aggressive, which ravages the sailors. <hi rend="bold underline">Especially the ports of Japan seem to be abominable</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It must imply no slight measure of virtuous resolution in a lad of 16 to hold loyally to the habits of "temperance, soberness, &amp; chastity, which he has formed in childhood. George is now 20, and, so far as I can judge, as simple &amp; true as ever.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>