<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[3]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">"Except the Lord build the city: their labour is but vain that build it."</hi> Today (for the infirmity of our nature compels us thus to fasten on particular points in time, &amp; to accumulate significance upon them) <hi rend="bold underline">I enter this diocese formally &amp; publicly as its bishop. It marks the opening of what (to all human estimate of probability) is the last chapter or phase of my official, perhaps also of my natural, life</hi>. The glaring contrast between my qualifications, and the requirements of my great office, bears heavily on my mind, and on my conscience, for what moral right had I, being such a man, &amp; so limited as I know myself to be, to accept the position of Bishop of Durham? Inevitably, I turn from myself to "<hi rend="underline">the mountains from whence cometh help</hi>". If the religious interpretation of the world be true, then all events as well on the little plane of personal life as on the vast ranges of history, are government by the Will of God, and behind the arrangements which have made me Bishop of Durham is the righteous purpose of the Almighty. To believe this is to have access to an unfailing source of encouragement: "<hi rend="underline">And such confidence have we through Christ to Godward: not that we are sufficient of ourselves, to account anything as from ourselves; but our sufficiency is from God; who also hath made us sufficient as ministers of a new covenant; not of the letter, but of the spirit; for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life.</hi>"</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p>As soon as I had breakfast, I went into the city and bought the "Yorkshire Post". <hi rend="bold underline">There I read the welcome news that a settlement had been reached. Sir Robert Horne announced it in the House last night</hi>. I hastened back to the Castle, and inserted a paragraph in my Enthronement Address. Then the Reporter came to make some extracts for his own purposes! I went to Auckland by the noontide train, &amp; was met at the station by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; the car. We (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName>, &amp; I) motored to Darlington, &amp; went first to the Vicarage, where we had tea. Lord &amp; Lady Gainford were there. <hi rend="bold underline">The function in the Corn Exchange went off, I think, successfully, and it was followed by a short service in the parish church</hi>. A lesson was read by the Mayor's Chaplain, a local Methodist minister; &amp; the Vicar said some words of welcome, before prayers were read by the Rural Dean. Then I gave a brief address from the pulpit, &amp; pronounced the Benediction. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marion</hi><persName xml:id="77"></persName> arrived from London, &amp; was present at both the functions. We all motored to Durham, where Ella &amp; Marion put up at the Deanery, &amp; I returned to the Castle. This initial function did on the whole impress me as both fitting in itself, and sincere in those who took part in it. <hi rend="bold underline">I dwelt at some length on railwaymen, and strikes because while the first abound in Darlington, the last are paramount in the public mind at this time</hi>. The photographers were, of course, busy both inside and outside the Corn Exchange; and the weather was ideal.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>