<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The dramatic defeat of the Prohibitionists in Scotland<note xml:id="532" n="1"></note> has greatly exasperated the Fanaticks of "Temperance",</hi> &amp; they are disposed to visit their anger on me. An anonymous correspondent writing from Edinboro sends me the following together with a newspaper cutting containing the account of a police&#8211;court trial at Gateshead for brutal neglect of children by drunken parents.</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear Sir, </p>
         <p>You will be sorry to learn the Brewers in the Canvas on the Scottish Temperance Bill circulated your address, and caused many to stumble. </p>
         <p>Please read what occurred in your own Diocese, &amp; ask yourself if it is fair to those who are in this desperate struggle against Drink and Crime. I would not be in your place for all the world. </p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a specimen of a good many communications which have reached me from Scotland, &amp; I doubt not that it expresses a considerable volume of opinion in Scottish religious circles. <hi rend="bold underline">For the Churches went "bald&#8211;headed" for prohibition, &amp; the result of the polls is a great humiliation for them demonstrating how slight importance is attached to their most solemn pronouncements.</hi> The argument from drunkenness to prohibition is a truly precipitate advance through fallacy to fatuity. Yet it commends itself more widely than ever to religious people. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi> [symbol] </p>
         <p>The parish council of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Gabriel's, Bishop Wearmouth, decided by protracted discussion by 11 votes to 9 that the practice of turning to the East for the creed should <hi rend="underline">not</hi> be introduced into the public worship. <hi rend="bold underline">This so disgusted the choir&#8211;men that they promptly struck, and even set pickets at the entrance of the vestry to ensure that no "blacklegs" should lead the praises of the faithful!</hi> This grotesque incidents illustrates the state of indiscipline which obtains in the population of these parts. </p>
         <p>I walked with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> in the Park after lunch, first having my haircut by a local artist, who attended me in my study. He is a citizen of importance, &amp; has been for many years one of the Town Council. Then I wrote a Christmas letter to Gilbert, and dictated letters to Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName>. Then the Ordination candidates arrived, and Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> from Bridstow. During dinner the lections were read by the chaplains in town from Bigg's volume of sermons. The service in the chapel followed. Maish played the organ: Clayton read Evensong: I read the Lessons: and Knight gave the address. Then he and I adjourned to my study, and discussed the future of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, and other diocesan matters. I paid &#x00A3;5 for the Lord Chamberlain's fee on my taking my seat in the House of Lords. I went to the bed shortly before midnight. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>