<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[86]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, December 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A bad post! The Rural Dean of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street reports the Vicar of Hedgefield (Rev<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> T. W. Hanson<persName xml:id="5291"></persName>) for embezzling a considerable sum of money belonging to a society of working people of which he was Treasurer. How can any effectual ministry survive such a failure as that? H. is an Oxford man, and was ordained in 1898 in this diocese.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> N. P. Williams</hi><persName xml:id="4447"></persName> came to lunch. He is a little rat&#8211;like man with that queer "under&#8211;look" of the sacristy which all our "Catholicks" acquire. I talked with him for an hour, &amp; was interested. His father, the Rev<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> J. P. Williams, is vicar of S. Mary, Tyne Dock.</p>
         <p>After he had departed, I walked in the Park for an hour, and then had tea. Which ended, Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> &amp; I did the letters.</p>
         <p>I inquired of Williams whether there was a good promise of Ordination candidates at Oxford, <hi rend="bold underline">and he said that mostly only "smugs" looked to be ordained</hi>. I asked why good men would not come to Durham, &amp; he replied that it was the poor quality of the incumbent, and the remoteness of the parishes. Both facts must be admitted, but none the less that they should have such influence argues an absence of an heroic temper in the young men. The loneliness of a young clergyman in an average mining parish is sad to reflect upon. Something, perhaps, might be attempted by way of reunions here at the Castle during the summer. But the clergy are morose &amp; unresponsive for the most part.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>