<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I continued work at the books. Miss Honeybun called to explain the present position of the Preventive &amp; Rescue Association. The Bishop of Sk&#x00E4;ra came to lunch together with the Vicar of Seaton Carew, with whom he has been staying. After lunch we went on with the books until tea&#8211;time, after which I dictated letters &amp;c. until dinner.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Down urges me to reconsider my refusal to accept his invitation to preach in Belfast, but I am more &amp; more disinclined to bind myself by pledges long in advance of the engagements concerned: and any proposal that involves crossing the sea needs no other title to my extreme dislike! I also, largely for the same considerations, declined a request from Sir Thomas Oliver that I would preach in Geneva next May to the Royal Institute of Public Health.</p>
         <p>Loney of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> James', Stockton writes to say that my sermon last Sunday night "was splendidly right for us all, &amp; for others whom it will reach." I hope he is not mistaken. He adds: "Men seem inclined to respond to a leadership, brave &amp; brotherly, that manifests sympathetic vision of their longing for a full manhood." Are they in the smallest degree likely to get that kind of leadership from the present Bishop of Durham? I doubt it.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>