<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[9]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"Autobiographies, epistolary correspondence, notes of table&#8211;talk, are of the highest value in determining the correlation between a writer's self and his style."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Symonds</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The suggestion is that in his more private compositions, a man will write more naturally than in compositions designed for the public, and this seems probably enough. But allowance must be made for two contingencies. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">A man's genius may not rise above brief compositions, so that he may bestow his art most carefully upon these: and a man may have a fastidiously egotistic temperament so that he bestows most labour upon what is ostensibly designed for his own eye, or for the eyes only of his intimates</hi><hi rend="italic">. I am not sure whether some autobiographies are not the least natural and self&#8211;revealing productions of their authors, just as no man really discloses himself in the prayers which he writes. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Something, perhaps, may be inferred from the circumstance that he writes prayers at all, but very little from the prayers themselves</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is almost impossible to exaggerate the tendency to posing which marks men of quick fancy &amp; agile minds. The autobiography expresses what a man would like himself to appear, rather than what he actually has been. There is an imaginary audience to which he is always addressing himself</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p>A sharp stab of lumbago handicapped me grievously all day. The newspapers give good &amp; fairly detailed accounts of the functions on Saturday. <hi rend="bold underline">My references to the strike are emphasized. Every allusion to me is kindly</hi>. Accompanied by my ladies I motored to Bishop Auckland, and opened an account in Barclay's Bank there with my quarterly cheque (&#x00A3;1750). I showed Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> over the Castle, and the gardens. Also I paid wages. Then we motored back to Durham. After tea at the Deanery, I returned to my rooms, and wrote letters. Also I sent off the following checks viz:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">J. Parker, Bootseller</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">10.12.6.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">King's Acre Nurseries	</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">4.18.6.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Ch. S. Anderson	Durham Hoardings Rents</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">3.0.0.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Ths. Forster			 "	</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">6.0.0.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Church Printing C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">4.5.9.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Wilson &amp; Philips</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">2.9.0.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">The Field Press (Crockford)</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">1.5.0.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Macmillan</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">11.12.1.</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;44.2.10.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>These are all (except the Bootsellers, &amp; Macmillan) Hereford accounts. I must now make a final end of that brief but important &amp; interesting chapter of my life by transferring my account, &amp; squaring matters with my successor&#8211;a tiresome business.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi></p>
         <p>I dined with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cruickshanks</hi><persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName> to meet <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi>, who is to receive a degree tomorrow. Unfortunately, I am compelled to go to Bishop Auckland to receive addresses &amp;c., &amp;, of course, make a speech. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Grey</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">looks well, and is most friendly. I asked him if his eyesight was better. He said that it was not worse, but could never get better. I expressed the hope that he would again come forward, and take a prominent share in public life</hi>. <hi rend="underline">He said that he had definitely retired save that he occasionally offered advice to his countrymen</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">I said that he should do more, &amp; that none would rejoice more than I to see him leading the country</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moulsdale</hi><persName xml:id="3159"></persName> was very anxious to get from me some opinion about the policy of the Diocesan Finance Board with respect to men who came not to the University. I replied that I was decisively opposed to ordaining men who were inadequately equipped. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Judge Moore</hi>, a large man, was presented to me. He is the successor of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Judge Bonsey</hi>, whose sudden death happened shortly after our departure from Durham. He has had hard work to find a house, but has now succeeded in buying the house in the Bailey hitherto occupied by Major Lowe. <hi rend="bold underline">I walked back to the Castle with Ellershaw &amp; his wife. He says that everybody was pleased with my speech, which he characterised as "stately", an adjective which it pleased me to hear!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p>The following from Ker<persName xml:id="22"></persName> merits insertion: &#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>All Hallow Eve, 1920.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">My dear Henson,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Yesterday being in the chair in Common Room I addressed the [word illegible] in a voice that stilled all controversy, &amp; proposed we should drink the health of Herbert the new throned Bishop of Durham. Instantly we filled or glasses &#8211; yes, Lang &amp; Robertson called in unison for red wine. And we drank your health, &amp; were glad.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Ever yours truly,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">W. P. Ker.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">This pleasant message carries my thoughts to the time now 36 years ago when first I drank wine with Ker in the Common Room at All Souls. My election to a fellowship, against all probability &amp; certainly against all expectation, had decisive influence on my subsequent career. It brought me within the knowledge of the late Lord Salisbury, who subsequently recommended me to the Crown for appointment to a Canonry of Westminster Abbey. My subsequent preferments have grown from the impression which I made during my ministry in Westminster. It is to All Souls College that all the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">success</hi><hi rend="italic"> of my career is mainly due.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>