<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The 'Times' contained what must be regarded as an unusually full account of yesterday's proceedings. By midday the debate was closured, &amp; the Parish Councils Bill given a general approval. I lunched at the House of Lords with Nickson. At 3.45pm <hi rend="bold underline">I took my seat in that august assembly</hi>. The ceremonial was brief, but very quaint. Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName> picked me up after the session, &amp; we had tea together. I dined at the Athenceum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. </p>
         <p>I had much interesting talk with a Judge, who sate next to me in the dining room. He made my acquaintance when I was Dean of Durham, &amp; he came there on circuit. He told me that he was himself persuaded that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Greenwood</hi><persName xml:id="5266"></persName> was guilty, &amp; that five judges discussing together the case took the same view, though one doubted. He admitted that the evidence was inadequate, &amp; that the case for the Crown had been badly handled. The L.C.F. thought that the judge should have directed the Jury to bring in a verdict of attempted poisoning. For arsenic had been given, &amp; probably by the prisoner, but the woman may have died from the morphia pills. He said that the work of a judge was very fatiguing. He felt more tired after his day in court, than he had felt after 15 hours work when at the bar. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hadow</hi><persName xml:id="3178"></persName> was in the club, brisk and cheerful as ever. I wish he was back again in Newcastle. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>