<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>A stiff chapter of Wicksteed<persName xml:id="4444"></persName> was relieved in the last paragraph of the following story:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"Some two years before his death, we learn, when his great work the Summa Theologioe was still incomplete, though well advanced in its 3</hi><hi rend="i superscript">rd</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; concluding section, as Thomas was celebrating Mass in Naples, he had some experience the nature of which is not further specified, which made him put his pen &amp; inkhorn on the shelf &amp; never write another word of his treatise. When he was reminded of the incomplete state of his great work, &amp; was urged to go on with it, he only replied, "I have seen that which makes all that I have written &amp; taught look small to me" (p. 391).</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the day in composing a sermon for use tomorrow. <hi rend="italic">It is a question whether it is worth while to expend so much time &amp; labour on preparing sermons for delivering to such a congregation as I shall have to address in S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName>. But I shrink from sinking into the crowded class of "extemporaneous" preachers. </hi>After lunch I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> in the Park for an hour. After dinner time the Church Lads Brigade<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> sang carols outside the Castle, &amp; were rewarded with 5/&#8211;. Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> went off for Christmas Day &amp; Sunday. He returns on Monday. The weather today has been damp &amp; unpleasant but not cold. In the Durham paper the appointment of two new hon: canons is announced. The general impression I have received is that the choice I have made is a good one in the judgement of the clergy &amp; public.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>