<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="i bold">Postils:</hi><hi rend="italic">&#8211; a term applied to sermons is derived from the rubric in the Homiliarium of Paulus Diaconus. 'Post illa verba textus'. Postillare was often used instead of praedicare in mediaeval Latin.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">v. Garvie, "The Christian Preacher" p.97</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>The day was so tempestuous that I gave up my intention of motoring to Birtley after lunch, and worked with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> at arranging the books. It is more woefully evident than ever that my bookshelves are quite inadequate.</p>
         <p>For once the "soft answer" actually succeeded in "turning away wrath". The parson in Poplar, whose insolent letter I returned with some kindly words about his work, writes to apologise for his "rude letter", and to ask me to preach in his church!</p>
         <p>Old partblind <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Adamson</hi><persName xml:id="4101"></persName> writes to announce his intention of resigning the famous &amp; well&#8211;endowed living of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. This is an important matter indeed. He will probably require a pension, but even so the income will be far above the average. It will be curious if the first piece of patronage which falls to my disposal is also the best. I have no doubt that many appetites are already quickened, but they will all be disappointed. I must use the opportunity for getting a good man into the diocese, and (if I can persuade him to uproot himself) the right man is not far to seek. But first the Rector's resignation must be signed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>