<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I essayed to prepare a sermon for Stockton on Sunday, but with woefully small success. Then the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> G. E. Brigstoke, Curate of Shildon, came to see me, and to explain why he desired to leave that parish after less than 3 months residence. It appears to be a case of temperamental antipathy between him and his vicar. I told him to do nothing hastily, &amp; hinted that I might want him shortly for a difficult work. In speaking thus I was thinking of Birtley, where a new district ought to be constituted. After lunch I went to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Diocesan Conference Committee. We agreed upon the agenda for the "Business Conference" which is to meet in the Chapter House on Saturday, Feb. 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. On my return to the Castle I went through the Reports of the Examining Chaplains on the work of the Ordination Candidates. <hi rend="italic bold underline">I rejected 1 deacon, and 3 priests. Those whom I accepted were mostly of very poor quality. This is the weak point of the diocese: &amp; I hardly see how it is to be righted.</hi></p>
         <p>I paid the poor rate (&#x00A3;64.15.9): the district rate which I paid yesterday was &#x00A3;41:0:2: and the water rate &#x00A3;9:9:0. This is a total for the half&#8211;year of &#x00A3;115:4:11, and for the year, &#x00A3;230:9:10 &#8211; a formidable sum. I have yet to pay the Mortgage charges, the Firstfruits &amp; Tenths, the Convocation charge, and the rent for the Inner Park. These will be not less than &#x00A3;350. Then there are the Income Tax &amp; Super Tax!!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>