<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>The cab failed to turn up. Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName> and I raced to the station through the rain, &amp; just succeeded in catching the train. My journey to King's Cross in a crowded smoking carriage was comfortless. On arrival I went to Garland's, &amp; deposited my luggage. <hi rend="bold underline">Then I walked to Westminster, and attended the meeting of the National Assembly</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> There was a large attendance, and evidently the members were in the mood to hustle through much business. We adopted the Standing Orders on <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Hugh Cecil's</hi><persName xml:id="314"></persName> motion: &amp; gave a general approval to a Bill for reforming the Lower Houses of convocation on the motion of the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName>. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">L</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parmoor</hi> introduced the <hi rend="underline">pi&#x00E8;ce de r&#x00E9;sistance</hi>, the Bill for giving Powers to the new Parochial Councils. I asked whether names sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> by sent in for speaking, &amp; was told that convenience was served best by that practice. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">Inskip</hi><persName xml:id="4783"></persName> spoke in criticism of the Bill, &amp; then the inevitable <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wolmer</hi><persName xml:id="1028"></persName>. I came away with the understanding that I would speak tomorrow morning. </p>
         <p>I dined at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, the Bishop of Chester sitting opposite to me. He asked me whether I was dining at "Nobody's", &amp; seemed surprised when I told him that I had not been asked to be a member. Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> was in the Club brandishing proofs of his Sermon on Divorce, &amp; bubbling over with the subject! I wrote a few letters, turned over a few books, &amp; so went back to the Hotel. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>