<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>My morning was frittered away. There were several callers, some indispensable letters, a visit to the Bank, and the long&#8211;overdue clearing up of my study&#8211;table. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Griffin, who for 5 years past, has been doing practically all the duty in Coxhoe, where old Canon Fleming has just died, came to see me by appointment. He is a widower: has been in Orders 16 years: professes himself a liberal&#8211;minded Churchman: &amp; declaims against "spikes"<note xml:id="527" n="1"></note>. He is an Irishman. <hi rend="italic">I do not think that, as a general rule, it is wise to appoint curates to be the incumbents of the parishes where they are actually working. </hi>Accordingly I wrote to the L. Chancellor who, for this turn is patron of Coxhoe, indicating that I did not wish Griffin to be appointed, and suggested Cecil Fortescue<persName xml:id="4760"></persName>. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived before lunch, and walked for an hour with me in the Park. After tea I wrote to Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName>, &amp; Chancellor Dowdall. Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName>, having decided to keep on until the end of the year, I was able to get through some rather important correspondence. <hi rend="italic">The worst problem of my office takes more intractable shape daily viz. how to find suitable Ordination candidates. </hi>There is but too evident reason for thinking that the Ministry has become in this diocese a kind of "dock&#8211;gates" for the lower middle&#8211;class, where men who cannot for their incompetence earn a living in any other trade or profession are able to secure a present maintenance. This is the root of the public contempt for clergymen, &amp; explains the failure of the Church. But where is the remedy?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>