<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "City of Hereford" Free Church Council sends me a formal address of Farewell</hi>. It has a certain measure of exceptional interest as referring to the Lambeth Conference, and to <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> eloquence:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The Council believes that your influence was felt in the Lambeth resolutions desiring the closer unity of the churches &amp;c. <hi rend="bold underline">The Council also desires to say the influence of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Hensley Henson<persName xml:id="112"></persName> &amp; particularly her admirable addresses were appreciated by every lover of what is good</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>"</p>
         </div>
         <p>I have not hitherto realized the oratorical gifts of my wife, but then I have never heard her speak in public.</p>
         <p>We went to Durham, and lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk. Then followed an imposing function. I blessed the colours of the Durham Light Infantry in Palace Green. <hi rend="bold underline">Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName></hi> made an excellent speech to the troups. We all then proceeded to the Cathedral, where the colours were presented to the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, &amp; placed on the Altar. After a brief oration from the Dean, the Band played the National Anthem, &amp; I gave the Blessing from my Throne. We had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Shafto<persName xml:id="3989"></persName>, &amp; then I walked with Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>. I dined at the Castle to meet the Judge of Assize (Rigby Swift<persName xml:id="5271"></persName>). It was pleasant company on the whole. I stayed for the night with Ellershaw in order not to compete with the Judge for my rooms!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The judge told me that the initials "C. J. D." appended to the little poem "At the Abbey Gate" are those of M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Justice Darling</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It runs thus:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Stay &#8211; Who goes there?</p>
         <p>A friend &#8211;</p>
         <p>What friend &#8211; Whence came you?</p>
         <p>From a dark cave beneath a ruined street.</p>
         <p>Oh friend, where fare you:</p>
         <p>Why would'st thou pass further?</p>
         <p>To lay my heart down at our Mother's feet.</p>
         <p>Whom call you Mother?</p>
         <p>England &#8211; Nelson's: thine:</p>
         <p>Her whom we proudly serve, in life, in death &#8211;</p>
         <p>Her do I guard, friend &#8211;</p>
         <p>Can'st thou also serve her?</p>
         <p>Aye, when they fail her who do yet draw breath.</p>
         <p>Who art thou, friend, then?</p>
         <p>I was &#8211; and am <hi rend="underline">No One</hi> &#8211;</p>
         <p>No name is ours &#8211; An unknown host are we.</p>
         <p>Pass on, brave spirit.</p>
         <p>Oh, 'tis Christ that passes.</p>
         <p>In thee, poor soldier, who didst die for me.		</p>
         <p>C. J. D.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>