<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Trinity, November 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">It is the privilege of a Bishop to possess an altar within his own house</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>An episcopal palace is in fact a church. Its life proceeds within consecrated walls, and the family tread ever on holy ground. For two great purposes particularly the Bishop's altar must be serviceable. On the one hand, it raises &amp; hallows the personal life of the Bishop himself, &amp; his household: on the other hand, it is the centre of intercession for the Bishop's work, &amp; for the flock of Christ committed to his charge.</p>
         <p>Such is the intention &#8211; <hi rend="underline">a central Hearth, whereon the Divine Fires of Faith &amp; charity, shall be glowing, &amp; the Spiritual Father be ever praying for his children</hi>. And the reality?</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in my chapel at 8 a.m. Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> assisted. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Berry, Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName>, and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The eastward position was adopted, and two candles were lighted, this being the practice in Durham Cathedral, and the standard to which I would like the diocese as a whole to conform</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Mostly, however, the Durham clergy are low churchmen of rather a rough type: and there is a small minority of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" to whom the simple ceremonial of my chapel would be wholly unsatisfying. Still, there is no other ceremonial which seems to have the smallest chance of securing general acceptance. The "North&#8211;end" has become as obsolete as the Black Gown.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p>After lunch we motored (in a hired car for which &#x00A3;4 was charged) to Tanfield far up in the hills. The weather changed, &amp; we returned through heavy rain. At Tanfield I dedicated a memorial clock, (which Ella started before the service began), and a Tablet with the names of 79 fallen soldiers from the parish. Major Waring<persName xml:id="5273"></persName>, the local M.P. unveiled it &#8211; a strapping young man with an honest face.</p>
         <p>I preached to the people from Joshua XXIV. There was a great crowd, many being unable to gain entrance into the church. After service we had tea at the Vicarage. Old Canon Archdale draws towards 80, and not long ago he had a stroke. But he is said to have done good work in his day. Philps of Stanley was there, &amp; I took occasion to inquire how many names were on the roll of his vast parish which contains no less than 25000 souls. He replied, "About 800"! Similarly in Bishop Auckland itself: S. Peter's parish<placeName xml:id="105"></placeName> contains about 5500 people: it has an electoral roll of less than 300. If this be at all generally the ratio of voters to population, it is sufficiently evident that the new "National Assembly" will possess small title to its name. All the powers which are to be bestowed on the new Parochial Councils must be transferred to them from some authority which at present possesses them&#8211;the incumbent, the parishioners, the patron, or the Bishop. It is very arguable that these are really better fitted for exercising these powers, if certain that they are not fully aware to their risk of losing them.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>