<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> brought some documents for me to sign. After some talk with Ellershaw, who is evidently throwing himself with devotion into the work of his office, I went to the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, &amp; discussed diocesan policy. We agreed that I had best hold my hand for the nonce, and declare myself in a letter to the diocese in January. I returned to the Castle at Auckland, &amp; was met at the station by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. I paid &#x00A3;879.1.0. to the executors of Bishop Moule for furniture which I had bought.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The secretary of the Golf Club which plays in the Park, writes to ask permission to play on Sundays</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>This is not wholly easy to refuse, and yet hardly prudent to concede. In any case, of course, somebody will have to be offended. The question is, which decision offends the least considerable or respectable section of people. It may be the best course to seize the opportunity of making a public pronouncement on the subject of what is called "Sunday observance", repudiating the Sabbatarian principle, but on grounds of the higher expediency endorsing in this particular Sabbatarian conclusion. A respectable minority of the club appears to be opposed to the petition which is said to be mainly supported by the "public&#8211;house section" of the members. Still it is a nuisance having to pronounce on the question.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>