<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Snow was falling smartly when I came into my study at 8 a.m. I wrote many letters, made some sermon notes, and paid some bills before lunch. Afterwards George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> walked with me to South Church. It is a fine open building, well adapted for congregational use. The tower is a noticeable feature. After tea, I wrote more letters. </p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I definitely refused to accept as a candidate for Holy Orders a man, otherwise well&#8211;fitted, &amp; possessed of a private income, who was blind</hi><hi rend="italic">. It does not appear to me that a man thus physically afflicted can fulfil a ministry of the word and sacrament in any effectual sense. He would always need assistance, &amp; he could hardly pursue any serious study. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The disposition of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring weighs on my mind</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">If K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> [Knight] would take it, &amp; give himself whole&#8211;heartedly to the work, I might, perhaps, do wisely to risk the local rage by bringing him in. On the other hand, there is something to be said for trying to find a younger man, &amp; getting a "school of prophets" established there. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Preferment is so slow in this diocese that I can hardly count on another chance of brining a good man in from outside</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">There are some legitimate ambitions within the diocese which will have to be disappointed: &amp; by appointing an outsider, I shall lose the opportunity of creating a vacancy, which could be seriously filled. </hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>