<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated. All the morning I remained in my study preparing a sermon for the evening. After lunch Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> &amp; I set out in the car for Boldon, but our way through the Park was blocked by a large beech, which had been blown down in Friday's gale. In endeavouring to get round it, the car stuck in the sodden grass, &amp; was extricated by the combined efforts of ourselves, the woodman &amp; his sons. We turned back, &amp; set out through the town, arriving after a curiously complicated journey, about 5 p.m. At Evensong I preach<hi rend="superscript underline">ed</hi> in the parish church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Nicholas, an interesting 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century church, distinguished by three tombs of former rectors &#8211; recumbent effigies in recesses against the north wall of the chancel, &amp; the south wall of the nave. There was also a fine double piscina. The congregation was beyond the capacity of the building which is not large. I preached with reference to the occasion &#8211; the 700 anniversary of the church &#8211; drawing a comparison between the XIII<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century &amp; the XX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, both as to resemblances &amp; differences, &amp; referring to the Boldon Book. After service, in the Vestry, I spoke strongly to the Rector &amp; Churchwardens on the necessity of getting the Electoral Roll under the Enabling Act properly prepared. There are but 200 names out of a population of 3000. The parson &#8211; Leake &#8211; is evidently a very High Churchman. We retuned to the Castle after supper, arriving a little after 11 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>