<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>As the <hi rend="underline">dies fatalis</hi> approaches, I grow restless and unable to concentrate my thoughts. <hi rend="bold underline">The dubiety as to the industrial situation adds to my embarrassment</hi>. This morning's papers report a set&#8211;back in the Strike negociations. The difficulty of discovering how far the Labour leaders are acting in good faith makes the gaining of industrial piece very difficult. It is impossible for me to decide what I will say until I know whether the strike is to continue.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A young man, Spencer, came to see me about Ordination</hi>. Neither physically nor educationally does he appear to be tolerably qualified, but the late Bishop seems to have encouraged him, and even made some kind of vague promise. His father saw me at my request later in the day, and I told him that I would accept the youth on the understanding (a) that he produced a satisfactory doctor's certificate, and (b) that he passed my Examination next September. He does not look very likely to do so</p>
         <p>Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> and Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came after lunch, &amp; did some necessary business, mostly of an unpleasant disciplinary character. Ernest Ager, one of the old boys from Barking, writes to ask my Blessing on his becoming a postulant of the Society of Divine Compassion at Stanford&#8211;le&#8211;hope, Essex. I remember him quite well, a serious boy, all but a hunch&#8211;back, with great black eyes and a manner of profound reverence. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></p>
         <p>I must own to being touched by Ager's letter. It is fully 25 years since I left Barking, yet he writes thus:</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Lord Bishop,</p>
         <p>When I was in France, you were kind enough to write me an encouraging letter as one of your old Barking boys, &amp; so I am again venturing to ask your blessing on the step I have taken in becoming a postulant of the Society of Divine Compassion. I have always felt how much I have to thank you for. If I may be allowed to say so, you were always my ideal priest. You prepared me for Confirmation, heard my first Confession, &amp; gave me my first Communion.</p>
         <p>And beyond this, you took me on one of you preaching visits to S. Philip's, Plaistow, where I came into touch with this Community. It is a long time ago, but I have held on through all kinds of difficulties, and now in the good Providence of God, I have been received into their house.</p>
         <p>So I ask our lordship's blessing and prayers, because I feel that I really did belong to you, and had a share, although young in years, in all that those dear days meant.</p>
         <p>Yours very faithfully.</p>
         <p>Ernest C. P. Ager.</p>
         <p>(Postulant).</p>
         </div>
         <p>I sent him a kind letter.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>