<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1920.</hi></p>
         <p>Symmonds is evidently casting himself in the r&#x00F4;le of a religious leader in this juncture. He sends me "An Open Letter" addressed to D<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Fraser, the Principal of the Presbyterian College, Montreal, and entitled "A Spiritual Forward Movement". The phrase "Forward Movement" appears to be applied to a Missionary effort in Canada analogous to the "National Mission" in this country. Symonds lays it down that "an old&#8211;fashioned revival, which has for its inspiration a theology untouched by modern thought, is doomed to worse than failure". He thinks that a "Forward Movement" on those lines "may, in the final analysis, prove a backward movement". I agree, &amp; think that England can provide the proof of his fears. He advances to an earnest appeal to "modern scholars" to come to the rescue, &amp; pleads that the results of Historical Criticism or Modern Science should be frankly acknowledged in our preaching, &amp; nothing advanced which those results have made untenable. I agree again, but point out that there is some difficulty in determining what these all&#8211;important "results" actually are. The spiritual nature of man and the Fatherhood of God are to be the two grand postulates of the "Forward Movement", and the idea of the Church must relate itself to these. Thus the "hierarchical" idea will be disallowed, &amp; the Church will be expounded as the "family of God". He thinks this version of X<hi rend="bold superscript underline">ity</hi> will match modern requirements.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Potts</hi> came to see me with respect to the Gate&#8211;keepership. He is willing to reside in the Lodge, &amp; undertake charge of the Gate. I will pay 10/&#8211; per week, &amp; give free residence. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Glyn</hi>, the curate, &amp; his wife will reside in the Lodge. This seems to be a promising arrangement.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Proud</hi> the solicitor, who is acting for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mess</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Ellis &amp; Sons</hi>, the present tenants of the Castle Gardens, saying that I w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> renew his tenancy on condition (1) that he rented the whole of the gardens, (2) that he paid &#x00A3;65 yearly as rent, (3) that he provided fruit &amp; vegetables for the castle at market rates, (4) that the agreement included a clause suggested by Downing. If this arrangement works out successfully, the problem of the Gardens will have been temporarily solved.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev: H. W. H. Birchen</hi>, Vicar of Barnard Castle, came to see me respecting an elderly curate whom he wished to employ. I consented to his taking duty for 3 months "without prejudice".</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Two candidates for Ordination called, &amp; were accepted, i.e. given leave to sit for the next examination. Both were poor creatures to look at: Henry John Walton, aged 23. B.A. Durham, has the use of but one eye. Frank Churchyard, aged 34, no degree, is almost a dwarf. Shall I never have the satisfaction of seeing an able&#8211;bodied &amp; educated man offer himself for Ordination? Everybody assures me that there is a prejudice against the Northern dioceses, and the work of the diocese of Durham is perhaps less varied and more arduous than in any other</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>