<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[116]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, January 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent two hours in revising, and adding to, an old sermon, with a view to rendering it available for use when I preach to the sectaries on January 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Then, accompanied by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, I motored to Durham and lunched with Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName>. Before lunch I went upstairs to see Charlie in bed, where he is recovering from an operation. <hi rend="bold underline">I discussed the C.E.M.S<orgName xml:id="207"></orgName> with L., but didn't get much farther. The Society is really useless, but, like Charles II, it "takes an unconcionable time in dying"</hi>! I inquired what precisely was his tenure of the Diocesan Missionership, and, as I supposed, it has no legal connexion with the canonry whatever. There was an understanding between Bishop Moule and himself that, if he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> act as Canon Missioner, he sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be made Canon of Durham: &amp; he is "honourably bound" so to act: but the understanding is not capable of being enforced, &amp; is most probably illegal! Something very similar is the case with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. L. and I attended a meeting of the Lay&#8211;workers Association. Both the Archdeacons<persName xml:id="590"><persName xml:id="3688"></persName></persName> were present. Then I called to inquire about the progress of Bishop Quirk<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> who is down with jaundice. We motored back to the Castle, &amp; arrived at tea&#8211;time. Then we did the correspondence, and I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. The weather, which has for some days been unwholesomly warm, became much colder today. We were glad to have the motor&#8211;car closed when we returned from Durham.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>