<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I breakfasted with Lord S. and Lady Serena. Then I <hi rend="bold underline">walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and prepared notes for a speech on the Divorce Bill, of which Gorell<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> is to move the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Reading this afternoon</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then I walked to 98 Park Street, and lunched with Willie Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName>, Vivian &amp; Eleanor. Willie walked back to the Athenaeum, where I picked up my paper&#8211;bag, &amp; walked to the House of Lords. Then I made a final revision of my speech, &amp; attended the debate. Lang spoke, and, when he sate down, I got up, but gave place to L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Parmoor. <hi rend="italic bold underline">When he had finished, I got up, and delivered my speech with sundry impromptus suggested by the debate. Lang, Ingram, Talbot<persName xml:id="105"></persName>, Watts&#8211;Ditchfield, &amp; Cecil<persName xml:id="31"></persName> were the other occupants of the episcopal bench. There were about 50 peers in the House, and quite a little crowd about the throne of eldest sons &amp; officials. The House was attentive: once it laughed, &amp; at the end it cheered. I was followed by F. E.<persName xml:id="2508"></persName> [F. E. Smith] who paid me an elaborate compliment. Lang said the speech was a great success: so did Lord Massarene, and Godfrey<persName xml:id="2685"></persName>. So I might have fared worse. Lord Scarbrough turned up, &amp; was, I think, pleased. </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Now I have to run the gauntlet of the Church Papers. The sinister Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName> was there, &amp; will be able to give </hi><hi rend="underline">his</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> account of what I said to the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName>! Anyway, on this very burning question, I have "crossed the Rubicon", &amp; that is, perhaps, worth something in these times of confusion</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[209]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Emmott</hi> came to dinner, and he agrees with Lord S. in saying that my speech was "a great success". The latter was really almost enthusiastic. "a breath of fresh air in the House &#8211; everybody was delighted." Well, well! "F.E." is said to have become a "Pussy&#8211;foot" for a period of six months, probably under doctor's orders. He certainly looks very well under the new r&#x00E9;gime. Lord E. thinks that the events in Russia are probably "the beginning of the end". The Bolshies may suppress this rising, but the economic position is desperate, and quite beyond their powers to rectify. We talked of the Milner Report on Egypt. Lord S. said that it was drafted by Rennell Rodd, who was enthusiastic about it. Lord E. said that he felt the deepest misgivings on 3 subjects &#8211; Ireland, Egypt, India.</p>
         <p>A message was brought to me from the Press Gallery when I sate down after delivering my speech to the effect that I had not been well heard in the Reporters' Gallery, &amp; asking for my notes that they might be used in the official Report. I certainly was very hoarse in speaking, &amp; the Reporters' Gallery is rather distant, still it is humiliating to learn that I was badly heard.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bell</hi><persName xml:id="4126"></persName>, the Archbishop's Chaplain, was among the company on the steps of the Throne while I was addressing the House. I told him to convey to his Grace my dutiful regards, and to wish him a speedy recovery. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bell</hi> himself professed a measure of agreement with my speech.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>