<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[345]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit&#8211;Monday, May 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Somebody from Sunderland sends me a copy of Saturday's issue of the "Daily News" with an article on its front page headed "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">A Bishop and a Miner. A case before the Lord Chancellor</hi><hi rend="italic">". </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Its point is simply an attack on the ^official^ Incomes of the Lord Chancellor ^&#x00A3;10,000^, and the Bishop of Durham:^&#x00A3;7,000^</hi><hi rend="italic">: its argument that the miner's work is more important than theirs, &amp; that, therefore, their remuneration ought to be no greater than his: its ^obvious^ object to discount the effect of their speeches on the Strike by raising irrelevant prejudice. Yet the "Daily News" was once a reputable newspaper.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The more I reflect on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Arthur Pease's</hi><persName xml:id="5262"></persName><hi rend="italic"> answers to my questions yesterday, the less satisfied I am. For instance, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I asked him whether it was true that the mine&#8211;owners were foregoing all profits for the next 4 months. He replied that 'like most statements about mining, it was both true &amp; false"; from which I inferred that without what may be technically called "profits", the mine&#8211;owners will gain sufficiently</hi><hi rend="italic">. I asked whether it was true that the mine&#8211;owners took for themselves without payment the stores of wood &amp;c carried into the mines during the period of control. His</hi> <hi rend="italic bold underline">answer was that they had done so, but that this was the custom of the industry not to reckon anything below ground in assets, &amp; that this was reasonable since, once carried below, timber &amp;c became rapidly valueless. The whole matter was trivial</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I challenged him on the alleged working of thin seams, and</hi> <hi rend="bold">[346] </hi>[symbol] <hi rend="italic">reservation of the better seams until the period of control had ended. He said (&#x3B1;) that when the war broke out, &amp; was generally expected to be short in duration, the mine&#8211;owners had ordered everything to be subordinated to coal&#8211;getting: &amp; had thus created a situation which had to be rectified as the war dragged on, (&#x3B2;) that the miners, seeing great blocks of coal left untouched jumped to the conclusion that these were being reserved for some selfish purpose of the mine&#8211;owners,: whereas it was generally the case that the reservation was necessitated by the safety of the mine, or by surface&#8211;structures which w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> be destroyed if the coal was removed, (&#x3B3;) that there were no doubt individual mine&#8211;owners who might be guilty of unfairly reserving the better seams.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I left the Castle a little before 10 a.m., and motored by way of Sunderland to Castletown in the civil parish of North Hylton. Here I consecrated a portion of the new cemetery. The local authority met me, and there was an odd concession to sectarian jealousy in the holding of a meeting immediately after the consecration service. Several ministers &amp; a female Salvation Army "Captain" made speeches. Then a hymn was sung, and for the second time I pronounced the Benediction. We motored back to the Castle by way of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, arriving a little after 2 p.m. The Park was full of people observing some kind of 'F&#x00EA;te' connected, I think, with Temperance Fanaticks. I shudder to think of the appearance of the Park tomorrow!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[347]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had arranged that a party of Knutsford men should visit the Castle; that there should be a Celebration of the Holy Communion in the Chapel: that then they should start for a long walk, to visit divers places of archaeological interest, &amp; should, before returning to Durham, have Evensong in the Chapel. This programme was carried through successfully, with the addition that I was induced to give an address at Evensong. I spoke to them of the difficulties of the Christian ministry, emphasizing the lack of the normal safe&#8211;guards ^of^ efficiency. I pointed out that the popular tests were entirely misleading in some cases, and trustworthy in none. A "popular preacher" was often no more than an idle wind&#8211;bag: a successful beggar might be only a persistent toady: a successful man with boys might be, and often was, only a self&#8211;indulgent sentimentalist. What, I asked, ought your training to give you? And I answered that it should teach at least 5 things:&#8211; 1. The power to run alone. 2. The habit of conscientious study. 3. Sufficient knowledge to be aware of ignorance. 4. Settled convictions on the main issues of discipleship. 5. Self&#8211;knowledge enough to avoid the worst pitfalls. I ended by begging them not to underrate the importance of intellectual preparation. Let them make their work at the University a part of their Religion. Afterwards I had some talk with Pestle<persName xml:id="5294"></persName>, the Chaplain of University College, who had come with them.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>