<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[308]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I copied from "The Challenge (April 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1921) the following extract from the leading article, headed 'Coal and the Churches':</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"if we are God's children the spirit of His family must ultimately control the relation of class to class and nation to nation: that in Christ Jesus is neither bondman nor freeman, nor any servitude, <hi rend="underline">whether under fetters or under economic law</hi>.</p>
         <p>To have political and social affairs outside the sphere of Christ's authority is to surrender not only the universalism of His claim but the possibility of His Coming.</p>
         <p>A test case has been presented: she (the Church) is commissioned to be the judge in matters moral and religious: is she to follow Pilate's prudent example? Or will she labour night and day to give an impartial hearing and an impartial verdict."</p>
         </div>
         <p>It is difficult to place any precise meaning on this language which shall be both adequate and relevant. It seems to imply </p>
         <p>(&#x3B1;) that Christians as such are not subject to economic law.</p>
         <p>(&#x3B2;) that Christ's claim and coming are to be matters of terrestrial history and import.</p>
         <p>(&#x3B3;) that the "Church" ought to take over the functions of the Government &amp; the law&#8211;courts.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[309]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>All this seems to me nonsense, and dangerous nonsense. Yet the leader is certainly the work of an able, ardent, and educated man. I suspect the author is <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Raven</hi><persName xml:id="4379"></persName>; the new editor of the Challenge.</p>
         <p>It was raining hard when I left Park Lane at 9.30 a.m. The 10 a.m. express ran as usual, but stopped at Darlington, so that I arrived there half an hour before <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> appeared with the car. At York <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Renshaw</hi> came into my carriage. I found <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Meyer</hi> at the Castle, and we went together to the meeting in the Chapel. We both spoke, and then I pronounced the Benediction. The chapel was crowded and I was interested to see that most of the assembly were men. <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Meyer</hi><persName xml:id="1798"></persName> is a master of the art of popular homiletics. His address was very simple, and very effective. There was a touch of farcical humour which no doubt commended it to the audience. My own speech was, of course, far duller, but it was well listened to, and I think some things that I said were timely. <hi rend="bold underline">The "churchwarden of Toronto<placeName xml:id="109"></placeName> called, and collected &#x00A3;1 from me for the miners' children, who are said to be starving</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It is a farcical position that we should be expected to subsidize the strikers in order to make it possible for them to hold out! <hi rend="bold underline">The evening papers contain hopeful reports of the situation</hi><hi rend="bold">,</hi> but all turns on factors which are but half&#8211;disclosed, &amp; on persons who are but half&#8211;known.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>