<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove me to the station for the 7.58 a.m. train. I travelled to King's Cross very comfortably, and managed to get a taxi at once. Dropping my bags at 21 Park Lane, I went on to the Ecclesiastical Commission House at Westminster, &amp; attended a meeting of the Committee on Church Property. Lord Cave presided, and we got through our business in an hour. Then I went to the House of Lords, &amp; attended the debate on the Bishop of London's Bill for raising the age of consent to 17. The proceedings were not uninteresting, and I stayed to the division. There were never more than 70 peers present. I dined with Lord &amp; Lady S. [Scarbrough] quietly. The evening papers report the assassination of the Spanish premier, Senor Dato, and the sudden death of Lord Moulton. <hi rend="bold underline">Shall I speak in the debate on L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Gorell's<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> Bill tomorrow, or not? If I do, it will be to confess myself in favour of the Majority Report, and, therefore, against the policy of the Archbishops &amp; bishops, as expressed in the recent debates on L</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">Buckmaster's<persName xml:id="3687"></persName> Bill</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>To do this, is to earn the hostility of the whole "Catholick" party, and to become more isolated than ever. But there comes a time when one must take one's stand: &amp; I am not sure whether the subject of Divorce doesn't raise the real issue, on which a stand ought to be taken, as well as anything else. I shall prepare a speech, &amp; see whether there is occasion to deliver it.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>