<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ash Wednesday, February 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. There were 12 com<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi> including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. After breakfast I did correspondence, &amp; worked at the speech for Hartlepool. In the afternoon, we (<persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, &amp; I) walked to Binchester<placeName xml:id="107"></placeName>, &amp; looked at the Roman remains. After tea, I wrote letters, including one to Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName> about Belmont.</p>
         <p>The following books I have read through with interest:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. Rebuilding Britain by Sir Alfred Hopkinson, K.C.</p>
         <p>2. A History of British Socialism by M. Beer.</p>
         <p>3. In search of a Peaceful World, by Sir Charles W. Macara.</p>
         <p>4. Nationalisation of the Mines, by Frank Hodges<persName xml:id="5263"></persName>. </p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">People's Year Book</hi>" for 1920 has an excellent article on "<hi rend="underline">Labour in the New Era</hi> by <hi rend="doubleunderline">J. R. Clynes M.P. </hi>He ends with one threatening sentence, designed perhaps to reassure his comrades &amp; constituents, &amp; permit them to see that there is an iron hand under the velvet glove:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"In making, during the new era, the changes which would wipe away the grievances suffered during the old, we need show to the useless drones of the kingdom no mercy whatever. But we shall require to show every quality of statesmanship to prevent any change upon which we may be able to insist being a change for the worse."</p>
         </div>
         <p>Who are "<hi rend="underline">the drones of the kingdom</hi>"? No doubt 'the classes' can produce many specimens, but what of 'the masses' among whom the cult of "ca' canny" is running like a mill race?</p>
         </body></text></TEI>