<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"If the fire burns brightly and vigorously, it is no matter by what means it was at first kindled; there is the same force, and the same refreshing virtue in it, kindled by a spark from a flint, as if it were kindled by a beam from the sun."</p>
         <p>South. 1667</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is spoken to illustrate the argument that "external objects" may help or hinder devotion, &amp; therefore that due care should be taken in a reverent ordering of "the work of devotion". Yet it may fairly be urged that there may be perilous or difficult methods of kindling the fire, &amp; that these may be wisely discouraged and avoided. In all human activities the sensitiveness of the spirit is such that the material things by which it is immediately affected do subtly and secretly conform it in some sense to themselves. Coarse methods of raising devout sentiments will make men devout, but they will also coarsen the spirit, and make it unresponsive to higher appeals. There must be a congruity between the end and the method by which it is pursued. Sensationalism in religion is akin to dram&#8211;drinking. An immediate result is dearly purchased by a permanent injury. The sectaries and the Papists point the same moral. Both adopt short cuts to an excellent end. The brass band of the one, and the mariolatrous excesses of the other, exalt the feelings but corrupt the spirit, &amp; lower its standard.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[189]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The Epistle and Gospel bore directly on the discussion as to the value of reticence in the conflict with impurity, which occurred in the Diocesan Conference yesterday. As most of the members will communicate today, I cannot doubt that they will recall my words as they listen to the service.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I wrote to George</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. After an early lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Jarrow. There, in S. Peter's Church<placeName xml:id="105"></placeName>, I confirmed 160 candidates, of whom but 40 were boys. The atmosphere was asphyxiating, and the coughing incessant. Having heavily charged the parson to have the windows and doors opened that the atmosphere might be changed before Evensong, I went to the parson's hired house (There is no Vicarage) and had tea. The Mayor and Burgesses of Jarrow met me at the church door before service, and presented an address. The Church was crowded at Evensong. Clayton read the Lessons, and I preached the sermon. After having supper with the parson, we motored back to the Castle, where we arrived a little before 10.30 p.m. <hi rend="underline">The Rev</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> <hi rend="underline">T. H. Lilburn</hi>, Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, has been incumbent for about 8 years. He is unmarried, and was ordained as long ago as 1902. Thus he must be more than 40 years old. He spoke with affection of the parishioners: and the service gave me the impression that they returned the sentiment. On the whole I was pleased.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>