<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[356]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Still the glorious weather, but the grass is getting a brown look as if in drought, &amp; farmers pray for rain. Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I left by the early train, and travelled as far as York together. The train was very crowded, &amp; did not arrive until 2.45 p.m. I drove to Park Lane, where I learned that Lady. S. had been detained in Yorkshire by her daughter's indisposition. I arrived at <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lambeth</hi> about 3.30 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">There was a lively discussion on the subject whether it was advisable for the Archbishops to issue yet another appeal for prayer. I opposed: there was much hesitency among the bishops: finally we carried an ambiguous resolution</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>As I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Justice Sankey</hi><persName xml:id="3403"></persName>, &amp; had <hi rend="italic">some talk with him about the Strike. He says that he doesn't like nationalisation, but that the feeling of the miners is such that no other policy can provide a permanent settlement. Also he says that </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Smillie</hi><persName xml:id="4849"></persName><hi rend="italic"> is an honester man than Hodges<persName xml:id="5263"></persName>. Then I went on, and met </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Geoffrey Dawson</hi><persName xml:id="2709"></persName>. I dined in the Club, and, after dinner, wrote to Lady S. and to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. I took up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hunter Blair's</hi> biography of the late <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marquess of Bute</hi>, &amp; found it interesting. His "conversion" to Papistry seems to have been the effect of temperament reacting against environment in circumstances which suggested irresistibly that particular method of expressing its revolt. The Jesuits, of course, assisted, but were not the prime agents.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>