<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[298]</hi> ^[Note that HHH loses 20 page numbers]^</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The spell of wintry weather continues. There are from time to time essays at snowing, and more often showers of icy rain, driven by a high &amp; bitter wind. But the spring asserts itself in episodes of sunshine, and the aspect of the country, over which the verdant mantle of summer is clearly beginning to creep, helps the delusion that winter lies behind us. I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> communicated: one of the maids fainted: both William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> were absent. It was very cold.</p>
         <p>After lunch Wilson, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and I motored to Jarrow, and there, in the old church in which the Venerable Bede is said to have worshipped, I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ritson, the newly&#8211;appointed Rector. The church was filled with a congregation which included old Utrick Ritson<persName xml:id="3822"></persName> of Muggleswick. The singing of the choir struck me as unusually good, and generally I was pleased with the service. In the course of my sermon <hi rend="bold underline">I allowed myself to make a few observations on the strike</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>We had tea with the Curate (Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> F. C. Tymms) who seems to be working well. Canon Loxley was for a very long time, I think, 27 years, the Rector of Jarrow, and I was assured that his work had left lasting and excellent impressions on the people. There was nothing to indicate any such extremes of "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" as those which obtain in his present parish, S. Oswald's, Durham. Beyond the customary two candles on the re&#8211;table, I observed nothing suggestive of "Catholick" teaching.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>