<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[334]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The deep&#8211;rooted selfishness which forms the general character of the existing state of society is <hi rend="underline">so</hi> deeply rooted, only because the whole course of existing institutions tends to foster it; &amp; modern institutions in some respects more than ancient, <hi rend="underline">since the occasion on which the individual is called on to do anything for the public without receiving its pay, are far less frequent in modern life, than in the smaller commonwealths of antiquity</hi>.</p>
         <p>J. S. Mill "Autobiography" p. 233.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Perhaps it would be truer to say that modern selfishness finds expression rather in avoiding public duty than in the indulgence of private appetites. Christianity is the religion of personal self&#8211;respect, only indirectly and contingently the religion of citizenship. The religions of antiquity were essentially State religions. Moreover, ancient society reposed on the foundation of slavery, and that fact secured to the ancient democracies both the vices and the virtues of modern aristocracies. They ^too^ were sensual, cruel, and vain, but they ^too^ had a very high estimate of public duty, and were able to make great ventures and sacrifices for the State. And they had ^what modern aristocracies cannot have^ no notion of any greater Authority, whose claim might conflict with the State's, and whose right to obedience was none the less supreme.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[335]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Prime Minister,</p>
         <p>I take leave to beg you to consider very carefully the reasons for recommending to His Majesty for nomination to the Bpk. Of Salisbury the name of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> A. C. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName>, the Regius Professor of Divinity in the University of Oxford.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Headlam is now nearly 59 years old. He is a man of exceptional vigour, independence, &amp; unusual distinction. The Commentary on the Epistle to the Romans which he edited in conjunction with the late D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Sanday as long ago as 1895, has taken its place as a model of modern commentaries: and his Bampton Lectures on "The Doctrine of the Church and Christian Reunion", which he published as recently as 1920, will certainly hold rank as one of the most notable series of Lectures, which that famous trust has given to the public.</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Headlam has great experience in educational organization, &amp; is himself a very successful teacher. As Principal of King's College, London, from 1903 to 1916, he proved his power to govern &amp; lead. His attitude on the urgent matters of clerical training &amp; ecclesiastical finance is commending itself increasingly to considering Anglicans. It would be greatly advantageous to the Church of England if the See of Salisbury, associated as it must need be with the monumental learning of Bishop John Wordsworth, could be bestowed on a scholar of recognized distinction, such as D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Headlam certainly is.</p>
         <p>His ecclesiastical opinions are those of a liberal <hi rend="bold">[336] </hi>and learned High Churchman, whose sympathies are rather with the great Cambridge school represented by my illustrious predecessors, Bishops Lightfoot &amp; Westcott, than with the Tractarian movement. His relations with the Leaders of Nonconformity are cordial, and I cannot doubt that his appointment w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be warmly welcomed by the religious public as a whole.</p>
         <p>I have known D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Headlam for nearly 40 years, &amp; my deliberate judgement is that there are few men who possess the capacity of strong &amp; wise government in larger degree.</p>
         <p>The great anxiety which, at this difficult juncture, I must needs feel for the interests of the C. of E. must be my apology for addressing you with respect to the vacant Bpk.</p>
         <p>I am, my dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Prime Minister, with great respect &amp; regard, most faithfully yrs </p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p>We motored to Shotton, where I confirmed 44 candidates, and then went on to Horden, where I confirmed about 100. After service we returned to the Castle, where we arrived at 9.30 p.m., and found that the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Maurice Pryke<persName xml:id="438"></persName> had just arrived to spend the night. He thinks that he will be able to effect an exchange with the Rev. L. S. A. Wells, the Vicar of S. Aidan's, South Shields. I trust that, if he comes into this diocese, he will prove that it is possible to be both a "liberal" and a good parish priest.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>