<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[201]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, March 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The tears of a family may flow together like those little drops that compact the rainbow, and if they be placed with the same advantage towards Heaven as those are to the sun, they too have their splendor; and like that bow, while they unbend into seasonable showers, yet they promise, that there shall not be a second flood. But the dissoluteness of grief, the prodigality of sorrow, is neither to be indulged in a man's self, nor complyed with in others."</p>
         <p>Andrew Marvell. 1667</p>
         </div>
         <p>Beginning a ministry must be a solemn &amp; sternly important event in a man's life, more particularly in the circumstances which condition it in the case of an English clergyman: for he may well be stepping into the groove from which he will not emerge 'till Death's mild curfew shall from work assoil". If he be unfitly placed, "the square man in the round hole" as the vulgar problem states the too common spectacle, he must live on in a continuing friction with the people and the parish, growing always more stereotyped in his incapacitating faults, more discontented, more earth&#8211;bound by his chronic discontent. If, more happily, he be what is called "a good parish priest", liking his people, and liked by them, he will be drawn into the unconscious lethargy which is the shadow on parochial life. In neither event is the spiritual outlook altogether pleasant to reflect upon.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[202]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> celebrated in the Chapel. I sate in my stall, &amp; did not communicate. At 9.15 a.m. we started in the car for <hi rend="underline">Pittington</hi>, stopping in Durham to pick up <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, and arriving there about 10.15 a.m. in good time for the service. In spite of the rain, the church was crowded and most part of the congregation was masculine. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi> took Mattins, &amp; then I preached &amp; instituted <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hughes</hi> to the benefice. Then I celebrated the Holy Communion, and as many as 100 people communicated. Among them, as I was informed, were some prominent local Dissenters, who had indicated their desire to communicate, &amp; whose communicating in the circumstances I had approved. We all lunched with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pembertons</hi><persName xml:id="2837"><persName xml:id="2843"></persName></persName>. <hi rend="italic">Then <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; I proceeded to Lambton, &amp; had tea with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName></hi><hi rend="italic"> and Lady Anne<persName xml:id="3504"></persName>. There is a peculiar charm about that versatile &amp; evasive peer. I really like him, &amp; he likes me, but I doubt whether the possibility of making anything out of his spoiled &amp; shadowed life survives. He told me that he was 66: and he is evidently losing heart about himself. From Lambton we went on to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Newcastle</hi><hi rend="italic">, and there I preached to a </hi>very large congregation in the Cathedral. In view of the inclement weather such a concourse was encouraging. After service we went on to the Vicarage, &amp; had supper with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Newsom</hi><persName xml:id="923"></persName> and his wife. They both seem very contented &amp; happy. I should judge that he had established himself in the affection &amp; regard of the Newcastle citizens. We motored back to the Castle, picking up Clayton in Durham, &amp; got back about 11.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>