<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[353]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Trinity Sunday, May 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The morning was brilliant, but its promise was not sustained, and the evening was clouded and chilly. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, Wynne&#8211;Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName>, and I motored to Durham in good time for the Ordination in the Cathedral at 10 a.m. The service occupied 2 3/4 hours, and was very impressive. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne Willson</hi> preached the sermon. <hi rend="bold underline">I ordained one deacon &amp; 8 priests</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>We lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk; afterwards I saw the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> who was confined to bed with a return of jaundice. Then Knight, Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and I motored to Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. <hi rend="bold underline">Here I instituted, and inducted, Knight to the Rectory</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>There was a considerable congregation, and a suggestive service. After looking at the House &amp; Garden, we returned to Durham, leaving Knight in his parish. We had tea with the Hows<persName xml:id="3685"><persName xml:id="3686"></persName></persName> in the Bailey. <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Miss Christopher</hi><persName xml:id="3679"></persName><hi rend="italic"> was there. She says that the reason why the girls from her training college are unwilling to become teachers in church schools </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">is the inferiority of the school buildings, and that this circumstance can be truly alleged of the majority of church schools</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">She expresses great concern at the irreligious temper of most of the girl&#8211;students. Christianity seems suddenly to have lost attractiveness in the case of young women. This is rather an alarming phenomenon, &amp; presents a problem which </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">is hardly to be solved by offering ordination of women to the diaconate</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi><hi rend="italic">We returned to the Castle, arriving about 6 p.m.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>