<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sexagesima, Sunday, January 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I preached twice, first, in Westminster Abbey, and next, in <placeName xml:id="106">Westminster Chapel</placeName></hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>In the one I took for my subject that which January 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> suggested: &amp;, in the other, I delivered an old &amp; much revised sermon contrasting Ecclesiastes &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul. I <hi rend="underline">think</hi> that both sermons were effective: whether they were also edifying, I cannot conjecture. There was an immense congregation at the evening service: the great building was filled to its utmost capacity, &amp; it holds 2,500 people. I was much impressed in the singing. My sermon took just 30 minutes to deliver. Afterwards, there were several persons who waited to see me e.g. Sir R. Barron &amp; his wife: Lionel Box<persName xml:id="1664"></persName>: an excellent woman named Badham who was a relation of William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. Barnes &amp; his wife accompanied me to the Chapel. As we were leaving <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Brent</hi> accosted me. I lunched with Sir Albert Spicer, &amp; met a crowd of his children &amp; their wives. There came to supper Canon Hepher and Nicholson, the organist of the Abbey. I am afraid I did most of the talking, being excited &amp; over&#8211;wrought. <hi rend="bold underline">I should thing that the combination of the Abbey &amp; a Congregational Church on the same Sunday was unique in any clergyman's experience</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I think my preaching, which was altogether non&#8211;polemical, will probably do good. At least it will have the effect of making it more than ever difficult for our Episcopalian fanaticks to stop intercourse with Non&#8211;episcopalians.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>