<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[268]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Mayor, who is a Wesleyan, accompanied me to Christ Church at 8.15 a.m. On the way he asked me whether I should object to his receiving the Holy Communion. I expressed cordial approval of his doing so. He then <hi rend="bold underline">told me that he had been confirmed when a boy at Barnard Castle School, but that he was then a Nonconformist. Apparently he had been actuated by a purely religious impulse, and had not associated confirmation with any ecclesiastical obligations</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>We both communicated in Christ Church.</p>
         <p>At 10.30 a.m. the service in the Parish Church was attended by the Mayor &amp; Corporation in state, attended by a numerous company of citizens &amp; a great gathering of the local ragamuffins to witness the procession. It was an impressive service. I preached from S. Paul's phrase in Rom: xiii.6. "<hi rend="underline">ministers of God's service</hi>". After service we went across to the Sunderland Orphan Asylum, &amp; I made a short speech to the boys. Then we lunched in the Rectory  ̶ &#8211; the dolefullest household in the world. They are all mentally, physically, &amp; morally anoemic. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Pater told me that she had had mumps three times!</p>
         <p>After lunch we went to the Gray's School, where I dedicated a War&#8211;memorial and made a speech. The Mayor rejoined me, &amp; we drove to the Thompson Memorial Sunday School, where I addressed 7&#8211;800 men, all sectaries of some description or other. My subject was "The Relation of Christianity to Democracy", &amp; I spoke for 35 minutes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[269]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>It pleased me that they sang the National Anthem with much heartiness at the end. <hi rend="italic">The Mayor's observation amused me. "The subject', he said, 'bothers me a lot; &amp; I have been trying to think it out for a long time: &amp; when you were talking I got what I wanted. It was just the X ray men coming on the scene!"</hi></p>
         <p>I motored next to All Saints, where an odd creature named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Boddy</hi> (reputed to be a saint though verily a crank addicted to faith&#8211;healing &amp; "Pentecostal Conventions") has laboured for 36 years. I was favourably impressed by him, and by the choir &amp; congregation. The reverent behaviour of the choir boys in the vestry &amp; in the church was very noticeable. There was a mighty crowd, many being unable to gain admission. I preached again the Eastertide sermon which I used in S. Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName> on Easter Day. Then we returned to the Mayor's house, and had supper. After which we motored back to the Castle arriving a little before 11 p.m.</p>
         <p>The weather was most kindly all the day through, and all the functions (judged by the fallacious standards which we much needs apply) were "successful". But what was the real state of the case, &amp; how far they had a tolerable appearance in the Eyes of Him with reference to whom they were all professedly arranged, who can say? "<hi rend="underline">Take thought for things honourable in the eyes of all men</hi>" says S. Paul: &amp; his words must be read in the light of the disconcerting formula of Christ: "<hi rend="underline">Woe unto you when all men shall speak well of you</hi>"!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>