<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[357]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I read Plato before getting up. What amazing good stuff it is! It is certainly intelligible that those who have drunk of the old fountains find the new substitutes very poor indeed.</p>
         <p>I walked to Lambeth, and there continued all day. We spent much time over the Report on Lay Readers.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Ernest</hi><persName xml:id="636"></persName> and I entertained <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nickson</hi> at dinner in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and afterwards had much talk. It is said that the Bishop of Bath &amp; Wells is about to resign. In that event there will be no less than 3 bishopricks vacant  ̶  Salisbury, Bath &amp; Wells, and S Edmundsbury &amp; Ipswich. It is said also that the Archbishop is trying to bring back <hi rend="doubleunderline">Donaldson</hi><persName xml:id="5295"></persName> from Australia for the first of these. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearon</hi> was in the club. He looks very cheerful and well since his retirement from his archdeaconry. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burge</hi> tells me that he has written an informing memorandum on the subject of "induction".</p>
         <p>The weather, which had been close and sultry all day, inclined to rain in the evening. If we could get some days of steady soaking rain with a high temperature, the prospect for the harvest, which the drought has gravely darkened, would again brighten. A bad harvest w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be the coping stone of general disaster.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>