<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[332]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Fraternity, the old watchword of the revolutionist ever since 1789, has fallen out of sight. However little its spirit has ever ruled in France or elsewhere, it was respected as heralding a time when Liberty and Equality would bring friendliness &amp; peace in their train. This kind of Idealism has disappeared; it is material benefits that hold that place in the minds of the most recent advocates of change which spiritual progress held in the earlier generation. There is more hatred than love in the apostles of the Class War and proletarian rule."</p>
         <p>Lord Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName>. ii. 629.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Surely it should be the highest task of Education to bring this vanishing element of Idealism back to democracy. Hence the calamitous treason against the educational Ideal implied in the modern tendency to secularise the schools and universities. For Religion is the one form in which for the multitude morality can become adequately authoritative, and philosophy adequately simplified. But Religion cannot be simply identified with the creeds and catechisms of the Churches, nor may its place in the process of education be defined on the curricula and time&#8211;tables of the schools. It is a pervading spirit born of personal convictions, and expressed in personal influence.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[333]</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham arriving there at 11.30 a.m. I called on the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> who has just returned from Africa. Then I went to the Chapter House, &amp; instituted &amp; licensed a number of clergy. Then I had an interview with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Then I lunched with J. G. Wlison. Then we motored to Thornley, where I confirmed 76 candidates. After tea with the Vicar, I went to Cassop, and confirmed 85 candidates. Then we returned to the Castle, arriving about 9 p.m.</p>
         <p>The Vicar of Thornley is the Rev. H. Blackwood<persName xml:id="5292"></persName>, formerly a C. M. S. missionary. He was one of Boddy's curates at All Saints, Sunderland. He tells me that the Pentecostal meetings, where the speaking with tongues was practised, ceased at the outbreak of war. They had been largely attended by foreigners, mainly Swedes.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The Vicar of Cassop &amp; Quarrington (</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Rev. T. Wardle</hi><hi rend="italic">) is a strange creature, hirsute and absent&#8211;minded, with a dingy suggestion of being unwashed. He hustled &amp; perturbed the candidates shockingly, &amp; it would have pleased me much to order him back to his stall. However, the confirmation itself was not unpleasing. The Church was crowded, and outside the church was a small crowd. There were 2 or 3 police constables in attendance, &amp; there appears some expectation of a demonstration against me, but I noticed nothing unusual in anybody's demeanour.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>