<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[199]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Of all the spiritual tricks and legerdemain, by which men are apt to shift off their duty, and to impose upon their own souls, there is none so common, and of so fatal an import, as these two: the plea of a good intention, and the plea of a good will.</p>
         <p>South. A. D. 1685</p>
         </div>
         <p>I received a letter telling me that <hi rend="bold underline">Goudy died last Wednesday</hi> morning. I wrote at once to explain that it was not possible for me to attend the Funeral. This is a very regrettable circumstance, for my absence will not only displease the College, but it will do violence to my own feelings. For I had a genuine affection for Goudy, and he for me. The Warden<persName xml:id="228"></persName>, Doyle, Raleigh<persName xml:id="14"></persName>, Compton, Goudy &#8211; all the conspicuous figures of my life in All Souls &#8211; have passed, or are quickly passing away.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to K.<persName xml:id="62"></persName> [Knight] offering him the living of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;spring, of which the net value is reported to be &#x00A3;2061</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The outgoing Rector has been assigned a pension of &#x00A3;450. If two curates be maintained as would seem to be requisite, the new Rector will not receive more than about &#x00A3;1100, which, in view of the extensive house &amp; garden, is certainly not excessive. The population numbers about 10,000, almost altogether miners, reported to be rather conspicuously disloyal and hostile to all established things. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi></p>
         <p>The new President of U.S.A is master of a turgid bombastic style which must make him acceptable indeed as a true representative of his "great nation". Self laudation &amp; compliment are the hall&#8211;mark of genuine democracy, &amp; both are found to perfection in this "inaugural address" of President Harding, which fills the columns of today's papers. It is interesting to reflect that these same characteristicks mark our English sectaries, and render them so distasteful to every educated Anglican that the largest charity is tempted to acquiesce in separation. The Americans might be described as a nation of sectaries, and their mannerisms disclose the fact.</p>
         <p>The Vicar of Beamish sends me local newspapers containing a full report of my confirmation address of Monday last! This is rather disconcerting, for the addresses on such occasions are apt to preserve a substantial identity. How can it be otherwise since both theme and circumstance are identical?</p>
         <p>Ought I to make an effort to attend the debate in the H͜ of Lords on L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Gorell's<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> Divorce Bill?<note xml:id="530" n="1"></note> It is to be debated on the second reading next Thursday, when I am pledged to travel back from London in order to take the Confirmation at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Helen's, Auckland. If I <hi rend="underline">don't</hi> turn up on such an occasion, it is difficult to imagine any occasion which would secure my presence. On the other hand, I could only cancel my diocesan engagement by inflicting much disappointment.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>