<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[160]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, February 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I left Colonel Thomlinson<persName xml:id="5284"></persName> house at 9 a.m., &amp; arrived in the Castle at 10.15 a.m. Then I went through the letters with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>. In the afternoon I presided at a meeting of the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children in the Edgar Hall, and made a speech. Harold Knowling<persName xml:id="113"></persName> arrived in the car which he advises me to purchase. Eleanor, Viscountess Gort, with her husband &amp; son came to tea. The old lady has become very feeble. Harold took William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> with him to Newcastle in the car in order that he might get knowledge of its working, and he returned fully satisfied, but I think the limited capacity, and inconvenient arrangement of the car itself are insurmountable objections. The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> E. S. G. Wickham, a son of the former Dean of Lincoln, who is now one of the tutors at Knutsford, came to stay the night, &amp; L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName> came to dinner in order to get talk with him.</p>
         <p>The new (January) issue of the Church Quarterly Review is a strong number. There is a learned article on "Collegiate Churches" by Watson<persName xml:id="250"></persName> which seems to belittle unduly the position of the Bishop in the Durham Foundation. The Bishop is not only Diocesan, but also Patron and Visitor. The Statutes of Philip &amp; Mary give him considerable disciplinary authority, provide for his honorific reception when he visits the church, and give him access to the pulpit whenever he wishes to preach. His installation in the Abbot's Chair in the Chapter House can hardly be altogether without significance.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>