<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Quinquagesima, Sunday, February 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The collect and the Epistle emphasize the necessity of that most difficult yet most alluring grace of charity. If one were perfectly charitable, how would one think and speak about a grievous clerical scandal?</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 9.30 a.m. and motored to Seaton Carew, where we arrived in good time for the service at 10.55 a.m. I dedicated a clock, and a tablet, and then, after Mattins, preached. The church was crowded. Among the congregation were the Mayor &amp; Corporation of West Hartlepool. After service we all walked to the Memorial Cross, which was unveiled by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Robson</hi>. I made a short speech, &amp; then dedicated the memorial. Afterwards we lunched with the Vicar (Beavan), <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Thomlinson</hi><persName xml:id="5284"></persName> being of the party. After lunch I went to Christ Church Vicarage, &amp; had speech with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi><persName xml:id="3698"></persName> about that woeful man, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Duff</hi>. Then we motored back to the Castle, where we arrived shortly before 5 p.m.</p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kirsopp Lake's</hi><persName xml:id="3172"></persName> "<hi rend="underline">Landmarks in the History of Early Christianity</hi>". It is a brilliant piece of work, and wonderfully well&#8211;written, but it is terribly destructive. The author's treatment of Jesus Christ is not merely unorthodox (which might not greatly matter) but even aggressively un&#8211;Christian. For in no possible sense could such a Person as he indicates be the Object of worship, or the Lord of life. Yet Lake is an Anglican clergyman.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>