<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[238]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Day, March 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Christ "changed the Persion superstition into the Christian devotion; and, without the least approach to the idolatry of the former, made it henceforth the duty of all nations, Jews &amp; Gentiles, to worship the rising sun." (South)</p>
         </div>
         <p>This morning that aspect of Christianity, "the worship of the rising sun"  ̶  is indeed attractive, for all the world is bathed in brilliant sunshine. "<hi rend="underline">Jesus lives</hi>"  ̶  that central fact may suffice for our worship, and yet leave the criticks free, if they be still so minded, to dissect, weigh, compare, and adjudicate upon the scanty fragments of narrative which have come down to us. Who cared to make affidavits, and cross&#8211;examine witnesses, when He, '<hi rend="underline">the Sun of Righteousness</hi>' was shining full upon them? If only the criticks would remember this, if only they would look up from their study&#8211;tables, open their study&#8211;windows, and look out on the sun&#8211;bathed landscape, they would take a different tone, and use another manner of speaking! It is their tone &amp; manner that wound Christian hearts so deeply. How could they write in that way of One Whose presence was the central fact of their personal Religion, to Whom they turned naturally at every contingency of life, Who was felt to be nearer to them than their nearest &amp; dearest Friend? That is the question which inevitably proposes itself to my own mind, when I read <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lake's</hi> books. It is abhorrent to me to even seem to judge another man in these high concerns respecting which '<hi rend="underline">no man can give account for his brother</hi>': but I can't see how Christ can mean anything more to him than just one out of many.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[239]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. All my household save one Dissenting maid were present: but <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was in her bedroom with this hateful malady, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> was celebrating in a neighbouring church. I preached at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName>, and celebrated the Communion there. The congregation was not large, but it was very attentive. There were about 60 comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>. After lunch we (Clayton, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; I) motored in to Durham, where we attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and had tea with the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName> &#8211; I had some conversation with him about patronage. The Dean &amp; Chapter have 2 livings, vacant or about to become vacant viz. S. Stephen's, South Shields, which will be vacated by the Vicar's (Kearney) transference to New Seaham, and S. Oswald's, Durham, which must shortly by vacated by Canon Loxley's death. I suggested that Barclay<persName xml:id="5283"></persName> should be provided for, but he didn't seem attracted by the suggestion.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName></hi>.</p>
         <p>Two letters from Sunderland assure me that the Good Friday procession made a great impression on the people. One was from a Salvationist: it is written in the distinctive manner of the Army. But I am disposed to think that the writer is sincere. He speaks of "5000 men witnessing for Jesus" in the procession: and that was the figure which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Aglionby</hi><persName xml:id="5267"></persName> used. If there were as many as that, I think the procession must be fairly allowed to have been significant. But there is generally much exaggeration in such statements of numbers.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>