<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[323]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Pluto has failed, and must be sent back to the infernal regions from which too rashly he was called forth. The combined efforts of Taylor, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> failed to induce him to draw the lawn&#8211;cutter; &amp; when his refusal took the form of rearing &amp; general violence, the attempt to domesticate him was abandoned. This is a nuisance, and the grass grows ever!</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored after lunch to Washington, whereof the Rector is the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Cyril Lomax, who has held office since 1899, when he succeeded his father. He is unmarried, served as chaplain in the War, and seems a good clergyman. The parish is in the gift of the Bishop of Manchester, and is valuable but saddled with an expensive Rectory &amp; garden. Here I visited a Home of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Barnardo's, and addressed the children, about 100 in number. Then, after tea at the Rectory, I consecrated an addition to the local Cemetery, &amp; addressed the people in a biting wind. <hi rend="bold underline">The members of the Burial Board were introduced to me, &amp; I had a brisk &amp; very interesting talk with them on the burning subject of the Strike. They were nearly all impenitent strikers, and defended themselves with energy. But I talked frankly to them, and we parted in good friendship</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then I confirmed more than 150 candidates in the parish church. This is a poor modern structure which replaced a Norman church demolished in 1830! We returned to the Castle after the Confirmation, and arrived about 10 p.m. I noted great numbers of idling miners everywhere.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>