<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[117]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Indeed there are well disposed persons, who much want to be admonished, how dangerous a thing it is, to discountenance what is good, because it is not better: and hinder what they approve, by raising prejudices against some under&#8211;part of it."</p>
         <p>Bishop Butler Feb: 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1739.</p>
         </div>
         <p>So <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler</hi> said with direct reference to the case of Foreign Missions. If "Christianity is very particularly to be considered as a trust, deposited with us in behalf of others, in behalf of mankind, as well as for our own instruction", then a <hi rend="underline">prima facie</hi> case for supporting Foreign Missions exists. Indeed, on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler's</hi> assumptions, the case is quite irresistible; but his assumptions are alarmingly remote from modern modes of thinking. Certainly they can only be accepted by a considering &amp; educated Christian of today with very large modifications, explanations, and reservations. In effect, we defend missions now for their occasionally excellent by&#8211;products, rather than for their avowed purpose. As to this last, we are no longer in any real anxiety as to the eternal future of non&#8211;Christians, &amp; we set little store by the apocalyptic scheme of the Final Consummation: but we see that our mere presence &amp; the process of our government are destroying non&#8211;Christian religions &amp; the moralities thereto annexed, and we think that we ought to offer as a substitute the Religion &amp; Ethics of Western Civilisation.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>