<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[318]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Rogation Sunday, May 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A gloriously beautiful day. Under a cloudless sky, with the morning sun shining upon a newly&#8211;born world, this beautiful place looked fair indeed. I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. using the Cosin plate. Both the Archbishop of Upsala<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> and William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated. In the interval before break<hi rend="bold underline">fast S&#x00F6;derblom and I walked in the garden, &amp; talked about the Unity of Christendom</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After breakfast, he went to preach in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's Church<placeName xml:id="108"></placeName>, and I set to work on a speech for tonight's meeting.</p>
         <p>I typed an address on slips of paper, which I might read from my hand (there will probably be no desk!).</p>
         <p>After a few preliminary observations about myself, &amp; expressing sympathy for the unemployed, I go on to consider the present situation of the country, too serious for mutual division. <hi rend="bold underline">The Miners think too little of the community, perhaps his isolation makes it difficult for him to realize the effect of his conduct on others. The "Triple Alliance" only 1/7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> of the people. The interests at stake are vital.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">̶  the Starvation of Great Britain. Strike = a Blockade from Within. The importance of coal. What are the causes of the crisis? Both General and Particular. General causes all summed up in consequences of the Great War. Particular causes are 1) Economic (2) Moral. "preternatural suspicion". Failure of the Strike negociations raises some grave questions. I end with some general observations, bringing the subject back to religion: and my last sentences are more or less hopeful.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[319]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop S&#x00F6;derblom</hi> accompanied me in the Car to West Hartlepool. There he was met by the Swedish chaplain, and carried off to preach to the Swedish sailors who had gathered from such ships as happened to be in port. I preached to a very large congregation in Christ Church, and then (together with the Archbishop who rejoined us) was escorted by a fine company of the Boys Brigade under the indefatigable <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Morison</hi> to the Empire Theatre, which was crowded with an audience mostly composed of men. <hi rend="bold underline">A number of employers sate on my right hand, and an equal number of workmen on my left</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonald</hi><persName xml:id="3698"></persName> presided. I spoke for 40 minutes, and delivered with extemporaneous embellishments the speech that I had prepared earlier in the day. It had been expected that there would be interruption from a body of "Communists" but they made no sign, and the meeting went off without any untoward incident. <hi rend="bold underline">I think the audience was impressed, though perhaps a little surprized at the absence of the usual cant and compliment</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The '<hi rend="underline">Hartlepool Employment Committee</hi>', which had organised the meeting, asked permission to print the speech as a pamphlet, and I left them my notes for the purpose. We had supper with the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Macdonalds</hi>, and then motored back to the Castle, where we arrived about midnight. I hope rather than expect or believe that my words will be of public service!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>