<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Sure when Religion did itself embark<hi rend="bold">,</hi></p>
         <p>And from the East would Westward steer its ark,</p>
         <p>It struck, and splitting on this unknown ground,</p>
         <p>Each one thence pillag'd the first piece he found:</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Hence Amsterdam, Turk&#8211;Christian&#8211;Pagan&#8211;Jew.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Staple of sects, and mint of schisme grew;</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">That bank of conscience, where not one so strange</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Opinion but finds credit, and exchange.</hi></p>
         <p>In vain for Catholicks ourselves we bear;</p>
         <p>The universal church is only there.</p>
         <p>Andrew Marvell "The Character of Holland" 1672</p>
         </div>
         <p>This suggests that Marvell held a mean opinion of sectaries. He was a Puritan conformist, but as the personal friend of Milton, he would have regarded ecclesiastical systems with little respect. On the other hand, he was a man of affairs, &amp; looked with dislike on the anarchic fervours of sectarianism. Moreover he wrote at a time when everything Dutch was odious in English eyes, and sectarianism had found its home in Amsterdam for more than a century. His satire "The character of Holland" is sufficiently savage:</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>'Holland, that scarce deserves the name of land,</p>
         <p>As but th' offscouring of the British sand,</p>
         <p>And so much earth as was contributed</p>
         <p>By English pilots when they heav'd the lead.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham, where I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Gough to the Rectory of Castle Eden, and licensed a curate. Then I called on Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName>, &amp; discussed some questions about the deacon's examinations. Then I lunched pleasantly with J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>; Captain Apperley<persName xml:id="2918"></persName> was there. His old raven poisoned itself by feeding on tit&#8211;bits from a dung&#8211;heap, but he has secured another. After lunch I went to my room at the Castle, and wrote letters. At 4 p.m. Major Slovach, the new organising secretary of C.L.B.<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> [Church Lads Brigade] came to see me, in order to discuss plans for developing that organisation in the diocese. He expressed a desire to be ordained with the understanding that he should devote himself to C.L.B. work. He is 26 years old, was training as a doctor when the war broke out, served in Gallipoli &amp; was invalided home, and now has undertaken C.L.B. He seems intelligent, sincere, and eager. Finally he made a dreadful allegation against one of the clergy, which disconcerted &amp; dismayed me. I do not yet see what my duty requires me to do.</p>
         <p>At 5.20 p.m. we left Durham, and motored to South Shields, where I confirmed about 100 candidates in S. Stephen's Church. After a brief visit to the Vicarage, where several of the clergy had gathered to meet me, we returned to Auckland, arriving at the Castle about 10.45 p.m. After supper I wrote to Col Bowes asking him to see me on Saturday to talk over Major Slovach's matter.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>