<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Feast of the Conversion of S</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold"> Paul, January 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The consecration of William Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> to be Bishop of Manchester took place in the Choir of York Minster</hi>. There was a very large gathering of Bishops. The Archbishop was vested in a white cope, and performed his central function with characteristic dignity. I read the Gospel, and the Dean of York the Epistle. The last was contrary to the Rubrick, and the Archbishop "made a public apology" to the Bishop of Wakefield, (who by right of seniority ought to have been Epistler,) after the service in the vestry. "<hi rend="underline">My dear Archbishop</hi>", I observed, "<hi rend="underline">the precedent of public apologies in episcopal gatherings should not be lightly set</hi>." The Bishop–elect was presented by the Bishops of Ripon and Southwark. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dick Sheppard</hi> preached the sermon, of which I could hear no more than disconnected sentences, as he drops his voice. <hi rend="bold underline">I could not avoid the reflection that the service indicated the completeness of the victory of Tractarianism</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The hymn appointed to be sung during the communion of the clergy was inspired by the Roman view of the Real Presence: &amp; the Archbishop's manner of reading the Consecration Prayer w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have shocked an old–fashioned Anglican. Altogether it was a noble and significant ceremony. <hi rend="bold underline">It was observed that Archbishop Temple had consecrated Lang, &amp; now Archbishop Lang had consecrated Temple</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The latter was said to be wearing his father's chimere and pectoral cross.</p>
         <p>I lunched alone with the Archbishop at Bishopthorpe, &amp; consulted <hi rend="bold">[133]</hi> him about my scheme for creating a Theological Faculty in Durham. He expressed himself favourably, &amp; thought that the right procedure w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be for me to introduce a Bill into Parliament. It w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> on many grounds be undesirable that the "National Assembly" should handle a subject of that kind.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Christian Caröe<persName xml:id="1951"></persName> appeared at the service, &amp; lunched at the Deanery. <hi rend="bold underline">I always have a sharp attack of medievalism when clerical females hang about the Bishops at a consecration</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I returned to the Hotel, and had an interview there with the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> W. Longdon, the organising secretary of the C.E.M.S.<orgName xml:id="207"></orgName>, in order that he might explain to me the methods, constitution, and actual value of the society. He so far succeeded that I told him I w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> bless the society in my diocese, &amp; commend it to the clergy. Then I had half an hour's talk with old Canon Scott, who then went off to Manchester.</p>
         <p>The "Yorkshire Post" reports a very sensible speech of the Bishop of Ripon on the Temperance Question.</p>
         <p>I dined in the Hotel with no other company (though the room was fairly filled with hotel visitors) than Cicero's Letters to Atticus, of which a volume from the Loeb classics had accompanied me from Durham. I went into the writing room, &amp; wrote a letter to Ella, before going to my bedroom. I retired early, &amp; enjoyed the luxury of reading in bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>