<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to the station for the early train, and I travelled very comfortably to London. From Darlington <hi rend="bold underline">I had the company of Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> who was starting for Uganda</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>At King's Cross I secured a taxi after some delay, and proceeded to the Club<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I deposited my bags. Then I went to the Hairdresser, &amp; had my hair cut. Returning to the Club, I found Buckle<persName xml:id="322"></persName>, &amp; had some talk with him. Then I carried my bags to 21 Park Lane, where I had tea, <hi rend="bold underline">&amp; received a note from Lady S. [Scarbrough] enclosing a latch key</hi>. There was a pleasant company at dinner, viz. Lady Lytton, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowther, Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Davies, the American Ambassador's wife., &amp; a son&#8211;in&#8211;law with <hi rend="underline">his</hi> wife, also Hadow<persName xml:id="3178"></persName>. I had a good deal of talk with Lady Lytton. <hi rend="bold underline">She spoke with enthusiasm about the Prince of Wales</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Haldane seemed to think that there would be a disposition in the House of Lords to regard any measure affecting the Dean and Chapter of Durham as properly belonging to the National Assembly. <hi rend="underline">There</hi>, however, I fear that my scheme for transforming the capitular foundation into an endowed Theological Faculty would be resented, partly, as alienating ecclesiastical property to academic uses, and, partly, as withdrawing a substantial amount from the divisible sum which could be allocated to the increase of clerical stipends. I must talk this over with the Archbishop.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>