<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[218]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Why there is, 'tis true, a winged sort of elephant, hath a peculiar trunk too like the other, is not so docile and good&#8211;natured, but impudent, flying in every man's face, and sanguinary, thirsting always after blood: and, as if it were some considerable wild beast, makes a terrible buzze; but in conclusion 'tis a pitiful, giddy, blind, troublesome insect, ingendered in a night's time in every marish, can but run a pore thorow and give but a skinne&#8211;wound, &amp; the least touch of a man's finger will crush it." ("The Divine in Mode" p.16).</p>
         </div>
         <p>This suggests the famous passage in <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burke</hi>, &amp; is certainly not inferior. On his visits to Holland, Sweden, &amp; Spain <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marvell</hi> had evidently made acquaintance with mosquitoes.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at noon, and motored to Durham, where I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, and then lunched with the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName>. Then I presided over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference Committee. After having tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk, we motored to Sunderland, and there I confirmed 112 persons in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Ignatius's Church. This was a dignified and well&#8211;arranged service. Before the Benediction I gave badges &amp; administered pledges to the members of the C.E.M.S.<orgName xml:id="207"></orgName> We had supper with Canon Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> &amp; his family very pleasantly, and then motored back to the Castle in bright moonlight, arriving about 11.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>