<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[324]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel. After lunch I motored to Greenside, where the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> A. D. S. Smith has been Vicar since 1917. This is one of the parishes that has been cut out of Ryton, and now contains a population of 9000 souls, and an electoral roll of about 300. Here I confirmed 113 candidates. After the service I had an interview with the Vice&#8211;chairman and the secretary of the Parochial Church Council of Hedgefield. They wanted me to remove their parson, the Rev. T. W. Hanson<persName xml:id="5291"></persName>, whom they accuse of totally neglecting his pastoral duties. He is also in debt, &amp; suspected of drunkenness! But he is married to an incompetent wife and is the father of 4 children, &amp; on these counts is held entitled to parochial sympathy. The situation is really difficult, for there is nothing tangible &amp; capable of proof, which could provide a foundation for episcopal action. After tea with the Vicar of Greenside, I motored to Whickham, where the Rector (Rev: C. E. Little) received me. Here I confirmed more than 200 candidates in the parish church, which was crowded to excess. The church is Norman, but has suffered many things in modern times. After service Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I had dinner with Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Thompson, whose house is hard by the church. Then we returned home, arriving at the castle a quarter before midnight. I have confirmed about 700 candidates in the last four days. Relatively to the population the number is petty enough, but it is not wholly insignificant.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[325]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"As on a rocky sea&#8211;shore one can tell how far the tide has fallen by observing how many limpets adhering to the rocks are to be seen above the level of the water, so the healthiness of public life may be judged by seeing how many rich men or their agents are found slipping into the halls of a legislature and approaching persons who can bring political influence to bear."</p>
         <p>Lord Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName> ii. 525</p>
         </div>
         <p>Miss Eleanor Rathbone<persName xml:id="5073"></persName> has an important letter in the "Times" of yesterday. It is headed, "<hi rend="underline">The Standard of Life  ̶</hi> <hi rend="underline">Wages &amp; Family Allowances. An Australian Scheme</hi>", and it is deservedly made the subject of a leader. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leslie Scott</hi><persName xml:id="4846"></persName> has a long letter in today's issue of the "Times" headed, "<hi rend="underline">The coal mines. Relation of Wages to Output. Political Demands</hi>". He points out that "contrary to the erroneous impression widely held by miners and others, the Government never at any time pledged itself to nationalize the mines should the Commission so recommend". He quotes <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bonar Law's</hi> actual words in the House on March 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1919: "That (i.e. nationalization) is a subject, which can never be decided by any section, however important it may be, of the nation, but must be decided by the Parliament which represents the community". On Feb: 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1921 Nationalization of the Mines was rejected in the House of Commons by 329 to 64. It is interesting to compare Sidney Webb's account of the Great Betrayal.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>