<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[271]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'Observe the cobra; however often it may slough its skin, it remains a cobra. In the same way, a sinner, even though he leaves his body, will remain a sinner in the next world. Character does not change with death.'</p>
         <p>The Sadhu. p.176.</p>
         </div>
         <p>A petition signed by a large number of persons, professedly communicants arrived from Wheatley Hill. <hi rend="bold underline">The complaints are partly the too&#8211;familiar ones about the parson's ceremonial vagaries, and partly concerned with his refusal to work the "Enabling Act"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The parson (Casey<persName xml:id="5150"></persName>) made himself notorious by audibly protesting in Durham Cathedral when D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett preached there on Welldon's<persName xml:id="114"></persName> invitation. He is reported to be (like so many of the more intractable Ritualists) an ex. Dissenting minister. I wrote to him inviting his "observations".</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">After lunch I went into the Park, and sate down on the grass with a set of pit lads, who were "kicking about" a football. We had a lively talk about the strike: &amp; again I was astonished at the extent and detail of their knowledge about their own grievances. They certainly have been amazingly well&#8211;coached by their leaders. I covenanted with them that I would show them the chapel &amp; Castle on Thursday at 3 p.m. It will be interesting to know if they keep tryst. </hi>That &amp; much else that is more important will turn on the issue of the conference in London.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>