<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[221]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>"<hi rend="doubleunderline">Young Vane</hi>" (1613&#8211;1662) was 8 years older than Marvell, &amp; sate for Hull in the "Short" and "Long" Parliaments. He was an intimate personal friend of Cromwell, with whom he subsequently quarrelled on political grounds. Hostility to a settled ministry and universal toleration were his two main religious principles, and it is plain enough that Marvell had much sympathy with both. </p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">James Harrington</hi> (1611&#8211;1678) was Marvell's senior by 10 years. "Although a republican in principle, he seems to have been attracted by Charles, whose death is said to have greatly shocked him." In 1656 he published the 'Oceana', the ms. of which was seized by Cromwell, &amp; restored thro' the intercession of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Claypoole.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>Sherwood came here from Ipswich in order to see me about Major S. He insists very strongly on the soundness of his character, and the saneness of his judgement; he scouts the suggestion that he may in good faith have exaggerated what took place. Major S. was also here: &amp; both stayed to lunch, and went with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; me as far as Durham on our way to Sunderland, where in S. Mark's Church, I confirmed about 70 candidates. We returned to the Castle after the service, arriving about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>The retirement of Bonar Law must needs be a great blow to the Government. It seems everywhere assumed that Austen Chamberlain will succeed to the leadership of the Unionist Party, &amp; to the office which B.L. was holding. This opens the way for a new man as Chancellor of the Exchequer.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>