<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[225]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, March 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>O God, forasmuch as Thou has willed that so great a burden of duty should come upon Thy servant, do Thou give to him the strength to bear it. Guide Thou his judgement, cleanse Thou his vision, quicken Thou his conscience, kindle Thou his affections, that, through the power of Thy Holy Spirit, he may not fail to carry out Thy Purpose, and serve Thy People, through Jesus Christ our Lord.</p>
         <p>Amen</p>
         <p>I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated, but, of course, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> was absent on her own unpleasant business &#8211; the old <hi rend="underline">mumpsimus</hi> with a vengeance! The Sunday post brought a series of unpleasant letters, and nothing in the smallest degree consolatory! I wrote to Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>, Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>, and Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName>. In the afternoon I confirmed 165 candidates at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew's<placeName xml:id="108"></placeName>. There was a considerable congregation. At Evensong I preached in S. Andrew's. Rather to my surprise the church was no more than four fifths full. I had assumed that there would be a great crowd! Probably the large congregation in the afternoon implied that many came then at the expense of their attendance at Evensong. I preached an old sermon on 'Repentance', originally composed for Westminster Abbey some 10 years ago. It seemed to be fairly suitable in view of the Easter Communion. William attended with the car, and brought me back to the Castle shortly after 8 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>