<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[174]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Lent, February 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"It is not the truth of an assertion, but the skill of the disputant, that keeps off a baffle; not the justness of a cause, but the valour of the soldiers, that must win the field: when a learned Paul was converted, &amp; understood the ministry, it stopped the mouths of those that said, None but poor weak fishermen preached Christianity; &amp; so his learning silenced the scandal, as well as strengthened the church."</p>
         <p>South. "Religion the best reason of state"</p>
         </div>
         <p>Against this set the "learned Paul's "own words: "<hi rend="underline">Not many wise after the flesh, not many mighty, not many noble are called: but God chose the foolish things of the world that he might put to shame them that are wise: &amp; God chose the weak things of the world, that he might put to shame the things that are strong: &amp; the base things of the world, &amp; the things that are despised did God choose, yea, &amp; the things that are not, that he might bring to nought the things that are: that no flesh should glory before God</hi>". South and Bunyan were contemporaries: which was the greater spiritual force? Which has been the most precious legacy, South's "Sermons", or Bunyan's "Pilgrim's Progress'? Which was the best result of a Christian ministry, Charles II and his courtiers, or the persecuted sectaries whom they jeered at and oppressed? Yet my mind moves more naturally in South's orbit, than in Bunyan's, and I won't ordain illiterate men, however ardent!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[175]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. The morning was spent in my study, where I prepared notes for an address on "Democracy and Christianity" which (rather foolishly) I promised to give at Trimdon Grange.</p>
         <p>After lunch, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Trimdon Grange; where I gave my address to a church full of men. The Vicar (a mean&#8211;looking little, pallid, pinched man named Rudd) told me that the building could accommodate 260 persons: but there were but 14 rows of 11 persons, 5 on one side of the gangway, and 6 on the other. This accounts for 154, and there may have been a few more in addition together with 15 in the Choir. The total congregation cannot have reached 200. <hi rend="bold underline">But with a strange folly, the clergy are everywhere given to the practice of self&#8211;cheating in the matter of church&#8211;attendance. They always exaggerate generally very grossly</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After service I was introduced in the Vestry to divers members of the Congregation. Then we had tea in the Vicar's house, &amp; returned to the Castle by way of Sedgefield.</p>
         <p>The "Modern Churchman" announces that Kirsopp Lake is to expound his heresies to the members of the Churchmen's Union<orgName xml:id="38"></orgName>, when they meet for their annual conference in Girton College next August. It is quite clear to me that his version of Jesus Christ provides no sufficient basis for a discipleship, but how to formulate its rejection without doing violence to the principles of "Liberalism" is not easy to discover.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>