<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[166]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, February 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I say nothing of friendships which endure unbroken to old age having acquired the binding force of a sacred duty: for initiation in the same studies has all the sanctity of initiation in the same mysteries of religions."</p>
         <p>Mitto amictcias, quoe ad senectutem usque firmissime durant religiosa quadam necessitudine imbutae. Neque enim est sanctius &#x00FC;sdem quam studiis initiari."</p>
         <p>Quintilian I.ii.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Quintilian</hi> offers the forming of friendships between fellow&#8211;students as one of the reasons why education at school is preferable to education at home. I agree with him as to the fact, and as to its value.</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>, Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName>, &amp; Harrison were also there. At 2.30 p.m. I presided at the meeting of the Diocesan Finance Board, which sate for two hours. Then I had tea with the Cruickshanks<persName xml:id="1898"><persName xml:id="2663"></persName></persName>, and afterwards walked to the Townhall. Here I distributed prizes &amp; certificates to the boys of the Johnson school, &amp; made a speech. The Hall was very crowded with boys &amp; parents. Finally, I joined the car in the College, &amp; motored back to the Castle.</p>
         <p>I received an intimation from Vicary Gibbs<persName xml:id="5288"></persName> that I had been elected a member of "Nobody's Club", together with 2 vols. containing biographical notices of the members from 1800 to 1902.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>