<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[272]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The question of the permanence of democracy resolves itself into the question of whether mankind is growing in wisdom and virtue, and with that comes the question of what Religion will be in the future, since it has been for the finer and more sensitive spirits the motive power behind Morality.</p>
         <p>Bryce<persName xml:id="389"></persName>. Ii. 666</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and presided at a meeting of the Finance Board. After having tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk, I returned to the Castle. I attended a meeting in the Town Hall convened in advocacy of the League of Nations. The other speaker, beside myself, was Peter Lee<persName xml:id="5212"></persName>, the chairman of the Durham County Council. He is a tall, fine&#8211;looking man, with an intelligent countenance, a good speaker but evidently uneducated. He expressed himself in a religious manner, &amp; would seem to be all but a Pacifist. The Town Hall was completely filled, &amp; 146 persons joined the "League of Nations" Association. I spoke for 35 minutes. <hi rend="italic bold underline">It is reported in the evening papers that the "Triple Alliance" is going to strike at 10 p.m. on Friday evening</hi><hi rend="italic">. I take the impression that the Leaders are gambling on the chance that the threat will suffice to force the Government to surrender, &amp; that nothing would disconcert them more than to be forced to carry out their brave threat.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>