<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote cheques for &#x00A3;450 and &#x00A3;100 for the Wolesley car, and the new body with which it is to be equipped, &amp; sent them to Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName>. Then I revised, &amp; partly rewrote, my sermon for this afternoon. After lunch we motored to Sedgefield, and lunched with the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="3688"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Derry. Colonel Vaux<persName xml:id="4022"></persName> and his wife were there. At 3 p.m. there was service in the Parish Church, when I preached to a crowded congregation. After service the choir &amp; clergy followed by the people proceeded to the Memorial Cross which had been erected in the churchyard. Here I read the prayers of dedication, and Colonel Vaux gave a short address. Then everything was concluded with the Benediction. Unfortunately the rain was falling briskly all the time, and the effect on my episcopal robes was not impressive. I was surprised at the steadiness with which the considerable concourse of people endured the weather. After tea at the Rectory we returned to the Castle, where I went through the correspondence with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>.</p>
         <p>Sedgefield Church is one of the finest and most interesting parish churches in my diocese. It contains remarkably fine choir&#8211;screen, stalls, and panelling of the Restoration period, when the Rectory was held by the famous Granville<persName xml:id="3796"></persName>, Dean of Durham, and son&#8211;in&#8211;law of Bishop Cosin, from whom, it would appear, he acquired that passion for elaborate wood&#8211;carving which is gloriously disclosed in the Cathedral &amp; Castle of Durham, &amp; in Auckland.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>