<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[165]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I resolved, in the course of dressing, that I would devote the time before breakfast <hi rend="bold underline">to the Book on Reunion to which I am practically pledged by way of a reply to the essay of the three Bishops</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The first thing was to collect the indispensable materials for giving a true account of the actual proceedings in the Conference with a view of making clear (&#x3B1;) how far there was genuine agreement among the bishops, (&#x3B2;) what my own course has been throughout.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Darlington, and lunched with two old maids named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Forster</hi>. Then I addressed a meeting of men in the Town Council Chamber convened in support of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Agnes Home, a Preventive &amp; Rescue Agency, which has become so embarrassed financially, as to be threatened with extinction. From this meeting I went on to a meeting mainly attended by women, which had been gathered in the same interest. Here I made another speech. Then, after having tea with the before mentioned old&#8211;maids, we returned to the Castle, our journey being cheered by a sunset of rare beauty.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" contains a long letter on the Irish situation written by Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName>. It includes a very outspoken denunciation of the Roman Catholic Church in Ireland for its condonation of murder. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cardinal Bourne</hi> has re&#8211;issued Manning's pronouncement against the crimes of the Fenians. But his action is quite obviously dictated by Protestant public opinion.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>