<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"O Lord, I beseech Thee, make me to remember how much more than other men I have need to call upon Thee. My charge is great, &amp; my strength little: O give grace to come often before Thee, &amp; ask that help, which Thou are readier to give than I to ask: through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen. </p>
         <p>Laud.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A hostile letter in response to my Message to the Miners arrived</hi>. It is conceived in the heavily sarcastic vein, &amp; raises the old party cries to provoke prejudice. Its only <hi rend="underline">interest</hi> lies in the fact that it represents the line of commentary which is being adopted by the opponents of peace. For their purpose, I doubt not, that line is well chosen. </p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Butler's</hi> sermon before the House of Lords in Westminster Abbey on Jan. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1741, and decided to preach on the same text there on Jan. 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1921. <hi rend="bold">"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">Not using your freedom as a cloak of wickedness, but as bondservants of God</hi><hi rend="bold">".</hi></p>
         <p>After walking in the Park for an hour, I wrote my letters, and also paid some accounts including &#x00A3;125:4:4 for paperhanging &amp;c &amp;c in the Castle. The cost of my incoming steadily mounts. </p>
         <p>Rather to my surprise the "Times" has a leading article strongly supporting the suggested appointment of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Reading</hi><persName xml:id="5276"></persName> as Viceroy of India. Surely it is not merely "anti&#8211;Semite" prejudice that makes the notion of Jew in that great place repugnant to me. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>