<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[303]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Last night I was aroused by a knocking at my bed&#8211;room door. It was the maid with a telegram which had been sent on from Auckland with an answer pre&#8211;paid. The telegram was from the sub&#8211;Dean, &amp; ran thus:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The King would be very glad if you could preach at the ten oclock service Buckingham Palace Sunday as well as at Chapel Royal. is this possible?"</p>
         </div>
         <p>After breakfast I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; answered to the effect that the King's command should be obeyed. I wrote to Colin Kennedy<persName xml:id="2432"></persName>, and then walked to Westminster, where I called on Lea, &amp; spent an hour over my income&#8211;tax returns. Then <hi rend="bold underline">I called on Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, &amp; learned to my satisfaction that he held with Headlam's<persName xml:id="552"></persName> criticism of Lake's book</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After lunching at the Athenaeum, I went to 98 Park Street, and saw M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray<persName xml:id="666"></persName>. To my surprise Buff<persName xml:id="836"></persName>, &amp; her husband were there, having returned from Borneo. I walked back to the Club, &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, and Headlam. The weather became almost oppressively warm. <hi rend="bold underline">I called on the Sub&#8211;Dean. He told me that the King liked extempore sermons, &amp; that he was becoming deaf. I said that there doubtless [sic] preachers enough who would gratify H.M. by their unpremeditated effusions, but that I was not one of them</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>The Prime Minister was reported to have convened a meeting of the Mine&#8211;owners &amp; the Miners this afternoon.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>