<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[349]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I was called at 6.45 a.m., breakfasted in my room, caught the 8.17 a.m. train, and reached Darlington at 11.5 a.m. There the car met me &amp; carried me to the Castle.</p>
         <p>I had an interview with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Francis</hi>, the Vicar of New Shildon, a little, nervous, voluble man who fails to ^win^ confidence. He has grievances against his curate, infinitely petty &amp; immensely plausible. He stayed to lunch, &amp;, hardly had he vanished from the scene, before <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Warth</hi>, the curate, appeared, &amp; told his story, equally plausible &amp; vastly more adequate. I counselled reconciliation, &amp; a continuance of relations!</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> went to Wallsend to fetch the Wolesley car, and had instructions to be back in good time to take me to West Auckland, where I was pledged to dedicate a war memorial. But he never turned up! I was thrown into the most painful anxieties. What but an accident could have hindered him? And what might not an accident involve for him, &amp; for the car? I never knew how much I loved the boy before! However I had to keep tryst: so I drove out in a hired "growler", &amp; fulfilled my duty. When I reached the Castle, I was informed to my infinite relief that William &amp; the car had arrived safely. He had been detained at Wallsend, where the finishing touches were being put on the car.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>