<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[182]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, February 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">May the words of my lips, and the meditations of my heart, be always acceptable in Thy sight, O Lord, my Strength and my Redeemer</hi>!"&#8211;that is the aspiration with which my mind is filled on the first occasion of attendance in the Upper House of the Northern Convocation. In my present position, and in the present juncture of affairs, I can't afford to make mistakes, even in a Convocation speech.</p>
         <p>The proceedings in the Upper House of the Northern Convocation were neither impressive nor exciting. We were only 10 bishops including the President, so that "impressiveness" was out of the question. Half the morning was spent in paying compliments to Bishops Moule and Knox. I kept silence yea, even from good words, because, if I had spoken, I could not have avoided some observations on the pitiable weakness of my predecessor's action as Bishop. Then Lang introduced the motion endorsing the Lambeth resolution authorising Bishops to permit Nonconformists occasionally to preach in the Churches. On this I made a speech, in the course of which I said some things that needed saying about the Lambeth Appeal. Temple<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> made a short speech, and the motion was agreed to without a division. Then followed the Bishop of Chester with a motion in favour of the revival of the Order of Deaconesses. I opposed in a speech which reviewed the Lambeth Resolutions rather severely. Of course, when the vote was taken, I was in a minority of one!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Sheffield moved for a Committee on "Synods", and I acquiesced, but made a short gibing speech on the subject, which provoked some hilarity, though there was a serious purpose in what I said. Then we returned to Bishopthorpe. I fear it is impossible to feel sure that my matutinal reflections have been justified by any particular wisdom in my utterances, and I should not be surprized to discover that I <hi rend="underline">have</hi> made a mistake in speaking at all.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" has a descriptive article on the Northern Convocation. It pays particular attention to the Bishops of Durham &amp; Manchester, whom it describes as oratorical prize&#8211;fighters! There is, perhaps, an impression that the recent episcopal appointments have had the effect of making the Upper House of York more personally interesting than that of Canterbury. The Dean of York seemed to think that the change of <hi rend="underline">personnel</hi> in the Northern Province justified a claim to confidence in the Bishops which could not have been reasonably or hopefully urged in recent years. Perhaps this is the case: and the circumstance that the Lower House agreed (with but 4 dissentients) to approve the Lambeth Resolution respecting the preaching of Nonconformists in the parish churches, may be an evidence that it is the case. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> is a good chairman, and a dignified President. He has acquired the art of sonorous non&#8211;committal speech which in his Chair is invaluable &amp; all but indispensable.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>