<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[327]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A letter arrived from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, dated April 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> from Port Said. It had evidently been immersed in the sea. He asks me to write to S.S. Eurypylus c/o Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Booth &amp; C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi>, 17 Battery Place, New York, U.S.A. and mentions that his friend, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bryson, would be staying in Durham, &amp; would call on me.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in sermon&#8211;preparation. Slovach came to lunch. I promised to draft a letter of appeal for the C.L.B.<orgName xml:id="45"></orgName> [Church Lads Brigade] and gave him ten guineas as my own contribution. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Ushaw Moor, where I dedicated a war memorial, and gave an address. The Hon. Joseph Pease<persName xml:id="2216"></persName> unveiled the memorial, and said a few words very effectively. After this function we motored to Collierley, where I confirmed 55 candidates. The Vicar (Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. Maxwell) is in the last stage of decrepitude, &amp; quite incompetent for his duties. Both the churchwardens were eager to impress me with the necessity of his removal. I doubt, however, whether he is sane enough to resign. The curate (Rev. F. Ferguson) was very anxious to show that he was the main upholding pillar of the church in those parts, and that he was refusing livings out of loyalty to his present duties. But I did not feel much impressed! We returned to the Castle after service, arriving about 8.15 p.m. After dinner we went through the correspondence, which was rather more exacting than usual.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>