<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[113]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Miners' Association at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring sends me a strongly worded recommendation of the Vicar of Escombe for the vacant Rectory. It is clear to me that the gentleman himself is not far removed from this proceeding. I returned a civil answer</hi> saying that I would fully weigh what they said, that the appointment was a very important one, &amp; that I would do my best to find a really suitable man. This <hi rend="underline">ought</hi> to show them that I do not intend to be hustled.</p>
         <p>Then I replied to the Archbishop of Canterbury, <hi rend="bold underline">consenting</hi> to sit on the Committee for inquiring into the Church property, and taking occasion to lay before his Grace my project for creating a complete Theological Faculty in Durham. I marked the letter "private &amp; confidential".</p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and instituted two new hon: canons, Ellershaw and Loxley. Also I licensed two curates. The, after lunching with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, he and I motored to Whickham in order to inquire into the case of the Vicar of Hedgefield. Colonel Simpson, &amp; the incumbents of Whickham &amp; Ryton met us in Whickham Vicarage, &amp; we discussed the best method of procedure. We finally decided that Hunter, as parish priest of Ryton, sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> warn the grocer, to whom the said V. of H. owes a large sum, that he had better get his money. We think that, if the grocer c<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be incited to take action, the other creditors w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be quickened into self&#8211;disclosure, &amp; a situation might be created in which I could intervene. <hi rend="bold underline">Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> arrived to take up his duties as chaplain.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>