<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[326]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Newcastle Daily Journal</hi>" reports the "answers" which a certain M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Batey returns to the questions which I asked at West Hartlepool. They are rudely expressed, but I thought it worth while to write a mild letter thanking him for his information, and re&#8211;stating the main position. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Miller, the editor of the "North Eastern Daily Gazette" called, &amp; I gave the letter to him for as wide a circulation as he could secure. <hi rend="bold underline">He tells me that my reference to the "shirking" in the pits has provoked lively discussion</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The bitter resentment which it provokes suggests that my shaft has gone home. In the afternoon I went into <hi rend="bold underline">the Park, and had some talk with a party of young miners whom I found sitting round a fire on the grass. They were very civil, &amp; very vehement both in their assertion of a desire to go back to work, and in a refusal to go back on the "starvation" wage offered by the owners. Some of the older men look very unhappy</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>As I returned to the Castle, Miss Baker&#8211;Baker and a Miss Cator were taking their departure. So I had them back, shewed them the House, &amp; gave them tea. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edgar Dobbie</hi> had tea, and sate in my room for an hour talking. We went into the Chapel &amp; said prayers together before parting. I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Willie Murray</hi><persName xml:id="227"></persName> very sad, but manly. Also a note from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Budworth</hi><persName xml:id="2692"></persName> accepting the Hon. Canonry. The '<hi rend="underline">North&#8211;Eastern Daily Gazette</hi>' prints the letter that I wrote this morning. It will hardly please the Trade Union folk, &amp; the fire&#8211;eaters.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>