<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[219]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The moral hereticks do the Church more harm than all the Nonconformists can do, or can wish it."</p>
         <p>Andrew Marvell. A. D. 1676</p>
         </div>
         <p>This passage of "<hi rend="underline">The Historical Essay on General Councils</hi>" in which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marvell</hi> draws the description of a true clergyman by denouncing clerical faults reflects his recollection of his father, a typical &amp; very admirable Puritan minister.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"A good life is a clergyman's best syllogism, and the quaintest oratory and ʾtill they outlive 'm they will never get the better of the fanaticks, nor able to preach 'with demonstration of spirit', or with any effect or authority."</p>
         </div>
         <p>The essence of the Protestant, and <hi rend="underline">a fortiori</hi> of the Puritan, position could not be better stated than in this Essay, where he protests against the imposition of Creeds by external authority, and insists on the incommunicable responsibility of the individual Christian:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The soul is too precious to be let out at interest upon any humane security, that does or may fail; but it is only safe when under God's custody, in its own Cabinet."</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marvell's</hi> dislike and contempt of bishops is everywhere apparent. Nicaea was vitiated for him by its exclusively episcopal composition:</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I do not think it possible for any Council to be free that is composed only of bishops, and where they only have the decisive voices: nor that a Free Council that takes away Christian liberty."</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sheldon</hi><persName xml:id="5301"></persName> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cosin</hi> must have been ill folk to live with, or under.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[220]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Marvell</hi> speaks of "the mean English way of giving reasons". He contrasts it with the method of Louis XIV, who, in declaring war on Holland, contented himself with adducing his own feeling that "without diminution to his glory" he could no longer "dissemble his indignation" against the Dutch.</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Wordsworth</hi> names together as "great men";</p>
         <p>"The later Sidney, MARVEL, Harrington,</p>
         <p>Young Vane, and others who call'd Milton friend."</p>
         <p>These moralists could act and comprehend:</p>
         <p>They knew how genuine glory is put on:</p>
         <p>Taught us how rightfully a nation shone</p>
         <p>In splendour: what strength was, that would not bend</p>
         <p>But in magnanimous meekness.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Algernon Sidney</hi> (1662&#8211;1682) was almost exactly Marvel's contemporary (1621&#8211;1678)</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 1.40 p.m. and motored to Grangetown, where I confirmed 80 candidates. Then we went on to Bishopwearmouth, where we had an early dinner with Canon Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> &amp; his wife. After dinner we went to the parish church, where I confirmed 177 candidates. The sexes were very evenly divided, and in both these confirmations there was good order &amp; reverence. We returned to the Castle immediately after the service, and arrived shortly before 10.30 p.m. An evening paper, which I picked up in Canon G's study, announces the retirement of Bonar Law on the score of health.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>