<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, January 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> sent me newspaper cuttings from the "Glasgow Herald" of the Bishop of Peterborough's sermon to the University last Sunday. He had preached on the Lambeth "Appeal", and undertaken to interpret it. Of course he spoke magniloquently of the "vision" which had come to the Bishops at Lambeth, and the new "ideal" which they had been marvellously led to adumbrate. There was the usual repudiaton of "prelacy", and the usual emphasis on a "constitutional" episcopate". Then he came to the highly original proposal of a lop&#8211;sided reciprocity, which sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> without reflecting on anybody's orders, secure the universal acceptance of episcopacy, &amp; thereby create an united church.</p>
         <p>"With that object in view he personally sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not stumble at the word ordination. He was an ordained Bishop of the Church of God, but as a humble sacrifice for the unity so much desired he w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> ask to be included in their order so that together they might be consecrated to a wider service &amp; leave no stone unturned for the rebuilding of a truly Catholic Church."</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">In the course of the discussion at Lambeth, I quoted this declaration</hi> of the Bishop's willingness to be "reordained", &amp; stigmatized it as 'profane'. I supported the proposal that the Appeal sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be considered at the next session of Convocation, &amp; announced my determination to have its ambiguities thoroughly cleared up. I referred to the account of the Appeal given by the 3 bishops (Peterborough, <hi rend="bold">[139] </hi>[symbol] Zanzibar, &amp; Hereford), and said that it seemed to me so misleading that I had resolved to answer it at length. It was proposed by the Archbishop of York that a standing committee of bishops should be appointed to form an advisory &amp; consultative body in connexion with the "propaganda" for the Appeal. I opposed strongly on the ground that such a body w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> inevitably take an authoritative character to which it had no rightful claim. Several bishops expressed a measure of hesitancy, &amp; the resolution was finally withdrawn. <hi rend="bold underline">But the Archbishop of Canterbury was visibly chagrined</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I dined in Park Lane. Herbert Fisher was the only guest beside</hi><hi rend="bold">,</hi> and we talked much, &amp; interestingly about persons &amp; politics. <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Reading</hi><persName xml:id="5276"></persName><hi rend="italic"> had observed to him how singular was his own fortune. He would visit Calcutta as Viceroy: the last time he visited that city had been as a penniless cabin&#8211;boy.</hi> Fisher said that the lack of discipline among the British forces had been very serious, but limited to a comparatively few individuals. He said that the overwhelming prestige of Great Britain was very apparent at Geneva during the League of Nations' meeting. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Viviani's</hi> eloquence was amazing. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Paderewski</hi> also was astonishingly eloquent. He also spoke in French. Fisher thinks that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Robert Horne</hi> will probably be Prime Minister. He has the ear of the Labour leaders: is a ready speaker: &amp; a good parliamentary manner. Add that he is still in the forties, has a cheerful disposition, &amp; an admirable constitution.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>