<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[248]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>How useless and even pitiful is the continued complaint of moralists &amp; divines, to whom none lend an ear, whilst they endeavour, age after age, to check youth and pleasure, &amp; turn the current of life and nature backward on its course...... How can we read this endless story of humanity with any thought of blame!</p>
         <p>John Inglesant. Ii. 126, 8</p>
         </div>
         <p>Thus the morbid sensitive Englishman meditates in Rome, as he contemplates the eager shameless pleasure of the half&#8211;pagan crowds. His reflection on the futility of moral protest against natural self&#8211;expression occurs often enough to the Christian Minister, more often as the fervours of his 'first love' die down in his spirit, and he goes on in the way of familiar duty without illusion and with little hope. If, indeed, he could succeed in 'the more fearful war within', and hold himself faithful to the austere disciplines of which he speaks so much, and of which he is clearly bound to exhibit the value in his own person, he might be able to stand up against the monotonous testimonies of his pastoral experience, but inasmuch as he fails even in his own case, or at best succeeds but fitfully and in partial degree, how can he avoid an extreme despondency, and a paralyzing doubt? '<hi rend="underline">O Lord, there is mercy with Thee: therefore shalt Thou be feared</hi>.'</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[249]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The morning papers announce that work has ceased in all the mines throughout Great Britain, even the men needed to preserve the mines from damage and even destruction being withdrawn. A Royal Proclamation declaring that "a state of emergency exists" carries us back at once to the fears &amp; disciplines of War</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The "principle" at stake is the determination of wages by a "national" standard, in plain words, the old fallacy of the 'minimum wage' which has slipped into the position of a postulate during this orgy of sentiment &amp; sophistry which the War stimulated &amp; raised to fever heat. <hi rend="underline">Luo tendimus</hi> [I pay, we retain]?</p>
         <p>I motored to Barnard Castle, and there presided at the meeting of the Governors of the N.E. County School. It is, perhaps, a sign of the increased wealth of some sections of the population, that, although the school&#8211;fees have been raised &#x00A3;18 per annum, only seven boys out of about 300 have been withdrawn. One of the Governors, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> R. T. Richardson, shewed me a house, and about 3 acres of ground well placed beside the main road, which he desired to present to the church. I motored to Darlington. The road ran beside the Tees, &amp; traversed a very beautiful country. After having tea with Canon Cosgrave, I went with him to view the mission church which was burned down last week. Also I visited the parish church, now used as a schoolroom, &amp; the new church which has replaced it for public worship. I returned to the Castle in time for dinner. Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> had made a copy of my Marvell sermon. I sent the original M.S. to Hull.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>