<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[350]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Yesterday the papers announced the death of</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Vesey Knox</hi><persName xml:id="313"></persName>. He was two years my junior. I really liked him, &amp; I think, he really liked me. Tonight I received a telegram reporting the death of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Freeman</hi><persName xml:id="2809"></persName>, the head&#8211;verger in the Cathedral. He was a very loyal friend of mine. I shall not forget his affectionate telegram on my appointment as Bishop of Durham. My life is emptying. After an early lunch I motored to West Hartlepool, and went to Christ Church Vicarage. There <hi rend="doubleunderline">MacDonald</hi><persName xml:id="3698"></persName> brought to me the Roman Catholick woman who desires to rejoin the Church of England. I would not allow her confirmation as she had been confirmed by the Papists, but I thought it right to satisfy myself that she realized what she was doing before sanctioning her admission to the Holy Communion. Then <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Maurice Gibb</hi> came, &amp; explained the projected developments of new works &amp;c in the neighbourhood. After he had gone, Macdonald and I motored to Bellasis, and saw the site for the church, &amp; the plans. After tea with the Churchwarden we returned to W. Hartlepool, where I left Macdonald, &amp; went back to the Castle. Here I found that the <hi rend="underline">Ordinandi</hi> had arrived. After dinner, at which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Church's</hi> <hi rend="underline">Discipline of the Christian Character</hi> was read, there was Evensong in the Chapel, when <hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> gave his first address.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>