<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in dictating letters, and interviews with 1) Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Cyril L. T. Barclay. 2) Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> L. S. Merrefield. The latter came to report the situation as touching his curate, a deacon, (Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> C. R. Coates) <hi rend="bold underline">ordained by Bishop Moule's authority last Trinity, who has developed epileptic fits, and is really "impossible"</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>I look up his 'dossier', &amp; it is woeful. After being twice rejected at the Deacon's examination, <hi rend="bold underline">he was passed at the almost bullying insistence of his friend the Vicar of Escomb</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He failed at the Advent exam<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> for Priests. Now it is abundantly clear that he must not be encouraged to suppose that, in any circumstances, he could be ordained to the Priesthood. <hi rend="bold underline">Here is one more example of Bishop Moule's weakness</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Freddie Macdonald came to lunch. He is 6 foot 2 in: but still recognizable. He matriculates at Oriel in October.</p>
         <p>I received an affectionate letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> posted at Port Said. Also, a rather quaintly&#8211;worded letter from the youngish clergyman <hi rend="italic">who, I thought, addressed me with undue freedom last night. It appears that he had not comprehended who I was!</hi></p>
         <p>I ordered 6 bottles of Communion Wine from Hicks &amp; C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi>, 27 George Street, Plymouth. Also, on J. G. Wilson's<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> recommendation, 4 dozen white wine @ 39/&#8211; per dozen from Ehrmanns, 43 &amp; 44 Finsbury Square E.C.2.: and an experimental bottle of port @ 96/&#8211; from M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Edward Shildon, Wine&#8211;merchant, Shipston&#8211;on&#8211;Stour.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p>The account for the removal of our furniture from Hereford to Auckland came in from Robson &amp; Sons L<hi rend="superscript underline">td</hi>. It is no less that &#x00A3;450 and is accompanied by an explanatory letter, which in view of the fact that in 1918 the same furniture had been transported the same distance for &#x00A3;250 must be considered requisite.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Making comparison with our charge for your previous removal, we w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> respectfully point out to your lordship that since that removal, railway rates have increased by 100%, also the cost of labour &amp; haulage has risen considerably."</p>
         </div>
         <p>The explanation is adequate, and I ruefully sent the cheque, but how difficult the whole position is becoming! The cost of entering this Bishoprick mounts steadily:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Fees</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;273.14.6 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;2269.16.1</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Removal</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">450.0.0 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">19.11.0</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Workmen</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">296.7.7 </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;2289.7.1</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Furniture</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">1249.14.0</hi> 
               </cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;2269.16.1</hi> 
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>Beside the cost of travelling to &amp; fro, ourselves &amp; servants:</p>
         <p>Against this must be set the Income received during the vacancy i.e. from May 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> to July 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> poudsign1616.16.11 minus taxes &amp; divers charges. The net amount was not more than &#x00A3;1000. We sold to my successor at Hereford furniture &amp;c to the amount of &#x00A3;942. So that on the balance about &#x00A3;400 has to be charged to the income of the current year.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>