<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[176]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, February 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>The episcopal dignity added to a good preaching faculty, is like the erecting of a stately fountain upon a spring, which still, for all that, remains as much a spring as it was before, and flows as plentifully, only it flows with the circumstance of greater state and magnificence.</p>
         <p>South. A. W. 1666</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">South</hi> held preaching to be the distinctive function of the Christian Minister, as sacrifice had been of the Jewish priests. "<hi rend="underline">Burning of incense was then the ministerial office amongst them, as preaching is now amongst us</hi>" he says in his great sermon on "Religion the best reason of state": and preaching implied in his view a learned and leisured ministry. "<hi rend="underline">God would not accept the offals of other professions</hi>." His wrath was particularly fierce against the ignorant zealots who, without knowledge or commission, had usurped the preacher's office, and degraded it almost irrecoverably. What was distinctive of the Christian Ministry generally was in special degree true of the Episcopate; but "<hi rend="underline">since experience fits for government, and age usually brings experience, perhaps the most governing years are the least preaching years</hi>", and "<hi rend="underline">he who ordains &amp; furnishes all his churches with able preachers, is an universal teacher: he instructs where he cannot be present: he speaks in every mouth of his diocese: &amp; every congregation of it every Sunday feels his influence, though it hears not his voice</hi>".</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> J. Todd writes very resentfully in reply to my letter advising him to remain in Canada rather than return to my diocese. He describes Canon M. as a very ignorant and bigoted, though kind&#8211;hearted person. I fear he (M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Todd) is a self&#8211;estimating man. It is the common fault of the humbly&#8211;born and self taught. <hi rend="bold underline">They appraise their attainments of knowledge by the amount of toil involved, not by their actual value: and they are apt unduly to estimate the significance of the professional successes which may come to them. I have noticed that enjoyment of ecclesiastical rank is most evident in those who were not "born in the purple", to whom, therefore, that rank has opened to them for the first time the delicious experiences of importance &amp; the service of others</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>"Prelacy" has small charms for the man who has been cloyed and cumbered by privilege &amp; flattery from his cradle. But 'put a beggar on horse&#8211;back", and what proud riding will there be! Perhaps, indeed, there is as much sinful pride in the scornful humility of the aristocratical ascetick as in the vulgar ostentation of the low&#8211;born pontiff. Who can say? Both men exhibit the same disgust of what is familiar, the same appreciation of what is a novel experience. "<hi rend="underline">The Lord seeth not as man seeth</hi>", and He knows us all better than we know ourselves. '<hi rend="underline">O Lord, there is mercy with Thee: therefore shalt Thou be feared</hi>" writes the paradoxical psalmist disconcertingly.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p>After an early lunch, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Dawdon, where I confirmed a consumptive girl in bed. Then I went to Dalton&#8211;le&#8211;Dale, and confirmed 67 candidates in the modern church. There was too great a preponderance of females, otherwise the service was satisfactory. Then we motored to New Seaham, where I confirmed 173 candidates. Here there was a fair proportion of men &amp; lads. The church was densely crowded, and I was assured that everybody was connected with the mines. The Vicar (Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> R. R. Fenning) assures me that there is no real foundation for the statement that, unless the boys are confirmed before they go to work in the pits, there is no likelihood that they would be confirmed at all. He thinks there is no practical objection to the diocesan rule which requires candidates for confirmation to have attained the age of 14 years. This confirms my suspicion that the objections are really based, not on practical grounds, but on doctrinal. We had supper at New Seaham Vicarage, and then motored back to the Castle, which we reached about 10.45 p.m. Durham was very foggy, so that our pace was necessarily reduced in going through the city.</p>
         <p>The Cardigan election has resulted in a victory for the Coalition in spite of the frenzied efforts of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bonham Carter and the "Times". There certainly has not yet appeared any serious alternative to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lloyd George, &amp;, if he could solve the Irish problem, he might have yet a long term of power. But &#8211;</p>
         </body></text></TEI>