<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, February 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The Vicar of Sacriston writes to me in these terms:&#8211; </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I am in somewhat of a quandary. Some children under 14 years of age offer themselves for Confirmation. I have pointed out to their parents your direction as to age. They reply that if your Lordship insists on that age for Confirmation they wish them to be admitted to the Holy Communion, as they fulfil the requirement of being 'ready &amp; desirous to be confirmed'. This does not seem to be a desirable course, yet I do not see that I can refuse to accede to their request".</p>
         </div>
         <p>To which I reply without delay:</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hutton,</p>
         <p>You must in no case admit to Holy Communion unconfirmed persons under the age of 14 years. The rubrick as to those who are 'ready &amp; desirous to be confirmed' has no relation whatever to their case, &amp; cannot be seriously quoted in connexion with it.</p>
         <p>Boys cannot leave school under the present law before they are 14, and certainly they are not very responsible persons before that age. I am, of course, always prepared to consider really exceptional cases on their merits, but I desire the rule to be generally observed, &amp; I expect the clergy loyally to observe it.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 11.15 a.m., and motored viâ Durham &amp; Lanchester to Consett where I arrived at 12.45 p.m. Here I lunched with the Rural Dean (Fedden<persName xml:id="5285"></persName>). Old Firth of Esh was also a guest. After lunch I attended a meeting of the clergy of the Rural Deanery of Lanchester, in the Vicar's drawing&#8211;room. After the Rural Dean had formally welcomed me, I addressed the clergy for about half an hour. I took occasion to speak very plainly about the standard of Ordination candidates, clerical poverty, &amp; other burning questions. I think they were impressed, and, perhaps, somewhat startled. Then I was taken to the school&#8211;room where the Ruri&#8211;decanal Conference had assembled &#8211; about 80&#8211;90 clergy and laity. Here I was again welcomed with flatterous speeches. (I wonder how much sincerity there is in what they say!). M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Priestman spoke for the laity. I made a speech of more than half an hour's length, in which I spoke strongly about the necessity of making the Electoral Rolls more adequate. In that Deanery, with a population now estimated to be not less than 90,000 souls, the enrolled electors are little more than 4500. I think the lay&#8211;folk were impressed. I motored back to the Castle, and arrived about 6.30 p.m. After dinner I wrote a short note for the paper which the tradesmen of Bishop Auckland are issuing as an advertisement of their shopping carnival: &amp; I sent them a photograph.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>