<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[211]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, March 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Colonel Bowes came to see me, and we discussed the perplexing situation created by Major S. [Slovach]. Both the Colonel &amp; the Major lunched here: and afterwards I had rather a distressing interview with the latter, who certainly leaves on my mind a very favourable impression. I wrote to Sherwood asking him to come here, &amp; talk the matter over with me. There for the present the subject must be left.</p>
         <p>I received the unrevised Report of my speech in the H. of L. Lang's speech takes just over 6 columns: L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Parmoor's just over 3 1/2: mine just over 7: L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Braye's<persName xml:id="5298"></persName> 2: L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Buckmaster's<persName xml:id="3687"></persName> 4 3/4: Earl Russell's<persName xml:id="5072"></persName> just over 6: Lord Gorell's<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> introducing the Bill 8 1/2: L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Chancellor's 4 3/4: L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Phillimore's<persName xml:id="1940"></persName> 1 3/4. The debate began at 4.15 p.m. and was over something after 7 p.m. This works out at about 5 minutes to the column. <hi rend="bold underline">My "maiden speech" required about 35 minutes to deliver</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi></p>
         <p>After dinner I wrote to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. It is odd that, having once promised him a fortnightly letter, I should feel that particular obligation peculiarly binding on my conscience. But such is the case. There seems a singular baseness in disappointing the expectations of a simple, affectionate youth, whose friendship one has gained. Besides, there <hi rend="doubleunderline">is</hi> the off chance that the letters have a certain value as moral auxiliaries, keeping him in mind of spiritual purposes and ideals, which are remote enough from his present experiences.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>