<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, January 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921. </hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'As being towed is not steering, and, on damage to the tow&#8211;line, may be shipwreck, so is an externally directed morality.'</p>
         <p>Oman<persName xml:id="2141"></persName>.</p>
         </div>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went with me to Newcastle, where the Rural Dean of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, (the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> C.E. Little, Rector of Whickham) had gathered his Ruri&#8211;decanal Conference to "Welcome the Bishop". After lunching at the Station Hotel, we were taken to the Connaught Rooms, where complimentary speeches were addressed to me, &amp; I made a speech in reply. Then we all had tea. We motored back to the Castle arriving about 6.30 p.m.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I received a formal communication from the Archbishop of Canterbury inviting me to join the Committee to inquire into "the property &amp; finances of the Church as at present administered." His Grace adds a post&#8211;cript in his own hand urging me to accept:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="italic">"The foregoing is of course formal. But I must add a line to say that considering the great questions of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">policy</hi> <hi rend="italic">&#8211; quite apart from finance &#8211; which must inevitably occur, it is </hi><hi rend="italic underline">me judice</hi> <hi rend="italic">[in my judgement] of the first importance that you sh</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> agree to serve on the Committee. I am trying to make it as strong as I possibly can. The task is not an easy one."</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">R.J.C.</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">That is sufficiently pressing. Nevertheless I doubt whether I shall do wisely in putting my neck into the noose.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>