<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended mattins in the parish church. Beside the Rector, a curate, &amp; myself there were none but the angels present. Then we came away, &amp; motored back to Auckland, arriving at the Castle about noon. Among my letters were very kind ones from Lord Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName>, Frank Pember<persName xml:id="66"></persName>, Lady Scarbrough, and S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Loe Strachey. Also a canting effusion from Moore, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, Hereford. I walked with Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> for an hour in the Park, &amp; then did letters with Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName>. Then Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> arrived, and explained to me the financial position of the Cathedral, which is tending to improve by reason of recent sales of property, though the great increase of wages &amp; charges goes a long way towards counteracting the improvement. The fabric &amp; the school are clamouring for large new expenditures. Bayley expresses high approval for my scheme for connecting the canonries with professorships. It would provide a well equipped Faculty of Theology.</p>
         <p>1. Regius Professor of Theology.</p>
         <p>2. Regius Professor of Hebrew.</p>
         <p>3. Regius Professor of Greek.</p>
         <p>4. Regius Professor of Ecclesiastical History.</p>
         <p>5. Regius Professor Comparative Religion.</p>
         <p>The two Archdeacons would hold canonries, &amp; these only would be in the gift of the Bishop. To assist in providing their incomes, the two little united parishes in the Bailey might be annexed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>