<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[270]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The Headlams<persName xml:id="552"><persName xml:id="553"></persName></persName> went off after breakfast. I frittered away the morning being over&#8211;fatigued from yesterday's exertions. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, where I attended a meeting of the Bede College Committee: and had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Then we returned to the Castle.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Apperley</hi><persName xml:id="2918"></persName> writes that a pit pony, too old for going down the shaft, but vigorous enough to draw a lawn&#8211;mower, will be sent from the Londonderry Collieries. No charge will be made for the beast, and (presumably) we shall have the felicity of giving him a brief episode of peace before his final exit.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Church Socialist League</hi><orgName xml:id="324"></orgName>", over which the egregious "Father" <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bull</hi>, of Mirfield, presides as Chairman, sends me a long &amp; windy resolution passed by the "<hi rend="underline">National Executive Committee</hi>" on the Coal Strike. It "calls on the Government to end in the coal industry a type of organisation which is fundamentally un&#8211;Christian, degrades the miner, &amp; which robs the consumer, and to substitute for it a system which shall transfer mines and minerals to communal ownership &amp; shall vest the control of the industry in the hands of public bodies representing both mine&#8211;workers &amp; consumers". The latter arrangement would presumably be fundamentally Christian. In a note "The League recognizes that no political, economic, &amp; social emancipation can be permanent without a change of heart &amp; mind &amp; will."!!!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>