<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[302]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I left the Castle after an early breakfast, and motored to the station in time to catch the early train. There were but few passengers: so I travelled to King's Cross very comfortably. Having left my bags at 21 Park Lane, I went to the hair&#8211;dresser: &amp; when I had done with him, I walked to the House of Lords, and there found Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>, who is in attendance to read prayers. I attended the brief discussion of the Report Stage of the Divorce Bill<hi rend="bold underline">, and made a few remarks in comment on an absurd speech by Earl Russell<persName xml:id="5072"></persName>. </hi>Then Pearce and I looked in at the House of Commons, and being quickly bored by the proceedings there, we walked into the City, where I bought myself an umbrella (18/6). Then we parted, &amp; I went on the Deanery of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's, where I found Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName> &amp; Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> with Craufurd<persName xml:id="4597"></persName> and the two little girls. Jacks, the editor of the Hibbert Journal, came in, and we had some conversation. After dining with the ladies, I returned to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. The Prince of Wales has postponed the dinner of the Royal Society of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George<orgName xml:id="329"></orgName>, which had been arranged for Saturday next. There was an announcement to this effect in the "Times" and on my arrival in Park Lane, a telegram confirming it was placed in my hands. At least I escape the trouble and risk of making a speech.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>