<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[273]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The miners turned up, 26 of them, at the appointed time, and I spent rather more than an hour in walking them through the Castle</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>They were very well&#8211;mannered, and seemed to be interested. Of course they know extremely little, &amp; the objects which pleased them most were not those which, perhaps, most merited their concern. Beck's sword, Queen Victoria's fauld&#8211;stool, the carpet in the State&#8211;room, the pastoral staff, above all, the moose's head in the stone&#8211;hall appeared to fascinate them most. They were very polite, &amp; thanked me when they parted. There is, I think, no feeling against the Bishop, though, of course, it might easily be roused if the Bishop were to cross their path.</p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Muir Mackenzie</hi> with reference to the debate on L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Gorell's<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> Bill<note xml:id="530" n="1"></note>, from which I was so unfortunately absent. It would seem that his Grace of Canterbury was more brazenly dogmatick than ever: &amp; both the Bishop of Birmingham &amp; the Bishop of Worcester voted with the minority against L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Buckmaster's<persName xml:id="3687"></persName> amendment making desertion for 3 years a ground of divorce. It is difficult to think that these prelates were acting quite candidly, for (unless they are grosser humbugs than I care to believe) neither of them believes in either the canonical or the literalist law of marriage. Yet they cast their vote with the fanaticks without a syllable of explanation: and the hollow simulacrum of episcopal unanimity is again set on its legs to befog the public!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>