<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[301]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Lloyd George replies at length to the Bishop of Chelmsford as one of the signatories of a protest against the proceedings in Ireland</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>If the situation were normal, such a pronouncement from the Prime Minister would make an immense sensation. As it is, nobody will be in the smallest degree influenced one way or the other.</p>
         <p>I frittered away the day in making preparations for my departure, especially in arming myself for my interview with Lea<persName xml:id="4306"></persName> [Lee] for income tax purposes. The complexity &amp; worry of those hateful yellow forms baffle belief. However, if once the beastly things could be intelligibly filled up, a load would be lifted from my mind. </p>
         <p>The evening paper announces the death of poor Loxley. He has lingered a long time. I am glad I was able to give him a little pleasure by making him an honorary Canon. It was, of course, a small thing, but it did give the touch of official recognition, which hitherto his ministry had not received. I hope the Dean &amp; Chapter, in whose patronage the living is, will not send there some extravagant "Anglo&#8211;Catholick", of the type now becoming so common. Loxley was very "advanced, but he was a genuinely religious man, and a hard&#8211;working parish&#8211;priest. The impression he made during his long ministry in Jarrow is said to have been very excellent and lasting. R.I.P.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>