<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[299]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, April 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"An Indian Christian, who had travelled widely, said once: 'I saw Muhammad's tomb. It was very splendid, decorated with diamonds &amp; all manner of precious things. And they told me: "Here are Muhammad's bones". I saw Napoleon's tomb &amp; they said: "Here are Napoleon's bones". But when I saw Christ's tomb, it was open. No bones lay there.' Christ is the Living Christ. The tomb has been open thus for nearly 2000 years. My heart is also open to the Lord. He lives in me. <hi rend="bold underline">He is the living Christ because He lives in the lives of Christians</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Real Christians are not those who profess, but those who possess, Christ."</p>
         <p>"The Sadhu" p. 65&#8211;66</p>
         </div>
         <p>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> went off after breakfast. My morning's work was interrupted by an interview with the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> R. D. Parker, an Irish clergyman, who seeks admission to the diocese of Durham. I wrote to the Bishops of Cork and Killaloe making inquiries as to his character.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I had some talk with 3 miners in the Park. All expressed themselves as thoroughly sick of the strike: but they are extraordinarily suspicious of the mine&#8211;owners: &amp; towards the Government their attitude is frankly hostile</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I motored to Durham, &amp; made a speech at a meeting in the Town Hall in advocacy of the League of Nations. It was largely attended. I returned to the Castle afterwards.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>