<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[144]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, January 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Barnes is very confident (as befits a preacher in mid&#8211;course of his success) of the possibility of presenting a version of Christianity which shall be acceptable to scientifically trained men of our time: and he is courageous enough to think that such a version could be accepted in, and authenticated by, the Church of England. I was depressing [sic] with respect to both points. I doubt whether the time has yet arrived for effecting such a harmony, and I am sure the Church of England, as it now exists, is the least likely church in the world to embrace a harmonizing attitude. The fortunes &amp; forms of Religion are intimately connected with, and shaped by, the history of society: <hi rend="bold underline">and I suspect that any effectual re&#8211;casting of Christianity will have to follow from, and be conditioned by, the re&#8211;casting of the economic, social and political fabrick of civilized society</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Therefore, I incline to think that the Church of England must march to ruin with the whole system to which it belongs. But, if Christianity be Divine, it must also be indestructible. It will emerge one day in new shape, competent to take up its Providential mission in circumstances disconcertingly novel, and able to fulfil it as God designs &amp; enables. Before this blessed result has been reached, there must be years of confusion and distress. The revolution in the economic &amp; political spheres will bear hardly on the Anglican clergy &amp; their families: for they have committed all their terrestrial interests to the weakest part of the imperilled industrial system: &amp; before a sound synthesis of tradition &amp; truth has been worked out, there will be many failures of faith &amp; character.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and wrote letters. Then I walked into the City, and changed a cheque. Returning to the Club, I lunched, <hi rend="bold underline">and then went to Westminster for the meeting of the "National Assembly"</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The business was got through in good time. Then I fetched my bags from 3 <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, picked up Archdeacon Spooner<persName xml:id="383"></persName>, and drove him to the Athenaeum, where I got out, sending him on to the S. Paul's Deanery. There Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> joined me, &amp; carried me off to have tea with Elsie<persName xml:id="2056"></persName>, and the children at 9 Ralston Street, Chelsea. Rex<persName xml:id="2799"></persName> is growing a fine boy, and Peggie<persName xml:id="2764"></persName> is sweet. The one is 4, &amp; the other 8 years old. Having parted from them, I went to the Deanery, arriving in good time for dinner.</p>
         <p>There were short extracts from my sermon in the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" &amp; some other newspapers. The "<hi rend="underline">Manchester Guardian</hi>" and the "<hi rend="underline">Yorkshire Post</hi>" also printed them. They all describe me as having worne the cassock &amp; surplice in the <placeName xml:id="106">Westminster Chapel</placeName>. A correct description of a bishop's dress is rather beyond them.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Rather to my astonishment, I learn that Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> has resigned his membership of the Athenaeum on grounds of economy</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He draws the line at an annual subscription of twelve guineas. Certainly it becomes more &amp; more difficult to know what non&#8211;necessary expenditures are morally permissible.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>