<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[230]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">The great man, and the judge, and the mighty man, shall be glorified: and there is not one of them greater than he that feareth the Lord. Free men shall minister unto a wise servant; and a man that hath knowledge will not murmur thereat</hi>.</p>
         <p>Ecclesiasticus X. 24, 25.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This, perhaps, will serve as a text, or rather as a motto or heading, for the sermon on Marvell; as the Puritan citizen. Masson speaks of Marvell's "discipleship" to Milton, and ascribes to Milton's influence the fact that he abandoned his Royalism and became "in all points Oliverian and enthusiast for the Protectorate".</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Barnard Castle, and there I confirmed 39 boys in the chapel of the North Eastern Counties School. After the service, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Brereton, the Headmaster, shewed me over the buildings, which are commodious, well&#8211;arranged, &amp; beautifully situated. During the last few years the fees have been raised from &#x00A3;35 to &#x00A3;84 per boy, and hardly any parents have withdrawn their sons. This fact hardly suggests that ruin of the middle class, which is so confidently affirmed. The crowded state of all the public schools points in the direction of affluence, rather than poverty. It has been suggested that nobody is any longer putting money by, and investing it. Hence there is a larger immediate expenditure. So uncertain is the future that prudence seems to recommend prompt enjoyment of such money as one has.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>