<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[300]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The evidence of Christianity will be a long series of things, reaching, as it seems, from the beginning of the world to the present time, of great variety and compass, taking in both the direct, and also the collateral, proofs; and making up, all of them together, one argument: the conviction arising from which kind of proof may be compared to what they call <hi rend="underline">the effect</hi> in architecture or other works of art: a result from a great number of things so and so disposed, and taken into one view."</p>
         <p>Bishop Butler. 'The Analogy'. p.221</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the whole morning in preparing a sermon for the Chapel Royal. In the afternoon I motored in to Durham, in order to examine an Ordination candidate, named Herbert, on Butler's 'Analogy'. When I had done with him, and given him tea, I returned to the other Castle. <hi rend="italic">There I had an interview with the Vicar of Wheatley Hill (Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> P. T. Casey<persName xml:id="5150"></persName>), an insolent &amp; pig&#8211;headed Ritualist, who positively refuses to carry out the provisions of the Enabling Act, to which he objects. He holds it to be 'preposterous' that he should be required to obey an act which was not on the Statute Book when he was ordained! His churchwardens were worthy of him, a pair of dittoing dolts. He said that he was one of many clergy who were resolved not to work the Act.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>