<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[320]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">S&#x00F6;derblom</hi><persName xml:id="2203"></persName> left by the early train. Some anonymous correspondent sends me a copy of a Toronto paper, "The Globe" (April 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1921) with a leader on "Prohibition and Christianity". It starts with an extract from an article of mine, &amp; quotes an answer which has been written to it by the Editor of the "Expository Times". With it came the following letter which is not without interest:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p><hi rend="underline">The Incarnation</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Did Jehovah really come and live in a Living Temple?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">If so,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">how can you cheapen it and degrade it by your academic teaching as you do</hi>!</p>
         </div>
         <p>I am reminded of a pronouncement put forth by some of the Neo&#8211;Tractarian Radicals at the time of Gladstone's introduction of the Home Rule Bill. It argued, they said, "lack of faith in the Incarnation" to oppose the Bill! Here, in these strange linkings of theology with party programmes, I perceive one of the most formidable causes of ecclesiastical division. Nonconformity is pledged to this union of religion and politics, and is, in consequence, the most exasperating and unreasonable factor in English political life. "The Nonconformist conscience" is the synonym of cant and bigotry. It raises a kind of moral nausea in the minds of ordinary level&#8211;minded Englishmen.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[321]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Titcomb</hi>, the assistant&#8211;curate from Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, came to see me. He defended his indefensible action in rebuking a communicant for "draining the chalice", and in refusing to obey his Vicar's request, that he should attend at the Vicarage together with the aggrieved person. I told him that he had, perhaps, seek his next curacy in another diocese. His complaint that his Vicar was lacking in confidence and sympathy struck me as unreal and unconvincing. If true it was irrelevant, and it was probably untrue.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There was a miners' demonstration in the Park at 2.30 p.m</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Rain was falling briskly enough to damp any enthusiasm for any cause. <hi rend="bold underline">I talked with a party of miners who were on their way to the meeting, and found them very disconcerted and melancholy. One old man was vehemently in favour of the Strike, but he was incapable of reasoning, &amp; seemed to alienate the younger men. They are all very incredulous of the statements and offers of the mine&#8211;owners</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Gateshead, and, after dining with Stephenson, we went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's Church, where I confirmed 157 candidates. Then we returned to the Castle, arriving about 10 p.m. It rained all the outward journey, but had cleared on our return. The spectacle of great numbers of miners, many of them boys &amp; very young men, all hanging about in self&#8211;imposed idleness, is very melancholy. If idleness be indeed the devil's opportunity, he must be fruitfully active in my diocese just now.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>