<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[359]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I read Cicero's De Officiis before getting up. It also is full of good things, but all on a lower plane than that of the divine Plato.</p>
         <p>I arrived at King's Cross at least 45 minutes before the train started, but I could obtain a seat only with difficulty, and it <hi rend="italic">was an undesirable one! However I had </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Robert Cecil</hi><persName xml:id="131"></persName><hi rend="italic"> for my companion, and I found him a pleasant conversationalist. He is certainly a man who thinks for himself, and is willing to admit the necessity of large departures from precedent. I asked him whether </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Keynes'</hi><hi rend="italic">s book was trustworthy, and he replied in the affirmative. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">He agreed with me that, if we have a representative to the Vatican, he ought to be a Protestant diplomatist of a thoroughly representative type</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>We talked of possible political eventualities, and agreed that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Grey</hi> was the one possible alternative to the present Prime Minister. At Darlington <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> had come to meet me with the car. We were back in the Castle about 4 p.m. Rain fell heavily all the way. In view of the inconveniency of the trains, I determined to abandon my visit to Manchester, and to send the M.S. of my sermon. After dinner Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went through the letters. There was little of interest or importance. The evening was distinguished by two beautiful rainbows  ̶  an omen of consolation.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>