<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[328]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Wingate, where I preached to a congregation in which were a good many men. The occasion was locally called "Trades Sunday", but the traders were not very obviously present. The miners, angered by my speech at West Hartlepool, had refused to attend officially! However, I preached from notes, my text being composed of 2 passages from S. Paul, Rom: xii. 16, &amp; Col: iii. 2, which have an appearance of contradiction. The congregation was very attentive. I was distressed at the pinched proportions and mean architecture of the parish church, which serves no less than 7000 people. The parson, Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> F. E. Bowman, has been 2 years in the parish. <hi rend="bold underline">The miners are much in evidence everywhere: they stare at me as I pass in the car, but I do not think they are unfriendly. There are no signs of hostility, yet these could hardly be lacking if the men were really hostile</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">At 3 p.m. the Masonic Service in the Chapel was held. It was numerously attended. 300 service papers were distributed and were far too few. L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ravensworth<persName xml:id="3719"></persName>, as P.G.M., sate in my stall, and read the Lesson. I addressed the Brethren from the altar&#8211;step. The singing of the hymns, and the close attention while I was speaking, were most impressive. Many of the congregation came through the Castle afterwards. L</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ravensworth &amp; 3 others had tea with me. On the whole, I think this was really a very successful function.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[329]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>At 6 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Miller</hi>, the journalist, and a miner named Gent, who was, he assured me a reasonable man, came, and, for nearly 2 hours, talked with me about the "Stoppage". <hi rend="bold underline">The miner justified his reputation: he expressed himself with intelligence, moderation, and good feeling: but his knowledge outside the narrow confines of his personal experience was evidently limited. He was very severe on the Government, and maintained (not without justification) that the whole treatment of the mines had been blundering &amp; exasperating. Those were not his words, but the gist of his argument. Before they went away, I took them into the Chapel, and shewed them the Cosin plate: and suggested that we might have a miners' service in the chapel. M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Gent rather jumped at the idea; and said that, after the strife is ended, we might arrange it. </hi><hi rend="underline">Possibly</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> something may grow out of this. It is extraordinary how loveable these men are when one actually gets into touch with them. If only I were not so woefully poor, I would bring them here &amp; feast them</hi><hi rend="bold">!</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, and Ernest Pearce<persName xml:id="636"></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">On this day last year Bishop Moule died. His personal sanctity is attested by all who knew him: but his official incompetence can only be certified adequately by his successor. He bequeathed to me a number of thoroughly unfit clergymen who ought never to have been admitted to Holy Orders, &amp; whose future is an insoluble problem</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[330]</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to Streeter<persName xml:id="3230"></persName> with reference to the Examining Chaplaincy:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>"If you will accept appointment as Examining Chaplain on the understanding that you will do what you can, and will try to direct to this diocese such men as you think suitable, I shall be content.</p>
         <p>My mind runs on two main lines in respect to this matter. First, I desire to indicate my approval of the broadly liberal view of Churchmanship which you take, and Next, I desire to have a link in the teaching body of the University between my diocese and Oxford.</p>
         <p>There is a field of spiritual work in this diocese crying out for men of zeal who are also modernly educated. If only I could get some good man to take the place of the woeful incompetents whom I am rejecting, I believe the diocese might yet revive by God's Blessing. My predecessor was a saintly man but he left the ill legacy of an illiterate and unspiritual ministry, whom his inability to discriminate or deny admitted to Holy Orders. Help me in this matter, my dear Streeter, and I will be grateful indeed."</p>
         </div>
         <p>There appears to be a prospect of Maurice Pryke's<persName xml:id="438"></persName> exchanging into this diocese. He is a modernist, but whether he is also a competent parish priest I know not.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>