<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, January 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi><persName xml:id="1820"></persName> was obviously pleased with my compliments to his edition of the Apocalypse. He writes:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"What you say of my edition of the Apocalypse is most kind. My friends have been more than kind in their felicitations. If it does a tithe of what they say it does, I am more than repaid. At any rate I have found the work a labour of love &amp; have felt it a real joy to rescue in some degree from the hopeless misinterpretations of so many expounders some of the sublimest writers of all time.</p>
         <p>As regards yourself there are "&#x3B5;, &#x3C0;, &#x3B9;, &#x3C3;, &#x3BA;, &#x3BF;, &#x3C0;, &#x3BF;, &#x3B9;" and "&#x3B5;, &#x3C0;, &#x3B9;, &#x3C3;, &#x3BA;, &#x3BF;, &#x3C0;, &#x3BF;, &#x3B9;". You belong to the few amongst them to whom we look for spiritual courage &amp; leadership &amp; great service."</p>
         </div>
         <p>It is rather terrifying, knowing what I really am, to be written to in such terms. If, indeed, desire could of itself accomplish anything I should be brave, &amp; a leader, &amp; greatly serviceable, but the programme of the spirit always falls to the ground with me "through weak endeavour". How ought one to be affected by the gross eulogies or really absurd over&#8211;estimates of one's friends? Ought one in the interest of one's self&#8211;respect to cry from the house&#8211;tops that one is verily quite other than they think? It is the actual impossibility of setting forth the precise truth about one's self that compels, if it does not really justify, one's acquiescence in the grotesque flatteries of others. But there is One who does know, &amp; Who cannot be hoodwinked, &amp; Who will put up with nothing but the Truth. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="bold">"</hi><hi rend="bold underline">The foreigner who believed that Othello on the stage was enraged for the loss of his handkerchief was not more mistaken than the reasoner who imputes any of the more vehement passions of men to the impressions of mere profit &amp; loss</hi><hi rend="bold">".</hi></p>
         <p>Ferguson quoted by Leslie Stephen ii, 215.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a sagacious observation, much to be remembered in times of revolutionary unrest, when a demented idealism possesses men's minds, &amp; they embrace with enthusiasm courses of action which are obviously inimical to their material advantage. </p>
         <p>I spent most of the day in reading again <hi rend="doubleunderline">Leslie Stephen's</hi> "<hi rend="underline">English Thought in the Eighteenth Century</hi>" &#8211; an interesting &amp; thought&#8211;provoking book. </p>
         <p>J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> came to see me after lunch, &amp; we discussed together what had best be done in the case of the Vicar of Hedgefield. He advised caution in the matter of prosecution, which might appear the obviously right course. The enormous cost to the Bishop, even when at every point successful, is really prohibitive. A similar case cost Bishop Westcott not less than &#x00A3;600. Yet it is absurd to suppose that a great diocese can be governed without recourse to the coercive or punitive action of Law. This is yet one more ill consequence of the woeful poverty of the clergy &#8211; the Bishops can no longer afford to do their duty in the matter of enforcing discipline. I decided to issue a commission of inquiry, and to await its report before taking any litigious step. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>