<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[352]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated Holy Communion in the chapel at 8.15 a.m. Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> served. All the morning was spent in seeing the Ordinandi separately. Then Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham, where <hi rend="bold underline">I took part in the funeral service for Freeman<persName xml:id="2809"></persName>. There was a considerable company in the Cathedral, and at the Bow cemetery</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>I called on the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, who is again reported ill. Then I went to my room in Durham Castle, and tried to prepare a 'charge' for tonight, and an Institution address tomorrow.</p>
         <p>The last is not very easy. I might perhaps draw a contrast between the XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, when <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bernard Gilpin</hi><persName xml:id="4232"></persName> lived, and the XX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> when his successor is living: between the rude uncivilized North then, and the industrial North now: between Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring then &amp; now.</p>
         <p>I dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName>, and then delivered my "charge" to the ordinandi in the Deanery chapel. They were very attentive, and probably were impressed. <hi rend="bold underline">They asked me afterwards if I would have it printed for them, that everyone might have a copy</hi><hi rend="bold">! </hi>But therein they forgot the poverty of bishops, and the largeness of printing costs. After the service, Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>, Wynne Willson, and I returned to the Castle, leaving Clayton in Durham. The exceeding beauty of the country seen in the failing light of a brilliant day arrested our notice, and evoked our ardent admiration. Before going to bed, we sate in my study, and talked over many things.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>