<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[354]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Under the early Empire the enervating effect of the school training was to a considerable extent obviated by later practical discipline.... But gradually the civil &amp; military careers were entirely dissociated, and from this time onwards the really important officials had no training at all except that of the bureau. The same division of function prevails in modern nations. But the result of the separation must be greatly to increase the influence of the school, and we may say that the Roman school was much fitter to produce amateur actors than efficient servants of the State."</p>
         <p>Bigg. "The Church's Task within the Roman Empire" 17</p>
         </div>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a whole sheaf of letters. After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Annfield Plain, where I confirmed 56 candidates<hi rend="bold underline">. The parson, Talbot, is a quite intolerably and aggressively little vulgar canting man</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then we went on to Blackhill, where I confirmed more than 180 candidates. <hi rend="bold underline">Last night the Sinn Feiners attempted to burn down the railway station. This was one of a numerous series of outrages which those miscreants carried out in this part of the country</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>We motored back to the Castle after the Confirmation, arriving about 9.45 p.m. <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">The strike still continues</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>There is persistent expectation of some settlement, but day follows day without anything being done: &amp; the country remains serenely optimistic.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>