<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[237]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, March 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I finished the sermon for the Marvell Tercentenary. The expenditure of time in its preparation has been excessive, but I have found some compensation in acquiring a better acquaintance with Marvell's writings</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>In the afternoon I inspected Bishop Cosin's desk., which is preserved with the heirlooms, and found in it several letters of interest about some of my predecessors, addressed to Bishop Westcott.</p>
         <p>I wrote to the Mayor of Sunderland, Aglionby<persName xml:id="5267"></persName>, Gamble, Fawkes, &amp; Arthur<persName xml:id="3128"></persName>.</p>
         <p>Feb: 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1891. Letter from Lowther Barrington to the Bishop of Durham giving some account of Bishop Barrington his great&#8211;uncle.</p>
         <p>Oct: 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1900. J. M. Clemens to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Boutflower, <hi rend="bold underline">denying that the marble slabs in the State drawing room were ever parts of the Becket shrine in Canterbury Cathedral</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Ash Wed. 1893. Letter from Hon: Augusta Maclagan to Bishop Westcott: with reminiscences of Bishop Barrington.</p>
         <p>July 4. 1894. J Grey Howick to Bp. Westcott about the sweat flags in the pond.</p>
         <p>Oct: 2. 1900. H. Montague Villiers to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Boutflower about the slabs of marble in the State Drawing Room.</p>
         <p>Sept. 21. 1877. Extract from 'Auckland Chronicle' giving an account of the pictures of the patriarchs by Zurbaran.</p>
         <p>"A short account of the life of Richard Trevor', typed.</p>
         <p>A note on the carpet &amp; screen in the State Drawing Room.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>