<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[203]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>When the sword glitters ore the judge's head,</p>
         <p>And fear has coward churchmen silenc&#x00E9;d,</p>
         <p>Then is the poet's time, ʾtis then he drawes,</p>
         <p>And single, fights forsaken Vertue's cause.</p>
         <p>He, when the wheel of empire whirleth back, </p>
         <p>And though the world's disjointed axle crack.</p>
         <p>Sings still of ancient rights and better times,</p>
         <p>Seeks wretched good, arraigns successful crimes; </p>
         <p>Andrew Marvell. "Tom May's Death." 63&#8211;70</p>
         </div>
         <p>These lines, perhaps, set forth Marvell's conception of his own rôle as a poet in the reign of Charles II. Most of the satires, however, were not published until after his death. "Satires so outspoken were necessarily printed in secret or circulated in manuscript", writes Firth in D.N.B. Thomas May seems on the whole to have deserved his fate at Marvell's hands. "His contemporaries in general justly regarded him as neither impartial nor honest."</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I resolved to attend the discussion of Lord Gorell's<persName xml:id="5303"></persName> Matrimonial Causes Bill, of which the 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> reading is set down for Thursday next</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>It seems to me that, if I don't show up in the House at all, I shall give ground for the supposition that I don't value the seat in the Lords at all. This would be both untrue and unfortunate. It is more than probable that the Bishops will disappear from Parliament at the next turn of the wheel. Let them at least shew fight to the last.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi></p>
         <p>Barry, the Principal of Knutsford, came to see me. He has a pleasant smile, and makes the impression of a good and capable man. But he is so deaf that conversation is all but impossible. He seems to think that this physical disadvantage closes the door of parochial work to him. I must needs agree with this view.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I motored to South Shields, where I took two Confirmations, in Holy Trinity and in S. Hilda's. The former was arranged at the Vicar's request because in 1898 &#8211; 23 years ago, I preached a mission in that church. He shewed me my signature in the Book. How little I could then forecast the course of my life! There were but 35 candidates. At S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hilda's there were nearly 200. We returned to the Castle immediately after the service, arriving about 10.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>Names of the Household</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Ernest Alexander<persName xml:id="5214"></persName></cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Butler</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">James Foreman</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Under&#8211;butler</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">John Taylor</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Gardener</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">William Badham<persName xml:id="4501"></persName></cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Chauffeur</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Henry James Smith</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Gardener</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Elizabeth Berry</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Cook</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Esther Clark</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Clara Oyston</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">Bertha Grey</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         </body></text></TEI>