<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[355]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Another brilliant day, and a very bad show of work! I wrote letters all the morning, that is, all that was left after I had got rid of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Storrs</hi> and Miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arnold</hi>, who pestered me about <hi rend="bold underline">another silly society for making silly girls into silly "Catholicks</hi><hi rend="bold">"!</hi> In the afternoon Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> and I strolled about in the Park, <hi rend="bold underline">chatting to miners. They all seem anxious to get back to work</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After tea <hi rend="doubleunderline">Clayton</hi><persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Holmside, where I confirmed nearly 50 candidates in a woefully mean church set on a hill. The beauty of the country, as we saw it on our way back to the Castle, was wonderful. The gorse with its wealth of golden bloom framed the road magnificently, and from this vantage ground of neighbouring splendour, we looked upon a wide expanse of hill and moorland, illumed weirdly by the setting sun. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> stopped the car at the well&#8211;known spot where the view of Durham Cathedral bursts suddenly upon the traveller's gaze, and overwhelms him by its strange unearthly dignity. The towers were bathed in a rosy light, mysteriously beautiful, and the amazing ^church^ had the aspect of a dream&#8211;woven fabric. I have never gazed on a fairer scheme: even my good William was impressed. We arrived at the Castle about 9.15 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>