<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[322]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went off to Scotland. <hi rend="italic">I went through the Reports of the Chaplains on the work of the Ordination Candidates. They are lamentable. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I rejected six out of the nine men who presented themselves for the 1</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> part of the Priests' Examination. They are ignorant and illiterate men who ought never to have been ordained the Diaconate. My sainted predecessor has much to answer for</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>Then I wrote cheques for rates &amp;c &amp;c.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Gateshead, and after tea with the Rector, went to Dunston, where we were met by the Incumbents of Whickham &amp; Dunston together with the Church officers of the latter, and were shown the proposed site for a new church. Then we returned to the Rectory, and dined, after which we went to S. Paul's Church, where I confirmed more than 70 candidates. Canon Stack<persName xml:id="5290"></persName>, who has led the parish for 24 years, has an unusual practice in the matter of confirmation. Every candidate is accompanied by two witnesses, whom he or she chooses from among the communicants. These witnesses kneel beside the candidate before the Bishop, and are held responsible for the space of one year. Everything seemed very reverent and sincere. I inquired how the practice worked, and was assured that it worked fairly well. Of course there were failures with it, as with every other part of parochial work, but on the whole Canon Stack thought it was beneficial, and would be reluctant to give it up.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>