<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">S. Matthias, Thursday, February 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The collect for this day with its significant reference to "the traitor Judas" will always in my memory stand connected with my consecration to the episcopate, since it was circulated as a suitable prayer for the use of those who were opposing my appointment to Hereford. And it moves in me rather apprehension than resentment, for there is so much in me which is not inaptly as pictured by the traitor Judas that I tremble lest, like Caiaphas, my enemies unwittingly uttered a prophecy!</p>
         <p>We had before us the subject of Clerical Poverty, which was well introduced by the Bishop of Wakefield. I seconded his motion in a speech which appeared to command general approval. My object in speaking was to link the effort to improve clerical incomes with that to improve clerical quality. After the session had ended I went to a hair–dresser &amp; had my hair cut and shampooed. Then I lunched at the Railway station, &amp; returned to the Castle, being met at Darlington by <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> with the car.</p>
         <p>I went through the correspondence with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and then wrote to Lord Muir Mackenzie about the Parochial Councils (Powers) Bill. It has now been formally laid before the Ecclesiastical Committee of the Privy Council [sic], where, I fear, there is little hope of holding it up. Then I read some of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Crees's Essays in order that I be able to thank him for sending me a copy.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>