<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[114]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, January 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"I know perfectly well that an insurance office would tell me that at 86 one must count the year before you as probably the last year of one's life. I admit this. But years ago I chanced upon a sentence <hi rend="bold underline">of Littre's to the effect that one ought always to plan one's work as though one were going to live for ever, &amp; work at it as though one were going to die tomorrow</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>He, I believe, really acted upon this maxim. It is not one which I have ever had the vigour to adopt, or in effect to pursue. Still, one of the best friends I ever possessed tried to teach me that "in all labour there is profit." Even this dictum is of course only a half&#8211;truth, but it gives one a little patience in the attempt to get through the 'Conflict of Laws. 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> edition'."</p>
         </div>
         <p>This quotation from a letter of dear old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dicey</hi><persName xml:id="403"></persName>, which reached me this morning, is too characteristic, and too intrinsically precious, to be let slip in the dusty oblivion which befalls private correspondence. It is illustrated by the tireless industry and unflagging interest in human affairs which I wondered at in Dicey, when first I met him 35 years ago, &amp; which I wonder at still when, at the age of 86, he is still eagerly working. The religious interpretation of life; "as ever in the great Taskmaster's eye", is surely better exhibited by such a man, half Quaker, half Unitarian, than by most of us professed Exponents of Religion!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[115]</hi></p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">d </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">T. L. Lomax</hi><persName xml:id="5279"></persName>, Vicar of Ferryhill, came to see me about the projected division of his parish, and also about his scheme for a Retreat House. I insisted upon the following points:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. The Bishop would have to approve the clergyman in charge.</p>
         <p>2. The said clergyman w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have to be licensed, and therefore subject to diocesan control</p>
         <p>3. The Retreat House w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have to be a stable institution</p>
         <p>4. The Committee of Management w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have to be approved by the Bishop.</p>
         <p>5. The ceremonial of the chapel &amp;c. w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> have to be approved by the Bishop.</p>
         <p>I made some comments on his "four points of doctrine", &amp; suggested that the language should be modified or explained in a note.</p>
         <p>The rain fell in torrents all through the day, so that I did not go out but remained in my study. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> motored into Durham in order to attend some fool&#8211;function of a children's party. I delved among the masses of old sermons in order to find something to preach to the sectaries in <placeName xml:id="106">Westminster Chapel</placeName> on January 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, for I despair of getting anything fresh written. The War has made so deep a chasm between the period before 1914, and the period since, that all the sermons written in the former are curiously obsolete. I might as well make a bonfire of all my sermons, though they constitute almost the sole memorials of my life! Paternal affection withholds my hand at present, but my heart hardens steadily &amp; I doubt not that before long I shall consummate the sacrifice.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>