<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[119]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Epiphany, Sunday, January 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Between the period of national honour and complete degeneracy, there is usually an interval of national vanity, during which examples of virtue are recounted and admired without being imitated."</p>
         <p>Robert Hall in 1793.</p>
         </div>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 10 minutes after 9 o'clock, and motored to Sunderland. Shortly after leaving Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring a tyre was punctured. This incident made us five minutes late at Christ Church. Here I preached, &amp; celebrated the Holy Communion. After service we lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi>Cullough, the Vicar. Then we went to Bishopwearmouth Rectory, where I rested until 4.30 p.m., when we went to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Gabriel's. Here I had tea in the Parish Room, &amp; there talked with the Church Council, and their wives. Then followed Evensong in the Parish Church which was crowded. I preached again on behalf of the C.M.S.<orgName xml:id="124"></orgName> In the vestry I spoke a few words to the Choir, &amp; then explained the pastoral staff to the boys. The Archdeacon of Uganda was staying at the Rectory. After the ladies had retired, <hi rend="italic">Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> gave me a truly grievous account of several dishonest &amp; disreputable clergymen </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">whom my sainted predecessor admitted to the diocese. This depresses me greatly, for the diocese cannot be better than its clergy</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi>The weather again became quite warm.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>