<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[341]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Chief Constable of the County Police sends me the telephone message which he received from Ferryhill on Thursday night. It is interesting as an example of the inaccuracy of official reports, as well as a contemporary record of a specific incident by an eye&#8211;witness.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"From Inspector on duty Ferryhill. 8.45 p.m. 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> May, 1921. The Lord Bishop of Durham was at Ferryhill tonight at a Confirmation service  ̶  he spoke on the Strike, and at one time I thought there was going to be trouble: as he was passing through the village, some miners jeered at him. The Bishop stopped his car, got out, and made a speech. By the time he had finished speaking, a crowd of about 500 persons had collected, and <hi rend="bold underline">they were so pleased with what he said – and he did not mince matters  ̶</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">that they cheered him loudly</hi>. The Bishop then left in his car. I believe the Bishop did more good by that speech than all the speakers put together who have come to Ferryhill since the Strike started."</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I did not speak on the Strike at the Confirmation: and I did not get out of my car, but spoke from it. There was some cheering when I went off, but I think it is excessive to say that I was cheered 'loudly'. Still, the record is interesting</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[342]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">The Edinburgh Sir Walter Scott Club</hi> have asked me to be President for next year in succession to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Robert Munro K.C. M.P. Secretary for Scotland. The only duty of the office is to occupy the chair, and propose the memory of Sir Walter Scott at the annual dinner of the Club in November. I shall have to do this in November 1922. It is a compliment which appeals to me as the successor of "honoured Barrington". I replied as follows:</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear Sir</p>
         <p>I have to thank you for your letter of the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> inst. in which you convey to me the invitation of the Council of The Edinburgh Sir Walter Scott Club to be President for next year. I appreciate very highly the compliment implied by that invitation, and, alike as the successor of "honoured Barrington" whose relations with Sir Walter are part of the tradition of this House, and as a devoted admirer of the romances which charmed my boyhood and now relieve the anxieties of middle age, I cannot hesitate in accepting the proposal so courteously made.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>Kenneth Sanderson Esq. W.S.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>