<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[312]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I squandered the day in dictating letters, preparing a speech for the House of Lords, reading the newspapers which are full of the scandalous Archdeacon<persName xml:id="5282"></persName>, and finally in going to <hi rend="bold underline">Darlington and meeting Archbishop<persName xml:id="2166"></persName> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">S&#x00F6;derblom<persName xml:id="2203"></persName></hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>They came from Oxford, where they had been staying with the Headlams<persName xml:id="552"><persName xml:id="553"></persName></persName>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[</hi>Diogenes' sketch (of Theophrastus B.C. 370&#8211;285) ends with the quotation of some sayings attributed to him, of which the most noteworthy are 'Nothing costs us so dear as the waste of time'. 'One had better trust an unbridled horse than an undigested harangue'.<hi rend="bold">]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">S&#x00F6;derblom</hi> has preached in Peterborough Cathedral, and carried his medieval staff with him. Rather to my astonishment he has brought this very precious heirloom of his see with him. He tells me that the Bishop of P. wore mitre and cope. I told him that the Archbishop of Canterbury had never used these baubles, &amp; had too much sense to start doing so now after they had been disused in his see for 350 years, or more. <hi rend="underline">S. professes himself opposed to the adoption of desertion as a ground of divorce: alleging that it has been the easy victim of collusion, &amp; has certainly lowered the standard of marriage. But I took the impression that this was not the wily Swede's real mind, but rather an attitude adopted for use in England, where it pleases greatly the English bishops</hi>!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>