<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[358]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the volume of Plato, having read through in M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Fowler's excellent translation the following Dialogues&#8211;Euthyphro, The Apology, Crito, Phoedo, Phaedrus. The closeness of the night rendered sleep difficult: it was fortunate that I was so well&#8211;armed against sleeplessness.</p>
         <p>I baptized <hi rend="doubleunderline">Martin Francis Tallents</hi> at 3 p.m. in <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName> West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi>. Fedarb turned up in the vestry, &amp; had some talk. He is very loyal to the old days. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Stephen Tallents</hi> is going to Dublin as private secretary to the new Viceroy. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bridget</hi><persName xml:id="1650"></persName> may be pardoned for feeling a measure of anxiety.</p>
         <p>I bought a little book, hardly more than a pamphlet, by <hi rend="doubleunderline">T. R. Glover</hi><persName xml:id="3000"></persName> "<hi rend="underline">The Free Churches and Re&#8211;union</hi>". It is cordially endorsed in a prefatory note by <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Clifford</hi><persName xml:id="57"></persName> as "<hi rend="underline">expressing the convictions &amp; experiences of Baptists everywhere (as well as of many Free Churchmen outside the Baptist hosts,) of the ten millions of us in the States, in Canada, Australasia, &amp; at home</hi>". It affirms decidedly, even aggressively, the attitude of Protestant Nonconformity on the subject of the ministry, &amp; suggests a present policy of exchanging pulpits and intercommunion. It is evident that in this quarter the Lambeth Appeal falls very flat indeed.</p>
         <p>I dined at the Caf&#x00E9; Monico with the English Association and proposed <hi rend="underline">the Toast of the Ass</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi>. Prothero<persName xml:id="1394"></persName>, Lord Ernle, presided and made some amusing speeches. Miss Elizabeth Robins<persName xml:id="5296"></persName>, author of "The Magnetic North", and Lord Buxton were also guests &amp; made interesting speeches.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>