<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[348]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whit&#8211;Tuesday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"It may interest a few philosophers to know the truth, but the peoples will always prefer dreams."</p>
         <p>Gustave le Bon.</p>
         <p>Not in all history can one cite an example of a belief destroyed or reduced by means of refutation.</p>
         <p>Gustave le Bon.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I motored to Darlington, and there took train at 1.58 p.m. to Scarborough. At York I had time enough to get my hair trimmed. In the carriage was Fisher, the minister of S. Cuthbert's. He introduced himself to me, for I certainly should not have recognized him. At Scarborough, where I arrived at 6.15 p.m., I put up at the Grand Hotel at the cost of the Co&#8211;operators. At 7.30 p.m. the meeting was held in a Hall called Olympia. It was crowded, something over 1000 people being present. I spoke for 45 minutes on "<hi rend="underline">Democracy and Education</hi>", and was well received, though there certainly were opponents in the room, and I suspect that much that I said was unpalatable. The total absence of the accustomed eulogies probably surprised them. But, whatever their sentiments, they kept them under decent control. The Chairman, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Rae of Sunderland, walked back to the Hotel with me. He expressed agreement with what I said, but I should doubt his feeling it judicious to do so openly.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>