<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[47]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Auckland Castle</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">We left Sauchieburn</hi> shortly after 10 a.m. in a violent rain which continued until about <lb/>3 p.m., when the weather improved, and the last stage of our journey, when we had entered the Bishoprick, the sun shone brightly on a vivid rain&#8211;washed country.  At one point on our journey, between Denny and Falkirk, the road was submerged, and Leng drove the car through the water with caution and trepidation.  We had lunch at Berwick, sitting in the car, &amp; devouring as much as we could of the lavish supply of varied victuals with which our hostess <hi rend="superscript">^</hi>had<hi rend="superscript">^</hi> provided us.  We had tea in the Railway Hotel, &amp; there I was spoken to by strangers who claimed acquaintance with me, and who, I think on reflection, were Colonel &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Joicey.  My inability to remember names and faces is a great practical weakness. The views of Lumley Castle and Durham Cathedral, to say nothing of the country, were wonderful. We arrived at Auckland Castle shortly after 6 p.m. having driven 180 miles.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[48]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> announces that Neville Talbot is to be translated from Pretoria to Newcastle N. S. W.  I am unfeignedly glad that he is disposed of in the Antipodes, for some years, if not for the term of his natural life.  When I recall his performances at the Lambeth Conference, I must needs think that the Church of England is well rid of a man, so persistent, so puzzle&#8211;headed, and so pretentious. His loquacity is irrepressible, and will be felt in the Synods of Australia!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Coulton</hi><hi rend="italic"> sends me his pamphlet – "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Malta – and Beyond.  The real meaning of the conflict between the Vatican and the British Traditions of Government</hi><hi rend="italic">".  It is acute, learned, effective, and extraordinarily well&#8211;written.  Why will it (as it assuredly will) fall flat?  Why did </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Geoffrey</hi><hi rend="italic"> treat </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Coulton</hi><hi rend="italic"> with something less than justice, and a good deal less than courtesy?  Why should the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> be so very careful not to offend the Papists?</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
