<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[56]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Very warm: fine: high wind.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Stack</hi>, the lay&#8211;reader from S. Andrew's, Tudhoe, came to tell me that the Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marsh</hi>, is clearly dying in the Nursing Home, whereto he was carried some weeks ago.  This is an untoward event, for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Marsh</hi> was certainly one of the better incumbents, whose influence on his people was visibly spiritual.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Clifford Wilson</hi>, an Ordination candidate, who has just completed his first year at Oxford (Keble) came to lunch, &amp; then walked around the Park with me. He seems keen, &amp; intelligent. He says that there is a strong Evangelical group among the undergraduates at Keble.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Edwin Charles Aubrey</hi>, aged 21, &amp; residing at Witton Park, of which parish his grandfather was vicar, came to see me with a view to being accepted as a candidate for Ordination.  He has a bequest of &#x00A3;250, which he desires to expend in getting a degree.  But the poor lad has had no other education than that of an elementary school, &amp; has 'loafed' since he left school.  I told him to pass matriculation, &amp; then, if his purpose held, to see me again.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[57]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the evening I received a telegram telling me that Marsh was dead. He was ordained in 1896, so that his ministry did not extend beyond 34 years. He had only held the parish for 5 years. I was impressed by the hold he seemed to have over the youths of his congregation, and by the simplicity and devoutness of their worship. There are now vacant the following parishes:&#8211;</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Christ Church, Sunderland (Canon M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cullagh)</item>
            <item>Pittington (Boddy)</item>
            <item>Dinsdale with Sockburn (Greatorix)</item>
            <item>S. Andrew's, Tudhoe Grange (Marsh)</item>
            <item>Hebburn (Marr)</item>
         </list>
         <p>Probably also, S Ignatius, Sunderland</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ropner, the wife of Leonard Ropner, of Stockton, has died rather unexpectedly.  She was a kind&#8211;hearted woman, much liked in the place where she lived.  Her husband, who was devoted to her, will be greatly afflicted.  He is now the Conservative candidate for the Stockton division, but whether he will have the heart to go on with his political venture without the support of his wife is, I should imagine, doubtful. Her popularity was an electoral asset of some value.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
