<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[53]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A bright morning infinitely welcome after the rain.  I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> assisted, but did not communicate as he was to celebrate later at Shildon.  There were 7 communicants including [symbol] <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>. I used the Collects for S. Matthew's Day &amp; the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sunday after Trinity, &amp; the Epistle and Gospel for the former.</p>
         <p>I spent most of the morning in writing a long [symbol] <hi rend="italic">letter to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Bishop Lawrence</hi><hi rend="italic"> thanking him for the gift of a little biographical sketch of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Phillips Brooks</hi><hi rend="italic">, into which he had introduced his own personal impressions and reminiscences of the great man, for whom he had an unbounded admiration, and whom he succeeded in the bishoprick of Massachusetts.  As I read the book, I realized more vividly than ever how remote </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Phillips Brooks</hi><hi rend="italic">, and his generation, are from the present age.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">F. D. Maurice</hi><hi rend="italic">, who was his spiritual master, was totally uncritical in temper and habit, so that his teaching seems to be resting at every point on mishandled or misunderstood texts. It is as remote from us as the patristic literature which, though often beautiful and acute, is everywhere vitiated by its treatment of Scripture.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[54]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> accompanied me to Hart where I read the lessons and preached in the old church. The roof has been restored, that is, replaced at an expenditure of &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">500</hi>, the old roof having been destroyed by the death watch beetle. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi>, the quaint old Vicar, desired to mark the completion of the work by a special service. There was, however, nothing special about the service except the fact that the Bishop was the preacher.  My text was <hi rend="underline">S. Matthew xxii. 34&#8211;40</hi>, and my subject, '<hi rend="underline">Religion</hi>'.  The congregation was very attentive, but cannot be considered large, for the population of Hart is said to be 1350, and the number in church could not have been more than 150.  After the service we looked at the beautifully carved 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century font, which is said to have been buried during the Commonwealth, &amp; thereby to have survived the general wrecking of church furniture, which marked the reign of the Saints. We were back in the Castle by 8.45 p.m.  I noticed that the crops were standing in the fields woefully discoloured.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
