<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[55]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Heaver</hi><persName xml:id="5584"></persName> came to talk over the proposal that he should become Secretary of the Industrial Christian Fellowship.  I advised him to decline it, pointing out that it would hardly satisfy the pledges on which he was ordained: &amp; that it would be a mistake to retire from pastoral work just when he had learned how to do it.  He seemed to accept this view.</p>
         <p>I walked in the Park with <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">c</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Cullagh</hi>, who expressed approval of my sketch of an address to the medial students. </p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to Durham, where I called on the Bishop of Jarrow, and discussed diocesan business with him.  He had just concluded, as returning officer, the ludicrous task of conducting the election of diocesan representatives in the Church Assembly.  <hi rend="bold underline">By enormous efforts at the 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> hour a sufficiency of nominations to keep out M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Probert (!) was secured.  Nothing could be more farcical than these elections</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  We went on to Gateshead where I attended a meeting in Christ Church Hall of the Seamen's Mission.  There were hardly more than 100 persons present though the Mayor was in the Chair, and the Bishop was one of the speakers. Spencer Wade who had organized the meeting ought to have done better.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
