<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[3]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>	
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Scotland</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My post brought the important news that Canon <hi rend="doubleunderline">McCullagh</hi>, Vicar of Christ Church, Sunderland, desires to resign his benefice.  He is 73, and has worked in the diocese for 46 years.  His health requires his retirement from active duty.  The net value of his living is set down as £682, and the population as 4197. The patronage is mine.</p>
         <p>[symbol] M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Körsteiner</hi> went away after breakfast.  I received a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi> &amp; from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gerald Rainbow</hi>.</p>
         <p>We said goodbye to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Berry with rather doubtful minds.  She is going to South Africa to see a son, &amp; it does not seem <hi rend="underline">very</hi> improbable that she should elect to spend the remainder of her life, a decision which would deprive us of an excellent cook, who is also a trusted friend. However she declared her full purpose of returning to us, &amp; on that understanding we parted.</p>
         <p>We left the Castle about 10.30 a.m. and motored by way of Barnard Castle, Appleby, &amp; Penrith to Carlisle which we reached about 1 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[4]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Here we left Fearne to continue her journey to Helensburgh by train: &amp; ourselves went on to Murraythwaite. We lunched off sandwiches by the roadside a little way from Gretna, and arrived at our destination shortly after 2.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>We found M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray at home, &amp; sate with her in the garden until tea–time, after which we walked in the fields.  Eleanor joined us.  Harvesting was in active progress.  The crop (oats) looked abundant, but it had been badly "laid" by the recent storms.  However the "reaper &amp; binder" machine did its work effectively &amp; expeditiously.  If the weather will but be propitious much of the harvest may yet be saved.  Tonight the weather is delightful, the country seen in the level rays of the declining sun looked most beautiful.  <hi rend="italic">The place is filled with memories for me. I saw the present house in building: I officiated in the parish church at Buff's wedding, &amp; I buried her father.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
