<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[10]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, September 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Rain to start with, but developing into sunshine.  I worked at the Article, (of which I am heartily sick,) and then strolled in the garden with Major Lake &amp; Eleanor.  After lunch, we drove to <hi rend="bold underline">Caerlaverock Castle, the ancient seat of the Maxwells</hi>, now a picturesque ruin. In the early 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century a residence in the style of a French Chateau was built inside the medieval fortress: but both were ruined in 1640.  We went on to Dumfries, where I got my hair cut. Then we called on M<hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi> Morgan, &amp; had tea.  Her house – Rockhall – is a typical Scottish mansion.  It was the house of the Griersons, &amp; enters into 'Redgauntlet'. We were shown over by M<hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">rs</hi> Morgan, a pleasant woman, who told us the ghost stories &amp; laughed at what she half–believed.  Also we visited Ruthwelf Church and saw the wonderful Celtic Cross which gives dignity to a very mean building. We read the inscription on a tombstone in the churchyard were commemorates a minister of the parish who in the XVII<hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi> century held the office for 54 years &amp; had no less than 31 children.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[11]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Lake</hi> has recently returned from service in the far East.  He gives a most unfavourable account of the American Navy, which he has seen when the ships visit the ports.  The men have so much money and throw it away in such continuing debauchery that they degrade the reputation of all Europeans, and have a most demoralizing effect on the men of other navies.  <hi rend="underline">The proportion of venereal disease among the American crews is monstrous – 50 per cent</hi>.  This evidence connects itself in my mind with the statement, which I saw some months ago in the '<hi rend="underline">Eugenics Review'</hi>, to the effect that, at their great 'jamboree' of Boy Scouts recently held at (I think) Birkenhead, <hi rend="underline">the ill morals of the American contingent was apparent and distinctive</hi>.  If the picture of American Society which is given in Judge <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lindsey</hi>'s notorious volumes, &amp; in popular American fiction, can be accepted as even an approximation to the facts, <hi rend="underline">there can be no doubt that sexual morality in the great Republic had 'crashed'</hi>. The official statistics of crime and divorce point to a moral which really cannot be missed save by the wilfully blind.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
