<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[67]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">["]Some read secular literature for pleasure, taking delight in the inventions of elegant language of the poets, but others study the literature for the sake of scholarship, that by their reading they may learn to detect the errors of the Gentiles and may devoutly apply what they find useful in them to the use of sacred learning.  Such men study secular literature in a laudable manner.  So for Bede.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Taking this salutary instructions to heart, let the detractors of those who study the poets henceforth hold their peace, &amp; let not those who are ignorant of these things require that others should be as ignorant of them as themselves, for this is the consolation of the wretched. And therefore let every man see that his own intentions are upright and he may thus make of every subject, observing the limitation of virtue, a study acceptable to God. And if he have found profit in poetry, as the great Virgil relates "that he had done in Ennius, he will not have done amiss.["]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Richard de Bury "Philobiblon' p. 223. Ed. by Ernest C Thomas.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[68]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I worked at my speech on Virgil, and was fortunate enough to remember my great predecessor, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Richard de Bury</hi>, that most ardent of medieval book lovers. In the Philobiblon I found some serviceable references to Virgil.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sandys</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">History of Classical Scholarship</hi> – a book which I have long possessed, but never yet read, turned out to be "full of meat".  These with the references and discussions in the books of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dill, Glover</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ward Fowler</hi> provide ample materials for a post&#8211;prandial speech.</p>
         <p>After lunch Charles and I walked found the Park, Bryden assisted by Ashton &amp; William were sawing up beech trees for the Castle.</p>
         <p>Beck, in a high state of excitement, &amp; probably some pain, was worrying a hedge&#8211;hog, but Elland rescued the creature before it had been killed.</p>
         <p>Lady Thurlow arrived. Evidently she and her husband were well&#8211;pleased to get to Sedgefield.</p>
         <p>The weather has been still and fine.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
