<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A heavy dew on the ground, and a mist in the air proclaimed that Autumn had arrived. As the day advanced the weather became hot, &amp; we seemed to be back again in the summer.</p>
         <p>A note from the Rural Dean informed me that yet another incumbent has been laid low.  Old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Greenway</hi>, the Vicar of Eldon, is in the infectious hospital with diphtheria – an ill disease for so old a man.  He was ordained as long ago as 1883.  Within 3 weeks 4 incumbents have fallen out of the fighting line: &amp; how to provide for their parishes is a hard problem. In the old days, when there were as many assistant curates as vicars there was no difficulty about getting through intervals of illness, Holiday, &amp; vacancy. But now that everybody is single – handed the case is widely different.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> looked in on me as he passed through the town on the way to the Yorkshire cottage, where he will spend the remainder of his holiday.  Only when he is absent do I realize how indispensable he has become.  </p>
         <p>I made a prodigious effort to clear up my study before leaving for Scotland tomorrow, but my success was trivial while my fatigue was extreme.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The newspapers report the death of old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Spooner</hi>, long the Warden of New College, at the age of 86.  Very rapidly the generation which was in power when I was young is passing away: it has long ceased to hold office. My generation is coming into the duty of resignation.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lillingston</hi> came to see me, and explained the action of the Dean &amp; Chapter in the matter of the minor&#8211;canon, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wall</hi>, whose foolish &amp; offensive observations on the Cathedral Body in a lecture at Sacriston this summer have given general offence. I thought they oughtn't to make a martyr of him, but they hold, perhaps rightly, than, in his own interest, he ought to leave Durham. It is a regrettable business.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Seaton&#8211;Christophers</hi> went away this morning.  They seem to have enjoyed their visit.  I gave him a copy of my "<hi rend="underline">Notes on Spiritual Healing</hi>".</p>
         <p>I have <hi rend="underline">not</hi> succeeded in finishing the short article on "Ought the Establishment to be maintained?" which I rashly promised to the Editor of "The Political Quarterly".</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
