<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[37]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A brilliant morning. Ella &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mitchell left the house soon after 10 a.m. in order to motor to Helensburgh, and see divers folks there.</p>
         <p>The post brought yet another incumbent's resignation.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Greatorex</hi>, Rector of Dinsdale with Sockburn, resigns his living on the grounds that he is 77, and has lost his voice.  I wrote to him accepting his resignation, and to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Cecil Ferens</hi> directing him to do what is necessary.  <hi rend="underline">Then I read through again the Encyclical Letter and the Resolutions of the Lambeth Conference. The South India Scheme, as there presented, has an excessively</hi> pretentious appearance.  I feel still what I felt strongly 10 years ago that this much vaunted method of seeking reunion on the basis of the episcopate while affecting to admit the ecclesiastical character of the non&#8211;episcopal churches, &amp; even the reality of their ministries, is paradoxical, and will lead nowhere.  In spite of much rather pompous language, which suggests that an epoch&#8211;making new departure has been made in South India, I incline to think that, save in the temper of the church, which is admirably charitable, no movement has been made from the old impossible demand.  <hi rend="underline">Episcopacy is still one of the essentials of Christianity.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[38]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Saturday has a short review of Inge's new book, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Christian Ethics &amp; Modern Problems</hi><hi rend="italic">".  According to the reviewer, the Dean 'finds nothing further removed than institutional religion from the spirit &amp; intention of Christ.'  Yet he has spent his life as the officer of an Established Church, &amp; holds a great position in its hierarchy. The Lambeth Encyclical sets forth a very lofty doctrine of the Church, &amp; its character as the production of a gathering of Bishops certifies sufficiently its institutional character.</hi>
           
<hi rend="italic">"With the ascetic temper," we are told, the Dean is "in declared sympathy": yet he is by no means an ascetic in personal habit, and, indeed, might almost be described as a favourite in "Society".  His wife is 'heart and soul' in 'the world'.  "The Dean has no belief in Christians ever being more than a small minority", yet he defends the Establishment which assumes, and is only defensible on the assumption, that the citizens generally are Christians. He is in feeling, and largely in belief, a Quaker, though he adorns the hierarchy of a church which disallows Quakerdom at every point.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[39]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Our life is but a Winter's Day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Some only </hi><hi rend="italic underline">breakfast</hi><hi rend="italic"> and away.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Others to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Dinner</hi><hi rend="italic"> stay and are full fed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The oldest only </hi><hi rend="italic underline">sups</hi><hi rend="italic"> and goes to bed.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Largest his Debt who lingers out the Day.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Who goes the soonest has the least to pay.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A correspondent in the</hi> 
<hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> (Sept. 13</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> 1930) states that this epitaph is '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">in the churchyard of S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> Bunyan on the grave of a child</hi><hi rend="italic">'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The 'Scotsman' states that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Arnold Lupton</hi> (83) of Westminster left property of the gross value of &#x00A3;5896.  He directed that not less than &#x00A3;400 &amp;, if necessary, as much as &#x00A3;500 should be expended on his cremation and funeral expenses.  I remember the man, a cadaverous looking fellow, who was a fanatic "anti" everything that was patriotic or sanitary!  He sent me a mass of poisonous literature advocating resistance to Vaccination, &amp;, if my memory does not betray me, he made himself conspicuous during the War as a Pacifist.  I doubt if any notion produces so rank a crop of mischievous cranks of his type as our own.   It is part of the price we have to pay for Nonconformity. Individualism has literally run amok in Great Britain. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[40]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>"I enclose the brief and dignified lines engraved in exquisite lettering on a mural stone at Coddenham in memory of an 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century vicar.</p>
         <p style="text&#8211;align: justify;">Solid in Diversity</p>
         <p style="text&#8211;align: justify;">Laborious in 's Ministrie</p>
         <p style="text&#8211;align: justify;">Heavenly in Societie,</p>
         <p style="text&#8211;align: justify;">A Mirror of sound Pietie."</p>
         <p>[v. Times. Sept: 11<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1930.]</p>
         <p>Welldon has a letter in the same issue of the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> on "Christian Unity. The Testimony of Lambeth". It is platitudinous and mainly mischievous.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Gilbert and to Ernest.</p>
         <p>Ella and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Mitchell returned just before dinner reporting a successful expedition.</p>
         <p>After dinner I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jack Carr</hi>.  His time for leaving the diocese draws near.  He seems determined to undertake missionary work in Africa, though, so far as my judgment of him goes, he is better fitted for work at home.  "<hi rend="underline">The Spirit bloweth where it listeth, &amp; thou canst not tell whence it cometh or whither it goeth. So is everyone that is born of the Spirit</hi>."</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
