<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[17]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>We left Murraythwaite after breakfast.  The weather was threatening when we started at 10.15 a.m.: but it improved as the day advanced, &amp; ended brilliantly.  I was not feeling well, and the motoring did not better my condition, with the result that, when we arrived at Daljarrocks, where we had arranged to lunch, I felt sufficiently indisposed to accept with gratitude the hospitable proposal that we should stay the night. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Coltman, her sister, and her daughter Lillian were at home, but Major Copland was in England shooting partridges.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I retired to bed, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">read through the rest of Glover's book on Virgil</hi><hi rend="italic">.  It is interesting, acute, learned, and suggestive.  I think it provides me with material for a sufficient 'after dinner' speech in proposing the toast of 'Virgil' at the dinner in Durham in October.  The </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">longer I live, the more I lament the mishandling of my boyish years.</hi><hi rend="italic">  If, instead of reading an amalgam of history and controversial divinity, I had been properly grounded in the classics, I should have been incomparably better equipped for my present situation.  As it is I have to live intellectually "from hand to mouth'!</hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
