<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[51]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Lay Helpers Association</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>There came to lunch a young man named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hall</hi>, who is in receipt of a grant from the Diocesan Fund as an Ordination candidate.  His parents are opposed to his being ordained, but an incumbent near Middlesbrough has hitherto financed him.  Now, however, according to his own statement, he has "broken" with his patron <hi rend="bold underline">because he would not consent to be legally adopted</hi>. He was going back to his parents to invoke their assistance. I told him to inform me of his parents' decision, &amp; so let him go.  It is an odd tangle.</p>
         <p>About 120 lay&#8211;readers attended the annual meeting.  At 3.30 p.m. there was a service in the chapel when I admitted new readers, among them the recently retired Director of Education, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson</hi>.  I gave an address from the words: "<hi rend="underline">Then saith He unto His disciples, The harvest truly is plenteous, but the labourers are few. Pray ye, therefore, the Lord of the harvest, that He send forth labourers into His harvest</hi>".  Then followed tea in the large dining room; &amp; then the Conference in the State Room.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Parry&#8211;Evans</hi> read a paper on the "<hi rend="underline">Lay&#8211;reader's duty in Church – the Lessons &amp; the Address</hi>".</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[52]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It was a very carefully prepared paper, and admirably expressed and delivered, but I could not help suspecting that it had been originally composed for a gathering of clergy. In any case it was far better suited for clergy than for lay&#8211;readers. However it seemed to make a great impression on the company. I made a short speech in a lighter vein than is my wont, but I didn't want the good men to go away with "swelled heads". They went off shortly before 7 p.m., apparently well pleased.</p>
         <p>Then Frank my former butler's boy came to see me. He is a footman now in the employment of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Marshall Field.</p>
         <p>I wrote to William in Bulawayo, telling him of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Berry's visit to South Africa.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Modern Churchman</hi> containing the papers read at the recent Conference of Modern Churchmen in Oxford arrived, &amp; I read through most of it.  The most abject subordination of the Church to the State is urged, indeed, it is scarcely excessive to say that the idea of the Church as a Divine society has no place in these men's Christianity.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
