<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[205]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">School Confirmation</hi>.</p>
         <p>There was a considerable fog at daybreak, but it had mostly cleared by 10.40 p.m. [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] when I left the Castle in order to motor to Durham for the School Confirmation, a function which generally gives me pleasure.</p>
         <p>Only 27 boys and 3 choristers were presented – the smallest number on record.  But the number of the School has fallen rather seriously, &amp; we are entering on the "lean years" of the War, when few boys were born.  I spoke on the Collect for the week, &amp; was listened to very attentively.  On the whole I was pleased with the service.  Afterwards, I had a few words with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Derek</hi>.</p>
         <p>Then I went to the Castle, &amp; licensed five assistant curates, after which I returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>I wrote a short letter to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Baldwin</hi>, thanking him for the decision to vote so handsome a contribution out of the Harkness Fund to the Durham Castle Fund.</p>
         <p>The fog had again become dense when Charles &amp; I left the Castle at 6 p.m. in order to go to Stockton.  There I dedicated a Mission Room.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bott</hi> had got together five of his young men, all educated at the Secondary School, who are now preparing for Ordination.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
