<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[188]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Downing about the projected re–arrangement of buildings at the Castle gate, taking care to display no great ardour for it, but not rejecting it </hi><hi rend="italic underline">tout court</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Also, I wrote to the Bishop of Coventry (Lisle Carr) who, to my surprize, is evidently much</hi> 
<hi rend="italic bold underline">perturbed at the thought that I should officiate at the marriage of an innocent divorcée in his diocese</hi><hi rend="italic">.  I sent his letter to </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Harris</hi><hi rend="italic">, suggesting that, in the circumstances, he might acquiesce in a registry wedding, followed by a service in church.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I walked round the Park, &amp; had some talk with the unemployed youths, who were playing football there.</p>
         <p>I went to Spennymoor, &amp; presided at a meeting of the British &amp; Foreign Bible Society in the Methodist Chapel. It had been organized by the Vicar. The Minister, Henderson, said that he used often to hear me preach in Westminster, &amp; that, when I was Dean of Durham, I shewed him &amp; a company of ministers over the Cathedral. The weather became foggy.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[189]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A Scot and Jesuit, hand in hand,</p>
         <p>First taught the world to say</p>
         <p>That subjects ought to have command,</p>
         <p>And monarchs to obey.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">George Buchanan</hi>, in his <hi rend="underline">De Jure Regni apud Scotos</hi>, 1579, justified the deposition of Mary, and the Jesuit <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mariana</hi> in his <hi rend="underline">De Rege et Regis Institutione</hi> in 1599 defended tyrannicide.  The combination of these knavish sophists is indicated in squib quoted above.  <hi rend="underline">It was produced during the English Civil War</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Old </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> James Wilson</hi><hi rend="italic">, who is now 94 years old, has a letter in the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">' accusing me of following into "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">the old and too familiar fallacy that the Church is alone spiritual &amp; the state secular</hi><hi rend="italic">" because I spoke in my letter of "the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">spiritual society</hi><hi rend="italic">".  He still cleaves to the identification of Church and State which was maintained by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hooker</hi><hi rend="italic">, &amp; expressed in the Tudor policy of religious uniformity enforced by law. It is probably not worth while embarking on a controversy with the venerable man on that issue, which is really exhausted, &amp; may, perhaps, with some reason, be said to have been formally disallowed by the Enabling Act.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
