<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
      
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[142]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>William Brook came to lunch, &amp; afterwards walked round the Park.  He has been staying at the Gateshead Rectory, and would like to have a title from the Parish of Gateshead.  But he has received grants from the Diocese of Norwich, and is thereby "earmarked" for work therein.  He prefers an industrial to a rural parish.  I told him to write directly to the Bishop of Norwich, &amp; state his case.  I found him an ingenious &amp; interesting companion on a walk.  He told me that he had been bred a Wesleyan: that he had passed through a phase of acute Anglo Catholicism: that he had been familiar with Buchmanism at Oxford: that he was greatly attracted by the Cowley Fathers: that he went to Confession to them about twice in the year.  On the whole he gave a rather re&#8211;assuring account of Oxford.  D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> McCullagh joined us in the Park.  He expressed approval of the new issue of the 'Bishoprick'.</p>
         <p>I wrote cheques for the household accounts and for the half&#8211;year's rates.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[143]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Copies of the Bishoprick were sent to the following:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>31.</cell>
               <cell>The Dean of Bristol.	</cell>
               <cell>40.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Bishop Knox.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>32.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Bishop Eden.</cell>
               <cell>41.</cell>
               <cell>Bishop Talbot.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>33.</cell>
               <cell>Sir Harry Reichel.</cell>
               <cell>42.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Professor Burkitt.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>34.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Canon Osborne.</cell>
               <cell>43.</cell>
               <cell>Sir William Gray.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>35.</cell>
               <cell>Canon Boot.	</cell>
               <cell>44.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Bishop Wood.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>36.</cell>
               <cell>Miss Haldane.</cell>
               <cell>45.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Bishop Wood.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>37.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Xan Wynne&#8211;Willson.</cell>
               <cell>46.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Archbishop of Dublin.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>38.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] Xan Wynne&#8211;Willson.</cell>
               <cell>47.</cell>
               <cell>Headmaster of Westminster.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>39.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] John McKitterick.</cell>
               <cell>48.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] L.R. Phelps.</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>The Obituary notice in the Times contains the announcement:&#8211;</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Fawkes</hi><hi rend="italic"> – On Nov. 2 1930 at Brighton the Rev</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic"> Alfred Fawkes, Vicar of Ashby Sr Ledgers &amp; Hon. Chaplain to the Bishop of Durham, aged 80.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">It was but a few days ago that I received a letter from him explaining that he could not come to us as had been arranged, since he had been ordered to Brighton by his doctor.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">His death completes the trinity of losses from the narrow &amp; shrinking ranks of my personal friends in a fortnight – Hutton, Pearce, Fawkes.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
