<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[210]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">D U R H A M C A S T L E</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[quotation in Greek]</p>
         <p>2. Corinthians iii. 4&#8211;6.</p>
         <p>This passage occurred in the position which it fell to me to read in its order with my private prayers, and it accorded so well with the time &amp; purpose of my presence here that I transcribed it into my Journal.  For, indeed, as I consider these ill&#8211;trained, rather helpless men, and reflect on my own tragic incapacity to help or guide them, my heart would fail me altogether if I could not depend on their great assurance of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>. Paul, that in and with His Church there is a Power of God, making possible what otherwise were wholly impossible, and 'giving us the victory through Jesus Christ our Lord':</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[211]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Osborne</hi>'s Second Address was quite admirable in itself and for its purpose.  It nearly persuaded me that I am myself a liberal Catholic like himself. But I suspect that, if we came to close quarters, I should not pass muster into that fold!  The Bishop of Jarrow joined the Canon and me in my room after lunch, and conversation turned on Eucharistic doctrine. The vehement Protestantism of the Bishop's opinions was rather disconcerting to me, &amp; evidently rather startling to the Canon.  It is a pity that my admirable Suffragan hasn't a better appreciation of historic Christianity as a whole, and a larger sympathy with types of disciplines and devotions other than his own. </p>
         <p>I attended Evensong in the Cathedral, and then witnessed the taking of the Declaration in the Chapter House.  After tea with the Bishop of Jarrow &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Knight, I proceeded to the Castle for dinner: &amp; after Compline I delivered my Charge to the candidates.  </p>
         <p>I heard A. J.'s Confession: &amp; then talked with the Canon &amp; Rawlinson for an hour.  And there ended a rather busy day.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
