<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[179][sic]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, November 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A white frost gave a wintry aspect to the world.  I spent the morning in writing a letter to the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> which I headed, "<hi rend="underline">The Moral of Birmingham</hi>."  I described the situation in Birmingham as "Gilbertian", and drew the moral of Disestablishment.  I took occasion to refer to the new Commission on Church &amp; State, &amp; to express my wonder at the assumption that it would take years to do its business.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Harriman</hi>, the clergyman from Glasgow whom Booth meditates appointing to Hebburn, came to see me. We had much talk together, and he impressed me favourably.  He had tea, &amp; departed.  I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Booth</hi> telling him that if he decided to offer the appointment to M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Harriman</hi>, I should be well content.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> reports the death of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Mary Maxwell</hi> of Dayarval.  It is, indeed, difficult to realize that I shall never see again in this world that vital, vigorous, &amp; essentially generous woman, under whose roof I have enjoyed much pleasant hospitality. This has been a very fatal year for my friends.  I find my world of acquaintance emptying rapidly.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
