<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[216]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, December 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I received form the Prime Minister's Patronage Secretary a letter with reference to the appointment to Belmont, &amp; mentioning the names of three clergymen now working in the diocese – <hi rend="doubleunderline">Suthrien</hi>,<persName xml:id="5364"></persName> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sharpley</hi>, &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Taylor</hi>.  I strongly recommend <hi rend="doubleunderline">Suthrien</hi>. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote to Lords Londonderry and Scarbrough: and, at some length, to old D. Wilson, in reply to his defence of the Establishment.  The old man still thinks and speaks as an Erastian Latitudinarian of 1860!  But I have a fondness for him, and should like to retain or recover his good opinion.  </hi>
         </p>
         <p>The post brings an avalanche of Christmas cards &amp; gifts: and they are welcome as tokens of affection, but the acknowledgment of them is a weariness to the flesh and a frightful expenditure of time.  </p>
         <p> I walked to the Park Gates &amp; back.  The Park was entirely empty safe for one loving couple.  The weather is extraordinary mild.  </p>
         <p>I read through Bernard Shaw's, "The Apple Cart", it is amazingly good fooling, and however earnestly he may disclaim the fact in the Preface is a savage &amp; most effective satire on "Democracy" as we have it in England today. </p>
</body></text></TEI>
