<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[159]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters, among them one to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Burkitt</hi>, sending with it a copy of my pamphlet, "<hi rend="underline">Church and State in England</hi>'.  Those Cambridge professors played an ill part in the long controversy over Prayer Book Revision, &amp; they are as self&#8211;satisfied as they are mischievous.  I suspect that they are beginning to see their victory in defeating the Revised Book may have consequences which they did not contemplate, and do not like.</p>
         <p>Charles accompanied me to Hedworth where, in an asphyxiating atmosphere, I confirmed 51 persons from the parishes of West Boldon (Leake), S. George, East Boldon (Richardson), and Hedworth (Wilton), of which the combined population is about 11,000.</p>
         <p>I received a letter from M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Francis Brett Young</hi>, thanking me for the flatterous reference to his novel, "<hi rend="underline">My brother Jonathan</hi>", which I made in my address to the Medical Students.  He had read it in the <hi rend="underline">British Medical Journal</hi>.  He writes: "It touched me particularly, I think, because, in all my literary career, this is the first time that I have ever received a compliment from a dignitary of the Church."</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
