<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[86]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">College of Medicine</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A brilliant autumnal day, so brilliant that I deserted my study at noon, &amp; sauntered in the Park.  I tried to put together some material for a post&#8211;prandial speech</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went into Durham, &amp; presided at a meeting of the Board of Training &amp; Maintenance until 3.15 p.m. when, resigning the chair to my Suffragan, I proceeded to Newcastle.  Picking up Sir Thomas Oliver &amp; his daughter at their house.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I went to the College of Medicine, &amp; delivered the Inaugural Address on "The Genesis of the Physician's Ideal". The audience consisted of the academic chiefs &amp; their ladies together with a crowd of rather noisy students. However, they listened fairly well, &amp; cheered at the close.</hi><hi rend="italic">  Then we had tea, &amp; I was introduced to various persons, among them a pleasant looking girl, the daughter of the surgeon, Grey Turner, who is himself in Canada. After this I returned to Sir Thomas Oliver's house, and changed for dinner. The dinner was held in the Railway Hotel.  I was the guest of the teaching staff of the College of Medicine.  The company numbered about 35.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Thomas Oliver</hi><hi rend="italic"> presided, &amp; I sate on his right hand, having on my other side </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir William Morris</hi><hi rend="italic">, with whom I had much interesting conversation.  </hi><hi rend="i bold strikethrough underline">The Chairman</hi> 
<hi rend="i bold subscript">^</hi><hi rend="i bold">A pundit</hi><hi rend="i bold subscript">^</hi> 
<hi rend="italic bold underline">proposed my health in flatterous terms, &amp; I replied in a short speech which seemed to please everybody! Then we sang "Auld Lang Syne", and "God save the King</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi>
           
<hi rend="italic">Leng was ready for me, &amp; I returned home arriving a few minutes after 11 p.m.  So that is over, &amp; I am left to the sad question, whether so considerable an expenditure of time &amp; money was worth while.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">As Visitor of the University I can hardly disclaim some kind of responsibility for its conduct, &amp; a refusal of the invitation to give this address might fairly have been resented.  I became, perhaps, a little more intelligible to some of the dons, and passed for the first time within the range of the students' knowledge.  So much is not altogether valueless: but the total result seems pitiably little for so large an effort.  "Side&#8211;shows" implying, as from the nature of the case they cannot but imply, labour in preparation, are always very costly performances, &amp; interfere woefully with one's true work.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
