<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[178][sic]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> November, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Mine host has two sons, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Swithin</hi> and<hi rend="doubleunderline"> John</hi>, aged respectively six and three – very pleasant little fellows. I left Edinburgh at 10.15 a.m. and was met at Newcastle by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> with the car.</p>
         <p>The "<hi rend="underline">Women's Offering</hi>", which amounted to something over &#x00A3;600, was presented to the Chapel after a short service.  There had previously been a meeting in the State Room, at which <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Thurlow</hi> gave an address, from which I gathered that she is far advanced in all the follies which meet in the arch&#8211;heresy of "Feminism".  How much my predecessors escaped by being in an age which was innocent of "Church work"!</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Stenhouse</hi>, the widow of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Stenhouse of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, (who financed the Protestant agitation in Pelton) came to see me with reference to my (alleged) neglect of an (alleged) application for a licence to officiate made to me by her late husband. I could but say that neither I nor my chaplain had the faintest recollection of having received any such application. There is something more in all this than appear on the surface!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
