<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[69]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>My morning was again devoted to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Virgil</hi>: but I made no progress. It was not so much the lack of material that hinders me as the difficulty of constructing a post–prandial speech, which shall both match the mood of a Dining company, and be not wholly unworthy of the theme. I must not speak otherwise than is fitting in the Visitor of the University.</p>
         <p>After lunch Charles drove me into Durham in his little car.  But my main purpose was defeated for the Bishop of Jarrow, whom I desired to see was not at home.  </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Murray Smith</hi> called, and had tea.  Scarcely had they departed before old Bishop <hi rend="doubleunderline">Talbot</hi> &amp; his wife arrived on a visit, for which They had proposed Themselves. He is 86, very infirm &amp; halting on his leg, withal very deaf. She, poor lady, is stone deaf.  Conversation is a noisy &amp; futile affair.  </p>
         <p>Charles and I motored to Darlington, where I instituted the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rev. J.C.R.C. Coen</hi><persName xml:id="5577"></persName> to the perpetual curacy of S. James, Darlington, from which the Socialist Gobat has retired.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
