<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[75]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Meeting of Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet morning, and very depressing. Why are we so woefully dependent on our physical setting?</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8.15 a.m. All the Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans communicated.  The weather became close &amp; warm, and its effect on me was almost to incapacitate me for my duty.  However I managed to preside at the conference from 10 a.m. to 12.15 p.m.  We had a considerable discussion, rather illuminating than practical, on the subject which the Bishop of Jarrow introduced viz: classes for church teaching.  It appears that this diocese stands high in the general record as having many such classes organized by the C.T.C.S.: but when I questioned the Rural Deans, it appeared that these classes were not markedly different from the familiar 'Bible Classes'.  I expressed myself rather unsympathetically towards "ways of renewal": for, indeed, I think we need rather a worthier standard in the performance of normal duty, than organized devotions.  "Mind not high things: but condescend to things that are lowly."</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[76]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>After an early lunch the Archdeacons &amp; Rural Deans left the Castle.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> and I motored to Leadgate, where I consecrated an addition to the Churchyard.  The service was reverent and well&#8211;arranged.  There was a large choir, which sang well while marching round the ground – a severe test of efficiency.  I was favourably impressed.</p>
         <p>On returning to the Castle I had an interview with an aspirant to Ordination, sent to me from Whitburn, by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Linnell</hi>.  His name was <hi rend="doubleunderline">Anthony Sugden</hi>, and he is 18 years old. I liked him, but he knows nothing, &amp; seems rather good than able.  I told him that he must pass the Durham Matriculation, &amp; then see me again.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fearne</hi> went into Durham to attend a concert in aid of the Castle.  I wrote letters, among which was one to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Little</hi>, the Vicar of Monkhesledon, offering him the appointment to S. Andrew's, Tudhoe Grange.  This living is worth &#x00A3;100 less than that which he now holds: but he is said to possess private means, &amp; to be desiring a change of work. The patron of Monkhesledon is the Dean &amp; Chapter.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
