<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[136]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi> 
<hi rend="bold">1930</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">CONSECRATION AT YORK </hi>
         </p>
         <p>A wet foggy morning, all the world under a dirty grey blanket, infinitely depressing. </p>
         <p>The Bishop of Jarrow arrived in good time, and at 8.30 a.m. we started for York, arriving there in ample time for the consecration of the Bishop of Hulme (Canon Sherwood Jones) in the Minster at 11 a.m.  There was a considerable muster of Bishops <hi rend="underline">including the newly–married </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Goulburn</hi>.  He appears to be still vaingloriously happy, a senile dogmatist!  The organ being under repair, there was nothing but a piano to assist the choir. Nevertheless the singing was excellent. I read the Gospel, and Bradford, the Epistle. After the service, we went to the Station Hotel, and lunched there very comfortably.  Shortly after 2 p.m. we started on our return journey, and arrived at Auckland Castle at 4.10 p.m. </p>
         <p>Two ordination candidates came to see me, both of whom impressed me favourably. One, Alfred Toomey, was a student at S. Augustine's Canterbury, who desired to take his degree at <hi rend="bold">[137] </hi>Durham.  He is destined to work abroad, but, as his health is precarious after an operation for appendicitis, the S.P.G. authorities think it advisable that he should work for 4 years in England.  I did not feel able to decide on his application, and bode him see me again on Monday.  The other candidate, Thomas Alderson, is an elementary school teacher, who has a London degree.  I was much taken with his bright manner, and evident earnestness.  I promised to ordain him at Advent, 1931, if he passed my Examination.</p>
         <p>In Toomey's case I may fairly consider that my responsibility for his Ordination would be limited.  He has been accepted for foreign service by the S.P.G. which has satisfied itself that he is in all respects competent for such service as soon as he has had time to recover from a physical weakness, which the doctors certify to be neither incapacitating nor permanent.  All I am asked to do is to Ordain him to the Ministry on the understanding that he works in my diocese for 4 years, being more or less of a 'lame duck' during his service.  If I am persuaded that he is morally and intellectually fit for Ordination, ought the physical disadvantage to hinder me from Ordaining him?  </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
