<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[199]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi> sends me a friendly note about the Newcastle Address.  "<hi rend="underline">Personally, I never enjoyed an address so much in my life, &amp; I don't think I ever laughed so much</hi>". Yet. There was nothing particularly humorous in what I said: only it was set off by the portentous dullness of the other speakers.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters, &amp; making notes. In the afternoon I walked to the Park Gates, where I fell in with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Dawson</hi>, the farmer, who exclaimed to me the experiments he is making with various chemical fertilisers on segments of the Park.  He hoped greatly to improve the eatage.</p>
         <p>I motored to Stockton, and distributed prizes to the boys of the Secondary School in the Jubilee Hall.  There was a considerable gathering of parents &amp; boys.  I spoke for about 40 minutes, &amp; was listened to very attentively.  They seemed to be impressed &amp; gratified.  There was some Shakespeare performed after the prize&#8211;distribution.  I came away at 9 p.m.  The Headmaster, who has been only a year in his post, accompanied me to the door when I departed, &amp; expressed himself in terms of ardent gratitude.  I did not dislike the man, and can well imagine that in his eyes it is not an unimportant circumstance that the Bishop consents to give away his prizes.</p>
        
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
