<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[121]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic">' reports the death of the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Dean of Winchester</hi><hi rend="italic">, at the age of seventy.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Hutton</hi><hi rend="italic"> played a decisive part in my life.  He was my private tutor for two terms before my History Finals in 1884: and it was at his suggestion that I entered myself as a candidate for the All Souls Fellowship later in the same year.  Since, beyond all reasonable question, my election in November, 1884, determined my subsequent career, he, more than any other man, was "the author of my fortunes". It would not, I think, be true to say that I ever regarded him as a personal friend, for I differed from him decisively on ecclesiastical matters, &amp; I regarded with something like contempt his type of religion, his dilettantism, &amp; his tendency to be a '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">malade imaginaire</hi><hi rend="italic">'.  But I always kept in touch with him, &amp; generally went to see him while he lived in Oxford. I did not esteem his historical work highly, though I could not question his knowledge, industry, &amp; consistent effort to be impartial. The heavy cloud which enveloped his personal reputation in his later years, distressed me extremely, and embarrassed our relations with one another.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[122]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">What is the obligation of friendship when a friend falls under the shadow of some ignoble disgrace?  Much must turn on the measure and description of the friendship: &amp; something on the nature &amp; degree of the disgrace.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The last time that I saw Hutton was when I visited Winchester in order to preach to the School in 1928, I stayed with</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Williams</hi><hi rend="italic">, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">the Head Master, for the week&#8211;end: &amp; on the Sunday afternoon I called at the Deanery</hi><hi rend="italic">. We talked for half an hour about the rejection of the Revised Prayer Book, but there was a feeling of embarrassment &amp; constraint on my part, and, I think, also on his.  What ought to have been a visit of affection had come to be a visit of obligation.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">What is my final judgement on the facts</hi><hi rend="italic">? On the most favourable estimate, a depraved sentimentalism, &amp; an almost incredible degree of folly. Beyond that verdict, which is unchallengeable, nothing can be known.  "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Honi soit qui mal y pense</hi><hi rend="italic">".  The hand of Death purges all records, and silences all criticisms.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[123]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wasted the whole morning in cleaning up my study, and writing letters. In the afternoon, I walked in the Park with Charles for an hour &amp; a half. The autumnal foliage illumined by a brilliant sun, and seen in a singularly clear atmosphere was beautiful beyond all description.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Shaddick</hi> came to tea, and to discuss the question of giving a title to the rather unprepos<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>ess<hi rend="sub">&#x032D;</hi>ing young man from this town.  I took occasion to 'sound' him on the matter of finding holiday work as a lay&#8211;reader for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Malcolm Ross</hi>, and he seemed rather to welcome the prospect.</p>
         <p>That hateful society, 'the Church Association' <hi rend="italic">is trying to make capital out of the incident at </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Pelton</hi><hi rend="italic">: and I fear there may be some reaction in favour of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi><hi rend="italic">, which might have very ill consequences. An anonymous post&#8211;card came:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"I write on behalf of hundreds, how delighted we are in the way you have asserted your rights in connexion with Pelton, County Durham. Such an example is a lesson for other Bishops to do likewise. (It) is needed"!!!</hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
