<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[191]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The fog continues, and there is no wind to shift it.</p>
         <p>The <hi rend="underline">Times</hi> has a short and rather ill&#8211;natured letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">W.D. Morrison</hi>, the Vicar of Marylebone, whom I used to know when I lived in Westminster.  It is more rudely expressed than I should have expected, and winds up with the sentence "<hi rend="underline">But Auckland Castle is far from London</hi>". He is 10 years older than I.  </p>
         <p>I wrote a very brief letter to the '<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>' in reply to him and to old Dr. Wilson.  There is really nothing to answer in their letters.  The '<hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi>' and the '<hi rend="underline">Church Times</hi>' refer to me civilly, the '<hi rend="underline">Record</hi>' &amp; '<hi rend="underline">the Ch. Of E. Gazette</hi>' rudely.  So much might have been expected.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Is the commission on Church and State designed honestly as the first step in the process of vindicating the self&#8211;respect of the Church of England? or is it a mere device for shuffling out of the way an acknowledged but intensely unwelcome moral obligation which English Churchmen cannot rightly ignore or belittle?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">For myself, I am more than ever convinced that if the C. of E. shall be led to acquiesce in the situation which the rejection of the P.B. Measure has disclosed, a mortal blow will have been inflicted on its spiritual authority. A brief avoidance of trouble will be bought by a lasting loss of moral influence".</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
