<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[162]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I finished the Mayor's sermon, &amp;, then, began to consider the paper on '<hi rend="underline">The Church and the Modern State</hi>', which I have undertaken to write by February 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">I thought it worth while to make an effort to get a clear notion of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic">'s view of the Church, as set out in his new book, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Christian Ethics and Modern Problems</hi><hi rend="italic">". His language is vigorous, but also loose and sometimes contradictory, reflecting rather the vehemence of his antipathies than the range of his learning and the power of his mind.   His hatred of the Roman Church has become an obsession, too strong for the control of his good sense, &amp; his facility in coining glittering epigrams has overmastered his literary good taste.  I cannot think that the main effect of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Inge</hi><hi rend="italic">'s book will be other than mischievous.  It cannot but tell as a formidable accession of strength to the movement against "institutional Christianity", which is already disastrously strong. The worst enemies of historical Christianity can find in the writing of the Dean of S</hi><hi rend="i superscript">t.</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">Paul's the materials or their most effective attacks.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[163]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Robert William Bell</hi>, an Ordination candidate, came to lunch, &amp; afterwards discussed his position with me.  He is 31; has no degree: is engaged to be married: &amp; has served in the Great War.  A typical Ordinand of the post&#8211;War period.  To regard him as a teacher, still less as a religious leader, would be almost grotesque.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> and I visited the Chrysanthemum Show in the Town Hall, &amp; then we parted company.  I went into the Park, and watched a Football Match.  She went off to some kind of a beneficent Committee.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">John Simpson</hi> came to see me. He will be 19 in February, &amp; is growing, but still rather solid and stockish. A loyal soul notwithstanding.  </p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, &amp; there dined in the Castle with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r </hi><hi rend="doubleunderline">Justice Roche</hi>.  There were present <hi rend="doubleunderline">Pemberton</hi> &amp; his wife, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Luxmore</hi> &amp; his wife, a certain <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hogge</hi> from Darlington &amp; his wife, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Roche</hi>, her brother, &amp; her fianc&amp;#x00E9;.  The judge asked me whether I would officiate at his daughter's wedding in the Temple Church next spring, &amp; I gave a conditional promise that I would. I came away shortly before 10 p.m., &amp; returned to Auckland.  Roche gave an encouraging account of the prospect of getting something from the Harkness Trust for the Castle.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
