<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[212]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">(S. Thomas)</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">T H E O R D I N A T I O N</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">[quotation in Greek]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Again, the passage which confronts me in my private reading was directly &amp; most helpfully relevant to the solemn business of the day.</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">Preaching ourselves</hi>" is no inapt description of a ministry which is tenderly sensitive to every censure however well merited, and eagerly receptive of every compliment, however undeserved. </p>
         <p>Trust in God is a better Protection against morbid egotism than distrust of one's self.  So S. Peter's call for humility is based on the assurance that God has our concerns in His own Hands, &amp; that our fretful vanity is the real cause of our own worrying over them as if they were in ours. [quotation in Greek]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[213]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> arrived in good time, affirming that he was recovered of his sickness.  The service in the Cathedral was moving in its simplicity &amp; dignity.  It began with an admirable sermon from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Osborne</hi>, delivered extemporaneously, but evidently prepared with much care. His text was S. John ii.2,3. "<hi rend="underline">But he that entereth in by the door is the shepherd of the sheep.  To him the porter openeth; and the sheep hear his voice : and he called his own sheep by name, &amp; leadeth them out</hi>."  The service proceedeth without any hitch, except that the Dean forgot to make his offering, &amp; caused some delay on the part of those who waited for his lead, and, as usual, far too much bread and wine were consecrated.  These incidents, however, hardly affected the congregation.  The candidates gave me the impression of deep sincerity.  After the service I walked with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> in the Banks, where the reflections in the river were amazingly clear &amp; beautiful.  Then I entertained the candidates and their relations at lunch in the Hall of the Castle.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Osborne</hi> accompanied us to Auckland, where he saw the Castle and had tea.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lang</hi> motored him to Wallsend in time for evensong.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>
