<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[214]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, December 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I thought it prudent to leave <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> at home since the threatenings of pleurisy are not wholly absent, when I motored to Sunderland for the consecration of S. Mary Magdalene's new church.  There was a great gathering of clergy, a very carefully arranged ceremonial, a large &amp; evidently interested congregation.  <hi rend="bold underline">In deference to me, illegalities were avoided</hi>, &amp;, on the whole, I was pleased.  There followed a luncheon in the Palatine Hotel, and I found myself sitting beside a very unpleasant woman, <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Marion Philips</hi>, M.P., one of the representatives of the borough in Parliament, &amp; a truculent member of the Labour party.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi> made an impudent speech, glorying in his law&#8211;making, &amp; trailing his coat very insolently.  But I mainly ignored him, though I did remind him that both he and I had taken very solemn pledges at our Ordination.  Then I went to the Rectory where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wynne&#8211;Willson</hi> &amp; his wife presented me with a silver gilt ciborium, which was part of the loot of a French Church recovered from a German officer.  Then I returned to Auckland calling on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Rushworth</hi> in Durham on the way, but unavailingly, to get a present for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi>.</p>
</body></text></TEI>
