<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[80]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The newspapers are filled with the tragedy enacted yesterday in France, when the great airship, on which so much money &amp; so much thought have been bestowed, came to grief.  No less than 46 persons, including <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Thompson</hi>, the Air Minister, &amp; many leading experts have perished miserably.  I recall the lines of Vergil which, as <hi rend="doubleunderline">Boswell</hi> tells us, <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Johnson</hi> was fond of quoting:&#8211;</p>
         <p>optima quaeque dies miseris mortalibus aevi</p>
         <p>prima fugit: subeunt morbi tristisque senectus</p>
         <p>et labor, <hi rend="underline">et durae rapit inclementia mortis</hi>.</p>
         <p>One could hardly find a better illustration of the ruthlessness of unfeeling death.</p>
         <p>I set to work on the Vergil speech, &amp; wrote about half of it. The expenditure of time on these "side&#8211;shows" is out of all proportion to the achievement and the occasion. The post brings a request from Middlesborough[sic] that I should "give the introductory lecture on January 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> when the 'second series of Lectures for the People' is to begin.  But I shall say, No.  The game is not worth the candle, and I have more on my hands than I can do.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[81]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A note from young Pater informs me that old <hi rend="doubleunderline">Septimus Pater</hi>, the late Rector of Sunderland, has died. I wrote a letter of condolence to his widow.</p>
         <p>Ella accompanied me to Sedgefield when I went there in order to institute <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Thurlow</hi> to the Rectory.  There was a crowded church, the congregation being swollen by an influx from personal friends who had known <hi rend="doubleunderline">Thurlow</hi> when he was Vicar of Bishop Auckland.  I was interested to see how large a number of clergy attended the service.  Everything was well arranged &amp; impressive.  I told <hi rend="doubleunderline">Moore</hi>, the assistant curate, that I should shortly ask him to accept a living.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Philip Strong</hi> came here to discuss with me the possibility of his succeeding Baily as Vicar of S. Ignatius, Sunderland.  After dinner I had some talk with him.  He is a fine young fellow, full of ardour, &amp; of more than average ability, but he is deeply bitten with Anglo&#8211;Catholicism: &amp; I am not sure whether he would be moderate enough for S. Ignatius. However, he must go and see Baily.           </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
