<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>[sic]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A damp, warm uncomfortable day.  After breakfast with mine host, I walked to Westminster and attended the session of the Assembly.  After finishing with a petty measure affecting the channel islands, which gave </hi><hi rend="i bold">[</hi><hi rend="italic">the egregious</hi><hi rend="i bold">]</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Douglas</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">ample opportunity for exhibiting his recondite lore and argumentative acuteness, we got on to an Educational debate</hi><hi rend="italic underline">.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I made a short speech supporting a resolution which urged on the Church the importance of maintaining and extending the Training Colleges.  I took occasion to say that the C. of E. had to "shorten its front", that the abandonment of the tiresome &amp; hopeless effort to maintain the Dual System was the most obvious point at which to start to process, &amp; that if we did this, we could centre our efforts on the Training Colleges.</hi><hi rend="italic">  This brought up a "die&#8211;hard", named </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Thicknessse</hi><hi rend="italic">, who spoke with some vehemence in defence of Church Schools, and drew the applause of the Anglo&#8211;Catholicks. The motion was carried unanimously.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Lewis Dibden</hi><hi rend="italic"> called me aside, and explained his statement about my having</hi> 
<hi rend="i bold">[168a] </hi>[symbol] <hi rend="italic">induced the Ecc: Com</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> to purchase[a?] part of the capitular estates.  He had looked up the matter, &amp; found that the capitular estates concerned belonged, not to the Dean &amp; Chapter of Durham, but to the  University of Durham.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Thus his statement was entirely misleading &amp; irrelevant.</hi><hi rend="italic">  He did not, however, think it necessary to make a public explanation: and I, with my usual indifference to merely personal issues, suffered the matter to rest unexplained. But, of course, the newspaper reports made merry at my expense!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I had tea with </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Car&amp;#x00F6;e</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Alban</hi><hi rend="italic">.  The late Bishop of Wakefield, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Eden</hi><hi rend="italic">, encountered me in the passage of the Church House and thanked me warmly for the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Bishoprick</hi><hi rend="italic">".  He said that he had read the article on "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Memory of Vergil</hi><hi rend="italic">" twice, with much enjoyment.  I walked to the Athenaeum and wrote to Ella.  Canon </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jenkins</hi><hi rend="italic"> was in the Club.  He expressed regret at our failure to get Durham excluded from the </hi><hi rend="i bold">[169a] </hi>[symbol] operation of the property clause in the Cathedrals Measure.</p>
         <p>I dined at <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Grillions</hi>. There were present:</p>
         <p>Sir Austen Chamberlain.</p>
         <p>The Editor of the Times</p>
         <p>The Editor of Punch.</p>
         <p>Lord Hanworth.</p>
         <p>Lord Crawford &amp; Balcarres</p>
         <p>Lord Fitz. Alan.</p>
         <p>Lord Midleton.</p>
         <p>Sir Roger Key<hi rend="strikethrough">e</hi>s.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Durham.</p>
         <p>I took the chair, &amp; had beside me Lord FitzAlan, &amp; Sir <hi rend="bold underline">Austen Chamberlain</hi>. With the last I had much conversation which came to take almost an intimate character.  <hi rend="bold underline">He spoke strongly against the Bishop of Birmingham's tactlessness &amp; political partisanship</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi>  He spoke of Disestablishment with aversion: and I promised to send him my pamphlet on "<hi rend="underline">Chuch &amp; State in England</hi>".  Altogether it was the pleasantest meeting of the Club that I can recall.  I was back in Park Lane shortly before 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[170]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I was much interested by meeting that most gallant sailor, </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Sir Roger Keyes</hi><hi rend="italic">, the hero of Zeebrugge.  He did not look like a warrior of renown: for his aspect was gentle, his manner shy &amp; almost bashful, and his expression sweet and winning.  I could not but compare him with the aspect &amp; reputation of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Nelson</hi><hi rend="italic">, and conclude that the two men belonged to the same category.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We spoke of the manners &amp; customs of The House of Commons.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Austen Chamberlain</hi><hi rend="italic"> said that on one occasion the Speaker had referred to him as an old member of the House on the point whether decorations might be worn in the House.  A member who had come straight from Buckingham palace, had been refused admission by the door&#8211;keepers because he was wearing medals, &amp; had had appealed to the Speaker.  </hi>  
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Chamberlain</hi> was unable to discover the origin of the custom which the doorkeeper pleaded, but conjectured that it might indicate a certain jealousy of the civil authority as against the military.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
