<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[193]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The fog still hangs over the country, menacing to motorists. There is no wind to shift it.</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  There were 7 communicants.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> kept her room with some kind of a chill, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Elland</hi> communicated.  The opening words of the Gospel are an almost exact description of the world situation as it presents itself to a considering man today.  It is no wonder that Adventist cranks are again becoming vocal.</p>
         <p>I motored to Sunderland, and confirmed 52 candidates in <hi rend="underline">S. Columba's, Southwick</hi>.  Then I had tea with the Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">McMunn</hi>, and his two curates, of whom the senior, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Nigel Cornwall</hi>, leaves for the mission field in January, and the junior, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Langdon&#8211;Davies</hi> is to be ordained to the priesthood at Advent.  I preached at Evensong to a congregation which did not fill much more than half the Church.  No doubt the persistent rain kept many away.  <hi rend="bold underline">It was, however, overwhelmingly feminine, thus confirming in my mind the suspicion created by the fact that of the 40 candidates presented from the parish only 11 were males. Why is it that these Anglo&#8211;Catholicks cannot get hold of men &amp; boys? Is it that they press Confession on them?</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
