<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[200]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, December 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A beautiful day, sunny and quite mild.  I finished the charge, and frittered away the rest of the day very uselessly.  Also, I essayed to order my study–table, which had again become chaotic to the point of practical paralysis.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I read through a little book by </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Edwyn Bevan, </hi><hi rend="italic">"</hi><hi rend="italic underline">The Hope of the World to come'</hi><hi rend="italic">, in which he makes something like a protest against the anti–eschatological teaching of the Dean of S. Paul's.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> volume of the <hi rend="underline">Cambridge Ancient History</hi> arrived, a monstrous volume of more than 700 pages.  It deals with '<hi rend="underline">Rome and the Mediterranean.  218–133 B.C.</hi>'.  I buy these books, but I have no time to read them: and the pace of their publication is ever quickening.  Before one book is finished with, it has become obsolete, and another must be read.  I wonder whether it would not be a wiser course to leave all these modern books altogether alone, &amp; limit one's reading to the great standards and the texts. The question of providing book–space for the waxing flood of new publications is becoming serious.  And I draw near to the Three–score years &amp; ten!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
