<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[144]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, November 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A bright sun, and a white frost. WINTER. The papers announce an increase in the number of unemployed last week of more than 38,000. The increase during the year now exceeds 1,000,000.  We are marching to disaster.  In Parliament the discussions on unemployment are futile and insincere, for nobody knows what to do, and everybody pretends to have a remedy.  I can see no break in the clouds in any part of the horizon.  If unemployment were an insular calamity, one might hope that it would pass, &amp; the general prosperity extend across the channel: but it appears to be a universal disaster, so that we can look nowhere for any remedial factors.  Are we witnessing the death&#8211;throes of Industrialism?  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">And are these [accursed] Bolshevists really leading the way to a new kind of civilization? I am too old easily to accept the total falsification of all the reasonings on which we have hitherto grounded our notions of civilization.</hi>
           
<hi rend="italic">"Apart from its godless philosophy", writes 'Artifax' in today's M.G., there is much in the ideals of Bolshevism that attracts me!</hi>
           
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[145]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jowett</hi><hi rend="italic"> and </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Thirlwell</hi><hi rend="italic"> were the Masters of Fawkes's thinking on all religious and ecclesiastical subjects.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Loisy</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">French Modernists</hi><hi rend="italic"> carried on their tradition with a difference: but they remained for him supreme.  He took from his long career as a Roman priest a curious fear of ecclesiastical authority, and an enormous suspicion of episcopal policy.  To the end his aspect and manner were unmistakably Roman: but he was notably free from the hatred for Rome which marks most of those who have left her pale. He would give no countenance to the persistent.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Protestant assertions of the sacerdotal vice, and often surprized me by his championship of Roman methods.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">He despised "Anglo&#8211;Catholicism" as nothing better than an unskilful and undignified mimicry of Rome: but he also feared it as likely to bring into the Church of England the doctrinal rigour, the practical unscrupulousness, &amp; the clerical servility which had revolted him in the Church of Rome</hi><hi rend="italic">. He was the master of an effective literary style, terse and epigrammatic. His curious felicity in quotation adorned and strengthened his literary work &amp; he could draw on a full treasury of knowledge.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[146]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I was motored to Durham by Charles and there collated D. Jackson to the honorary canonry, and licensed a brace of curates. Then I gave lunch in the common room to D<hi rend="superscript">r. </hi>&amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs. </hi>Jackson, Cecil Ferens, &amp; Charles.  Ella joined us with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Murray &amp; Fearne.</p>
         <p>From 2 p.m. to 3.15 p.m. I interviewed 10 Ordination candidates in my room, and then Charles carried one back to Auckland.</p>
         <p>There was a one&#8211;legged man from Bede College came to see me. He lost his leg in the War, and was earnestly desirous of being Ordained. In view of the excellence of his testimonials, of his war&#8211;service &amp; of the favourable impression he made on me, I accepted him as a candidate.</p>
         <p>Charles accompanied me to the Primitive Methodist Church at Willington where "Jubilee" celebrations were proceeding.  M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Angus Watson, a perfervid sectarian presided, &amp; spoke at rather excessive length. The Rector, Hudson, read the lesson, &amp; there was an extemporaneous prayer, of which the lefs said the better.  I spoke for about 40 minutes.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[147]</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The gathering at the Primitive Methodist Church was certainly not impressive, for not only was the building (not a large one) no more than two thirds full, </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">but also there was a marked absence of young men.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Now the occasion was extraordinary, &amp; my presence not less so.  It may be afsumed that, but for these unusual circumstances, the attendance would have been even smaller.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The coincidence of "Guy Fawkes Day" may pofsibily go some way towards explaining the absence of young men</hi><hi rend="italic">, but this does little towards disallowing the obvious inference from the facts viz: </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that this P.M. Church has a very slight hold on the people of Willington. There is far more life in the parish church</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p> 
<hi rend="italic">I took occasion to express the opinion that it was desirable that the observance of "Armistice Day" should soon cease.  There was the certainty that, as Time passed, the fate which has befallen "Gunpowder Plot Day" would overtake this commemoration also.  I expressed approval of the Government's actions in making an end of the official practice of depositing wreaths on the 'unknown Warrior's' grave in Westminster Abbey, a practice which was degenerating into a lifeless convention.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
