<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[198]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I received from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="i superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline"> Morrison</hi><hi rend="italic"> a curiously ungracious letter, indeed almost brutal.  It discloses the depth of the hostile feeling against myself in the circle which he frequents.  He is most of all angered by my advocacy of Disestablishment,</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">"Forgive me for telling you that in spite of your brilliant talents you are steadily destroying your influence both in church and state.  This last step of yours into secular politics – for this is what it means – where you are not at home is the most disastrous of all".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Probably he is right, but it might have been more kindly phrased.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I read through <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir James Jeans'</hi> little book – "<hi rend="underline">The Mysterious Universe</hi>" – which is making so great a sensation, and selling madly.  He holds that the universe is best understood in terms of pure mathematics, &amp; the Creator pictured as the Great Mathematician.  I can't follow his arguments, nor understand his language, but his conclusions are less repugnant to Christianity than most pronouncements of the Scientific Pundits. At least he proclaims sentence of death on the materialistic mechanism of Huxley of his tribe.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
