<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[208]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Friday, December 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold doubleunderline">DURHAM CASTLE</hi>.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Jack Carr</hi><hi rend="italic"> went off in the course of the morning.  The "Church Times" gives prominence to some statements by 'D</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Philip Cook, Bishop of Delaware', in an article on the Lambeth Conference published in 'The Spirit of Missions, the official publication of the American Episcopal Church'.  It purports to give a descriptive account of the debate on Resolution 15, &amp; represents me as the protagonist in advocacy thereof.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The obligation of secrecy under which the bishops debated would seem to be very lightly regarded by the Transatlantick bishops.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Charles developed threatenings of pleurisy, and was ordered to bed. Accordingly, I was compelled to raise a chaplain from the candidates.  Dru Drury, who was last Advent's Gospeller, rose to the occasion excellently.</p>
         <p>Canon Osborne's address at Evensong was full of good things.  Basing himself on the record of Isaiah's Vision, he "spoke large" for 40 minutes.  He speaks too rapidly so that he was not always easy to follow, but I heard enough to get much satisfaction.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[209]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I saw every one of the 11 candidates separately, &amp; presented them with copies of Lightfoot's Ordination Addresses, &amp; <hi rend="bold underline">my own 'Notes on Spiritual Healing</hi><hi rend="bold">'</hi>. On the whole I was pleased with them: they are not brilliant, or well&#8211;bred, or well&#8211;educated, but they give me the impression of sincerity &amp; earnestness.</p>
         <p>Canon Osborne came into my room after Compline, and talked for an hour and a half. He seems both a cultivated and a liberal&#8211;minded man, &amp; his personal acquaintance with Father Dolling &amp; Father Tyrrell brought him into personal contact with a wide circle of interesting people.  He expressed himself in favour of Disestablishment. We talked of the Lambeth decision in favour (under certain conditions) of the use of contraceptives, &amp; he acknowledged a real doubtfulness on the subject.</p>
         <p>There is no doubt that Rawlinson's influence is beginning to tell on the younger clergy, who are either confirmed in Anglo&#8211;Catholicism, or attracted to it. I am not entirely contented with this, though I must needs be pleased that they can find any source of spiritual help in the diocese!    </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
