<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[160]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I occupied the morning with preparing a sermon. It is a proceeding which does not grow easier as time passes.  I reflect sadly that much, very much, of my time and strength has been devoted to it. Might not more have been made of my life if I had been as the rest, a mere chatterer of surface thoughts?</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Baxter</hi>, the curate of Hebburn, lunched here, and after lunch I had a 'heart&#8211;to&#8211;heart' talk to him about the foolish stuff which he has written in the 'Parish Magazine', of which a copy was sent to me last week by some justly&#8211;aggrieved parishioner.  He is a very feeble specimen, &amp; this "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" nonsense is too much for him!  Yet he is probably good, &amp;, up to his lights (which, however, are dim) sincere.  If he plays the Hildebrand thus as assistant&#8211;curate, what would he develope [sic] into as an incumbent?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Miss Headlam</hi> arrived to stay the night, and attend some meeting.  She is rather a formidable advocate of any cause she elects to champion.   Her own parson is, of course, marked out by his position for her victim: I do not envy him his privilege of pasturing such an ewe lamb!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
