<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         
         <p>
<hi rend="bold underline">[155]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The papers overflow with answers to (i.e. denunciations of) the Bishop of Durham. The Bishop of Ripon (!) and General Montgomery are the best known of the champions, but the lesser fry are not lacking.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I went in to Durham for the new Mayor's Installation.  Alderman Pattison is a confectioner by trade, and a Salvationist by profession.  His co&#8211;religionists attended in force, so that the Town Hall was crowded.  He is a native of Durham, a circumstance evidently appreciated by his fellow townsmen.  There was an orgy of extravagant eulogy, which made me almost literally sick, and this protracted the proceedings for nearly two hours.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">The atmosphere was akin to that of the 'Black Hole' in Calcutta, but this mattered nothing to the company.</hi><hi rend="italic">  We walked in procession to the Freemasons' Hall, &amp; there a 'stand&#8211;up lunch' and another orgy of speech&#8211;making followed. I replied to the toast of "the Bishop &amp; Clergy of all Denominations". A popish priest &amp; a Salvationist 'major' also replied.  Robin was there, &amp; proposed the Toast of the City &amp; County in a brief &amp; well=expressed speech. Then I came away, &amp; returned to Auckland.</hi> 
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[156]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> went with me to Castle Eden, where I instituted an ex&#8211;Papist named <hi rend="doubleunderline">Huntley</hi> to the Rectory.  After the service we dined with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Burdon</hi>.  He had some shooting guests staying with him; &amp; one of then, whose name I have forgotten, was most interesting.  He was an ornithologist and had actually <hi rend="italic">witnessed a fight between a golden eagle, &amp; red deer. He had taken part in the landing at Suvla bay, &amp; gave me a vivid account of his experiences.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">I noted that he regarded Winston Churchill as the villain of that piece</hi>.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Colonel Burdon</hi> was very friendly.  He told me that he has agreed to give &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">700</hi> towards the better endowment of the parish, if the Ecclesiastical Commission could meet his gift by a grant of the same amount. The poor man is becoming very blind. He has in his drawing room a mezzotint picture of a soldier, who, he said, had been on <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wolfe</hi>'s staff, &amp; carried to England the despatch which announced the capture of Quebec.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
