<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[99]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I finished the Vergil speech, which is a poor stilted thing as of a hog dancing in tights!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then I read through a pamphlet by Bishop Gore on </hi><hi rend="i bold">"Contraceptives", strenuously disputing the resolution of the Lambeth Conference. A new Society has been formed solely with the object of opposing the use of Contraceptives.  It seems to consist of Tractarians, Papists, and dissentient Doctors, and calls itself "The League of National Life</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Charles and I walked round the Park: &amp; on our return I received D</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r </hi><hi rend="italic">Jackson, and the two churchwardens of Pelton. I propounded three questions to the latter:</hi>
         </p>
        
     
<p> <hi rend="italic">Were they present at the "Excommunication"?</hi></p>     
<p><hi rend="italic">Did they know of the suspension of Evensong?</hi>
            </p>
          
<p> <hi rend="italic">Are the three "excommunicates" resident and reputable parishioners?</hi></p>
            
       
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Then I read out the account of the proceedings in the Newcastle Journal, </hi><hi rend="i bold">&amp; they assured me that it was entirely accurate</hi><hi rend="italic">. We had a considerable discussion, and I sent them away with a strait charge to deal faithfully with the Vicar, and make him realize the gravity of his conduct.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[100]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I inquired whether the Vicar visited the people faithfully: and, with evident reluctance, the Churchwarden who was in favour of the services as now conducted, admitted that he did not.  The other churchwarden, who is the schoolmaster in the little Church School (160 children) said that he came into the school and taught on one day in the week.  The parish contains 10,000 people, but the Easter Communicants did not exceed 70. In the late Vicar's time there were as many as 300. I pressed on the Churchwardens that they were not the Vicar's servants, but the representatives of the Congregation and the officers of the parish.</p>
         <p>[symbol] An excellent public–house keeper in London writes to me a furious letter, protesting against <hi rend="doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi>'s statement that the three excommunicates were to be treated as 'Heathens &amp; <hi rend="underline">publicans</hi>'. Having been a respectable publican for more than 25 years he feels that he must protest against this libel on his profession. I must write him a soothing letter.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
