<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[112]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">This is the 28</hi><hi rend="i sup u">th</hi><hi rend="italic"> anniversary of my marriage: and it lends itself to many reflections.  At least we remain united, and in my mind so to continue.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Our guests, except Captain &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi><hi rend="italic"> Capon, went away after breakfast; and then Charles and I walked to the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Unemployment Instruction Centre</hi><hi rend="italic">, where I went through the rooms in which rather more than 300 unemployed lads between the ages of 14 and 18 were at work.  Many of them looked very dull, and would be certified as 'subnormal; but many appeared quite averagely intelligent lads.  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I inquired whether the lads were sufficiently fed: and I was told that, beyond question, a certain proportion were not</hi><hi rend="italic">: that the ending of the Mansion House Fund left the staff without resources: &amp; that voluntary gifts were the only available supply.  I told the superintendent that he might </hi><hi rend="italic underline">privately</hi><hi rend="italic"> draw on me for an amount not exceeding &#x00A3;10. for providing cocoa etc. for really necessitous cases.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[113]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Wright</hi> came to lunch, and afterwards I had a "heart&#8211;to&#8211;heart" talk with him.  He tried to justify himself, but not very ardently, and, on the whole, took my admonitions better than I had expected. He professed great loyalty to me, but I am not quite comfortable about him.  "<hi rend="underline">A man's foes are they of his own household</hi>", and, in his case also, his masterful personality brings specific temptations. I went through the list of "ornaments", and disallowed some of the items.</p>
         <p>Then I went in to Durham, and visited Bede College, where the Principal explained to me what was designed in the matter of building additional accommodation for the students.  Then I had tea with him &amp; his wife.</p>
         <p>[symbol] I called on the Bishop of Jarrow, &amp; discussed some matters of business with him. We had a considerable discussion on religious matters, in which he expressed himself with a vigour which rather surprized me, &amp; in a manner which somewhat disturbed me.  His dislike of Anglo&#8211;Catholicism is growing into an obsession.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[114]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote for some more port wine to the Firm that carries on its business in Durham House, the building which stands on the site of the medieval palace of my predecessors.  Since January 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> I find that I have expended no less than &#x00A3;31:2:0 on Wine, Whiskey, and Cider.  Is this excessive?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Drury</hi> came to see me about the question of his schools, evidently seeking to strengthen himself by pleading my sanction for the course on which he had already determined.  I was weak enough to pronounce an opinion on the issue which he presented to me: and I doubt not that I shall find that opinion exploited with more confidence than candour.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Hamblin Smith</hi>, the lady who is to make a copy of Bishop Cosin's picture for Lord Chalmers, arrived.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Captain Crapon</hi> talked most interestingly about the French generals. He was no great admirer of Foch, and held that Weygand was probably much greater than had been generally recognized.  He greatly admired Sir Henry Wilson.
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
