<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[132]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The circumstance that as Bishop of Durham I had precedence over every other bishop, save only the Bishop of London, had the effect of separating me at all episcopal meetings from </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Ernest Pearce</hi><hi rend="italic">, beside whom I had generally sate, &amp; thus threw him into the hands of the Bishops of Birmingham, Bristol, Norwich, and Bath &amp; Wells, whose influence was far otherwise toned and directed than mine. Had I sate with him during the long discussions over the Revision of the Prayer Book, I incline to think that his course might have been different.  But I cannot be very sure, for his Protestant prejudices were extraordinarily strong, and he was almost absurdly unable to rise above them.  The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> has an appreciative obituary notice. He certainly did succeed in making a much more considerable figure than his modest powers might have seemed to make possible: but, nowise gifted, he had sterling practical qualities which commended him to greater men than himself.  Like </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Godolphin</hi><hi rend="italic">, he was an ideal official, 'never in the way, and never out of it'.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[133]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I wrote a letter of condolences to the Bishop of Derby, Pearce's brother.  He will be much afflicted by Ernest's death, for I never knew a more affectionate family.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">Ella went with me to the Town Hall for the meeting which preceded the opening of the enlarged and renovated Barrington School.  The Hall was densely crowded, &amp; the atmosphere was deadly.  Not a window seemed to be open.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Why will the clergy be so indifferent to ventilation? They owe much discomfort, much ill health, &amp; not a little failure to the quite unnecessary circumstance that they minister in poisonous atmospheres</hi><hi rend="i bold">.</hi><hi rend="italic">  M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> &amp; M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">rs</hi> 
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Braley</hi><hi rend="italic"> came to tea, and also </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Spencer Wade</hi><hi rend="italic">. That tiresome little boy Basil is now developing, or threatening to develope, tubercular trouble, &amp; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">must</hi><hi rend="italic"> be transferred from Gateshead to moorland air!  </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Sic volo, sic jubeo</hi><hi rend="italic">! And where do the interests of the 12,000 parishioners come into the argument?</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="i doubleunderline">Welch</hi><hi rend="italic"> sends me from Nigeria a long and illuminating letter.  He is evidently chafing against the strait waistcoat of C. M. S.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
