<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[166]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, November 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">LONDON</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>Charles went with me to Darlington, where I took the early train to London.  From York I had the compartment to myself, save that I was visited, first, by the Bishop of Newcastle, and then, by the Bishop of Jarrow, with both of whom I had much talk.  But I felt woefully ill, and this feeling continued until we neared King's Cross, when it left me, &amp; I felt normal.  <hi rend="bold underline">After leaving my bags at Park Lane</hi>, I went to the hairdresser, &amp;, when he had done his duty on me, I went to the Church House, &amp; attended the session of the Church Assembly.  <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop read out the names of the Church &amp; State Commissioners</hi>, &amp; this brought up the Bishop of Norwich and Lord Brentford, who wished to have some of the anti&#8211;Revised Prayer Book zealots included in their company.  The Abp of York briefly replied, and they were defeated by a large majority.  Then the proceedings became so dull that I came away shortly after 4 p.m.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[167]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[<hi rend="italic">symbol</hi>]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I had tea in the Athenaeum.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lord Blanesborough</hi><hi rend="italic"> was there, &amp; was most friendly, but </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">he has not forgiven me for not being an Archbishop!</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I dined in the Club with </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Headlam</hi><hi rend="italic"> and the Bishop of Jarrow.  After dinner I was reading in the large room, when </hi><hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Harris</hi><hi rend="italic"> joined me.  He told me that he was going to get married: that the lady was </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">an innocent divorc&amp;#x00E9;e</hi><hi rend="italic">: that, after the recent pronouncement of the Lambeth Conference, he was in doubt as to the possibility of his getting any clergyman to marry him.  I told him that, if he could find a clergyman who would lend his church for the purpose, I would myself officiate.  He seemed to be much relieved, &amp; walked with me to Park Lane, telling me the story of his engagement.  I doubt the </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">wisdom</hi><hi rend="italic"> of my undertaking, but not its </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">rightness</hi><hi rend="italic">.   The refusal of our ecclesiastics to recognize the distinction between guilt and innocence in this matter of marrying those who have been divorced, agrees neither with human equity nor Christian charity.   </hi>  
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
