<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[215]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, December 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">[symbol]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Simmonds</hi> came to lunch, &amp; afterwards, I had some speech with him about his situation, in view of the probability that the Archbishop will seek from me some information about him. He assured me that at S. Mary's, Tynemouth, they did not advance beyond the limit of the first Rubrick in the 1928 Prayer Book. He said that this w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. be his own practice in any parish, to which he might be appointed, &amp; that he w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. not advance beyond it without the Bishop's knowledge.  "But if the Bishop objected, would you obey him?".  He would not give an affirmative answer. There is the difficulty.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Eric Knowles</hi>, an Ordination Candidate, came also to lunch. I approved him for a training grant.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Durham, where I visited <hi rend="doubleunderline">Andreas</hi>'s Book Shop, &amp; ordered some gift books. Is this waste of money, or not?</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">", the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Manchester Guardian</hi><hi rend="italic">", the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Newcastle Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">" and the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Darlington paper</hi><hi rend="italic"> give considerable prominence to my reference to Disestablishment in yesterday's sermon, &amp; to my "rebuke" to "</hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Father Bill</hi><hi rend="italic">" in my speech at the Luncheon.  He certainly was himself the cause of my references to his lawlessness.</hi>
         </p>
</body></text></TEI>
