<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[97]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Monday, October 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The newspapers give great prominence to mad proceedings at Pelton yesterday where this precious Vicar "excommunicated" the Three parishioners who gave evidence in the Consistory Court, and used much fatuous and inflammatory language.  It is difficult to see either how I can avoid taking action, or what possible good can come from any action that it is legally possible for me to take.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="bold superscript doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Jackson</hi>, the Rural Dean, called to see me. He told me that the 3 excommunicates had acted after consultation with him: that he had no reason for thinking that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Kensit'</hi>s hand was in the business: that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi> was absolutely intractable. He shares my doubts as to the wretched creature's sanity. Such megalomaniacal egotism as he exhibits can hardly be interpreted except as a consequence of mental instability.  I asked him whether he could find out from M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> M. whether there was reason for suspecting mental trouble: and he undertook to do so.  After a hasty lunch, I went to Durham, and saw <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lazenby</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ferens</hi>. They seemed curiously uncertain as to the action which I could legally or wise to take. </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[98]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>We proceeded to Dipton, where I preached to a large congregation of the Mothers' Union from the Rural Deanery of Lanchester.  I took as my text the passage from S. Mark's Gospel which forms the lesson in the Baptismal Office.</p>
         <p>The Bishop of Birmingham preached a sermon in Birmingham yesterday, which is reported in the <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>.  He told his hearers that "we were now passing through a second Renaissance".  He does not appear to have named either God of Christ.  "One task of the instructed religions humanism of the future would be elimination of degenerate human stocks".  On the whole I think the old version of religious effort was better – <hi rend="underline">"The Son of man came to seek &amp; save that which was lost</hi>". Everything in the coming religion is earth&#8211;born and earth&#8211;bound.  "That faith would show its presence in the enterprizes of human idealism, &amp; especially in attempts to secure international peace and to prevent the existence of social injustice". The secularist's paradise – Voila tout!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
