<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[174]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, November 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A brilliant day, very welcome after the storm &amp; rain. I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. We were but five, for Ella was away, &amp; Charles was celebrating at Sherburn.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Observer</hi><hi rend="italic">' announces the death of yet another "old friend" – </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Arthur Hassall</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Christ Church.  He was a fast friend of Henry Wakeman, and I made his acquaintance through knowing Wakeman.</hi>
           
<hi rend="italic">I contributed to a little volume of 'Historical Essays' which he edited.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">It was my first appearance in print, and, commercially, my most successful</hi><hi rend="italic">, for the volume had a steady sale for some years. Hassall was a pleasant fellow, popular with everybody, &amp; (mentally &amp; morally) comfortably conventional.  He was 77.  How rapidly my stage is emptying.  Already "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">I am a stranger unto my mother's children</hi><hi rend="italic">".</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I wrote to William.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Ashton</hi> tells me that the local gossip ascribes the appointment to Eldon to the influence of Hodgson, the notorious vicar of Escombe, and that public opinion disapproves of the appointment. The new incumbent has no degree, and has been in Orders for 14 years.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[175]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>It is difficult to overestimate the injury to religion that cannot but follow from so flagrant an evidence of Erastian subordination of the Church to the State.  The facts that <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hodgson</hi> has openly &amp; frequently insulted his Bishop, and that he is an aggressive "Labour" man do add appreciably to the scandal.  A blow is struck at diocesan discipline, for the Bishop is seen to be ignored and helpless. I note that the usual practice of inviting my opinion on the names considered for appointment was not followed in this case.</p>
         <p>I left the Castle at 5 p.m, &amp; picked up Charles in the marketplace, but at the going out of Gilesgate the car came to a standstill, and, after fiddling about for 10 minutes, Leng declared himself unable to proceed. Charles sprinted to the College, where he had left his car, &amp; carried me therein to Chilton Moor, when I confirmed 53 persons at Evensong.  The Church was crowded, and the service seemed to be edifying.  The Vicar, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shore</hi>, is evidently making progress.  We got back to the Castle about 8.15 p.m.</p>
         <p>Leng succeeded in remedying the mischief in the car, &amp; followed us to Chilton Moor, but arrived after we had started homewards.</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
