<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[206]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, December 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The weather became much milder, as the day advanced. I wrote to Buchan and L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Macmillan thanking them for their good offices in securing the grant to the Castle Fund from the Pilgrims' Trust.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I sent &#x00A3;100 to Carter as an emergency contribution to the Diocesan Fund.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Charles and I walked round the Park during the afternoon.  <hi rend="bold underline">Jack Carr arrived at tea&#8211;time</hi>, with his broken arm still fast bound in the splints. He had a narrow escape in that collision between his motor&#8211;cycle, &amp; a suddenly turning lorry.  He desires to leave for Africa next October. I am sorry to lose him, but he seems clear that he ought to go.  And, indeed, there is nothing I would shrink from more than to frown upon the devout movements of a young clergyman, even though they seem to me unwise and ill&#8211;directed.  Who can tell whether after all he is not Divinely called to the work of missioning to the Africans?  He has within himself a more authoritarian Oracle than he can find without. Even if he be mistaken, he will not permanently suffer on account of blunders honestly made in the pursuit of what looked like his duty.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[207]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Candidates for Deacon's Orders</p>
         <p>1. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Clark</hi>, Sidney Harvie, Jesus Coll. Cambridge, B.A., born 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Aug. 1905, to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>  
         </p>
         <p>2. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Harrison</hi>, Joseph, Durham, B.A. , born 1905. to South Westoe.</p>
         <p>3. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Mitchell</hi>, Frank, Durham, March 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1906, B.A., to S. Edmund, Gateshead.</p>
         <p>4. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Toomey</hi>, Alfred James, Durham, L. Th., born April 22<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> 1906, to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew, Bp. Auckland.</p>
         <p>Candidates for Priest's Orders</p>
         <p>1. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Clothier</hi>, Harry Legg	 to S. Mary, Tyne Dock</p>
         <p>2. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Drury</hi>, Reginald Dru.	 to South Westoe.</p>
         <p>3. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">James</hi>, William to Norton.</p>
         <p>4. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Marr</hi>, Cyprian to S. Mary Magd., Sunderland.</p>
         <p>5. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">c</hi><hi rend="underline">Manners</hi>, Joseph to Ferryhill.</p>
         <p>6. [symbol] <hi rend="underline">Shreeve</hi>, John Frederic to Brandon.</p>
         <p>7. <hi rend="underline">Slater</hi>, Percy William to Stanton</p>
         <p>They all went into a Retreat at Gateshead conducted by Archdeacon Rawlinson, <hi rend="underline">before</hi> going to the Castle for such devotional arrangements as I had myself provided for them there.  Rebellion inheres even in these Anglo&#8211;Catholick prayers!</p>
</body></text></TEI>
