<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>[157]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, November 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>My <hi rend="underline">obiter dictum</hi> – it was hardly more – about the desireableness of fixing a date for the discontinuance of Armistice Day by an announcement from the proper authority has clearly moved much resentment.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lady Adam Smith</hi> writes to me from Aberdeen in terms of excited, almost hysterical protest.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Jellicoe</hi> expresses him vehement repugnance, &amp; the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Ripon</hi> 'replies to the Bishop of Durham' at great length.  There is, of course, the usual stream of abusive and largely anonymous letters.</p>
         <p>Ella and Charles went with me to Durham where I attended to service for Armistice Day in the Cathedral.</p>
         <p>There seemed to be a large congregation.  <hi rend="italic bold underline">The Dean gave an address, in which, of course, he expressed his dissent from his diocesan!</hi>  After service, I had speech with the Bishop of Jarrow about the affairs of the miserable <hi rend="doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi>. The man lies still at Mirfield, reported to be ill.</p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">In the afternoon I had a conference of incumbents on the question, urged vehemently upon me by Walls of Shildon.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">Ought the church as such to make an effort to raise funds for providing shoes etc to the poorer children attending the elementary schools.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[158]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>There are present the following incumbents:&#8211;</p>
         <p>1. Canon Stephenson, Gateshead</p>
         <p>2. Canon Poole, Ch. Ch., West Hartlepool.</p>
         <p>3. Canon Stock, S. Paul's, Gateshead.</p>
         <p>4. Watson, Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring</p>
         <p>5. Watts, Shildon</p>
         <p>6. Morris Young, New Shildon.</p>
         <p>7. Heselton, West Rainton.</p>
         <p>8. Shaddick, S. Michael's, South Westoe.</p>
         <p>9. Rambow, Shotton.</p>
         <p>10. Richardson, Heworth.</p>
         <p>11. Salter, Hartlepool.</p>
         <p>12. Appleton, Seaham Harbour.</p>
         <p>13. Garland, S. Mary's, Tyne dock.</p>
         <p>14. Canon Jackson, Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street.</p>
         <p>15. Davison, S. Helen's, Auckland</p>
         <p>16. Myers, South Moor.</p>
         <p>17. Booth, Jarrow</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">We decided that it would be inadvisable to make a general appeal, but the desire was expressed that I should make some public statement about the situation in the County.  I promised to consider this suggestion. After tea in the Library the company dispersed.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
