<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[180]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Saturday, November 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic bold underline">The newspapers have alarming reports of another great coal stoppage are imminent.</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">Neither masters nor men are in a reasonable, still less a conciliatory mood. The one are exasperated &amp; poverty&#8211;stricken; the others are miserable and reckless. In the present plenitude of secular cares, it seems almost intolerably trivial to be bothering about ecclesiastical affairs.  Who cares two pins about the Church when the State itself is dissolving?  In </hi><hi rend="italic underline">theory</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">Religion is the greatest of all human interests:   in </hi><hi rend="italic underline">fact</hi><hi rend="italic">, it is one among a number of hobbies, which no sane man has time or mind for in times of crisis. A man who really acted on the assumptions of his conventional religious language would be voted an insufferable crank.  Secularism is not so much the heresy of this age, </hi><hi rend="i strikethrough">but</hi> 
<hi rend="italic">as its reigning temper, and, whatever our theories or pretensions, it has us in its grip.  Contrast the eager interest with which one opens the '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times'</hi><hi rend="italic">, with the languid &amp; almost reluctant spirit in which one opens the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Greek Testament! It is this deep pervading alienation from the main stream of contemporary life which is the greatest trial of the considering &amp; sympathetic modern Christian.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[181]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Winchester Diocesan Gazette</hi><hi rend="italic"> contains two articles on the late Dean.  Both are initialled, &amp; must be taken as the offerings of personal friendship. Nevertheless, in view of facts, which were almost notorious, and which in the diocese itself occasioned a far&#8211;resounding scandal, one may well doubt the wisdom of such lavish and indiscriminating eulogy.  </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Baxter</hi><hi rend="italic">'s reflections on the untrustworthiness of history when considered in the light of one's own knowledge of affairs recurs often to one's mind.  </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">On the whole, the inference is unavoidable that the evil stories, which are told of the greatest &amp; saintliest figures of the past, must not be too summarily swept aside. When allowance has been made for the great concealing, &amp; perverting influences, there is not left much ground for confidence.</hi><hi rend="italic">  The Dean was a prominent Anglo&#8211;Catholick, and for that reason his personal reputation was a valuable asset of that party, which anything discreditable thereto would be injurious to the same.  Hence a vested interest in eulogy, and </hi><hi rend="italic underline">suppresio veri</hi><hi rend="italic">. It is well for us that the Final Judgment is not entrusted to men.  "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">We must all be made manifest before the Judgment Seat of Christ</hi><hi rend="italic">."</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[182]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Ella and Fearne went with me to Blackhall, where I consecrated the new parish church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Andrew. This church was interesting as being the discarded church of S. Paul transferred (in fragments) to Blackhall, and there re&#8211;erected at a total cost of something a little more than &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">6000</hi>. The architect told me that, if it had been a new church in the ordinary sense, it would have cost at least &#x00A3;<hi rend="doubleunderline">10,000</hi>. There was a very large congregation, and a large gathering of the local clergy. After the service, I had tea with Vicar (Rev. J.W. Heap) and his wife. We returned by way of Durham, where I stopped at the College, and spent an hour in going through diocesan business with the Bishop of Jarrow. We were back at Auckland by 6.45 p.m.</p>
         <p>Very reluctantly I have decided to reject one of the five candidates for the diaconate. But, unless the examination is to degenerate into a mere form, I cannot "pass" such papers as his.  With much hesitation I have decided to ordain to the priesthood the miner&#8211;candidate from Ferryhill. He knows little, &amp; cannot even spell tolerably, but he will never be able to improve!</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
