<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[82]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">The papers give prominence to the proceedings in the Consistory Court, which was held yesterday in Durham. </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Merryweather</hi><hi rend="italic"> was there, though not officially.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">He seems to have secured the attendance of a number of supporters for, when he refused to give an assurance that he </hi><hi rend="italic underline">w</hi><hi rend="i sup u">d</hi><hi rend="italic underline"> remove</hi><hi rend="italic"> the illegal ornaments, and said that it was against his conscience to do so, he was "loudly applauded".  In the "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Yorkshire Post</hi><hi rend="italic">" he is reported to have said that '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">the Bishop of Durham has given him permission to reserve the Sacrament</hi><hi rend="italic">, which, so far as I know, is a complete falsehood. He appears to have introduced a 'tabernacle', &amp; set it up behind the Holy Table.  Clearly we are entering on one of these woeful and interminable "ritual" disputes, which may develop into far–resounding scandal, and, incidentally, involve me in a ruinous expenditure.  Entrenched in his freehold, and supported by the "Anglo–Catholick" faction, which cannot afford to have him effectively dealt with, this worthless man can snap his fingers at the Law, the Bishop, and the parish. </hi>    
           
           
            
            <seg>    </seg>
           
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[83]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>I motored to Newcastle, and preached at a midday service in the Y.M.C.A. building. The room was filled mainly with men, of whom I should judge that the majority were middle aged <hi rend="bold">[</hi>Sectaries habituated to chapel going.<hi rend="bold">] </hi> After the service, I visited Dellow, and had my hair cut etc. Then I went to Winter &amp; Son, the Oculists, &amp; had my eyes tested. [struck through] After this, I returned to Auckland, where Mr. Haswell had already arrived. He is a middle–aged man, bald–headed, &amp; rather heavy in aspect &amp; manner. He seems, however, to be reasonable, and has moderate views.  In view of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop Eden</hi>'s hearty recommendation, I think it will be safe for me to offer him the living of Christ Church, Sunderland: but whether he will accept it does not appear quite clear.  The pension on the outgoing Incumbent has a daunting effect!  But it is evident that he desires to accept the appointment, and, as he draws his origin from Sunderland, where his father was a solicitor, his coming might not be wholly unacceptable to the people there.  His father was also an artist, &amp; painted a portrait of Bishop Lightfoot. [end]</p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
