<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[201]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday in Advent, December 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A mild fine morning, very pleasant after the storms.  I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Ella</hi> was absent, being still chained to her bed, but with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Charles</hi> &amp; <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi>, we numbered seven comm<hi rend="superscript underline">ts</hi>.</p>
         <p>I motored To Sunderland in the afternoon, and presided at a great meeting in the Victoria Hall, at which the <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of York</hi> delivered an address on '<hi rend="underline">The meaning of Fellowship</hi>'.  The floor and one of the galleries were filled, largely with men: &amp; there was a sprinkling of people in the upper gallery.  <hi rend="doubleunderline">Temple</hi> spoke well.  His address was well planned, well phrased, and well&#8211;delivered.  It would bear reading.  The Mayor moved a vote of thanks, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">Sir Walter Raine</hi> seconded.  A rather sinister looking woman, who was introduced to me as <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Marion Phillips M.P</hi>., one of the representatives of the borough, sate beside me.  After the meeting I went to the Rectory, &amp; had tea.  <hi rend="italic">Also, I had some conversation with the Archbishop.  He expressed approval of my letter in the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Times</hi><hi rend="italic"> about the situation in Birmingham; &amp; seemed rather puzzled as to the range, method &amp; result of this precious Commission on Church &amp; State, of which he is a member.  I returned to Auckland &amp; was there about 6 p.m. </hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
</body></text></TEI>
