<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[148]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">Thursday, November 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1930.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>A hard frost last night, and today a brilliant sun.</p>
         <p>Booth, the Rector of Jarrow, came to lunch bringing with him the Rev. Lionel Arnold Howe, assistant curate of Oxford, whom he is 'considering' for appointment to Hebburn.  M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Howe is a good&#8211;looking, up&#8211;standing fair&#8211;haired man, 33 years old, who served during the War, was twice wounded, and left the Army with the rank of Captain.  After the War had ended, he went to Oxford and took his degree.  He is an Anglo&#8211;Catholick, but protests that he is not 'extreme'. He is married, but childless. I liked him sufficiently to suggest to Booth that he would be better suited for S. Hilda's, Darlington than for Hebburn. I arranged that he should telegraph for his wife to come here, that they should both stay here on Friday night, and go over to see S. Hilda's on Saturday morning.</p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">I walked round the Park, &amp; was joined by </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">D. McCullagh, who expressed agreement with my opinion that the Observance of Armistice Day should be brought to an end at an early date. </hi><hi rend="italic"> He had read the report in the Yorkshire Post.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="bold">[149]</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="doubleunderline">Braley</hi>'s friend <hi rend="doubleunderline">D</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Scott</hi> came to tea – a fat, unhealthy looking batchelor, who desires a benefice in the north.  He disclaimed the title "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" and declared himself to be an Anglican.  He said that he was a friend of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Adderley</hi>'s, a fact which could not remove my doubts as to his reasonableness in ecclesiastical matters. We talked amicably for half an hour, and then parted. I was careful to make no kind of promise.</p>
         <p>I sent copies of the <hi rend="underline">Bishoprick</hi> to the following:&#8211;</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell>49.</cell>
               <cell>S.I. Bartle Esq.</cell>
               <cell>57.</cell>
               <cell>[symbol] The Warden of All Souls.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>50.</cell>
               <cell>Lord Daryngton.</cell>
               <cell>58.</cell>
               <cell>Kenneth Hope Esq.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>51.</cell>
               <cell>H. I. Torre Esq.</cell>
               <cell>59.</cell>
               <cell>George Nimmins.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>52.</cell>
               <cell>J. G. Adderley.</cell>
               <cell>60.</cell>
               <cell>George Nimmins.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>53.</cell>
               <cell>H. Bunnell Burton.</cell>
               <cell>61.</cell>
               <cell>Brooke Westcott.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>54.</cell>
               <cell>E. B. Fielden.</cell>
               <cell>62.</cell>
               <cell>Prof. Burkitt.</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>55.</cell>
               <cell>Lawrence Hardy.</cell>
               <cell>63.</cell>
               <cell>Angel</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell>56.</cell>
               <cell>Albert Mitchell.</cell>
               <cell>64.</cell>
               <cell>Unwin</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p> [symbol] </p>
         <p>
<hi rend="italic">A reporter from the </hi><hi rend="italic underline">Daily Herald</hi><hi rend="italic"> wished to know whether I would favour the change of the observance on Armistice Day, so that it should become an annual Festival of Peace; I replied in the negative.  The less of these "festivals" the better.</hi>
         </p>
         
            
         
        </body></text></TEI>
