<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The weather continues warm, but the rain has ceased. I spent the day at Lambeth in the <hi rend="bold underline">Bishop's Meeting</hi>. We spent 2 hours in discussing Reservation in communities. The subject was introduced by the Bp. of Norwich, and briskly discussed by many bishops. It appeared that Burge has conceded Reservation, which Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> had always refused: but Gore is now pressing the Bp. of Chichester to concede it! Strong, rather to my surprize, and much to my relief, came down on the side of refusing permission. I brought forward the question of the Official Press Bureau, &amp; was answered by the Bishop of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Alban's. Afterwards, the Archbishop of C. said to me, "I agree with you very largely about the Press Bureau", but his Grace gave me no support in the meeting! In the afternoon we discussed that odious subject of "Birth Control". I was surprised at the change which has passed over episcopal opinion since the Lambeth Conference. The Abp. of York, &amp; the Bps of Norwich, Hereford, &amp; Manchester spoke well. I dined at the Literary Fund Dinner. Lord Ernle<persName xml:id="1394"></persName> was in the Chair, and Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> proposed the toast of the Evening. Both were excellent speeches: as was also Sir Rennell Rodd's in replying.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[107]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I asked the following questions about the Press Bureau</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">1. What kind of information is issued to the Press?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">2. Who is responsible for (α) the substance, (β) the form of this information?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">3. To what newspapers is this information issued?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">4. How far are "inspired" articles contributed to the Press?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">5. Who writes such articles? and under what control?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">6. Are local representatives of the Press Bureau appointed to have dealings with the local newspapers?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">7. What control has the Church over the Press Bureau?</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I pointed out that an "Official Press Bureau" tends to discredit all independent information, and finally to close the Press to it. It robs the Press notices of ecclesiastical affairs of their only real value viz: as giving an independent judgement.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I protested against the tendency to advertisement – a bad leaf taken from the Nonconformist Book.</hi> <hi rend="i doubleunderline">Furse's</hi><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="1602"></persName> answer was in his characteristic style of breezy buffoonery, which seems to be so pleasing to clerical assemblies: and in spite of their private assurances of agreement, &amp; promises of support, none of the Bishops took part in the discussion. It is ever thus. One is always "thrown over" by one's friends when it comes to the "sticking point" of open conflict. Well, well!</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>