<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The proposal to revise the Prayer–book might seem truly fundamental, for the issues raised by the treatment of the Communion Office, &amp; its rubricks go to the root of the controversy between Reformed &amp; Unreformed C<hi rend="superscript underline">stins</hi>. But the habit of "make belief" which has now become "second nature" to English Churchmen will prevail, and the whole subject will be discussed as if we were all of one mind in seeking to improve our "incomparable Liturgy" as the Use of the Church of England! The proposed changes will, if adopted, have no effect whatever in securing that uniformity of practice which the Tractarians destroyed: for the variant procedures of the "Anglo–Catholicks" are now based on "Catholick principle", and do not admit of being surrendered. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Bishop of Gloucester<persName xml:id="3536"></persName></hi>, in opening the discussion, denied with some heat <hi rend="doubleunderline">Athelstan Riley's</hi><persName xml:id="213"></persName> suggestion that the intention of the Revision Committee had been to placate the "Anglo–Catholics", but since only the "Anglo–Catholicks" objected to the Prayer–book as it is, and since their lawlessness originally compelled the attempt to revise the Book, it is difficult to deny justly M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Riley's assertion. The fiction of Anglican harmony must at all hazards be preserved! But there will be "a day of the Lord" upon these persistent unrealities, and "the idols shall be utterly done away". Where will the Church of England be, &amp; how will it fare in that Day?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I travelled the normal cycle of my duty. At 9.45 a.m. I had an interview with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watkins<persName xml:id="2762"></persName> at the Club, &amp; then went on to Westminster for the National Assembly. The discussion on the Bp. of Gloucester's motion continued the whole morning. <hi rend="bold underline">I made the closing speech, which was more than commonly successful, if success may be measured by applause and compliments. My point was that revision of the Prayer–book must imply enforcement of the P. B.: and that raised the whole question of the character &amp; claim of the C. of E. Was it a "go–as–you–please" church? This implied 2 conditions – the consent of the people, and the willingness of the clergy to tolerate one another. But neither of these conditions c</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> be counted upon. I ended by quoting my favourite Butler 'tag', and applying it. I was greatly surprised at the applause with which this speech was received</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The Report was "received" by a great majority. I lunched with the Dillons<persName xml:id="3784"></persName> at 18 Cowley Street. The proceedings during the afternoon were dull enough. I walked to Lambeth where the Archbishop<persName xml:id="128"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Davidson were giving a "reception", which was spoiled by the rain. We all dined with Sir Laurence &amp; Lady Jones in Harrington Road, near Gloucester Road Station. The rain made going &amp; coming difficult. The late Bishop of Madras<persName xml:id="5157"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Whitehead were there. They have taken a house at Ledbury. She talked much &amp; offensively! I detest these forward prating women. Cody, the Canadian divine, who has declined the Archbishoprick of Melbourne, was in the gallery at the Church House during my speech.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>