<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[169]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to Darlington where we caught the early express to King's X. He left the train at Peterboro <hi rend="underline">en route</hi> for Ely. On arrival in London, I drove to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> and left my bags in 4 Dean's Yard. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where I found Tallents and the Dean of Westminster<persName xml:id="325"></persName>. I called on Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName>, and had some talk with him. Barnes<persName xml:id="3581"></persName> &amp; his wife came in to dinner.</p>
         <p>Our conversation turned inevitably on ecclesiastical affairs. Barnes is very optimistic about the outlook, but, so far as I can see, with no great reason for his confidence. He is probably right in thinking that the "Anglo–Catholic" movement cannot prevail in a people, so sane &amp; morally robust as the English; but that doesn't preclude the possibility of its capturing the Church of England. And <hi rend="underline">that</hi> is, in my view, precisely the real gravity of the movement. Thanks to the policy of the Tractarians who from the first exerted themselves to get hold of the training of the clergy, the "Anglo–Catholics" are strongly entrenched in the Universities &amp; Theological Colleges. Whatever the Bishops may desire and design, they cannot ignore the convictions of the clergy, whom they ordain, institute, &amp; license. What the clergy do and teach in the parish churches determines what the Church of England really <hi rend="underline">is</hi>. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>