<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[85]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended the celebration of Holy Communion in the palace Chapel at 8 a.m., and received the Blessed Sacrament. We despatched our business in the Convocation very rapidly, and I was able to return to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName> in time for dinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">It was agreed beforehand that we would have no speeches, except that in which the Bishop of Ripon introduced the motion for adopting the doctrinal statement</hi>. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Strong</hi> made an excellent speech, and in seconding it formally, I limited myself to a few compliments which were both deserved on his part, &amp; sincere on mine. The Archbishop with his suffragans attended the Lower House, where his Grace formally communicated our pronouncement. It seemed to be very well received. <hi rend="underline">Of the 78 lines which the Statement contains, 56 were taken from my draft: 18 from Strong's: &amp; 4 were contributed by the Archbishop. One or two verbal corrections were supplied by other bishops</hi>. <hi rend="bold underline">It is odd to reflect that four years ago I was being prayed against as a second Judas in many churches all over the country</hi>.</p>
         <p>On reaching the Caste I received the unpleasant intelligence that the motor could not possibly be repaired this week, &amp; that the Wolseley Motor C<hi rend="superscript underline">y</hi> could not yet say when the car could be ready for use! This immerses me in great inconvenience, and, I fear, in much expense , for I am pledged to a round of confirmations next week. Then I miss <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and don't like to think of him hanging about in idleness for so long. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>