<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I breakfasted pleasantly in the common room with Dibblee and his friend. Before leaving by the 10.5 express, <hi rend="bold underline">I went to the Clarendon Press, &amp; ordered Murray's English Dictionary! I shall associate it with the memory of Dicey's<persName xml:id="403"></persName> funeral</hi>. On arriving in London, I visited the hair–dresser, &amp; then went to King's Cross, where I caught the 1.10 p.m. express to Darlington. I travelled with Gurney Pease, a boy of 13, who was going home for his holiday. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Lady Lawrence were in the car, &amp; met me with the uncomfortable news that Penelope<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> had developed measles!! In view of the circumstance that the two boys are staying in the Castle this is doubly unfortunate, and has the immediate effect of bringing our Easter plans into chaos.</p>
         <p>Here is another example of a phenomenon, which I have observed to be of not infrequent occurrence in human life, viz: the largest inconveniences caused by conduct with implies the smallest measure of moral turpitude. Nobody can fairly said to be blameworthy for the arrival of this maiden in an infected condition: none the less, that circumstance causes the greatest inconvenience &amp; confusion to several people, and no slight degree of apprehension to at least two affectionate parents!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>