<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[196]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I went through the correspondence with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> before breakfast, and afterwards completed my preparations for the services later in the day. We motored into Durham in time for institutions in the Castle Chapel at noon. Then we went to a conference in Lillingston's<persName xml:id="3262"></persName> house. He and Moulsdale<persName xml:id="3159"></persName> united to press me to sanction some kind of a mission in the diocese. Now I distrust the union of Anglo–Catholicks and Protestants, &amp; I dislike all <hi rend="bold">[196]</hi> missions. Accordingly I gave no favourable response to the request that I should favour a Moulsdale–Lillingston Crusade! </p>
         <p>After lunching with Lillingston, I went to the Cathedral and preached to an immense congregation of women, members of the Mothers Union<orgName xml:id="220"></orgName>. The vergers assured me that there were more than 3000 present. A banner was presented &amp; blessed at the conclusion of the service. After tea with Lillingston, we motored to Shincliffe, where I consecrated an addition to the churchyard, and gave an address in the teeth of a high wind. We returned to Durham, and lunched in the Club with J.G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, who brought with him Sir George Riddell. This was a pleasant function enough. We motored back to Auckland after dinner, arriving a few minutes before 10 p.m. The weather today has been thunderous and uncertain, with rain–falls at intervals and sudden gusts of wind.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>