<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Macmillans send me a review of "Anglicanism" which has appeared in the 'Tablet'. It is polite, and even complimentary, which, perhaps, indicates a consciousness that Papists have nothing to lose from an exposure of "Anglo–Catholicism"</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Still it is something to be told that one has been fair, by an opponent. "Naturally he considers the Catholic version of Christianity to be wrong and mistaken: though in expressing this conviction, as indeed in all says, he is studiously moderate and charitable". "The discussion (of the Anglo– Catholic position) is conducted with perfect good temper: indeed, the whole book is a model of courteous controversy".</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> reported that the car was too seriously damaged for use. I wrote indignantly to inquire who the responsible road authority might be. A hired car was obtained, and by its means I was able to carry out my engagements. At 3 p.m. I confirmed 39 boys of the North Eastern Counties School at Barnard Castle in the school chapel: and afterwards distributed prizes to the boys. After tea with the Headmaster, I returned to the Castle, from whence after a brief interval I went out again in order to take a Confirmation at Sunnybrow. Here I confirmed 115 candidates. There was a considerable congregation, the Church being crowded, &amp; this was the more noteworthy since the weather was most unfavourable. We motored back to Auckland through the rain, and arrived in time for a belated dinner at 9 p.m. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[30]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>March 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear Sir, </p>
         <p>I should be obliged if you would inform me of what local authority is responsible for the road leading to Washington from Chester le Street. Last night I was held up on my way to Southwick by an accident, of which the sole cause was the absence of any indication visible in darkness of the fact that the road was under repair, &amp; was impassable for cars. A considerable mass of road material was lying almost at the turn of the road, so that the chauffeur could not avoid it. The car stuck fast, &amp; was extricated in a damaged condition, while I continued my journey in a hired car. My chauffeur carried me back to Auckland with difficulty, &amp; now reports that the injuries are so serious that I can have no use of the car for some days. At this time, when I am in the midst of my confirmations, the inconvenience is very great, &amp;, of course, the cost is not inconsiderable. </p>
         <p>In the interest of other travellers, I think it my duty to call to attention to these facts, &amp; to inquire whether any compensation can be obtained. </p>
         <p>Yours v. truly </p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm</p>
         <p>The Clerk D.C.C </p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>