<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[73]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to the hair–dresser, &amp; was trimmed for the function! Then to the Club, where <hi rend="italic bold underline">I wrote a letter of condolence to Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName> on the death of his wife</hi>, &amp; to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>. After lunching at the club, I walked to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's, and <hi rend="bold underline">performed the marriage ceremony for Carola Oman, whom I baptized</hi>. Gibbon, the chaplain of Balliol, assisted together with a curate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. There was a considerable gathering of friends &amp; relations. I gave a short address, which was admirably listened to by the congregation. <hi rend="bold underline">My Godson, Charlie Oman<persName xml:id="1679"></persName>, had speech with me. He is now an undergraduate at New College</hi>. From S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's I proceeded to Victoria, and caught the train for Birchington – Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName> met me on the platform. I found Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> frail but cheerful.</p>
         <p>I had an interview with Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName> in the course of the morning. He expounded some scheme for restoring a 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century porch which, he alleges, originally adorned the main entrance of Durham Cathedral, &amp; had been swept away by the destructive Wyatt. He also read me a letter from the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> practically asking him to make out as large expenditure on the fabric as possible to be necessary. Welldon over–reaches himself.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>