<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[66]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, April 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>For some reason or other I had a sleepless night, and felt the ill effects of the fast all day. I had some talk with Ernest about the Bishops' proposed declaration, &amp; showed him the drafts. At 4.30 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> and I left the Castle, &amp; motored to Hereford by way of Worcester, Malvern, &amp; Hereford. We arrived at St Peter's Vicarage about 6.15 p.m. Bateman<persName xml:id="4471"></persName> was there to welcome me! Moore had gathered a party to meet me at dinner. There was Roberts, the Tory member for Hereford. To balance him was Manders the Liberal candidate for Sudbury. The Dean, &amp; Wynne Willson<persName xml:id="4448"></persName> represented the Church. Frank James<persName xml:id="4292"></persName> &amp; his wife were also there &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wynne Willson. At 7.30 p.m. there was a meeting in the Shire Hall in advocacy of the League of Nations. The Hall was well–filled, &amp; I was the first speaker. The politicians followed, &amp; Moore wound up. All were commendably brief, so that the meeting was over by 9 p.m. <hi rend="bold underline">William motored me to Wylands, five miles from Ross, where M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Clayton received me hospitably. Her son, Bryan was also present.</hi> Before going to bed I settled accounts with William, paying £3.5.0 for divers sums expended by him, &amp; giving him £5.0.0 to be accounted for in due course. He is to get up early, to motor to Birmingham leaving the car in Wolseley's works for overhauling.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>