<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, April 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A bright morning, and a white frost. I received a rather woeful letter from poor old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Dicey, which I answered at once, &amp; copied my answer into this journal as recording my feelings about the Professor at this juncture.</p>
         <p>I motored to Etherley, &amp; confirmed 114 persons. <hi rend="bold underline">The mean little church was densely crowded, and apparently without ventilation. Therefore, the atmosphere was asphyxiating.</hi> Later, I motored to Spennymoor, &amp; confirmed 120 persons. The same conditions were repeated in a larger church. <hi rend="bold underline">The indifference of the clergy to the infamous lack of ventilation in the churches is both exasperating and melancholy. I believe this is the cause of much somnolence and inattention. But the clergy, though themselves the principal sufferers, are quite acquiescent in an evil which they could easily mitigate or remove.</hi> If my reckoning is correct, I have in the space of one calendar month confirmed no less than 3430 persons. It cannot truly be said that I am not in touch with the people. On the whole I have been favourably impressed with the aspect &amp; demeanour of the confirmation candidates. They appear to be very earnest and reverent. I am pleased also with the age of most of them. Few are under 14, and these are almost entirely found in the few Anglo&#8211;Catholick centres. Most are over 16, &amp; not a few are adults.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>April 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dicey,</p>
         <p>I am indeed distressed to hear of the Professor's grave illness, and I need not tell you how deeply I sympathize with you in this trouble. It is nearly 40 years since he and I became acquainted: and we have been close friends all the time. His indomitable industry &amp; astonishing interest &amp; alertness of mind, combined with a certain simplicity of character which I feel it natural to describe in the Gospel phrase "as a little child", made him one of the most striking and, at the same time, one of the most loveable persons, I have ever had the privilege of knowing.</p>
         <p>It must be a great comfort to you to know how universally your husband is respected and admired, &amp; also to know how entirely devoted he has always been to you. If, as we may not refuse to think, is now probable, you are called to bear the heavy trial of parting, you will fasten your thoughts on that 'sure &amp; certain' hope of recovering your fellowship in the higher life beyond the grave, which has no ending.</p>
         <p>May God bless and strengthen you, my dear Friend!</p>
         <p>Yours affect<hi rend="superscript underline">telly</hi></p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>