<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[172]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Big Ben has now a consort as clamorous as himself – the new clock in the Abbey tower. Every quarter is doubly chimed, &amp; the hours enormously emphasised. I heard the whole series from 11 p.m. to 7 a.m.!</p>
         <p>After breakfast I had my hair cut. Then I went to the Ecclesiastical Comission, &amp; had an interview with Downing. I went to Adeney in Sackville Street, &amp; ordered a suit of clothes. Then I lunched with Sir Henry<persName xml:id="344"></persName> &amp; Lady Craik<persName xml:id="793"></persName>. On his recommendation I went to Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cockburn &amp; Campbell, 14 Berkeley Street, Piccadilly, and ordered 5 doz Moselle. Also I called at Mess<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lock &amp; C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi>. &amp; ordered a new hat. Iremonger<persName xml:id="4290"></persName> came in while I was there, &amp; I spoke to him about my Durham Scheme.</p>
         <p>Then I went to King's Cross, and caught the 5.30p.m. express to Darlington, where my William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me with the car.</p>
         <p>The "Daily Telegraph" had a column of my sermon. The "Yorkshire Post", not only printed what I sent, which filled more than a column of its front page, but also had a sort leader on the subject. I hope that the sermon will have some effect in compelling Churchmen to realize whereto this Anglo–Catholick movement is really tending.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>