<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[22]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>March 21<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Lord, </p>
         <p>At Durham, as at Oxford, teaching and examining are open, as also are the theological degrees: but in <hi rend="underline">both</hi> the chairs which are held by canons are limited necessarily to men in priest's Orders. You will have observed that I propose to give the Dean and Chapter power, if funds permit, to create from time to time scholarships &amp; lectureships in Theology &amp; kindred subjects. These would be open to non&#8211;Anglicans at the discretion of the D.&amp;L. It might be well to give appointments of these to the Faculty of Theology. </p>
         <p>Lord Cave's position is not clear to me. The question surely is to whether the canonies are unnecessary, but <hi rend="underline">whether they are being used to the best advantage</hi>: and, further, in view of the relatively large &amp; probably increasing endowment of Durham Cathedral, whether we should not make sure that it is being applied to objects which are of primary value. In my view &#8211; &amp; it is shared I think by the Bishops, &amp; by the majority of the Canons, if not the whole – it would be little short of disaster if this great Foundation, historically associated as it is with the University, were impoverished, &amp; its endowments perhaps scattered for the general purposes of the Church &amp; the purpose, which it alone can serve, were lost altogether. </p>
         <p>The Dean of Durham, like the Dean of Christ Church, Oxford, has an income of &#x00A3;3000, which is greater by &#x00A3;1000 than <hi rend="bold">[23]</hi> any other dean's. This greater income was no doubt conditioned by the circumstances that those two deaneries alone were linked to academic obligations. In Christ Church the Dean was Head of a great College: in Durham, he was the warden of the University. But the Durham University Act, 1908, 1908 abolished the Wardenship, while leaving the income untouched. I think the alternative must be faced – either restore an academic function to the Dean, <hi rend="underline">or</hi> reduce the Decaual income to the normal scale, &#x00A3;2000 per annum. I prefer the first horn of the dilemma, but if the latter be taken, &#x00A3;1000 is released from one of the professorships I desire to create. </p>
         <p>The canonies of Durham are now very useful, but, I think, if my scheme could be adopted, they would be far more useful: &amp; their usefulness would be not limited to the diocese of Durham, but extended to the whole Church of England, especially the Northern Province. </p>
         <p>I can conceive the objection being taken, &amp; indeed you suggest it, that the professorships being tied to Holy Orders would be incongruous with the general character of a modern University. My answer is that the subjects dealt with, being Theological &amp; Ecclesiastical, reduces the gravity of the fact: that the endowments being ecclesiastical ought not to be secularised: that the new professorships would be in precisely the same position relatively to the University as those of Christ Church: &amp; that if the state should adopt the policy of Disestablishment, <hi rend="bold">[24]</hi> [symbol] both foundations would have to be dealt with. But I make two important concessions in the scheme 1. By the surrender of patronage to the crown: 2. By providing scholarship and lectureship (if faults permit) which would be open. </p>
         <p>All ecclesiastical arrangements are now of the nature of inferior arrangements, I mean, they could not be maintained in face of disestablishment &amp; disendowment. My scheme for Durham Cathedral is no more &amp; no less contingent than every other proposal that may be made and adapted. </p>
         <p>There are a good many details of my scheme on which opinion among its supporters is not unanimous: but I do not think these are incapable of being arranged: the essential thing is to secure agreement on the main point: that Durham Cathedral shall be recognised as unique, &amp; that the line of its development is academic, &amp; not merely ecclesiastical. </p>
         <p>I send you a memorandum <hi rend="underline">which you might cut about &amp; realises</hi>. You see, my friend, how completely I take your affection for granted, &amp; lay burdens on you, which nothing short of affection could venture to propose, or consent to sustain. Would it be wise or unwise of me to write to Low Love? </p>
         <p>Yours aff<hi rend="superscript underline">ly</hi></p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm. </p>
         </div>
         <p>Who would be the right person to draft a Bill in the event of that course being adopted? </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Snow covered the country, and snow fell at intervals during some hours. I doubted the wisdom of going again to South Shields by car: but my William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> was in valourous mood, in spite of last night's blizzard, and voted for going. I spent the morning writing letters. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> went into Durham to inquire whether, if necessary, the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> could take my confirmation next week so that I might go to the House of Lords. M. Bickley, the curate of Benfieldside, lunched here. He is ordered by the doctor to "go south" on account of his lungs – the too familiar story. We have too many physically 'lame ducks' in orders. </p>
         <p>At 5p.m. I left the Castle, and motored to South Shields, picking up Clayton in Durham on the way. I confirmed 206 candidates in S. Michael's Church, Wesloe. It is a fine modern church, adorned with an elaborate choir screen and resedors, set up as a War Memorial. Immediately after the service, the Vicar carried me to a private house, not from the Church, where I confirmed a youth in bed. Then we had coffee in the Vicarage, and returned to Auckland, where we arrived about 10.35 p.m. The snow had disappeared from the roads, though it still lay on the land, the wind had fallen, and our journey proceeded without difficulty and with comparative comfort. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>