<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[94]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>May 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Eayrs,</p>
         <p>I am greatly indebted to you for the gift of your edition of John Wesley's Letters, which I am very glad to possess, as, though both the Journal and the Sermons are well known to me, I do not possess any copy of the Letters. Your forth–coming work has a most attractive appearance, &amp; I shall look forward to its appearance. Bishop Butler must needs be supremely interesting to his Successor, but my reverence for him had been created long before I had known of sitting in his Chair: It is not altogether what he says – though that is extraordinarily impressive – nor his style of writing which has itself an amazing authority, but the indefinable spirit of awful reverence which exhales from his pages, &amp; makes one when reading Butler become solemnized as by a greater than any human Presence, that gives him an influence so exalted and so distinctive.</p>
         <p>Again thanking you,</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>Most sincerely yrs,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev. George Eayrs.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[95]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>May 10<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName>,</p>
         <p>D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Murray's case is indeed melancholy &amp; full of sinister suggestiveness. What can be the end of it all? I have always been, and I still am, an Unionist: but I hardly expected that my belief in the incapacity of the Irish for self–government would receive such emphatic confirmation.</p>
         <p>I hardly think that a man of D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Murray's abiity could be fitly placed in charge of an industrial parish, such as is typical of this diocese: but I cannot doubt that in one of the Southern dioceses he would be welcomed.</p>
         <p>I mean to send you something for the E.R. as soon as this tremendous pressure of work lightens.</p>
         <p>If you are going to Scotland, remember to break your journey at <hi rend="underline">Darlington</hi>, where you can be motored to this Castle.</p>
         <p>Yours ever,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>Harold Cox Esq.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[96]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A thrush is nesting on the ledge of the Chapel Door. I put up my hand to feel if there were any eggs, &amp; the bird itself flew out. <hi rend="bold underline">Not even the Freemasons last Sunday had scared it, though many of them felt the eggs with their fingers.</hi> A blackbird's nest with a half–fledged brood, which was in the stone screen, was wickedly destroyed by some unknown miscreants. There is a pigeon's nest on the top of the said screen with young birds in it. </p>
         <p>After lunch <hi rend="doubleunderline">Frank Berry</hi> motored me to Barnard Castle, whither Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> had bicycled in advance. Here I confirmed 130 candidates. Then we motored to Darlington, where I confirmed 257. The great disproportion of the sexes distressed me, but at Barnard Castle the numbers were nearly equal. I returned to <placeName xml:id="55">Auckland Castle</placeName> immediately after the service, arriving about 9.15 p.m. In the last 3 days I have confirmed no less than 1019 persons viz.</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">At Blaydon</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">204</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">" Tanfield</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">196</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">" Birtley</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">233</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">" Barnard Castle</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">130</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">" Darlington</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">257</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">–</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">1019</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">Confirmed during Lent</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">3691</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">–</cell>
               <cell style="text–align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">4710</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>There are 17 confirmations yet to be taken and the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> has confirmed a considerable number. I think it is probable that we shall exceed a total of 7000 candidates for this year.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>