<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[105]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, May 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A hot night followed by a wet morning. After breakfast I walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> and read the papers. They contain the reasoned verdict of the Court of Appeal rejecting Armstrong's appeal. This is a triumph of good sense, though some lawyers seem to think its interpretation of the law of evidence doubtful and perilous. Headlam<persName xml:id="552"></persName> joined me at the Club, and we drove together to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> for the meeting of the Church Property Committee. Lord Cave presided, and the Session lasted, with an interval for lunch from 10.45 a.m. to 5.45 p.m. We occupied the time in hearing the evidence of 4 bishops – Gloucester, Carlisle, Worcester, and Manchester. Sir Lewis Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName> was particularly irrelevant, long&#8211;winded, and tiresome. Nickson and I lunched together at the House of Lords, and, in the Library afterwards, talked pleasantly with Muir Mackenzie and Finlay. Afterwards I went to the Athenaeum, and wrote to <persName xml:id="112">my wife</persName> before dinner. The weather continued very warm. Last night the Government was defeated by 3 votes on the Education Estimates. <hi rend="bold underline">It is a triumph for the N. U. T., which has grown to be one of the strongest and most cynically selfish of the Trade Unions</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>