<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>There had been a considerable snow&#8211;fall during the night and the bright morning sun shone on a shrouded world. I wrote a letter to Tymms, the Curate of Jarrow, condoling with him on the death of his wife. Then I wrote to Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> invoking his assistance for my Durham Cathedral project. In the course of the morning William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> brought his camera, &amp; photographed me in my study&#8211;chair.</p>
         <p>Lloyd George carried his vote of confidence by a majority of 278, after a hollow &amp; futile debate. His own speech was studiously moderate. He evidently realizes that he is rather tolerated than obeyed.</p>
         <p>I motored to Burnmoor, and there confirmed 100 candidates. On my return to the castle, I found that Ruth Spooner<persName xml:id="2161"></persName> and Edward Inge had arrived.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A letter from Dibblee informed me that dear old Dicey<persName xml:id="403"></persName> was at the point to die, and inquired whether I could take the funeral when the disaster happened. I wrote at once to say that I would come if I possibly could.</hi> Also, I heard that Johnson was ill, &amp; I wrote to him. Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> wrote to tell me that that wonderful old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Story, the Principal's widow, was under the impression that I was offended! She says (and it may be true, for I remember nothing on the matter) that she wrote to congratulate me on my appointment to Durham, &amp; had received no acknowledgement. I wrote to her.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>