<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 11.30 a.m., &amp; motored to Durham, where I instituted two curates in the chapel of the other Castle. Then I went to Andrewes, and ordered some books for <hi rend="doubleunderline">Michell Pierce</hi>. We lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Wilson</hi><persName xml:id="2748"></persName> very pleasantly. <hi rend="doubleunderline">How</hi> being the other member if the party. I spoke to him with some earnestness on the subject of my Scheme, &amp; expressed my hope that the University would ignore the vapourings of the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> &amp; the Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName>! Then, in the Chapter Office, I had an interview with one of the Deaconesses, who has had the temerity to read Evensong &amp; preach in a parish church on the invitation of the incumbent! I spoke severely to her, &amp; reserved judgement until I could hear from the Warden of the Deaconess' Society. We motored to West Hartlepool, where I was taken to a house, &amp; confirmed there a sick girl. Then, after tea with Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>, I took in succession two confirmations, first, in S. John's Church where about 130 candidates were presented, next, in S. Paul's, where they numbered 150. I was struck by the large attendance of witnesses &amp; others in both churches. We returned to Auckland immediately after these functions were concluded, &amp; arrived at 10.15 pm. It is difficult when one sees large churches crowded with reverent and attentive congregations, &amp; observes so many young people of both sexes coming up very gravely &amp; devotedly to receive the laying on of hands from the Bishop, not to allow one's self to suppose that Religion yet retains its hold over the English people.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>