<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[37]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Mayor's house at 9.45 a.m. and visited Peter at the Parish Church. He showed us round his woeful parish, &amp; we visited the school. Then we went to S. John's where the Vicar, Jackson, showed us the house in which he desires to establish a curate, &amp; the church. Clayton then left me at Canon Goldsmith's<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> Vicarage. Here I had an interview with young Richardson, the curate at St Matthew's Hebburn, who wants to leave that parish. When he had departed, Goldsmith and I motored to Cleadon, &amp; picked up the Vicar, Moorson, who guided us to the place where South Shields corporation have erected 300 houses, &amp; where many more are projected. It is thought that a site should be secured for a church etc, in case a new parish should ultimately be necessary. Hudson Barker joined us, &amp; we agreed upon a sight. We visited Harton church, a small building said to be very ill attended. After lunching with the Mayor &amp; Mayoress we went to Silksworth where I confirmed 160 persons. Then, later, I went accompanied by the Mayor to All Saints, Monkwearmouth, &amp; confirmed 120 persons. We had supper with the Mayor &amp; Mayoress, &amp; then motored back to Auckland, where we arrived about 11.30 p.m. The Mayor's attendance at 2 of these confirmations, &amp; evident interest in them, pleased me.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>