<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, March 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The landscape presents a wintry aspect, snow having fallen during the night. Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName> sends me a copy of the declaration on the Cambridge Essayists, which he was prepared to propose to the Lower House of Convocation. It is too much concerned with snubbing the petitioners of the E.C.U.<orgName xml:id="20"></orgName> to be of any possible use to re&#8211;assure the distressed 'faithful'.</p>
         <p>After lunch I motored to Barnard Castle, and presided at a meeting of the North&#8211;Eastern Counties school. We had a considerable discussion with the representatives of the Board of Education on the proposed expenditure of the Governors for providing sick&#8211;rooms for the school. The Vicar of Barnard Castle adopted a line in debate contrary to that of his diocesan, and evidently commanded a measure of sympathy. However he was outvoted by 8 to 4. I sate outside with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> when motoring back to the Castle, but it was mortally cold.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">How</hi>, referring to my motor&#8211;disaster, sends me the following:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Nos aequo, Praesul, petimus caelestia cursu:</p>
         <p>Tu cave praevenias horridiore vi&#x00E2;.</p>
         </div>
         <p>And as an alternative rendering of the same thought:&#8211; </p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Te duce nos aequo petimus caelestia cursu.</p>
         <p>O salibrosa cave ne via proripiat.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The peccant official sends me a letter of apology, which I accepted, though it is no more than obvious justice that my losses should be made good!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>