<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[203]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I received the Holy Communion together in the School Chapel. It was a moving sight to see so many bright lads coming to the Sacrament. After breakfast with the Provost &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Woodhouse his sister (to which meal 3 boys came) we went to Chapel for Mattins. I sate beside the Provost until the Holy Communion service began, when I went up to the Altar, &amp; read the Gospel. After the Nicene Creed came a hymn, and then I preached. My text was S. John XXI. 18., but it had little connexion with the sermon, of which the "burden" was an appeal to Etonians to look forward to Ordination. The boys were very attentive, &amp; I was assured that they were impressed. I lunched with the college, and afterwards walked with Ella into Windsor, &amp; called on M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Baillie. The Dean<persName xml:id="4115"></persName> was absent. His wife told me that he is not infrequently approached by wealthy man, who offer to provide whatever sums may be necessary for the restoration of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George's Chapel if only he will secure them a baronetcy! <hi rend="italic">Old Canon Dalton<persName xml:id="2383"></persName> met us in the street, &amp;, after his own indecent fashion, began forthwith to speak of the prospective vacancy in the Primacy! "They say that Cantuar won't resign because he fears that he will be succeeded by the Bp. of D–m!" How preposterous &amp; potentially hurtful this kind of fooling is! We dined with the Alingtons<persName xml:id="541"></persName><persName xml:id="777"></persName>. I had some talk with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Dawson. Before going to bed, I talked with the Provost</hi>.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>