<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[190]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The "British Weekly" has a leader on the subject of "Reunion", in which the course of events since the publication of the Lambeth Appeal is reviewed, and the conclusion is reached that no progress has been made, or, on the basis of that Appeal can be made. Reference is made to my Westminster Sermon, and the position therein maintained is endorsed. The "Tablet" also refers to that sermon, and accepts (as it naturally would) the contention that the Church of England cannot "have it both ways". This agreement of Puritans &amp; Papists will no doubt appear to the good "Anglo–Catholick" as natural, familiar, and significant. He will even draw from it an inference, consoling to his vanity and soothing to his fears. But he forgets one circumstance of crucial importance, which differentiates the Church of England which was pictured as a <hi rend="underline">via media</hi>, and the Church of England as he would represent it. The first was Protestant, its mediating moderation was displayed in a superstructure which rested on the principle of private judgement applied to the single &amp; conclusive authority of Holy Scripture. The last is Catholick, its distinctive features are limited to a few insularities &amp; permissible archaisms included in a system which rests on authority, the authority of the historic institution: &amp; <hi rend="underline">that</hi> authority declines to recognize it.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[191]</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName> and, after revising my discourse, proceeded to the Chapel Royal, and preached the sermon. The little building was quite full. In the congregation were Milo Gates, L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Charnwood<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> with his wife<persName xml:id="2768"></persName> &amp; daughter. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Channing, Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName>, Sir John Struthers<persName xml:id="2244"></persName>, &amp; the Dean of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. I lunched at the Deanery, and afterwards walked with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> as far as Charing Cross. Then I went to the Club, and stayed there until it was time for me to go to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's, Vere Street where the 200<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> anniversary of the church was being celebrated. There was a considerable congregation, but the galleries were by no means filled. Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> was said to have been present, but I did not see him. My sermon seemed curiously out of place for the occasion: but it was closely listened to. I returned to the Deanery for supper. Mary Radford<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> joined us.</p>
         <p>I wrote to my nephew Harold<persName xml:id="1097"></persName>, and sent him £20 as a wedding present. The young fool enters into matrimony this month. Sir Henry Newbolt was in the club. He said that the miners in Durham had asked him to lecture to them. I suggested that he should come &amp; stay at Auckland. Lord Muir Mackenzie<persName xml:id="601"></persName> was also in the club, and I had some speech with him. He thinks that the Ecclesiastical Committee of the Privy Council<note xml:id="567" n="1"></note> might well take the view that increasing the episcopate was a proceeding which affected the public interest generally, and on that ground might hold itself free to reject a measure sent up by the National Assembly.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>