<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[199]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote a short sermon for the Etonians, but with a quite absurd expenditure of time &amp; effort. My brain must be beginning to soften! In the afternoon I spent 1<hi rend="superscript underline">1/2 </hi>hours in playing bowls with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>.</p>
         <p>The Editor of "The Leicester Herald" sends me the consignment which he received from the <hi rend="bold underline">"Press Bureau of the Church of England",</hi> &amp; which purported to give an account of the recent meetings of the National Assembly. "You will note that this report reached us on Wednesday in this week, following the conclusion of the business last Saturday, &amp; is, therefore hopelessly out of date. It is a waste of money to send out reports like this so long after the event". If the editor finds the Report belated: I find it misleading. <hi rend="bold underline">My speech on P.B. Revision is not reported at all, and yet, not only was it by general consent the speech of the session, but also it carried the Evangelicals into supporting the B</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">p</hi><hi rend="bold underline">. of Gloucester's motion.</hi> It is of course true that the same oblivion is meted out to other speakers, but if the Press made its own report it w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> certainly differentiate between the speeches which counted and those which did not.</p>
         <p>I wrote to Gilbert<persName xml:id="1095"></persName>. It is woeful that my correspondence with him should be so infrequent but long absence breeds estrangement, and great distance obstructs mutual understanding. It is difficult to create community of interest when personal association is only an affair of a few weeks in the course of adult life. Duty rather than affection perpetuates the link of nature.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[200]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>July 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Jubb, </p>
         <p>I have read with care &amp; sympathy the letter which you have addressed to me. Your son came to me, not for advice on the main question of secession, but on the very different question, namely whether, having made up his mind to become a Roman Catholic, he could for the present continue to hold office in the Church of England. To that question, I apprehend, there was only one answer possible. I offered your son a week's delay for consideration but he declined my offer, affirming that his mind was fully made up, &amp; that he was in communication with the Roman ecclesiasticks. In these circumstances there was no other course open to me than to revoke his license without delay.</p>
         <p>I have received no application from him on the subject of restoration to the Church &amp; Ministry which he has renounced. If, and when, such an application comes to me, I shall certainly give it careful consideration: but I cannot pretend to think it probable that I should sanction his ministry in my diocese. I take a very grave view of secession, and cannot allow clergymen to change churches without marking their behaviour as implying very grave consequences.</p>
         <p>Perhaps I should add that the so called "Anglo–Catholic" opinions which your son held while still officiating in <hi rend="bold">[201] </hi>this diocese appear to me far more congruous with membership of the Church of Rome than with that of the Church of England. Probably, having been admitted to the Roman Communion, he had better continue in it.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> L .H. Bromley Jubb</p>
         <p>1028 Chamberlain S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi>, Victoria B.C.</p>
         <p>July 7<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lyttelton<persName xml:id="3584"></persName>, </p>
         <p>I am at one with you in thinking that the tone &amp; temper of the school teachers are of the greatest importance, &amp; I sh<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> not be indisposed to do anything in my power to assist any well–considered scheme for helping the teachers themselves to realize how much depends on them. But I confess to considerable scepticism as to the success of anything organised by the Rev. L. L. Barclay<persName xml:id="5283"></persName>, whom I know to be in other connexions an extremely unwise man, &amp; <hi rend="bold">[201]</hi> who certainly "carries no guns" in the diocese. This is, of course, for your private ear, but it needs saying.</p>
         <p>Believe me, Yours v faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Hon. &amp; Rev. E Lyttelton.</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>