<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[60]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Eve, April 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A high wind with bright sun and occasional showers. I began my day by writing to Stephenson a letter of appreciation for his workers &amp;c. in Gateshead. Then, until lunch time, I wrote letters. After lunch I read M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Darling's summing up in the Armstrong case. There could hardly have been any doubt about the wretched man's guilt. The jury quickly decided on a verdict of "Guilty", &amp; sentence of death was pronounced. Few poisoning cases have been more astonishing.</p>
         <p>After dinner I took John to my study, and had some talk with him about the Holy Communion, which he hopes to receive for the first time tomorrow morning. He had received no instruction on this subject from tutor, who prepared him for Confirmation, but he had read through the service, and thought for himself. I contented myself with pointing out the significance of the Sacrament as the appointed act of public witness, the central energy of corporate worship, and the supreme instrument of personal religion. I explained Christ's Presence in the sacrament as the fulfilment of His Promise, "Where two or three are gathered together, there am I in the midst of them". Then we went through the service, which John evidently liked and admired: &amp; so with a few kind words of encouragement we parted. He is an unusual and attractive boy, intellectual perhaps beyond his physical strength, with a humour &amp; affectionateness which are unusual.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>