<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[142]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Whitsunday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>"<hi rend="underline">A right judgment in all things</hi>" – that might seem to be of all boons, the one for which a bishop should pray most earnestly. For none is more needed for his work. To judge of the fitness of persons, of the lawfulness &amp; expediency of methods, of the soundness and prudence of policies – that is what he is continually being called to do. He labours always under grave disadvantages for he rarely hears the truth about himself or about others; he is dependent on the information &amp; counsel of men who are rarely, if ever, disinterested; and his own preferences, prejudices, and even reasonable desires will be always thrusting irrelevant considerations into his particular judgments. The resources, human and material, which are at his disposal are ludicrously inadequate. He has to consider how far the requirements of duty can be adjusted to the limitations of his means. His theoretical authority is out of all proportion to his actual power. He has to lead a double life, speaking the natural language of his own convictions only where those convictions are understood and shared: and everywhere else using the foreign tongue of conscious make–belief. If he be a liberal–minded, educated, and genuine man, he will chafe under the strain of this dualism, which will fret, wound, and humiliate him at every turn. The more conventional he is, the more intelligible he will be to others, &amp; the more contented in himself.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[143]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>There was no celebration of the Holy Communion in the chapel because I had undertaken to celebrate later at S. Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName>, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> was celebrating in Spennymoor. I went into the Chapel &amp; was alone with God, my thoughts, and its memories. At breakfast time Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> arrived with a friend on a side–car &amp; motor cycle. He consulted me about applying for the wardenship of a hostel at Birmingham, and I dissuaded him: but, of course, he will take his own course.</p>
         <p>I preached in S. Anne's, and celebrated the Holy Communion. After lunch we (i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Caröe<persName xml:id="648"></persName>, &amp; I) motored into Durham and attended Evensong in the Cathedral. I occupied the Throne, and indulged in historical imaginings. After tea with Dawson Walker<persName xml:id="3161"></persName> I ascended the Tower with Caröe, &amp; was shown the work which is in progress. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came with us, and was intelligently interested. We then walked to <orgName xml:id="16">S. Margaret's</orgName>, where I preached to a large congregation. After supper at the Rectory we returned to Auckland, arriving about 10 p.m.</p>
         <p>Harrison, the organ–builder, who is churchwarden of S. Margaret's, came to supper. He said that the Organist of Notre Dame, ignorant of the nature of the building, accepted an engagement at the Hippodrome in Bishop Auckland, for which he received a fee of 25 guineas. He was not a little disgusted when he realised the situation. <hi rend="bold underline">Harrison considers him to be probably the greatest of living organists</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>