<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[58]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Good Friday, April 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>What is, here and now, the message of the Cross? Assuredly it is the case that the grand supposition of every doctrine of Redemption – the Fact of Sin – is with us still, terrifying, persistent, enigmatic as ever. But all that background of belief which lies behind S. Paul's formula "Jesus Christ &amp; Him Crucified" does not any more exist. We come to the Gospel with minds filled with the theories of "comparative Religion", and we discuss the resemblances &amp; differences of Christianity as compared with other "mystery cults". There is no redemption here. To talk about the Gospel is not to proclaim it: &amp;, of all the preachers who shall preach today, how many will do more than talk about their presumed message? It may indeed be the case that we ascribe to the general body of our hearers the scepticism and perplexity which darken our own minds, and that the hallowed phrases which have lost significance for ourselves do still bring to them the truth they need &amp; desire. But even so, how can we be other than, in the first place, true to ourselves? How can we without forfeiture of self&#8211;respect say to others what we could not sincerely say to ourselves? Would He, the Truth Incarnate, desire, commission, or validate such an accommodation? If but one could be true to one's whole vision of the truth, would the scepticism of the mind or the insistent testimony of the conscience shape one's message? And would the message be recognizably that of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[59]</hi></p>
         <p>I read the Ante&#8211;Communion service in the chapel at 8 a.m. After breakfast I went to my study and wrote a sermon for use in the evening. After lunch we (i.e. Aleck Lawrence, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, and I) motored into Durham, and attended evensong in the Cathedral. The wretched weather – it was raining "cats and dogs"&#8211; explained the smallness of the congregation. After service we motored to Gateshead, and went to the rectory. Here we had tea, &amp; then I had interviews with a young man named Wall, who, having been bred a Papist, now desired to become an Anglican, and (when he had departed ) with Crick, a youth who was considering whether or not he should accept Stephenson's offer of a title? He appears to be under "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" influences, and I doubt whether he will be permitted to come into this heretical diocese. We had been hoping against hope that the weather would permit the carrying through of the plan, which had been so carefully arranged, for preaching in the streets. But the rain was pitiless &amp; persistent. Perforce we limited ourselves to the brief walk from the Town Hall to the parish church, where we held our service. The church was filled with men, and there was a considerable service outside in the rain. We returned to Auckland immediately, being much impeded on our way by the fog which grew ever denser as we approached the Castle.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>