<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, May 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather is so warm that I can work with my window widely opened. Perhaps for this reason I feel physically disordered, and extremely disinclined for my duty!</p>
         <p>On the 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> March I sent a parcel of books to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Michell Pierce</hi> in Canada. This morning I received a letter from him thanking me for the gift. He says that the books arrived on Easter Eve i.e. April 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Bickmore, the Vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Peter's. came to tell me that he had decided to resign his parish. He is but in his 61<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> year, &amp; looks younger, but he alleges that his health is no longer adequate to the work, and that his wife's health is as little satisfactory as his own. Happily he has private means. The next appointment is in the Crown.</p>
         <p>Archdeacon Derry<persName xml:id="3688"></persName>, who is admitting Churchwardens, lunched here, and so did Burrill, his official.</p>
         <p>The copies of the Memorandum arrived from Caldcleugh, and I sent 15 copies to Lawrence for distribution to L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Cave's C<hi rend="superscript underline">tee</hi>. Also I myself sent copies to the Archbishops, &amp; the Northern Bishops.</p>
         <p>Frank Berry motored me to Gateshead, where I confirmed 150 persons in the parish church, and had interviews with 4 persons. We returned to the Castle immediately after the service had ended, arriving about 10 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>