<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> left by the early train, &amp; Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> did the correspondence with me before breakfast. I occupied the morning on my address for the Diocesan Conference. After lunch Clayton and I motored to Castle Eden, where I confirmed 104 candidates. The church was built at the end of the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, &amp; has been handsomely restored in the 19<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. A considerable congregation came together to witness the confirmation. Among them was Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName> from Hartlepool. We had tea in the Rectory. The Rector, Gough, is a brother of the fire&#8211;eating windbag at Brompton, to whom the War brought notoriety. We motored to Deaf Hill, and their [sic] in a crowded church with an asphyxiating atmosphere, I confirmed 120 candidates. The confirmation evidently interested the inhabitants, all mining folk, who gathered about the church&#8211;door in numbers, &amp; watched my arrival &amp; departure with much attention! We motored back to the Castle after service, and arrived at 9.15 p.m.</p>
         <p>We started the correspondence at 7.45 a.m. and have been continuously active "on our job" to 9.15 p.m. – 13 1/2 hours. This is a fairly average day in the life of an episcopal house. It cannot be fairly described as idle, but what is the real value of the diverse activities which have filled it, may fairly be questioned!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>June 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Lea,</p>
         <p>I have been carefully through my record since 1918 in order to find exactly what my "literary earnings" amounted to, and I find that they were sufficiently petty:</p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">In 1918</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;6.6.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">" 1919</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#x00A3;84.0.0</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">" 1920</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="underline">&#x00A3;32.7.0</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">&#8211;</cell>
               <cell style="text&#8211;align: left;">
                  <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;122.13.0</hi>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>From this must be deducted books purchased for the purpose of producing the articles which earned this amount. The cost of these was certainly not less than &#x00A3;8.0.0. Thus the net amount would be &#x00A3;114:13:0, on which the sum payable in any one year should not exceed <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;38:4:4</hi></p>
         <p>I find that under the item '<hi rend="underline">stationary, stamps, &amp; telehone</hi>' I omitted the first item, which cannot be placed at less than &#x00A3;20 per annum: which would bring the total to <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;70</hi>.</p>
         <p>I find that I paid two insurances which are for heir&#8211;looms, viz: the Chapel Plate &#x00A3;9.9.3, &amp; the Pictures &#x00A3;7.10.0 making together <hi rend="doubleunderline">&#x00A3;16.19.3</hi>. </p>
         <p>I think I have answered everything.</p>
         <p>Yours ever, </p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[153]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>June 8<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Courtney,</p>
         <p>I do not like to leave your letter unanswered, though of course I cannot enter on a discussion of the large &amp; complicated issues which it raises.</p>
         <p>Temperance is, obviously, an integral part of morality, and no Christian could possibly think lightly of the disgusting vice of drunkenness. But I find no warrant for identifying Temperance with Total Abstinence, in the Scriptures, or in the tradition of the Christian Society, or in the practice of modern Christians.</p>
         <p>I think we have no right to impose a restriction, as a necessary element in an honest profession of Christ's Religion, for which we have no authority in the Teaching &amp; Example of Christ &amp; His Apostles; and I am sure that, in proportion as we do this, with however excellent intention, we throw the general conscience into revolt against our message, &amp; thereby hinder men from "entering the Kingdom".</p>
         <p>As to Prohibition in America, I think it is far too early for judging its effects. <hi rend="underline">Immediately</hi> so drastic a policy must work dramatic change: but wait 30 years, &amp; see what has happened. I am clear that the <hi rend="underline">principle</hi> of total abstinence is unsound, &amp; that the policy of <hi rend="underline">compulsory</hi> total abstinence is both unjust &amp; unwise. I shall oppose prohibition, &amp; every <hi rend="bold">[154] </hi>approach to it, in this country: though I will heartily support any social policy which is both economically sound &amp; friendly to temperance among the people.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev. A. Jeans Courtney</p>
         </div>
         <p>Macdonald sends me a letter from Freddie, who has encountered an agnostic undergraduate, &amp; is perturbed by his argumentation. He suggests that I should write to him. The agnostic was both voluble and dogmatic, so that the ingenuous Freddie was perplexed. I must send a letter of sympathy &amp; reassurance. It is pleasant to read the final paragraph: "I absolutely yearn to be the means of leading this otherwise admirable man to know God, but I don't know what to say at present".</p>
         <p>I finished the Presidential Address. In the afternoon, the "Tristram Society" from Durham School, about 30 boys, came to have tea, &amp; see the Castle. About 6 p.m. the 4 Ordination candidates arrived, and also Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName>. He gave the address in the Chapel at Evensong. After dinner Knight and I walked in the Park, &amp; had some talk with 4 young men, of whom 3 had been out of work for many months.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>