<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[122]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Ascension Day, May 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>There was a tremendous thunder&#8211;storm about 6 a.m. with heavy rain. I returned to Auckland after breakfast. As far as York I had the company of the Abp. of York, &amp; much conversation. He showed me the conclusions to which the Committees, Anglican &amp; Nonconformist, over which he has been presiding, have arrived on the 3 cardinal issues of the Church, the Ministry, and the place of creeds. I find it difficult to believe that any other practical result can come from these conferences than a steady weakening of Protestantism, which is weak enough already. The rank and file of the sects are not really interested in the subject, and all the 'vested interests' of sectarianism will rise in revolt as soon as any practical step is proposed. The true question in all discussions of Reunion is, What are you prepared to give up?, and nobody faces that. So long as the discussions are abstract &amp; impersonal, they prove nothing and advance nothing.</p>
         <p>My dear William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> met me at Darlington, looking rather thin, not at all as if he had had a month's holiday in his face!</p>
         <p>Colonel Lowe, the Bursar of University College, Durham, died suddenly yesterday. He was only 42.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[123]</hi></p>
         <p>Can I connect the history of Bede with an exhortation to the students of Bede College? He was both a great teacher and a hard student: this combination is the only real guarantee of didactic efficiency. He was regular at the monastic services as well as keenly interested in larger interests than those of the monastic life: this combination is the security against dissipation of energy. His whole life (saving a few visits, possibly one to Rome) was spent at Jarrow. The school&#8211;teacher has commonly little change of sphere. Bede's vivid interest in the events of his own time – to which we owe his "Ecclesiastical History" – was quickened rather than restrained by his learned labours. His enthusiasm for work, which kept him at his task on his death&#8211;bed, discloses the teacher's temperament. I want to tell these vainglorious &amp; hide&#8211;bound students that the N.U.T. which dominates their profession is a thoroughly degrading influence: that in organizing for the professed purpose of "raising the status of the educational profession", it has only succeeded in obscuring the educational ideal, &amp; inflicting damage on educational method. They are exchanging a spiritual pastorate for a mechanical labour, selling their birthright for a mess of Red pottage!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[124]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Aedesius</hi> the Cappadocian was extremely well&#8211;born, but his family was not possessed of great wealth, and therefore his father sent him away from Cappadocia to Greece to educate himself with a view to making money, thinking that he would find a treasure in his son. But on his return, when he discovered that he was inclined to philosophy he drove him out of his house as useless. And as he drove him forth he asked: "Why, what good does philosophy do you?". Whereupon his son turned round &amp; replied: "<hi rend="underline">It is no small thing, father, to have learned to revere one's father when he is driving one forth</hi>." When his father heard this, he called his son back, &amp; expressed his approval of his virtuous character. And for the future Aedesius devoted himself entirely to finishing his interrupted education. Moreover his father eagerly encouraged his son to go, &amp; rejoiced exceedingly, as though he were the father of a god rather than of a man.</p>
         <p>v. Eutropius 'Lives of the Philosophers'. p. 379. </p>
         <p>It is not increases of salary that can permanently '"raise the status" of the educational profession, but the homage of the general conscience gained by high and unselfish service. The millionaire is not the most respected of modern men, &amp; such homage as he receives is paid to his money, not to himself. The doctor is, perhaps, more widely respected than any other professional man though he is far indeed from being the most highly remunerated.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>