<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[221]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I read through Leslie Stephens's Article on Sir Walter Scott in the Dictionary of National Biography. It fills 24 two&#8211;coloured pages, and is admirably balanced and concise.</p>
         <p>Twelve Rural Deans with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Quick came to attend a conference, dine, and sleep. After tea we discussed my project for financing the diocese by levying a voluntary rate on those whose names are on the Electoral Rolls. We did not get to much practical result, but I think some impression was made. Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> raised the question of a Memorial to Bishop Moule. Opinion was much divided on the subject. At dinner it interested me to notice that of the whole company, numbering 18, only 3 viz: Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>, Boutflower<persName xml:id="3585"></persName>, and I, took wine. Total abstinence is becoming the habit of the clergy. Is this a fact to be rejoiced over, or lamented? The organist of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Anne's<placeName xml:id="104"></placeName> came to Evensong, &amp; played the organ.</p>
         <p>Today William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> completes three years in my service. He has certainly done his chauffeur's duty well, and has grown into a considerable intimacy of personal friendship. We are so constantly together, and I depend on him so much, that in any case we must have become something more than master and man: but the spiritual relation between us created by his receiving Baptism and Confirmation from my hands has hallowed &amp; ennobled our union.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>