<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[212]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I put together some notes for an address to the lay&#8211;workers on Sunday observance, a subject on which I apprehend that they are often holding faith, and probably with little wisdom. It is a very difficult subject for me to handle, for I cannot endorse the severely religious teaching, which on practical grounds I am distressed at the rapid secularisation of the Lord's Day. I seem doomed to raise expectations which I must needs disappoint. It is so with the subject of Temperance. It is so with the subject of Theological Liberalism. Men cannot understand why, since I go with them so far. I do not go with them the rest of the way to their fanatical conclusion.</p>
         <p>Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lowe with their son Ralph came to lunch. Ralph is just back from India where he saw something of the Prince of Wales's tour. At Peshawar, the visit was a complete failure. H. R. H. was interrupted, &amp; the ride through the City was abandoned. There had been a great resentment to this arrangement, &amp; the dispute was not yet settled.</p>
         <p>After lunch Murray<persName xml:id="227"></persName> &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="666"></persName>, Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I motored to High Force. The water&#8211;fall was in fine condition, but the weather was too wet &amp; misty for enjoyment. We motored to Whorlton, where I consecrated an addition to the churchyard, &amp; gave an address in the parish church. We got back to the Castle in good time for dinner. Cruickshank talked with me before going to bed. He described the situation within the Chapter. It is certainly neither comfortable, nor creditable, nor, indeed, wholly intelligible.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>