<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[188]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The National Assembly gave general approval the Archdeacon of Oakham's Dilapidations Measure, and then got on to the Bishop of Manchester's<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> motion for increasing the Episcopate. <hi rend="bold underline">I made a speech in opposition which held the house.</hi> After a long discussion the Report was received, &amp; a much truncated motion passed. On the whole this meant a partial rebuff for "Life &amp; Liberty". <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury declared himself against "small" bishoprics, and the Bishop of Ely confessed that he repented of his efforts to divide his own bishoprics.</hi></p>
         <p> I lunched again with the Dillons<persName xml:id="3784"></persName>: &amp; then went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. It is stated in the 'Times' that 30 "Anglo&#8211;Catholick" leaders have signed a repudiation of Athelstan Ridley's speech in the Assembly. The usual hypocritical process is evidently repeating itself. There will be a short pause on a greatly advanced plane, &amp; then the process of going forward will be resumed!</p>
         <p>I dined at the Deanery. Campbell Dodgson &amp; his wife, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Belloc Lowndes , Lord Lowe, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Stanley Leathes &amp; ourselves were the company. I had a good deal of talk with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Belloc Lowndes on the present state of "Society". She gave me a rather startling description of her own knowledge of it, &amp; illustrated with many particular examples of depravity. In spite of the fact that she is a Roman Catholick, she expressed very "liberal" views on the relation of the sexes, though she declared herself resolutely opposed to divorce. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>