<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[36]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, March 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>Was not this love indeed?</p>
         <p>We men may say more, swear more: but indeed</p>
         <p>Our shows are more than will, for still we prove</p>
         <p>Much in our vows, but little in our love</p>
         <p>"Twelfth night"</p>
         </div>
         <p>Today I have to make a speech on the unhappiest subject in the world, that namely which is implied by a Rescue Home for Women &amp; Girls. I dislike the subject infinitely, but as Bishop I cannot wholly avoid it. The horrible obsession of "social workers" with venereal disease &amp; hateful proposals of the doctors, to many of whom there is no moral aspect to sexual irregularity, make public speaking on the matter as difficult as it is invidious.</p>
         <p>In woeful weather Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the castle at 1.30 p.m. and motored over the worst road in the county to Sunderland. Here I addressed a very small meeting in the Town Hall in the interest of St Agatha's Rescue Home. Then we had tea with Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> and his family. We went to the Mayor's before going to the Confirmation in a poor little church, St Peter's, tucked away in very mean streets. It was densely crowded. I confirmed 80 persons. We returned to the Mayor's house for the night. He talked rather alarmingly about the communist movement in Sunderland. He says there is a school – Proletarian Sunday School – with about 300 children, &amp; promised to send me specific information.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>