<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[75]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A white frost speedily dispelled by a brilliant sun. The post brought a communication from Wolseley Motors C<hi rend="superscript underline">o</hi> which was sufficiently disquieting. They estimate the necessary repairs will cost &#x00A3;229:, and ask for a longer time in which to get them done. This unexpectedly large expenditure following upon the large payment for the new boiler tc. goes far to derange my finances: &amp; brings up the cost of the car to at least &#x00A3;1000. It is often observed than in the long run second&#8211;hand cars rarely prove cheaper than new ones. I spent the day in preparing for my work tomorrow, &amp; the measure of my success was woefully small. A young man, named Strong<persName xml:id="5382"></persName>, who desires to be ordained on a title to St Mary's, Tyne dock, lunched here. I wish he were going to a more moderate type of parish.</p>
         <p>The new Vicar of Bishop Auckland who is to be instituted in South Church tomorrow morning arrived with his wife. I had some talk with him before going to bed. He has hitherto failed to obtain curates, a fact which he explains by 1.) The circumstance that he is not himself an Anglo&#8211;Catholic, 2.) that he can offer no more than &#x00A3;250 per annum. It appears that a minimum of &#x00A3;300 is now expected. It is not a little remarkable that while the popular demand for their services steadily wanes, the clergy should estimate the value of their services at an ever higher rate. And by universal agreement the quality of their services ever deteriorates!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>April 29<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Macdonald<persName xml:id="3698"></persName>,</p>
         <p>Your letter came into my hands too late for me to be of any service to you. I think it is of very great importance to distinguish clearly between the interest of morality, which directly concerns the Church, and the interest of health which directly concerns the State. Therefore, I am not disposed officially to offer any opposition to any steps, not in themselves morally wrong, which the State may take in order to restrict the ravages of venereal disease. I might even, as a citizen, agree to much which w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> be highly repulsive to my feelings as a Christian. I incline, however to think that the doctors greatly overrate the practical effect of their prophylactics &amp; detailed counsels. The conditions, local &amp; temperamental, required for obedience to the last rarely exist in the case of sexual indulgence: &amp; I know that opponents of this method of combating venereal disease argue energetically that it is rather a theoretical than a practical remedy. Nor do I think its advocates quite realise the far&#8211;reaching mischief of the disastrously welcome assurance that with a little care immunity from disease can be secured by the vicious. Self&#8211;control, assisted by healthy exercise, &amp; fairly early marriage, is the only effectual method.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77]</hi></p>
         <p>The doctors are as eagerly credulous in their own sphere as the parsons are in theirs. In spite of the prodigious efforts to inform, protect, and warn, I do not observe any appreciable improvement in the matter of sexual vice. On the contrary, I suspect that the gross familiarity with which the subject has now been invested has had an appreciable effect in lowering the moral temperature, &amp; so far facilitating moral failure.</p>
         <p>I think he clergy cannot fitly be asked to do more than <hi rend="underline">acquiesce in</hi> such measures as the civic authorities adopt, and they must keep a very stiff back as to the absolute inconsistence of sexual irregularity &amp; the Christian profession. Personally I think the less said &amp; written about the subject the better. Whatever is done should, as far as possible, be done in <hi rend="underline">a decent obscurity</hi>.</p>
         <p>If Freddie is with you, give him my love, &amp; tell him I feel rather badly about not seeing him.</p>
         <p>With kind regards to M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs </hi>Macdonald,</p>
         <p>I am,</p>
         <p>ever yours.</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         </body></text></TEI>