<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, March 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing letters, and in preparing a short memorandum about my scheme for reconstituting the college in Durham. This will be circulated to the Dean &amp; Canons before Saturday, when I have a conference with them.</p>
         <p>Atkinson, the Vicar of Silksworth, lunched here. He is not an impressive man, but he seemed to show cause why I should ignore the complaints of his churchwarden, Binding. He gave a grievous account of the mischiefs which arise from the worthless character of some of the scout&#8211;masters. This is the weakest point of the Boy Scout movement.</p>
         <p>Today the Park was closed to the Public in order to vindicate the Bishop's proprietary rights.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Hartlepool, &amp; there, in Trinity Church. I confirmed about 150 candidates of whom rather more than half were males. This is satisfactory but unusual.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Another ruinous strike has broken out. The engineers have refused the terms offered them</hi>. Only 50,000 out of 400,000 members of the Union voted for rejection: but they suffice to inflict this disaster on the country. It is difficult to see how any compromise can be arranged, for the point of issue is really vital – the power of the employers to manage their own works.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>