<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[205]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The question of limiting the tenure of benefices to a single year was raised, and I asked the Archbishop whether he had considered the effect of the change on the recruitment for the clergy. His Grace replied that he thought it would not deter the kind of men which we desired to bring into Holy Orders. I rejoined that I held the opposite view viz: that it was precisely that type which probably would be deterred from seeking Ordination. The incident disclosed the distance which the Archbishop has travelled on the road to "Life and Liberty", and the chasm which now separates him and me. From what that foolish old canon said to me at Windsor it is plain that our discord is becoming evident to the onlooking, gossiping world. So long as the old system continued we used the same, or similar, language, and I was useful to his Grace in many ways, but since the Enabling Act, &amp; the establishment of "Autonomy", our feet have been set on different and diverging roads. It is clear enough to me that the "Church Times" said no more than the truth, albeit spoken in spite, when it declared that the Enabling Act "marked the end of the Bishop of Durham's influence". That is precisely my own opinion. It has practically closed to me the scene in which, if I am any judge of my own powers, I could have made the greatest impression, for there is no sphere for episcopal influence in the House of Lords since almost all the subjects, with respect to which such influence might most fitly be exerted, have been relegated to the so–called 'National Assembly'.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I breakfasted pleasantly with Lord S.<persName xml:id="3465"></persName>, and then walked to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, where some letters awaited me. Among them were two from the Boys, one from George Nimmins<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, who so far has caused me less anxiety than any other, and one from Harold Knowling<persName xml:id="113"></persName> who has caused me more! I sent the latter a cheque for £20 with a kind letter. The desperate straits of young men are grievous to look at. Then I went to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, &amp; spent the day in the Committee on Church Property. The Bishop of Truro gave evidence before lunch: the Deans of Peterboro and York after. The Bishop of Bristol and I lunched at the H. of Lords.</p>
         <p>Archbishop D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> was in the Club. He talked of the situation in Ireland. The gunmen in Belfast are the revolutionary &amp; criminal elements of both parties. They have now been got under control. Republicanism prevails in the South and West. Some prophets foretell a tripartite system in Ireland – loyalist in Ulster, Free State in the East &amp; Centre; Republican in South &amp; West. In some southern districts the Protestant population had been either massacred or driven out of the country. I mentioned the horrible atrocity, which was discussed in Parliament a few days ago, and expressed my surprise that outrages on women should occur among a people so renowned for chastity as the Irish. <hi rend="italic">The Archbishop assured me that the raping of Protestant girls was no uncommon occurrence in Roman Catholic Ireland, and that the reputed chastity of the Irish was mythical</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName>, who also hails from Northern Ireland, confirmed this statement, &amp; added divers authenticating facts. Is this witness to be discounted as Protestant prejudice? Both D'Arcy and Charles are distinguished men. Cody, the Canadian divine, who is now visiting England, told Charles that he bought flowers of an Irish woman in the street the other day: and the dame (who was half–seas over, &amp; mistook him for a Popish priest) said "Are you one of us, Father? Wasn't that business with Wilson well done. We are just beginning. There are many more on the list. We're going to have the King, &amp; many others". Does this babble signify anything at all?</hi></p>
         <p>I dined with the Club<orgName xml:id="328"></orgName>. Here were six of us viz. Lord Dunedin, Lord Stamfordham<persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, Sir George Murray, Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName>, George Trevelyan, and myself. We talked casuistry and politics, &amp; the casuistry of politics. The conversation was animated &amp; occasionally brilliant, never dull or vulgar. Would it have been possible if women had been present? The authorship of "Pomp and Power" was discussed. Everybody agreed that it could not be credited to Lord Esher. L<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Stamfordham said that he had found Anthony Macdonell, a veteran Home ruler, in the deepest despondency over the state of Ireland. I had to borrow from Hugh Cecil in order to pay my reckoning, having come away without any money. I got back to Park Lane about 10.30 p.m. "<hi rend="underline">Vanitas vanitatum omnia vanitas</hi>" – these things have come to me too late for enjoyment!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>