<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Palm Sunday, April 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m.; William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; Frank communicated, &amp; it pleased me to see them, save that the coldness of the chapel and the vehemence of William's cough made me wonder whether he ought to have been there. The weather continues very cold: a smart snow–show was proceeding during breakfast. The day was however, bright as well as cold: &amp; sunshine makes amends for much.</p>
         <p>At 3 p.m. I began the Confirmation service at South Church, &amp; confirmed 180 candidates, <hi rend="bold underline">among whom was John. His mother was in the congregation</hi>. Lucie Söderblom was also there, &amp; evidently surprised at the slightness of the service. In Sweden Confirmation which is administers by the presbyters is more of a serious examination in faith &amp; morals. She thought it "more solemn" than in England. This ends the confirmations for the present – I have laid hands on 3691 persons.</p>
         <p>Lady Lawrence and John went with me to Coundon, where I preached to a considerable congregation, of which an unusually large proportion were men. The choir contained 14 boys &amp; 21 young men, all of the artisan class. I preached from the text: "<hi rend="underline">Far be it from me to glory save in the Cross of our Lord Jesus Christ".</hi> Both William and Frank Berry were in the congregation. On returning to the Castle I completed my arrangements for a night journey to London!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>