<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[67]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A most glorious spring morning. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> started for Birmingham about 8.45 a.m. We exchanged farewells from my bedroom window.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Wylands is a pleasant house, pleasantly placed on the bank of the Wye.</hi> After breakfast I established myself in the smoking room, &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> , Lady Oman, the Dean of York and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Haslewood. Then I joined M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Clayton &amp; Bryan for lunch, and a stroll in the garden. <hi rend="bold underline">We drove to Ross, where I took the train to Gloucester. Gee met me at the station. Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> was on the platform</hi>, about to proceed to London.</p>
         <p>At 6 p.m. the Ordination Candidate, Hill, came to see me at the Deanery. I questioned him about Jewel's "Apology", which was the Anglican standard he had selected, &amp; had some talk with him. He impressed me very well.</p>
         <p>There was a pleasant party at dinner. I had beside me a sister of Huxley, whom I found very interesting. There was a local baronet, a soldier, who had command during the war in Egypt and Gallipoli, who spoke very nicely about the chaplains. Their horsemanship appears to have been their weakest point. An old lady, M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Cutter, said that she was a relation of the Thurlows<persName xml:id="5272"></persName>, &amp; apparently connected with half the aristocracy! Gee &amp; I had some intimate conversation before we finally decided to go to bed!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>