<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A bright morning, and a white frost. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went into Durham, and I licensed 3 clergymen in the Chapel at the Castle. Then we lunched at the Club with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> very pleasantly. The new sheriff, Sir John Barwick, was there. Also Capt. Apperley<persName xml:id="2918"></persName>, and Woods of Coxhoe. I went next to the Cosin Library, &amp; presided over a meeting of the finance Board, which went on until 4 p.m., when Clayton rejoined me, &amp; we motored to Gateshead, where, after tea at the Rectory, I had interviews with various clergy until it was time to go to S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>Chad's for the Confirmation. There were 234 candidates. I confirmed them in fours, for the first time. It doesn't please me, but it saves time. Squance &amp; Stephenson discussed the Socialist School, which has been started in Gateshead. It has no more than 53 children, &amp; appears to be relatively harmless. But the hymn&#8211;book is very revolutionary. I told Squance to find out all he can, and let me know. Gipsy Pat Smith, who has been holding a mission in Gateshead, came to see me. He is 28 years old, &amp; has been an evangelist for 11 years. He served in the War, being promoted from private to Captain, &amp; he evangelized all the time. He is a plump, well&#8211;brushed young man, with rather a professional manner. His account of his conversion in Glasgow was interesting, but had been told so often as to lose spontaneity. He said that he had most success with college students both in England and in America, and least with the poorest people. He had had little education of any kind.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>