<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> and George Trevelyan had a 'set to' last night at the Club, which was not uninteresting since it disclosed their respective characters rather vividly. The former is the more brilliant; the latter the more reasonable. Cecil has the temper of a medieval schoolman; Trevelyan that of a modern historian. The ruthless temper of the fanatick gleams through the subtleties of the one; the balancing habit of the student clashes the dogmatics of the other. Both have the ardour &amp; vehemence of undergraduates.</p>
         <p>I attended the Church Property Committee or, as we now call it, <hi rend="underline">Commission</hi>. We spent much time in discussing the relation of the Commission to the National Assembly. After lunching at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, I returned to Auckland by the 5.30 p.m. express. It only stopped at Doncaster, and arrived at Darlington at 10.5 p.m., doing the whole distance in 4 hours 35 minutes. The weather in London was brilliant, but as we travelled northwards, the sky was overcast with clouds, and when I reached Durham, the rain was falling.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The morning papers announce the death of George Prothero</hi><persName xml:id="319"></persName>. He was a good friend of mine, though my knowledge of him was comparatively slight. I judge him to have been a man of firmer character &amp; more solid achievements than his brother, Lord Ernle. He did much useful work during the War, and probably put a strain on himself, the full extent of which he hardly realized at the time.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>