<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, March 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>In response to Prothero's appeal I sent five guineas to the Royal Literary Fund, and promised to 'support' him at the dinner on May 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. Lord Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3465"></persName> sent a telegram saying that the passage of the Treaty Bill was assured, &amp; that I need not come up for the debate. </p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> &amp; I motored to Durham, &amp; there, in S. Nicholas' Church, I confirmed 197 persons. Bothamley was much in evidence – a preposterous creature in aspect and manner. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> was there to witness the confirmation of his paper boy, Albert, &amp; Watkins to do as much for some female student, whom he had prepared. I had tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>; &amp; then we went to Brandon where I confirmed 115 persons. The service was well arranged. We got back to the Castle in time for dinner. </p>
         <p>It would be difficult to imagine a greater contrast between churches than that presented by S. Nicholas Durham, and Brandon. The one is aggressively &amp; repulsively Protestant: the other is impudently "Catholick". Bothamley and Hayward are not unsuitable as exponents of the contrasted systems. The first is ludicrous: the last is vulgar. Physically, they are strongly contrasted, &amp; laughably so: for while the Protestant hero is a grim ascetic giant: the Catholick champion is almost a dwarf with the smartness of the English street boy!! </p>
         </body></text></TEI>