<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[88]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Adamson<persName xml:id="4101"></persName>, the late Rector of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring, is reported to be dead. This releases his pension, &amp; thereby increases Knight's<persName xml:id="62"></persName> income by &#x00A3;450 per annum. How vain are human plans &amp; hopes! The old man had counted on some years of quiet living.</p>
         <p>I received a melancholy budget from Fenton about X. against whose restoration to the ranks of the working clergy he is relentlessly opposed. I wrote to the Abp. of C. making inquiry, and also to Watson of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Margaret's. </p>
         <p><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Lawrence Holt</hi><hi rend="italic"> sent for my reading a report from the London agent of the Firm on </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">George Nimmins</hi><persName xml:id="3571"></persName><hi rend="italic">. It was as good as possible, and pleased me greatly.</hi></p>
         <p>I ^was^ preparing in a tearing hurry a sermon for tomorrow, and a speech for tonight. Frank Berry motored me to Newcastle in his two&#8211;seater. We took just an hour and a quarter over the journey. The Brunswick Square Methodist Chapel is a large building. It was completely filled for the Missionary Meeting. I spoke for 25 minutes, &amp; was followed by a missionary from Nigeria who held on for 50. He said a good many interesting things, on which I would have liked to question him. Frank motored me back to the Castle in Durham, where I had arranged to stay the night.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>