<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p> A dull morning and with threatenings of rain, which developed into actuality of a vigourous down–pour in Oxford. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Darlington where I caught the 9 a.m. express. A "through carriage" was on the train, &amp; I had no companion all the way to my comfort. I arrived about 2.45 p.m., and drove at once to Exeter College, where I was to stay with the Vice-Chancellor<persName xml:id="3297"></persName>. Leaving my bags at the Lodge I went to Ripon Hall, where I interviewed an Ordination candidate named Woods, who desires to be ordained in September. He chose for his Anglican divine Jeremy Taylor's "<hi rend="underline">Liberty of Prophesying</hi>". I had some conversation with Major<persName xml:id="3660"></persName>, and with Brillioth<persName xml:id="5198"></persName>, who is staying at Ripon Hall. Then I went to Exeter College, where <hi rend="doubleunderline">Farnell</hi> received me with much kindness. After tea he walked with me in Worcester &amp; S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> John's gardens, both more beautiful than I remember.</p>
         <p>I dined pleasantly with the Omans<persName xml:id="2141"><persName xml:id="2142"></persName></persName>. Carola &amp; her husband were there, and two of the probationer fellows from All Souls. My godson, Charlie<persName xml:id="1679"></persName>, was also there, an odd silent youth with an amiable but abstracted aspect, reputed to be interested in antiquarianism &amp; history. After returning to mine host I had some talk with him before M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Farnell returned from the play (Molière) in New College Gardens: &amp; we all betook ourselves to bed.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>