<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[72]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, April 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Carlisle went off by an early train, but Wakefield and I joined the Bishop at the Celebration in his chapel. After breakfast he walked us round his domain. I asked him whether he desired to get rid of the Palace, &amp; he replied in the negative. We, i.e Wakefield &amp; I motored to Harrogate, where we caught the London express, &amp; travelled together as far as Wakefield. On arriving at King's Cross, I proceeded to 22 Marsham Street, &amp; deposited my bags. Then I went to the Athenaem<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; wrote to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. <hi rend="italic">I dined at the Café Royal, Regent Street, with the Club<orgName xml:id="328"></orgName></hi>. Only Fisher &amp; Kenyon came, &amp; we three dined pleasantly together. Our conversation ranged over a great variety of subjects. <hi rend="bold underline">Fisher &amp; I walked together as far as <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName> through a deluge of rain. He expressed great admiration of Lloyd George, whose prestige in Europe was, he said, unprecedented. There had been nothing like it since Napoleon</hi>. He thought a general election would hardy take place before the autumn: &amp; that the effect would probably [be] to give Lloyd George a small but sufficient majority. The Coalition Liberals would lose many seats, &amp; might not number more than fifty members in the new Parliament, but they would hold the balance of power.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>