<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Easter, April 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The collect, epistle, and Gospel for this Sunday are all admirably fitted to the occasion of a Vicar's Institution. The collect brings together the two aspects of the Gospel which the Christian minister is to proclaim – the message of redemption and the higher moral demand. Christ has been given "to be unto us both a sacrifice for sin, and also an example of godly life". It goes on to pray that me honestly receive both. In the Epistle S. Peter points out what that Law of our Master's Example will involve: and in the Gospel our Master pictured Himself as 'the good Shepherd' who 'giveth his life for the sheep'. This self&#8211;sacrificing Pastorate must be recognizably exhibited by those who are ordained to be "Bishops and Pastors of Christ's Flock", in confessed and distinctive sense. His representatives on earth. And the grand objective of His Pastorate – the gathering into one of all God's people – cannot but be also the end of their Ministry. This consideration must check the narrowing ardours of a merely denominational loyalty, and infuse a genuinely Catholick spirit into the clergyman's work. He cannot acquiesce in the alienation of any genuine disciple from the common life of Christ's Flock. "And other sheep I have which are not of this fold: them also I must bring &amp; they shall be my sheep, and they shall become one Flock, one Shepherd". That is the only possible objective for the Christian minister.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[79]</hi></p>
         <p>A brilliant morning, with a mild temperature. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> arrived before breakfast. At 10.30 a.m. I collated <hi rend="doubleunderline">Parry Evans</hi> to the vicarage of Bishop Auckland. There was a considerable congregation which was, I think, really interested and impressed by the ceremony. I celebrated the Holy Communion, and administered the Sacrament to more than 200 persons: The service lasted so long that I had scarcely time for a hasty lunch before I had to start for Gateshead in Frank Berry's two&#8211;seater. The weather had now degenerated, &amp; we travelled much of the way under rain. We wet directly to the parish church, where I addressed a congregation of perhaps 250 men on "Citizenship". Then we had tea at the Rectory, &amp; rested for an hour. We next motored to S. Mark's, Millfield, where the 'Jubilee' of the church was being observed. There was a considerable congregation. I read the lessons &amp; preached the sermon. Immediately the service was over, we returned to Bishop Auckland, making very good time, for we went the distance of 35 miles in just an hour and a quarter. Frank Berry drives with skill and determination. At one point I noticed that a pace of 42 miles an hour was being registered. His help got me through my arrangements for this day. But the absence of the car is a disastrous circumstance, and I miss William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> in a hundred ways. The waste of time involved in using the railway, ever when, which is not often, its use is available for my purpose, is intolerable. </p>
         </body></text></TEI>