<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>Rain fell heavily until about 3 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored me to Northallerton, where I preached to a considerable congregation of Freemasons in the fine parish church. The atmosphere was almost stifling and in consequence I preached with discomfort and was heard with inattention. Why are the clergy so indifferent to the ventilation of the churches? Bad air <hi rend="bold">[198]</hi> is probably more disastrous then bad theology, the last may be unavoidable, but why give both? After service I lunched at the Vicarage. The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> F. M. Thompson was ordained as long ago as 1872. He cannot be less than 73 years old. He was for 14 years Vicar of Tudhoe, and professes a great affection for the diocese of Durham.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Spencer Wade<persName xml:id="5332"></persName></hi>, a curate in Sunderland, writes to thank me for my speech in the National Assembly: he proceeds thus:–</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Despite the lugubrious outpourings of the 'Church Times' the younger clergy of your diocese are experiencing a deepening confidence in their Bishop, and are learning to value an attitude in ecclesiastical affairs which they have too frequently been advised to scout as Erastianism".</p>
         </div>
         <p>Possibly this is a straw indicating a current. But nothing will avail anything at all so long as the problem of recruiting for the Ministry remains unsolved.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>