<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[126]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, May 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham to attend the commemoration service in the Cathedral organized by Bede College. It began by my placing a wreath on Bede's tomb in the Gallilee [sic]. Then the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> read prayers, and a motet was sung by the students. A procession was then formed into the Church, and shortened Mattins followed. At the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> collect the students, who all wore surplices, left the choir &amp; seated themselves in the nave. I went into the pulpit, and preached from the text, "<hi rend="underline">It is more blessed to give than to receive</hi>".</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I think the congregation, which included a large number of former students, was rather disconcerted by a discourse, which was so evidently condemnatory of the N.U.T.</hi></p>
         <p>After service I walked to the Drill Hall in Gilesgate, &amp; presided at the luncheon. I proposed "the College" in an extemporaneous speech, which added yet more to the offence already given by the sermon! We all adjourned to the College, where I dedicated a Memorial Cross in honour of the students (83) who died in the War. This was a very well&#8211;arranged and effective function.</p>
         <p>From Bede College I passed to the Cathedral, where a memorial service had been arranged in connection with Colonel Lowe's funeral. There was a large attendance of students &amp; dons. After tea with the Bishop<persName xml:id="2785"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Quirk, I returned to Auckland, where I spent an hour in the garden. The trees are extraordinarily beautiful, &amp; the well&#8211;mown lawns are creditable to Laws.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>