<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[237]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The "2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> year of our Translation" ends today. It has, perhaps on the whole illustrated the common saying that "in his 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> year the Bishop can do nothing right". He has outlived the hopes and expectations which his coming evoked, dashing the first and disappointing the last, &amp; he is now regarded with the cold eyes of the disillusioned! In my case the normal reasons for a bishop's unpopularity are reinforced by my total inability either to accord with the prevailing tendencies or to approve the newly established system. "Anglo–Catholicism" and "Life and Liberty" are equally repugnant to me, &amp; therefore equally disgusted with me.</p>
         <p>A dreary day with rain falling and the gloomiest sky. I made away with the morning in writing letters, &amp; making a few notes for the Cleott speech. After lunch I walked in the rain for an hour with Brillioth<persName xml:id="5198"></persName>.</p>
         <p>Newman writing to Rogers in 1840 says " M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Palmer of Magdalen seems to have difficulty to convince the Russians that we are much of a church; their definition of us was a Church which had cast off its patriarch, was somehow Calvinistic, and had no discipline". And again in 1841. "Palmer of Magdalen is returning [^Greek word^]. The Russians will not believe him against the evidence of all the English they ever saw before. They think him a theorist or worse." Have they changed their mind about us?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[238]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>July 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Rural Dean,</p>
         <p>I do not propose to interfere with the discretion of the Ruridecanal Conference in the matter off the University Students Missionary Campaign. Personally I think University Students serve God best by sticking to their proper studies: but these are strange topsy–turvy days, and of course we must remember that "<hi rend="underline">Out of the mouth of babes &amp; sucklings Thou has perfected praise"</hi>. Still I prefer your method of 'steady pastoral visitation and continuous attention to Bible classes &amp; Confirmation candidates'. </p>
         <p>I note and approve your decision about the Anglo catholic movement.</p>
         <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev J. Hudson Barker.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The car was towed ignominiously back to the garage by a lorry which William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> had telegraphed for after prolonged but unavailing efforts to discover the reason why the car refused to travel. He came to report himself about 6 p.m., &amp; found me beginning to develop that kind of annoyance &amp; anxiety which is called <hi rend="underline">fussing</hi>. This untoward episode will not make for economy! </p>
            </body></text></TEI>