<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[91]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, May 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>The weather has suddenly become much warmer: this circumstance cooperated with the fatigues of a rather too strenuous Sunday to give me a sleepless night. I read old D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Whyte's ecstatic eulogies of the Puritan, or rather, Presbyterian, fanatick Samuel Rutherford. His superlatives are freely poured out on the long forgotten (by the generality of educated men) rhapsodies of the persecuted and persecuting bigots, who are the calendared saints of the Kirk of Scotland.</p>
         <p>I called on Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, &amp; found him discussing with Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> the evidence that they should give before Lord Cave's Committee. The Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, Cruickshank (Treasurer), and Bayley are to appear before the Committee. It seems that the Dean in filling up a series of questions for the Committee last year emphasized the importance of giving academic functions to the Dean and Canons! He has evidently forgotten that he did so.</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> brought the letters, &amp; the reports on the Ordination candidates. There will be but two deacons and two priests for the Trinity Ordination. In the old days it was not unusual for more than 20 men to be ordained at Trinity, &amp; then the diocesan population was considerably smaller. As yet there is no clear sign that the tide has turned: &amp;, of course, the practical situation worsens daily.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[92]</hi></p>
         <p>I lunched with Cruickshank &amp; his wife<persName xml:id="2663"></persName>. They have just returned from Holland, where they had gone for a brief holiday. They report that much happened in that country during the War which was not known in England, e.g. a considerable rising of the Socialists, which was suppressed by the Roman Catholicks. The Queen, exhibiting the hereditary courage of her race, visited the most disaffected districts, and shewed herself freely in the streets. She was received with great enthusiasm. Protestantism seems to be moribund: while the Roman Catholic Church advances rapidly.</p>
         <p>I took part in the funeral of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lillingston<persName xml:id="3263"></persName>. The first part of the service was taken in the Cathedral: the second, in the Cemetery, to which we walked in procession. I read the prayer of committal, and pronounced the Benediction. Then I had tea in the Castle, &amp; started in Frank Berry's two&#8211;seater for Blaydon. There I confirmed 204 persons, adopting for the first time the arrangement recommended by the Bishop of Newcastle, viz. having always 4 candidates kneeling before me, but confirming two at a time, thus avoiding the delay caused by the slowness of the candidates in coming forward. We returned immediately after the service had concluded, and arrived at Durham Castle about 9.45 p.m. I found the proof of my Memorandum for Lord Cave's Committee awaiting me.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>