<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing an <hi rend="underline">address on the Age of Confirmation candidates for the Diocesan Conference.</hi> After lunch Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Stanhope where I confirmed 42 candidates. After the service we had tea in the Rectory, and walked in the garden. The Rector Shebbeare<persName xml:id="5363"></persName>, is an interesting man of some distinction as a philosopher. He is at present engaged on an exposition of Hegel's philosophy. We had some discussion of the situation created by the Cambridge Conference, &amp; he expressed himself very reasonably. He holds Major<persName xml:id="3660"></persName> to be a sincere man, but also fundamentally an ass!</p>
         <p>The sun–dial on the southern wall of Stanhope Church bears the date 1727, and the inscription <hi rend="underline">"Ut hora sic Vita".</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Butler</hi> became Rector in 1725 and held the benefice until 1740 when he was appointed Dean of St Paul's, and resigned his other preferments held <hi rend="underline">in commendam</hi> with the Bishoprick of Bristol. It is interesting that, when Bishop of Durham, Butler suggested a plan for establishing bishops in the American colonies.</p>
         <p>After dinner Clayton &amp; I walked in the garden &amp; park for an hour. We picked up a 'hewer', and took him round the garden to show him the trees. He said he was 23 years old, and had worked in the pit since he was 14. He worked 4 shifts a week, &amp; earned about £2:10:0. This hardly corresponds with the popular notion about miner's exorbitant wages.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>