<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[93]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, May 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A most beautiful morning, almost summer–like in its mildness, though the bare branches of the trees disclosed too clearly the nearness of winter for the least considering to be deluded.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I read for an hour before getting some more of </hi><hi rend="i doubleunderline">Whyte's</hi><hi rend="italic"> "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Appreciations</hi><hi rend="italic">". His fondness for superlatives, &amp; his ridiculous exaggerations of thought &amp; style, become very tiresome. The individuals whom he does not scruple to make equal to Augustine, Pascal, and Dante are for the most part totally unknown even by name to everybody who is not a Scot, a Presbyterian, and a zealot! How many of his congregation, to whom these appreciations were addressed, had read a line of any of them?</hi></p>
         <p>I corrected the proof of my Memorandum on the Cathedral, and took it to Caldcleugh<persName xml:id="3693"></persName>. On the way, Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> overtook me, and I showed to him. He suggested that I should alter one word "exceeds" into "approaches" in the statement that the income of the Foundation now "exceeds £40,000".</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> arrived with the letters. Then I licensed 3 curates in the Castle Chapel. I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, &amp; sent him a cheque for 2 week's [sic] wages. Then we lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName>, after which we motored to Tanfield, where I confirmed 194 candidates: and then went to Birtley where I confirmed 233 candidates. We got back to Auckland about 9.45 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>