<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[181]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A wet day, such as the farmers have longed for. I left Exeter College in time to get to London by the 10 a.m. train.</p>
         <p>I attended the meeting of the National Assembly at 3 p.m. Most of the time was occupied with a succession of belated rantings by Evangelical laymen who were "dying in the last ditch" over the ridiculous issue of a reformed lectionary. The voting was by orders. Twenty&#8211;five bishops voted for the change, and none against. It is the first time that I remember seeing the Bench unanimous. There were but 4 opponents among the clergy, and 52 among the laity. <hi rend="bold underline">The last figure probably gives the full strength of the Evangelical party in the Assembly, as the speeches disclosed its intellectual quality. The first is insignificant: the last squalid</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> That the "Anglo&#8211;Catholicks" should enjoy a "walk&#8211;over" is explicable when their only rivals are seen to be such miserable folk. Most of them were over 60: none of them disclosed the faintest perception of the actualities of the modern world. <hi rend="bold underline">Yet I cannot doubt that they represent the main multitude of English Christians</hi><hi rend="bold">:</hi> If any issue of theological liberty were raised they w<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> vote as one man for the suppression of truth. After having tea in the Club, I went to the S. Paul's Deanery, where I dined with Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went out to dine with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Fox.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>