<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote another sermon for the Mothers' Union<orgName xml:id="220"></orgName>. We motored to Durham, &amp; lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watkins<persName xml:id="2762"></persName>. <hi rend="underline">Iste Archidianconus</hi><persName xml:id="590"></persName> was also there!</p>
         <p>The Cathedral was again thronged with women. Yesterday's collection exceeded £30: today's will be hardly less. That some 6000 women from the Archdeaconry of Durham should come to the Cathedral for the annual service indicates no slight vitality in the Mothers' Union. We had tea with Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName>, &amp; then motored to Thornley, where I addressed a large gathering of Wesleyan Methodists who were holding their "annual rally". The impudent parson Casey, who was ejected from the Cathedral on the occasion when D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Jowett preached there, sent me a very insolently–worded letter protesting against my action: but I contented myself with instructing Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to send a formal acknowledgement with the usual assurance that his letter would receive the Bishop's careful attention. I was interested to observe the considerable number of young miners who were among the audience. We motored back to Auckland by way of Sedgefield, and arrived at the Castle about 9 p.m.</p>
         <p>It is satisfactory to learn that the Court of Appeal has rejected Bottomley's appeal and refused to reduce his sentence. The Judges announce that they will give the reasons for their decision next Friday.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>