<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[52]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>A milder day, and misty. After breakfast Laws took me to the garden to plant six silver birches. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came with us, and assisted.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, and lunched with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>. Then I presided at a meeting of the Diocesan Conference Committee, and afterwards we motored to Middleton S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> George, where I dedicated a memorial cross, in the churchyard. There was a considerable crowd, and the service was not without impressiveness, but the weather had become bitterly cold, &amp; I had to speak against a keen east wind. As we passed through West Auckland on our way home, we ran over a dog.</p>
         <p>Lady Lawrence<persName xml:id="1908"></persName> and John arrived about 9 p.m., having failed to change at Darlington. Penelope<persName xml:id="2937"></persName> &amp; her maid had arrived during the afternoon. So the old house is full of young people. <hi rend="bold underline">John Lawrence had expressed a desire to be confirmed by me, and I yielded to the request of his parents</hi> in consenting to confirm him. He is a clever but very delicate lad, whose mind is perhaps too much for his frail little body. How far it is really wise to associate religious experiences with personal preferences is a question not altogether easy to answer: but I like the boy, and he likes me: and there is something to be said for weaving friendship into religion.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>