<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in revising sermons &amp;c in preparation for next Sunday and the Sunday following. Also I paid the wages, &amp; several accounts.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My letter in rejoinder to Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> appears in the "Daily Telegraph". I think this is the first communication over my signature that has ever appeared in that newspaper</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> The degradation of the "<hi rend="underline">Times</hi>" has gone so far that I feel reluctant to appear in its columns: and I think this feeling cannot be limited to myself, for the correspondence columns of that newspaper are not to be compared with those of the past.</p>
         <p>In the afternoon <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> had a tennis party. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shebbeares</hi><persName xml:id="5363"></persName> from Stanhope were among the guests. I had a good deal of talk with <hi rend="doubleunderline">Shebbeare</hi>, who had just returned from a visit to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gore</hi>. He is a liberal churchman, who has been completely taken in by the pretence of tolerance &amp; liberality, which is made by the modern "Anglo&#8211;Catholick". He seems to acquiesce in the notion of a "go&#8211;as&#8211;you&#8211;please" Church, ignoring the fact that the only condition under which such a Church could be justified viz: complete mutual toleration, is refused on principle by the Anglo&#8211;Catholick factions. It claims, not recognition as a permissible type of Churchmanship, but the sole &amp; exclusive title to be recognized as Anglicans. "<hi rend="underline">We are they that ought to speak: who is lord over us?</hi>"</p>
         </body></text></TEI>