<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>April 12<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1922.</p>
         <p>My dear Archbishop</p>
         <p>I share your dissatisfaction with some features of Lomax's<persName xml:id="5279"></persName> statement of "Donor's wishes", but he modified it in deference to my wishes as far as (I think) to make it not incompatible with a satisfactory interpretation, and, in any case, it remains no more than a record of his own desires, <hi rend="underline">most</hi> of which are beyond all question admirable.</p>
         <p>I thought it better to emphasize the direct &amp; practical character of my own position by separating myself from the Presidency, which must in the circumstances be more nominal, &amp; holding office as Ordinary and Visitor. I hope, therefore, that you will consent to be Patron: &amp; I gather that the Bishops of Ripon and Newcastle will consent to be Presidents.</p>
         <p>The idea of such a House of Retreat is excellent: the risks lie in the fact (which faces us at every turn in our administration) that this newly&#8211;organized Anglo&#8211;Catholick movement is not only ardent, ubiquitous, &amp; aggressive but also undercuts the established system at almost every point, so that words no longer carry their natural meanings, pledges have no more validity, and loyalty has altered its direction. This mischief is profound, but it is also inherent in the whole system.</p>
         <p>Yours aff<hi rend="superscript underline">tly</hi></p>
         <p>Herbert Dunhelm</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, April 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward Inge</hi> fainted in chapel. We are in so nervous a condition as to the health of our guests that we could not but be alarmed. However, he seemed little the worse when once he had recovered himself. The correspondence occupied the whole morning until lunch time. Then I took Lady Lawrence, Ruth<persName xml:id="2161"></persName>, and John into Durham, and showed them the Cathedral, the Deanery, Kitchen and the Castle. The astonishing majesty of this series of buildings impressed me more than ever<hi rend="bold underline">. I presented John with a copy of Donne's Poems as a memento of his confirmation. It is rather beyond his present years, but he will grow to appreciate it.</hi></p>
         </body></text></TEI>