<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, April 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me to Darlington: and Frank Berry asked to be allowed to sit with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. We motored to the station in a snow&#8211;storm. I beguiled the way by reading the Loeb translation of the Odyssey. It seems quite well done.</p>
         <p>On arriving at King's Cross, I drove to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, &amp; left my bags. I walked to Westminster, and called fruitlessly – for they were both out – on Vernon Storr<persName xml:id="1899"></persName> and Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName>. Then I went into the Abbey church, and looked at the tomb of Edmund Crouchback, &amp; the two coeval tombs in the sanctuary. They have been cleansed, and "freshened up" rather startlingly. I walked back to the Club, and had tea. Fearon was there, and talked pleasantly enough. Then I drove to Paddington, and <hi rend="bold underline">travelled to Windsor by the 5.40 p.m. train,</hi> which went through without changing, and arrived at 6.18 p.m. A Royal Carriage was awaiting me, &amp; so I came to the Castle, where the Master of the Household received me, and showed me my room. It is the same as that which I occupied in 1920 – 352 Edward 3rd's Tower. He also gave me news of the Boat Race – Cambridge won by 3 1/2 lengths, a result which appears to have been generally expected.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[41]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>I was carefully shepherded to the drawing room, where we awaited their Majesties, and I sate at the Queen's right hand during dinner. We talked amicably about many subjects, but there was little that was remarkable in our conversation. The Queen spoke of the annoying insistence of the photographers, &amp; said that she had been compelled to decline being photographed <hi rend="underline">at tea</hi>! After dinner the King talked to me with great energy. <hi rend="bold underline">He got on to the subject of drink, and told me again the story of being 'let in' to total abstinence by L.G. during the War. He said (which was new to me) that he had drunk his wonted moderate amount of alcohol under doctor's orders, but had perforce done so privately, &amp; had been unable to do so openly. He could give no drink to his guests. He talked much of Russia, &amp; asked me whether I thought we ought to recognize the Soviet Gov</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> in order to bring Russia again into touch with Europe. I replied rather evasively that the advocates of the opposite policy were were also the "Die&#8211;hards" in Irish matters, and in my judgment were very unwise counsellors. We got on to unemployment, &amp; the King spoke with natural resentment of the ill&#8211;behaviour of the unemployed men, ex&#8211;service men, whom he had ordered to be taken on as beaters when he shot the covers in Windsor Park. He gave the men</hi> <hi rend="bold">[42] </hi><hi rend="i bold">[symbol]</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">6/&#8211; a day, &amp; a good lunch: but they were none the less insolent and discontented, not even touching their caps to him. Colonel Willoughby,thte deputy&#8211;ranger, had advised that they sh</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> not be employed again. The King said that Hanson, of whom he spoke with much respect, had been completely hoodwinked by the Bolsheviks, who had persuaded him that Denikin &amp; Koltchak were responsible for the total break&#8211;down of agricultural life on the Volga, whereas they had never got within 250 miles of the famine districts. 'Nothing,' said H.M., 'will ever induce me to shake hands with any of these murderers, if they are permitted to send representatives to thi country.'</hi></p>
         <p>The Countess Fortescue, Lady in Waiting, sate beside me, but the Queen held me so closely in conversation that I had little opportunity of talk.</p>
         <p>I inquired of both their Majesties whether thy had received satisfactory news of the Prince's health in India, &amp; neither of them gave me a very satisfactory answer. The Prince, I was told, cannot take rest. When his official programme is over, he resorts to violent exercise. He is greatly given to dancing which, he says, is preferable to conversation with persons who do not interest him &amp; on subjects in which he is not interested!</p>
         </body></text></TEI>