<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[204]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>I left Eton after breakfast. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> remained in order to lunch with some friends. On arriving in London, I left my luggage in Park Lane, and Ella's in Eccleston Square. Then I visited the barber, called at Whippell's, &amp; ordered shirts, finally went into the City, &amp; got a cheque changed not without difficulty. After lunching in the Club, I walked to Westminster, &amp; attended a meeting of the Patronage Committee. <hi rend="bold underline">The Archbishop of Canterbury gave evidence, looking the while at every corner of the ceiling</hi>! We discussed Dibdin's<persName xml:id="909"></persName> draft of a Bill for prohibiting the sale of livings. I opposed the creation of Diocesan patronage boards, &amp; though nobody admitted agreement with my opinions, it was finally decided to omit the clause which created the boards. I walked to Park Lane, &amp; dined with mine host &amp; hostess. A certain M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Scovell also dined. He is one of Lloyd George's Secretariat, &amp; is most concerned with organising his interest in the constituencies. He appeared an interesting &amp; well&#8211;informed man. We discussed many things until 11 p.m., when he took his leave, and I retired to my room.</p>
         <p>I saw Archbishop D'Arcy<persName xml:id="1361"></persName> in the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. He said that Ireland outside of Ulster was the prey of bands of banditti who pillaged the country at will. The retirement of the British forces had been followed by anarchy.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>