<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Easter Tuesday, April 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I spent this morning in copying out my drafts of an episcopal statement on doctrine, writing letter and reading an American book, sent to me by the author, and strongly recommended by Rashdall<persName xml:id="117"></persName>, "The Creative Christ", a study of the Incarnation in terms of Modern Thought by Edward S Drown D.D.</p>
         <p>All the guests under <persName xml:id="112">Ella's</persName> control went off in the motor to High Force, and I, after a walk in the Park, sate down to a futile attempt to write something about the Position of Women in the Church. But I abandoned it in disgust after wasting an hour. <hi rend="bold underline">I am too hostile in feeling to the whole feminist craze to be able to write with adequate prudence.</hi></p>
         <p>Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> arrived from Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. He reports a very successful Eastertide. There do seem to be signs that the parish is waking up to the fact that it has at last obtained a genuine pastor. I must needs think that the effect of his ministry will be wholesome on the rest of the Deanery. <hi rend="bold underline">I showed him the drafts of the doctrinal statements and he expressed relief and approval at their tone.</hi> He thinks I might wisely accept Temple's<persName xml:id="1173"></persName> phrase "true Deity" in lieu of my "plenary Divineness". The latter might be misunderstood in a Unitarian sense. I doubt very much whether we shall be able to find a "form of sound words" which Chavasse, Burrows, Strong, Wild and I will be able to subscribe. The differences with emerge in discussion.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>