<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[182]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A fine warm day, with wind and much dust. I walked to Westminster, and attended the meeting of the National Assembly. Most of the day was spent over the Budget, with respect to which there is evidently much misgiving &amp; discontent. <hi rend="bold underline">I moved an amendment cutting out the money required for the Official Press Bureau, and there was a brisk discussion which ended in my defeat. Nevertheless, I think some good was done</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi> Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> and I lunched at the H. of L., and then returned to the Assembly, where the Bishop of Gloucester introduced the Report on the Revision of the Prayer&#8211;book. I left early in order to keep faith with Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, who had a "reception" at the Deanery. Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> returned from Liverpool, and we had much talk. <hi rend="bold underline">He says that Curzon<persName xml:id="1018"></persName> did offer him the Principalship of Hertford, but he declined</hi> it. I dined in the Club. There were but 4 of us – Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName>, Kenyon, George Trevelyan and myself – but we had a pleasant evening. Haldane's bland optimism is a little exasperating. Trevelyan told me that he was now engaged on a history of Venice and Manin. He says that much of his material is in the British Museum, where it was collected by the librarian, who, at the time, happened to be an Italian refugee.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>