<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[156]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>More sheafs of questions from the income tax people! The one thing that I want, and cannot get, is their demand, that I may satisfy it!</p>
         <p>Laws reports that both the pigs have been found dead in their sties. This is both humiliating and costly.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored into Durham, &amp; there I preached from the throne to a considerable congregation of women, past &amp; present students of S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Hilda's Training College. My text was S. Mk. X. 44. "Whosoever w<hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi> be first among you shall be servant of all", and I took up my parable against the base mechanical spirit which now holds the minds of the elementary school teachers. The Precentor celebrated, and there were nearly 300 communicants. It was a moving &amp; significant spectacle that I looked down upon from my Throne. After lunching with Clayton in the Castle, <hi rend="bold underline">I attended a meeting of the Diocesan Conference: My Presidential address dealt solely with the question of the right age for Confirmation. I don't think the Conference liked what I said, but they listened very closely, and the effect must needs be educative</hi>. Then Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> introduced the Resolutions on the new method of financing the Diocesan Fund. He spoke badly, &amp; <hi rend="underline">all</hi> the speakers were hostile. I made a virtue of necessity, &amp; advised him to withdraw his Resolutions. This was done, &amp; the Conference dispersed having "sat on" the Bishop triumphantly!!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[157]</hi></p>
         <p>I was certainly surprised at the general hostility of the Conference, and think there must have been some active canvassing against the proposals. I think Gouldsmith is not very popular: and that any suggestion to alter the existing method is resented as almost a personal affront by those who have acquired a measure of personal importance by working it. Still the complete absence of support for resolutions which were readily adopted by the Board of Finance astonished me. </p>
         <p>I went to the Chapter House, and formally witnessed the taking of the Oath of Allegiance, &amp; the making of the legal declaration of Assent: and I urged the candidates to realize the gravity of what they did.</p>
         <p>Then I dined pleasantly at the Castle in Hall: and after dinner went to the Deanery, and delivered a final "charge" to the Ordination Candidates. When this was over, I motored back to Auckland with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>.</p>
         <p>A tiresome confusion has arisen about the date of my preaching in Westminster Abbey, but the responsibility does not lie with me. I was able to send Charles<persName xml:id="1820"></persName> his own letter in which he accepted my substitution of the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> for the 20<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of June: evidently he omitted to report the change of dates, and in the interval has himself forgotten that he made it!! </p>
         </body></text></TEI>