<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[127]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Sunday after Ascension Day, May 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God the King of glory, who has exalted thine only Son Jesus Christ with great triumph unty [sic] thy kingdom in heaven; We beseech thee, leave us not comfortless; but send to us thine Holy Ghost to comfort us, and exalt us unto the same place whither our Saviour Christ is gone before, who liveth &amp; reigneth with thee &amp; the Holy Ghost, one God, world without end.</p>
         <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <p>This collect is from an unique source, viz the Sar. Antiphon for Vespers on Ascension Day, which was however addressed directly to Christ.</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"O rex gloriae domine virtutum qui triumphator hodie super omnes coelos ascendisti, ne derelinquas nos orphanos: sed mitte promissum patris in nos spiritum veritatis alleluia.</p>
         <p>O King of Glory, Lord of all Grace, who hast this day ascended with great triumph above the heavens, leave us not orphans, but send upon us the promise of the Father, the Spirit of truth. Alleluia."</p>
         </div>
         <p>There are extremely few prayers addressed directly to our Saviour, and yet if such prayers are legitimate, it might well be thought that there could hardly be too many of them. We worship God in Christ, and, perhaps, the separation of Christ from the Father even in devotion has an element of danger. "Ye believe in God, believe also in Me" suggests that we reach our worship of Christ by way of an inference from our worship of God. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[128]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated. After breakfast I motored to Durham, &amp; attended service in the Cathedral. <hi rend="underline">Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName> preached the second of the University Sermons. He preached at great length, and in the course of his sermon said many true things, and said them with characteristic fervour &amp; eloquence.</hi> But the sermon gave me the impression of a tired man repeating himself. It was ill&#8211;arranged and too discursive. <hi rend="underline">There was a considerable congregation, but it was overwhelmingly feminine save for the school boys.</hi> The University was not numerously represented. After service Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I lunched at the Deanery. Gore was excellent good company. I returned to Auckland, &amp; completed my notes for the evening's sermon. Then I motored to Collierley picking up Clayton in Durham. While he preached at South Moor, I preached at Collierley. The little church, which has to serve more than 10,000 people was filled, &amp; the attention was close. Fisher Fergusson, who has just been made Vicar, is a poor little sycophantick man, who is said to have commended himself to the people, &amp; who certainly does not hide his light under a bushel. I told him privately not to be too adulatory, lest he becomes like the Dissenters, living in an orgy of mutual compliment. After service I picked up Clayton &amp; motored to Auckland arriving about 9 p.m.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>