<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1922.</hi></p>
         <p>A chilly wet day. The Bishop and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Wild left after breakfast. I went through Wolseley 'Motors' account with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and sent a cheque for £236.6.0. Then I settled down to a Sermon on the 39 Articles for West<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Abbey! What a subject at that place! I fear it is quite impossible to persuade people to think. The cheap cant of toleration fills all minds, and any infusion of reason into the fashionable shibboleths is impossible! Parry–Evans came to see me with a sheaf of parochial conundrums. The poor man has the worst of luck. He can get no hint of curates, and even his lay-workers are departing! It argues much for his character that he does not "throw up the sponge" &amp; depart. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Southmoor, where I confirmed 150 more candidates. The road from Lanchester was execrable. We returned to the Castle after the service arriving at 9.45 p.m. The evening was fine after a wet &amp; gloomy day. William drew up as usual for the wonderful view of the Cathedral which bursts on the traveller after leaving Neville's Cross. The great church was vested in a luminous purple haze, infinitely mysterious. Mary Radford<persName xml:id="1204"></persName> gives an ill account of the situation in India. The English are discontented, and alarmed. Many of then are abandoning the country, and returning to England to seek in middle life the start of a new career.</p>
         </body></text></TEI>