<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>Common affliction is the parent of mutual acquaintance. The American discussed with me our experiences of the night. He had crossed the Atlantic 12 times, &amp; never known a worse passage. The Captain said this was the first bad weather of the season: &amp; that, sometimes, Lake Wetter was so violent that the steamer was delayed several days. The scenery thro' which we crawled was extremely pleasing – sometimes we moved along a slow &amp; curving stream overhung to the water's edge with woods; at intervals we came out into lakes studded with pine&#8211;clad islands: about 5 p.m. we reached the Baltic, &amp; found ourselves steaming close in shore among innumerable islets. The sunset was glorious. Hanging vapours, tinged with crimson which deepened into purple, hung above the belt of brilliantly&#8211;lighted sky, which marked the departure of the Sun: then, against the brilliance, a long &amp; varied line of pine&#8211;woods, &amp; then, the light&#8211;tipped wavelets rippling to the steamer&#8211;side. It was worth being ill last night in order to witness this splendour. The American exchanged cards with me. His name is Mr. J. F. Anderson Jr. New York City, U.S.A.: &amp; he is the chairman of the Church&#8211;Committee of a huge Congregational Church in Brooklyn.</p>
         <p>In the course of the day I read 'Rhoda Fleming' [Geo. Meredith], and finished it early next morning. A powerful &amp; melancholy book.</p></body></text></TEI>