<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>On Saturday I caught cold in the tram returning from our expedition: &amp; this morning, after a miserable night, I found myself nearly speechless, &amp; generally in a dilapidated condition. In deference to the Reichels<persName xml:id="413"></persName> I went to a doctor, &amp; got some mixture. He was Prof. Wising, 4 Vasagat: &amp; charged 20 kronor for my consultation. I bought a peasant's apron for Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, &amp; a brooch for Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>: also a Tauchnitzch edition of Miss Fowler's last novel for reading in the train. Then I spent the day as best I could, packing, loafing &amp; reading an unclean, little foolish book which had been making a flutter in England – 'The visits of Elizabeth'. It bored me. As the afternoon advanced my head began to ache so badly that I abandoned the purpose of travelling, &amp; resigned myself to bed &amp; a warm bottle. This craven performance lasted until noon the next day: when I got up better but still rather a wreck.</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">On Tuesday Sept</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> 3</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="underline"> 1901</hi> I began my return journey by leaving Stockholm at 8.40 pm and travelling to Malmo, where I got on the steamer and went to Copenhagen, which we reached at 10.35 a.m. on <hi rend="underline">Wednesday Sept. 4</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. After getting my bags to the Railway Station I had the day before me. The time went heavily as the wheels of the Egyptian in the Red Sea, for I was tired by the night's journey.</p>
         <p>However I got through the day by driving round the town, visiting the Thorvaldsen Museum, dining &amp;c, and at 7.25 p.m. started again on my journey. The passage between Korsor and Kiel was fairly comfortable: but the steamer was very much crowded, &amp; my cabin was stifling. From Kiel I went on to Hamburg and arrived about 9 a.m. on <hi rend="underline">Thursday Sept. 5</hi> at the Closterthor Station. Then I killed the time in divers ways until 2.35 p.m. when I started in the Schnell&#8211;zug for the Hook of Holland. The journey was without incident: at the Hook we straightway went on board the steamer &amp; started for Harwich. The sea was smooth: there was no wind: the steamer excellent. I elected to remain on deck when I found that my cabin was in the bowels of the vessel; and I did wisely. The sun rising was beautiful, and we got into Harwich half an hour before we were due. Then train to London, &amp; hansom to Westminster &amp; I am at home at 8.30 a.m. on <hi rend="underline">Friday Sept</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> 6</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. </p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>