<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[25]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>A dull morning tending to rain. The Post brought the Spectator for Reichel<persName xml:id="413"></persName>, &amp; I read it for an hour: <hi rend="underline">then was shaved by the ladies</hi>, and mouched about the city, for two hours. The market on a raft in the harbour is a busy &amp; curious spectacle. Huge baskets full of repulsive, green, crawling cray&#8211;fish were everywhere on show: the fish were more noteworthy than the fruit &amp; vegetables. I made my way to the English Church, &amp; studied the notice&#8211;board, in the hope that there might be an early Celebration tomorrow: but I was disappointed: the unusual &amp; perverse arrangement adopted in this Church allots the early Celebrations to the 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> &amp; 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Sundays of the month. So my last hope of attending service disappears, for I cannot in cold blood subject myself to the frightful experience of last Sunday. So much for the practical worth of ecclesiastical theory!!</p>
         <p>The afternoon we spent very pleasantly in an excursion by means of the steam&#8211;tram to [left blank] </p>
         <p>The route lay through woods through which at intervals burst ravishing glimpses of the blue water. The place itself is delightful: &amp;, as the weather cleared up, we got some wonderful effects of light and shadow. Returning, I fetched letters from the Post. There was one from Kirshbaum containing the dolorous news that M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Walter Hobhouse is dead. She is only 37 years old, &amp; it seem but yesterday that I was sitting on the low stools in her drawing room joking over Irish ways. Peace be to her soul! She was a sweet &amp; kindly woman, who had no mean burden of care, &amp; bore it bravely. It is a crushing blow for poor Hobhouse.</p>
         <p>After dinner we strolled round the quays. The moon, almost at the full, was brilliant, &amp; the long lines of flickering lights reflected on the waters gave a weird aspect to the scene. It was an ideal night for sauntering &amp; the light converse, which goes with it: but I had no mind for talk: the shadow of death was on me, &amp; I could not resist it. Why should such be taken, &amp; the useless left? "The economy of Heav'n is dark". I must write to Hobhouse, but what can I say which will seem anything more than the veriest commonplace of conventional condolence? "<hi rend="underline">Tua voluntas fiat</hi>". It is a warning to me also: a reminder of the prosaic truth, familiar as the daylight &amp; as unregarded, that my tenure of life is uncertain &amp; feeble. "<hi rend="underline">The night cometh when no man can work</hi>" &amp; we are not consulted as to <hi rend="underline">that</hi> advent. "<hi rend="underline">So teach us to number our days that we may apply our hearts unto wisdom</hi>". </p></body></text></TEI>