<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>Woke at 5 a.m. &amp; got up shortly after. We were well into the great lake, which even here, at its narrow end, is a noble sheet of water. The shores are well&#8211;wooded: between the trees at intervals are patches of cultivated land, from which the crops were being gathered. The timber&#8211;built houses, painted red after the pretty Swedish fashion, are scattered about, &amp; at some places a tall chimney, belching smoke masks the site of some factory, commonly a ship&#8211;building yard. We left the lake &amp; entered on a course of locks, designed to lift the boat over another great elevation. During this tedious process we left the ship, &amp; walked on the banks. I read through Ibsen's Peer Gynt – a very powerful work, penetrated with a fine dramatic sense. The weather continues fair, but the journey tends to become monotonous. I wrote to Miss Lathbury, and Tommie<persName xml:id="75"></persName>.</p>
         <p>The last 2 hours of daylight were spent amid the most beautiful scenes. The sun went down in a cloudless sky behind the pine wood, and the afterglow of its departed glory showered a deep orange light on one side of the lake, &amp; reflected itself in roseate on the opposite shores. The number of thickly wooded islands in the lake, &amp; the brilliant moon streaking the wavelets with rippling light, &amp; the innumerable stars from the background of profound azure, across which occasional meteors shot like damned spirits hurled from the battlements of relentless heaven – all united in a spectacle of incomparable beauty. This splendour was the gorgeously&#8211;clad herald of a tragedy. Lake Wetter was in evil temper, &amp; gave us a nasty passage. The vessel, not built for storms, rolled in the most violent way, &amp; there was much distress among the passengers. I was on deck, and <hi rend="underline">at the deck&#8211;side</hi>. The crossing occupied just 2 hours, after which we were again in the canals, and began the long series of docks which brought us down by slow steps from the altitude we had slowly reached.</p></body></text></TEI>