<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[20]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901</hi>.</p>
         <p>The morning disappointed happily the dark promise of the night. It was brilliant. I breakfasted in the caf&#x00E9; adjoining the H&#x00F4;tel, &amp; then went in search of a barber. I found one (not feminine) after a long wandering. The Swedes do not hang out the accustomed symbols to guide the unshorn alien. Then to the post but found no letter. We visited the Royal Library, where the Librarian, to whom Reichel<persName xml:id="413"></persName> had a letter of introduction, showed us much courtesy. <hi rend="bold underline">We saw the 'Devil's Bible', an immense 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> century codex written on the skins of 32 asses, &amp; adorned with a large &amp; lurid figure of Satan. It was brought from Prague in 1648</hi>. At lunch we were struck by the unusual height of two soldiers who, with a shorter comrade, were dining at the next table. The waiter afterwards informed us that the taller of the two was Prince Karl: &amp; that his father, King Oscar, was 'a little longer'. We spent the afternoon in a steamboat excursion to <hi rend="underline">Saltsjobaden</hi> – rather more than an hour on the water. The views are most beautiful. After dinner we went to the Opera, &amp; witnessed a rather inferior performance of the 'Huguenots'. <hi rend="bold underline">I wrote to Gore<persName xml:id="49"></persName>, making some criticisms on his articles in the 'Pilot' anent the new Criticism</hi><hi rend="underline">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>