<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>The mosquitoes penetrated by an unguarded place in the circle of my fortification, &amp; attacked me with energy &amp; alas! success. I slew two but it was only to stain the coverlid with my own blood, for they were in a sated condition, while I was <hi rend="underline">rising</hi> in protest.</p>
         <p>In duty bound we sought out the English Church &amp; attended the service. There was a small congregation. The chaplain was an old man, plainly little educated &amp; very Evangelical. He read the service passably, but the sermon was an intolerable performance, which reduced us both to desperation. The preacher began with an extremely superfluous &amp; under&#8211;bred reference to the late Empress Frederick. After lunch we took the steam&#8211;boat on the canal, &amp; got some air &amp; a good view of the dikes &amp; the country. We returned in time to get away comfortably by the afternoon train to Utrecht, which we reached in about 3/4 of an hour. Here we put up at the <hi rend="underline">Hotel Chateau d'Angers</hi>, &amp; dined immediately on arrival, as table d'hote was at the awkward hour 5.30 p.m. i.e. 5 p.m. by railway time.</p>
         <p>We noticed that the engines on the Dutch line were English made – Manchester. It may be noted that the steam&#8211;boats on the canal bore the names of Boer generals – de Wet &amp; Botha<persName xml:id="2528"></persName>. We were astonished by the number of Jews &amp; Jewesses, who frequented the Caf&#x00E9; &amp; Restaurant Krasnapolsky, &amp; crowded the canal steamer. They are curiously repulsive. After dinner we strolled in Utrecht for awhile &amp; then returned to our hotel.</p></body></text></TEI>