<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1901.</hi></p>
         <p>The forenoon was spent in seeing Bremen. It is worth seeing. The Cathedral is a great Romanesque building, much altered &amp; now undergoing thorough repairs, which include a vigorous painting up of the whole interior. The effect is gorgeous. It is pleasing to find some evidence that the citizens value &amp; use their church. Opposite the Cathedral is the Rath&#8211;haus with a fine hall &amp; underneath the famous Rath's&#8211;kellen. Here, as in duty bound, we drank wine &amp; were shown the vast accumulation of Rhine wines, in tuns of immense bulk &amp; long antiquity. The "Twelve Apostles" were notable. <hi rend="bold underline">The oldest tun bore a date of the middle of the 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> century</hi>. This apotheosis of drinking must be equally profitable &amp; degrading to the state. Then we visited another big church. St. Catherine's, so varnished, pewed, &amp; painted that history had vanished, save for the eloquent protest of the fabric itself. After lunch we went on to Hamburg, about 11/2 hour's ride, in a schnell&#8211;zug for which we had to pay extra. Here we put up at the <hi rend="underline">Hotel Belvidere</hi> on the Alsta, &amp; strolled about the city before going to bed. The aspect of these great lakes surrounded by the lights &amp; movement of a great city was, in the evening light, very remarkable &amp; romantic.</p></body></text></TEI>