<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[39]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>I left the Castle after an early breakfast, and caught the early train to London, where I arrived at 2.30 p.m. A stout &amp; amiable ex&#8211;publican or brewer, who lives near Barnard Castle, was my compagnon de voyage. He brought in to see me Sir William Gray<persName xml:id="5324"></persName>, the Hartlepool ship&#8211;builder, who was also travelling in the train</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I left my bag in Park Lane, and then went on to S</hi><hi rend="i sup u">t</hi> <hi rend="italic">Margaret's Westminster, where I baptized</hi> <hi rend="i bold doubleunderline">Morwenna Colenso Thelwell</hi><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">. </hi><hi rend="italic">The child screeched all the way through most evilly! </hi><hi rend="bold underline">Then I went across to the House of Lords</hi>. While I was having tea, I was joined by <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Joicey</hi><persName xml:id="3464"></persName>, who was very amiable. The <hi rend="doubleunderline">Archbishop of Canterbury</hi> moved the rejection of the Bill for <hi rend="underline">legalizing</hi> the marriage with brothers&#8211;in&#8211;law. His Grace was amusingly and effectively criticised by the Lord Chancellor<persName xml:id="2508"></persName>. <hi rend="bold underline">I made a poor ineffective speech, and then abstained from voting. </hi>The 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> reading was carried 55 to 17. Then I went to the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. Athelstan Riley<persName xml:id="213"></persName> was there, very full of his seigneurial obligation to present two ducks to the King when he visits Jersey next week. I dined with Ernest<persName xml:id="636"></persName> as my companion, and afterwards we walked in the Mall together.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">The Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> drew me </hi><hi rend="bold underline">aside</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> in the H. of L. this afternoon in order to complain of the cold disdain with which</hi> <hi rend="italic">I invariably treated him!! The coal strike is "settled!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>