<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[100]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, August 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A heavy mist shrouds the whole landscape. Mine host worked out a route for William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and I sent it on to him. Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName> wrote to inform that Thomas<persName xml:id="3958"></persName>, the quaint little litigious Welshman who is vicar of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Giles's Durham, is stricken with a fatal malady, &amp; must undergo an operation forthwith. I wrote to say that I would contribute &#x00A3;10 to the expense. Also I wrote sympathetically to the unhappy man himself. I spent the morning in revising &amp; continuing the Preface. After lunch some wounded soldiers from a local convalescent hospital, and spent the afternoon playing games. <hi rend="bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Maugham, with his wife &amp; daughter also came. Bobbie Bruce is their son&#8211;in&#8211;law. I had some interesting conversation with M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Maugham. He is more optimistic than I am about the world's outlook</hi>.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked to the monument of Sir Beville Grenville, who was killed at the battle of Lansdown in 1643. It is a fine monument adorned with Clarendon's charming description of Grenville on the one side &amp; by contemporary verses on the other. The blank sides are richly garnished with <hi rend="underline">graffiti</hi>. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Young, the Vicar of the parish, came to dinner. He is an elderly man of a grave &amp; intelligent demeanour, who is evidently much regarded by our hosts, &amp;, I should judge deservedly so. He has served in Australia, &amp; thus brings to his work a rather wider range of experience than is generally possessed by a country clergyman. We sate round the drawing&#8211;room fire after dinner, and told stories to one another's infinite contentment, and so to bed.</p></body></text></TEI>