<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[151]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Still the brilliant weather, with a growing suggestion of the autumn in feeling and aspect. Before descending to breakfast, I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>. After reading prayers, which followed breakfast, I was seized upon by Hal, who insisted on showing me many wholly uninteresting things and exhibiting to his own immense satisfaction his authority over the household! <hi rend="bold underline">Then I wrote a letter to be read next Sunday at the annual Demonstration of the Trades' Union Council at Holy Trinity, Hartlepool. </hi></p>
         <p>After lunch we motored to Southwell, and visited the Minster. It is a very noble church, though not on the noblest scale. The Triforium of the nave is unusually ample: but the principal glory of this church is the exquisite carving of the chapter&#8211;house. Nothing could exceed the delicacy &amp; beauty of this work. The stone chancel screen in the Decorated style is also very notable. There is no episcopal throne: the bishop uses the Abbot's stall.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">We went on through Newark to Elston, and called on the <persName xml:id="3512">Darwins</persName><persName xml:id="3813"></persName> with whom we had tea. </hi>It was very pleasant to see them again. Gilbert<persName xml:id="3981"></persName> came in before we took leave. He has left Cambridge, and is about to start work as an engineer in Darlington. We go home shortly after 7 pm. <hi rend="bold underline">"Every church is different from the rest"</hi> was William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> observation as we left Southwell Minster. I judge this to be a wise remark, &amp; one that indicates both intelligence &amp; interest. When the individuality of the old churches has been grasped, the first step to a just appreciation has been taken.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[152]</hi></p>
         <p>After dinner I was led into some conversation of a graver type than is common. <hi rend="bold underline">But the forwardness &amp; garrulity of Master Hal had forced on our attention the question, What kind of a future did the world promise for one trained as he is? His tutor was not very helpful about him: &amp; my own observations tended to add emphasis to whatsoever was unfavourable &amp; ominous in the tutor's works. Accordingly, I allowed myself to speak with some freedom to M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Laurie. I told her that she should train her son for living in a world dramatically different from that which he now knew: that he would discover the hollowness of much that he now thought to be secure: that he must unlearn the time&#8211;honoured distinction of all men into "cads" &amp; "gentlemen": that he would have to learn the true value of "privilege" and "form", &amp; that would be disconcertingly little. I declared my firm believe that the present order was doomed, &amp; that, whether gradual or violent, Revolution was certain &amp; near. The good lady was evidently surprised, and somewhat alarmed. I judge her to be a foolish but well&#8211;meaning woman, fond of her children, but unable to control them, vaguely conscious that they are not being wisely handled, but unable to perceive any better method of handling them. Her task in on any showing a difficult one, for her son is a high spirited lad who drinks in eagerly the adulation of servants, &amp; needs prominently the paternal control which he lacks.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>