<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[5]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, Sunday, June 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol] </p>
         <p>A chilly and heavily clouded morning, which we regretted the more as our way led us through some of the finest scenery in the diocese. Besides, my business was not of the cheerfullest, and I stood in no spiritual need of depression from without! Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle a few minutes after 9 a.m. and motored to Forest by way of Cockfield, Lynesack, Ronaldkirk, and Middleton. The mist lay heavy on the land all the way, &amp; shrouded the scenery. At Forest I preached, and celebrated the <hi rend="italic">Holy Communion. After service, the Churchwarden, a fine old farmer named Nixon said to me, "</hi><hi rend="italic underline">You be the youngest bishop I've known</hi><hi rend="italic">". '</hi><hi rend="italic underline">Guess my age'</hi><hi rend="italic">, I replied. "Forty&#8211;two" was his rejoinder! We lunched with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Oddie, the organist, who had retired from the Headmastership of the Council School. He impressed as an excellent example</hi> of his type. The account he gave of the relationship between Rector &amp; people was disconcerting. At 3 p.m. I confirmed 8 persons in <hi rend="bold underline">Middleton Church</hi> (a modern building of the "copy&#8211;book Gothick" style which some years ago replaced the Norman Church, which was pulled down!). After this service I interviewed the Churchwardens on the subject of the Rector's return: and then had to tea with a widow lady, whose language about the said Rector &amp; his wife was more decisive than charitable. Next I went to the rectory and had a long conversation with the Rector himself. The Rev. W. J. Y. Rooker<persName xml:id="5312"></persName> is presumably a man of my own age: he has been 35 years in orders, and has exchanged livings twice already. He is <hi rend="bold">[6]</hi> physically a short slightly&#8211;built man, with a peering suspicious look, and a manner which, as his mood requires, may be either wheedling or aggressive. His crimes are two &#8211; a German wife and debt. I catechised with him rather brutally about the last. He alleged that he had got into the hand of the money lenders since he had recourse to them at the time of his child's birth, when his expenses exceeded his income. The said income was no more than &#x00A3;180 per annum. He had "gone bankrupt" to escape from an impossible situation: but his debt would be paid in 3 years, and he would shortly receive his discharge. Meanwhile he has to do the dilapidation on the Rectory &#8211; a 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house in woeful condition. The garden, which must have been beautiful when properly kept up, is a sad spectacle of weed grown neglect. I spoke severely to the wretched man, &amp; to his wife: but consented, since I could do no otherwise, to his resuming his duty in the parish. Then I told him to be present at Evensong, and to read the Lessons. There was a considerable congregation. Stephenson read the Service, &amp; Rooker the lessons. I preached from the words <hi rend="underline">"The disciples were called Christians first in Antioch"</hi>: &amp; turned my discourse into an obviously designed exhortation to mutual forbearance and forgiveness. The attention was of that intimate closeness which indicates that the shaft has gone home. Rooker has a hard task before him. Then we returned to the castle, arriving at 9 p.m. The weather had cleared up. Our homeward journey was made under the most favourable conditions. The country looked beautiful in the level lights of the failing sun. </p></body></text></TEI>