<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[53]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>What ought to be said to the commissioned lay&#8211;readers of the diocese, who gather in Durham today for their annual gathering? Many of them have been, and are, accustomed to read service and to preach even in consecrated buildings, so great has been the shortage of clergy. Since, then, they have been doing practically all that a clergyman commonly does, save the celebration of the Sacrament and the reading of the Absolution, it is not easy to make clear to them what the limits of their ministry properly are. Their educational level is not visibly inferior to that of a considerable proportion of the clergy, and not infrequently they adopt a manner of dressing which is apparently clerical. Moreover, it seems very probable that the future will witness a considerable increase in their number, and a marked rise in their status. There is a continuing agitation for a "permanent diaconate" which finds its strongest support in the aspirations of the lay&#8211;workers. They covet the character and style of ordained clergymen. That they are bumptious, ignorant, and greedy may go without saying, but these ill qualities are all out balanced by the single fact that they are also indispensable. Their relations with Nonconformity, from whose ranks a considerable number of them have come, and with whose methods most of them are in hearty agreement, provide another, and very difficult, question. Friction with the incumbents arises from this service very often. What are the conditions of a licensed lay reader's efficiency? What are his distinctive difficulties? What are the most trustworthy tokens of his success?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[54]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Col. Burdon</hi><persName xml:id="1659"></persName>, the patron of Horden, writes to tell me that Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName>, the Vicar of Horden, has accepted another living, he invites a suggestion. The same post brought me a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brigstocke</hi>, whose health seems to prohibit a return to Oxbridge. I made a venture, &amp; asked Burden to offer Horden to him. If the place is healthy, &amp; the house, though small, hygienic, it might be the case that Horden would suit him quite well. In order that Burden<persName xml:id="1659"></persName> might appreciate the facts, I enclosed to him both Brigstocke's<persName xml:id="5328"></persName> letter, and that of his Vicar. As a "second&#8211;string" I suggested Shaddick<persName xml:id="5358"></persName>, the curate of Stanhope.</p>
         <p>Accompanied by <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>, I motored to Durham, and there admitted 19 lay&#8211;readers to office in the Cathedral at Evensong, and gave an address to the Layhelpers Association. After tea in one of the University lecture&#8211;rooms, there was a "conference" in another. Then we all returned to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The heat this afternoon has been extreme. No rain has fallen over most of the country, &amp; the harvest is certain to be a very light one.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Hughes</hi><persName xml:id="2953"></persName>, the new Vicar of Pittington, is reported to ^be^ <hi rend="underline">hors de combat</hi> with a nervous breakdown! Considering the lofty eulogies with which I introduced him to his parishioners at his institution as recently as the 6<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> of March, this is rather disconcerting. I fear that his experience as Minor Canon, Librarian, &amp; Sacrist of the Cathedral, left him very ill&#8211;equipped for pastoral and parochial work.</p></body></text></TEI>