<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[97]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, August 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>This 'Preface' weighs on my mind. I cannot forget that I must needs write as Bishop of Durham, whose words must be reckoned both within my own diocese where clergy &amp; laity will reasonably understand them as an interpretation of my mind &amp; purpose, and in the Church generally where they must be read as an appeal to the general reason &amp; conscience. It follows that I cannot wisely limit myself to criticisms of the 'Enabling Act', and the 'Anglo&#8211;Catholics' &amp;c &#8211; although in a preface to a volume on "Anglicanism" such criticisms can hardly be avoided, but I must indicate, however briefly, in what direction I myself look for light, what policy I am myself prepared to recommend to my fellow&#8211;churchmen, &amp; what advice I can offer to my own clergy &amp; laity. It is not very easy to do this in so limited a space as a 'Preface', or rather the 'tale&#8211;end' of a 'Preface' provides, but in some measure it must be attempted.</p>
         <p>After lunch I went to the local hair&#8211;cutter, and, greatly daring, subjected myself to his ministrations. Another customer addressed my by name, and explained that he had been one of my audience at Worcester when I spoke in advocacy of the League of Nations. I wrote to William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, and (privately) to Marion<persName xml:id="77"></persName>.</p>
         <p>Later, <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked along the front, and through the pinewoods. The views across the bay were very beautiful, and the clearness of the atmosphere showed the white cliffs on the Welsh coast very distinctly. We returned through the woods, the way being slippery for the pine&#8211;needles. We got in about dinner&#8211;time very warm, but pleased with ourselves for the energy, and recompensed by the experience. </p></body></text></TEI>