<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[82]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I have been reading a novel by J.A. Cramb, the author of "Germany&amp; England", the book which in the beginning of the war, attracted much attention. It is called 'Sch&#x00F6;nbrunn', &amp; appears to be a study of Napoleon.</p>
         <p>Shortly after 10 a.m. we left Condover Hall, and motored to Hartlebury Castle. We stopped for an hour at Much Wenlock in order to see the fine parish church, and the ruins of the Priory. We called on Lady Catherine Milne&#8211;Gaskell, and had some converse with her. Then we went on to Monk Hopton, &amp; called on the Wenlocks, but to no purpose as they were absent. We visited the fine parish church at Morvill, &amp; then went on to Bridgnorth, where we lunched at the Crown Hotel (13/8). Then we continued our journey to Hartlebury, where we arrived about 2.45 p.m. &amp; were warmly welcomed by the Bishop and his sister. We spent some time in walking about the Castle &amp; gardens. The water, now adorned wih swans, is a beautiful feature, and the lawns, though parched by drought, are dignified with peacocks! In some respects, Hartlebury has the advantage of Auckland. The noble Hall, the graceful drawing&#8211;rooms, the galleries, the library, the stair&#8211;case  ̶  Auckland has nothing to equal them. Only its Chapel, State&#8211;room, &amp; noble architectural lines are superior. The beautiful park has almost passed out of connexion with the Castle, &amp; become the possession of the people.</p></body></text></TEI>