<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[109]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended matins in the cathedral, and then was joined by Williams, with whom I made the tour of the church, working conscientiously through the guide&#8211;book, and filling nearly the two hours very pleasantly. We turned up the <hi rend="underline">mis&#x00E9;ricorde</hi> seats, and looked at the beautiful, grotesque,&amp; always interesting carvings. As rain fell almost continuously, we were fortunate in being so comfortably placed. </p>
         <p>After lunch the ladies went off in the car to pay calls: Gamble<persName xml:id="249"></persName> and I walked and talked for two hours. As we stood on a bridge over the Exe by Countess Weir, we were over&#8211;taken by two motors, from one of which there descended a man named Swan, whom we met many years ago at Sauchieburn. He was motoring there with his family.</p>
         <p>The papers report on a truculent speech from De Valera, in which he reaffirms his demand for an Irish Republic, and refuses to negotiate with Great Britain. This doesn't look promising. </p>
         <p>We dined pleasantly enough with no party. Conversation was free enough, and, perhaps, ranged too discursively, for, beyond a vague sense of satisfaction, left nothing in the memory which could make a record. </p>
         <p>Somebody thought it worth wile to send me cuttings from the "Morning Post" about the murder of poor old M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lindsay. I share to the full the horror which so cruel a crime must needs provoke in every rightly constituted mind, but what can I do, or what can be done to avenge it?</p></body></text></TEI>