<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[146]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A most glamorous day from beginning to ending. We walked about 2 miles to church at Rouseham. The service was Mattins, Sermon, &amp; Holy Communion, and the parson did his duty quite well. He is evidently a scholarly man. After service at which we all communicated, including William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, we were introduced to the Vicar, and the Squire (M<hi rend="superscript underline">r </hi>Cotterell Dormer). With the former was a young man who had made a special study of Marsilius of Padua. He told me that he had discovered in the Bodleian an unpublished tract by this great legist, &amp; had sent in an edition of it as a thesis for the D. Litt. at Cambridge. He also told me that Henry VIII paid &#x00A3;20 for the English translation of the "Defensor Pacis", which he caused to be published by way of justifying his ecclesiastical policy. It was odd to light on this knowledge in a small country parish. In the afternoon we called on Lord Dillon, and had tea with him. He was full of interesting talk, and showed us his pictures.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Our kind hosts, having one bottle of 1863 port, opened it in my honour, as that was the year of my birth</hi>. These small kindnesses are the decorations of human intercourse, &amp; draw people together with a power wholly out of proportion to their intrinsic importance. They go outside &amp; underneath the conventions, &amp; fix anchors in our hearts. </p></body></text></TEI>