<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[111]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a long and interesting letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> addressed on July 16<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1921 from 'Off South Coast of Ceylon'. Also a letter from <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macmillan</hi>, acknowledging the receipt of the Preface, and expressing "<hi rend="underline">both interest and approval</hi>". After breakfast a telegram arrived from M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Buchanan, begging us to postpone our visit until tomorrow: so we had to invoke the hospitality of the Dean &amp; his wife for a further stay under their roof. <hi rend="doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> counselled the using of the interval for the cleaning of the car at the garage. This would cost &#x00A3;3., but, in view of the consumption of petrol which has become excessive, he thought it worthwhile. So I gave order that it should be done, &amp; then went to the cathedral for Mattins. After service Anthea guided <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; me to see the Priory, and Guildhall: then, the day being her birthday, I presented her with "The last days of Pompei" (which she chose) &amp; a box of chocolates. The chancellor<persName xml:id="5338"></persName> of this diocese (<hi rend="doubleunderline">Henry Newbolt's</hi><persName xml:id="3946"></persName> brother) came to lunch. He was severe on the incompetence of the clergy in the matter of memorial tablets. They sanction inscriptions which are neither seemly nor suitable, nor even grammatical! After lunch I wrote to George. Then I went to tea with Archdeacon Leake, with whom was old M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Luxmoure, Gerald Marshall's<persName xml:id="18"></persName> uncle, whom I remember some 30 years ago, when he entertained a party of boys from Barking, who had travelled to Eton on a bank&#8211;holiday. He looks amazingly well, &amp; very little older than he looked then!</p></body></text></TEI>