<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[77] [sic]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 24</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The excellent <hi rend="doubleunderline">Gray</hi> made his appearance at the Castle in good time, &amp; few minutes after 9 a.m., we set out for Sunderland in his car. We arrived in good time at the humble little mission church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary Magdalene. There I celebrated the Holy Communion and preached. After service I was formally welcomed by the Church Council. We lunched with <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Prideaux</hi><persName xml:id="3181"></persName>, the Vicar, a young man of promise. At 3.30 p.m. I went to S. Stephen's and dedicated War Memorials. <hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Nedwill</hi>, the Vicar, had evidently taken great pains with the arrangements. There was a crowded congregation, and admission was by ticket! I don't like this, but it may have been necessary. Gray motored me to South Shields. We dropped Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> in Sunderland on our way. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hudson Barker</hi><persName xml:id="3575"></persName> gave us tea. He and Gray were fellow&#8211;students in Durham. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Jones</hi>, the curate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Aidan's came to see me. I like him, &amp; promised to help him to pay the cost of his terms at Durham, if he can manage to get a curacy there. We motored to All Saints, where I dedicated War Memorials, and preached. My staff was carried by a young choirman, whose name was <hi rend="doubleunderline">William Reay</hi>. He told me that he was a bank&#8211;clerk. We motored back to Auckland, recovering Clayton <hi rend="underline">en route</hi>, and arrived about 9.30 p.m. I was surprised &amp; delighted by the news that William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> had succeeded in repairing the car, the missing pieces having arrived at 9.30 a.m. today.</p></body></text></TEI>