<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[193]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The Lord's divinity was from the first as fixed an axiom of Christianity as the unity of God, while his humanity was plainly declared by the original apostolic testimony, and both together were necessary to give reality to the Incarnation: It remained to reconcile this view of the Lord's Person with the first fundamental principle of the unity of God."</p>
         <p>Gwatkin<persName xml:id="4241"></persName>. Studies p. 5.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I worked on the Congress Sermon most of the day, &amp; finished it</hi>. Laws, the gardener from Colonel Carter, Colton House, near Rugeley, came to see me, &amp; I undertook (if his reference was satisfactory) to engage him on a weekly wage of &#x00A3;3, with cottage, coals, &amp; light. He would be ready to undertake his duties on November 1<hi rend="superscript underline">st</hi> next. </p>
         <p>The <persName xml:id="383">Spooners</persName><persName xml:id="2162"></persName> arrived on a short visit. He has resigned the Archdeaconry of Maidstone and the Canonry of Canterbury, and now resides in Oxford.</p>
         <p>Armstrong<persName xml:id="5352"></persName>, aged 75, Bursar &amp; prospective Provost of Queen's College, Oxford, has engaged himself to marry his type&#8211;writer, a young lady of 23! Oxford is scandalized: &amp;, indeed, the arrangement doesn't look pleasant.</p>
         <p>The "Times" reports the death of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Gee<persName xml:id="3484"></persName>, wife of the Dean of Gloucester<persName xml:id="2920"></persName>. This was not altogether a surprize, for she had been ailing for some while past.</p></body></text></TEI>