<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[12]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I received an affectionate letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>, written from New York, and dated May 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>. His ship is held up by the desertion of 20 of the Chinese crew. He describes a service at the Seamen's Institute:&#8211;</p>
         <p>" There must have been between 3&#8211;400 men in the congregation, most of them Britishers &amp; not a few from other European Countries &amp; the singing was fine. The Clergyman made most of the congregation feel bitter, as he talked <hi rend="underline">far</hi> too much about America, &amp; ran down the European nations. Also he spoke at some length on Prohibition, &amp; he was certain that ere long England would have followed the fine example of this fine free Country. I don't think he knows what the working man in England would do without his glass of beer."</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Clayton motored with me into Durham, where I presided in the Chapter House over a meeting of the Diocesan Conference. The proceedings were certainly not dull. Thanks to the intervention of the Archdeacon, the proposal to appoint a paid secretary was adjourned. After tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, I returned to the Castle picking up Sam Adams on the way.</p>
         <p>I was surprised to observe the loud applause which greeted some crudely socialistic remarks made in the conference. There were indications that my severe attitude towards Ordination candidates is resented, &amp; that my condemnation of the Strike has not added to my popularity.</p></body></text></TEI>