<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[99]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, August 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>We left Minehead by the 11.10 a.m. train, &amp; travelled as far as Taunton where we stayed for more than 2 hours, which we spent in lunching at the Castle Hotel, and in seeing the fine parish church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary Magdalene. This is a large building with double aisles, a fine southern porch, &amp; an unusually magnificent tower, all in the Perpendicular style. We visited also the museum at the castle, which contained a good many Roman and Stone&#8211;age objects of interest found in the district, beside the usual collection of heterogeneous curiosities. <hi rend="bold underline">At 3 p.m. we left Taunton and travelled to Bath, where we were met by a motor, and carried out to Brockham End, where we were kindly received by Sir Alexander Lawrence </hi>and his wife. The boys, John and George are here with a French friend, Maurice. Also a very intelligent Irish lady, Miss Dickinson. In the field immediately behind the house are the foundations of a Roman villa, the uncovering of which &amp; extracting of fragments of pottery etc., afford unfailing occupation to the family. The view from the terrace is most magnificent. As the house is 750 feet above sea level, it commands very noble and extensive prospects. We had much very pleasant conversation after dinner.</p>
         <p>I found a letter from William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> awaiting me. He writes as if for him also idleness is not altogether pleasing: "Although on holidays, and amongst all my old friends, I have missed you very much, my Lord. It will be pleasant to be with you again." I too shall be glad to be at work again.</p></body></text></TEI>