<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[17]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Fuller notes that the seal of the Bishop of Durham "in form resembleth royalty in the roundness thereof, and is not oval, the badge of plain episcopacy." (v. Ch.Hist. iv. 103) Van Mildert's seal was the last of the round ones: all subsequent bishops have used the oval shape.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Durham, where I licensed several curates, &amp; then collated Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName> to his honorary canonry. This I did in the presence of the Boys, for whom I bespoke a half&#8211;holiday. Then we lunched with Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> at the County Club; he had made up a pleasant party by the addition of his brother&#8211;in&#8211;law, Eade, the Vicar of Aycliffe, an odd parson named Gregson, who holds property in the diocese, and Major Vaux. After lunch we motored to <hi rend="bold underline">Gateshead</hi>, where I inspected the Industrial School, witnessed the boys' gymnastic performances, and made a speech at a meeting presided over by the Mayor. After tea I went to the new cemetery, and consecrated a portion for the use of church people. The Mayor, who is a Dissenter, walked in the procession, robed &amp; preceded by his mace&#8211;bearer. I gave an address. Then we motored back to the Castle, traversing the distance in less than an hour. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> says that he attained to 43 miles an hour on the open road. </p>
         <p>The notice of the Archbishop's intention to move the resolution approving the Parochial Councils (Powers) Bill tomorrow reached me tonight!</p></body></text></TEI>