<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[145]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, September 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>In the morning we went into Kidlington, and looked at the ancient seat of the Dashwoods, which has just been again sold to some wealthy proprietor. It is a noble mansion built in the early decades of the 18<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century, when the architectural influence of Blenheim was paramount in Oxfordshire. Then we inspected the cement works which the enterprize of mine host has established in the place. These now employ about 100 men, &amp; are prospering. The stone and clay are quarried, pulverized, burnt, sifted, packed, &amp; despatched by barge to the centres in Oxford &amp; Birmingham. After lunch we motored to Broughton Hall, the seat of <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Say &amp; Sele</hi><persName xml:id="5345"></persName>, and had tea. After tea the noble owner showed us over the house. It is a 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century mansion, enlarged &amp; re&#8211;cast in the reign of Elizabeth. The ceilings in the Tudor rooms are unusually beautiful and elaborate. <hi rend="underline">A small room at the top of the house was pointed out as the meeting place of the Parliamentary chiefs when they planned the rebellion against Charles I</hi>. After visiting the parish church, where is a fine stone chancel screen, we returned to Barton. Two neighbours came to dinner, and we had much pleasant conversation. Lord S. &amp; S. told me that he had endeavoured, but vainly, to induce the Duke of M.<persName xml:id="5346"></persName> to resign the Lord&#8211;lieutenancy, since his divorce &amp; subsequent marriage had rendered him objectionable. He had written to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lord Stamfordham</hi><persName xml:id="3220"></persName>, from whom a sympathetic reply had been received. He hoped to succeed in his virtuous endeavour.</p></body></text></TEI>