<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[68]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"No Pope ventured to dispute Henry VII<hi rend="superscript underline">th's</hi> nominations for English preferments: <hi rend="underline">and they were made with strict regard to the interests of the Crown.</hi> Morton, Deane, Warham, Foxe, Ruthal, Sherborne, Urswick &amp; others received their bishoprics and deaneries as rewards &amp; endowments for civil &amp; not for spiritual services: &amp; popes agreed that churchmen, if not the church, should serve the state ….. <hi rend="underline">From so accommodating a Catholic jurisdiction, Henry appeared to derive as much profit as he could hope to do from an insular royal supremacy".</hi></p>
         <p>A. T. Pollard<persName xml:id="1948"></persName>. "The reign of Henry VII". p. lxi.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I frittered away my day in correspondence, reading, &amp; making notes for the address on the League of Nations which I delivered in a Wesleyan Chapel at Darlington in the evening. The other speaker </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">was the Labour Leader, M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Arthur Henderson</hi><persName xml:id="4263s"></persName><hi rend="italic">. He is a short square man with a local preacher's manner, and a rather raucous voice. His manner of shaking his finger vehemently at his audience when he roared most loudly disturbed me. He read his speech, which (as I was informed on the platform) had already been sent to the newspapers. He chapel was quite full: a considerable proportion of the audience consisted of young men.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>