<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[11]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold doubleunderline">Harold Begbie</hi><persName xml:id="5310"></persName> sends me a pamphlet: <hi rend="bold underline">The Betrayal of Labour, An Open Letter to the Rt. Hon. J. R. Clynes<persName xml:id="4739"></persName>"</hi>. It is written in the stagey, exstatick style adopted by modern "prophets", but it is too loose in texture, and vague in expression to be of any practical value. <hi rend="bold underline">Publications of this kind suggests the inspiration, not of the prophet, but of the publishers!</hi> <hi rend="underline">"The Gentleman with a Duster"</hi> struck a profitable vein which is not wholly exhausted. But it shows evident signs of giving out.</p>
         <p>I motored to Esh, and there confirmed 49 candidates. On the way I passed Wreford Brown, the parson of Ushaw Moor, with five girls, confirmation candidates. Their omnibus had failed them and they were in doubt how to reach the church in time for the service. I packed them into the motor, and brought them on with us.</p>
         <p>After tea at the Vicarage, I went to Durham &amp; had an interview with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName> about the special service on June 26" which the Archbishops have chosen for general prayers. I said that I would myself preach in the Cathedral, &amp; use the prayers which are to be put forward by authority. Then we returned to Auckland. <hi rend="bold doubleunderline">William</hi><persName xml:id="4501"></persName> came to me in woeful guise: a cricket ball had struck him in the mouth, and broken two of his front teeth, interfering with his utterance, and spoiling his beauty! The bill from the Wallsend Motor Co. arrived. It amounts to &#x00A3;137:11:6. Thus the cost of my 2<hi rend="superscript underline">nd</hi> hand Wolseley car approaches &#x00A3;800.. viz Chassis &#x00A3;450: Body &#x00A3;100, Commission &#x00A3;60: Work &#x00A3;137:11:6 = &#x00A3;747:11:6. There are further expenses incurred here.</p></body></text></TEI>