<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[35]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>We want more revolutionary feeling in this country: but we must make our own revolutionary conceptions, and not import the less successful from France. For this country the Social General Strike is irrelevant".</p>
         <p>G.D.H. Cole. "The World of Labour", p. 202. (pub. 1913)</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">M</hi><hi rend="sup doubleunderline">r</hi><hi rend="doubleunderline"> Cole</hi><persName xml:id="4741"></persName> is, or was, a Fellow of Magdalen College, Oxford. He writes on economic subjects with <hi rend="bold underline">the concentrated malignity of the mere irresponsible theorist, who has heated his imagination without really informing his mind. He preaches the "class&#8211;war" sans phrase: and pours out on the English Trade&#8211;Unionists many "gibes &amp; flouts &amp; sneers" because they are concerned with "benefits", and unconcerned with developing "class&#8211;consciousness". It is a disquieting circumstance that a writer of this kind should find so large a welcome for his books. </hi>This book, "<hi rend="underline">The World of Labour</hi>", published in 1913, is in its 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> edition. Its tone is even worse than its argument.</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in preparing a sermon for Monkwearmouth. Plummer's edition of Bede's History was very useful. The notes are mines of serviceable information. Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> and I weeded the path, though the great heat made exertion difficult. After dinner we walked to Wolsey's pool, and had much talk together. He is a very baffling mixture of good sense and an almost childish fatuity, of an even acute intelligence and a simplicity which would astonish one in a maidservant! He has seen more of the world than most men of his years.</p></body></text></TEI>