<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[133]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, August 28</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Preaching to soldiers is no easy task, least of all is it easy to a preacher as accustomed to take pains in the composition of his sermons, &amp; grown old in the habit of formal preaching. For he is deprived of all the familiar adjuncts &#8211; pulpit, manuscript, church. He is cut down to half his usual measure of time. His audience is not present voluntarily, nor does it feel much interest in him, or his speech. It is hostile in its criticism, and extremely prompt &amp; severe in its verdict.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic"><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I went to the village church at 8 a.m., and received the Holy Communion. It was all very calm, rural, English. These little parish churches are the best things that remain to us. If only the clergy knew how precious they are!</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I preached to the troops at Batford camp at 10 a.m. The service was held in a theatre, and I preached from the stage. Many men could not get into the building which was filled to its utmost capacity. It could not contain more than 750 men. I spoke for about 20 minutes, and the men were very attentive. The chaplains (of whom one was a V.C.) seemed to think the address all that it should be! Half of what I had meant to say was omitted, and, perhaps, the best part. When the sermon was over William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove us all for an hour, the General sitting beside him and explaining everything. The plain has an impressiveness of its own, and must form an admirable manoeuvring ground for troops. It is so healthy that children are said to flourish exceedingly, though their mothers are apt to be "nervy".</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[134]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">At luncheon there was Colonel Brocklebank, who gave me an interesting account of Ireland, from which he had recently returned.</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">He said that the "Black and Tans" had undoubtedly behaved very badly, though of course the provocation had been very great. He thought we should cut southern Ireland adrift. </hi>He thought we should cut southern Ireland adrift, &amp; let them "cut their own throats"! In the afternoon older officers came in, and I was favourably impressed by them. There seems much good feeling among them.</p>
         <p>We attended Evensong in the parish church, where a Harvest Festival was being held. There was a considerable congregation, and the service was hearty. I was rather surprised to see a large choir, including a number of young women, all vested in "red cassocks". It appears to be a hobby of M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Haking (?) the wife of our representatives at Dantzig, who normally resides here. She plays the organ when at home. The sermon was preached by a young chaplain, who spoke with perilous fluency, &amp; without a note. His discourse was void and formless. <hi rend="underline">Why will the youth be so venturous and so vain? If at 30 he is thus incoherent &amp; verbose, what will he have become at 50? Youth covers much which advancing years expose in nakedness.</hi> This young man wore the hood of a Dublin M.A., and had the brogue of the sister isles. His sermon belonged to a type of composition which I had supposed to be quite obsolete, but I am bound to admit that it was listened to with close attention, and probably thought to be very fine! </p></body></text></TEI>