<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[31]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, June 21</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>The common problem, yours, mine, everyone's,</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Is &#8211; not to fancy what were fair in life</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Provided it could be, &#8211; but, finding first</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">What may be, then find how to make it fair</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Up to our means: a very different thing!</hi></p>
         <p>No abstract intellectual plan of life</p>
         <p>Quite irrespective of life's plainest laws,</p>
         <p>But one, a man, who is man &amp; nothing more, </p>
         <p>May lead within a world which (by your leave)</p>
         <p>Is Rome or London, not Fool's paradise.</p>
         <p>Browning: "Bishop Blougram's Apology</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">These lines are a fair criticism of Tawney's Economics</hi>.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">Yet another letter from the inexhaustible Begbie<persName xml:id="5310"></persName>! He presses me to "lead a national crusade for personal righteousness"!! </hi><hi rend="italic">I suppose that in all the population of these islands, there is no man less qualified by temperament, training, taste, age, &amp; position than the present Bishop of Durham for the leading of any crusade whatever.</hi></p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a short sermon for use in the Cathedral next Sunday. There is no more difficult subject for the modern preacher than that which I must perforce take next Sunday &#8211; the subject of prayer.</p>
         <p>The Durham Regatta started today. In the evening a drizzling rain began to fall, breaking a very long spell of dry weather.</p>
         <p>This pestilent strike discloses no prospect of settlement.</p></body></text></TEI>