<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[43]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I completed the sermon for Monkwearmouth. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> <hi rend="doubleunderline">Edward J. Bolus</hi> I.C.S. called on me with a letter of introduction from Canon Streeter<persName xml:id="3230"></persName>. He meditates Ordination on retiring from the Indian Civil Service at the age of 48. I was sympathetic but non&#8211;committal. These are no days for turning down any application which is not patently unacceptable; but there are many weighty objections to a candidate so old. It occurred to me that it might be worth my while to publish the Swedish lectures, &amp; I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">George Macmillan</hi><persName xml:id="1330"></persName> on the subject. Also I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName> sending felicitations on her Birthday. On July 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> she completes 80 years.</p>
         <p>I read through the Lecture on "The Lambeth Conference" after dinner aloud to my family, and my own judgement accorded with their dutiful assurances that it could serve significantly well for publication!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">A Presbyterian minister, the Rev. John Middleton, writing from The Manse, Irongray, Dumfries, appealing to me to resist the passage of the Bill for uniting the Scottish churches</hi><note xml:id="534" n="1"></note>: "It is especially to you, my Lord, with your definite views on National Religion, that we look to preserve our Church, or at least to lend your great power of advocacy in helping to preserve our church, as indeed a National Church, &amp; not merely as this Bill would make it a mere sanctified Soviet". But how could I stand forward as an opponent of Presbyterian Unity?</p></body></text></TEI>