<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[106]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, August 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Sir Aleck Lawrence, Miss Dickenson, and M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pazzini went off after breakfast. Then the boys took themselves off. Finally, Lady Lawrence went into Bath with us. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> arrived with the car about 1 p.m., and after lunch we motored to Exeter, stopping at Wells to get a glimpse of the cathedral, and at Glastonbury, to look at the ruins of the abbey, &amp; the Abbot's kitchen, which is inferior to the Deanery kitchen at Durham. <hi rend="bold underline">Also we stopped at Wellington, and had tea with the Bookers</hi>. We reached the Deanery in Exeter about 7.30 p.m. On the way, I learned that De Valera had sent a truculent answer to the Prime Minister, asserting in crude terms his demand for Irish independence, &amp; declining the "Dominion status" with asperity. This is very grave news, for these are situations in which to offer the olive&#8211;branch unsuccessfully is to make it extremely difficult to draw the sword, although the only alternative to the olive&#8211;branch <hi rend="underline">is</hi> the sword.</p>
         <p>In Wells Cathedral the Dean has set up a Crucifix with figures of S. Mary &amp; S. John in the inverted arch under the Tower. This conspicuous departure from Anglican tradition, which is also a bold breach of the law, must needs have considerable effect in stimulating illegality in the Church. It also throws an interesting light on the personal influence of the learned Dean who is responsible for it.</p></body></text></TEI>