<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[131]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">The difficulty of a "liberal" bishop in speaking on an issue of doctrine is very great. To begin with he is himself doctrinally suspected by most of those to he must address himself. </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">In my case, I am not so much suspected as believed to be 'heretical'. It is little more than 3 years since an active campaign against my appointment as bishop was carried on throughout the country</hi><hi rend="italic">. A 'liberal' bishop can hardly take the tone of </hi><hi rend="italic underline">authority</hi><hi rend="italic"> for that will imply his acceptance of the very method of handling doctrinal issues which his 'liberalism' prohibits. If however he descend into the arena of debate, and proceed to argue the point at issue, he may easily find himself over&#8211;matched, and earn condemnation for his temerity rather than gratitude for his championship. The recent case of the Bishop of Ely's duel with Glazebrook is an example of this. Yet, clearly, his position as a bishop, charged with the task of admitting or rejecting men who seek to be ordained, and publicly pledged to the guardianship of the Faith, makes it impossible for a bishop, however 'liberal', to </hi><hi rend="italic underline">decline</hi><hi rend="italic"> all responsibility. It remains that he should state, simply and clearly, how the matter under debate presents itself to his own mind, why the reasoning of the "hereticks" appears in his judgement to be unconvincing &amp; unsound, and how far he feels able still to affirm in substance if not in actual form, the affirmations of the Creeds. He will hardly succeed; and he will most certainly disappoint the expectations of the "hereticks". </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[132]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">There is an article in the "Times" on the need of theological reconstruction no doubt inspired by the flutters which the Cambridge vapourising have caused. It alters the usual Gamaliel&#8211;like vapourings and balances between the "extremists" on both sides, but does not really help matters. </hi><hi rend="italic underline">I feel that the main question of Nicaea has got to be faced again by the Christian Church, and answered not less decisively: and, I feel persuaded that the answer must be essentially the same, &amp; that it will determine the future course of Christianity</hi><hi rend="italic">. But I do not see any modern substitute for the Nicene Council, nor do I know any formula which may serve our turn as well as the formula of the Nicene Council served the need of Athanasius to his contemporaries.</hi></p>
         <p>After ten <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked across the meadows (Addison's walk) to Millston, where we visited the little parish church, a 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century building with Perpendicular windows. Then we continued our walk to Darrington, where we visited the fine parish church. It consist of a Norman nave with a modern aisle added on the north side, a perpendicular tower, and an early english chancel. The pulpit and reading desk of elaborately carved oak are Elizabethan (c. A.D. 1590) and the fine carved benches in the nave date from 1633. They reminded me of Brancepeth.</p>
         <p>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, after working hard on the car for 3 days, reported that it wa again fit for use. He tested it by a run into Amesbury and back.</p></body></text></TEI>