<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[57]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 12</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I went to Westminster, and spent the day in the "National Assembly", which was all the time concerned with this so&#8211;called Budget. On the subject of an official press, presupposed by a proposal to allot &#x00A3;700 to the organisation thereof, I made a speech strongly opposing it: but, by a (wrong) ruling of the President was unable to make a motion to omit the item. I moved the adjournment of the House on the proposal to vote &#x00A3;18,500 for the organisation of a central test school.</p>
         <p>Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName> had a very successful dinner&#8211;party. The guests were Lord<persName xml:id="1394"></persName> &amp; Lady Ernle, Sir Frederick<persName xml:id="414"></persName> &amp; Lady Macmillan, Sir Charles &amp; Lady Monro, Lady Cromer<persName xml:id="1144"></persName>, Sir F. Leggatt (?), &amp; Sir C. &amp; Lady Orrid (?). We all talked energetically until nearly 11 p.m. Old Sir Frederick Macmillan, when we parted, spoke to me rather mysteriously about the MSS. of my Swedish lectures. He said that he hoped they would be able to publish them. I said that I thought it desirable that they should be on record. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Westminster Gazette" has a column of report on the proceedings of the "National Assembly". It refers to my contribution to the proceedings as "a slashing speech", but it fails to bring out the main points that I made. The truth is that the whole method of ecclesiastical debate is so remote from the common procedures of the journalistic mind, that intelligent reporting is rarely to be secured.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>