<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[167]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, September 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I attended the Holy Communion in the chapel at 8 a.m. but did not celebrate or communicate. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> was the celebrant. After breakfast I motored into Durham, and there I instituted M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Morris to the vicarage of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's. The electrical machinery of the organ went wrong, but the unaccompanied singing of the choir was very good. There was a smaller congregation than I had expected. In my sermon <hi rend="bold underline">I took occasion to speak about the Cambridge Conference</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>After service I lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Ritson. Then we motored to Langley Moor, where I preached at a "united service" of churchfolks &amp; sectaries in the Church Hall. There was a crowded attendance, and the service seemed to be sincere. After tea with the Vicar of Esh, I preached at Evensong in the little parish church which was filled to its utmost capacity. The congregation was very attentive. It included William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>, whose honest fresh country&#8211;face with its pleasant boyish good&#8211;humour looked very attractive amid the pallid &amp; rather unfriendly countenances of the miners. He is much taller &amp; stouter than most of them so that he was the more conspicuous. After service I returned to the Castle, arriving about 8.30 p.m. The roads are in a terrible state, &amp; the 'wear &amp; tear' of the motor must be extreme. Possibly we have been spoiled by the excellent roads of southern &amp; central England, but certainly it is the case that both William and I think the Durham roads have deteriorated grievously during our absence.</p></body></text></TEI>