<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[33]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>With me, faith means perpetual unbelief</p>
         <p>Kept quiet like the snake 'neath Michael's foot</p>
         <p>Who stands calm just because he feels it writhe.</p>
         <p>Bishop Blougram's Apology</p>
         </div>
         <p>I received a note from the egregious <hi rend="doubleunderline">Partridge</hi> (the advertising quack who has made such a muddle of the Central Finance Board) informing me that "<hi rend="underline">the Church of England Press Bureau has been established and work is now undertaken by it</hi>". Thus we make a start with an "official Press", and another blow is struck to the tottering edifice of Anglican liberty. We are getting on!</p>
         <p>I spent the morning in writing a sermon for the Freemasons. It is humiliating that every petty discourse costs me so much labour. There came to lunch M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Perrott &amp; his wife together with their son. The last&#8211;named had just returned from Roumania. He assures me that the Roumanian people is idle, living on credit, &amp; moving quickly towards economic disaster. He was for some while a prisoner with the Bolshevists, of whom he give a black account.</p>
         <p>Dolphin<persName xml:id="2798"></persName> came from Edmund Byers ^[Edmundbyers]^ to assist me in the task of filling up the paper of questions issued by the Committee on Church Property. After dinner he sang songs in the State Room. We undoubtedly lose much through our lack of musical skill. A party of scouts from Sunderland encamped in the Castle enclosure.</p></body></text></TEI>