<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[45]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I left the Castle at 9 a.m., and motored to Monkwearmouth by way of Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street and Washington, avoiding thus the infamous main road. We arrived in good time for the service at 10.30 a.m. It was a choral celebration, preceded by the dedication of a tablet set up by some parishioners to the memory of their parents. I celebrated and preached. There was a large congregation, including a good number of Freemasons, with whom I shook hands after the service. There were no less than 125 communicants, and, for the first time in my life, I had to re&#8211;consecrate twice. Everything was very reverent, &amp; I was better pleased than I had dared to hope I should be. I lunched with Canon Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName>, and at 3 p.m. dedicated War Memorials in S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Ignatius, &amp; preached again. There was a great congregation, &amp; an immense throng outside the church. At Evensong, the church was thronged, many standing throughout. I preached for the third time, being much disturbed by a coughing female. After service we motored back to the Castle, arriving about 10 p.m. It is difficult to appraise justly the value of crowded churches, but certainly I find it difficult to attach <hi rend="underline">no</hi> importance to the apparently eager congregations which I have addressed today. The Church appears to be far stronger in the ship&#8211;building centres than in the mining districts. Sunderland &amp; Hartlepool are the most "churchy" places in the diocese</p></body></text></TEI>