<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[26]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, June 17</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The reports of the miners' ballot show that the terms of settlement offered have been rejected by a large majority. In this county the numbers are about 70,000 against to 20,000 for. Yet every independent observer had foretold the acceptance of the terms by an overwhelming majority. The English working&#8211;man is becoming as secretive and cunning as a Chinaman. It may, perhaps, be the case that the large Irish element is telling. However explained, it is extremely unfortunate, for it is difficult to see how a way out can be found.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I motored to Durham, and lunched in my rooms at the Castle. Then we proceeded to Newcastle, and there I presided at the annual meeting of the Northern Counties Orphan School. I made a speech, Ella distributed prizes, then followed votes of thanks. We adjourned to the Garden, &amp; witnessed the gymnastics of the children. After tea, we returned to Auckland, calling at Dryburn on the way only to find the Vauxes<persName xml:id="5041"></persName> absent. The drought continues, and the county is becoming a brown study.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Warde Fowler's</hi><persName xml:id="5159"></persName> death is announced in the papers. I knew him but slightly when I was resident in Oxford, but my liking for him was out of proportion to my acquaintance. His deafness made communication difficult, and conversation impossible: but his kindly expression and evident sweetness of nature compelled affection.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[27]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Begbie<persName xml:id="5310"></persName></p>
         <p>In deference to your request, I have read through the Interview again, &amp; make a few alterations. If you think it worth while to publish it with these modifications, &amp; with a note that <hi rend="bold underline">the Bishop of Durham accepts responsibility for the substance, but not for the form of what is attributed to him. I leave you free to publish it</hi>. </p>
         <p>My own feeling is always opposed to what are sometimes called "topical" pronouncements. They are read or neglected only as far as they harmonize with men's immediate interests. The shaping of the popular mind &amp; the wakening of the popular conscience are slow &amp; difficult tasks. "<hi rend="underline">It cost more to redeem their souls</hi>". However, have it as you will.</p>
         <p>You were good enough to send me an "Open Letter" to M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Clynes which I read with much interest. The position of a Labour "Leader" is extraordinarily difficult. In no other sphere of public life is the gulf between the leader's importance &amp; the constituent's insignificance more marked, &amp; in none is the dependence of the leader on the constituent more absolute. I am reminded of the case of a Neapolitan Madonna, whose worshipper oscillates between Worship and blows!</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         </div></body></text></TEI>