<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[183]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, September 26</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921. </hi></p>
         <p>Last night I was haunted by that woeful man, Dowson. On the one hand, how can I encourage him to go forward in the ministry? On the other hand, how can I allow him, for lack of liberty to ministers, to perish in the gutter? Apart from the question of discipline which must determine my treatment of the man himself, what place has charity in the business? He has a wife &amp; 3 children, are their miseries relevant to a determination of my duty? How must the Bishop's duty as laid on him at his consecration be interpreted? How ran the words? </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p><hi rend="underline">"Be so merciful, that you be not too remiss: so minister discipline, that you forget not mercy"</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <p>How is this observation to be interpreted in the case of Dowson? He has had too many chances of passing his exam<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> for the priesthood: &amp; twice he has failed. If that had been all, I would have suffered him to try twice again: but not only did the Rural Dean make very adverse reports on his behaviour, &amp; throw grave doubt on his pre&#8211;Anglican record, but old W.B., one of the most tolerant &amp; long&#8211;suffering of men, as I judge, wrote to ask permission to get rid of him for quite intolerable incapacity. In these circumstances, I could not have ordained him to the priesthood, even if he had passed the Chaplains' examination. What can be done with him? To give him doles, even if the money could be found, would solve no problem, but only postpone the inevitable crisis with its aftermath of scandal. I see no way out of the business. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[184]</hi> [symbol] </p>
         <p>Moved by such reflections I wrote to Gouldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName> suggesting that he should, as a disciplinary method, employ the poor wretch for a month, &amp;, if he did well, extend the period. I offered assistance to meet immediate needs. Chelmsford<persName xml:id="65"></persName> &amp; Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> walked with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to Escomb, &amp; were shown the old church by the Vicar. I stayed in my study, and wrote letters. Craik went off by the 1.27 p.m train, &amp; the Chelmsfords by the 3.55. Before going, Chelmsford had an hours talk with me. He is a very straight simple fellow, and seems to be genuinely a Christian. Would there were more such among our great folks!</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"An English bishop … will have to represent before the world all parties in the church, &amp; to hold himself more or less responsible for them". </p>
         </div>
         <p>This sentence forms Sanday's<persName xml:id="359"></persName> paper on "The positions of Liberal Theology" gives one cause to think. He adds, "An English bishop assumes that all the three regular parties have a right to exist". The difficulty is that while "High Church" and "Low Church" are terms with a fairly constant meaning, the term "Broad Church" is always changing its sense. Are there no limits to the "liberal" revision of the formularies? Must the Bishop be entirely acquiescent in whatever claims are advanced by "Rationalists" and "criticks" ? In short, is there any essential core of Christianity, which must at all hazards be maintained? The latest claims of "Liberal Anglicanism" seem to extend to the cardinal belief as to Christ's "Lordship", confession of which has, since the time of S. Paul, been the constituting fact of Christian discipleship?[sic]  Can these claims be allowed even by the most tolerant bishops?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[185]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Clergy to be considered for appointment as Honorary Canons </hi></p>
         <p>Barker<persName xml:id="3575"></persName>, J. W. Hudson ordained 1893</p>
         <p>Boddy, A. A. ordained 1880. </p>
         <p>Davison<persName xml:id="5289"></persName>, S. ordained 1889. </p>
         <p>[symbol] Knight<persName xml:id="4092"></persName>, P. Y. ordained 1885. </p>
         <p>[symbol] Knowlden<persName xml:id="5439"></persName>, W. J. ordained 1887. </p>
         <p>[symbol] Stephenson<persName xml:id="3883"></persName>, H. S. ordained 1895. Appointed 1922. </p>
         <p>Short, J. ordained 1887. </p>
         <p>Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName>, Lord. ordained 1898. Left the diocese [symbol] 1922. </p>
         <p>Watson<persName xml:id="5392"></persName>, R. ordained 1892. </p>
         <p>Wykes<persName xml:id="4460"></persName>, W. M. ordained 1880 (appointed Sept 26<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1921). </p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Bishop Butler is the one philosopher who has been with me all through my career, from my school days &#8211; and I count it a special place of good fortune that my attention was directed to him in my school days &#8211; until now. <hi rend="bold underline">I would say that Hooker and Butler are the most genuinely British theologians we have had: &amp; they remain so still".</hi></p>
         <p>Sanday, "The Position of Liberal Theology". </p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Sanday</hi> could not have meant by '<hi rend="underline">British</hi>' anything other than "<hi rend="underline">English"</hi>. Certainly neither <hi rend="doubleunderline">Hooker</hi> nor <hi rend="doubleunderline">Butler</hi> can truly be called British in mental type and temper: but both are pre&#8211;eminently and apparently English &#8211; in their caution, their honesty, their dislike of mere theorizing, their moral gravity. </p></body></text></TEI>