<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[4]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I sent Harold<persName xml:id="113"></persName> &#x00A3;50. as a commission on the car. After breakfast Ryle<persName xml:id="325"></persName> left in the car to spend the weekend with Welldon<persName xml:id="114"></persName> at the Deanery. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> returned from Durham in time to take Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and me to Eastgate, where the Vicar, Canon Croudace<persName xml:id="5311"></persName>, had convened the clergy &amp; laity of his rural deanery (Stanhope) to meet me. The weather had changed for the worse during the night, and we motored through the loveliest country in a closed car under a dropping sky. All the clergy of the Deanery were present except Espin<persName xml:id="5315"></persName> of Tow Law, who is abroad. The parish of Stanhope still remains vacant. I was formally welcomed, and then I addressed the clergy by themselves. When I had finished with them, the laity were admitted, and I went through the same process again. Then we had tea in the garden. Rather foolishly the Vicar then asked me to address the members of his parish council, which I did but, of course, very ineffectively. After this silly epilogue I returned home, arriving shortly before 6 p.m. Then I had to prepare notes for my teaching tomorrow, and to clear off some correspondence. Finally I ended the day by reading to <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> &amp; Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> some of Strachey's<persName xml:id="4684"></persName> book on Queen Victoria. He writes amusingly enough, &amp; succeeds in conveying a clear impression. There is an undercurrent of mockery running through all he says about Albert &amp; Victoria, but he cannot conceal the fact that they were admirable persons, of more than the average intelligence. </p></body></text></TEI>