<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[149]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, September 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>In brilliant weather we started from Barton Manor about 10.30 a.m., and motored to Peterborough, where we arrived about 4.30 p.m. Our road lay through Northampton, where we stopped to visit two unusually interesting churches &#8211; S. Sepulchre's, one of the 4 round churches existing in the country, &amp; S. Peter's, a late Norman building with many remarkable features. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> took photographs of both of them. We lunched very pleasantly by the road&#8211;side, &amp; then continued our way, visiting two other churches viz. Islip and Oundle. The latter has a 15<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century eagle&#8211;lectern, which William photographed. After tea I went to Evensong in the cathedral. Burroughs<persName xml:id="3777"></persName> was the canon in residence, &amp; I had some speech with him after service. Although the hour of service was comparatively late &#8211; 5.30 p.m. &#8211; there were but 4 persons present beside the choir &amp; clergy. <hi rend="bold underline">I had much talk with the Dean<persName xml:id="1813"></persName>. He says that the Bishop's<persName xml:id="3933"></persName> Socialistic opinions are not improving his position in the diocese: that his appointment of Donaldson<persName xml:id="2419"></persName> to a residential canonry is generally disapproved: that his suffragan bishop, Lang<persName xml:id="3298"></persName>, who resides at the Palace, exercises a dominating influence over him, &amp; that he has now altogether ceased to be connected with the Evangelicals, who once reckoned him one of their leaders: that by consequence he no longer "sees eye to eye with" Burroughs whom he appointed to a canonry: that in Leicester he has most of all lost ground although it is Socialist centre</hi>.</p></body></text></TEI>