<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[32]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Almighty God, the Giver of all good things, without whose help all labour is ineffectual, and without whose grace all wisdom is folly, grant, I beseech Thee, that in this my undertaking, Thy Holy Spirit may not be withheld from me; but that I may promote Thy glory, and the salvation both of myself and others: grant this, O Lord, for the sake of Jesus Christ. Amen.</p>
         <p>D. S. Johnson, 1709&#8211;1784.</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">There is a telegram from Australia reporting Donaldson's appointment to the Bishoprick of Salisbury</hi>. A letter from Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> agrees with this. He is nine months older than I am.</p>
         <p>I motored into Durham after lunch, and went to the river&#8211;bank in order to see the Regatta. Then I had tea in my room in the Castle, where also (in Hall) I dined. After this I walked to the Town Hall, and distributed the prizes to the successful crews. There was much enthusiasm. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> fetched me in the car, &amp; carried me back to Auckland.</p>
         <p>The rain last night was sufficient to disperse the company gathered in Durham for the open&#8211;air concert organized by the Regatta Committee, but not enough to do any substantial good to the farmers. Tonight there was again a "sound of rain", but beyond a few drops nothing fell, and the drought goes on, adding yet another shadow to the gloom which overspreads the national outlook.</p></body></text></TEI>