<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[29]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, June 19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion at 8 a.m. in the Chapel. Miss Rait and one of the maids fainted, &amp; left during the service. After breakfast Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Hartlepool where I preached to a great congregation including the mayors &amp; corporations of both boroughs. The whole centre of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hilda's church was filled with men. After the service, the congregation standing the while, I unveiled &amp; dedicated a monument to the memory of 19 members of the S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Hilda's Court of the Ancient Order of Foresters. After lunching at the Vicarage, I was escorted by the Boys Brigade in great force to a Wesleyan Chapel where I addressed more than 1000 men on "Christianity and Democracy". The Hartlepool Brotherhood is one of these "unsectarian" associations so characteristic of this age, in which the older forms of association both sacred and secular appear to have lost attractiveness, and new forms of slight texture &amp; ambiguous quality to be replacing them in popular acceptance. Then I had tea with Councillor Parkinson, &amp; met some of the dissenting Ministers. One, a Presbyterian, struck me as an able man: the others, Methodists of various sorts, were of the weedy emotional type general in that denomination. We motored back to Auckland, turning aside to Kirk Merrington in order that Clayton might get out to preach at Evensong. After dinner I filled up the census paper. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishop of London<persName xml:id="166"></persName>, his companion, M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Allen, and his chauffeur, who came for the night from Stockton, where he had been advocating temperance, were included</hi> in my return. The total numbered 17.</p></body></text></TEI>