<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[161]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 14</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"It is better to face the difficulties arising from the varied opinions of the competent than to remain among the worst confusions of unguided thought."</p>
         <p>L. P. Jacks<persName xml:id="320"></persName></p>
         <p>"When once criticism has been started in a certain direction, and he most moderate degree of change suggested, the door is at once opened on the unknown. There is no controlling the reaction of other men's minds on a new idea or a new method: and if other men, employing the very method which we ourselves have introduced, reach, by its means, results which repel us, we have no right to condemn them harshly."</p>
         <p>L. P. Jacks</p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Tyrrell's</hi><persName xml:id="1084"></persName> paper, "The point at issue", printed in the Hibbert Journal Supplement 1909, 'Jesus or Christ?', contains an effective comment on what is essentially Rashdall's<persName xml:id="117"></persName> position: "<hi rend="underline">At most, then, Jesus would be the most Godlike of men. But man owes no adoration, no unqualified self&#8211;surrender even to the most Godlike of men &#8211; only to the absolutely Divine. Between God and Godlike the distance is infinite</hi>."</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>'John, the mystic dreamer, saw the depth and breadth of Divine love and the reality of Divine Sonship in Jesus; the shrewd and sensible Caiaphas did not; and it was impossible to bridge the gulf."</p>
         </div>
         <p>This is a luminous sentence from <hi rend="doubleunderline">James Drummond's</hi><persName xml:id="5348"></persName> article in the same symposium, and it carries far.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[162]</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at a sermon to be preached at the institution of the new Vicar of S. Oswald's, Durham. <hi rend="bold underline">It seemed a fitting occasion on which to make some reference to the Cambridge Essays in Creed&#8211;making</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>But, as soon as the task is actually attempted, its extreme difficulty becomes apparent. </p>
         <p>After lunch everybody went into Durham except Ernest<persName xml:id="2841"></persName> &amp; I. We went for a walk, in the course of which I spoke to him seriously about his Ordination. If it is really his purpose to be ordained, then he ought not to postpone his carrying out of it indefinitely: for (1) such postponement cannot really be reconciled with a genuine belief in a Divine vocation: (2) it is imprudent to wait until his mental &amp; moral muscles have grown stiff, &amp; he is both reluctant to be taught, &amp; incompetent to learn. (3) it is professionally unwise to waste any more time in beginning. The Bishop of Newcastle<persName xml:id="1980"></persName> brought Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName> &amp; Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, &amp; himself stayed to dinner. He is an excellent straight fellow, in whom the improving influence of family responsibilities is very evident. He must keep young, &amp; become sympathetic in order to hold &amp; help his boys: and they more than compensate for the anxieties they cause. They are so many links between him and his people, so many points in which they find him interesting &amp; intelligible. And besides all this, <hi rend="bold underline">they give him, what no man really can dispense with, a continuing motive for exertion, an honourable &amp; cogent reason for desiring to stand well with his neighbours, and a legitimate interest in what he does, &amp; what he possesses, which does not end with himself. I, alas, am solitary, &amp; self&#8211;centred</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>