<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[28]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, June 18</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>After an early lunch I motored to Gateshead, and there made a speech at the opening of a new hall in connexion with the "Poor Children's Holiday Ass<hi rend="bold superscript underline">n</hi> and Rescue Agency". The hall was opened formally by Sir G.B. Hunter, a prosing person with strong inclinations to Prohibitionist views. After the function I returned to Auckland. </p>
         <p>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Espin, the Vicar of Tow Law, who has just returned from the continent, sends me a copy of a notice which he read in the Porch of the Eglise St Sylve, Toulouse, on June 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi>. it runs thus:&#8211;</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>Avis</p>
         <p>Par la modestie de J&#x00E9;sus et de le Vierge Marie nous supplions les femmes qui ont l'honneur et la grace d'&#x00EA;tre chretiennes de ne pas nous affliger par la scandale du d&#x00E9;colletage et d'autres modes inconventantes &#8211; Arri&#x00E8;re toute mode qui met en p&#x00E9;ril la vertu, le plus bel ornament d'une cr&#x00E9;ature humaine &#8211; Nous supplions encore avec instance les m&#x00EA;mes personnes d'avoir un grand respect pour leurs enfants que la bapt&#x00EA;me a rendus les fr&#x00E8;res de anges. Il est si triste de voir ce chers petits habill&#x00E9;s ou plut&#x00F4;t d&#x00E9;shabill&#x00E9;s, contres toutes les r&#x00E9;gles du bon go&ucirc;t et de la biens&#x00E9;ance.</p>
         <p>It would be interesting to know whether this appeal has had any effect on the behaviour of the ladies of Toulouse.</p>
         </div>
         <p>[By the modesty of Jesus and of the Virgin Mary we beg the women who have the honour and the grace to be Christian not to afflict us with the scandal of d&#x00E9;colletage (uncovered cleavage) and of other forms of display. Away from all fashions which place virtue in peril is the most beautiful ornament of a human being. We beg again with respect to the same people to have a great respect for their children whom baptism has made the brothers of the angels. It is so sad to see these dear little ones dressed, or rather undressed, contrary to all the rules of good taste and of propriety.]</p></body></text></TEI>