<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[55]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, July 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="verse">
         <p>"For what, my small philosopher, is Hell?</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">'Tis nothing but full knowledge of the Truth</hi></p>
         <p>When Truth, resisted long, is sworn our foe"</p>
         <p>And calls Eternity to do her right.</p>
         <p>Young<persName xml:id="5329"></persName>, 1684&#8211;1765</p>
         </div>
         <p>I celebrated the Holy Communion in the Chapel at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> was one of the 10 communicants. After breakfast I prepared an address for the Brancepeth cyclists, and wrote a long letter to George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName>. The hill&#8211;side on the further side of the Gaunless started to burn about luncheon time, ignited probably by some carelessly thrown match, or possibly by the unassisted sun, which has blazed with a torrid fierceness.</p>
         <p>I held a confirmation in the chapel at 2.30 p.m., when one male and nine females were confirmed. Some choir&#8211;boys from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Anne's attended, and Lady Thurlow played the organ. The service occupied about 35 minutes.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> accompanied me to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Brancepeth</hi> where an open&#8211;air service had been arranged in the courtyard of the Castle for cyclists. Odd&#8211;fellows, Buffaloes, Scouts <hi rend="underline">et hoc omne genus</hi> [and all of this kind]. The heat was excessive, and many of the company fainted. I preached for nearly half&#8211;an&#8211;hour, and was attentively listened to. Then I took William into the parish church, and showed him Cosin's wood&#8211;work. We had tea in the Rectory, and then returned to Auckland Castle, dropping Clayton on the way home at Willington, where he had undertaken to preach.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Thomas</hi><persName xml:id="5036"></persName>, the railway men's leader, is holding a meeting tonight in Bishop Auckland. </p></body></text></TEI>