<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[56]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>We left the Castle at 7.45 a.m., &amp; motored to the station in time to catch the early train for King's Cross, which brought us there at 2.15 p.m. We went in a taxi together as far as the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> went on with the bags to Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName>: &amp; I went to the Club, then to the hair&#8211;dresser, finally to <placeName xml:id="5">Dean's Yard</placeName>, where the "National Assembly" was beginning its session. Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> introduced finance, &amp; was, on the Archbishop's motion, elected Chairman of the Central Board. <hi rend="italic">He and Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName> dominated everything. The Church of England has shrunk into an </hi><hi rend="italic underline">ecclesiola Coeciliana</hi>. I had tea in the Athenaeum, where I had some talk with Sir Lewis Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName>, &amp;, picking up George Macmillan, drove with him to Elvaston Place. Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> came to dinner, &amp; seemed very bright and well. I walked with her to South Kensington Station, and on the way she told me that she believed that Crauford Inge<persName xml:id="4597"></persName> would become a Roman Catholick, so evident and so strong is his reaction from the contemptuous intellectualism of his distinguished father. This would be a severe blow to Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, and I trust may not happen: but there is evidently little confidence between the boy &amp; his father, &amp; the spectacle of the sons of liberal&#8211;minded parents embracing the narrowest of creeds is too common to make one more instance improbable. Certainly it would give the enemy a mighty handle, if such a "conversion" could be effected. In its way it would be hardly less polemically valuable, &amp; personally humiliating, than the conversion of young Cosin!</p></body></text></TEI>