<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[177]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 23</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>If we accept the command to '<hi rend="underline">prove all things'</hi>, and '<hi rend="underline">hold fast that which is good</hi>'; we must be prepared for the possibility of having to cast aside at last, after the most painful and watchful trial, this or that which we have been accustomed to receive as true. How far the loss if it comes will be other than a semblance of loss, or how far it will be outweighed by unlooked&#8211;for gains, we may not know. <hi rend="underline">Assuredly many will take part in the trial unversed in all the needful discipline, enslaved to inappropriate modes of investigation, ignorant of what patience &amp; watchfulness mean, reckless meanwhile in inflicting wanton injury on all forms of human welfare, except the one or two which circumstances have enabled them to appreciate</hi>. Assuredly, many a weak or hasty soul will be stricken with spiritual palsy, and many a strong soul with sadness, while the work goes on. Yet so it has been in every great crisis of the Church by which the kingdom of God has made a swift advance. If we stop to count the falling or the fallen, no battle will ever be won. </p>
         <p>Hort<persName xml:id="1965"></persName>. "The Way, the Truth, &amp; the Life' p. 88. </p>
         </div>
         <p>This seems very relevant to the methods of the "modern Churchmen", &amp; perhaps, indicates our line of action with respect to them. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[178]</hi></p>
         <p>I worked at an address to the Diocesan Conference: after lunch I motored to Darlington, &amp; met the <persName xml:id="65">Chelmsfords</persName><persName xml:id="1857"></persName>, who came here for a short visit. J. G. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> arrived about tea&#8211;time: I walked in the park with him &amp; C. Sir Henry Craik<persName xml:id="344"></persName> arrived in time for dinner. We had much pleasant conversation at dinner, &amp; afterwards in my room. A telegram arrived in the course of the afternoon announcing the death of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Holburn, the Vicar of St Luke's, Darlington. This facilitates many things. The poor man had become a difficult problem to himself and others. The parish is in my gift, and is stated to be worth &#x00A3;300 yearly with a house. I have also an honorary Canonry to give away. </p>
         <p>"<hi rend="bold underline">I become more of a democrat daily" observed Lord Chelmsford as he marked a crowd of lads kicking about footballs in the Park to the utter destruction of the turf, and he went on to express his admiration of the vast char&#8211;&#x00E0;&#8211;bancs and omnibuses as making every beautiful sport or place of historic interest accessible to the multitude. "On coming back from India</hi> after some absence", he continued, "everybody seems to me better clothed, better off, &amp; far more full of enjoyment". I pointed out that along with this improvement (itself very fallacious) was growing a discontent which deepens daily, and many signs of moral deterioration, which disallowed the old comfortable assurance that education would raise the character of the people. They are far more dishonest, far more unchaste, and far more lawless than they were, though less drunken, less violent and better mannered. </p></body></text></TEI>