<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[44]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A considerable piece of stone from the mullion, of one of the clerestory windows in the chapel, fell, and, as it fell, carried down the nimbus of the angel on the northern wall. What does this ill omen portend? It serves at least to remind me that there are fabrick&#8211;expenses of an unknown amount looming in the future.</p>
         <p>I wrote a "Birthday letter" to Gilbert<persName xml:id="554"></persName>.</p>
         <p>I worked at a sermon for use at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Ignatius, Sunderland. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maurice Gibb<persName xml:id="5326"></persName> and his wife came to lunch. I had some interesting conversation with him on the economic situation. He impresses me as a man of sound judgement &amp; large knowledge of men. I asked him whether the process of ship&#8211;building imposed burdens on his conscience by compelling adoption of, or acquiescence in, procedures which are either unfair or actually dishonest. He assured me that it did not. Unless competitive business &amp; the making of profits be condemned as incompatible with Christianity, there is no reason why a Christian man should not carry on ship&#8211;building with a clean conscience.</p>
         <p>I read aloud the Lecture on Puritanism. It seems to me to contain much truth, but it will certainly please neither Anglicans nor Nonconformists!</p>
         <p>After service in chapel I put together materials for an address tomorrow in unveiling War&#8211;Memorials.</p></body></text></TEI>