<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[7]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>After an early lunch, we i.e. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> and I, motored to Pittington, and there, in the glorious parish church which was crowded, <hi rend="bold underline">I performed the ceremony of marriage between Major Wallace and Penelope Pemberton<persName xml:id="2895"></persName>. </hi>After the service, Ella &amp; Fearne went to the house. I motored to Seaham Hall, where I addressed a numerous company of women, members of the mothers’ union. The brilliance of the weather showed the house and grounds to the greatest advantage. I returned to the Castle, stopping at Ramside on the way in order to pick up the ladies. We were home about 6.30 p.m. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dillon<persName xml:id="3784"></persName>, Lord Londonderry's<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> agent at Seaham, spoke to me rather earnestly this afternoon on the subject of future relations with the miners. He suggested my getting together at Auckland Castle a conference of mine owners and labour leaders to consider the possibility of finding a principle on which the industry might proceed in the future without these rapidly recurring crises. I said &#8211; and here he professed agreement &#8211; that nothing could be done until the present conflict had been brought to an end. After that, it might be worthwhile attempting something, though I could not profess to much hopefulness. The whole question has taken such vast proportions, and become so distressingly non&#8211;local and impersonal since the advent of vague theories running up into a new philosophy and impressing a new morality &#8211; both anti&#8211;Christian &#8211; that the action of a Bishop is hard to fit in. </p></body></text></TEI>