<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[62]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">My impressions of the 'National Assembly</hi><hi rend="bold">'</hi> are mingled. On the one hand there is undoubted purpose &amp; enthusiasm: there is generally a fair treatment even of unpopular speakers: &amp; an evident consciousness that the credit of the Church requires good behaviour. On the other hand, there are clear indications of organized partisanship: a brazen display of 'Catholic' zeal: not a little rudeness to the episcopate: and an undercurrent of clericalism which is disconcerting. The archbishop did not seem very clear in his rulings, but his patience &amp; courtesy never fail. <hi rend="bold underline">The feebleness of the evangelicals can hardly be exaggerate. They are not only a minority, but a minority that is petty in number and contemptible in quality</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The dominance of "the Family" was more than ever apparent. Lord Hugh Cecil<persName xml:id="314"></persName>, Lord Salisbury<persName xml:id="582"></persName>, Lord Wolmer<persName xml:id="1028"></persName>, &amp; Lord Selborne<persName xml:id="311"></persName> were always in charge. The Lawyers, Dibdin<persName xml:id="909"></persName>, Parmoor<persName xml:id="1736"></persName>, Phillimore<persName xml:id="1940"></persName>, Clarke<persName xml:id="4002"></persName>, &amp; Inskip<persName xml:id="4783"></persName> are fairly prominent, &amp; never unanimous. Some of the newly elected clergy made a figure. A vulgar person, from Essex, named Atkinson, half&#8211;buffoon, half attorney, quickly made himself odious. <hi rend="bold underline">The Bishops are evidently unpopular both with clergy &amp; with laity. Why this should be so, it is not easy to see, but the fact is indisputable</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>The conditions under which the business is carried on are not favourable to expedition. About 500 out of the 704 members attended, &amp; the interest was well&#8211;maintained. The suggestion of the public meeting was inevitable, &amp; of course, was unfortunate. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[63]</hi> [symbol]</p>
         <p>Miss Mundella<persName xml:id="2712"></persName> gave a dinner&#8211;party which was entirely successful. It goes without saying that "food &amp; fittings" were ample &amp; excellent. The company was well chosen &#8211; Lord<persName xml:id="65"></persName> &amp; Lady Chelmsford<persName xml:id="1857"></persName>, Lord<persName xml:id="2685"></persName> &amp; Lady Charnwood<persName xml:id="2768"></persName>, Lord<persName xml:id="1246"></persName> &amp; Lady Emmott, Commander &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Paget, Sir Aleck Lawrence<persName xml:id="1907"></persName>, Lady Battersea, Lord Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> &amp; Miss Haldane<persName xml:id="1386"></persName>, &amp; the Dean of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Paul's<persName xml:id="427"></persName>. I took down Lady Chelmsford, &amp; had some pleasant talk with her. Haldane<persName xml:id="956"></persName> was in his best conversational form. <hi rend="bold underline">He said that Parnell<persName xml:id="3549"></persName> once told him that Froude's<persName xml:id="1409"></persName> English in Ireland was the truest version of Irish History. </hi>Both he and his sister were very full of Einstein, and "Relativity". Ralph tells me that his unpleasant colleague, Alexander<persName xml:id="1778"></persName>, is begging hard in Downing Street for the bishoprick of Bath &amp; Wells. This is odious hearing indeed, and may not be true: but Alexander is assuredly one of those men who give the impression that they blow their own trumpets, and grind their own axes! Lady Emmott very kindly presses me to stay with them when occasion took me to London. It would seem that Lady Scarbrough's<persName xml:id="3466"></persName> example is infectious! Sir Aleck Lawrence also pressed us to visit him when we go into this West of England next month. He says that he is digging out a Roman Villa on his property: &amp; that he has a charter conveying the village, &amp; bearing date in the 9<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century. All this sound very interesting.</p>
         <p>Today S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Swithun's day, has been rainless. A breeze has somewhat mitigated the tropical heat: but the temperature are still very exhausting. </p></body></text></TEI>