<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[46]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 4</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>How can the just demand of the workers for a higher standard of life be satisfied without so raising the costs of production as to lead to a paralysis of industry? It is becoming increasingly obvious that failure to find an answer to this dilemma will sooner or later mean revolution.</p>
         <p>Eleanor Rathbone<persName xml:id="5073"></persName></p>
         </div>
         <p>This is the concluding paragraph of an article in the current issue of the Hibbert Review, on "Wages &amp; Family needs" by Miss Rathbone. The proposal to graduate wages according to family needs appears to be so reasonable that one wonders at its late emergence in these interminable economic discussions.</p>
         <p>I motored with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> to Durham, and in the Chapter House instituted Kearney<persName xml:id="3995"></persName> to the parish of New Seaham. Then I went to the County Buildings, &amp; lunched with the High Sheriff, whose health I proposed. After lunch, I sate beside M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Justice Lush<persName xml:id="1274"></persName>, &amp; heard a deplorable looking miner being tried for arson. He was acquitted. Then I returned to Auckland, &amp; immediately set to work on a sermon for tomorrow.</p>
         <p>The papers are filled with detailed accounts of the boxing match between Dempsey<persName xml:id="5327"></persName> &amp; Carpentier<persName xml:id="506"></persName>. The little Frenchman was easily defeated by his big opponent. Vast sums of money passed over this foolish business, &amp; two continents were absorbing it.</p></body></text></TEI>