<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[10]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> went to Newcastle. Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I went through the correspondence: &amp; hardly had we finished before one of the curates of Ferryhill came to see me. He poured out a long &amp; incoherent complaint against his vicar, from which I gathered that Lomax<persName xml:id="5279"></persName>, though in his queer way a saint, is a despotic &amp; rather capricious chief. After lunch, Clayton and I motored to Tow Law where I confirmed 42 persons. The Vicar, Espin, was absent in France. The curate showed me (Espin's) telescope, for he has a distinguished position among astronomers. The house was full of books, the library of old Chancellor Espin<persName xml:id="3552"></persName>, the Vicar's father. This is the first parson's house that I have visited <hi rend="bold underline">in my diocese which displays the signs of scholarly occupation! </hi>From Tow Law <hi rend="bold underline">I motored to Stanley where I confirmed 62 persons. </hi>The church was thronged, the behaviour of the congregation being excellent. Our return journey through Crook was relieved by the beauty of the scenery illuminated by a setting sun shining from a sky heavy with wind driven clouds. Mrs Clayton arrived on a short visit.</p>
         <p>I received a typed report of my conversation with Harold Begbie<persName xml:id="5310"></persName> written in the best Begbie manner, with a request that I would permit its publication. This permission, however, I did not think it prudent to grant, for the report, though containing nothing actually false, did certainly fail to give a true impression of what I said to Begbie.</p></body></text></TEI>