<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[150] </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, September 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The brilliant weather continued, &amp; it was very hot. <hi rend="bold underline">We spent the morning pleasantly enough in viewing the Cathedral under the Dean's guidance. </hi>I asked that William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> might come with us, and he brought his camera.</p>
         <p>The magnificence of the church is even greater than I had thought, but it does not attain to the majesty of Durham. After lunch we started for Carlton&#8211;on&#8211;Trent, but had not gone less than 9 or 10 miles when <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> discovered that she had forgotten her bag!! So we had to go back, and, when it had been recovered, nearly an hour had been lost. We journeyed through Stamford, where we stopped to see two notable Churches, S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's &amp; All Saints; and then went on to Grantham, where we had tea, and visited the famous parish church. I had often admired the great spire as I saw it from the train when travelling to or from London, but I had not realized its splendour until I stood beneath it. The Church is very ample &amp; impressive, though the western windows are filled with execrable glass. I noticed an unusually fine font with an elaborately carved cover. We motored through Newark, about six miles north of which is Carlton&#8211;on&#8211;Trent, where our hostess M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Lawrie resides. We found the house without difficulty, and arrived in confortable time to prepare for dinner. The company at dinner consisted of our hostess, her eldest son Hal, an Eaton boy, his tutor, and an aged clergyman related to the family, who lives in the neighbourhood.</p></body></text></TEI>