<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[51]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, July 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>A young clergyman from S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Chad's who is about to go to Africa as a member of the Universities' Mission, came here bringing the Chalice &amp; Paten which the students had presented to him in order that I might dedicate them. He had wisely armed himself with a short service. This queer little medievalist function having been performed in the chapel, we lunched &amp; then went off to Barnard Castle, where I dedicated a Memorial to the officers, n. c. o's, and men of the 4<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Bt<hi rend="superscript underline">n</hi> D.L.I. This memorial consisted of a tall crucifix of stone set up in the grounds of the Bowes Museum. Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> unveiled it, and made a speech. Then I dedicated it, and it was handed over for custody to the Trustees of the Museum by Brig. Gen. N. Conyers Surtees. The beauty of the place, seen to advantage in the brilliant weather, made the function notable. Everything had been carefully arranged, and went off without hitch. Afterwards we had tea with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watson, and then returned to Auckland, where I wrote to George MacMillan, and sent him the MSS. of the Swedish Lectures in order that he might determine whether publication could be prudently adventured in these evil times.</p>
         <p>I received an affectionate and cheerful letter from George<persName xml:id="3571"></persName> dated June 24<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, and addressed from Port Said.</p>
         <p>Then, after an early dinner, I went off to York to fulfil my promise to the Freemasons by preaching at their centenary service in the Munster. </p></body></text></TEI>