<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[81]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Last year on this day I was "confirmed" in York Minster, and thus became fully charged with the Bishoprick of Durham. Today, therefore, I enter on "the second year of my translation".</p>
         <p>After breakfast I had much conversation with Col. D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hunter, who saw much service as a doctor during the war in Egypt and Serbia. <hi rend="italic">His admiration for the Serbs is only equalled by his contempt for the Greeks. He said that it was a current saying in Serbia, that if a Serb woman gave birth to a child whose father was a Turk, it was usual to strangle the babe, whereas, in the like circumstances, a Bulgar woman would bring the child up. The saying expresses the Serbian boast of purity of blood. Such independence &amp; courage as were found among the Greeks came from the islands: the Greeks of the mainland were effete. Our host joined us, and our talk turned on to home politics. I was struck by the distrust of L.G. which found expression, and the inability to suggest a possible alternative as Prime Minister.</hi></p>
         <p>After an early lunch we all motored to Pontesbury where the wedding had been arranged. There I united in wedlock Nicholas Fielden and Noel Swire. The large church was crowded, and the service proceeded well enough, though the nagging incompetence of the local clergy impressed me. I made a brief oration to the people instead of the appointed address. Afterwards we proceeded to the reception in the bride's house. A very large company came together, and everything appeared to proceed satisfactorily.</p></body></text></TEI>