<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[15]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, June 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The Editor of the "Central Council for Economic Information", <hi rend="italic bold underline">M</hi><hi rend="i bold superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="italic bold underline"> Gerard Fiennes<persName xml:id="5316"></persName>, wrote to request me [to] "recast" Harold Begbie's<persName xml:id="5310"></persName> precious "interview" into a signed article for publication broadcast</hi><hi rend="i bold">. </hi><hi rend="italic">I replied thus:&#8211;</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p><hi rend="italic">Dear Sir,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">I am obliged to you for your letter. The subject raised in my conversation with M</hi><hi rend="i sup u">r</hi><hi rend="italic"> Begbie is too large &amp; complex for useful handling in an article, and phrases however telling are apt to "darken counsel" rather than point the way of escape. Besides, if, as I hope will be the case, the miners vote for acceptance of the terms offered them, it is important to avoid the appearance of doing what moralists are always too apt to do, &#8211; </hi><hi rend="italic underline">rubbing it in</hi><hi rend="italic">: a procedure the least helpful in the world, and, perhaps, the most exasperating. For the present I incline to think that the less said the better.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Believe me, Yours v. faithfully,</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">Herbert Dunelm:</hi></p>
         </div>
         <p>These vague declarations about the moral causes of economic confusion, in which Harold Begbie and all the Christian Socialists abound, leave me cold: for they never disclose any clear grasp of the essential distinctiveness of the moral and the economic spheres. <hi rend="underline">In so far as moral factors enter into the economic process</hi> an unsound state of morale will be reflected in economic confusion: but all the moral soundness conceivable can effect nothing in that large area where economics are untouched by morals.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[16]</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The whole mechanism of society rests on confidence: it permeates all life, like the air we breathe: and its services are apt to be taken for granted and ignored, like those of fresh air, until attention is forcibly attracted by their failure. When confidence is shaken by a rumour of war or of civil commotion, or of disturbing financial legislation, or of extensive frauds or rash trading by important firms, then business life is stifled: &amp; men yearn for the wholesome atmosphere that is associated with the general re&#8211;establishment of confidence."</p>
         <p>Marshall<persName xml:id="5297"></persName>. "Industry &amp; Trade" p. 165.</p>
         </div>
         <p>I frittered away the whole morning in writing letters, making notes for tomorrow's speech, and having an interview with the Churchwarden of Witton&#8211;le&#8211;Weir respecting that parish, where the old antiquary D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Hodgson<persName xml:id="5317"></persName> at the age of 94 begins to meditate on the advisableness of resigning the benefice! The difficulties are, perhaps, insurmountable, for he has nothing to live on, and nowhere to live in!</p>
         <p>I spent the afternoon in trying to master the motor lawn&#8211;mower, and so far succeeded with William's<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> help to break the chain!! He mended it, &amp; I completed the mowing of one of the lawns. It is a truly lamentable thing to be so ignorant of mechanics, and so helpless with machines as I am!</p>
         <p>The weather, though apparently worsening, continues rainless, and the cry of the farmers waxes louder. Everything is getting to look very parched.</p></body></text></TEI>