<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[23]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"South Shields is celebrated as being the port in which the life&#8211;boat was originated, the first boat placed here designed and built by Henry Greathead of South Shields being successfully used for the first time January 30<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi>, 1790 in the rescue of some mariners who were wrecked in the offing.</p>
         <p>Kelly's Directory, 1921. p. 345</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Mayor, Aldermen &amp; Burgesses of the County Borough of South Shields in the address of welcome which they are to address to me tonight, refer to the foundation of the town, by the Prior &amp; Convent of Durham in 1245, and the earlier foundation of a "chapel &amp; nunnery" by "the Princess Hild", in 648. These references have a certain interest. At least they indicate a desire to escape from the vulgar activities of the present time.</p>
         <p>A correspondent, G. W. K. Grange, who, I conjecture, must be an assistant master at Durham School, and also was present when I collated Budworth<persName xml:id="2692"></persName> to his canonry on Tuesday, appears to be a man of scrupulous conscience and a facile pen &#8211; a combination familiar enough in the history of sectarianism. He sends me a <hi rend="bold underline">long letter on the subject of the oaths &amp; subscriptions which offend his conscience</hi>. He is uncertain as to their moral legitimacy in view of Christ's teachings in the Sermon on the Mount, and very sure of their mischievous effects in the circumstances which now obtain. I replied in the following terms:&#8211;</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[24] </hi>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Grange,</p>
         <p>Your interesting letter merits a far more careful and complete consideration than I have time to give it just now. </p>
         <p>There are really two distinct questions, one of the principle, Are oaths permissible to Christians in view of our Saviour's Teaching in the Sermon on the Mount? the other of expediency, Are these particular oaths advisable here and now? Obviously the second question only arises when the first has been answered in the affirmative.</p>
         <p>Apart from a simple literalism which could not be reasonably or systematically applied to the Gospels, I do not suppose any one would now press the Words of Christ as a prohibition of oaths imposed by lawful authority. The XXXIX<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> Article "Of a Christian Man's Oath" seems to me to state the truth very admirably. </p>
         <p>On the question of expediency there is more room for difference of opinion. I have always held that "subscription" should be limited as far as possible and always conditioned by a reasonable latitude of interpretation; but I cannot see my way to advocate an abolition of all <hi rend="bold underline">subscription: and I am fully persuaded that,</hi> when fairly and reasonably interpreted, the <hi rend="bold underline">pledges as to belief &amp; behaviour</hi> legally required from an English clergyman are not unfair, still less, intolerable. The great risk, perhaps the greatest, which threatens "the rising generation" is a disordered <hi rend="bold">[25] </hi>individualism which not only ignores the claims of others, but also forgets the true sources of all that explains and consecrates individuality.</p>
         <p>With kind regards, Yours sincerely,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm.</p>
         </div>
         <p>The Prime Minister is reported to have said some sharp, but not undeserved, things about the interference of clergymen in economic disputes, pointing his observations by reference to the foolish Discussion of the Coal Strike in the Upper House of Convocation. <hi rend="underline">The Daily News</hi> scenting "copy" sends me a telegram, with 48 words prepaid, thus "Will you kindly wire freely your view prime minister's statement Churches and Politics". But I ignored the editorial request!</p>
         <p><hi rend="underline">Then Harold Begbie<persName xml:id="5310"></persName> writes to "implore" me to "reconsider my decision" not to let him publish his preposterous "interview" with me!</hi></p>
         <p>Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> and I motored to Sunderland, where we had tea with Canon Goldsmith<persName xml:id="1780"></persName>, and I interviewed Petrie<persName xml:id="5351"></persName>, Pater, &amp; Jackson. We then went on to South Shields, where I was presented with an address from the Mayor &amp; Corporation at the Town Hall. After this little function, we walked in procession through the streets to S<hi rend="bold superscript underline">t</hi> Thomas's Church, where I dedicated a Memorial Window to the men of the parish, who had fallen in the War. There was a large congregation. After the service I interviewed an aggrieved parishioner in the Vestry. Then we motored back to the Castle, arriving about 10 p.m.</p></body></text></TEI>