<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[84]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, July 30</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The sun shines again brilliantly, and there is the promise of great heat. I am sorry to leave this pleasant house. <hi rend="bold">[</hi>William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> gave me his new address, which I note here to make sure that it is not forgotten ̶  M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> William Badham, 3 Cornwall Street, White Cross, Hereford.<hi rend="bold">]</hi> We left the Castle about noon &amp; motored to Worcester, where we lunched with the Dean<persName xml:id="1814"></persName>, &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Moor Ede. He showed me with legitimate pride the painted memorial windows in the Cloisters. They present in a carefully considered scheme the connected history of Christianity in this part of England. He said that he had taken the idea from the cloisters of Hereford. Nearly half the scheme has been completed already. After lunch we continued our journey as far as Ledbury, where we stopped to take tea with Canon<persName xml:id="3619"></persName> and M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Bannister at their Hospital. Then we went on to Hereford where we were received at the Palace by M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Linton Smith, the Bishop<persName xml:id="4851"></persName> being absent in Shropshire. There was some difficulty in getting the car into the garage, on account of its length. The dean &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Waterfield<persName xml:id="5128"></persName> came to dinner. I had much pleasant talk with him. He told me the rather squalid story of the quarrel about the War Memorial. It would seem plain that the memorial Committee have treated Car&#x00F6;e<persName xml:id="648"></persName> with rudeness &amp; injustice, but he did not commend his case by a truculent letter, &amp; in standing out for his full charge, he may be defeating himself. Harold Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> writes a friendly letter accepting my suggestion to write for the <hi rend="underline">Edinburgh</hi> in January.</p></body></text></TEI>