<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[98]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 10</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"Calling Socrates to an argument is calling cavalry into an open plain." </p>
         <p>^[Greek verse]^ (p. 155. Loeb, ed.) </p>
         </div>
         <p>This would appear to be the Greek equivalent of the slang expression, "asking for trouble", or the more respectable phrase "riding for a fall". I came across it as I read Plato's dialogue 'Theoetetus' in bed. This dialogue is full of good things, though the main argument draws to no conclusion.</p>
         <p>I worked at the Preface all the morning and wrote a good deal which will probably go to the w.p.b.!</p>
         <p>After lunch we all motored to Cleeve Abbey, which the local guide&#8211;book calls, not perhaps excessively, 'the ecclesiastical gem of the district'. It was a house of Cistercian monks founded in 1188, &amp; dedicated to 'Our Blessed Lady of the Cliff[']. Hooper, one of the Marian martyrs, was one of the 17 brethren who were resident at the dissolution. Over the 13<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century Gate house is the inscription '<hi rend="underline">Porta patens esto. Nulli clauderis honesto'</hi> [Gates be open. To nothing honest be obstructive]. The church has been totally ruined, but much of the conventual building has survived. The Refectory (early XVI<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century) is a beautiful building, with a roof of Spanish chestnut very richly carved. The whole place gave forth a rare impression of religious repose. We had tea in the open, and then returned to Minehead. Then I wrote to Carissima<persName xml:id="76"></persName>, and packed up my books and papers for departure tomorrow.</p>
         <p>I think the weather has definitely broken.</p></body></text></TEI>