<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[78]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, July 25</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>The day was not very promising when we started for our holiday, &amp; the final preparations for departure were more than commonly exasperating. The luggage was with difficulty bound on to the car, some surprising bills were "sprung on" me at the last moment, and, after waiting for half an hour in the open street for one of the car windows, which had had its glass cracked, we had finally to come away without it, as the motor&#8211;repairers were short of materials! We travelled as far as Sawley Hall with the motor closed on account of the rain threatening but never falling; &amp; thus we failed to see to real advantage some very beautiful scenery. Sir John<persName xml:id="2069"></persName>, &amp; Lady Baron [Barran], received us with kindness, &amp; entertained us at an excellent lunch. We had the car opened, and as far as Skipton enjoyed the loveliest moorland views. Here we had tea (7/&#8211;), and then unwisely we decided to take what appeared the directer route to Rode Hall. We speedily entered on a continuing series of manufacturing towns, unlovely and crowded, which were linked together by roads seamed with tram lines. Burnley, Rochdale, Oldham, Stockton &#8211; a hideous succession. We ran out of petrol about 13 miles from Congleton and bought 6 tins (35/6) on the road. Then we had to close the car on account of the rain; finally we reached our destination at 9.15 p.m. and were warmly welcomed by our friends, Sir Philip<persName xml:id="1427"></persName> &amp; Lady Baker&#8211;Wilbraham<persName xml:id="1428"></persName>. The conversation turning on the "National Assembly", I allowed myself in a freedom of adverse comment which was extremely foolish.</p></body></text></TEI>