<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[163]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, September 15</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p> A fine day, but rather cold. At 11 a.m. I left the Castle, taking with me in the motor Ralph<persName xml:id="427"></persName>, Kitty<persName xml:id="1209"></persName>, Dorothy<persName xml:id="950"></persName> &amp; her two girls. The last we deposited at Edmundbyers, while we went on to Muggleswick, where we were hospitably entertained at lunch by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Ritson<persName xml:id="3822"></persName>. He had assembled his sons &amp; their wives, so that the party at luncheon numbered no less than 14. After lunch we all motored to Blanchland in order to see the country. Certainly the views were magnificent. Dorothy, though fresh from Fairlie where certainly the prospects are amazingly beautiful, was loud in admiration. We returned to Edmundbyers for tea: &amp; then all went back to Auckland in time for me to take the chair at a lecture on "Polar Geography" by Professor Lyde<persName xml:id="5349"></persName>. There was a large audience, &amp; a very attentive one, but I thought the lecture ill&#8211;connected &amp; dogmatic.</p>
         <p><hi rend="italic">A statement appears in the "Times" announcing the death of Neville Talbot's<persName xml:id="2023"></persName> wife shortly after she had given birth to a son. This is truly sad. I am very sorry for him, for he was evidently devoted to his wife.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="italic bold underline">I read an interesting article, "In memory of Scott" by Archibald Macmechan. It appears in "The Dalhousie Review" for July 1921. He comments on the decline in Scott's popularity. "Booksellers will not even stock his works</hi><hi rend="i bold">."</hi> <hi rend="italic">This is both significant and melancholy. I have made William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> read most of the novels; &amp; I think he </hi><hi rend="italic underline">was</hi><hi rend="italic"> faintly interested in a few of them!</hi></p></body></text></TEI>