<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[47]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, July 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from two laymen in Sunderland, interceding for the woeful Dowson, who is now, I doubt not, coming into full view of the disaster which awaits him. It is a miserable business, but I cannot see my way to recede from the position which I have taken up. If I were to yield to my compassionate sentiments, and ordain him to the priest&#8211;hood, I am as certain as in such cases it is possible to be that he would quickly get again into debt, and very probably drift into mendicancy, mendacity, and even actual fraud. Had he passed his examination, I should have been gravely embarrassed, for his record is not one that could justify ordination; but he failed, and I registered the failure as final. Then, there arises the further question, whether any, and if so what, responsibility ought a Bishop to admit in the case of a rejected candidate for Priest's Orders? It is evident that no man, not even a Bishop, can be held to measures of responsibility beyond his powers; and most certainly I cannot afford to pension rejected Ordination candidates. Nor, indeed, can I give temporary assistance, which could not be on a scale adequate to be effectively helpful, and would almost certainly have the consequence of encouraging the dolorous optimism of the case&#8211;hardened mendicant. It remains, therefore, that literally and finally I "wash my hands" of this miserable creature, knowing full well that the scandal of his destitution lies ahead of me, and, as I must needs think, at no great distance of time. </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[48]</hi></p>
         <p>I finished the sermon for the Mother's Union, and then motored into Durham &amp; delivered it to an immense assembly of women, which filled the Cathedral. I exerted myself to the utmost, but even so, I doubt whether my voice carried to the end of the transept, to the space behind the Font, and to the Chancel, where many of the company were placed. It was certainly an impressive &amp; encouraging service, &amp; reflected much credit on those who organised it. Before the service I lunched with M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Watkins<persName xml:id="2762"></persName>, and afterward I had tea with her. The Archdeacon<persName xml:id="590"></persName> was absent in London. </p>
         <p>I called at the Castle, and <hi rend="doubleunderline">fetched the Justice &amp; Lady Lush</hi>, in order to carry them out to Auckland, &amp; show them the last remaining possession of the Palatine Bishop. They professed themselves greatly interested in all they were shown. Indeed I can well believe that the impression made by a first view of Auckland Caste is great. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> motored them back to Durham. George MacMillan asks me to send him the MS. in order that he may "go carefully into the matter and see what number of copies, &amp; at what price we could hope to sell, and then we can come to a decision". It is evident that he is not exactly keen to add another to the series of books which he has published for me without financial advantage. I have no luck in publication, for reasons which I can guess at. I have no party whose interest &amp; prestige are served by what I write!</p></body></text></TEI>