<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[76]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, July 22</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Cox<persName xml:id="2131"></persName> writes to ask me to write an article on the lines of my speech in the National Assembly for the October issue of the Edinburgh. I replied that I was too tired to write now, but that I would, if he wished, write for the January issue.</hi></p>
         <p>I wrote to <hi rend="doubleunderline">Welldon</hi><persName xml:id="114"></persName> accepting his invitation to preach at the Commemoration Service on Jan. 27<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> 1922, and suggesting that the date should be shifted to the summer, perhaps to the last Sunday in term, when it might play the part of Commem. Sunday at Oxford.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Major Archibald McGill</hi>, who is the Baptist Minister here, called to ask me to back up an effort to raise funds for an University in Shantung. I was very civil, but would not do what he wanted. I told him there were other &amp; more urgent objects for which I had to beg.</p>
         <p>I travelled to Durham by train, and presided at a meeting of the Diocesan Board of Education, convened to consider the case of Bede College which, its Principal holds, is deeply injured by the proposed arrangement for educating school teachers, which the academic authorities are making with the Durham County Council. On my return to Bishop Auckland, I was met by Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> with a hired car, wherein I was motored to Tow Law. Here I had tea with Espin, the eccentric Vicar, and then dedicated War&#8211;memorials in the parish Church. We motored back to the Castle through a fairly heavy rain, arriving about 9 p.m. M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Dennistoun<persName xml:id="4890"></persName> and her daughter had arrived in their motor <hi rend="underline">en route</hi> for Scotland.</p></body></text></TEI>