<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Thursday, June 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>My guests went with <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> on an expedition to Escombe while I remained at home, &amp; did my correspondence with Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName>. At noon a weird person, Pratt, came to see me. He is the curate of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t </hi>John's, Sunderland, &amp; has quarrelled with the Vicar. After lunch, Clayton and I motored to Heworth, where we had tea with Major &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> English. He is the agent of the local mines, &amp; evidently a very intelligent man. He motored us round the parish before the Confirmation. I confirmed 80 persons, of whom only 19 were males. During the laying on of hands a Litany of the Holy Ghost was sung softly with choir and congregation. We returned to the Castle after service arriving about 9.30 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove at a great pace. <hi rend="bold underline">Lord Thurlow<persName xml:id="5272"></persName> and his wife came to dinner, and I joined them in the dressing room later. She told me that she had bought coals from miners at 4/&#8211; a bag. I told her that beyond question she had been a receiver of stolen goods, for the coal thus purchased had almost certainly been stolen from the Park! It must amuse the miners to find themselves warned by the police, admonished by the bishop, and threatened with prosecution by the Eccl. Commission for digging coal which the Rector of the parish buys readily! But there is no end to the paradoxes bred of a coal strike. The strikers begged Major English to persuade the Owners to advance the Union &#x00A3;1000 in order that they might the better continue the strike! It is this ridiculous mingle&#8211;mangle that saves us from revolution</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>