<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[112]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>After breakfast we packed, bade farewell to the Dean and his family, and went off <hi rend="bold underline">to Hallshanger, near Ashburton, where we had been arranged to spend the week&#8211;end with M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi> <hi rend="bold underline">T. R. Buchanan</hi><persName xml:id="977"></persName>. The weather was fine and warm: our route lay through charming country. We turned aside from the main road in order to visit Boevey Tracey, a picturesque village with a fine parish church, distinguished by an unusually pleasant rood&#8211;screen. We continued the journey through Ilsington, where we saw another fine church, also adorned with a rood&#8211;screen. Here the parson was sufficiently disclosed by the appearance of the Church to be a "spike". He was (or at least a clergyman whom we assumed to be the parson) in the churchyard, and had some avid speech with us as we passed out. We continued our way over the moor by a very indifferent road to Hallshanger, where we arrived in good time for lunch. In the afternoon, Commander Paget<persName xml:id="5339"></persName> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Paget<persName xml:id="5340"></persName>, who are also M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Buchanan's guests, motored with us to Sharpham, where M &amp; M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Parker reside. This house with its ample and beautiful grounds commands the noblest prospects of the Dart valley. We stopped at Totnes, &amp; viewed the very magnificent parish church. The tower is a conspicuous object, &amp; the coloured stone&#8211;screen is notable even in a county so full of chancel screens. The main street of Totnes is a quaintly interesting object, very narrow &amp; steep, yet constituting the main road between London and Cornwall. The beauty of the evening added to that of the country made the drive very agreeable. </p></body></text></TEI>