<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[164]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, September 16</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Ralph's<persName xml:id="427"></persName> impression of the Cambridge Conference, after reading the "official report" was unfavourable</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>"It leaves an ill impression on one's mind", he said, "the papers contradict one another". He pointed out the unpleasant suggestion of the page of advertisements headed "Books for modern churchmen", and containing a series of admittedly anti&#8211;Christian publications viz: the works of J. M. Robertson<persName xml:id="5350"></persName>, &amp; others of that type. After prayers, Ralph and I strolled round the garden. <hi rend="bold underline">He asked me what I thought was the duty of those members of the Churchmen's Union, like himself, who disapproved of the pronouncements made at the Conference. I said that I thought they should make their position clear, by publicly dissociating themselves from what had been said. He told me that he had projected a volume to be called "Confessio Fidei", in which he would state his own belief, but that this w</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">d</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> not appear before next year</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi></p>
         <p>Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName> &amp; his wife came to lunch: also M<hi rend="superscript underline">rs</hi> Burkitt<persName xml:id="573"></persName> &amp; Miles<persName xml:id="1863"></persName>. I motored into Durham, and there presided at a meeting of the High Sheriff's Fund. Then I went to the Castle, and had interviews with two persons &#8211; King and Connor. After tea with them in my rooms, I returned to Auckland. <hi rend="bold underline">Ralph had some more talk with me about the Cambridge Conference. He is evidently perturbed, and meditating some pronouncement. I think it could do nothing but good, if he would speak out; at least it would open the eyes of those inflated "Liberals", and make them see the risks of their action.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The "Yorkshire Post" contains</hi> a lengthy communication "From the <hi rend="bold underline">Official Press Bureau of the Chur</hi>ch of England". We are getting on!</p></body></text></TEI>