<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[40]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 29</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>S. Peter's Day &#8211; the dedication day of my great chapel &#8211; should be observed with magnificence and general joy, commemorating the almost miraculous recovery of Church and monarchy after the catastrophe of the Great Rebellion. Bishop Cosin's<persName xml:id="2820"></persName> reflections must have been mingled, when he called to mind his whole course in Durham since his early conflicts with old Prebendary Smart<persName xml:id="5325"></persName>, and his triumphant consecration of Pudsey's re&#8211;constructed Hall.</p>
         <p>I went to the Hair&#8211;dresser, and was trimmed. Then I walked to Westminster, and had an interview with Lea respecting income&#8211;tax! I lunched at the Athenaeum<orgName xml:id="89"></orgName>, and then went into the City, and dedicated a Tablet to the memory of members of the Accountants' department of the General Post office. M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Kellaway unveiled the tablet, &amp; made a short speech. Then I picked up my bags at 21 Park Lane, and went to King's Cross, where I caught the 5.40 p.m. express. My compagnon de voyage was a well&#8211;built man of about 30&#8211;35, who (as he told me) had entered the War as a private in 1914, and come out of it unscathed as a Colonel in 1918. He was a great friend of Simon<persName xml:id="1008"></persName>, &amp; evidently a dissenter. We reached Darlington a few minutes past 11 p.m. There I was met by William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> &amp; James, &amp; was motored to the Castle, arriving shortly before midnight. </p>
         <p>I gave a guinea to the presentation to Miss Walpole, the Lady Assistant Librarian, who is going to Canada as Sec. to B. Byng.</p></body></text></TEI>