<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[101]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, August 13</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I received a letter from Ramsay, whom I ordained at Hereford. He aspires to come into the diocese of Durham as an assistant curate of Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring. I wrote to him approving the proposal. Also, I wrote to Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName>. Then I resumed work on the Preface, and brought it to some sort of an end.</p>
         <p>After lunch we all motored to Dyrham house, a fine 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century mansion full of fine pictures and tapestries. The owner, M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Blathwayte, descended from an official of William III's, and obligingly shewed us his possessions. In the library was a report, illustrated by maps, of William's progress from his landing up to London, evidently the work of a staff officer, written in French. We had tea very comfortably, &amp; then went on to Hamwell House, belonging to the Whittington family, but now leased by M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Maugham. This is a 17<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century house, much altered. It is beautifully situated on a hill&#8211;side commanding a wide prospect. A telescope placed on the terrace gave an excellent view of the White Horse of Westbury. In the ground attached to the house is an ancient wishing well, of which the water is used for drinking. This house before the Reformation was one of the possessions of Bath Abbey. A certain M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Pitsani (?) arrived to stay the night. He is a British subject of French descent and comes from Mauritius. His views are very imperialistic, and he adopts with ardour the French policy towards Germany. We had a close, and almost heated discussion on the latter around the fire after dinner, everybody being properly confirmed in his own opinion! He is said to be a devout Papist.</p></body></text></TEI>