<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[38]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, 27</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> June, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>I motored to Durham, and had a luncheon party in my room. Judge Moore<persName xml:id="5322"></persName>, Garvin<persName xml:id="5323"></persName> the Editor of the Observer, Cruickshank<persName xml:id="1898"></persName>, Bayley<persName xml:id="2806"></persName> and Clayton<persName xml:id="5074"></persName> were my guests. Garvin was of course the Mercury, or chief speaker of the party. Then I presided at a meeting of the Diocesan Church Building and Extension Board: <hi rend="underline">then I had an interview with M</hi><hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi><hi rend="underline"> Strophair, the curate of Sunderland Parish Church. </hi>Then I returned to Auckland, bringing with me the Judge, Garvin, his daughter, &amp; Clayton. After tea, I shewed them Castle, &amp; then sent them home in the motor.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Garvin is a great talker, and he talks as he writes, with rapid generalisation and a taking suggestion of omniscience</hi>. He knows many people, as is the custom with journalists, but whether he is so frankly admitted to the counsels of the great as his talk appears to imply, may perhaps be fairly doubted. I found him interesting and interested.</p>
         <p><hi rend="doubleunderline">Knight</hi><persName xml:id="62"></persName> arrived after dinner. He is cheerful, pleased by the demonstrations of affection which have been evoked in Bridstow by his departure, and prepared to attack his new task with a good courage.</p>
         <p>I lent to Judge Moore my copy of 'Sylvestra': and I note the fact here in order to protect myself against that forgetfulness in the lender which facilitates the dishonesty of the borrower of books!</p></body></text></TEI>