<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, June 1</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>"The employment of children at an excessively early age was common under the domestic system: and, though they were for the greater part under the protection of their parents, yet on the whole the evidence seems to show that they were often treated by their parents more cruelly than the great majority of children in the factories were."</p>
         <p>Marshall, "Industry &amp; Trade", p.73. </p>
         </div>
         <p>It would appear, therefore, that the vehement denunciation of Industrialisation based on the shocking oppression of children which it induced, were founded upon an error. The truth is less serviceable for perorations than the lie! </p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">I motored in to Durham, &amp; confirmed in the Cathedral 188 candidates. The service began at 4.15 p.m. and ended at 5.30 p.m. After tea with the Bishop of Jarrow<persName xml:id="2785"></persName>, I returned to the Castle. The Deans of Westminster and York together with M</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rs</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> Norris &amp; Miss Norris arrived during the afternoon. </hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">The Superintendent of Police reports that the miners are stealing coal in the Park, &amp; recommends prosecution. But, as the misdemeanour takes place in the outer Park, I suppose the Ecclesiastical Commissioners would be the right persons to prosecute. Wilson<persName xml:id="2748"></persName> undertook to write to them on the matter.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>