<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[138]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, August 31</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">st</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Another gloriously fine day. After breakfast <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I walked into Shanklin, and tried (but vainly) to see <hi rend="doubleunderline">Monty Bere</hi><persName xml:id="74"></persName> &amp; his wife. His large vicarage is let to a number of tourists, while he &amp; his wife live in comfortless fashion in a corner. He is said to be a very good parish priest, but a very poor preacher &#8211; a reversal of the familiar qualities. His use of slang phrases in the pulpit is resented by those (a minority of the congregation) who can hear his sermons. Moreover he worries the people by little ceremonial egotisms, which are equally illegal and irrational! Yet he is in private life the most attractive of men. How strange men are! We walked on to the pier, &amp; viewed the mixed bathing which looks much more decent in the water than it does in the picture papers! We returned to the house by way of "The Chine", a picturesque ravine running up almost to our door.</p>
         <p>After lunch we motored to Brading, &amp; visited the parish church, which is comparatively large &amp; fine; then we visited Yaverland, &amp; looked at the very interesting Norman church. There is a fine Jacobean mansion hard by, of which we admired the exterior. We called on George Dennistoun<persName xml:id="3560"></persName> &amp; his wife. There came to tea a pleasant old paralyzed clergymen, <hi rend="doubleunderline">Canon Rees</hi>, who showed with pride a photograph of his son conversing as a prisoner with his captor, the Kaiser, in May 1918.</p>
         <p>Before dinner the Bishop and I walked for an hour, inquiring <hi rend="underline">en route</hi> after <hi rend="doubleunderline">Page Roberts</hi>, who is reported better.</p></body></text></TEI>