<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[49]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, July 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 2021.</hi></p>
         <p>[symbol]</p>
         <p>The Rev. John Middleton received from me the following answer, which will, perhaps, settle sufficiently, and confirm him in his worst fears for the world!</p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear Sir,</p>
         <p>I am obliged to you for your letter, and I can sympathise with the point of view which it discloses. If I were a Scotchman, I should find it very difficult to determine my course, for my desire to unite the Presbyterian churches would be so strong that I doubt whether any considerations short of cardinal belief (which could not enter) would be strong enough to carry me into an open opposition to the Bill.</p>
         <p> As an Englishman I should be reluctant to interfere in a purely Scottish question. As a Bishop I should deem it improper to intervene in the domestic concerns of a Presbyterian Church. As a Christian I must needs be in accord with the avowed purpose of a Bill for uniting separated branches of the Christian Church. On all accounts, I could not think it right, or seemly, or edifying, to oppose in the House of Lords a Scottish measure so weightily supported, with the object of which I must be in such hearty agreement.<note xml:id="534" n="1"></note></p>
         <p>Believe me.</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully,</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p>It is surely an odd situation that an English Bishop should be appealed to in order to defeat the Scottish "high&#8211;fliers"!</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[50]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName> accompanied me as far as Durham, &amp; then went on to South Shields for a Sale of Work, which Ella had undertaken to open. I presided at a meeting of the Diocesan Conference at 12 noon. There was an evident desire to get Divorce discussed at the meeting in October. I said that it seemed to me superfluous to discuss that subject as the conclusion was known in advance. The discussion would only be another case of shouting "Great is Diana of the Ephesians". Finally, we decided to have 3 subjects in the following order 1. The new paid secretary for the Finance Brd. 2. The Reform of the Courts. 3. The Matrimonial Causes Bill. </p>
         <p>I lunched with the Lillingstone<persName xml:id="3262"></persName>, and then, at 2.30 p.m., presided over a meeting of the Board of Finance. Little<persName xml:id="5330"></persName>, vicar of Whickham, was the principal speaker, &amp; there was a brisk discussion, on the hoary &amp; boring subject of 'Dilapidations'. I had tea twice over; first with the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>, and next with the Archdeacon. Then after kicking my heels for about half an hour, William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> appeared with the car, I rejoined the ladies, &amp; we all motored back to Auckland arriving about 6.30 p.m.</p>
         <p>Rain fell quitely, but almost continuously all day, not indeed at all heavily at any time, but, bringing a welcome refreshment to the parched land.</p>
         <p>I learned that D<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Symonds<persName xml:id="1567"></persName>, the Dean of Christ Church Cathedral in Montreal has died recently. He shewed me kindness when I was in Canada, &amp; was a brave &amp; liberally&#8211;minded man.</p></body></text></TEI>