<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[198]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Monday, October 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O God, there is mercy with Thee: therefore shalt Thou be feared.</p>
         <p>Shew Thou me the way that I should walk in, for I lift up my soul unto Thee.</p>
         </div>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Fearne<persName xml:id="3805"></persName>, &amp; Lucy arrived in the car with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> at 10 a.m. Before leaving Walworth Castle, I showed William the astonishing chestnuts. We motored to Darlington, where I had an interview with Canon Cosgrave<persName xml:id="5313"></persName>, &amp; dropped the ladies. William motored me back to Auckland.</p>
         <p>M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Frank Blackburn, the Deputy Divisional Controller, Northern Division, lunched with me <hi rend="underline">t&#x00EA;te&#8211;&#x00E0;&#8211;t&#x00EA;te</hi>. He had prepared an elaborate set of figures of unemployment. The situation is far worse than I had supposed, and the winter's outlook is most unpromising. After he had departed, I walked into the Park, &amp; finding a group of about a score of young pitmen, sitting in a circle on the grass, I got into talk with them, and eventually took them for a walk round the castle. They seemed to be both interested and impressed.</p>
         <p>My letter for W. must deal with (&#x3B1;) citizenship (&#x3B2;) marriage (&#x3B3;) friendship (&#x3B4;) religion (&#x3B5;) amusements.</p>
         <p>I wrote a belated letter of thanks to Linetta<persName xml:id="1255"></persName> for her wonderful criticism of Guillaume's article. Also, I wrote to thank Lord Durham<persName xml:id="3462"></persName> for a haunch of venison: &amp; to Londonderry<persName xml:id="2818"></persName> in answer to an inquiry about patronage. I sent the copy of my Congress Sermon, which Fearne made during my absence, to the <hi rend="underline">Guardian</hi>, asking that it might be sent on to the Congress Secretary.</p></body></text></TEI>