<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[197]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">19</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 2</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">nd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>We (mine hostess &amp; hostess [sic] and I) motored to Denton, where is a small church built about 25 years ago to serve the small community of farmers &amp; labourers numbering about 170 souls<hi rend="italic">,</hi> which forms the spiritual charge of the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d </hi>M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Apter . He has governed these people for 28 years, and has not (unless he be gravely calumniated) succeeded in gaining either their respect or their affection in that long time. The church was completely filled, but not solely or mainly with parishioners. The Vicar both read the service, and played the harmonium. I preached and celebrated. There were 25 communicants. The service was thoroughly congregational, and reverent.</p>
         <p>At 6 p.m. Sir Alfred &amp; Lady Palmer accompanied me to Heighington, where I preached in the parish church of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Michael. The Harvest Festival was being observed, and the church was crowded. There are four churchwardens in this parish. They preceded me with their staves, or rather, I was led like a prisoner between them, two going before me, and two following after. The church is an interesting medieval building, ill&#8211;handled by modern restorers. The pulpit is pre&#8211;Reformation, &amp; is a seemly structure of panelled wood. The parson, Maclean, is unmarried: his mother, who told me that her age was 82, lives with him. He has been Vicar since 1916. The patronage of Heighington is vested in the Dean &amp; Chapter of Durham: and the population is under 900. Bolam, which goes with it, adds 100 more. </p></body></text></TEI>