<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[207]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Saturday, October 8</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>It is a mistake to suppose that the Church learned cruelty from the heathen, who indeed were very spasmodic &amp; inefficient persecutors. The old persecutions were neither very numerous nor very fatal, and, so far as they did not originate in the fury of the vulgar mob, were almost entirely political, like that of Queen Elizabeth, not inquisitorial, like that of Queen Mary. But the Christian emperors and bishops were guided not by the example of their old enemies, but by that same mistaken reverence for the Hebrew Scriptures which caused so much injury in other directions.</p>
         <p>Bigg. "<hi rend="underline">The Church's Task in the Roman Empire</hi>" 85</p>
         </div>
         <p>It must be added in the case of Christian persecutors that their consciences being enlisted on the same side as that on which their preferences and interests were engaged, and sacred authority being given to their resentments, there was no check left to mitigate the worst excesses of resentful passion. "The time shall come", said Christ, "when he that killeth you shall think that he doeth God service". A later time came when Christ's disciples held themselves required by their service of God to kill, even worse to insult and torture, those who were not Christians. The fact remains after prodigies of extenuating explanation a heavy burden on the mind, and an insoluble problem. "<hi rend="underline">If any man hath not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of His</hi>."</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[208]</hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>Dear M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Frost,</p>
         <p>I must call your attention to the situation of your brother, the Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Walter Frost, who is without employment, and without any prospect of obtaining employment, as an assistant curate. He writes to me in terms which are highly improper, and, even when allowance has been made for his circumstances, rather disconcerting. For they raise a doubt in the mind whether, apart from the heavy disadvantages of his blindness, he may not have disqualifying defects of temper &amp; temperament.</p>
         <p>It is obvious that he cannot be maintained by the Church: &amp; equally obvious that his family cannot repudiate responsibility for his maintenance.</p>
         <p>I shall be glad to hear that you are in touch with him, &amp; ready to bring him the assistance which he needs, &amp; may fairly look for from you.</p>
         <p>Believe me,</p>
         <p>Yours v. faithfully</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         <p>The Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> Samuel Frost</p>
         <p>Withern Rectory. Alford. Lincs.</p>
         </div>
         <p>A long, incoherent, and almost abusive letter from the blind curate arrived by the morning post. It was in a registered envelope. I wrote the above to his brother, who was really responsible (for he coerced Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName>!) for his Ordination.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[209]</hi></p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> and I left the castle at 10.15 a.m., and motored to Newcastle, where we arrived about 11.30 p.m. Here I had my hair cut at M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Dellow's establishment in Grey Street. Rejoining the car at 12.15 p.m. we motored to Bedlington, arriving a few minutes after lunch time at 1 p.m. We lunched pleasantly with the Campbell Frasers<persName xml:id="4038"></persName>, &amp; then went to the parish church for the dedication of the War Memorial. This memorial had taken the form of restoring the 14<hi rend="superscript underline">th</hi> century porch&#8211;chapel, &amp; setting up there an altar with crucifix, &amp; on the walls tablets containing the names of 415 men from the district of Bedlingtonshire who had fallen in the War. I dedicated the memorial, &amp; preached to a crowded congregation. After being photographed twice over, I had tea, &amp; then was taken to the elementary school, where I unveiled a tablet containing the names of 95 old boys who had fallen in the war, and made a speech to the large company of parents &amp;c who had come together. After this we returned to the Castle, where we arrived about 7.50 p.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> drove admirably. The crowds in Newcastle, Gateshead, Chester&#8211;le&#8211;Street, Spennymoor, &amp; Auckland must have been a severe test of any driver. On my return I found a letter from Prof. Edward Moor<persName xml:id="1266"></persName> written from Harvard. The weather throughout the day was fine and warm, so warm that we motored with the car open both going to Bedlington, and returning thence.</p></body></text></TEI>