<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[214]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Tuesday, October 11</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>We were at the Town Hall in time for the public reception by the Mayor. I sate beside the Archbishop on the platform. A very small procession, including only 2 bishops, Newcastle &amp; Bradford, went with me to the Parish Church, the main body of members going after the Archbishop. <hi rend="bold underline">However, I preached my sermon: to a church that was nearly full. Newcastle expressed strong approval, &amp; I think it impressed the congregation</hi><hi rend="bold">. </hi>Then we lunched with Sir John Holder<persName xml:id="5357"></persName>, &amp; I sate next Robertson<persName xml:id="251"></persName>. This was quite a pleasant function. There followed the Congress Meeting in the Town Hall, at which <hi rend="bold">[215] </hi>deputations of Sectaries appeared, and made speeches which savoured overmuch of self&#8211;advertisement. The Archbishop made a speech, &amp; received an "ovation". Then came the Presidential Address, which was really a pitiably inadequate performance. It roamed over many subjects, &amp; dealt with none usefully. Some very foolish things were said.</p>
         <p>Instead of going to the evening session, I stayed at the Rectory and had much talk with mine host. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Grose Hodge</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> is a prominent member of the Evangelical Trusts, and defended their existence with more ardour than intelligence. He argued that without these Trusts, Evangelicalism would have died out altogether in the Church of England. I could not but reply that this was an extraordinarily damaging admission. </hi><hi rend="underline">Inter alia</hi><hi rend="bold underline"> he told me </hi><hi rend="italic bold underline">that letters from Bishop Moule<persName xml:id="276"></persName> commending candidates for Trust livings were received with a smile, and ignored</hi><hi rend="i bold">! </hi>About 11 p.m. <hi rend="doubleunderline">Fletcher</hi>, the Headmaster of Charterhous<hi rend="bold">&#8211;</hi>, arrived, and <hi rend="underline">I had talk enough with him to discover that he also was bitten with the Socialist madness</hi>. When Bishops and Headmasters adopt revolutionary opinions one's head turns. The "very elect" are being led astray. He joined the Bishop of Chelmsford<persName xml:id="2462"></persName> in vehemently denouncing <hi rend="doubleunderline">Lloyd George</hi>! Yet even he admitted that the unspeakable <hi rend="doubleunderline">Massingham</hi><persName xml:id="1299"></persName> was impossible to digest.</p>
      </body>
   </text></TEI>