<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[202]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Wednesday, October 5</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <p>Warm wet weather, the worst in the world for sightseeing. However, there was no chance for it but to take our visitors to see Durham. Accordingly, after an early lunch we all set out in the two motors, theirs and ours, and went to Durham. I shewed my guests over the cathedral, &amp; we all stayed to service. The new minor canon monotoned the last part of Evensong. I was delighted with his voice. Poor Dennet's inadequacy was, by comparison, very apparent. We called on the Dean<persName xml:id="114"></persName>s, and were shown over the Deanery. Then we went to the Castle and had tea. After seeing the Hall, Kitchen, &amp; Chapel, we motored back to Auckland. <hi rend="bold underline">I read my Congress Sermon to George Macmillan, &amp; he expressed approval of it. He told me that Loeb had originally proposed that the publication of his Classical Library should be undertaken by Macmillan &amp; Co. When his offer was declined as unprofitable from a business point of view, he betook himself to Heinemann, who finally undertook the publication, but Loeb undertook all the risks. Macmillan thought the venture had never been financially successful. He spoke with much enthusiasm of Warde Fowler, to whose friendly offices he owed his Oxford degree, and his honorary fellowship at Lincoln College. It is obvious that a publisher enjoys many opportunities of becoming acquainted with his more distinguished contemporaries. Personal friendships sometimes grow out of the commercial relations, but perhaps, there must be always an unexpressed &amp; even unperceived temptation to cultivate intimacy with the more successful authors.</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[203] </hi></p>
         <div type="letter">
         <p>My dear M<hi rend="bold superscript underline">r</hi> Warth,</p>
         <p>The sudden death of M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> J.G. Holburn has vacated the vicarage of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Luke, Darlington. I am anxious to find a successor who would be capable of undertaking the charge of a great population of artisans, and who would be ready to complete the arrangement (which was on the verge of being completed when M<hi rend="superscript underline">r</hi> Holburn died) for constituting the Mission district of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Matthew an independent charge.</p>
         <p>If you feel that you can satisfy these conditions, I hope you will accept appointment to St Luke's, Darlington.</p>
         <p>Even with St Matthew's district taken off, there would be a population of about 9000 good souls. The income is not less than &#x00A3;350, if I am correctly informed, and there is a sufficient house. </p>
         <p>With all good wishes</p>
         <p>I am, sincerely yrs.</p>
         <p>Herbert Dunelm:</p>
         </div>
         <p>This will be the 3<hi rend="superscript underline">rd</hi> occasion on which I have nominated to livings as Bishop viz:	</p>
         <p>1. Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring…Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> S. K. Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName></p>
         <p>2. Belmont…Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> E. Maish<persName xml:id="5213"></persName></p>
         <p>3. S. Luke's, Darlington…Rev<hi rend="superscript underline">d</hi> S. F. Warth<persName xml:id="5354"></persName></p>
         <p>This is all the episcopal patronage to be exercised in a period of 18 months. It represents an extraordinarily slow pace of preferment in so large a diocese.</p></body></text></TEI>