<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[210]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">20</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold"> Sunday after Trinity, October 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>O Lord, I beseech Thee, make me to remember how much more than other men I have need to call upon Thee. My charge is great, and my strength little; O give me grace to come often before Thee, and ask that help, which Thou art readier to give than I to ask; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
         <p>Archbishop Laud<persName xml:id="3468"></persName></p>
         </div>
         <p><hi rend="bold underline">Is there a suggestion of exorbitant egotism in this humble prayer</hi><hi rend="bold">? </hi>It is assuredly the petition of an honest and dutiful spirit; it breathes a genuine piety; and is instinct with a strong faith: but is there not something that indicates in the petitioner the conviction that he himself is an important, perhaps an indispensable, factor in the work which he is carrying on? It does not occur to him to doubt whether the work itself has not become in his hands something that lies apart from, nay conflicts with, the Will of God. Laud was not one of those severe, and self&#8211;torturing persons, who are all the way through shadowed by the suspicion whether they are on the right track, whether, for all their zeal and labour, they are not resisting the Divine Purpose. In this respect, perhaps, he stood on the same level with his opponents. The Puritans, though they used a different language, were equally certain that they were right. And this assumption argues more self&#8211;confidence than is decent in a man, or permissible in a sinner.</p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[211]</hi></p>
         <p>I celebrated in the Chapel at 8 a.m. William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName> communicated. The collect for the day is precisely congruous with my present needs. If but I could be "ready both in body and soul", and "cheerfully accomplish those things which God would have done", I should be a worthy Bishop.</p>
         <p>I spent the whole morning in my study engaged in preparing a sermon for use at Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring in the evening.</p>
         <p><persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName> accompanied me to Houghton for Evensong at 6 p.m. There was an immense congregation, a hearty but thoroughly reverent service, &amp; close attention to the sermon. Lady Scarbrough<persName xml:id="3466"></persName> and her daughters were in church. We had supper at the Rectory. It is evident that Knight<persName xml:id="62"></persName> has made an excellent start. The blind curate, Smith, has not yet succeeded in finding another curacy. If, as it is not quite unreasonable to expect, Houghton&#8211;le&#8211;Spring becomes a really vigorous centre of Church life, the effect on the whole diocese will be excellent. It is a mining parish, and contains the most "advanced" of the miners' leaders. Under old purblind Adamson the Church was prostrate, but Knight is evidently making an impression. As Rural Dean he comes into personal touch with the clergy of the district. He finds them both socially and educationally a very weak lot: but they seem disposed to accept his leadership, and this at least is creditable. We arrived back at the Castle about 10 p.m. riding with the car open for the strange mildness of the weather.</p></body></text></TEI>