<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl" ?><TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>An entry from the Journals of Hensley Henson</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><distributor>Durham University</distributor></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl>Edited from the manuscripts in the custody of Durham Cathedral Library.</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>
         <p><hi rend="bold">[206]</hi></p>
         <p><hi rend="bold">Friday, October 7</hi><hi rend="bold superscript underline">th</hi><hi rend="bold">, 1921.</hi></p>
         <div type="quote">
         <p>But going over the theory of virtue in one's thoughts, talking well, and drawing fine pictures, of it: this is so far from necessarily or certainly conducing to form a habit of it, in him who thus employs himself, that it may harden the mind in a contrary course, &amp; gradually render it more insensible, i.e. form a habit of insensibility to all moral considerations.</p>
         <p>Bishop Butler. Analogy. Pt.I.ch.v. (p.80)</p>
         </div>
         <p>Before breakfast I worked on the letter. <persName xml:id="112">Ella</persName>, Lucy, and Lady Thurlow accompanied me in the motor to Durham; I sate with William<persName xml:id="4501"></persName>. I presided over a meeting of the Preventive &amp; Rescue Association, at which we discussed the future of S. Catherine's Home, an excellent but financially unsuccessful institution. Finally, we passed 2 resolutions, of which the one requested the Committee of S. Catherine's to carry on for another year: &amp; the other requested the Governors of S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Mary's, a relatively flourishing institution, to consider whether they couldn't assist S. Catherine's. Then we lunched with Lillingston<persName xml:id="3262"></persName>, and afterwards returned to Auckland. Sykes<persName xml:id="3470"></persName> reported to me that John<persName xml:id="5355"></persName>, lately curate at S<hi rend="superscript underline">t</hi> Oswald's, whom I sent to S. Ignatius for special reasons, was working excellently. This is good hearing. Stephenson of Gateshead did not report so well of Rooker, the Vicar of Middleton&#8211;in&#8211;Teesdale, but he knew nothing positive, or very recent.</p></body></text></TEI>